<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Governor-Elect Gets Set, Hopes High, Profile Low</title>
    <meta content="Y02CALI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Gray (Lt Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Edmund G Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hart, Gary (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DA143BF931A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Governor-Elect Gets Set, Hopes High, Profile Low</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Dec. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California Gov-elect Gray Davis's low profile seems to be helping him as he moves to step up from lieutenant governor, put together new administration and cope with flood of pent-up demands from Democrats, who have not had governor from their party since Edmund G Brown Jr 16 years ago; Davis recently announced his first staff appointment--former State Sen Gary Hart as education secretary--in keeping with his campaign pledge to revitalize state's sagging public schools; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For months, Gray Davis was mocked as California's slow but steady gubernatorial candidate. So it was perhaps fitting that he made one of his first full-dress appearances as Governor-elect, at a news conference this week in the children's department of the Los Angeles Central Library, in front of a display copy of ''The Hare and the Tortoise.''</p>
        <p>But since his 20-point victory over State Attorney General Dan Lungren a month ago, Mr. Davis has behaved more like a groundhog, burrowing down in private and reviewing his options as he prepares to take over from Gov. Pete Wilson in January. He surfaced at the library on Monday only to announce his first staff appointment -- that of his Education Secretary, in keeping with his campaign pledge to revitalize the state's sagging public schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For months, Gray Davis was mocked as California's slow but steady gubernatorial candidate. So it was perhaps fitting that he made one of his first full-dress appearances as Governor-elect, at a news conference this week in the children's department of the Los Angeles Central Library, in front of a display copy of ''The Hare and the Tortoise.''</p>
        <p>But since his 20-point victory over State Attorney General Dan Lungren a month ago, Mr. Davis has behaved more like a groundhog, burrowing down in private and reviewing his options as he prepares to take over from Gov. Pete Wilson in January. He surfaced at the library on Monday only to announce his first staff appointment -- that of his Education Secretary, in keeping with his campaign pledge to revitalize the state's sagging public schools.</p>
        <p>And just as Mr. Davis's calm caution served him well in a campaign that many pundits initially said he could not win, so his low profile seems to be helping him now as he moves to step up from lieutenant governor, put together a new administration and cope with a flood of pent-up demands from Democrats, who have not had a governor from their party since Edmund G. Brown Jr. 16 years ago, and from state employees, most of whom have not had raises since 1995.</p>
        <p>Ten days ago the State Legislature's chief fiscal adviser said the new Governor could face a $1.2 billion shortfall in the state budget of about $75 billion that he will be required to outline just a week after taking office on Jan. 4, and other officials have said the gap may be even larger. Mr. Davis, who enjoyed major support from the state's powerful teachers union and has plans for new programs like $10,000 merit raises for teachers who agree to stay in the field, sounded a cautionary note this week about any across-the-board raises.</p>
        <p>''I think we'll be looking at very limited'' flexibility, said the Governor-elect, who was generally careful during his campaign not to promise much in the way of specific spending.</p>
        <p>State economic experts said they did not believe that the projected shortfall, driven by higher-than-expected Medicaid costs and a slowing in economic growth, marked any major downturn in the California economy, which continues to outpace the nation significantly in job growth. Instead, they said, it amounts to a fairly routine dip that could be made up by a strong Christmas retail season and greater-than-expected income tax receipts next spring, by the time the real budget is put together beginning in May.</p>
        <p>''I think California is substantially stronger than the nation, so much so that we may be the engine that is preventing a national recession,'' said Philip J. Romero, Governor Wilson's chief economist. ''Much has been made, and quite appropriately, of California exporters' exposure to the Asian downturn. But they're only about 40 to 50 percent of exports, and the next-largest is Europe, which is holding strong. And a couple of mainstay industries, like entertainment and multimedia, have remained strong.''</p>
        <p>Last summer, with revenue running about $2 billion ahead of projections, pressure grew for election-year tax cuts, and the Legislature and Mr. Wilson agreed to a vehicle fee reduction that will trim about $1 billion in revenue from Mr. Davis's first full fiscal year in office, which starts on July 1. So the wary budget projections give Mr. Davis some welcome political running room.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to be a genius'' to know that ''surpluses are a rare occurrence, and they should be disposed of on a one-time basis,'' Mr. Davis said. ''In my 25 years in public service, there may have been three or four surpluses over that entire time of any consequence.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Romero added, ''Having some reason to take some time before making major fiscal decisions has the added advantage of being a good idea, given that there'll be a lot of good information available in April and May.''</p>
        <p>For the moment, Mr. Davis is concentrating on education, the issue that polls showed ranked No. 1 among voter concerns. At his news conference this week, he broke with incoming governors' usual practice of introducing a chief of staff or a finance director as the first appointee and instead named former State Senator Gary Hart, a friend and fraternity brother from their days at Stanford University, as his chief education adviser.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart, former chairman of the State Senate's Education Committee and most recently co-director of the California State University Institute for Education Reform, has long been an advocate of class-size reduction and charter schools.</p>
        <p>The Education Secretary's post, which Mr. Wilson created in 1991 to gain greater control over education policy, is only a quasi-Cabinet position, since the Democratic-controlled Legislature has declined to grant formal status to it. The school system is overseen by an independently elected State Superintendent of Public Instruction.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Davis said that whatever the title, Mr. Hart would be his chief education policy adviser as he begins  his term with a special legislative session intended to focus on improving school accountability, increasing teacher preparation and assuring that every child learns to read by the end of the third grade.</p>
        <p>''I am convinced,'' Mr. Davis said, ''that a back-to-basics, high-expectation approach to education will greatly enhance the future prospects'' of California's schoolchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
