<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Possible Motto: 'Help Yourself'</title>
    <meta content="02TOGO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TO GO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Piccola Cucina (NYC Takeout Shop)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Between the Bread (Caterer)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Comptoir Sud (Takeout Shop)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7D7173BF931A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Possible Motto: 'Help Yourself'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov rates the food and three takeout shops: Between the Bread, Comptoir Sud and Piccola Cucina; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN corporations require more than the usual coffee and rugelach for their meetings, they turn to caterers like BETWEEN THE BREAD. But Between the Bread also serves retail takeout customers at two midtown locations, east and west.</p>
        <p>This fact is not readily apparent, particularly on the West Side, for the tiny storefront offers no menu and no description of what is available. Instead, you have to ask about the attractive foods on display. Not that that will do much good: the woman at the counter when I visited was far more interested in looking over my shoulder and heaving great sighs than in answering questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN corporations require more than the usual coffee and rugelach for their meetings, they turn to caterers like BETWEEN THE BREAD. But Between the Bread also serves retail takeout customers at two midtown locations, east and west.</p>
        <p>This fact is not readily apparent, particularly on the West Side, for the tiny storefront offers no menu and no description of what is available. Instead, you have to ask about the attractive foods on display. Not that that will do much good: the woman at the counter when I visited was far more interested in looking over my shoulder and heaving great sighs than in answering questions.</p>
        <p>But it's hard to choose badly. Tender slices of filet mignon coated with crushed pepper are excellent, at $10.50 for the main course and two side dishes. (I selected superb beet salad with onions, and roasted sweet potatoes oozing juice.) Gemelli, thumb-size braids of pasta, were terrific with bitter broccoli rape and earthy Tuscan beans ($7.95). A fruit salad ($3.95) was fabulous, full of ripe honeydew, cantaloupe, strawberries, pineapple, grapes and apple.</p>
        <p>The East Side branch presented a puzzle, too, though the service was friendlier. Boneless chicken breast coated with a Cajun spice blend ($8.95) was peppery but a little dry, served with a crescent of sweet acorn squash and a tangle of al dente green beans. For dessert, a small lemon tart ($2.50) was bracingly delicious, while rice pudding ($2.25) was creamy as could be.</p>
        <p>The shops' huge, tasty muffins are not too sweet; they include tart cranberry walnut ($1.80) and chocolatey cappuccino ($1.80). After 2:30 P.M., a second muffin is half price, but only on the East Side, because the West Side branch closes at 3.</p>
        <p>Between the Bread, 141 East 56th Street, (212) 888-0449; 145 West 55th Street, (212) 581-1189. Free delivery: 10 blocks.</p>
        <p>From the cheery ''Bonjour'' on the telephone to the Gallic numerals on the handwritten menu, French pervades COMPTOIR SUD , a new takeout shop and cafe near Union Square. It has no relationship to the Upper East Side restaurant formerly known as Le Comptoir. Two of its owners are Jean-Jacques Dartau, who previously owned a catering shop in Atlanta, and Francis Reynard, who was a cook at Restaurant Daniel.</p>
        <p>Even the simplest dishes have hints of luxury, like creamy, beautifully spiced pumpkin soup ($3.05) and juicy roast chicken ($9.95) with rosemary and shallots.</p>
        <p>Sandwiches depart from the usual selections with French choices like ham and cornichons on a buttered roll ($5.50) and merguez, the savory Moroccan lamb sausage, with a dijonnaise sauce ($5.50). The bread, from Ecce Panis or Amy's, is of good quality, but it ought to be fresher.</p>
        <p>Desserts range from cookies and brownies to a fine creme caramel ($2.65) and an unusual pear poached in red wine, tasting of cloves and cinnamon ($2.25).</p>
        <p>Comptoir Sud, 15 East 15th Street, (212) 647-1515. Free delivery: two blocks; the range is to expand in the future.</p>
        <p>Try to imagine a savory pie stuffed with two kinds of ham, Italian sausage, salami, mortadella, broccoli rape, mozzarella, mushrooms, onions and roasted peppers. As you might imagine, a wedge of this pie the size of an outstretched palm weighs about as much as a bag of gold bullion, but at LA PICCOLA CUCINA, a tiny takeout shop, it costs just $3. It goes down lighter than you might expect, especially when heated gently for a few minutes. Nonetheless, one slice is enough for two lunches.</p>
        <p>I'm almost as daunted by the generous but tasty Italian sandwiches, like mortadella, prosciutto, mozzarella, roasted peppers and tomatoes ($6.75). If this all sounds like too much, try the roasted vegetables ($8 a pound) or the terrific farfalle salad ($2 for eight ounces), bow-tie pasta with broccoli, garlic and olive oil accented with pine nuts.</p>
        <p>La Piccola Cucina, 2770 Broadway (107th Street), (212) 222-2381. Free delivery: 96th to 122d Streets, Central Park West to Riverside Drive.</p>
        <p>TO GO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
