<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Nightmare of 2003 to a World Series Dream</title>
    <meta content="23inge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/23/sports/baseball/23inge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Inge, Brandon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DC173FF930A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Nightmare of 2003 to a World Series Dream</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Nightmare of 2003 to a World Series Dream</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Craig Monroe was here when the Tigers lost 119 times in 2003, here for so many games when they played before thousands of empty seats and here for all the jokes about how terrible they truly were. Monroe was trying to avoid embarrassment then. The World Series was but a dream.</p>
        <p>But playing in the World Series is not a dream anymore for a vindicated player like Monroe. After living through one of the worst seasons in baseball history, Monroe is helping the Tigers roll through a remarkable October. He is not embarrassed anymore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brandon Inge rebounded from a sluggish Game 1, in which he made two errors on the same play, to single twice and do anything to help the Tigers prevail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Craig Monroe was here when the Tigers lost 119 times in 2003, here for so many games when they played before thousands of empty seats and here for all the jokes about how terrible they truly were. Monroe was trying to avoid embarrassment then. The World Series was but a dream.</p>
        <p>But playing in the World Series is not a dream anymore for a vindicated player like Monroe. After living through one of the worst seasons in baseball history, Monroe is helping the Tigers roll through a remarkable October. He is not embarrassed anymore.</p>
        <p>Monroe had a monstrous homer in the first inning that helped the Tigers stop the St. Louis Cardinals, 3-1, in Game 2 on Sunday and even the best-of-seven series. Kenny Rogers, who was not here three years ago, continued pitching as if he owned the month with eight spotless innings to give him 23 straight scoreless innings.</p>
        <p>While the Cardinals were wondering why Rogers had a discolored spot on the palm of his pitching hand, Monroe powered Jeff Weaver's first pitch into the left-field seats. It was Monroe's fifth postseason home run in his 35th at-bat in the playoffs, setting a team record. He surpassed the four homers Hank Greenberg had in 85 at-bats, which all came in World Series games.</p>
        <p>When Monroe finished jogging 360 feet around the bases, he acted like a professional wrestler. He pointed to the fans behind the plate, he punched his chest twice, he screamed, ''Let's go!'' and slapped hands with teammates as if every high-five earned him another $1,000.</p>
        <p>After witnessing 119 losses three years ago, Monroe helped the Tigers secure their first World Series victory in 22 years.</p>
        <p>''You remember being in the backyard and being a little kid and you dream of being in the World Series,'' Monroe said in a television interview after the game. ''You talk about it and you put yourself in these situations. To be living out this dream is something you dream about.''</p>
        <p>First baseman Sean Casey said the Tigers had a pregame meeting in which they reminded themselves to be aggressive against Weaver and ''set a tone.'' Casey said the player the Tigers call ''C-Mo'' quickly did that.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to see on a stage like this that he's doing the same stuff he's done all year long,'' Casey said. ''It's nice to see him get that recognition.''</p>
        <p>Monroe, who is always smiling and who definitely acts as if the glass is half full, added, ''I've shocked myself sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Besides Monroe, Brandon Inge, a slick-fielding third baseman, is another Tiger who lived through that dreary season. Inge rebounded from a sluggish Game 1 in which he made two errors on the same play to single twice and do his usual diving around the infield.</p>
        <p>Before Sunday, Inge had been 6 for 30 with 1 homer, 3 runs batted in and 10 strikeouts, measly postseason statistics.</p>
        <p>''If we win the game,'' Inge said, ''I don't care if I go 0 for 10.''</p>
        <p>When Sparky Anderson, the Hall of Fame manager who threw out the ceremonial first pitch, was asked about the Tigers, the first player he mentioned was Inge.</p>
        <p>''Don't look at stats; he can play baseball,'' Anderson said.</p>
        <p>Inge acknowledged that it was poetic justice that he and Monroe were able to experience a memorable Sunday night after so many forgettable days.</p>
        <p>''What Craig did was huge,'' Inge said. ''We need him to keep doing that and to keep stepping up for us.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees were interested in drafting Inge eight years ago, so they asked Paul Keyes, his coach at Virginia Commonwealth University, for an evaluation. Inge was a shortstop who also served as a closer.</p>
        <p>Keyes told Mark Newman, a Yankees executive who had also been Keyes's coach at Old Dominion University, why he believed Inge would be a solid major leaguer. But to be sure Newman understood how strongly he felt about Inge's abilities, Keyes added one compelling anecdote.</p>
        <p>''I told him if I was on the second story with my newborn baby and there was a fire and I had to throw my son down, I'd want Brandon to be the one to catch him,'' Keyes said.</p>
        <p>The Tigers, not the Yankees, eventually drafted Inge in the second round in 1998. When the Tigers told him that they were moving him to catcher, which he had never played, Inge reasoned it was a quicker route to the majors.</p>
        <p>''Baseball is his life,'' Keyes said.</p>
        <p>Keyes recalled how he returned to campus late one night and heard the familiar sound of a bat hitting a ball. He peeked into the indoor batting cage and spotted Inge having a party with the pitching machine.</p>
        <p>As a survivor from that 2003 nightmare, Inge is savoring every moment of this magical run. Inge said that putting on a uniform made him feel as if he were ''in heaven.'' October heaven is three victories away for Inge and Monroe and the rest of the Tigers.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
