<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serbs Make a Gesture at Sarajevo, Then Dig In Heels</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT IGMAN (YUGOSLAVIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT BJELASNICA (YUGOSLAVIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D71230F933A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serbs Make a Gesture at Sarajevo, Then Dig In Heels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Aug. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A melancholy smile spread across the face of a sodden Bosnian soldier standing in a forest clearing on Mount Igman today.</p>
        <p>"A Serbian withdrawal?" Samir Kozar said, shaking his head so that raindrops ran in rivers down the garbage bag he was using as a poncho. "Let me tell you: when you reporters are around, or the United Nations, the Serbs behave like babies. But as soon as you go, pow! Tanks, howitzers, mortars, antiaircraft guns -- everything."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A melancholy smile spread across the face of a sodden Bosnian soldier standing in a forest clearing on Mount Igman today.</p>
        <p>"A Serbian withdrawal?" Samir Kozar said, shaking his head so that raindrops ran in rivers down the garbage bag he was using as a poncho. "Let me tell you: when you reporters are around, or the United Nations, the Serbs behave like babies. But as soon as you go, pow! Tanks, howitzers, mortars, antiaircraft guns -- everything."</p>
        <p>Starting at 9 A.M. today, the Serbian nationalist forces besieging Sarajevo were to have begun what their commander, Lieut. Gen. Ratko Mladic, described as a "phased withdrawal" from Mount Igman and Mount Bjelasnica, two peaks that dominate the southern approaches to the Bosnian capital. But seven hours later, at the front line between the Serbian and Bosnian troops on Mount Igman, not a single Serbian tank, howitzer or mortar appeared to have moved.  A Deflecting Strategy</p>
        <p>General Mladic announced the pullback on Sunday evening, as he and other Serbian leaders maneuvered to head off the air strikes that have been threatened by the United States and its NATO allies if the Serbian forces continue the strangulation of Sarajevo and other United Nations-designated "safe areas" in Bosnia. The risk to Sarajevo has been greatest recently from the Serbian thrust on these mountains, which has come close to cutting off supply routes vital to the city.</p>
        <p>When the deadline came this morning, the Serbian commander was as good as his word in respect to the peak of Mount Bjelasnica. Through the mists swirling about the 6,800-foot summit, reporters could see that the white, blue and red crossbars of the Serbian flag had been lowered from the ski lift terminal atop the mountain, leaving only the blue United Nations flag fluttering in the stiff winds.</p>
        <p>United Nations officers said that as a last gesture, the Serbian special forces unit that led the assault, named Cobra, dynamited the television tower atop the mountain, and the tower could be seen leaning like a broken matchstick on the bare granite peak.</p>
        <p>But as dusk fell, 14 hours after the scheduled start of an operation that is supposed to roll back all the gains made by the Serbian forces since the attack on Mount Bjelasnica, there were strong signs that the Serbian forces, far from pulling back, were still settling in on the territory they have seized along the strategic road that runs past the foot of Mount Bjelasnica and along the spine of Mount Igman.</p>
        <p>"They have absolutely no intention of withdrawing, as far as I can tell," said a French captain commanding one of three United Nations reconnaissance teams on Mount Igman.  Less Than It Seemed</p>
        <p>Even the withdrawal from Mount Bjelasnica was less significant than it was made to seem by United Nations commanders in Sarajevo and peace negotiators in Geneva. Both were anxious for evidence of a Serbian pullback to slow the momentum for NATO air strikes and to lure the Bosnian President, Alija Izetbegovic, back to talks.</p>
        <p>But even Serbian officers belittled the action, pointing out that their advance had carried them five miles past the base of Mount Bjelasnica, making control of the mountain's summit militarily unimportant.</p>
        <p>At the front line, at a ski village named Malo Polje, Serbian tanks and howitzers lurked beneath shrouds of pine branches beside the road, their gun barrels trained on Bosnian positions half a mile ahead. Serbian soldiers in tented camps could be seen fetching water and cooking over wood fires. Spent shell casings littered the road. When a reporter asked one soldier if he was preparing to pull back, he replied testily: "Pull back? Why? This is Serbian land."</p>
        <p>The only indication that the Serbs might be anticipating a pullback was the sight of burning buildings. Between the Veliko Polje and Malo Polje, about five miles, almost all of the buildings had been torched. One, the Hotel Igman, was the finest ski hotel in the region.</p>
        <p>Serbian commanders could have been destroying properties that they knew they would have to give up in a withdrawal. But scorched-earth tactics have been a signature of the Serbian forces since the start of the Bosnian war 16 months ago, usually in areas that they have had no intention of leaving. As part of the policy known as "ethnic cleansing," Serbian units have been ordered to destroy all buildings belonging to Muslims, so as to discourage their return.</p>
        <p>When two reporters crossed the front line at Malo Polje and found the road blocked by a fallen tree, they could hear a man's voice singing a Muslim chant in the forest. Scrambling up a bank, they found Mr. Kozar and 10 other soldiers standing over a wood fire, with nothing but assault rifles to defend their positions.</p>
        <p>As one of his fellow fighters bent close to the fire in an attempt to dry out the camouflage shirt that was his only protection from the rain, Mr. Kozar said that the Serbian attacks, backed by helicopters, had been so sudden and overpowering that the Bosnian forces had no chance of resisting. Now, he said, survivors waited in the forests, without even dugouts to protect them.</p>
        <p>Asked what sustained the soldiers' morale, Mr. Kozar smiled again, this time brightly. "Just this," he said, pointing to his heart. BALKAN UPDATE</p>
        <p>Meeting at NATO headquarters in BRUSSELS yesterday, the allies approved a plan that calls for graduated air strikes that could come in response to Serbian military actions in BOSNIA. But the 16 NATO members put off a decision on specific bombing attacks and confirmed that such missions would come only after specific approval by the United Nations Secretary General.</p>
        <p>In GENEVA, President Alija Izetbegovic of BOSNIA said again that he would not return to peace talks until Bosnian Serbs withdrew all their troops from two strategic mountains near SARAJEVO, the capital.</p>
        <p>But despite plans by the Bosnian Serb commander to withdraw from the mountains, MOUNT IGMAN and MOUNT BJELASNICA, not a single tank, howitzer or mortar appeared to have been moved seven hours after the pullback was to begin.</p>
        <p>In SARAJEVO, a 5-year-old girl severely wounded by a Serbian artillery shell was evacuated by a British military aircraft and flown to BRITAIN, where she reported to be in critical condition.</p>
        <p>In WASHINGTON, a third State Department official has resigned in the last year in protest over the Clinton Administration's policy on BOSNIA, saying it was not tough enough.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
