<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Trying Out Nonexistent Homes</title>
    <meta content="26NJZO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/26/realestate/26njzo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hoboken (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pinnacle Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Antoinette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D71030F935A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/New Jersey; Trying Out Nonexistent Homes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trying Out Nonexistent Homes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTOINETTE MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Antoinette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Urban-oriented condominium developers in New Jersey are creating 'virtual homes,' apartment 'vignettes' and model apartments to market units in mid- to high-rise towers; sales office for Pinnacle Ltd's Hoboken project cited; photo (In the Region/New Jersey) (M)y</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Hoboken, it's possible to visit your condo before it is even built by pushing buttons on a big computer screen. In Jersey City, you can wash your hands in a precise replica of your future condo's bathroom while looking out the window at bulldozers and cranes preparing the land to put up the building. In North Bergen, you are invited to feel the granite countertops of your potential new kitchen -- while gazing across the Hudson River to Manhattan, or else across the street to a site where a building containing that exact kitchen is about to rise.</p>
        <p>On the coastline of New Jersey across from Manhattan, where large condominium developments are proliferating, a new marketing process has emerged: you can shop for a home away from the home itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Hoboken, it's possible to visit your condo before it is even built by pushing buttons on a big computer screen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Hoboken, it's possible to visit your condo before it is even built by pushing buttons on a big computer screen. In Jersey City, you can wash your hands in a precise replica of your future condo's bathroom while looking out the window at bulldozers and cranes preparing the land to put up the building. In North Bergen, you are invited to feel the granite countertops of your potential new kitchen -- while gazing across the Hudson River to Manhattan, or else across the street to a site where a building containing that exact kitchen is about to rise.</p>
        <p>On the coastline of New Jersey across from Manhattan, where large condominium developments are proliferating, a new marketing process has emerged: you can shop for a home away from the home itself.</p>
        <p>Suburban developers have long used the ''model home'' to market single-family houses and town homes before they are actually built. Now, urban-oriented condo developers are creating ''virtual homes,'' apartment ''vignettes'' and model apartments to market units in mid- to high-rise towers.</p>
        <p>''We're building 800-plus homes,'' said Mary Boorman, sales director for Pinnacle Ltd., which is about to begin construction of Maxwell Place on the Hudson, a project in Hoboken that it is developing in partnership with Toll Brothers. ''We have 28 different floor plans. It's hard for a buyer to just imagine what an apartment's views will be, how the layout flows, or even sometimes just to figure out where exactly in the building a particular unit is located.''</p>
        <p>Right now, the Maxwell Place development looks like a muddy pit on the banks of the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Interested buyers are encouraged to drive by the site at Hudson Street and Frank Sinatra Drive to take in the river ambience and Manhattan skyline vista, Ms. Boorman said. But it is at an office four blocks away on Washington Street in Hoboken that they are invited to ''enter'' individual apartments for sale.</p>
        <p>The Maxwell Place sales office is outfitted with a mock-up of the maple wood rotunda designed by Michael Graves that will grace its lobby, a table-top model of the development's four buildings and a plasma screen featuring a ''lifestyle'' video with helicopter views and also virtual renderings of individual buildings and apartments from inside and out. Meanwhile, at two interactive computer-screen kiosks, interested buyers can ''walk'' themselves through a particular unit, appointed with fixtures they choose by pushing a button, including Michael-Graves-designed kitchens and baths.</p>
        <p>Available on the video tour are 700-foot studios priced at $350,000 as well as million-dollar three-bedroom penthouses as large as 2,185 square feet. Kiosk visitors are able to view units furnished or unfurnished and to ''look'' out the windows of an apartment at the view, whether it be of a brick wall or the Empire State Building across the river.</p>
        <p>Sales of the Maxwell Place apartments began Dec. 14 and so far, 77 of the 832 have been spoken for with a $2,500 deposit and nonbinding reservation. ''Interest is very strong, very intense,'' Ms. Boorman said. Eventually, she said, model units and a sales office will be built at the site.</p>
        <p>Next to the Montgomery Greene Condominium site in Jersey City, meanwhile, an actual kitchen and bathroom, looking just as they will in the 19-story brick tower about a year from now, currently inhabit the sales ''gallery'' in a converted industrial building at 66 York Street.</p>
        <p>''We really went for a gallery feeling in here,'' said Edward Yorukoff, sales director for the KOR Companies, which is developing the project. He gestured to the historic photographs on the wall, the artfully designed seating area, and the special exhibits: a Bahian travertine marble bathroom with tall windows overlooking the construction site, and a sleek black-and-stainless steel kitchen with oak plank flooring and paneled maple cabinets.</p>
        <p>KOR, which is constructing Montgomery Greene in partnership with Time Equities, wanted home shoppers to be able to literally lay hands on the high-grade fixtures and appliances that it will provide in the condo tower, which is going up next to the low-lying brownstone neighborhood of Paulus Hook.</p>
        <p>''We can't quite show them the view they will enjoy,'' Mr. Yorukoff said, ''because we couldn't lease a sales office up that high. So we do that with the artwork and the brochures.''</p>
        <p>Montgomery Greene penthouses and upper floor apartments will have glass walls and views of the Hudson, New York Harbor and the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, all displayed in panoramic photographs on walls in the sales office, and in printed pamphlets. The building, being marketed as ''city-style living at its best,'' offers studio, one- and two-bedroom units, and penthouses with up to 2,600 square feet of space.</p>
        <p>Mirabelle-on-the-Hudson, a seven-story condo going up on the west side of River Road in North Bergen, is opening a sales ''pavilion'' on the east side of the road, right on the riverfront.</p>
        <p>Finishing touches were still being put on the sales office last week, and the 23 units in the new building priced from $500,000 to $1.75 million will not officially be marketed until next month. More than 300 potential home buyers have already made inquiries.</p>
        <p>''We built a nearly 2,200-square-foot pavilion and tried to incorporate into it as many of the same high-end products, finishes and appointments that will be found in the building,'' said Ira Shapiro, a principal with the builder, Slaver Development.</p>
        <p>That includes nine-foot ceilings with recessed lighting, Brazilian rosewood floors with a marble inlay, and a kitchen with granite countertops and imported custom cherry cabinetry. A complete master bath built into the sales office features a limestone floor, custom wood vanities and a Kohler cast-iron soaking tub with mosaic limestone deck.</p>
        <p>The sales pavilion is even equipped with the same Andersen windows that the building will offer and also three sets of sliding glass patio doors that lead to a rear deck showing off the riverfront and Manhattan skyline views that will be available from each unit's terrace.</p>
        <p>Westminster Communities, the home-building arm of the Kushner Companies, plans to use more of the ''vignette'' approach with the sales office for 390 condominiums that it seeks to build in Atlantic City, just as it did with last year's riverfront redevelopment project in Perth Amboy, according to Westminster's president, Sam Gershwin. This entails building small-scale versions of residential units without ceilings so that they can be viewed from above as well as entered.</p>
        <p>In Asbury Park, where Westminster is one of three developers collaborating on redevelopment of the oceanfront, Mr. Gershwin said, ''we have rented an off-site sales office in the retail district, and we will take a virtual-reality approach to home tours.''</p>
        <p>''The main thing is,'' Mr. Gershwin said, ''you can't just show someone a blueprint and expect them to 'see' the property. You've really got to show it, one way or another.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
