<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="26WEBRIEF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1D61030F935A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA WEST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dishing Fresh Dirt On Deer, Worms and Water</p>
        <p>As if decimated gardens, frequent car accidents and the spread of Lyme disease were not reason enough to fret about too many deer, here's another: They are apparently eating the forest right out from under us.</p>
        <p>''You do not see any rejuvenation of the forest because the deer eat any saplings that grow,'' said John Hannon, president of the Bedford Chapter of the National Audubon Society. ''They eat the acorns before they can germinate and they eat right through the understory of forests, the lower branches where birds make their nests.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dishing Fresh Dirt On Deer, Worms and Water</p>
        <p>As if decimated gardens, frequent car accidents and the spread of Lyme disease were not reason enough to fret about too many deer, here's another: They are apparently eating the forest right out from under us.</p>
        <p>''You do not see any rejuvenation of the forest because the deer eat any saplings that grow,'' said John Hannon, president of the Bedford Chapter of the National Audubon Society. ''They eat the acorns before they can germinate and they eat right through the understory of forests, the lower branches where birds make their nests.''</p>
        <p>The problem is said to be particularly acute in Westchester and Putnam, where development creates a perfect browsing environment for deer and where residents prefer seeing venison in a Burgundy stew to seeing Bambi through gun sights.</p>
        <p>Birders, alarmed at the loss of once-common understory species like Red-eyed vireo and American woodcock, are calling for the management of the white deer population before more birds are lost -- ''management,'' in this case, being humane-speak code for ''hunting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hannon stresses ''the impact the deer are having on themselves because of overpopulation, and the overall balance of the environment.'' His society wants to encourage hunting again, especially of female deer.</p>
        <p>''This is not about trophies,'' Mr. Hannon said. ''This is about preservation.'' And people who feel the teensiest bit bad about it can tell themselves it's for the deer's own good.</p>
        <p>WHILE RUMINANTS -- are attacking Westchester's forests from above, annelids are devouring them from below. Think worms -- not the familiar night crawler, that soil-aerating, fish-baiting friend, but its feistier cousin.</p>
        <p>The Asian worm, or Amynthas agrestis, is four inches long and very hungry.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't live underground,'' said Peter Groffman, a soil ecologist with the Institute of Ecosystem Studies in Millbrook. ''It lives in this organic schmutz that protects the soil from erosion.''</p>
        <p>The Asian worm, he explained, eats through all this leaf cover in a few short months, leaving the ground barren. For those of us suffering from leaf-blower deafness, an efficient leaf-eater may not sound like a bad thing, but soil without leaf cover is definitely not like a fish without a bicycle. Bereft of its blanket, the soil cannot gather the nutrients that sustain the trees.</p>
        <p>The Asian worm was introduced into New York City perhaps 20 years ago, either hidden in soil of imported plants, or brought in by ''people in the worm business,'' Dr. Groffman said, explaining that there are those who cultivate worms for fishing and composting.</p>
        <p>By the 1990's the worms had migrated to Westchester, where they continue to proliferate each summer, changing the composition of the soil.</p>
        <p>WATER QUALITY -- might be of more immediate concern than soil composition, though. That's what Katherine Desmond of the Village of Mamaroneck fears, anyway. She used to swim in the Long Island Sound at the beach in Harbor Island Park every summer day, she says. Of course that was back before contamination became such a danger that a boom had to be installed to protect the beach.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, something about only being allowed to swim behind a boom just does not appeal to me,'' said Ms. Desmond, 60, a tile designer.</p>
        <p>So she converted some of that swimming time into water-quality time. A chairwoman of the village's advisory committee on that issue, she is urging everyone to ''Adopt a Stream.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Desmond and other volunteers hope to monitor the streams that traverse the village almost unnoticed: the Sheldrake and Mamaroneck rivers and the Beaver Swamp Brook.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be watchdogs, not police,'' Ms. Desmond said. ''And we need all the help we can get.''</p>
        <p>DEBRA WEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
