<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Season's Greetings, Merry and Somber, From an Eclectic Town</title>
    <meta content="26TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/26/nyregion/26towns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Our Towns"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nyack (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D71E30F935A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Season's Greetings, Merry and Somber, From an Eclectic Town</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Season's Greetings, Merry and Somber, From an Eclectic Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>NYACK, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome column on Christmas season in Nyack, NY, community that is rich in diversity of opinion; artists, theologians, veterans and townspeople offer their opinions on season and how it is celebrated now in contrast to less secular times; many note effect of Iraq war; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN BOUZAKIS, artist, entrepreneur, creative director of the 21st Century Gallery on Main Street, likes to think of himself as the Home Depot of fine art.</p>
        <p>You want a Renoir-like nude of your wife? He can paint that for you, personalized from the photograph of your choice. You want Impressionism, neo-Realism, Pop Art? He can do that, too. If you really want to see the vivid oil he painted of his ex-wife and her boyfriend, the latter bare-chested, carrying a bloody dagger and triumphantly brandishing Mr. Bouzakis's ripped-out heart, that's on display too, along with Beatles art and the four 70's-era versions of the Winston Man -- one white, one black, one Hispanic, one Asian -- calmly puffing away for placement on billboards in appropriate neighborhoods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Nyack, N.Y., an eclectic bastion on the Hudson, people have a, shall we say, nuanced view of Christmas 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN BOUZAKIS, artist, entrepreneur, creative director of the 21st Century Gallery on Main Street, likes to think of himself as the Home Depot of fine art.</p>
        <p>You want a Renoir-like nude of your wife? He can paint that for you, personalized from the photograph of your choice. You want Impressionism, neo-Realism, Pop Art? He can do that, too. If you really want to see the vivid oil he painted of his ex-wife and her boyfriend, the latter bare-chested, carrying a bloody dagger and triumphantly brandishing Mr. Bouzakis's ripped-out heart, that's on display too, along with Beatles art and the four 70's-era versions of the Winston Man -- one white, one black, one Hispanic, one Asian -- calmly puffing away for placement on billboards in appropriate neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>So, man of many moods that he is, it's perhaps not surprising that Mr. Bouzakis has had a hard time getting a clear line on Christmas 2004.</p>
        <p>''I think Christmas is becoming not as Christmasy,'' he said. ''I'm an old-time guy. I love the old Coca-Cola paintings of Santa, but a woman came in and complained, 'You have all these Santas in the window,' like they didn't belong there. I said, 'Yeah, it's Christmas.'''</p>
        <p>He paused and continued: ''Even Santa is becoming passé, and it's becoming more of a seasonal thing, like it's the December holiday. So Santa Claus is going out, and now it's Season's Greetings, but that's great too. That's what's great about this country. We're all the same, if you know what I mean.''</p>
        <p>In this eclectic bastion on the Hudson, he's not alone. It's partly Nyack, a place where, in fact, very few people are alike.</p>
        <p>So American Legion Post 310, perched right above the river, doubles as a dance and Tai Chi studio across the street from a house with a bright banner reading, ''We the people say no to the Bush agenda.'' There's a bracing mix of poor and rich, black and white, right and left, and even the fliers in store windows (''Belly dancing by Salacia and her dance ensemble,'' ''Holiday decorating a hassle? Let me handle it for you.'') suggest a, how you say, nuanced view of Christmas 2004.</p>
        <p>For many, the holiday was inseparable from the war.</p>
        <p>Samantha Lee, 16, and Trístan Pittman, 18, sat on a bench downtown, she white in a puffy white jacket, he black in a puffy black one.</p>
        <p>''I think it feels more like Christmas because of the war in Iraq,'' she said. ''People realize they need to be closer and love the ones around them, because you might lose them.''</p>
        <p>HE nodded: ''My brother's going. Two of my cousins down South are going over there.''</p>
        <p>At the Farmer's Market on a balmy Thursday, Scott Easter of Scotty's Soul Food Cafe and Mike Panzarella, who sells home-made mozzarella cheese and soups, agreed.</p>
        <p>''It's huge this year,'' Mr. Panzarella said. ''Everyone seems a lot closer, because you never know. I know seven or eight people over there, and I haven't heard from four of them in two months. I don't where they are or what they're doing. I don't know if they received anything I sent them. I hope they're still well.''</p>
        <p>At the American Legion Hall, with its wooden plaques for battles and wars past and present -- Normandy and Hue, Iraq and Kosovo -- Adam Peel, the manager, wasn't so sure.</p>
        <p>''If it's not your family, I don't think most people are really aware of it,'' he said. ''I hate the thought of that, but I think it's true. In the paper every day they have the honor roll of people who died, perhaps a little story. I honestly don't think people pay attention.''</p>
        <p>To some, the issue goes beyond the peculiarities of Christmas 2004.</p>
        <p>''I think the teachings of Jesus are wonderful, as are the teachings of the Cabala, as are the teachings of the Sufis, as are the teachings of the American Indians,'' said Ken Pollinger, who spent 13 years in a Jesuit seminary studying philosophy and theology, but now runs Nyack's New Age Center. ''But that's different from organized, bureaucratic, authoritarian religions. If Buddha came back today, he'd vomit to see big statues of himself. If Jesus came back he'd probably be crucified on the cross by the Catholic Church.''</p>
        <p>Still, even with 60-degree shopping weather, the shadow of war and the clatter of commerce, Christmas remains Christmas.</p>
        <p>Outside the First Reformed Church people have scribbled names on tags marked Christmas Prayers of Nyack -- Julie, G.G., Troops in Iraq, Peace.</p>
        <p>Thomas Danney, the pastor, said that the shadow over Christmas was not just Iraq, but the specter of violence everywhere: Iraq, Israel, Palestine, Sudan and closer to home.</p>
        <p>''Violence is the backdrop,'' he said, the radio behind him alternating between Mozart and war news, ''but to me as a pastor what I see is the message of Christmas trying to assert itself, so there's something in this season that wants to intrude, that is trying to intrude into what we're being bombarded with. That's what matters, that there's this intrusive message of the first Christmas that's still powerful, that offers hope, that's still available in our lives.''</p>
        <p>Our Towns E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: peappl@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
