<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Look It Up: Librarians Needed</title>
    <meta content="26NJLIBRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1637449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nussbaum, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D71030F935A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1221" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Look It Up: Librarians Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA NUSSBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nussbaum, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rutgers University offers only accredited library sciences program in state to address need to replace generation of librarians nearing retirement; plans online masters degree program in library and information sciences; many jobs now go unfilled; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLAUDIA SUMLER remembers sitting in a board meeting of the Public Library Association 10 years ago, looking around the table and realizing that she and every other librarian at the table were close to 50.</p>
        <p>''I thought, where are the younger faces?'' said Ms. Sumler, who is director of the Camden Country Library System, based in Voorhees. ''What's going to happen when we all retire together? As years went by, I could see this was getting worse and not better.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLAUDIA SUMLER remembers sitting in a board meeting of the Public Library Association 10 years ago, looking around the table and realizing that she and every other librarian at the table were close to 50.</p>
        <p>''I thought, where are the younger faces?'' said Ms. Sumler, who is director of the Camden Country Library System, based in Voorhees. ''What's going to happen when we all retire together? As years went by, I could see this was getting worse and not better.''</p>
        <p>What Ms. Sumler was seeing is alarming librarians from New Jersey to New Mexico; of the 125,000 librarians in the United States, almost half of them will reach retirement age by 2010. And in six years, 45 percent of the today's librarians will be 65, said Carol Brey-Casiano, a library director from El Paso, who is president of the American Library Association.</p>
        <p>Moreover, said Ms. Brey-Casiano, there are about 50 accredited library schools nationwide that turn out about 4,000 graduates a year, but that will not be enough to fill the anticipated openings.</p>
        <p>''The baby boomers are retiring,'' Ms. Brey-Casiano said. ''It's the natural progression. We need to somehow meet this demand.''</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, nearly half of the estimated 4,000 working librarians in schools, universities and public libraries will reach retirement age by 2015, according to Patricia Tumulty, executive director of the New Jersey Library Association.</p>
        <p>To try to meet the demand -- as well as the new technology -- Rutgers University, which offers the only accredited program in the state for library science majors, will begin offering an online masters degree program in library and information science next fall. Currently, about 325 library students graduate from Rutgers each year, and the plan is to add 40 online students in the fall and 20 in the spring over the next three years.</p>
        <p>Libraries around the state are already feeling the pinch. In Camden County, for example, officials began looking for a head of reader services in August, but only a few résumés initially came in, and they did not hire someone until earlier this month.</p>
        <p>In Ocean County, a position was advertised for a children's librarian for more than six months.</p>
        <p>''At times we received no résumés and at times we received one,'' said Kathleen Carr, who for three years has been director of human resources for the Ocean County library system. ''There's been problems recruiting qualified librarians all that time and a crucial shortage of children's librarians.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the position in Ocean County was filled by a woman who graduated from Drexel University in Philadelphia this month with a masters degree in library science. The starting salary is about $38,000 a year plus benefits, a 35-hour work week and 24 vacation days a year.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, salaries can go as high as $90,000 a year for experienced library directors. But with one graduate for every eight vacancies, even attractive positions are difficult to fill, Ms. Carr said.</p>
        <p>''People just aren't looking at this as a viable career,'' Ms. Carr said.</p>
        <p>Librarians are trying to meet the demand by establishing Web sites like one set up by the Central Jersey Regional Library Cooperative that portray librarians as something more than ladies in buns and black-rimmed glasses who keep saying ''shush.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the cooperative portrays librarians as dynamic seekers of information who are there to serve the public by teaching people how to find the material they need -- from teaching the elderly how to use computers to helping college graduates research the job market.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the case can also be made that libraries are not going out of business. In 2003, more than 41 million residents used New Jersey's public libraries, according to Tina Keresztury, an associate state librarian at the New Jersey State Library, an increase of 3 million people from the previous year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Keresztury said that one librarian in her 50's likes to use the comparison that you could fill Giants Stadium 519 times with the residents who used libraries last year, or that more people came to the libraries than to the casinos in Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>''We're not your grandmother's library," she said. ''They are community centers today. They are destinations. There's programming, art exhibits, book clubs and computer instruction.''</p>
        <p>The Central Jersey Regional Library Cooperative, one of four such cooperatives financed by the state, started a campaign five years ago to attract young people to the library profession.</p>
        <p>Connie Paul, director of the Central Jersey cooperative, said her group held open houses and established a Web site to interest potential librarians.</p>
        <p>In 2002, when Norma Blake became the New Jersey state librarian, she asked the Central Jersey cooperative to expand its recruiting efforts throughout state. It started with two brochures, one on choosing a career and one on changing careers.</p>
        <p>Today, there is a brochure aimed at teenagers and at students in grades four to six. In addition, the cooperative has started bilingual story times in 14 libraries in central New Jersey by employing high school and college students as storytellers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Paul, who spent much of her career as a school librarian in the Monmouth County schools before going to the cooperative, plans to retire in about five years, when she reaches 65. Until then, she said, she wants to insure that more people learn about library careers.</p>
        <p>''We are trying hard to recruit people,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Karen Novick, director of professional developments studies for the school of communication, information and library studies at Rutgers University, said she frequently gets calls from school districts seeking librarians, and that those in urban areas have been among the hardest hit. To help ease the shortage, the federal Institute of Museum and Library Services gave a $969,773 three-year grant to Rutgers to finance the online degree program it is starting in the fall.</p>
        <p>''We are just unable to educate enough people to fill the need,'' said Dr. Nicholas J. Belkin, director of the masters in library and information science program at Rutgers.</p>
        <p>For now, Dr. Belkin said, the school accepts about 120 library students each year, and that does not have room for all of the qualified applicants.</p>
        <p>''They are all very qualified and we don't want to turn them away," he said, adding that the school is operating at capacity.</p>
        <p>The hope is that the online program will be able to serve qualified students who want to pursue degrees but cannot get to the Rutgers campus on a regular basis.</p>
        <p>Ms. Brey-Casiano, the president of the American Library Association, explained that she took her first job working at a library while in high school in Springfield, Ill. Her assignment was to type up library cards.</p>
        <p>''The people were so wonderful about really nurturing me along,'' she said. ''I loved it. It was a great orientation.''</p>
        <p>COMMUNITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
