<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Couples Takes Lead in Honda</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514354"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HONDA CLASSIC GOLF TOURNAMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAZ, JAIME</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D6163FF936A25750C0A964958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Couples Takes Lead in Honda</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAIME DIAZ,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAZ, JAIME</byline>
      <dateline>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla., March 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although ageless Raymond Floyd stumbled slightly this afternoon, his tag-team partner, the presently peerless Fred Couples, took up the slack and rushed into the lead after three rounds of the Honda Classic.</p>
        <p>As Floyd was finally losing a lead after five consecutive rounds of being on top of the leader board over two tournaments, Couples today shot a seven-under-par 65 for a total of 14-under 202. That was one shot better than Mark Brooks, who burned up the Weston Hill Country Club with a course-record 64 today, and two ahead of Blaine McCallister, who had his third straight 68.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although ageless Raymond Floyd stumbled slightly this afternoon, his tag-team partner, the presently peerless Fred Couples, took up the slack and rushed into the lead after three rounds of the Honda Classic.</p>
        <p>As Floyd was finally losing a lead after five consecutive rounds of being on top of the leader board over two tournaments, Couples today shot a seven-under-par 65 for a total of 14-under 202. That was one shot better than Mark Brooks, who burned up the Weston Hill Country Club with a course-record 64 today, and two ahead of Blaine McCallister, who had his third straight 68.</p>
        <p>In sum, it means that at least one member of the dynamic Floyd-Couples duo, who made up the United States' best team at the Ryder Cup last year, have led or had a share of the lead in the last nine rounds played on the PGA Tour. The 32-year-old Couples won at Los Angeles two weeks ago, and the 49-year-old Floyd won last week at the Doral Ryder Open.</p>
        <p>At Doral, Floyd led Couples by three going into the last round and hung on to win by two. Now, with Floyd tied at 205 with Greg Hickman and Corey Pavin, the tables are reversed, a fact that does not dishearten Floyd. 71 for Floyd</p>
        <p>"I know how well Freddy is playing; he played fabulous today," said Floyd, who had a third-round 71. "Today, I wasn't as sharp as I have been. I just hope I got a bad round out of my system. Any player, all he wants is to be in position to win the tournament. Three shots is not insurmountable."</p>
        <p>The way Couples has been playing though, the last thing he needs is a head start. Since last year's United States Open, Couples has finished in the top six in 15 of 20 tournaments. He has been in the 60's in his last seven rounds, and 21 of his last 27 rounds. And more important than any statistics, he is seeming more and more impervious to the pressure that used to dissolve his game.</p>
        <p>"I'm putting better than usual, I'm driving the ball well, and I'm playing more consistent," Couples said. "I'm not making too many mistakes, and if I do, it doesn't seem to bother me."</p>
        <p>Couples gave credence to his last statement today when he missed a two-foot putt on the 11th hole for his only bogey of the day. Rather than getting upset or losing confidence, he promptly came back with his sixth and seventh birdies of the day on the next two holes to regain control. Explosive Round by Brooks</p>
        <p>Floyd and Couples will almost certainly be the gallery favorites, but with 12 players within six shots of the lead, the Honda is much more than a two-man tournament.</p>
        <p>Brooks had the most explosive round of the day, beginning with an eagle-3 on the par-5 first hole, followed by birdies at the second and fourth. Brooks had a minor disaster at the par-4 sixth, where his 7-iron approach rolled into a steep swale in front of the green. His first attempt to pitch onto the green failed to make it up the hill and rolled back to him. His next pitch made the green, from where he two-putted for a double-bogey 6.</p>
        <p>But Brooks demonstrated resilience that dwarfed even Couples by getting birdies on five of the next six holes. He then held firm over Weston Hills's tough finishing stretch before finally birdieing the 585-yard par-5 18th.</p>
        <p>"The last five holes here, you really have to play," Floyd said. "The key is to go out on the first 13 holes and get your scoring done, and then try to play the rest of them in par. Anybody that gets any birdies on those last few holes will really be doing something."</p>
        <p>And probably what will be required to beat Fred Couples. Daniel Extends Lead</p>
        <p>TUCSON, Ariz., March 14 (AP) -- Beth Daniel birdied the first three holes today and shot a five-under-par 67 to extend her lead to four strokes after three rounds of the Ping-Welch's Championship.</p>
        <p>Daniel, who has won 27 tournaments in 14 years, was at 11-under 205 after 54 holes. That left her comfortably ahead of Pat Bradley, Dale Eggeling and Brandie Burton.</p>
        <p>Bradley, the only player ahead of Daniel on the Ladies Professional Golf Association's career-money list and the newest of 12 members of the L.P.G.A. Hall of Fame, put an end to memories of her 76 the day before. She knocked six shots off par on the last 10 holes with four birdies and an eagle on the 458-yard 18th for a six-under 66.</p>
        <p>Alice Ritzman, Colleen Walker, Hollis Stacy and Anne-Marie Palli stayed within hailing distance of the lead at 211, six shots back. Kris Tschetter was all alone at 212.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
