<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Still Suit, Suit, Suit For the Home Team</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARAMOUNT COMMUNICATIONS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBRENNER, GEORGE M 3D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D8113EF936A25750C0A964958260" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Still Suit, Suit, Suit For the Home Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla., March 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Periodically over the last several months, George Steinbrenner has privately threatened to file the lawsuit of all lawsuits, the King Kong lawsuit, against Commissioner Fay Vincent, challenging their 1990 agreement that sent Steinbrenner paddling to baseball's Elba.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees owner turns his threats into reality and files the suit, he would not be the owner very long. According to lawyers for major league baseball, the commissioner would almost certainly throw Steinbrenner out of baseball, and then maybe Paramount Communications could buy the Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Periodically over the last several months, George Steinbrenner has privately threatened to file the lawsuit of all lawsuits, the King Kong lawsuit, against Commissioner Fay Vincent, challenging their 1990 agreement that sent Steinbrenner paddling to baseball's Elba.</p>
        <p>If the Yankees owner turns his threats into reality and files the suit, he would not be the owner very long. According to lawyers for major league baseball, the commissioner would almost certainly throw Steinbrenner out of baseball, and then maybe Paramount Communications could buy the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Paramount's effort to purchase the team, which the corporate giant confirmed last week, would be meaningless if no one wanted to sell -- either Steinbrenner, who owns 55 percent, or the dozen-and-a-half limited partners, who own the other 45 percent.</p>
        <p>For now, Steinbrenner isn't selling, so Paramount isn't buying. But there are circumstances under which Steinbrenner might sell, or be forced to sell. If no limited partner came forward to buy the team from Steinbrenner under the partnership agreement's right-of-first-refusal provision, Paramount would be a natural buyer. But the company, which owns the Knicks, the Rangers, Madison Square Garden and Madison Square Garden cable, most likely would face serious problems in gaining approval from the owners of the other major league clubs.</p>
        <p>The owners, who a few years ago rejected a television company's proposed purchase of the Texas Rangers, could oppose a Paramount purchase because of the cable part of its stable of enterprises. The Saga of the Suits</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner has acknowledged meeting with Paramount executives. He has also said he is not leaving the Yankees or baseball. But Steinbrenner's link to the Yankees and baseball has been lean for the last 19 months, after his ouster as managing partner of the team because of his relationship with Howard Spira, an admitted gambler who was convicted last year of extortion.</p>
        <p>The refrain, by now, is familiar:</p>
        <p>Vincent has told Steinbrenner he will not meet with him to discuss reinstatement until Leonard Kleinman, the Yankees' dismissed chief operating officer, drops his lawsuit against the commissioner, a suit that Steinbrenner instigated and funded.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner says he has no control over Kleinman and that Vincent should meet with him despite the continued existence of the lawsuit. The commissioner, however, has held to his ground rule, which means Steinbrenner won't be returning in the near future. Waiting for the Judge</p>
        <p>Judge Leonard B. Sand of United States District Court in Manhattan could have a decision on the commissioner's motion for summary judgment in the Kleinman suit by late April or early May. If he rejects the motion, a trial would be held late this year or early next year. If the judge grants the motion, Kleinman could appeal, and that process could take the case into 1993.</p>
        <p>One major league official said he didn't believe that Steinbrenner would sell the team because his ownership of the Yankees defines his existence. If, however, Steinbrenner concludes that he won't regain his position as managing partner, and he cannot arouse interest in either of his two sons to operate the club, he could decide to transform his 55 percent into millions of dollars and go home.</p>
        <p>Or given the same set of circumstances, he could decide to file the big lawsuit. That would prompt Vincent to expel him for violating both their agreement, in which Steinbrenner agreed not to sue the commissioner, and the major league agreement, which prohibits owners from suing the commissioner.</p>
        <p>If either combination of events occurs, Paramount would pounce on Steinbrenner's share. Unless one or more of the limited partners exercised their right of first refusal and somehow put together enough millions to make the purchase themselves. Is Paramount Acceptable?</p>
        <p>Assuming, on the other hand, that Paramount would prevail, how might they fare with the other owners?</p>
        <p>Stating the prevailing objection to ownership by television interests, one lawyer active in ownership matters said: "What could Paramount do vis-a-vis the baseball club that might not be in the team's best interest but could be in the company's best interest? They could want to make the team better to attract viewers and have a $70 million payroll. It would have a major adverse effect on other clubs."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Paramount, not bound by the salary cap that exists in the National Basketball Association, could make Steinbrenner look like a miser. They could, for example, sign Barry Bonds and Ruben Sierra as free agents, putting them in the outfield with Danny Tartabull. Paramount, after all, is in the entertainment business, and that would be an entertaining outfield.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Cubs' recent veto of realignment of the National League's two divisions illustrated the conflicting interests that a television owner faces. From a baseball standpoint, realignment makes sense, and the other three teams involved approved a shift. The group included the St. Louis Cardinals, who operate in the same time zone as the Cubs.</p>
        <p>But the Cubs show their games on a superstation owned by their owners, the Tribune Company. And the Tribune Company didn't want the Cubs moving into the Western Division, which would have meant having to televise more games from the West Coast with later starting times. On the Other Hand</p>
        <p>The owners could view Paramount as that kind of an undesirable. Or they could see the obviously successful corporation as a stabilizing factor in one of the major leagues' most important franchises.</p>
        <p>"Having a good team in New York is good for baseball," one official acknowledged. "They have good management."</p>
        <p>Given the deterioration of the Yankees in the last decade, Paramount could be seen as an attractive alternative to the Steinbrenner regime.</p>
        <p>Unless all of the factors fall into place, however, Paramount might have to be content with televising Yankee games and paying out the rest of its $486 million commitment over the next nine years.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
