<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Is Set To Back Ban On Cloning Of Humans</title>
    <meta content="Y27CLO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/27/politics/27CLON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">House of Representatives (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cloning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE153CF934A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Is Set To Back Ban On Cloning Of Humans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">House Is Set to Make Cloning of Humans a Crime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL GAY STOLBERG</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dolly the sheep is dead, but the political controversy she engendered lives in the House of Representatives, where lawmakers are expected on Thursday to pass a bill making human cloning a crime.</p>
        <p>The Republican-backed measure would outlaw cloning experiments -- or, more precisely, the scientific procedure known as somatic cell nuclear transfer -- either for baby making or medical research. Scientists who cloned human embryos would face up to 10 years in prison and a $1 million fine. The bill would also prohibit the importing of medical therapies derived from cloning research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dolly the sheep is dead, but the controversy she created lives on in the House, where lawmakers are expected to pass a bill that bans human cloning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dolly the sheep is dead, but the political controversy she engendered lives in the House of Representatives, where lawmakers are expected on Thursday to pass a bill making human cloning a crime.</p>
        <p>The Republican-backed measure would outlaw cloning experiments -- or, more precisely, the scientific procedure known as somatic cell nuclear transfer -- either for baby making or medical research. Scientists who cloned human embryos would face up to 10 years in prison and a $1 million fine. The bill would also prohibit the importing of medical therapies derived from cloning research.</p>
        <p>The bill is nearly identical to legislation that passed the House in the last Congress by more than 100 votes in July 2001, and it has the strong support of President Bush. The real question is what will happen in the Senate, where lawmakers are split over whether to ban human cloning entirely or to prohibit reproductive cloning while allowing cloning for research to proceed.</p>
        <p>The Senate voted once, in 1998, to reject a broad cloning ban, and last year, the Democratic-controlled Senate would not take up the bill passed by the House. That will change now that Republicans are in charge.</p>
        <p>''Our job has been made harder because of the elections,'' said Dan Perry, director of the Alliance for Aging Research, an advocacy group that supports cloning for medical research. Mr. Perry said he and others had been lobbying heavily to persuade lawmakers that ''there is a difference between cloning a human and cloning cells in a dish that could lead to cures that save lives.''</p>
        <p>The debate over cloning is fraught with ethical issues. Should the ban pass, it would be a historic decision to criminalize a type of scientific research. ''In my view, that's the equivalent of book burning,'' said Representative Anna G. Eshoo, a California Democrat who supports an alternative measure that would ban reproductive cloning only. The bill is sponsored by Representative James C. Greenwood, a moderate Republican from Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The controversy pits scientists, biotech companies and patients -- who say the research holds the promise of treatments for diseases including diabetes and Alzheimer's -- against conservatives and some religious leaders, who denounce experimenting on human embryos as immoral and tantamount to murder.</p>
        <p>''We're having a debate about whether society can place any ethical limit whatever on the powers the new biology has given to us,'' said Richard Doerflinger, an official of the United States Conference of Catholic Bishops, which strongly opposes cloning for any reason.</p>
        <p>But the debate does not fall entirely along party lines. Some prominent Republicans, including Senator Orrin G. Hatch of Utah, support research cloning. Mr. Hatch, who has proposed legislation that would ban reproductive cloning only, recently received a letter from Nancy Reagan, the wife of former President Ronald Reagan, who has Alzheimer's disease.</p>
        <p>''Orrin, there are so many diseases that can be cured, or at least helped, that we can't turn our back on this,'' Mrs. Reagan wrote. ''We've lost so much time already. I can't bear to lose any more.''</p>
        <p>Ever since the announcement of the birth of Dolly, the first cloned mammal, in 1997, many politicians and some philosophers have warned that cloned babies -- infants that are, in essence, genetic replicas of adults -- would follow. Late last year, the Raelians, a religious sect that contends that space travelers created the human race, claimed to have produced the first human clone, but the baby never materialized, and most experts now say the announcement was a hoax.</p>
        <p>The Raelians' announcement, coupled with the recent death of Dolly, which had a lung infection, is certain to figure into the House debate. Dolly's creators say her death on Feb. 14 was probably not related to being a clone, but cloning opponents are skeptical.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
