<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A War of Succession With 70's Soul</title>
    <meta content="27MASL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/27/books/coll27MASL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D8143CF934A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A War of Succession With 70's Soul</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A War of Succession With 70's Soul</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOUL CIRCUS  By George P. Pelecanos  341 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's no great feat to begin a new mystery right where the last one in the series left off. What is harder -- and what George P. Pelecanos does so easily in his latest, ''Soul Circus'' -- is to bring established characters back to such a warm welcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>George P. Pelecanos's new novel is both tragedy and thriller, especially as it describes the all but accidental casualties of urban warfare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOUL CIRCUS  By George P. Pelecanos  341 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's no great feat to begin a new mystery right where the last one in the series left off. What is harder -- and what George P. Pelecanos does so easily in his latest, ''Soul Circus'' -- is to bring established characters back to such a warm welcome.</p>
        <p>The central figure in this author's most recent books is Derek Strange, a Washington private detective in his 50's whose taste for smooth, tender, optimistic soul records of the 1970's is as emphatic as his moral code. Derek on the job embodies the spirit of the music he loves. To the sounds of the O'Jays and the Chi-Lites and Harold Melvin and the Blue Notes, he keeps his considerable cool and sustains faith in the kind of Love Train that could make this a better world.</p>
        <p>But the world of ''Soul Circus'' needs a lot more than music to improve it. Once again Mr. Pelecanos zeroes in on reckless gangsters in Washington's predominantly black districts, like Anacostia, which ''was the most beautiful section of town and also the ugliest, often at the same time.'' And with the same kind of narrative advocacy that John Grisham brings to tort reform in his latest hit, Mr. Pelecanos looks across the state line into ''Mer-land'' and sees where trigger-happy Washington toughs are getting their guns.</p>
        <p>''Soul Circus,'' which thanks three Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms employees and a clergyman in its acknowledgments, describes the gangland power vacuum created by the arrest of Granville Oliver at the end of its predecessor, ''Hell to Pay.'' Oliver's incarceration has left all manner of drug dealers and hangers-on jockeying for position and aligning themselves with new power brokers. And when the players in this story choose to stake out turf and assert their manhood, guns are an essential part of their transactions.</p>
        <p>One of the new book's principals is Ulysses Foreman, a former cop with a lucrative new gun-dealing business. He now lives within a mile of Anacostia in a fairly rural setting. ''You could even hear crickets chirping on summer nights,'' the book reports, ''though those sounds were sometimes mixed with the occasional crack of gunshots riding up from Southeast, if the wind was right.'' It is to this book's credit that Ulysses is a vital, entertaining figure as well as a symptom of social ills.</p>
        <p>For all the weapons floating through ''Soul Circus'' -- in one scene, Mr. Pelecanos simply describes how a criminal drives a young woman with no prior convictions to Maryland and has her buy him a gun, because she can pass the legally required background check -- this is not a book built on violence. Instead, Mr. Pelecanos once again looks for the roots of angry, bullying behavior and examines them through the knowing eyes of Derek Strange.</p>
        <p>Like the novels of Richard Price, whose influence is evident here, ''Soul Circus'' is both tragedy and thriller, especially as it describes the all but accidental casualties of urban warfare. Much of the trouble in this book is kicked off by the insecurities of a little guy (''Boy looked like a water rat ain't had nothin' to eat for, like, forever'') filled with pent-up resentment and trampled pride.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Pelecanos continues to display a sharp eye for detail and a terrific ear for street dialogue. (''Two of my boys just got deaded by one of your guns; you know this.'') He further culminates an Elmore Leonardesque wry economy and a lilting way with back-and-forth banter, never more so than when Strange hits the streets with his younger white partner, Terry Quinn. (Terry is so white, at least by Derek's standards, that he has sex to the music of Neil Young.)</p>
        <p>''Careful, man,'' Quinn says, as Derek goes into musical raptures while driving. ''You keep shutting your eyes when you're gettin' all soulful like that, you're gonna get us killed.'' Derek replies that he doesn't need to look because he can drive from memory.</p>
        <p>Derek turns even more reckless late in the novel, when it becomes payback time for some of the story's most heinous characters. And Mr. Pelecanos, in letting Derek gruesomely humiliate a man who has disrespected a woman, risks letting his hero's avenging virtuousness go too far. Mr. Pelecanos also treads a thin line between cogent argument and oversimplification when he ascribes the woes of young men in ''Soul Circus'' to the lack of worthwhile father figures -- and lets Derek try to pick up that slack. But in the end, Derek proves as soul-stirring and eminently likable as his favorite songs.</p>
        <p>''Soul Circus'' provides some wrenching turns of plot, even as it assures the reader that this series is alive and well. Once again, Mr. Pelecanos ends a book with a clear, promising notion of where a subsequent one will start. And once again, he will leave readers eagerly awaiting his next move.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
