<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DeLay PAC Draws a Fine And Agrees To Shut Down</title>
    <meta content="21delay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/21/washington/21delay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1777407"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Election Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Delay, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA173FF932A15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DeLay PAC Draws a Fine And Agrees To Shut Down</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">DeLay PAC Draws a Fine and Agrees to Shut Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The political action committee used as a vehicle to power in Congress by Representative Tom DeLay has agreed to pay $115,000 in fines for violations of federal campaign rules and will close its doors permanently, the Federal Election Commission said Thursday.</p>
        <p>According to an agreement with the commission, Mr. DeLay's committee, Americans for a Republican Majority, agreed to the fines to settle accusations that it had failed to report more than $322,000 in debts and other obligations to its vendors and had misrepresented more than $240,000 in other financial activity in 2001 and 2002.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A committee that helped Representative Tom DeLay make millions of dollars in contributions to political allies agreed to pay fines for violations of federal campaign rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The political action committee used as a vehicle to power in Congress by Representative Tom DeLay has agreed to pay $115,000 in fines for violations of federal campaign rules and will close its doors permanently, the Federal Election Commission said Thursday.</p>
        <p>According to an agreement with the commission, Mr. DeLay's committee, Americans for a Republican Majority, agreed to the fines to settle accusations that it had failed to report more than $322,000 in debts and other obligations to its vendors and had misrepresented more than $240,000 in other financial activity in 2001 and 2002.</p>
        <p>The pact did not provide a timetable for the shutdown of the committee, which for years was Mr. DeLay's chief fund-raising arm, allowing him to make millions of dollars in contributions to political allies who then supported his rise in the Republican leadership in Congress.</p>
        <p>The committee's demise had been widely predicted as a result of Mr. DeLay's decision to resign from the House. The resignation was linked to his indictment in Texas on charges that he violated state election laws, as well as the guilty plea this year by the lobbyist Jack Abramoff, a close friend who has confessed to conspiring to corrupt members of Congress. Two former aides to Mr. DeLay have pleaded guilty in the investigation.</p>
        <p>As a result of the Texas indictment, Mr. DeLay was forced to step down last year as the House majority leader.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay's daughter, Dani DeLay Ferro, said in a statement on her father's behalf that the settlement with the Federal Election Commission was ''a voluntary resolution of issues discovered in an audit made public last year.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ferro, a top political adviser to her father, said, ''It concerns highly technical F.E.C. reporting rules, which due to their complexity, the commission has since reformed and simplified.'' She said the political action committee ''resolved all issues in the audit and intends to voluntarily terminate.''</p>
        <p>The election commission released an audit last year that outlined a series of ethics laws violations by Americans for a Republican Majority, including the illegal use of $200,000 in so-called soft money political contributions, which are relatively easy to raise in large amounts, for overhead expenditures. The commission found the payments should have been made from pools of ''hard money,'' which is harder to collect because it is more tightly regulated.</p>
        <p>Specialists in federal election law said that while the election commission fines were large, they were not extraordinary.</p>
        <p>''It's certainly substantial, but it is not out of line with what the F.E.C. has been imposing recently,'' said Stan Brand, a former Democratic Congressional aide who specializes in ethics law. ''The fines have been getting heftier and heftier.''</p>
        <p>Jan Baran, a Republican lawyer in Washington, said the $115,000 fines were ''not chopped liver, but it's not a record by any stretch of the imagination.'' Mr. Baran said there was no surprise in the decision to close Americans for a Republican Majority, since ''with DeLay's retirement, there was not much prospect for raising more money.''</p>
        <p>The election commission said the agreement with Mr. DeLay's committee had been prompted by a complaint by Citizens for Responsibility and Ethics in Washington, a private watchdog group that has called for corruption investigations of several members of Congress, especially those tied to Mr. Abramoff.</p>
        <p>Melanie Sloan, the group's executive director, said in an interview that the shutdown of Americans for a Republican Majority was a final ''demonstration of the end of the DeLay era -- because all of DeLay's power really derived from his fund-raising prowess.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
