<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Gifts, Welcome and Unwelcome</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="166373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, RON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB1538F932A05754C0A96E948260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Gifts, Welcome and Unwelcome</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON ALEXANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALEXANDER, RON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A CROQUET set, Lorna R. Cameron thought. Yes, a croquet set would be an inspired house gift for the weekend she was invited to her friends' new place in the Poconos. There, she was led to believe, she would find a lovely green ''English-type rolling lawn'' in front of the house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A CROQUET set, Lorna R. Cameron thought. Yes, a croquet set would be an inspired house gift for the weekend she was invited to her friends' new place in the Poconos. There, she was led to believe, she would find a lovely green ''English-type rolling lawn'' in front of the house.</p>
        <p>A CROQUET set, Lorna R. Cameron thought. Yes, a croquet set would be an inspired house gift for the weekend she was invited to her friends' new place in the Poconos. There, she was led to believe, she would find a lovely green ''English-type rolling lawn'' in front of the house.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Ms. Cameron, who lives in Brooklyn Heights, waited until the last minute before dashing into Hammacher Schlemmer to make her purchase. To her dismay, it set her back $225.50 plus tax. That was nothing compared with the dismay she felt when she saw the ''English-type rolling lawn.''</p>
        <p>''It was scraggly and rocky and full of crater-sized holes and ugly shrubs,'' she said. Needless to say, the croquet set never saw action on that weekend, if ever.</p>
        <p>That is, admittedly, an atypical story on the hazards of choosing gifts for weekend hosts and hostesses. But this, after all, is the time of year for that perennial quandary: What to take?</p>
        <p>''Nobody really knows what to bring, so they go out of their way to seek the unusual,'' said Viola Sylbert, a fashion designer whose summer home is in Bridgehampton, L.I. This summer Ms. Sylbert has been geting ''lots and lots'' of imported oils and exotic vinegars, she said.</p>
        <p>''Walnut oil, balsamic vinegar, tarragon vinegar, basil vinegar . . . You name it, I've gotten it,'' said Ms. Sylbert, who in summers past has been the recipient of ''Museum of Modern Art things, ice tongs and such.''</p>
        <p>What she doesn't want: ''Large ceramic objects.''</p>
        <p>Cut flowers are at the top of the ''please don't bring us these gifts'' list, according to an informal poll.</p>
        <p>''They take forever to arrange,'' said Murray Fishman, a textile designer who owns a farmhouse in New Milford, Conn.</p>
        <p>''It disrupts the cocktail hour,'' said Jean Tailer from her home in Southampton, L.I. ''You have to stop everything to display them.''</p>
        <p>BUT Mrs. Tailer would be delighted to receive ''a lovely orchid plant, especially if it's white,'' as well as ''things that can be used, such as Dom Perignon, Moet &amp; Chandon, French soaps, lovely bath oils.''</p>
        <p>Marylou Whitney was impressed with the paperweight with a rattlesnake's head inside but really wouldn't mind if she never got another. While she does enjoy receiving ''anything linen,'' what she appreciates most of all, she said, is that guests at her home in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., honor her request not to tip the staff.</p>
        <p>Cutesy gifts are not appreciated, either. ''You try to remember to bring them out of the back of the linen closet when the givers return,'' said Barbara Kling, who owns a public relations firm in New York.</p>
        <p>Couldn't she say they broke? ''Good heavens, no,'' she replied. ''They may buy you a replacement!''</p>
        <p>Among the other gifts that hosts wish their guests would pass up: peanut-butter-making machines. ''They've replaced Cuisinarts as the big kitchen gift,'' said Deran Mizrakjian, an advertising executive who has a weekend home in Germantown, N.Y., and three peanut-butter-making machines on a kitchen shelf.</p>
        <p>In some circles, energy-promoting crystals are clearly very in. By mid-July, Tony Ingrao, an antiques dealer who summers in Montauk, L.I., had already received six at his place, which is now filled with positive vibes.</p>
        <p>INVITE Alfredo Ortiz-Murias for the weekend, and you'll receive a bonsai tree. ''I understand not too many people give them,'' conceded Mr. Ortiz-Murias, the president of Casita Maria, a settlement house in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Trays!'' said Janice Levin. ''Trays are always useful gifts for serving your guests breakfast in bed or lunch around the pool. Beach towels are useful, too. My guests seem to take them home.''</p>
        <p>What Mrs. Levin is ''not crazy about getting'' are baskets of jellies and crackers or ''food of any kind.''</p>
        <p>That doesn't seem to be the feeling on Fire Island, where stores are few and the items costly. There, perishable foods and paper goods are particularly welcome. ''Believe me, three melons are more appreciated than another corkscrew,'' said Helen Kornblau of Fair Harbor.</p>
        <p>Hollywood DiRusso, a makeup artist and stylist, can be depended on to show up with boxes of cereal. ''I hate precious foods,'' she said. ''The cereals I bring are always high-fiber. And perfect for nibbling when you're stuck in traffic on the Long Island Expressway.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
