<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Star Vehicles Sometimes Get Detoured</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="125039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="TV VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LAURA LANSING SLEPT HERE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SIDE BY SIDE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE123BF935A35750C0A96E948260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Star Vehicles Sometimes Get Detoured</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John J. O'Connor</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Although at times the small screen seems to be overflowing with young marrieds, adorable children and teen-age heartthrobs, television is in many ways proving a boon to what might diplomatically be called the ''veteran performer.'' This is the actor who once may have enjoyed considerable success in television and/or films but now, having reached a ''certain age'' or run into a luckless stretch of unemployment, finds decent job offers more and more scarce.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Although at times the small screen seems to be overflowing with young marrieds, adorable children and teen-age heartthrobs, television is in many ways proving a boon to what might diplomatically be called the ''veteran performer.'' This is the actor who once may have enjoyed considerable success in television and/or films but now, having reached a ''certain age'' or run into a luckless stretch of unemployment, finds decent job offers more and more scarce.</p>
        <p>Although at times the small screen seems to be overflowing with young marrieds, adorable children and teen-age heartthrobs, television is in many ways proving a boon to what might diplomatically be called the ''veteran performer.'' This is the actor who once may have enjoyed considerable success in television and/or films but now, having reached a ''certain age'' or run into a luckless stretch of unemployment, finds decent job offers more and more scarce. Show business still is, and no doubt always will be, a tough game, but television has brightened the picture considerably as far as seasoned talent is concerned.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the sheer quantity of material devoured by the TV machine each year guarantees a steady and probably increasing demand for talent. In terms of employment possibilities, television is where the action is. Also, as the nation's population profile gets older, there is a growing demand for the kind of ''mature'' actors with whom a large and influential segment of the population can identify. And, finally, there is the nostalgia factor. Aging audiences love to see their favorite old shows resurrected with as many of the original performers as can be found. ''Reunions'' of various sorts are proving surprisingly popular in the ratings. Occasional movies starring Raymond Burr in his familiar role of ''Perry Mason'' have already gone through eight editions on NBC, with more on the way.</p>
        <p>Hardly a week goes by without veterans of stature being given a fresh showcase on television. Bette Davis and Helen Hayes have been starring in TV movies for years. Katharine Hepburn, who has taken to the electronic medium with characteristic gusto, can be seen tomorrow night at 9 on NBC in ''Laura Lansing Slept Here,'' in which she plays with inimitable relish a fabulously successful novelist who, wanting to see how ''normal'' people live these days, moves in with an understandably stunned family in Hicksville, L. I. It is, quite shamelessly, a Hepburn vehicle, and she takes it for a feisty ride.</p>
        <p>Not all performers are so fortunate. There are the occasional mishaps. Consider, for example, ''Side by Side'' on CBS tonight at 9. Someone had the clever idea of recruiting Milton Berle, Sid Caesar and Danny Thomas to depict three old friends who refuse to go quietly into that dull night of retirement. They have grown up together, lived all their lives in Brooklyn and still indulge in a little basketball at the local gym. When Louie (Caesar) is forced to retire from his garment-center job at the age of 65, he discovers that Abe (Berle) lost his sales job months earlier and that the widower Charlie (Thomas) is desperately lonely. They are consoled by the sympathetic owner of Moe's Delicatessen, who is played by none other than Morey Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>Refusing to be counted out, the inveterate jokesters decide to go into business for themselves. The gimmick: making sophisticated clothes for people over 65. It's a reasonably promising premise, but the story by Rosemary Edelman and Anthony Velona quickly disintegrates into what resembles a cliche contest. There's only so much mileage to be got from the fact that Mr. Thomas and Mr. Berle smoke huge cigars, much to the annoyance of Mr. Caesar. As the scenario becomes more frantic, all concerned are less funny. These guys and their women - Marjorie Lord, Georgann Johnson and Edith Fields -deserve and are capable of far better. This particular vehicle self-destructs.</p>
        <p>It's not that the general run of prime-time entertainment is awash in profound concepts. But, at a minimum, there is an element of reasonable sturdiness. Andy Griffith, for instance, has found life after Mayberry as the title character in NBC's ''Matlock,'' a wily Atlanta lawyer who, in the Perry Mason tradition, wins his cases in court week after week. And William Conrad, once the portly hero of ''Cannon,'' has put on even more weight and is having a decent run in CBS's ''Jake &amp; the Fatman.''</p>
        <p>The British, as usual, seem to have a knack for doing this sort of thing better, regularly providing veteran stars with productions of unquestioned quality. In the decidedly upper echelons can be found Peggy Ashcroft in ''The Jewel in the Crown'' and Laurence Olivier and John Gielgud in ''Brideshead Revisited.'' A ''small'' movie called ''December Flower,'' directed by Stephen Frears (''My Beautiful Laundrette''), a simple tale about a newly widowed woman going to visit her aging aunt, delivered memorable performances by Jean Simmons and Mona Washbourne.</p>
        <p>And the adaptations of Agatha Christie's Miss Marple stories, recently seen here on PBS's ''Mystery!'' series, have made a star out of an octogenarian actress named Joan Hickson. One of the tales, ''At Bertram's Hotel,'' features several delightful scenes with Ms. Hickson and the formidable Joan Greenwood, who died a few months after production was completed.</p>
        <p>That lofty level of quality and rewarding experience can also be found, at least occasionally, on American television. Several weeks ago, for instance, on a ''Hallmark Hall of Fame'' presentation on CBS, Jessica Tandy and Hume Cronyn starred in ''Foxfire,'' adapted from the play about Appalachia they had performed on stage. Two fine performances were recorded for posterity, and, in the process, the production garnered remarkably strong ratings.</p>
        <p>The opportunities provided by television for seasoned talent are obviously uneven and perhaps even treacherous at times. But the possibilities are encouraging, not least for viewers.</p>
        <p>TV VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
