<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. May Delay Departure Of Some Troops in Iraq</title>
    <meta content="Y08MIL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/08/politics/08MILI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1572633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: THE MILITARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sadr, Moktada Al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7D61438F93BA35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. May Delay Departure Of Some Troops in Iraq</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. May Delay Departure of Some Troops in Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">This article was reported and written by Douglas Jehl, Eric Schmitt, and David E. Sanger.; Douglas Jehl and David E. Sanger reported from Washington and Eric Schmitt from New York.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas; Sanger, David E; Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Sec Donald H Rumsfeld signals that Pentagon might delay bringing home as many as 25,000 soldiers as scheduled from Iraq, even as new troops meant to replace them are arriving; cites need for 'seasoned troops' after days of intense combat in both Shiite and Sunni cities; military officials say some reinforced American troops in Baghdad area will probably be sent to cities in southern Iraq to help other occupation forces put down insurrection by forces loyal to Moktada al-Sadr; military moves reflect deep sense of concern by Bush administration and American commanders about deteriorating situation in Iraq, where Sadr's militant Shiite followers have added second front to anti-American campaign previously limited to Sunni insurgents (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After days of intense combat in both Shiite and Sunni cities in Iraq, the Pentagon signaled on Wednesday that it would probably delay bringing home as many as 25,000 soldiers from the First Armored Division as scheduled, even as the new troops meant to replace them are arriving.</p>
        <p>Some of the reinforced American troops in the Baghdad area will probably be sent to cities in southern Iraq to help other occupation forces put down an insurrection by forces loyal to a rebellious Shiite cleric, Moktada al-Sadr, military officials said Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pentagon signaled that it would probably delay bringing home some 25,000 soldiers from the First Armored Division as scheduled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After days of intense combat in both Shiite and Sunni cities in Iraq, the Pentagon signaled on Wednesday that it would probably delay bringing home as many as 25,000 soldiers from the First Armored Division as scheduled, even as the new troops meant to replace them are arriving.</p>
        <p>Some of the reinforced American troops in the Baghdad area will probably be sent to cities in southern Iraq to help other occupation forces put down an insurrection by forces loyal to a rebellious Shiite cleric, Moktada al-Sadr, military officials said Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The military moves reflected a deep sense of concern by the Bush administration and American commanders about the deteriorating situation in Iraq, where the new wave of attacks by Mr. Sadr's Shiite followers has added a second front to an anti-American campaign previously limited to Sunni insurgents.</p>
        <p>At the Pentagon on Wednesday afternoon, Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld said that postponing the return home of ''seasoned troops'' was part of a plan ''to systematically address the situations we are facing.''</p>
        <p>The challenge of taking on Shiites in addition to Sunni insurgents was clearly a complication that President Bush and his aides did not expect, prompting a day of emergency meetings between Mr. Bush, who was beginning his Easter vacation at his ranch in Texas, and senior military commanders and Bush administration officials in Iraq and in Washington via a videoconference.</p>
        <p>And the new challenge comes as Condoleezza Rice, the national security adviser, is scheduled to testify on Thursday about what the administration knew about the potential for terror attacks before Sept. 11, 2001.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of balls in the air this week,'' one senior official said. ''And no one around here can tell you where they are going to land.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, White House officials officials tried to portray an atmosphere of calm, saying there was no discussion about having Mr. Bush return early from his vacation in Crawford. They also tried to put down critiques -- many fueled by Democrats -- that with less than 12 weeks to go before the planned transfer of sovereignty to Iraqis on June 30, Mr. Bush still cannot explain who will be taking control of the country.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, some Republican lawmakers, including Senator John McCain of Arizona, urged the administration to send more troops to Iraq to address the security challenge. But Senator Robert C. Byrd, the West Virginia Democrat, called instead for the administration to outline an exit strategy.</p>
        <p>With 25,000 soldiers from the First Armored Division being joined in and around Baghdad by about 15,000 troops arriving from the First Cavalry Division, a total of 40,000 American soldiers are now in the Iraqi capital -- roughly 11,000 more than before the troop rotation began in January. An additional 10,000 soldiers from the First Cavalry are scheduled to arrive soon.</p>
        <p>Under a plan being mapped out by the top American commander for the region, Gen. John P. Abizaid, some of the more experienced troops will probably be sent to Shiite-dominated south-central Iraq. In recent days there, forces loyal to Mr. Sadr have tested British, Polish and other non-American troops in charge of what had been -- until last weekend -- a largely peaceful area.</p>
        <p>Gen. Barry McCaffrey, a retired four-star officer who served in the 1991 Persian Gulf war, said that while restoring order to Baghdad must be a priority, the need for reinforcements in the south was keen.</p>
        <p>''With the exception of the Brits, who have high-quality combat forces, the rest of the coalition forces have capabilities ranging from untrained light infantry with peacekeeping, not peacemaking, rules of engagement, to units barely authorized to protect themselves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush met with his national security team via the secure teleconference center in a trailer near his ranch in Crawford. Among those participating, the White House said, were Vice President Dick Cheney; Mr. Rumsfeld; George J. Tenet, the director of central intelligence; Secretary of State Colin L. Powell; L. Paul Bremer III, the American administrator in Iraq; General Abizaid; Gen. Richard B. Myers, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff; Ms. Rice; and Andrew H. Card Jr., the chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the meetings dealt with the enormous complications arising from the question of how to deal with Mr. Sadr, who has taken refuge in the Shiite holy city of Najaf. American forces had pledged to remain out of Najaf during the holiday of Arbaeen, which starts on Friday. The city, like Karbala, another holy city where there has been fighting, is already beginning to fill with Shiites.</p>
        <p>A senior White House official said Mr. Sadr would ''be dealt with, and I don't mean through negotiation.''</p>
        <p>American officials in Washington and Iraq, concerned that a direct attack now on Mr. Sadr might only fuel the fighting, said the forces sent there might focus more on quelling the violence his followers have unleashed. And some administration officials said their first priority was to enlist other Iraqi Shiites, including Grand Ayatollah Ali al-Sistani, in a bid to marginalize Mr. Sadr.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld issued a pointed call to Iraqis to join in condemning Mr. Sadr, and he renewed Mr. Bush's vow not to be driven out of Iraq by what Mr. Rumsfeld called ''a group of thugs.'' Even as American intelligence officials suggested that the Shiite uprising was reaching well beyond Mr. Sadr's followers, Mr. Rumsfeld said the resistance was coming from a force of no more than 6,000 armed fighters led by Mr. Sadr. General Myers also played down the new layer of conflict. ''It's not a Shia uprising,'' the general said at the Pentagon news conference.</p>
        <p>Both officials tried to lump Mr. Sadr together with Abu Musab al-Zarqawi, the Jordanian Sunni Muslim terrorist who American officials say has led attacks on coalition targets, and they characterized Mr. Sadr as an extremist whose anti-American campaign was at odds with the wishes of most Iraqis.</p>
        <p>At the White House, officials said that violence on this scale would not throw off the schedule Mr. Bush has laid out. ''The single most important fact in all of this is that the Iraqi people have it fixed in their minds that sovereignty will be transferred on June 30,'' said one senior administration official. ''It is an important point for them. And it will happen.''</p>
        <p>In both the Sadr City section of Baghdad and in the Sunni enclaves of Ramadi and Falluja, west of Baghdad, American troops are facing one of the commanders' biggest concerns when the Iraq war started over a year ago: prolonged urban combat. In Falluja, where four civilian contractors were killed last week, marines from the First Marine Expeditionary Force have set up barriers at routes in and out of the city. They are advancing through the city.</p>
        <p>Brig. Gen. Mark Hertling, an assistant commander of the First Armored Division, said in a telephone interview from Baghdad that resistance in parts of the city could last several more days.</p>
        <p>And he said the next few days could prove to be a turning point for the American-led operation.</p>
        <p>''The moderates, especially the moderate leaders in Baghdad, are watching what's happening,'' he said. ''What we can't afford as we advance toward the new government, is to allow a very small group of extremists to throw the governmental system off its tracks.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: THE MILITARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
