<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Better Laws to Settle the Port Labor Dispute</title>
    <meta content="10GOUL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/10/opinion/10GOUL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1430618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stevedoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor-Management Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oregon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Maritime Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Longshore and Warehouse Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, William B IV</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor-Management Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD81F3BF933A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Better Laws to Settle the Port Labor Dispute</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Better Laws to Settle the Port Labor Dispute</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William B. Gould IV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, William B IV</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William B Gould IV Op-Ed article urges final-offer arbitration as alternative to Taft-Hartley Act procedures in face of labor disputes that threaten national health or safety; say that while Pres Bush's invoking of Taft-Hartley in West Coast longshore workers' lockout may be smart legal strategy, it is fundamentally flawed as labor policy, inflaming labor-management passions and dissipating management's willingness to compromise</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last time a president tried to invoke the Taft-Hartley Act, which provides for federal intervention if a strike or lockout threatens ''national health or safety,'' he failed. In 1978, a federal judge rejected President Jimmy Carter's effort to use the act to halt a coal miners' strike.</p>
        <p>President Bush's invocation of the act this week to end the management lockout of the longshore workers' union on the West Coast is likely to be more successful, particularly if the evidence shows that national security is imperiled. The growth of globalization should make the court even more receptive to the president's argument, and courts have been willing to grant injunctions in past port disputes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor and management should get federal legislation that would allow for states to oversee final-offer arbitration in future disputes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last time a president tried to invoke the Taft-Hartley Act, which provides for federal intervention if a strike or lockout threatens ''national health or safety,'' he failed. In 1978, a federal judge rejected President Jimmy Carter's effort to use the act to halt a coal miners' strike.</p>
        <p>President Bush's invocation of the act this week to end the management lockout of the longshore workers' union on the West Coast is likely to be more successful, particularly if the evidence shows that national security is imperiled. The growth of globalization should make the court even more receptive to the president's argument, and courts have been willing to grant injunctions in past port disputes.</p>
        <p>But while invoking Taft-Hartley may be a smart legal strategy, it is fundamentally flawed as a labor policy. The Taft-Hartley procedures tend to inflame labor-management passions rather than promote the dialogue and compromise that are the necessary elements of collective bargaining. Management's willingness to compromise is dissipated by the knowledge that the federal government can intervene.</p>
        <p>The Taft-Hartley Act, passed in 1947, allows the president to seek an injunction against a work stoppage. If the courts grant it, there is an 80-day cooling-off period, during which the two sides may negotiate under the supervision of a federal mediator. If they are still unable to reach an agreement after 80 days, the workers can go on strike or management can lock them out; in effect, the dispute is no further toward resolution.</p>
        <p>The International Longshore and Warehouse Union, which represents 10,500 workers on the West Coast, has been working without a contract since Sept. 1. On Sept. 29, shippers and port operators shut down 29 West Coast ports, saying the union was engaging in a work slowdown. But the lockout was also meant to produce White House intervention. An injunction would allow companies to begin shipping again and, in the process, diminish their willingness to bargain through January.</p>
        <p>Supporters and opponents of Taft-Hartley in Congress make predictable arguments. Union-hostile Republicans and moderate or conservative Democrats are alarmed by the danger to the economy and favor federal intervention. Liberal Democrats are against intervention because it is inconsistent with free and autonomous collective bargaining. There is a third way, however, which is fair to both sides and produces a final and binding settlement: final-offer arbitration.</p>
        <p>Such arbitration would encourage the voluntary resolution of differences. It would require the third-party neutral arbitrator to select the final offer of one side or the other -- taking into account practices in other industries, economic considerations and questions of basic fairness. Thus it would create an incentive for each party to be more reasonable in its demands in order to have its position selected. This formula has been successful in public-employee disputes and in baseball salary arbitrations.</p>
        <p>There are both practical and political problems with this approach, however. While management generally favors arbitration, the dock workers would be fearful that they would get less from arbitration than from economic pressure. Moreover, organized labor would not have confidence in an arbitration process overseen by the Bush administration, given its intervention in airline negotiations and its bashing of public-sector unions in the debate over the Homeland Security legislation. Yet final-offer arbitration, if it contains new authority for state government leadership, might attract labor support.</p>
        <p>It might be difficult to put this procedure in place promptly enough to cope with the current dispute. Therefore labor and management should begin now to get federal legislation that would allow for states to oversee final-offer arbitration in all such future disputes.</p>
        <p>It may sound unrealistic. But there are ways to make it work: If the law required the arbitration panel to be appointed by governors of the states most affected by the work stoppage, for instance, labor's objections to federal oversight of the system might be answered. The involvement of state officials would also induce the strong political advocacy at both the federal and state level which is necessary for the bill's success.</p>
        <p>Legislation replacing Taft-Hartley's archaic and one-sided injunction process should be introduced without delay. It would be an invaluable tool in resolving future strikes and lockouts -- and the mere prospect of it could help spur meaningful negotiations in the current labor dispute.</p>
        <p>William B. Gould IV was chairman of the National Labor Relations Board from 1994 to 1998 and is author of ''Labored Relations: Law, Politics and the N.L.R.B.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William B. Gould IV was chairman of the National Labor Relations Board from 1994 to 1998 and is author of ''Labored Relations: Law, Politics and the N.L.R.B.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
