<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gains in Precision Bidding After a No-Trump Opening</title>
    <meta content="10CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/10/crosswords/bridge/10CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1430558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D61E3BF933A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gains in Precision Bidding After a No-Trump Opening</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gains in Precision Bidding After a No-Trump Opening</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column describes deal from World Women's Pairs tournament in Montreal; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most world titles have had winners from many countries. One exception is the World Women's Pairs, which has been won seven times by the United States, three times by Britain, and once by the Netherlands. In Montreal in August, Karen McCallum of Exeter, N.H., became the first player to win with two different partners: She was successful with Debbie Rosenberg of New Rochelle, N.Y., at 34 the second-youngest player ever to win the title. McCallum also won in 1990 with Kerri Sanborn of Stony Point, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal from the event illustrates how far styles have changed in selecting one no-trump opening bids. Seventy years ago Ely Culbertson and his group had stringent standards and hardly ever made the bid, even if the requirements were met, because their responding methods were unreliable. McCallum and Rosenberg believe in opening one no-trump at the drop of a hat, reasoning that they can usually find the right contract and that this policy makes life difficult for the opponents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two bridge players believe that in opening one no-trump at the drop of a hat, they can usually find the right contract and that this policy makes life difficult for the opponents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most world titles have had winners from many countries. One exception is the World Women's Pairs, which has been won seven times by the United States, three times by Britain, and once by the Netherlands. In Montreal in August, Karen McCallum of Exeter, N.H., became the first player to win with two different partners: She was successful with Debbie Rosenberg of New Rochelle, N.Y., at 34 the second-youngest player ever to win the title. McCallum also won in 1990 with Kerri Sanborn of Stony Point, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal from the event illustrates how far styles have changed in selecting one no-trump opening bids. Seventy years ago Ely Culbertson and his group had stringent standards and hardly ever made the bid, even if the requirements were met, because their responding methods were unreliable. McCallum and Rosenberg believe in opening one no-trump at the drop of a hat, reasoning that they can usually find the right contract and that this policy makes life difficult for the opponents.</p>
        <p>In this case, McCallum as South opened one no-trump with a 5-2-4-2 hand, a choice that few would make. It had the useful effect of silencing the opposition, who could have made at least 11 tricks in a club contract. After North's transfer response, showing spades, three diamonds promised at least a four-card spade fit. Three hearts was a re-transfer, and four spades became the contract. The North-South hands offered two chances: the club king might provide a diamond discard in the dummy, and the diamonds could provide a discard for dummy's singleton club. Both these plans were due to fail against accurate defense.</p>
        <p>A trump was led, and South won in her hand and crossed to dummy with a second trump. East discarded a discouraging club and a discouraging diamond, causing South to suspect that the minor-suit honors were badly placed for her. She therefore took an immediate diamond finesse, leaving a harmless trump at large. It was harmful to West, however, because it gave her a losing option. When she won the third trick with the diamond king she thought it was safe to exit with her remaining trump. McCallum showed that this was a misconception by winning and playing the ace-jack of diamonds to discard dummy's singleton club. Then she could claim her game, conceding two heart tricks.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
