<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="717955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOLDEN BOOKS SHOWCASE (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3D9143CF937A25753C1A962958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dulcie Leimbach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Golden Books Showcase</p>
        <p>630 Fifth Avenue (at 50th Street)  (212) 582-4323  Recommended for all ages  Daily</p>
        <p>You can still buy Little Golden Books, with their black-and-gold bindings and lightweight covers, in the supermarket. But it's likely you can't watch a video of the character Tootle the Train on a screen in the floor while you're shopping at the supermarket. In the windows of this new bookstore are Golden Books, games, large moving stuffed animals and a working train set; inside are half a dozen audio and video interactive displays, some in the floor. Were you expecting something ordinary in a store calling itself a showcase?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Golden Books Showcase</p>
        <p>630 Fifth Avenue (at 50th Street)  (212) 582-4323  Recommended for all ages  Daily</p>
        <p>You can still buy Little Golden Books, with their black-and-gold bindings and lightweight covers, in the supermarket. But it's likely you can't watch a video of the character Tootle the Train on a screen in the floor while you're shopping at the supermarket. In the windows of this new bookstore are Golden Books, games, large moving stuffed animals and a working train set; inside are half a dozen audio and video interactive displays, some in the floor. Were you expecting something ordinary in a store calling itself a showcase?</p>
        <p>Indoors, toy arrangements are near the ceiling. At floor level, one interactive screen implores you to "touch me" to find out what games are in stock, including a category especially for girls. (How about Pretty, Pretty Princess, for example?) You may notice on the shelves a game children can probably live without: McDonald's Flying French Fries. If you pull the wrong fry out of a box, all of them fly out. A display of sound-board books (press a button on a page, and a sound effect issues) shows you how much more fun the Poky Little Puppy can be. (He's one of the first Golden Book characters, from 1942.)</p>
        <p>Even a 10-month-old baby can reach the Golden Crayon display, to touch colored buttons and thereby fill in a drawing on the screen. A video of the irrepressible Madeline was shown on a wall screen while other videos in screens on the floor ran simultaneously. (They kept the baby quite happy.) There are books here, too, including serious ones on bugs, butterflies, rocks and weeds. And you can choose from a large selection of music cassettes and educational coloring books and videos. (The video on math looked good.)</p>
        <p>Hours are Mondays through Wednesdays, 9 A.M. to 7 P.M.; Thursdays through Saturdays, 9 A.M. to 8 P.M., and Sundays, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Storytelling</p>
        <p>Montclair Art Museum  3 South Mountain Avenue  Montclair, N.J.  (201) 746-5555  Recommended for all ages  Sunday</p>
        <p>A really good American Indian storyteller strives for humility, but Dovie Thomason admits she has a gift for telling tales. She is half Oglala Lakota, from the northern Plains, and half Kiowa Apache, from the southern Plains. But she's more loyal to her mother's Lakota side, from South Dakota.</p>
        <p>Now that she's living in the Northeast, she weaves her Plains stories with Iroquois and Algonquin ones, and Ms. Thomason is also hoping for a good frost. "That way, I can tell trickster and coyote stories, winter ones," she said. These come to her, she added, from children and from elders of the American Indian nations, and the stories are indirectly about how to rear children or how to correct adults' bad ways.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomason, who speaks softly but so firmly that she never needs a microphone, uses a lot of voices in her stories. Since she doesn't read them but tells them from memory, she can look right into the children's eyes. "The stories I tell are animated," she said. "The ducks and the moose and everybody needs their own voice."</p>
        <p>Her storytelling is tied into two American Indian exhibitions at the museum: "Kiowa Ledger Book" (through Feb. 5) and "Patterns in Culture" (through June). The ledger records daily life on an Oklahoma reservation in the mid-1870's. A children's guide to the patterns show is available.</p>
        <p>The storytelling program is at 3 P.M. It's free with regular museum admission: $4; no charge under the age of 12. On Sundays from 1 to 5 P.M. (2 to 5 P.M. starting in November), there are drop-in multimedia craft workshops for children, allowing parents to tour the galleries on their own. You can get to the museum from Manhattan by public transportation by taking the No. 33 DeCamp-line bus from the Port Authority bus station at 42d Street and Eighth Avenue; ask the driver to drop you off at South Mountain and Bloomfield Avenues, across the street from the museum. (The museum has no food service, so take your own snacks.) Photography Exhibition</p>
        <p>New York Public Library  Harlem branch  9 West 124th Street  (212) 348-5620  Recommended ages: 7 and up  Through Oct. 31</p>
        <p>Joaquin-Ben Cotten is a visual soul. At 9 years old, he's in the midst of an exhibition of his black-and-white photographs, but his shyness keeps him from saying too much except that he likes taking pictures. These are displayed in this branch library's lobby, and they tell a lot about Joaquin-Ben, who lives in East Harlem.</p>
        <p>One picture, a silhouette of his friend Isaac Weiner, won first place in a National Geographic World photography contest this year. (The magazine is a junior version of National Geographic.) A picture of Joaquin-Ben's father, Benjamin, reveals the son's abiding admiration. (In the display text, Joaquin-Ben said that his father, a firefighter, gave him his first camera and that they both love photography.)</p>
        <p>The other photographs are of streetscapes, sports scenes and other children. Joaquin-Ben is there, too, in a self-portrait with his face obscured by -- what else? -- a camera. His work should provide incentive to other children with an inclination toward photography. Joaquin-Ben said he is looking forward to his own retrospective some day at the International Center of Photography.</p>
        <p>The branch hours are Mondays, Tuesdays and Fridays, 1 to 6 P.M.; Wednesdays, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Thursdays, 1 to 8 P.M., and Saturdays, 1 to 5 P.M. The exhibition is free.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
