<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drop in Asian Travelers Affects Tourism in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="19REP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1010653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Zealand</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DD123DF93AA25757C0A96E958260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drop in Asian Travelers Affects Tourism in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Drop in Asian travelers as result of economic malaise that broke out in Asia last fall is affecting tourism in US; conditions that have made Asia such a good value for visitors portend bad news for tourist industries of Hawaii, California, Australia and New Zealand (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE economic malaise that broke out in Asia last fall has helped make much of that continent a bargain basement for American travelers. But the conditions that have made Asia such a good value for visitors portend bad news for the tourist industries of Hawaii, California, Australia and New Zealand. And the ripple effects, mainly the tighter grip that Asian visitors will keep on purse strings, are expected to be felt from the casinos of Las Vegas to the Mall of America in Bloomington, Minn.</p>
        <p>''Clearly tourism from Asia is going to be off this year,'' said John Marks, president of the San Francisco Convention and Visitors Bureau. ''We're already experiencing a dramatic decline from Korea. And tourism from Japan is also going to be off, but we just don't know how much. If I had to speculate, maybe 10 percent.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE economic malaise that broke out in Asia last fall has helped make much of that continent a bargain basement for American travelers. But the conditions that have made Asia such a good value for visitors portend bad news for the tourist industries of Hawaii, California, Australia and New Zealand. And the ripple effects, mainly the tighter grip that Asian visitors will keep on purse strings, are expected to be felt from the casinos of Las Vegas to the Mall of America in Bloomington, Minn.</p>
        <p>''Clearly tourism from Asia is going to be off this year,'' said John Marks, president of the San Francisco Convention and Visitors Bureau. ''We're already experiencing a dramatic decline from Korea. And tourism from Japan is also going to be off, but we just don't know how much. If I had to speculate, maybe 10 percent.''</p>
        <p>While Chinese tourists are turning up in greater numbers throughout Asia, the United States doesn't expect a significant number, at least in the short term. The main impediments are distance, cost and United States law requiring potential visitors to demonstrate to the United States consular officer in their country, and the immigration officer here, their intention to return home.</p>
        <p>Northwest Airlines, which has had extensive routes to Asia for more than 50 years, says that tourism from Japan to the United States is already down about 10 percent through March 20 of this year, compared with the same period last year.</p>
        <p>In 1996, the last year for which statistics are available, San Francisco had 384,000 visitors from Japan, 136,000 from Korea and 145,000 from Taiwan. Because the Taiwanese economy is comparatively healthy, Mr. Marks said, any drop in visitors from Taiwan this year should be minimal.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles is also bracing for a drastic decrease in Korean visitors, who numbered about 200,000 in 1997, according to Bob Moore, of the city's Convention and Visitors Bureau. But while Mr. Moore said fewer Japanese tourists will go abroad this year, his talks with tour operators suggest that Los Angeles may attract the same number of Japanese visitors as last year, about 750,000 -- mainly because of bargain tour packages. ''They're very attractive to the single female workers who make up a large part of the visitors from Japan,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These observations were seconded by Frank Murakami, general manager of the Los Angeles office of the Japan Travel Bureau International, Japan's biggest travel company. ''The trend this year is to Southern California,'' he said, because it is less expensive than San Francisco, and it is the jumping off point for Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>The so-called Golden Triangle for Japanese tourists, Mr. Murakami added, used to be Los Angeles, San Francisco and Las Vegas. ''Now it's Las Vegas, Disneyland and Universal Studios,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Japanese are attracted to Las Vegas  more for its entertainment than for gambling, according to Mr. Moore and others.  But many Asian travelers visit Las Vegas primarily to gamble. Jason Ader, an analyst for Bear, Stearns, said the expected falloff in Asian tourism to the United States, which he forecast at about 10 percent, could cause a 10 to 15 percent reduction in baccarat revenues in Las Vegas through 1999 -- or as much as $60 million annually. Moreover, any decline in Asian tourism to Las Vegas will also be felt at the Grand Canyon, a popular day trip from the gambling mecca.  The Mall of America is not making forecasts about numbers of Asian visitors, but a  spokeswoman said that those who come are expected to be more frugal.</p>
        <p>California still expects healthy tourism overall in 1998, spurred by domestic travel and more visitors from Canada and Mexico. But Hawaii is especially vulnerable to a drop in visitors from Asia -- or anywhere else. Tourism is far and away Hawaii's biggest industry, accounting for about $11 billion in revenues a year, a third of its jobs and a quarter of its tax revenues.</p>
        <p>Tony Vericella, the president of the Hawaii Visitors and Convention Bureau, predicted that arrivals from Korea, which numbered 122,000 last year, could drop as much as 80 percent in 1998. While arrivals from Japan are expected to be within 1 percent above or below last year's 2.1 million total, Mr. Vericella said, the weak yen means that the Japanese who do visit Hawaii will have fewer dollars to spend. Spending by Japanese tourists has already fallen from an average $354 a day a few years ago, the visitors bureau said, to $298 last year.</p>
        <p>The Asian economic crisis also slammed Australia and New Zealand, both of which had been expecting a strong 1998. Australia had especially high hopes, after a 7 percent gain in fiscal 1997 that resulted in a record 4.3 million foreign visitors and $6.1 billion in tourist revenues. Instead, international arrivals are expected to plummet between 6 and 9 percent, according to Australia's Tourism Forecasting Council, and tourism earnings could fall 20 percent -- despite a projected doubling of visitors from China, who still represent only a trickle. On the other hand low air fares and package tours enticed enough North Americans in the past two months that Australian tourist officials are projecting a 6 percent increase in their numbers this year. But with The World Tourism Organization predicting that the financial crisis within the Asia Pacific region will keep about 12 million Asian tourists from traveling throughout Asia by the year 2000, the outlook is not bright.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
