<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gifted Choices of a Sort of Guest Curator in Stamford</title>
    <meta content="19ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1010683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stamford Museum and Nature Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DF1F3DF93AA25757C0A96E958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gifted Choices of a Sort of Guest Curator in Stamford</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews art works on display in competition at Stamford Museum and Nature Center; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''NEW ART ANNUAL,'' the Stamford Museum and Nature Center's art competition, has an afterglow: The judge picks four top winners to share the gallery in an  exhibition later in the year. This willingness to, in essence, put curatorial duties in the hands of an outsider is the unique twist of this contest, open to artists living in Connecticut and Westchester County.</p>
        <p>For this year's edition, the hands belong to James Rondeau who, when he made his choices, was associate curator of contemporary art at the Wadsworth Atheneum and is now in  a curatorial post at the Art Institute of Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''NEW ART ANNUAL,'' the Stamford Museum and Nature Center's art competition, has an afterglow: The judge picks four top winners to share the gallery in an  exhibition later in the year. This willingness to, in essence, put curatorial duties in the hands of an outsider is the unique twist of this contest, open to artists living in Connecticut and Westchester County.</p>
        <p>For this year's edition, the hands belong to James Rondeau who, when he made his choices, was associate curator of contemporary art at the Wadsworth Atheneum and is now in  a curatorial post at the Art Institute of Chicago.</p>
        <p>He left behind a lively show. The four major winners are, for the most part, known entities with impressive  work marked by professionalism and wit.</p>
        <p>June Ahrens of New Canaan takes literally the notion of art with an edge, here provided by rusty razor blades. ''On the Edge'' is a length of bone with the blades implanted. But ''Holey Soap'' is a diversion, a cake of soap with a hole worn in it.</p>
        <p>Eleanor White of Ridgefield shares some of Ms. Ahrens's mordancy. Her pair of pants made out of resin is decorated with poison ivy. She has a benign side, too: a large resin mushroom-shaped dome is decorated with orange slides, possibly evoking a Tiffany lamp.</p>
        <p>The other two major winners both use photography, though neither is a photographer in the strict sense.</p>
        <p>Ann Chernow's grids of computer-doctored photographs of old movie stars have some of the presence of Andy Warhol's multiple portraits. The Westport artist originally installed this work in a chapel in St. Paul de Vence, France.</p>
        <p>Robert Zott of Huntington continues to photograph tombstones with  suggestive, or at least serviceable, names carved on them. Here he has come up with North, South, East and West, arranged in a compass format. Oddly Mr. Zott has mounted his photographs in heavy wooden frames with handles. They resemble desk drawers and are major distractions from the swiftly delivered humor on which the art depends.</p>
        <p>Other items chosen by Mr. Rondeau look pretty good. Another piece of swiftly delivered humor is the alert rabbit, ''Jack the Clipper,'' fashioned from a garden tool by Harry Saunders of Stamford. Almost an emblem of quickness is ''Boy With Paper Airplane, a pared-down-to-essentials composition, one of three similar works by Leonard Everett Fisher of Westport. Streamlined works like these might be regarded as set-ups for a deliberately draggy sculpture, and the figure personifying ''The Weight of Time,'' by Natasha Cohen of Armonk, N.Y., might be an exhausted shaman</p>
        <p>Photography is a component not just top winners' work. Lucy Sander Sceery of South Windsor identifies her medium as ''Black and white infrared heat transferred onto silk and stitched with silver thread.'' Her subject matter is often sheer netting blowing in the wind. (Mr. Rondeau gave Ms. Sceery the special award for painting.) Jan Murdock of East Haven has mastered the complex process of ''Polaroid emulsion transfer.'' ''Wavers'' is the highly exaggerated reflection of a row of slender trees in water, and is reminiscent of Monet's Impressionism. Elaine Best of Stamford shoots mundane objects but they turn out mysteriously. ''On Top of the Roof,'' for example, is an intricate abstract composition difficult to decipher.</p>
        <p>It's always surprising to see what found objects can be recruited for sculpture. Helen Zajkowski of Stamford papers two box sculptures with lottery tickets, calling them ''American Dream'' and ''Patriotism.'' Betty Ramey of Brookfield takes the insides of household machines, such as telephones and computers, and assembles them to make sculptures that sometimes, as with a primitive-looking mask, make paradoxical references to their high-tech origin.</p>
        <p>Old reliable landscape painting puts in an appearance with the meticulous panorama ''Sugar Beets at Sunset -- Williamset Valley'' by David Dunlap of Norwalk, with a classic Hudson River School feel to it. In contrast, ''Puss &amp; Boots in the Garden'' by Marc Simmons of Hartford is homey, possibly a cultivated look.</p>
        <p>At a remove from this exhibition, in the museum's adjunct gallery, Artex, are the deceptively simple paintings of Melinda James of Woodmont with the group title, ''F-light.'' In part the title indicates a resemblance between her method and the speed of a camera shutter. But her constant subject is birds in flight. Sometimes a single bird has the whole pale pastel field to itself. At other times, Ms. James has observed an aerial formation. She has said that she sits on a beach waiting for her subject matter to fly by. The birds are indicated by a minimum of strokes as in Sumi brush painting. Ms. James acknowledges that the time difference between spotting a bird and then translating it into pigment is significant.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless her technique is decisive and it has the effect of making the small speck, plus its surroundings, assume great importance.</p>
        <p>''New Art Annual '98'' is at the Stamford Art and Nature Center through April 26; Melinda James's paintings, through April 23.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
