<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Run Meetings, Raise Kids and Search for Their Inner Woman</title>
    <meta content="15LYAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/15/weekinreview/15LYAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1448935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Cherie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Blair, Cherie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Reagan, Nancy</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinem, Gloria</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Clinton, Hillary</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDD1E3AF936A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Run Meetings, Raise Kids and Search for Their Inner Woman</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Women Turn to Non-Traditional Methods to Find Refuge and Focus</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British news media's fascination with Cherie Blair's interest in New Age therapies discussed; photo; prime minister's wife, who is also full-time lawyer and mother of four children, has discussed stresses of her life, acknowledging that sometimes juggled balls get dropped in attempt to do too much; other working mothers comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRY as you might, it is hard to ignore a newspaper headline that says: ''They stood naked in the shower as Carole scrubbed the toxins out of Mrs. Blair's body.'' Such an article appeared last week in The Daily Mail, featuring an intriguing account of the purported New Age practices of Cherie Blair, the wife of Tony Blair, the British prime minister, and her so-called lifestyle adviser, Carole Caplin.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mrs. Blair has faced a bewildering barrage of allegations, involving the purchase of two modest apartments in Bristol, a city in southwest England, with the help of a convicted would-be diet-aid entrepreneur, who is fighting deportation to Australia and who also happens to be Ms. Caplin's boyfriend. But perhaps the most compelling and strange details to have emerged concern Mrs. Blair's unconventional health regime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why have prominent women like Cherie Blair, Nancy Reagan and Gloria Steinem turned to New Age therapies for spiritual refuge?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRY as you might, it is hard to ignore a newspaper headline that says: ''They stood naked in the shower as Carole scrubbed the toxins out of Mrs. Blair's body.'' Such an article appeared last week in The Daily Mail, featuring an intriguing account of the purported New Age practices of Cherie Blair, the wife of Tony Blair, the British prime minister, and her so-called lifestyle adviser, Carole Caplin.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mrs. Blair has faced a bewildering barrage of allegations, involving the purchase of two modest apartments in Bristol, a city in southwest England, with the help of a convicted would-be diet-aid entrepreneur, who is fighting deportation to Australia and who also happens to be Ms. Caplin's boyfriend. But perhaps the most compelling and strange details to have emerged concern Mrs. Blair's unconventional health regime.</p>
        <p>Among other things, Mrs. Blair, 48 and a high-profile lawyer, is said to wear inflatable ''Flowtron'' trousers to combat leg bloat. She has been photographed wearing stress-fighting acupressure earrings and a ''bioelectric shield pennant,'' believed to ward off harmful radiation from everyday appliances like personal computers. She also reportedly consults a psychic (faxing over her spiritual questions when she can't make it in person), and according to British news accounts, once took part in a ''rebirthing'' ceremony in Mexico in which she and the prime minister shouted and smeared mud and ripe fruit pulp on each other.</p>
        <p>As quirky as these habits might seem, Mrs. Blair is in good company. Nancy Reagan, during her husband's years in the White House, regularly consulted an astrologer who advised her on such matters as the timing of presidential trips. Gloria Steinem, the mother of modern feminism, has written about the benefits of hypnosis in her spiritual search for her inner ''wise woman.''</p>
        <p>Even the ultra-practical Senator Hillary Clinton, Democrat of New York, has admitted that when she was first lady, she met with an adviser who encouraged her to hold imaginary conversations with dead public figures like Eleanor Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>WHICH leads to an obvious question. Why?</p>
        <p>''These particular kinds of New Age therapies seem to be a spiritual refuge for more affluent people,'' said Wendy Kaminer, whose book, ''Sleeping with Extra-Terrestrials: The Rise of Irrationalism and Perils of Piety,'' looks at the growing fascination with the paranormal and supernatural in modern life.</p>
        <p>In the case of Cherie Blair, another factor is at work. Not only is she the prime minister's wife and a full-time lawyer, but she is also the mother of four children, spanning toddler-dom to teenage-hood. In a tearful speech last week, she spoke of the stresses of her life, saying that sometimes juggled balls get dropped in her attempt to do too much. She declared, ''I also know I'm not superwoman.''</p>
        <p>As Kathy Lette, a London writer and commentator, said, ''She's the ultimate kid-and-career juggler.''</p>
        <p>''All working mothers are a full nappies short of a pack of Pampers,'' Ms. Lette added, using the British term for diapers, by way of explaining how exhaustion and overload can send smart women rushing to foolish therapies. ''If crystal inner-thigh tantric seaweed waxing and thigh massage are going to stop you from stowing your baby under the sink by mistake, who cares?''</p>
        <p>Allison Pearson, the author of ''I Don't Know How She Does it,'' a best-selling novel here and in the United States that chronicles the efforts of a business executive to hold down her job, remain married and raise her children while getting some sleep once in a while, said that all Mrs. Blair wanted was to do a little something for herself, instead of for other people.</p>
        <p>''People like her are under tremendous stress,'' she said, ''and nice soothing mumbo-jumbo literally serves as balm for the soul.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Pearson had nothing but sympathy for Mrs. Blair's efforts, however extreme. She said she was still searching for a therapy that could combine self-pampering with a practical chore. ''I want a kind of yoga that you could combine with making Christmas dinner, some kind of turkey position,'' she said. ''Talking from experience, there are times when I've been so stressed out that if someone told me that sitting in a wigwam wearing pink plastic socks and chanting Bee Gees lyrics would give me my libido back or make me feel better about myself, I would have done it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
