<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; A Robin Hood for Today Sees the Humor in His Job</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="445161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ROBIN HOOD (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DD1638F930A25756C0A967958260" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; A Robin Hood for Today Sees the Humor in His Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beating Kevin Costner to the finish line, Patrick Bergin can be seen as "Robin Hood" tonight at 8 on the Fox network. Mr. Costner's "Robin Hood: Prince of Thieves" will be released this summer amid expectations of big box-office business. The Bergin version, meanwhile, will be distributed in theaters in Europe. The mechanics of movie marketing grind endlessly.</p>
        <p>Fox's "Robin Hood" is obviously determined to be different. In the 1938 classic film, "The Adventures of Robin Hood" starring Errol Flynn, the director, Michael Curtiz, whipped up pure swashbuckling adventure for his dashing star, all played out on a bright Technicolor landscape. This new rendition, filmed entirely on rather muddy British locations, is done in moody tones of blue and gray, the permeating damp made visible in the breath of the actors. At the same time, Mr. Bergin's Robin is far from being airily heroic. There is something slightly goofy about this curious rebel as, in standard post-modern manner, he seems to view his own exploits with wry amusement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beating Kevin Costner to the finish line, Patrick Bergin can be seen as "Robin Hood" tonight at 8 on the Fox network. Mr. Costner's "Robin Hood: Prince of Thieves" will be released this summer amid expectations of big box-office business. The Bergin version, meanwhile, will be distributed in theaters in Europe. The mechanics of movie marketing grind endlessly.</p>
        <p>Fox's "Robin Hood" is obviously determined to be different. In the 1938 classic film, "The Adventures of Robin Hood" starring Errol Flynn, the director, Michael Curtiz, whipped up pure swashbuckling adventure for his dashing star, all played out on a bright Technicolor landscape. This new rendition, filmed entirely on rather muddy British locations, is done in moody tones of blue and gray, the permeating damp made visible in the breath of the actors. At the same time, Mr. Bergin's Robin is far from being airily heroic. There is something slightly goofy about this curious rebel as, in standard post-modern manner, he seems to view his own exploits with wry amusement.</p>
        <p>Maid Marian, played by Uma Thurman ("Dangerous Liaisons," "Henry and June"), is also given a distinctively modern spin. This is a Maid with little or no interest in pointless modesty. Turning around the traditional male line, she tells Robin, "You're so handsome when you're angry." Marian gets quickly to the point, "What are you going to do with me?" Robin, teasing, "Could be a lashing?" Marian, purring in her best Madonna manner, "How many strokes?" Olivia de Havilland's Marian, a lady to her fingertips, would surely blush.</p>
        <p>While not terribly grand in scale, the production manages to convey a keen sense of physical authenticity for a story that is supposed to be taking place in the year 1195. No fetching green tights here, nor merrie bands of lovable rascals. These outlaws live in caves, not trees, and spend most of their time in soggy Yorkshire, not snug Sherwood Forest. The director, John Irvin ("Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy," "The Dogs of War"), keeps the story moving nimbly, from the banishment of the Saxon nobleman Robert Hode to his subsequent emergence as Robin Hood, who comes up with a spanking new idea: Tax the rich and give the money to the poor. Quick, send this man to Democratic Party headquarters in Washington.</p>
        <p>The supporting cast, an international lot, is consistently sturdy. On the nobility side, there is Jurgen Prochnow as Sir Miles, Jeroen Krabbe as Sir Roger Daguerre and Edward Fox as Prince John ("It's not good to be nice to your peasants; they'll just rob you"). Prominent among Robin's friends are Owen Teale as Will Scarlett and Jeff Nuttal as Friar Tuck. As for Mr. Bergin, perhaps best known from the movies "Mountains of the Moon" and "Sleeping With the Enemy," he relies more on knowing charm than brash theatrics, and comes off the better for it.</p>
        <p>There is, of course, ample opportunity for displaying sword and bow-and-arrow skills. One scene has a knockdown western-style brawl, complete with the participants being dumped into large barrels of various liquids. At one point, Robin even swings across a room on a chandelier. In the end, as Robin and Marian finally pledge their troths ("I will take this man because he brings springtime to my heart"), the sun suddenly appears, giving everything a surreal Technicolor glow. What more can one ask of a movie that, mercifully, doesn't take itself too seriously?  Robin Hood Directed by John Irvin; produced by Sarah Radclyffe. At 8 tonight on Fox. Robert Hode/Robin Hood . . . Patrick Bergin Maid Marian . . . Uma Thurman Prince John . . . Edward Fox Sir Miles Folcanet . . . Jurgen Prochnow  Sir Roger Daguerre . . . Jeroen Krabbe Will Scarlett . . . Owen Teale Friar Tuck . . . Jeff Nuttal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
