<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seville, Long a Plot Backdrop, Now Gets Its Own Opera House</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="445269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SEVILLE (SPAIN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAESTRANZA THEATER (SEVILLE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain/Andalusia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain/Andalusia/Seville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF1530F930A25756C0A967958260" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seville, Long a Plot Backdrop, Now Gets Its Own Opera House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>SEVILLE, Spain, May 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barely 100 yards from where Carmen met her death, near the streets where Don Giovanni had his trysts, in the city where Figaro made his name, Seville's first opera house opened on Friday with a dazzling exhibition of what Spain still contributes to the world of opera today.</p>
        <p>It was an emotional occasion, not only because never before have Spain's current crop of world-class singers made a joint appearance, but also because the audience seemed electrified to hear arias from some of the 24 operas set in Seville being sung in this very city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barely 100 yards from where Carmen met her death, near the streets where Don Giovanni had his trysts, in the city where Figaro made his name, Seville's first opera house opened on Friday with a dazzling exhibition of what Spain still contributes to the world of opera today.</p>
        <p>It was an emotional occasion, not only because never before have Spain's current crop of world-class singers made a joint appearance, but also because the audience seemed electrified to hear arias from some of the 24 operas set in Seville being sung in this very city.</p>
        <p>The Maestranza Theater, as the opera house is called, has been built for Seville's universal exposition, Expo '92, which will mark the 500th anniversary of Columbus's voyage to the Americas. And next year many of the world's great orchestras, singers and conductors will also perform here.</p>
        <p>But the opera stars did not wait. Among those on stage Friday were Placido Domingo, Jose Carreras and Alfredo Kraus as well as Montserrat Caballe, Teresa Berganza and Pilar Lorengar. Victoria de los Angeles, the grande dame of Spanish song, had to cancel because she was unwell.  Pavarotti Joins In</p>
        <p>In the coming weeks, as part of a six-week inaugural program, most of them will give recitals and concerts at the Maestranza. And the one famous tenor who did not sing on Friday, Luciano Pavarotti, is paying tribute to what he has called "the land of the tenors" by giving his own recital in the opera house on Monday.</p>
        <p>For the opening night, there was music by Verdi, Rossini, Puccini, Donizetti and of course Bizet, as well as by several Spanish composers. The singers, who also included the baritone Juan Pons and the tenor Jaime Aragall, first performed arias or duets and then came together for a rousing encore from Verdi's "Traviata".</p>
        <p>Judging by the applause, Alfredo Kraus, who is now 64 years old, won this battle of the tenors when he sang "La donna e mobile" from Verdi's "Rigoletto." But duets by Mr. Domingo and Mr. Pons, Miss Caballe and Mr. Carreras and Miss Lorengar and Mr. Aragall were also wildly received.</p>
        <p>In Seville, though, it was almost inevitable that the Habanera from Bizet's "Carmen" would close the program. And it was Miss Berganza, who will also sing Carmen when the Maestranza opens its Expo '92 opera season next April with Nuria Espert's Covent Garden production of "Carmen," who brought the audience, including Queen Sofia of Spain, to its feet.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Carmen seemed ever present. A round window in the theater's main hall offers a view of the Maestranza bull ring, outside which Carmen met her death at the hands of Don Jose. The front wall of the Artillery barracks where Don Jose was billeted has been incorporated into the new opera house (Maestranza means Armory). And the tobacco factory where Carmen worked is only half a mile away.</p>
        <p>But for opera lovers there are many other reminders. Behind the Maestranza is the Hospital de la Caridad, which was founded in a moment of penitence by a rich and licentious Sevillian, Miguel de Marana, who was supposedly the model for Tirso de Molina's play "Don Juan," which has inspired poets and playwrights for centuries and from which Mozart's "Don Giovanni" was taken.</p>
        <p>Donizetti's "Favorita" was partly set in the palace and gardens of the Alcazar; Beethoven's "Fidelio" had Florestan imprisoned in a fortress outside Seville; Verdi's "La Forza del Destino" has street scenes of Seville, while Rossini's "Barber of Seville" and Mozart's "Marriage of Figaro" capture this city's cheerful sensuality.</p>
        <p>With the opening of Expo '92 less than a year away, though, the gala also formed part of the selling of Seville in the hope of attracting 18 million visitors over a six-month period. And apart from the national pavilions on the Expo site, the city also hopes to draw crowds with a rich cultural program.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Domingo acting as its adviser, the Maestranza has planned a 1992 season of 12 operas, including Verdi's "Ballo in Maschera," to be performed by the Metropolitan Opera of New York on only its second trip to Europe. La Scala of Milan, the Maggio Musicale Fiorentino and the Dresden Opera will also bring productions.</p>
        <p>Further, the Maestranza will offer concerts by orchestras from Berlin, Paris, Leningrad, Munich, Oslo, Philadelphia, New York, Israel and Puerto Rico, while Daniel Barenboim, Riccardo Muti, Zubin Mehta, Kurt Masur, Mstislav Rostropovich, Lorin Maazel and Claudio Abbado will be among guest conductors.  10,000 Artists Expected</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Seville, both inside and outside the huge Expo grounds, there will also be both classical and experimental theater, cinema, dance and modern music ranging from jazz to rock. The plan, Expo's numbers-conscious organizers proclaim, is to bring 10,000 artists to Seville during the exhibition.</p>
        <p>But after five years of construction, the Maestranza has at least passed its first test. The $40 million opera house, which was designed by the Spaniards Aurelio del Pozo and Luis Marin de Teran, provides a direct view of the stage from all its 1,774 seats.</p>
        <p>On Friday its acoustics were also approved by both performers and critics. And this was a particular relief to the architects who developed a mobile system of fiberglass cylinders that, when in place, reduce the reverberation time from the 2 seconds needed for concerts to the 1.4 seconds deemed right for opera. The only odd thing was that they were not visible on Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
