<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Habitats/36 Gramercy Park East; To Get a View of the Park, First Get a Roommate</title>
    <meta content="21HABI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sparrow, Jeremy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB113FF932A15751C1A961958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Habitats/36 Gramercy Park East; To Get a View of the Park, First Get a Roommate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeremy Sparrow is able to rent $4,600-a-month Gramercy Park apartment, with park views, by taking on a roommate; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JEREMY SPARROW wanted an apartment on Gramercy Park,  and since there is only one rental building left there he flagged his broker months before he had to move.</p>
        <p>A call to look at an apartment in the building, at 36 Gramercy Park East, came just weeks before his lease was up. But the apartment, which was in his price range, about $3,200 a month, wasn't what he had in mind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JEREMY SPARROW wanted an apartment on Gramercy Park,  and since there is only one rental building left there he flagged his broker months before he had to move.</p>
        <p>A call to look at an apartment in the building, at 36 Gramercy Park East, came just weeks before his lease was up. But the apartment, which was in his price range, about $3,200 a month, wasn't what he had in mind.</p>
        <p>''There was a one-bedroom at the back of the building that looked out at a wall,'' he said about the 12th-floor apartment. ''To be on the park and not have a view to me was just ludicrous.''</p>
        <p>But his agent, Michael Nnawuchi of Citi Habitats, had something else to show: a just-renovated two-bedroom with park views on the sixth floor. ''I knew it was open, but I thought it was too expensive,'' Mr. Nnawuchi said.</p>
        <p>Still, he suggested they take a look at the apartment, which rented for $4,600, just for fun. ''We went to see it and he said, 'Wow,' '' Mr. Nnawuchi recalled. '' 'I hate your guts -- this is so unfair.' ''</p>
        <p>But within 10 minutes of leaving the apartment, Mr. Sparrow was back on the phone to his agent. ''We can do the two-bedroom,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sparrow, who works at Banque Paribas specializing in the sale of Russian securities to American institutions, had enlisted the help of a co-worker who was sharing space in TriBeCa. Within 30 minutes the colleague, George Kogan, had gone to the apartment, and arrangements were being made for the deposit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kogan, who also works at Banque Paribas selling Russian securities, said he had been thinking of renting another place but had not wanted to share. But when he heard about the apartment, he said, he jumped at it.</p>
        <p>''It's just a unique piece of real estate,'' he said. ''Nothing ever opens  up, at least not very often, on Gramercy Park.''</p>
        <p>Apartments in the stately 1906 building are being renovated as tenants leave, and what Mr. Sparrow latched onto was Old World charm with completely new fixtures: new kitchen, new bathrooms (although the fixtures are still in keeping with the building's style), fresh paint and gleaming parquet floors. Even the windows have been replaced.</p>
        <p>''It made sense to me to pay the phenomenal rent to get into it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Sparrow, a native of England who was transferred to New York by his company, had initially thought he would like to live alone, he found the apartment's layout conducive to sharing. Most important, both bedrooms have bay windows overlooking the park.</p>
        <p>THE bedrooms are made more private by a long hallway. Mr. Kogan has the smaller of the two, but he pays significantly less rent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sparrow said he was willing to take on $3,000 of the monthly rent because he gets a housing allowance from his company -- he declined to specify how much -- and so he got the larger bedroom.</p>
        <p>He acknowledged that considering current rents it might be better to buy. ''I thought about it,'' he said, ''but my view at the moment is it's not a good time to be buying real estate.''</p>
        <p>Having just rented an apartment a year before, he said, he found the difference in today's market a bit startling. ''It wasn't just a difference in prices,'' he said. ''It was the speed with which you have to make a decision. It's much easier for a realtor to say, 'If you want it you've got to take it now.' I think there's a certain amount of justification to it and I think there's a certain amount of hype. But there are certainly more people willing to pay more money than there were a year ago.''</p>
        <p>He said he contemplated staying in his apartment at The Rutherford, on Second Avenue between 17th and 18th Streets, but his two-bedroom duplex was going up from $3,700 to $4,100 a month, and with only one bathroom it wasn't conducive to sharing.</p>
        <p>Besides, he said, he really wanted to live on the park. The Old World charm of Gramercy Park has the feel of the Chelsea section of London, where he lives when working there. ''Obviously I gravitate toward old buildings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When he is ready to leave the serenity of his living room, the Gramercy Park neighborhood offers a wide variety of bars and restaurants, Mr. Sparrow said.</p>
        <p>As for sharing his home, he said, he has found some advantages. ''For me to be sharing with an American -- a very social American -- is not bad,'' he said. ''He's got the American crowd and I've got the English crowd and they all seem to get on very well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
