<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Other '04 Race: Building Copter For Presidents</title>
    <meta content="11HELI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/11/business/11HELICOPTER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1595968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Helicopters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lockheed Martin</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Technologies Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sikorsky Aircraft Division of United Technologies Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayne, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berlusconi, Silvio (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/National Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Federal Budget</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Helicopters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lockheed Martin Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Technologies Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sikorsky Aircraft</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D7103BF932A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Other '04 Race: Building Copter For Presidents</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Other '04 Race: Building Copter for Presidents</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wayne, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Competition to build next fleet of presidential helicopters has become brawl that pits flag-waving domestic maker against international team hoping to be rewarded for supporting United States in Iraq; Lockheed Martin has lined up European partners and lobbying juggernaut that includes British Prime Min Tony Blair and Italian Prime Min Silvio Berlusconi; also bidding is United Technologies Corp, parent to Sikorsky Aircraft, which is selling itself as all-American entrant; Navy will make final decision, but not until after election; both sides are lining up powerful political support; deal is valued at $1.6 billion, but might lead to another $40 billion for military helicopters; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No helicopter symbolizes executive power more than Marine One as it lifts off the White House lawn. Now, the competition to build the next fleet of presidential helicopters has become a bare-knuckles brawl that pits a flag-waving domestic maker against an international team hoping to be rewarded for supporting the United States in Iraq.</p>
        <p>One bidding team is led by the Lockheed Martin Corporation, the nation's largest military contractor, which has lined up European partners and a lobbying juggernaut that includes Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and his Italian counterpart, Silvio Berlusconi -- two of Washington's staunchest allies in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The competition to build the next fleet of presidential helicopters pits a domestic maker against an international team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No helicopter symbolizes executive power more than Marine One as it lifts off the White House lawn. Now, the competition to build the next fleet of presidential helicopters has become a bare-knuckles brawl that pits a flag-waving domestic maker against an international team hoping to be rewarded for supporting the United States in Iraq.</p>
        <p>One bidding team is led by the Lockheed Martin Corporation, the nation's largest military contractor, which has lined up European partners and a lobbying juggernaut that includes Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain and his Italian counterpart, Silvio Berlusconi -- two of Washington's staunchest allies in Iraq.</p>
        <p>Their Italian-designed craft, named US 101, would be the first of its kind to ferry the president.</p>
        <p>On the other side is the United Technologies Corporation, parent to Sikorsky Aircraft, whose founder, Igor I. Sikorsky, invented the modern helicopter.</p>
        <p>It is selling itself as the all-American entrant, and ads for Sikorsky's S-92 say that only ''skilled, trustworthy American hands'' can ''ensure mission safety and the security'' of the president.</p>
        <p>''There is a visceral and gut feeling that you don't want the president in a Mercedes or flying around in an Italian helicopter,'' said Jeffrey P. Pino, a Sikorsky senior vice president. ''You want the president in an American chopper.''</p>
        <p>To which Stephen C. Moss, president of the United States subsidiary of AgustaWestland, Lockheed's European partner, counters: ''The real issue is whether you want competition on a level playing field or a win based on jingoist antiforeign sentiment in an election year.''</p>
        <p>Charged with sorting this out is the U.S. Navy, which found selecting of one of these two teams to be such a political hot potato that it kicked the decision up to the defense secretary, Donald H. Rumsfeld. He agreed with the Navy to delay the final decision until after the November election. The current presidential helicopter fleet is now 30 years old.</p>
        <p>At the moment, both sides are revving up the rhetoric and lining up powerful politicians behind their cause. Lockheed, which will build much of the US 101 in upstate New York, has the support of Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, who logged many hours on Marine One as first lady, and Gov. George E. Pataki. Sikorsky, whose helicopters, built in Stratford, Conn., currently carry the president, has the Connecticut Congressional delegation knocking on the Pentagon door.</p>
        <p>For all the struggle over politics and jobs, the decision is also affected by some hard practical considerations. Since the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks, the presidential fleet -- 11 Sikorsky Sea King and 8 Sea Hawk helicopters -- has become so weighed down with new security equipment that the helicopters are less safe and less maneuverable when taking off than they once were, both companies say. This has accelerated the Pentagon's timetable for replacing the fleet.</p>
        <p>While many people may think the president flies in only one of the helicopters, in reality all 19 are used to ferry not only the president, but also foreign dignitaries. When the president is on board, the copter gets the Marine One designation.</p>
        <p>The competition has both symbolic and financial importance. Most obviously, the winner will gain the prestige of making the helicopter that flies the most powerful person in global politics, at least for short distances.</p>
        <p>In addition, the winner of the relatively modest $1.6 billion deal is set up to receive potentially another $40 billion or so in contracts for military search-and-rescue missions from the United States and foreign governments as well as from corporations seeking to transport executives and oil-rig workers.</p>
        <p>''This contract will have a huge impact,'' said Richard Aboulafia, a military analyst at the Teal Group, a northern Virginia consulting group. ''This is the last big undecided military competition on the horizon, and the issues are both psychological and financial.''</p>
        <p>Given its high profile and ''these politically charged times,'' Mr. Aboulafia added, the competition can easily turn into an issue of ''do we want to be hurting a U.S. contractor and helping a foreign one?''</p>
        <p>The Marine One competition raises the question of how far the Pentagon will go to aid countries that supported the United States in Iraq. AgustaWestland, an Anglo-Italian venture, designed the helicopter and has lined up Lockheed and Bell Helicopter, along with dozens of other United States subcontractors, to do much of the work and give it an American veneer.</p>
        <p>And Lockheed is not above flag-waving itself. Its red-white-and-blue US 101 promotional literature is headlined ''American Jobs. American Pride.'' It features a model who vaguely looks like President Bush striding toward the craft.</p>
        <p>But it also is not shy about using its international connections. Already Mr. Blair, the British prime minister, has written a ''Dear George'' letter to President Bush praising the US 101 design, which is already in use by the British, Italian and Canadian armed forces. An AgustaWestland helicopter also ferries the pope.</p>
        <p>Last March, a delegation of high-level Italian business executives and government officials trooped through Washington, telling any lawmaker and Pentagon official who would listen that the US 101 would create 3,000 American jobs.</p>
        <p>They also said that, after spending billions on American military hardware and sending their soldiers to support the United States in Kosovo and Iraq, Italy would like some Pentagon business, too. Among those meeting the Italians were Gen. Richard B. Myers, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and the deputy defense secretary, Paul D. Wolfowitz.</p>
        <p>On the other side is the question of domestic politics and how far the government wants to go to support a company, Sikorsky, whose future is heavily dependent on landing this contract.</p>
        <p>Just recently, Sikorsky lost a military contract worth as much as $38 billion when the Pentagon decided to cancel the Comanche helicopter program. The company's bread-and-butter helicopter line -- Black Hawks, Sea Hawks, Sea Stallions and a variety of other medium- and heavy-lift helicopters -- have been in production for decades and the S-92 would be part of the company's next-generation product line.</p>
        <p>Sikorsky's S-92 would essentially be an updated version of the Black Hawk helicopter, and the company has already spent $500 million developing it.</p>
        <p>Even though President Dwight D. Eisenhower kicked off the White House helicopter era in a Bell helicopter on July 12, 1957, when he flew back and forth to Camp David, nearly every Marine One since has been a Sikorsky helicopter. A loss to Sikorsky would be both a financial and a psychological blow.</p>
        <p>''Having the president choose anything other than a Sikorsky product is absolutely unacceptable to us,'' said Stephen N. Finger, Sikorsky's president. ''Sikorsky has invested its own money and developed state-of-the-art helicopter capacity and that should be rewarded.''</p>
        <p>Of course, times were much simpler in the Eisenhower era. In contrast to the top-secret equipment in the current Marine One fleet, President Eisenhower flew in an off-the-shelf chopper, which was guided to his Gettysburg farm by a strobe light placed on top of a barn.</p>
        <p>With many aviation experts saying that either the Sikorsky or the AgustaWestland helicopter could do the job equally well, both companies are trying to gain the edge. On the technical side, Lockheed claims its three-engine helicopter is safer, while Sikorsky claims to have a superior fuel tank design.</p>
        <p>Sikorsky also has made sure that it can promote its helicopter as the all-American offering. Originally, parts were to have been made in Brazil, Japan and China. But Sikorsky dumped its foreign suppliers to better position itself to win the Marine One contract, even though it will continue with foreign content on the rest of the S-92 helicopter line.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Lockheed and AgustaWestland have noted that, in dollar terms, a full 90 percent of the value of the US 101 contract will go to suppliers in the United States. By law, all military products purchased by the Pentagon must have at least 50 percent domestic content.</p>
        <p>AgustaWestland picked a powerful partner in Lockheed, which, as the nation's largest military contractor, has the biggest budget for lobbying and political contributions. Lockheed and AgustaWestland have also been playing smart politics with their choice of suppliers and factory locations.</p>
        <p>Lockheed has already broken ground on a new helicopter facility in Owego, N.Y. In January, Gov. Pataki attended the ribbon-cutting ceremony; so did the state's Democratic senators, Charles E. Schumer and Mrs. Clinton, who emerged from her spin in a US 101 remarking that ''it landed like a feather.''</p>
        <p>To line up even more political support, Lockheed and AgustaWestland have spread out subcontracting work to locations in Connecticut, Texas, Maryland and Kansas.</p>
        <p>Sikorsky, of course, is not about to be beaten at the domestic politics game. Its ads bluntly ask: ''Shouldn't the president's helicopter be American?''</p>
        <p>It, too, has lined up an impressive array of subcontractors across the country, including Northrop Grumman, which is based in Los Angeles and has facilities in dozens of congressional districts, and General Electric, which, like Sikorsky, is headquartered in Connecticut but has many operations across the country. Both companies bring with them teams of skilled lobbyists.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Senator Christopher J. Dodd, the Connecticut Democrat, has been particularly active on Sikorsky's behalf, calling last April on Navy Secretary Gordon England to press his case in a private meeting.</p>
        <p>Sikorsky proudly notes that its helicopters have safely carried the president for decades and that more than 500 of its employees have ''Yankee White'' clearance, the maximum White House security clearance.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Sikorsky executives sniff that Lockheed has not been in the helicopter business historically, while their decades of making Black Hawks and other craft have given them a strong track record.</p>
        <p>Besides, Sikorsky's executives point out that today's allies could become tomorrow's foes during the helicopter's 40-year life span.</p>
        <p>''You just cannot bring in a spare part from anywhere overseas,'' Mr. Pino of Sikorsky said. ''How do you modify a part that's been built with an Italian design? What if Italy is not so friendly to us?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
