<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roadside Fare: Clams and Carousel Rides</title>
    <meta content="11CTDI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1595780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joe's Fish Tale (Madison, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDE123BF932A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roadside Fare: Clams and Carousel Rides</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Lenny and Joe's Fish Tale restaurant in Madison, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the back of a saltwater taffy box sold at the counter of Lenny and Joe's Fish Tail on Route 1 in Madison, you can read that Lenny and Joe's started out as a roadside clam shack in 1979 with four picnic tables.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five years later, the place still has an appealing roadside eatery feel, but it has grown substantially. Now there is a main indoor restaurant area with a kitchen, an indoor lobster stand -- a side area that houses the lobster steamers and more wooden tables -- and outside picnic seating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the back of a saltwater taffy box sold at the counter of Lenny and Joe's Fish Tail on Route 1 in Madison, you can read that Lenny and Joe's started out as a roadside clam shack in 1979 with four picnic tables.</p>
        <p>Twenty-five years later, the place still has an appealing roadside eatery feel, but it has grown substantially. Now there is a main indoor restaurant area with a kitchen, an indoor lobster stand -- a side area that houses the lobster steamers and more wooden tables -- and outside picnic seating.</p>
        <p>You order at a counter and your number is called when the food is ready. I've been there when the wait at the counter was five or six people deep. But the food comes fast and it is not fast-food. Some of it is terrific; a lot of it is pretty average. But it is real food, and despite the fact that the restaurant is now open year-round, it has New England summer fare: lobster, fried scallops, fried clams, coleslaw, lobster rolls and onion rings.</p>
        <p>A manager I spoke to said the seafood was purchased from the Boston market, from day boats (presumably when possible). Lenny and Joe's strikes me as something of a theme park in the best sense of the phrase, where the theme is New England summer seaside, with its fried seafood, ice cream and sunburned children. You can buy T-shirts and baseball hats with the name of the restaurant emblazoned on them.</p>
        <p>Outside the restaurant there is a charming, working, wooden carousel, imported from the Dentzel Carousel Company in Port Townsend, Wash. All of the pieces are handmade and hand painted. True to the seaside theme, you can ride an orca whale, a seal and a chariot braced by two lobsters. Proceeds from the $1 ride go to charity.</p>
        <p>Lenny's also provides an outside ice cream stand, selling soft ice cream and frozen yogurt in various flavors; it is just fine for children, but the ice cream tastes a little artificial to me. The best thing about Lenny's is the fried scallops. They are about as good as any fried scallop I've had anywhere. They are fresh, sweet and definitely ''dry'' -- meaning they are not soaked, as many scallops are, in a chemical solution that lengthens their shelf life and gives them a funny taste. The light crust is crisp and cooked just right and doesn't hide the taste of the scallop. They're served with an excellent tartar sauce made with dill pickles that complements the scallops perfectly. With a glass of Minute Maid lemonade, they make a very satisfying meal.</p>
        <p>The next best thing is the coleslaw -- another research specialty of mine. Lenny's is made with a light mayonnaise dressing seasoned with celery seed, the mild bitterness of which is offset by a little sweetness. Delicious. A friend ordered the king crab and lobster combo one night. His father was in the seafood business in New England and dealt in lobsters for a time. Like a pro, he cracked open each piece of the lobster separately, dipped it carefully in the melted butter and considered it: the ''arms'' of the lobster were a bit mealy; the claws were better. The meat was firm, as was the tail meat. He rated it an 8 out of 10. Other things are not quite so successful.</p>
        <p>The fried clams are fine, but could be sweeter. The soft-shell crab is cooked right but the heavy crust obscures the taste of the crab. The king crab legs are too salty. The shrimp is O.K. but can't compete with the scallops, either fried, or in the shrimp cocktail. (Nice cocktail sauce.) Fried scrod, however, is quite good. The clam chowder is Rhode Island style, which I abhor. (How can you like a grey soup?) Lenny's rendition may be terrific, but I can't judge.</p>
        <p>Lenny and Joe now have two other establishments, one in Westbrook and another in Westerly, R.I. The menu at the Westbrook restaurant is more extensive than in Madison. The prices are fair. It is a great place for children. Go have the scallops.</p>
        <p>Lenny and Joe's Fish Tale  1301 Boston Post Road, Madison  (203)245-7289</p>
        <p>Good  ATMOSPHERE: Casual, busy clam shack with outdoor carousel and ice cream stand.  NOISE LEVEL: Moderate.  SERVICE: Very, very fast; friendly.  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Fried scallops, fried scrod, lobster, fried clams.  PRICE RANGE: Appetizers and salads: $2.50 to $11.95. Sandwiches and rolls: $3.75 to $11.95; Dinners: $8.95 to $17.95. Lobster stand: $14.95 to $24.50  CREDIT CARDS: Cash only, but there is an A.T.M. machine  HOURS Restaurant: Sunday through Thursday, 11 a.m. to 10 p.m., until 10:30 p.m. on Friday and Saturday. Lobster stand: Sunday through Thursday, 11:30 a.m. to 9:30 p.m., Friday and Saturday, 11:30 a.m. through 10 p.m. Ice cream stand: Sunday through Thursday, noon to 9:30 p.m., Friday and Saturday, noon to 10 p.m. Closed Mondays. (Hours good through Labor Day; after that, call.)  RESERVATIONS: No.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY: Good.  REVIEWED BY THE TIMES: July, 11, 2004.  RATINGS: Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
