<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Day of Upsets: Sampras Exits, As Does Agassi</title>
    <meta content="27TENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/27/sports/tennis/27TENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1403934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bastl, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampras, Pete</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Srichaphan, Paradorn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Agassi, Andre</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Florida</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Sampras, Pete</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DE123EF934A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Day of Upsets: Sampras Exits, As Does Agassi</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Day of Upsets at Wimbledon</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Bastl defeats Pete Sampras in second round of Wimbledon; Paradorn Srichaphan defeats Andre Agassi in straight sets; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The jolts to Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi were almost simultaneous as their Wimbledon runs ended today under Windex-blue skies, but the depth of their reactions was far from equal.</p>
        <p>Unable to counter the lion tamer's wrist snap on the uncanny strokes of Paradorn Srichaphan of Thailand, a disappointed Agassi quickly stuffed his racket bag after his straight-sets loss and hustled off Center Court, his mind moving forward, not back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pete Sampras, Andre Agassi and Marat Safin lost at Wimbledon on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The jolts to Pete Sampras and Andre Agassi were almost simultaneous as their Wimbledon runs ended today under Windex-blue skies, but the depth of their reactions was far from equal.</p>
        <p>Unable to counter the lion tamer's wrist snap on the uncanny strokes of Paradorn Srichaphan of Thailand, a disappointed Agassi quickly stuffed his racket bag after his straight-sets loss and hustled off Center Court, his mind moving forward, not back.</p>
        <p>Sampras was stuck, unable to budge in his disbelief. For several minutes after losing to the unknown George Bastl, Sampras sat in a chair on Court No. 2, aimlessly shifting around his racket strings, trying to sort through his devastation.</p>
        <p>''The future is flying home,'' Sampras said after a 6-3, 6-2, 4-6, 3-6, 6-4 loss in which he served 8 aces to 10 double faults. ''I plan on being back. You know, I'm not going to end my time here with this loss. And so. . . .''</p>
        <p>His voice trailed off, tears pooling in his eyes. He took a deep breath to gather himself. It was too overwhelming to contemplate for Sampras. After seven Wimbledon titles, just two years removed from winning a record 13th major, how could he hit bottom so fast?</p>
        <p>But there he was, faced with a lucky loser like Bastl, a 27-year-old Chicago native whose circuitous career led him through the University of Florida, Southern Cal, on to Switzerland and into anonymity.</p>
        <p>Somehow, Bastl chose a racket over a stick in a household where his father played minor league hockey for the Chicago Blackhawks' organization. Somehow, after an injury to Félix Mantilla gave him a spot in the draw, Bastl ended up on Court No. 2, the Graveyard of Champions, where the likes of John McEnroe and Jimmy Connors have vanished in upsets over the years.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't happy about it,'' said the sixth-seeded Sampras, more comfortable on the roomy show courts he has been used to at Wimbledon. ''But it's a moot point now.''</p>
        <p>After all, the measurements of the court were the same, as were the vast dimensions of Sampras's slump. He spent two and a half sets moving as if he had concrete in the soles of his Nikes, botching volleys fielded behind the service line, too far back to do any damage. Not long ago, he would have been on top of the net, perched like a gargoyle, waiting to stab an opponent's shot.</p>
        <p>''What he's going through is 90 percent mental,'' said Paul Annacone, who coached Sampras before their split last season. ''I don't want to see him stop. I think anyone who is a great champion doesn't want it to go away.''</p>
        <p>In an attempt to hang on to the match, Sampras found a burst of energy in the third set, able to fight back from a break down. Suddenly, his volleys were crisper, his thinking more clear. Desperate for positive reinforcement, he pulled a note from his bag after he came back to win the third set.</p>
        <p>''A letter I was reading just to keep me positive,'' Sampras said. ''It made me feel better.''</p>
        <p>It was a note from his wife, Bridgette Wilson-Sampras, who explained that it was ''just a wife's support for her husband.''</p>
        <p>This is the state Sampras is in: His confidence is in need of reminders.</p>
        <p>It was not as if he were the lone star loser on this day. Besides the third-seeded Agassi, the second-seeded Marat Safin, all 6 feet 4 inches of him, went into a mental fade against a player the size of an appetizer, the 5-4 Olivier Rochus of Belgium, and lost, 6-2, 6-4, 3-6, 7-6 (1).</p>
        <p>By the end of the day, the men's draw was in disarray, with fifth-seeded Yevgeny Kafelnikov and 11th-seeded Andy Roddick listed as two of the few survivors on a wicked day for big names.</p>
        <p>Yet the women's bracket remained intact, with Jennifer Capriati and Serena Williams easing into the third round.</p>
        <p>The American men were not so fortunate. Usually, at least one star, Agassi or Sampras, carries on in a major. For the first time since they have played Wimbledon together, Agassi and Sampras are out before the third round.</p>
        <p>Sampras did not take solace in his miserable company. Once, he was invincible. Now, at age 30, he feels nothing but vulnerable, exiting his 30th straight event without a title. For two years, the major that used to save his season has been betraying him.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a tough flight home,'' Sampras said, ''just knowing that this is going on, and I'm not there.''</p>
        <p>It's not like Agassi to pine. With tournament victories under his belt this year and a well-rounded life outside the court, Agassi is not wrestling with the same demons as Sampras. At age 32, his career is not in decline; his fitness is not an issue; his confidence is not in ruins.</p>
        <p>Agassi's loss to the talented if erratic Srichaphan, 6-4, 7-6 (5), 6-2, was chalked up to a day when Agassi was not at his best, nothing more.</p>
        <p>''I'm a little stunned, certainly disappointed,'' Agassi said. ''Just never found my rhythm. I played a very average match against a guy who was taking it to me and deserved to win.''</p>
        <p>The son of a schoolteacher, Srichaphan has been known to play above his 67th ranking on certain occasions, like the Davis Cup. He is proud of his country, citing his victory today as a ''great day for Thai tennis.''</p>
        <p>He made Thailand proud with his patience. Staying stroke for stroke with Agassi, he worked each point until he found an opening for one of his 33 winners. Any chance Agassi had at revival ended on a close line call during the second-set tie breaker. At 5-all, Srichaphan swiped a deep forehand that may or may not have clipped the line. Agassi thought it was out.</p>
        <p>Instead of facing a set point, Srichaphan gained the 6-5 edge, then smacked a service winner for the commanding two-set lead. Unable to find his trademark precision, producing 35 errors on the day, Agassi did not have a comeback in him.</p>
        <p>''You have to make adjustments; you have to keep working,'' Agassi said. ''There's no choice if you want to continue to be out there.''</p>
        <p>Adapting has always come easier for Agassi than Sampras. Although their names are as forever linked as Smith and Corona, they have maneuvered through their intertwined lives with contrasting evolutions.</p>
        <p>Agassi has always been a work in progress, with Sampras known as the creature of habit. Now, as the ends to their careers loom, Agassi seems more prepared to handle the passage into a finale, whereas Sampras is more fearful of the route to the inevitable.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to stop on my own terms, not when someone else thinks I should stop,'' Sampras said. ''What I've done here and what I've done in the game is going to stick, no matter what happens over the next couple of years.''</p>
        <p>If no one else, he was trying to convince himself.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
