<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lost and Found: A Museum of Misplaced Objects Is 200</title>
    <meta content="23PARI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/23/international/europe/23paris.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Paris Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lost and Found Property</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lost and Found Property</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71539F930A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lost and Found: A Museum of Misplaced Objects Is 200</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lost and Found: A Museum of Misplaced Objects Is 200</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lost-and-found office in Paris, France, celebrates 200th anniversary; last year, office and its 43 employees took in more than 173,000 objects; it is archive of the mundane, the valuable and the simply bizarre; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French Revolution provided liberty, equality, fraternity and the lost-and-found office.</p>
        <p>Two hundred years ago, Napoleon ordered his prefect of police to establish an office on the Ile de la Cité for lost objects, which officials here say was the first of its kind anywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Napoleon ordered his prefect of police to establish the first lost-and-found office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The French Revolution provided liberty, equality, fraternity and the lost-and-found office.</p>
        <p>Two hundred years ago, Napoleon ordered his prefect of police to establish an office on the Ile de la Cité for lost objects, which officials here say was the first of its kind anywhere.</p>
        <p>''It was in the spirit of centralization,'' said Jean-Michel Ingrandt, 58, who left the Interior Ministry four years ago to become the office's latest director, now in the southern 15th Arrondissement. ''To collect all objects found in the streets of Paris.''</p>
        <p>The anniversary is no large event in a nation that measures history by dynasties, empires and revolutions. So to celebrate it, Mr. Ingrandt has hung the broad reception room where Parisians come to claim their property with photos of documents illustrating the office's history.</p>
        <p>What he does not show is the immense warehouse under the reception room where unclaimed objects fill floor-to-ceiling shelves. Also not shown is what he calls the ''cabinet of curiosities,'' including several human skulls, muzzle-loading pistols, a violin, a wooden leg and even two chunks of masonry from the World Trade Center site in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>No Louvre or Musée d'Orsay, the office is nonetheless a kind of monument to the little man. Certain objects, like umbrellas, keys, wallets and handbags, resist time's tooth; others change with fashion and technology: men's cufflinks and ladies hats, once common, are now rarities; cellphones, unknown a decade or so ago, now come in at the rate of 40 a day.</p>
        <p>Most objects are found on or around some means of transportation -- in the Paris Métro, in taxis or buses or trains, at train stations and airports. The kinds of objects change with the season: in winter, skis; in summer, sunglasses and roller skates. ''We are, in a way, a museum of daily life,'' Mr. Ingrandt said.</p>
        <p>Last year, the office and its 43 employees took in more than 173,000 objects, 15 percent more than in 2003. Mr. Ingrandt attributes the increase to the pace of life today. ''The modern world is in a hurry,'' he said. ''We find medical files, student files, occasionally an entire doctoral thesis.''</p>
        <p>'That can have dramatic consequences,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In 1893, a legendary prefect of police, Louis Lépine, laid the groundwork for a system by which the office not only waits for Parisians to claim their property but does detective work to find them. Still, only about one in four objects finds its way back to its owner.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Ingrandt tracked down a woman in New York after a pouch was turned in that contained five cut diamonds and a doctor's business card. The doctor was able to identify the owner, who boarded a plane for Paris to pick up her diamonds in person. ''She was persuaded she would never see them again,'' Mr. Ingrandt said.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is as satisfied. Cyrin Gamin, 28, came by during a recent lunch break with his companion to see if her stolen backpack, which contained all her identification papers, had turned up. ''They said to return in a month,'' he said dejectedly.</p>
        <p>Indeed, such is the daily avalanche of objects that most are kept for only three months, unless they are particularly valuable or unusual, after which they are destroyed or sold at auction. Even so, the office's immense warehouse is bursting with objects.</p>
        <p>''A truckload arrives each day, just from the Paris subways,'' said Lean-Luc Faidherbe, 41, who has managed the warehouse for the last six years. Shelves from floor to ceiling are filled with keys, eyeglasses, motorcycle helmets, bicycles. ''The city government is pushing the use of bicycles,'' Mr. Ingrandt said. ''So last year we received 51 bicycles.''</p>
        <p>Some objects are either so valuable or so peculiar that they are not discarded but displayed in a corner of the warehouse. Some are grisly: five human skulls, probably left by medical students; a mechanical leg.</p>
        <p>Some are historic: a Napoleonic-era saber; helmets, including one from a World War I French poilu, or soldier.</p>
        <p>Others are scientific: a tripod and telescope from Victorian England; a boxed set of 200 light blue butterflies.</p>
        <p>Some are simply bizarre: a 250-pound coil of copper sheathing (Mr. Ingrandt surmises that someone stole it from a construction site, found it too heavy to carry and dumped it on the subway); two floor-length wedding gowns with shoes to match, also left on the subway.</p>
        <p>In a small locked room nearby, Mr. Faidherbe stores the largest collection of any one kind of object: more than 3,500 cellphones, numbered and nestled on shelves. More valuable items like phones are kept for 18 months to allow the owners more time to claim them.</p>
        <p>''Every now and then,'' Mr. Faidherbe said, ''one of them rings.''</p>
        <p>Paris Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
