<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Distinct Reality Is The One To Watch</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="619877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREMONT STAKES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DD163EF935A35754C0A965958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Distinct Reality Is The One To Watch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Belmont Park rang down the curtain on its booming holiday weekend yesterday with the 101st running of the Tremont, a race that has launched many 2-year-old colts into the big leagues of stakes racing. And the colt who was launched this time was Distinct Reality, winning his second straight race and doing it against a field of six other juveniles with breeding, credentials and great expectations.</p>
        <p>Distinct Reality ran a textbook sprint with Jerry Bailey riding, kept his poise when Fabulous Force shot the first quarter-mile in 21 1/5 seconds and the half-mile in 44 4/5 seconds, and then kicked into high in the homestretch. At the wire of the five-and-one-half-furlong race, he had two lengths on Gusto Z, who in turn had a length and a half on Slew Gen Fizz.  Then it was more than three lengths back to the favorite, Code Home. Lacking a Past</p>
        <p>Juveniles are probably the least predictable horses in the business, and for good reasons. They may come to the races with royal pedigrees and smart trainers, but none comes with a past-performance record or even a past. Many can run fast, but not many can run far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Belmont Park rang down the curtain on its booming holiday weekend yesterday with the 101st running of the Tremont, a race that has launched many 2-year-old colts into the big leagues of stakes racing. And the colt who was launched this time was Distinct Reality, winning his second straight race and doing it against a field of six other juveniles with breeding, credentials and great expectations.</p>
        <p>Distinct Reality ran a textbook sprint with Jerry Bailey riding, kept his poise when Fabulous Force shot the first quarter-mile in 21 1/5 seconds and the half-mile in 44 4/5 seconds, and then kicked into high in the homestretch. At the wire of the five-and-one-half-furlong race, he had two lengths on Gusto Z, who in turn had a length and a half on Slew Gen Fizz.  Then it was more than three lengths back to the favorite, Code Home. Lacking a Past</p>
        <p>Juveniles are probably the least predictable horses in the business, and for good reasons. They may come to the races with royal pedigrees and smart trainers, but none comes with a past-performance record or even a past. Many can run fast, but not many can run far.</p>
        <p>Still, the Tremont was won the last three years by Hansel, Salt Lake and England Expects, all of whom went on to good careers. And in the more distant past, it was won by Alydar, Foolish Pleasure, Bold Forbes, Buckpasser and even Man o'War, all of whom went on to stellar careers.</p>
        <p>This year's candidate for stardom, Distinct Reality, is a dark brown son of Distinctive Pro and the mare Cornish Art, and he won his only other race by simply taking the lead and holding it. That was three weeks ago, also at Belmont Park. On to Saratoga</p>
        <p>This time, he added the dimension of pace to his repertory. And the speed was still there. He finished in 1:04 3/5 and paid a rousing $18.80 for $2 to win. He's not likely to pay like that again. He also went home to the Triumviri Stable with first prize of $67,470.</p>
        <p>"He's done everything right so far," said his trainer, Stanley Hough. "He's got speed, but there was a lot of it in the race, anyway. It wasn't the plan to take him back; we were just going to take it as it came. Next? I'd like to have him ready for the first week at Saratoga."</p>
        <p>Bailey, the steady 33-year-old club pro who won the Kentucky Derby in May aboard Sea Hero, reported that Hough "told me if he gets outrun early not to worry about it."</p>
        <p>"And that's what happened," he concluded.</p>
        <p>Then, in a concurring opinion, he said: "He's two for two now, and hasn't done anything wrong." A Big Weekend</p>
        <p>So, who else fired skyrockets on Belmont's big holiday weekend?</p>
        <p>Leo O'Brien, for one. He opened the weekend on Friday by winning the Astoria Breeders' Cup with his 2-year-old colt Casa Eire, who not only established some juvenile credentials for himself but also outran the hotshot Camcorder. And he did it one week after O'Brien had scored at the other end of the age spectrum with his 8-year-old gelding Fourstardave, who won the Poker Stakes against some horses half his age. O'Brien's explanation: "He just gets better with age."</p>
        <p>But the heavy hitters of the weekend were Allen Jerkens and Julie Krone, who made the winner's circle twice on Saturday in major stakes races.</p>
        <p>They made it as a team after Jerkens saddled the classy filly Classy Mirage and Krone rode her to victory in the Prioress Stakes for 2-year-old debutantes. Then they made separate appearances: Krone as the winning rider on Llandoff in the Lexington Stakes, and Jerkens as the winning trainer of Devil His Due in the main event of the weekend, the Suburban Handicap. FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>The countdown to Saratoga's five-week season of stakes racing will continue next weekend at Belmont with the Tom Fool on Saturday, a sprint test of seven furlongs for some of the senior stars in residence. The lead roles are expected to be played by TOMMY VALANDO's Fly So Free, who is 5 years old and still rolling; BILL CONDREN's Loach, the onetime "rabbit" for Strike the Gold, and BARRY K. SCHWARTZ's Killer Diller, the old reliable of the stable. But the piece de resistance, the Coaching Club American Oaks, comes on Sunday, and it figures to call for Jerkens to make one more appearance in the winner's circle, this time with his incomparable filly, GEORGIA HOFMANN's Sky Beauty. If they win this one, they win more than a big race: They also win New York's Triple Tiara for fillies. Sky Beauty has already bagged the first two races in the series, the Acorn and the Mother Goose, and needs one more to complete the sweep.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
