<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Price of Illiteracy Translates Into Poverty and Humiliation</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="America's Illiterates - First of three articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="177234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ILLITERACY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MACK, IVA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGER, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illiteracy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DC133EF935A3575AC0A96E948260" item-length="1635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Price of Illiteracy Translates Into Poverty and Humiliation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERGER, JOSEPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Iva Mack nearly always orders a hamburger when she eats in a coffee shop. She is not especially fond of hamburgers. But she cannot read a menu and is fairly sure a coffee shop will have a hamburger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Iva Mack nearly always orders a hamburger when she eats in a coffee shop. She is not especially fond of hamburgers. But she cannot read a menu and is fairly sure a coffee shop will have a hamburger.</p>
        <p>Iva Mack nearly always orders a hamburger when she eats in a coffee shop. She is not especially fond of hamburgers. But she cannot read a menu and is fairly sure a coffee shop will have a hamburger.</p>
        <p>At the supermarket, she can pick out foods she recognizes, like a package of spaghetti, but she cannot distinguish pea soup from tomato soup unless the cans have pictures of what is inside. Mrs. Mack cannot read labels. The 51-year-old Mrs. Mack, who lives in Brooklyn and grew up in a sharecropper's family in South Carolina, is functionally illiterate. It has been estimated that there are more than 23 million people like her in the United States, and some experts say the number is growing at an alarming rate at the same time that the nation needs more workers with higher literacy.</p>
        <p>That means their problem is not just a personal one. In an economy that is increasingly shifting from manufacturing to service, businesses cannot find the secretaries, clerks, bank tellers, repair people and other entry-level employees they need because too many applicants cannot read, write or add well enough. The New York Telephone Company, for example, recently tested 22,880 applicants for operator and repair technician positions. Only 3,619, or 14 percent, passed. Some Turn to Crime</p>
        <p>Those who cannot find work end up costing the Government billions of dollars in welfare and unemployment compensation. Some end up turning to crime. One expert has estimated that 60 percent of the state and Federal prison population of 440,000 cannot read above the sixth grade level.</p>
        <p>As a reflection of national concern on illiteracy, the American Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation and the International Reading Association are sponsoring the National Adult Literacy Symposium at the National Press Club in Washington Thursday. Representatives from government, newspapers and education will convene, in part to focus national attention on the problem.</p>
        <p>Many schools, government agencies, corporations and private foundations are spending millions of dollars and years of effort to try to fight illiteracy. But leaders of these efforts acknowledge increasing frustration.</p>
        <p>Illiterate people's lives are crippled by their inability to read and write, are filled with anxiety and embarrassment because they cannot perform routines many take for granted. They are deprived of some of life's easy pleasures.</p>
        <p>It is not simply that illiterate adults cannot read books or newspapers. They cannot read street signs well enough to make their way around unfamiliar neighborhoods. They cannot read subway and bus signs to travel to remote sections. To cope, many rely on a variety of inventive strategies to find their way to places.</p>
        <p>''Urban living in the United States requires a certain level of reading skills,'' says David Harman, a professor of education at Teachers College of Columbia University who is the author of two books on adult illiteracy. ''Urban living is based on the notion that instructions to the public are communicated in writing.'' Share of Disheartening Experiences</p>
        <p>Illiterate adults cannot read leases, welfare forms or job applications. They cannot read the labels on medicine that warn of hazards. They cannot read the names of the Presidential candidates in a voting booth.</p>
        <p>Most disheartening for many illiterate adults is that they cannot help their children learn to read, said Jonathan Kozol, who wrote ''Illiterate America,'' which was published by Doubleday &amp; Company Inc. in 1985. Many pass on the deficiency that has given them such pain, often condemning their children to a life of poverty.</p>
        <p>''Most illiterate mothers know that it is important to read and they suffer terribly because they know it is important and they cannot help their children to do it,'' Mr. Kozol said. ''You see the specter of generations of illiterates and that is the darkest part of the story.''</p>
        <p>A glimpse into the life of Iva Mack suggests how difficult it has become for the illiterate to negotiate the dense texture of a modern society.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mack, a solemn woman who speaks in a soft voice, has worked most of her adult life cleaning homes and cooking. She now works for The College Board in Manhattan, making coffee and setting out pastries and other foods in an employee dining room.</p>
        <p>Even when she worked as a housemaid, she had problems because she could not read. Her employer would send her shopping and ''sometimes I would pick up the wrong things and bring it back and then I had to go back to the store,'' she said. When she had to change jobs, she had to find another by asking friends. She could not simply look in newspaper classified ads. A Legacy of Illiteracy</p>
        <p>From birth, there was almost a sense of destiny about Mrs. Mack's illiteracy. Her name was misspelled on her birth certificate as Iva, though it was meant to be and is pronounced Eva. Like so many other illiterate adults, Mrs. Mack grew up in a family and a community who provided no reinforcement for any impulse she felt to read.</p>
        <p>When she was an infant, her parents gave her away to neighbors in Wood Ford, S.C., whose members could not read or write. That family reared her and sent her to a two-room schoolhouse a mile from her home. She stopped going after the fourth grade.</p>
        <p>''We was on a farm, picking cotton and peaches, and somebody had to cook and there was four other kids, so I stayed home and cooked and cleaned and they went to school,'' she said. ''I was the oldest.''</p>
        <p>The school authorities never troubled the family about Iva's not showing up at school. ''When you live on a farm, who knows when you going to school,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Harman, of Columbia, points out that a fourth-grade reading level - if Mrs. Mack achieved that - would deterioriate with nonuse, becoming a first-or second-grade reading level by adulthood. ''It's not like bike riding,'' he said. ''If you don't ride a bike for 10 years you get on a bike and can still ride. But reading is one of those things that recedes if it is not used.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mack retained only a rudimentary and halting knowledge of the letters of the alphabet.</p>
        <p>She married when she was 14 and had two children. In 1959, when she was 22, she moved to New York because she wanted to earn money as a domestic so she could buy two air-conditioners for her children's rooms. ''I did never go back,'' she said. New York Is a Riddle</p>
        <p>New York, which the New York City Adult Literacy Initiative estimates has 1.5 million functionally illiterate residents, has always been a riddle to her.</p>
        <p>''It's terrible,'' Mrs. Mack says. ''You want to go someplace, you don't know how to spell the street. Let's say it's Tompkins Avenue and they tell you to go there and you have to ask somebody to write it down for you.''</p>
        <p>She might follow landmarks or compare street signs with the slip of paper she has, but even then there is the hovering threat of embarrassment. ''You could say to someone, 'Do you know where Tompkins Avenue is at?' And you could be right there at the place you want to go.''</p>
        <p>Her daughter, Emma Mae, is now 32 and her son, Emanuel, is 29, and both are high school graduates. But when they were small she could not help them with their homework.</p>
        <p>''They would ask you, 'What's this word, Momma?' And I'd tell them I didn't know, and we had to go downstairs and get my cousin.''</p>
        <p>When the children grew older, they returned to South Carolina, and Mrs. Mack would visit them several times a year by bus. She would have a friend write down the name of two large bus companies going to Columbia, S.C.: Greyhound and Trailways. Then she would take a taxi to the Port Authority Bus Terminal at 42d Street and Eighth Avenue and hunt for a sign that matched the words on her slip of paper. She kept the slip of paper for years.  ''If the page got ragged,'' she said, ''I would write it over or write it on my hand.'' She Masters the Airport</p>
        <p>In recent years, she has learned how to make the trip by airplane, and can recognize the name of the airline she takes by sight. ''I know Piedmont when I see it,'' she said proudly.</p>
        <p>Over the years, Mrs. Mack has improvised strategies to help her get along without reading. In her College Board job, she is often asked to shop for lunch, and she will write down J for orange juice, B for bread and so on. ''So when I go into the store, I have a list like anyone else,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Still, she has come to yearn to read simply for the pleasure of it. ''I want to read the paper,'' she said. ''I see people in the train reading books and it makes you feel, 'If I could read something like that, riding the train.' But you have to sit in the train and just look.''</p>
        <p>She also wants to read the Bible. ''When I go to church the preacher will say, 'You can read this verse from the Bible.' Some of it I can read, but some of it I have to skip over.'' Some time ago, she met a stranger on an airplane who learned of her interest in the Bible and sent her a copy of a children's Bible. She is trying to read it.</p>
        <p>Despite her illiteracy, she has long harbored the dream of returning to school, even of getting a high school equivalency diploma.</p>
        <p>''On television, I saw an 80 year-old woman graduating from high school. I cried and cried. She was crying and her kids were crying and her grandchildren were crying. and I said, 'Lord, if she can do it, I can do it.' ''</p>
        <p>The personnel officer at the College Board told her the Literacy Volunteers of New York City might help her learn to read. In June, she began taking tutoring twice weekly. She is working on writing down her life's story.</p>
        <p>''I want to learn to read and write,'' she said. ''I don't want to ask nobody to do stuff for me. You get tired of eating one thing - hamburger.''  Tomorrow: The effects of illiteracy on the nation's work force.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
