<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Life, New Pursuit For Hastings Watchdogs</title>
    <meta content="22wehast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1733826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D6153FF931A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Life, New Pursuit For Hastings Watchdogs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <dateline>HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS live-work lofts gain wide acceptance in other parts of Westchester, a proposal for 60 units here has reawakened the protective instincts of a watchdog group.</p>
        <p>Worried about pedestrian safety, flooding and overcrowded schools, the group, the Ravensdale Neighborhood Association, has reorganized after a period of dormancy. It formed in the 1950's but has existed only intermittently since then.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS live-work lofts gain wide acceptance in other parts of Westchester, a proposal for 60 units here has reawakened the protective instincts of a watchdog group.</p>
        <p>Worried about pedestrian safety, flooding and overcrowded schools, the group, the Ravensdale Neighborhood Association, has reorganized after a period of dormancy. It formed in the 1950's but has existed only intermittently since then.</p>
        <p>Galvanized by a public hearing in November at which Ginsburg Development presented plans for the Saw Mill Lofts near the Hastings border with Ardsley, Elizabeth Felber, an association member, said, ''We decided to start ringing doorbells and organizing again.''</p>
        <p>The units would be marketed to a mix of work-at-home types -- writers, consultants, artists, architects and other self-employed professionals. Each would include 600 square feet of work space in addition to living space, for a total of up to 2,000 square feet, depending on the number of bedrooms.</p>
        <p>Ginsburg is proposing to build them in two three-story elevator buildings near a commercial area along Saw Mill River Road, in keeping with the local zoning restrictions for that neighborhood. But according to Ginsburg's president and chief executive, Martin Ginsburg, few locales are as difficult to build in as this Hudson River community. A proposal that might succeed elsewhere, he said, could founder here.</p>
        <p>''The people in Hastings are always striving for Nirvana,'' said Mr. Ginsburg, whose firm is one of the leading developers in Westchester and has built other housing in this community. ''The problem is, Nirvana can't be built on earth, although I always try to get as close to it as I can.''</p>
        <p>The neighborhood organization, on the other hand, sees its concerns as more down-to-earth. One is that runoff from flooding would cause water problems in the nearby Ravensdale section of the village. Another is that even though the developer estimates that the project would add 16 children to the school district -- in this case Ardsley -- the association believes that the actual number may be two to three times that. ''A lot of people who work at home are young parents,'' Mrs. Felber said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsburg described his most recent efforts to build in Hastings as ''a saga,'' but he praised the planning and zoning board for being knowledgeable and committed.</p>
        <p>Francis A. Frobel, the village's manager for the past six months, expressed appreciation for the public scrutiny that such proposals get in Hastings. ''Residents here pay very close attention to local government affairs,'' he said, ''and that's not unique to this project. It's across the board, and it's refreshing to see people who take that kind of interest in their community.''</p>
        <p>In the late 1990's, the vacant seven-and-a-half-acre parcel that Mr. Ginsburg is eyeing for the live-work lofts was the subject of an application for a ShopRite supermarket. Villagers strenuously opposed the plan, largely because they feared traffic increases and flooding problems (the site is contiguous to a flood plain). Mr. Ginsburg acquired the land from ShopRite four years ago, proposing 157 rental town houses for the property, which contains two and a half acres of paved parking area, formerly used as spillover parking for a nearby office complex.</p>
        <p>''We thought we were coming into Hastings as a white knight,'' Mr. Ginsburg recalled. ''There was the threat of a major supermarket, and we got ShopRite to abandon that idea.''</p>
        <p>Over time, the white knight image ''has become a little dingy,'' he conceded. Instead, he describes himself as continuing to jump through hoops in the hopes of winning approval to build something.</p>
        <p>The live-work proposal was his response to the village planning board's rejection of the town house plan. If approved, he said, it would provide almost two acres of open space for playing fields or a park. He also said the plan fit in with a recent rezoning designation for the property as a ''mixed-use planned development district,'' which allows housing for the elderly, attached single-family town houses, a mixed-use residential building, health clubs and municipal parks.</p>
        <p>The planning board is studying the application, especially its potential environmental impact; the neighborhood association remains to be convinced.</p>
        <p>Even if his company is allowed to build the 60 units, Mr. Ginsburg says he is pessimistic about the financial outcome. According to the village's requirements, 10 percent of the units must be affordable, which reduces a builder's profits, he says. Sales prices for the units have yet to be set. Also, this project would be the first in the village required to pay a new recreation fee, which would amount to $7,500 or more. And one-third of the property would be donated as open space to the village.</p>
        <p>Patricia Speranza, chairwoman of the planning board, said: ''I understand Mr. Ginsburg's frustration, but the planning board's charge is not to ensure that anyone makes money. It's to make sure the development of any property is done in a way that doesn't jeopardize the village.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
