<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answered Prayers</title>
    <meta content="19RODBERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/19/books/review/19RODBERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1393770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodberg, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heuston, Kimberly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shakeress, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Shakers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Heuston, Kimberly</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3DD1030F93AA25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answered Prayers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Shakeress': Answered Prayers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Simon Rodberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rodberg, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Simon Rodberg reviews book The Shakeress by Kimberly Heuston; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SHAKERESS</p>
        <p>By Kimberly Heuston.</p>
        <p>207 pp. Asheville, N.C.:</p>
        <p>Front Street. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 12 and up)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The energy of Kimberly Heuston's orphan tale set in the 1830's is entirely aimed at the mystery of God.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SHAKERESS</p>
        <p>By Kimberly Heuston.</p>
        <p>207 pp. Asheville, N.C.:</p>
        <p>Front Street. $16.95.</p>
        <p>(Ages 12 and up)</p>
        <p>A POOR orphan searches for her way in the world, with the help of plucky comrades and her own stout spirit. As she reaches self-knowledge, the handsome heir of a wealthy family sees past her humble garb to ask for her work-stained hand in marriage.</p>
        <p>Sound like a fairy tale? Kimberly Heuston's thoughtful and ambitious novel ''The Shakeress'' doesn't end there. True love is not the answer for Naomi, the confident heroine of the title. The book's climax comes not with the lover on his knees in love, but with Naomi on her knees in prayer. In the annals of orphan literature, the success of the Harry Potter series comes largely from the intrigues of wizardry. The energy of this orphan tale set in the 1830's is entirely aimed at the mystery of God.</p>
        <p>After her parents' deaths in a fire, Naomi and her siblings move to one of the Shaker settlements that dotted New England. The Shaker way of simplicity and work comforts the girl, who develops a talent for herbalism and healing under the watch of a stern but compassionate mentor. Though she's a little too reflective to be convincingly 13, Naomi is sympathetic and likable. As she grows and leaves the Shaker community to become ''one of the World's people,'' our hearts go with her. Where her religious quest takes her, however, not every reader will follow.</p>
        <p>The world of the novel is authentic early Republic, the time of the Second Great Awakening. Every family Naomi comes across swears by a different religion, and God seems to be everyone's favorite conversational subject. The fervor never leads to conflict, or even mutual disrespect; Heuston, a teacher and first-time novelist, gives us a primer on American religion that is agreeably free of bombast. Her light touch extends to the history as well. Even those who dislike the ostentation of much historical fiction will welcome Heuston's smooth re-creation of New England when parts were still being settled.</p>
        <p>Heuston's talents extend to simple, affecting prose, and she maintains the book's forward motion despite its substitution of interior drama for plot. Naomi has essentially no antagonists or truly engaging co-conspirators. The interior drama is the staple of young-adult fiction, but conflicts with other people (boyfriends, parents, captains of the cheerleading team) usually help make the story dramatic. Here, Naomi's spiritual -- not even emotional! -- issues take us through seven years of adolescence in a brief 200 pages.</p>
        <p>These are seven years of spiritual heavy lifting. At 13, arriving at the Shaker village, ''she found herself praying with such intensity that the words seemed to surge through her veins with every heartbeat: Please be here. We want to stay, but we can't if You aren't with us.'' At 16, she explains her decision to leave: ''It's almost like He's waiting for me to do something, for me to finish becoming the woman I am underneath, before He can talk to me in a way that I can understand.'') These are not the life crises of a typical 16-year-old, but Naomi never displays any sign of typical adolescence. (Her siblings are similarly ageless.) She is easy to root for, but, to any teenager who spends most of her hours thinking about something other than God, she may be difficult to identify with.</p>
        <p>A children's book about God is almost necessarily proselytizing, but ''The Shakeress'' suspensefully holds off showing its cards. After Naomi leaves the Shakers to serve as healer in a tiny Vermont village and meet her Prince Charming, it seems possible that hers will be a more personal than denominational resolution. After Heuston transcribes a page-long excerpt from the Book of Mormon, though, the answer to Naomi's questions become increasingly obvious. The ending is a decent surprise, but readers in search of clues to the the author's sympathies might look to the biography on the jacket flap, which gives her home as Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>Thankfully, the arrival of revelation doesn't spoil the search. Without subscribing to her religious sympathies, it is possible to appreciate Heuston's sensitive portrayal of religious life. Despite her unadolescent sagacity, Naomi makes an attractive heroine, a girl with lessons to teach beyond the theological. ''Life's not designed for cowards. It surely wasn't. You had to grab at it, then plan hard and work harder to make it beautiful, just like a garden.''</p>
        <p>As an independent, self-reliant teenage girl, Naomi provides a model for any quickly maturing questioner, even those who don't share her questions. Her quest is recognizable and welcoming. Tolerance for God-related musings and a God-inspired ending are, however, necessary equipment for this journey.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S BOOKS Simon Rodberg teaches elementary school in Lawrence, Mass.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Simon Rodberg teaches elementary school in Lawrence, Mass.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
