<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Bridgeport; City of Bridges Weighs Repairing Two of Them</title>
    <meta content="19VIEW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1393442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Congress Street Bridge (Bridgeport, Conn)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pleasure Beach Bridge (Bridgeport, Conn)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holtz, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E1D91139F93AA25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Bridgeport; City of Bridges Weighs Repairing Two of Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF HOLTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holtz, Jeff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on controversy in Bridgeport, Conn, over whether to replace Congress Street Bridge, which has been closed since 1997, and Pleasure Beach Bridge, which closed after 1996 fire; part of $50 million in replacement costs could be obtained through state, but city is unsure it could find remaining money; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ACCORDING to city historians, bridges have been a source of controversy in Bridgeport since it became a borough in 1800, when it was named for its bridges over the Pequonnock River and its port on Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>''A lot of mayors have run on bridges: whether to reopen them or fix them,'' said Mary K. Witkowski, the director of historical collections for the Bridgeport Public Library and author of the book ''Bridgeport on the Sound'' (Arcadia Publications, 2001). ''And the Congress Street Bridge was one of the ones that really seemed to have the most trouble over the years. It was closed many times for repairs, especially during Jasper McLevy's time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ACCORDING to city historians, bridges have been a source of controversy in Bridgeport since it became a borough in 1800, when it was named for its bridges over the Pequonnock River and its port on Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>''A lot of mayors have run on bridges: whether to reopen them or fix them,'' said Mary K. Witkowski, the director of historical collections for the Bridgeport Public Library and author of the book ''Bridgeport on the Sound'' (Arcadia Publications, 2001). ''And the Congress Street Bridge was one of the ones that really seemed to have the most trouble over the years. It was closed many times for repairs, especially during Jasper McLevy's time.''</p>
        <p>Now more than 40 years after Mayor McLevy's tenure, the Congress Street Bridge is the center of attention again. Along with the Pleasure Beach Bridge, it is one of two bridges in the eastern part of the city that have been closed for years and must now be replaced at a projected total cost of $50 million.</p>
        <p>Part of the $30 million price tag for the Congress Street Bridge could be obtained through the state's Local Bridge Program. But because of budget problems, the city is not sure if it can find the remaining money.</p>
        <p>''The city has to consider, three years down the line or later, when it comes time to pay for the bridge, whether we will have the funds available,'' said Joe P. Gresko, the municipal government's spokesman.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Congress Street Bridge, many residents of the predominantly Hispanic East Side are feeling angered, alienated and frustrated. ''Because of the closing of the bridge, the whole East Side of Bridgeport has gone down the drain,'' said Millie Maldonado, the president of Bridgeport's Spanish Merchants Association. ''It has just deteriorated tremendously.''</p>
        <p>The drawbridge, which was built in 1919 and is on the Connecticut Historical Commission's list of bridges, connects the East Side of Bridgeport with downtown. The crossing, the fourth bridge at the site, has been left in the open position since 1997, when the state Department of Transportation determined that its substructures were moving.</p>
        <p>Many residents and business owners said they believed that the inoperative bridge had increased response times for emergency vehicles.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gresko said the East Side was served by a fire station and police station house. ''We use the Stratford Avenue Bridge and the East Washington Bridge, which are just blocks away from Congress Street -- maybe adding about one minute worth of response time to a fire that would potentially be happening on the East Side that the main firehouse would be responding to,'' Mr. Gresko said.</p>
        <p>Residents and merchants near Congress Street also said the economy of the East Side and downtown had suffered.</p>
        <p>Victor Soukarieh, who has owned the Casa Grande Supermarket (about a half-mile east of the bridge) for the last three years, said business at the store had dropped by 60 percent. ''I'm feeling like I'm on an island,'' he said. ''This area has been dead.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence Fernandes, who, along with his brother, Sam, owns Larry and Sam's Seafood at the eastern base of the bridge, said he was close to laying off employees.</p>
        <p>''As soon as they closed the bridge down, we lost about half of our clientele,'' he said. ''We've been working hard to get it back through advertising, but the best advertising is the traffic.''</p>
        <p>Karen Lee Pulver, who lives in nearby Harborview Towers, is concerned because the elderly people in the building can no longer walk downtown.</p>
        <p>''If the businesses start to leave because of the inconvenience, then this will become a ghost town,'' she said. ''I feel like we're being cut off.'' But not everyone is convinced that replacing the Congress Street Bridge is the right option. Councilman John D. Guman, a Democrat and co-chairman of the budget committee, who, along with the rest of the City Council, is studying the problem, insists he needs more information.</p>
        <p>''Do we spend $30 million to fix this bridge?'' asked Mr. Guman, ''Or can the $30 million be better spent somewhere else, and can there be a better solution?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guman said the same financial questions surround the Pleasure Beach Bridge, which joins the city's East End with Pleasure Beach. However, he feels that unless action is taken, Pleasure Beach could turn into a permanent wildlife sanctuary.</p>
        <p>''Again, to fix the bridge, you're talking millions of dollars,'' he said. ''But unless you fix the bridge, or come up with another solution, now you've got a prime piece of real estate that's going to the birds.''</p>
        <p>The Pleasure Beach Bridge, a wooden plank structure built in 1920 now in the Historic American Engineering Record, has been in the open position in the middle of the Lewis Gut channel since fire damaged its southern end in 1996.</p>
        <p>City council member James Holloway, a Democrat from the East End, said Pleasure Beach is important to his constituents.</p>
        <p>''Pleasure Beach is probably the only open-air space we have in the East End,'' he said. ''It's used for picnics, outings, weddings, for the kids to go out there and fish. And right now the kids in the East End can't go.''</p>
        <p>The state has agreed to offer the city a grant of $5.8 million and a loan of $8.8 million through its Local Bridge Program for the Congress Street Bridge, but said that it does not see a benefit in replacing the Pleasure Beach Bridge because no one lives at Pleasure Beach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gresko said the city would be ''considering pursuing the application'' for the Local Bridge Program money, and he hopes that a courthouse for juveniles that the state is planning to build on the west side of the Congress Street Bridge might lead to additional state funds.</p>
        <p>''The Congress Street Bridge is the priority of the city, because of the link that it creates with the downtown and the East Side,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The Pleasure Beach Bridge is still important, but obviously it's linking the East End with vacant land. So, we're going to treat the bridge that has more impact on people first.''</p>
        <p>According to the city's official historian, Charles W. Brilvitch, keeping the Congress Street Bridge out of service means the city has reneged on a promise it made when it bought the bridge from the late P. T. Barnum and annexed the highly industrialized East Bridgeport for its tax base.</p>
        <p>''We've gone against what the City of Bridgeport promised the residents of East Bridgeport in 1864: this bridge will be open and forever remain free and open to the public,'' Mr. Brilvitch said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
