<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Test All Hospital Patients for AIDS, New Jersey Doctors Urge</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MEDICAL SOCIETY OF NEW JERSEY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERR, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF1F39F932A35756C0A967958260" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Test All Hospital Patients for AIDS, New Jersey Doctors Urge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER KERR,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KERR, PETER</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY, April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Medical Society of New Jersey today called for testing all hospital patients for the AIDS virus. Homosexual rights groups were angered by the move and said it was the first such proposal by a medical society in the nation.</p>
        <p>As a result of a vote by more than 200 doctors representing the state's county medical societies, the state society, will urge hospitals around the state to test every patient they admit for the HIV virus as a part of standard practice, said the society's president, Dr. Joseph A. Riggs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Medical Society of New Jersey today called for testing all hospital patients for the AIDS virus. Homosexual rights groups were angered by the move and said it was the first such proposal by a medical society in the nation.</p>
        <p>As a result of a vote by more than 200 doctors representing the state's county medical societies, the state society, will urge hospitals around the state to test every patient they admit for the HIV virus as a part of standard practice, said the society's president, Dr. Joseph A. Riggs.</p>
        <p>The society may also ask the State Legislature to make mandatory HIV testing a matter of law, he said.</p>
        <p>The resolution also called for regular testing of all health-care professionals in the state, including doctors.</p>
        <p>The vote comes one week after a Superior Court judge in New Jersey ruled that patients have a right to know if their doctors have AIDS. The decision last week drew criticism from many health professionals who said that if there was mandatory testing for doctors, mandatory testing for patients would not be far behind.</p>
        <p>But doctors said that their resolution was not prompted by any specific incident and that the subject had been debated at previous annual meetings.</p>
        <p>Dr. Riggs said the society was moved to support universal testing of hospital patients by the increasing number of HIV-infected patients appearing at hospitals in New Jersey, one of the states hardest hit by the AIDS epidemic.</p>
        <p>And physicians attending the conference here said there was growing anxiety among health-care workers about the accidental transmission of the disease during medical procedures.</p>
        <p>A national survey of 26 hospitals by the Federal Centers for Disease Control last year found the highest rate of AIDS infection in Newark, where 7.8 percent of patients tested at the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey were found to be infected. The rate for all 26 hospitals was 1.3 percent. As a result of that study, Federal officials recommended that hospitals in areas with large numbers of AIDS cases routinely offer testing to all patients.</p>
        <p>Physicians at the conference here said there was growing anxiety among health-care workers about the accidental transmission of the disease during medical procedures.</p>
        <p>"I just think it is going to show hospital staff and the people that we are serious about this disease," Dr. Riggs said in an interview after the vote was taken. "We have got to put a handle on this disease."</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for homosexual rights groups concerned with the AIDS epidemic said such a policy would institutionalize discrimination against people infected with the virus. The vote, they said, also exaggerated the danger of the disease being contracted during medical procedures.</p>
        <p>"It is an invitation to segregate out a group of patients and expose them to discrimination and inferior treatment," said Evan Wolfson, a staff attorney with the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund in New York City. "There is no reason to test patients. There is no reason to test doctors."</p>
        <p>Currently doctors must specifically ask patients for permission to give the test for the HIV virus, which causes AIDS. If the recommendation of the society is adopted by hospitals, the blanket medical consent forms that patients sign on entering a hospital would include permission for a test for the HIV virus, and the resolution calls on hospitals to test every patient. Each hospital would decide how to respond if a patient refused to sign the form.</p>
        <p>A stronger proposal, to make such tests mandatory, was taken out of the society's resolution before it was voted upon.  2 Years' Discussion</p>
        <p>The resolution approved by the society also provides that the HIV test results would be treated "with the utmost confidentiality," but Dr. Riggs said the information would be shared among members of the hospital staff, and procedures protecting the patients' privacy would still have to be worked out.</p>
        <p>Dr. Riggs said the resolution had been discussed by the society for two years and had no relation to the recent court decision.</p>
        <p>The HIV virus can be transmitted through sexual contact or when the blood or other fluids from an infected person pass into the bloodstream of another person through a shared needle or through a cut or an opening in the skin. Practical Issues</p>
        <p>Since the outbreak of the epidemic, doctors and other health workers have been advised to treat all patients as if they could transmit the disease, taking special care during procedures where they come into contact with the patient's blood, such as during surgery or childbirth.</p>
        <p>But one of the doctors who voted for today's resolution, Richard H. McShane, a plastic surgeon from Glen Ridge, said it was unrealistic to expect all doctors to take extreme precautions with all patients. The determination of which patients are infected with the virus, he said, will aid physicians in giving care and help patients as well.</p>
        <p>"As surgeons, most of us wind up sticking ourselves with a needle from time to time," Dr. McShane said. "The universal precautions are just impractical. It is necessary to find out where the disease is in the hospital so the hospital personnel can protect other patients and themselves.</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for the homosexual rights groups said they believed the policy would be both illegal and harmful to efforts to contain the epidemic.</p>
        <p>David Hansell, the deputy executive director for policy of the Gay Men's Health Crisis, said such a policy could actually increase the danger of infection to doctors and others because tests for the infection usually appear negative during the first six months after a person is infected. Negative past test results can be deceptive, he said, and should not be depended upon.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, people who are infected with the virus already experience difficulty in obtaining medical and dental care. Such a policy would only segregate HIV-positive patients and make it far harder for them to gain adequate treatment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson, of the Lambda Legal Defense Fund, said there were only a handful of cases where patients have infected their physicians or where health workers have infected patients. "This is a potentially disastrous blow to the public health and the public health care delivery system," Mr. Wilson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
