<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 4 Years, Intifada Still Smolders</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="492718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB173EF93AA35751C1A967958260" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 4 Years, Intifada Still Smolders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
      <dateline>JENIN, Israeli-Occupied West Bank, Dec. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like clockwork, shutters rattled down on the shops at 1 P.M., as they do just about every day along Jenin's gray streets.</p>
        <p>Palestinian youths threw stones at patrolling Israeli soldiers, as they do just about every day, and soldiers chased the youngsters down alleyways, as they do just about every day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like clockwork, shutters rattled down on the shops at 1 P.M., as they do just about every day along Jenin's gray streets.</p>
        <p>Palestinian youths threw stones at patrolling Israeli soldiers, as they do just about every day, and soldiers chased the youngsters down alleyways, as they do just about every day.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the pattern snaps.</p>
        <p>There was an unusual event this morning, for instance. Dozens of university students tried to march through this town of 30,000 on the southern edge of the Jezreel Valley, only to be dispersed by tear gas. It was a bit of break from normal, residents said. But then the crowd melted and the air cleared. In the end, it was the same as just about every day.</p>
        <p>"The intifada has become a way of living for people," the owner of a food shop said. "Daily life revolves around the intifada."  Revolt at a Crossroads</p>
        <p>Even in Jenin, where anti-Israeli sentiments burn fierce, the Palestinian uprising known in Arabic as the intifada ended its fourth full year today on a low key -- a familiar face that no longer causes heads to turn the way it once did.</p>
        <p>Here as elsewhere in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, the revolt stands wearily at a crossroads. Its leaders, well aware that it is long past the point of being able to propel thousands of anti-Israel protesters into the streets, acknowledge that they are looking to reshape it in the hope of reviving its mass appeal.</p>
        <p>Faisal al-Husseini, the Palestinian leader in East Jerusalem, says that he would like the youngsters' endless, and pointless, stone-throwing to stop, because he says it scares away older Palestinians who might otherwise take to the streets. It is also time, Mr. Husseini adds, to find an alternative to the rigid regimen of commercial strikes that forces stores to shut from 1 P.M. each day, and throughout the day several times a month.</p>
        <p>That does not begin to deal with the problem of instant strikes called on the spur of the moment by one radical group or another, a phenomenon that has become routine since the Middle East peace talks got under way in Madrid in late October.</p>
        <p>"These sudden strikes are not acceptable, and the people have said so," said Samir Huleileh, an economist in the West Bank town of Ramallah. "It's not so much that people are tired of the strikes, although many are. But they should be regulated." One or two a month would be enough to flex muscles adequately, he argued; it is not necessary to have the repeated onslaughts that closed shops in Jenin for eight days in November.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the uprising resembles a dull toothache, throbbing and causing frequent pain, but not serious enough to change the course of one's life.</p>
        <p>Stones are thrown, tires are burned, gasoline bombs are hurled at patrolling soldiers. Dutifully, Israeli and Palestinian newspapers record this shooting death in Nablus or that punitive house demolition in Gaza by the Israeli Army.</p>
        <p>But the number of such incidents is about half what it was a year ago, before the start of the Persian Gulf war and the Palestinians' disastrous support of President Saddam Hussein of Iraq. And even though most Israelis are still so afraid of possible violence that they never set foot in the territories, the committed settlers among them have not been deterred. Since the uprising began on Dec. 9, 1987, their population in the West Bank and Gaza Strip has about doubled.</p>
        <p>Still, the revolt remains a force to be reckoned with because, like a toothache, it makes the body politic jump now and again. It did so last week when a Jewish settler was shot to death while driving through El Bireh, an Arab town next to Ramallah, six miles north of Jerusalem. Both towns have been under an army-enforced curfew ever since.</p>
        <p>B'Tselem, an Israeli human-rights group, condemned the curfew today as unfair mass punishment. It charged in a report that the army continued to violate Palestinian rights with methods like curfews, house-demolitions and detentions without trial, although it also said that the overall number of such cases had declined since 1989.  Army Denies Abuses</p>
        <p>The army quickly issued a rebuttal, denying human-rights violations and defending practices like curfews as "used only in exceptional cases, when it is absolutely necessary, and there is no other way to insure the public peace and security needs."</p>
        <p>As evidence that the uprising does not die, the casualty count continues to rise relentlessly. B'Tselem, whose figures tend to be reliable, has recorded more than 1,400 deaths to date.</p>
        <p>But the source of danger has shifted, raising laments among Palestinians themselves that their uprising is cannibalizing itself.</p>
        <p>Over the last two years, the Israelis have imposed stricter rules of engagement on their soldiers. Now, a Palestinian stands a much greater chance of being killed by a fellow Arab than by a Israeli bullet. In November, 13 people were reported killed in the occupied territories, and only 4 of them died at the hands of soldiers.</p>
        <p>B'Tselem charges that soldiers disguised as Arabs are increasingly responsible for killing Palestinians, although the army denies that it has organized "hit squads" to murder captured suspects. For their part, Palestinians almost always describe internecine slayings as executions of collaborators with Israeli occupiers. But Mr. Husseini acknowledges that the word "collaborator" is used sometimes to cover up murder by feuding families and criminal bands.</p>
        <p>Maj. Gen. Danny Yatom, who commands troops in central Israel, including the West Bank, cautions that even while the intifada has faded, there has been a leap in Palestinian use of firearms, against Israeli civilians as well as soldiers. If the peace process stumbles, or is seen by Palestinians as producing few gains, the uprising could easily be reignited, he warns.</p>
        <p>In Jenin, the Israeli commander gets no disagreement on this score.</p>
        <p>"If the negotiations are deadlocked, there will be an escalation of the intifada throughout the region," a businessman said. "The intifada can stop only when we have independence."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
