<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Even 'Smart Weapons' Need a Human Touch</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="400403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NOVA (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KILLING MACHINES (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D61F3BF930A25752C1A966958260" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Even 'Smart Weapons' Need a Human Touch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Killing Machines," tonight's report on "Nova," targets some of the weapons that American troops in the Middle East will rely on if they are ordered into battle. Known in the trade as "smart weapons," they use electronic sensors and computer brains to do the job of destruction faster and more accurately than conventional guns and bombs. Most have never been tried on the battlefield.</p>
        <p>The hour, at 8 on Channels 13 and 49, is filled with tests and simulations, accompanied by explanations of how the new weapons have revolutionized military tactics and warnings that they will not take the blood out of war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Killing Machines," tonight's report on "Nova," targets some of the weapons that American troops in the Middle East will rely on if they are ordered into battle. Known in the trade as "smart weapons," they use electronic sensors and computer brains to do the job of destruction faster and more accurately than conventional guns and bombs. Most have never been tried on the battlefield.</p>
        <p>The hour, at 8 on Channels 13 and 49, is filled with tests and simulations, accompanied by explanations of how the new weapons have revolutionized military tactics and warnings that they will not take the blood out of war.</p>
        <p>Viewers see the first successful test of the Amraam missile, which is supposed to be able to shoot down four enemy planes simultaneously, with little risk to the American pilot, since he never gets within glimpsing distance of his prey. Unfortunately, in the test before the one that the Air Force permitted to be shown, the Amraam missed all four targets. The question is, will it do its job as well in battle as it does in the new test?</p>
        <p>The Apache helicopter seen in action here would also be an important element in what the narrator calls "the few against many strategy." An Army colonel promises that with 18 Apaches, which use computer-driven weapons while flying at 200 miles an hour at treetop level, he could destroy an enemy regiment of 150 tanks. That, too, remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jasper Lupo, who actually has the title of director of smart weapons in the Defense Department, tells of work on a robotic killer that goes out hunting on its own, fires only if a target is found and then returns. He says such devices, which may be available in this decade, could be particularly useful against a training site for terrorists.</p>
        <p>One big problem with all the spinoffs from science fiction is that they require an army of technicians to keep them operating. Another is that they are so easy to come by these days from arms merchants, whose sales pitches are relayed here. Many of the Stinger missiles that helped the Mujahedeen in Afghanistan to fight off the Russians wound up in Iran. Given the assistance that Iraq received from the West during its war with Iran, the Iraqis too may have some surprises up their burnooses. So in any war, our smart missiles could be confronted by their smart missiles.</p>
        <p>Still another problem is that even at its best, a smart weapon cannot tell its operator whether the blip or dark mass or hot spot it homes in on is in fact an enemy plane or ship. A retired admiral warns that the information that has to be fed into the new weapons is not always as dependable in the rush of action as it is during testing. Yet a decision has to be made fast, before the supposed enemy can make use of</p>
        <p>its</p>
        <p>long-distance missiles. The program recounts the events of July 3, 1988, that led the captain of the missile cruiser Vincennes to order the shooting down of what turned out to be an Iranian passenger jet carrying 269 people.</p>
        <p>Gen. John R. Galvin, the NATO commander, warns that "the hand of man better be in the battle, or else things could go terribly wrong." But the program leaves the message that no man can always be smart enough to control the smart weapons at his fingertips.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
