<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>YACHT RACING: Sailing on Troubled Waters; First U.S. All-Female Crew Is Challenged by a High-Tech Boat and a Low Budget</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAILBOATS AND SAILING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITBREAD ROUND THE WORLD RACE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLOYD, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANK, NANCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D61E31F936A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="1434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>YACHT RACING: Sailing on Troubled Waters; First U.S. All-Female Crew Is Challenged by a High-Tech Boat and a Low Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LLOYD, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>KEY WEST, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Above the brick wall at Higgs Beach stands a chain-link fence. Behind it, a scraggly tropical garden grows as if in defiance of time. Nance Frank, dressed in a bright blue city dress and high heels, scaled a crumbling embankment. She had a meeting at 10 o'clock with a city commissioner, but she made time for a visit to the place where she played as a child.</p>
        <p>Through the fence, she peered at Spanish almond and sandbox trees, and at the effusive royal poinciana, her favorite blossom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Above the brick wall at Higgs Beach stands a chain-link fence. Behind it, a scraggly tropical garden grows as if in defiance of time. Nance Frank, dressed in a bright blue city dress and high heels, scaled a crumbling embankment. She had a meeting at 10 o'clock with a city commissioner, but she made time for a visit to the place where she played as a child.</p>
        <p>Through the fence, she peered at Spanish almond and sandbox trees, and at the effusive royal poinciana, her favorite blossom.</p>
        <p>"I fell out of my first tree in there," Frank said wistfully. "And over there, we used to eat the almonds. The garden was always a great mystery to me."  A Troika of Problems</p>
        <p>Frank, who is 44 now, learned to sail and swim on these shores. It is all very tranquil, far from the responsibilities of the boat, people and money problems that fill her life these days.</p>
        <p>Since announcing more than five years ago that she was going to skipper the first United States women's team in the Whitbread Round the World Race, Nance Frank has followed a rugged trail of high hopes and broken dreams.</p>
        <p>"I used to think about the adventurous life the shrimpers had," she said, gazing past the White Street Fishing Pier. "If I hadn't grown up on this beach, I wouldn't be doing what I'm doing now."</p>
        <p>On Sept. 25, Frank and her crew of 11 women plan to set sail from Southampton, England, in the Whitbread competition. A shortage of cash could mean that Frank's team, the United States Women's Challenge, is able to sail only the first leg of the six-stage race, or not start at all. But Frank is approaching the project as if she's going the full race against 15 male teams from 9 countries.  An 'Obsession and Obligation'</p>
        <p>The nine-month, 32,000-mile voyage has no place for timidity. Raging seas, maddening calms, submerged icebergs, gear breakdowns, crew injuries -- and even death -- haunt the crews like nightmares in waiting.</p>
        <p>Why then does Frank, a former educator who has taught comparative government and ancient history in Chile, want to subject herself to this?</p>
        <p>It is an "obsession and obligation," she said in a recent interview during a fund-raising visit here. "It's a really great race, a fascinating race. Having the opportunity to lead women in a space-age vehicle is a great honor. It really is like being Amelia Earhart and trying to break ground."</p>
        <p>Despite the noble purpose, there are also nagging questions about safety, credibility, and money. As the departure day draws near, the boat is still far short of the $3.4 million Frank said she needs to "comfortably" finish the race.</p>
        <p>The lean budget -- she says she has raised about $1.8 million so far -- has caused schisms within her group. "Because of a lack of funds, someone's going to get hurt big-time," said Debbie Dempsey, a 43-year-old sailor from Kilmarnock, Va., who has tentative plans to sail in part of the voyage despite her misgivings. "If she can qualify for the Whitbread, then she has the bare minimum. But as for having spare sails, halyards and a spare mast, she doesn't have the backups."</p>
        <p>Dempsey, a merchant marine captain with an unlimited tonnage license, is credited with averting disaster last January off the North Carolina coast by preventing a 634-foot freighter from going aground. She had planned to sail in the Whitbread race four years ago, in Frank's first attempt at a United States Women's Challenge. But when late sponsorship failed to materialize, the 1989-90 Whitbread team could not pay the additional $140,000 it needed to use its 64-foot boat. The women sailed out to the start anyway, a symbolic gesture that left the crew awash in tears.</p>
        <p>A former boat delivery skipper who has claimed at various times to have sailed anywhere from 50,000 to 100,000 miles, Frank pressed onward for a 1993-94 Whitbread challenge. Of the original 11-woman crew, only Dempsey is with her for 1993.</p>
        <p>Frank says that the others' lives took different directions. Dempsey says there's more to it. "We've stood by Nance for several years here," Dempsey said of the few other backers who stayed on. "But you don't see many of the 1989-90 people remaining. Obviously, here comes another deadline, and we're not there yet."</p>
        <p>Dempsey says that in Frank's fund-raising efforts, "She often lacks credibility."</p>
        <p>Jay and Elizabeth Kreitler, who befriended Frank when she decided to use Annapolis, Md., as her base five years ago, have resigned from the project. Jay Kreitler was the group's accountant; Elizabeth was on the crew. Jay Kreitler said he left last June over Frank's evasiveness about finances.</p>
        <p>The group's new boat is one of seven new Whitbread 60's designed by Bruce Farr of Annapolis. Frank says that she bought the boat, but is bound by a nondisclosure agreement from revealing how much it cost.</p>
        <p>Ross Field, skipper for the new Yamaha boat, said from England last week that Frank didn't buy the $1.35 million boat: She leased it with rights to purchase it.</p>
        <p>Still severely strapped for money, Frank left her team in Southampton earlier this month to look for more financial support at home. Frank's trip to Key West included a visit to the city's mayor emeritus, Wilhemina Harvey, an old family friend who is a county commissioner and, at age 81, the city's pre-eminent politician. Harvey paved the way for a $200,000 payment to the United States Women's Challenge from the city's tourist-bed-tax receipts.</p>
        <p>By befriending officials in the Florida Keys this summer, Frank upstaged the city of Annapolis, which had given the United States Women's Challenge free dock space for years. Annapolis officials were miffed, particularly when Frank organized a commissioning of the boat in Key West. A subsequent christening in Annapolis took place without the boat; the yacht was stalled on the way up from Key West with a rigging problem.</p>
        <p>Then, when the United States Women's Challenge left New York City for Southampton July 3 in the Gold Cup Trans-Atlantic Race, on the boat's transom, in bold letters, was: "Florida Keys &amp; Key West."</p>
        <p>Frank says she doesn't know why Annapolis is sniveling. "We have done millions of dollars worth of top-notch press for Maryland," she said.</p>
        <p>In the end, all the money problems come down to the basics: Frank is unable to pay her crew -- they're doing it for the experience -- or to buy spare equipment. The team lost an $8,000 spinnaker pole overboard on the way to England,and blew out five sails. The team has an inventory of 12 sails; other Whitbread teams have 40 or more.</p>
        <p>Despite the shortfalls, Field says the team is competitive. The yacht had been sailed about 12,000 miles before being leased to Frank.</p>
        <p>Since taking over the boat, the women have gone aground at least twice, apparently with minor impact.</p>
        <p>Barbara Span, the yacht's sail trimmer, said from England that she is thrilled with the boat. "It's really wild," she said. "The Whitbread 60's are just so fast and so light. On other boats, it's a thrill to get to 12 knots. On these boats, by the time it gets to 20 knots, it's really fun."</p>
        <p>Not everyone shares her enthusiasm. Amanda Swan, a crew member from Maiden, the British group that in 1989-90 became the first women's team to sail a Whitbread race, joined Frank's crew for the transatlantic competition in July. She left the boat afterwards.</p>
        <p>Swan said from New Zealand that the Whitbread 60's, a new class this year, are more complicated than previous boats of its size. "The new 60-footers are so much lighter, faster and more technologically advanced," she said. "Maiden had an international crew, but it was sailing we had to do, not figuring out about water ballast systems and asymmetrical sails." An Unforgiving Boat</p>
        <p>Swan's concern is that Frank's crew, which has fewer than 6,000 miles in training on the new boat, lacks enough pre-race experience. So far, only one woman, Mikaela Von Koskull of Finland, has sailed in the Whitbread before. "Anyone, given the right crew, should come through as long as they don't push it until something breaks," said the 28-year-old Swan. "But there is no forgiving in a 60-footer, and you can't win that race if you play it safe. You have to take risks, but you still have to be in control of those risks."</p>
        <p>Field, who has sailed in three Whitbread races, disagrees. "Of course, they could use a lot more time on it," he said. "They are hard boats to sail. But they have some good women on board. I'm sure as the race progresses, they'll get better. The race around the world is going to be very close. I think the girls will be competitive if they sail it right, and have a few lucky breaks."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
