<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elizabeth Worley, Teymour Farman-Farmaian</title>
    <meta content="24VOWS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/24/fashion/24VOWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1378339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WORLEY, DR. ELIZABETH MAI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARMAIAN, TEYMOUR FARMAN-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worley, Elizabeth (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farman-Farmaian, Teymour</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shattuck, Kathryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Jacobi Medical Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wharton, Edith</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DB1F38F937A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elizabeth Worley, Teymour Farman-Farmaian</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Elizabeth Worley and Teymour Farman-Farmaian</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vows column on wedding of Elizabeth Worley and Teymour Farman-Farmaian; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE part glamour girl, one part adventurer, one part children's advocate, Dr. Elizabeth Mai Worley is the sort of high-spirited woman Edith Wharton wrote about. Like Wharton's heroines, Dr. Worley's dance card was full, with men whose romantic fumblings often resembled a full-court press.</p>
        <p>And then Teymour Farman-Farmaian came to her with a simple request: ''Let me court you,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One part glamour girl, one part adventurer, one part children's advocate, Dr. Elizabeth Mai Worley is the sort of high-spirited woman Edith Wharton wrote about.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE part glamour girl, one part adventurer, one part children's advocate, Dr. Elizabeth Mai Worley is the sort of high-spirited woman Edith Wharton wrote about. Like Wharton's heroines, Dr. Worley's dance card was full, with men whose romantic fumblings often resembled a full-court press.</p>
        <p>And then Teymour Farman-Farmaian came to her with a simple request: ''Let me court you,'' he said.</p>
        <p>She stopped in her tracks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Worley, a pediatrician at Jacobi Medical Center in the Bronx, first met him four years ago at a dinner in an Indian restaurant given by mutual friends. ''Handsome but otherwise involved'' was her impression; he was married at the time. Soon her social path and that of Mr. Farman-Farmaian, a computer software consultant in Manhattan, began colliding, sparking friendship but not romance.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1999, Dr. Worley became a volunteer pediatrician in Kosovo, where at night she wrote e-mail missives to friends, including Mr. Farman-Farmaian, who was divorcing. ''Lucky will be the man who wins you,'' came his reply.</p>
        <p>She remembered thinking, ''Oh, my gosh, not the comment I expected from him.''</p>
        <p>At the end of the summer of 2000, after working on the Mosquito Coast of Honduras, she returned to Manhattan. Mr. Farman-Farmaian, who gushes about rhymed verse the way some men get worked up over the Yankees, mustered the nerve to ask her out to dinner. But for the hard-working Dr. Worley, whose closet contains both a pickax and a tiara, the calendar was full. January brought another invitation, and an acceptance. But their dinner together was by both accounts a disaster. Dr. Worley explained, ''I couldn't figure out if he was looking for a dinner partner or a date.''</p>
        <p>The relationship took another turn when he suggested that Dr. Worley come play with his nieces at a ''small'' family gathering. Forty guests arrived. (His grandfather, a Persian prince, had eight wives; Mr. Farman-Farmaian has 150 first cousins.) Charmed, Dr. Worley rethought the situation.</p>
        <p>One evening he looked into Dr. Worley's eyes and cautiously dangled his old-fashioned offer of courtship. For eight weeks they delighted in each other's company without so much as a kiss. Finally, last March, at her family's beach house near Charleston, S.C., their lips touched for the first time. ''What will I tell our grandchildren?'' Mr. Farman-Farmaian asked the next morning.</p>
        <p>They returned to New York that night, where he wrote in his journal, ''I have found the woman I am going to marry,'' and then asked Dr. Worley to dinner. She declined, requesting ''a little breather.'' And so she breathed for one fitful night -- the last they willfully spent apart.</p>
        <p>Last summer, they whirled through Syria, Ethiopia and Kenya with Dr. Worley awaiting a proposal that never came. Instead, on Aug. 29, Mr. Farman-Farmaian made a surprise appearance at Jacobi's urgent-care clinic. He dropped to one knee to the patients' shouts of ''You go, girl!''</p>
        <p>The couple's marriage came in two parts. The first, on March 15 at Sky Studios in Manhattan, was a Persian ceremony where guests lounged on pillows under a tent. Following tradition, four bridesmaids stitched together the corners of a cloth held over the couple, symbolizing the silencing of mothers-in-law. Sugar cones ground above the cloth ensured the union's sweetness.</p>
        <p>On March 16, they formalized their marriage at the Park Avenue Christian Church, as the Abyssinian Baptist Church children's choir looked on from the altar. Guests then boarded school buses for Cipriani 42nd Street, a vaulted former bank adorned with pink tulips like a prize horticulture display.</p>
        <p>Jane Penner, Ms. Worley's maid of honor, noted that it was Mr. Farman-Farmaian's thoughtful approach that finally won her friend's heart.</p>
        <p>''His slow and patient courtship got her attention in a way that whisking her off to Paris or the Venice Ball never would have,'' she said.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
