<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jayhawks And Ducks Fulfill Seedings</title>
    <meta content="24MIDW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/24/sports/ncaabasketball/24MIDW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1378507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: MIDWEST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Kansas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Oregon</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Unviersity of Kansas</org>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Oregon</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDE143BF937A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jayhawks And Ducks Fulfill Seedings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kansas and Oregon Fulfill Seedings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON, Wis., March 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Top-seeded Kansas University and second-seeded Oregon University will face off in NCAA Midwest Regional final for entree into Final Four (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When all was said and done Friday night, the cream had risen to the top in the N.C.A.A. Midwest Regional. On Sunday, the top-seeded Kansas Jayhawks, the Big 12 regular-season champions, will face the second-seeded Oregon Ducks, the Pac-10 regular-season champions, for the right to move on to the Final Four.</p>
        <p>In this regional, the tournament selection committee appears to have gotten it right. But that is not to say that advancing was an easy task for the first- and second-seeded teams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The top-seeded Jayhawks, the Big 12 champions, face the second-seeded Ducks, the Pac-10 champions, this afternoon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When all was said and done Friday night, the cream had risen to the top in the N.C.A.A. Midwest Regional. On Sunday, the top-seeded Kansas Jayhawks, the Big 12 regular-season champions, will face the second-seeded Oregon Ducks, the Pac-10 regular-season champions, for the right to move on to the Final Four.</p>
        <p>In this regional, the tournament selection committee appears to have gotten it right. But that is not to say that advancing was an easy task for the first- and second-seeded teams.</p>
        <p>Before a capacity crowd of 16,310 Friday night at the Kohl Center at the University of Wisconsin, the two teams withstood furious comebacks in their semifinal games before claiming victory.</p>
        <p>Oregon (26-8) won thanks to the the senior guard Frederick Jones, whose leaning runner in the lane with 2.8 seconds remaining broke a 70-70 tie against relentless Texas (22-12).</p>
        <p>With their victory over the sixth-seeded Longhorns, the Ducks went to a regional final for the first time since 1960.</p>
        <p>Texas had a terrific opportunity to send the game into overtime on the freshman guard T. J. Ford's drive as time expired in regulation. But his short runner bounced off the back of the rim to seal Oregon's 72-70 victory.</p>
        <p>In the second game, an open baseline jumper by Illinois's star guard, Frank Williams, which could have tied the score with seconds remaining, was too strong, and the Jayhawks (32-3) held on to win, 73-69. Illinois, seeded No. 4 in the Midwest, finished the season 26-9.</p>
        <p>Both winning coaches were thankful to have survived.</p>
        <p>''In the second half, they had a great run,'' Oregon Coach Ernie Kent said of the Longhorns, ''and it was just another classic battle, which we've had many of in that Pac-10 Conference. It came down to the stretch with Freddie making that huge, huge play for us.''</p>
        <p>Kansas Coach Roy Williams said, ''We controlled the game as much as you can in a game like that, but you can't control it too much because both teams are fighting for every inch.''</p>
        <p>Oregon's success was once again predicated on the stellar play of guard Luke Ridnour and his fellow sophomore Luke Jackson. They combined for 45 points. Ridnour had 20 on 8-for-15 shooting, including 4 of 9 from 3-point range. His jumper with 58 seconds left broke a 68-68 tie and set the stage for Jones's winning basket.</p>
        <p>Jackson, the game's top scorer with 25 points, shot 10 for 17. He was 2 for 6 from 3-point range and also added a season-high 8 assists.</p>
        <p>For Oregon to beat the well-rounded Jayhawks, however, will require a stronger effort from Jones. Saddled by foul trouble for much of the first half, he finished with only 4 points.</p>
        <p>''My overall game was terrible,'' he said. ''Coming down the stretch, I knew that we were going to need a big play, and I am just happy that I could be in a position to try and make a play and kind of redeem myself.''</p>
        <p>In the second game, Kansas advanced to a regional final for the first time since 1996. The victory avenged the Jayhawks' loss to Illinois in last year's Midwest semifinals. Not surprisingly, the Jayhawks advanced behind a fine performance from their 6-foot-10 junior forward Drew Gooden, who snared a game-high 13 rebounds and shared scoring honors with the freshman guard Keith Langford. Both players had 15 points. It was Langford's highest scoring game in the tournament.</p>
        <p>On a night when the Jayhawks' star guard, Kirk Hinrich, who had sprained an ankle in the first round, played a season-low 17 minutes largely because of foul trouble, their cause was furthered by the inspired play of another freshman, the 6-1 guard Aaron Miles. Miles also had a tournament-best 13 points on 5-for-11 shooting, including 11 first-half points.</p>
        <p>With both Oregon and Kansas more than willing to play at a fast pace, Sunday's final could showcase two of the country's more celebrated backcourts. That said, the outcome could also depend on which team controls the glass.</p>
        <p>Oregon will need its huge center, the 7-2, 300-pound Chris Christofferson, to neutralize Gooden and the 6-9 senior Nick Collison.</p>
        <p>In Friday's game, Collison was superb on both ends, scoring 11 points and grabbing 9 rebounds. Meanwhile, Texas outrebounded Oregon by 41-33. It was the seventh time in the past nine games that the Ducks were outrebounded.</p>
        <p>If it happens again, Kansas could book a ride to the Final Four.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: MIDWEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
