<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Staff Shake-Up Signals Big Push by Dole</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: THE STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES) ROBERTDOLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2D81139F934A15756C0A960958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Staff Shake-Up Signals Big Push by Dole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR;</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With evidence building that he may seriously contest President Clinton for California's huge trove of 54 electoral college votes, Senator Bob Dole plans to campaign the length of the Golden State in the coming week and, aides say, also  will shake up the top of his California campaign staff.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, according to the aides, the presumed Republican nominee will kick off his first tour of the nation's biggest state since the March 26 primary by appointing Ken Khachigian, a Los Angeles lawyer with long experience in Presidential races, to be the new day-to-day director of the California campaign effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With evidence building that he may seriously contest President Clinton for California's huge trove of 54 electoral college votes, Senator Bob Dole plans to campaign the length of the Golden State in the coming week and, aides say, also  will shake up the top of his California campaign staff.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, according to the aides, the presumed Republican nominee will kick off his first tour of the nation's biggest state since the March 26 primary by appointing Ken Khachigian, a Los Angeles lawyer with long experience in Presidential races, to be the new day-to-day director of the California campaign effort.</p>
        <p>The current director, Marty Wilson, a former state government official with  limited national campaign experience and little input or assistance from Dole headquarters up to now, will be given another, as yet undetermined assignment, the aides said.</p>
        <p>"The timing of the visit and the shake-up can be taken, frankly, as a sign that Bob Dole has suddenly gotten dead serious and focused about California," said one aide, who did not want to be identified.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khachigian, who will take command of the California campaign at a time when Mr. Dole trails President Clinton in the state by at least 20 points, and who will also advise the Dole camp on strategy in other states, declined to confirm the plan for his appointment.</p>
        <p>But he did say he had begun working with the Dole team in a "meaningful capacity" in recent weeks and expected to remain aboard to help Mr. Dole make "an all-out, multimillion-dollar run" in California.</p>
        <p>"What I can confirm," Mr. Khachigian added, "is that there's a history in California of Republicans coming from way back to win. Bob Dole can do it too because Clinton's support is thin as water. Nothing could be further from the truth than the speculation that Bob Dole, like George Bush, has given up on California and will let Bill Clinton have it for free. If you deny Clinton California, you take the Presidency from him. He's got to have it."</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Khachigian, the Dole campaign will spend at least $10 million of its $60 million in Federal campaign money in California and the Republican National Committee will throw in $3 million or so.</p>
        <p>"You can't get any more serious about California than that," said Mr. Khachigian, who worked as a strategist and speech writer in the Presidential campaigns of both Ronald Reagan and George Bush and also has directed state and  Congressional campaigns in California.</p>
        <p>Some of the National Committee's money will go into a major California television blitz, beginning in a few days, in which President Clinton's record on such issues as welfare, defense cutbacks, immigration control and law and order will be sharply attacked as part of the effort to close the 20-point gap in the polls.</p>
        <p>"Clinton's record is where you beat him and we're going after him all the way in California," said Nelson Warfield, Mr. Dole's chief campaign spokesman. "He's broken one promise after another and we're going to point that out time and time and time again. California has good reason to be looking for a new President."</p>
        <p>The Republican National Committee, as well as the California Republican Party, also will pick up as many of Mr. Dole's campaign bills as possible in coming weeks because the Dole campaign coffers were almost emptied during the primary season and will not be refilled until Federal money is handed out for the fall campaigning.</p>
        <p>The Dole campaign has long argued that the Senator could probably win the Presidency without carrying California, an assertion many political professionals agree with -- providing the Senator shows plenty of strength elsewhere in the country. But hardly anybody argues that Mr. Clinton could win re-election without California, given the way his strength varies elsewhere.</p>
        <p>By spending $10 million in California, Mr. Dole would, of course, have less to spend elsewhere, for instance in some of the critical states of the Middle West. But by forcing Mr. Clinton to defend himself in California, the Dole campaign also reduces the money available to the President to spend in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Khachigian sees the Dole campaign unfolding in California: "Of course, he'll spend a limited amount of time in downtown San Francisco and Los Angeles -- that's hardcore Democrat territory. But a heck of a lot of the rest of the state is Bob Dole country -- down the eastern side, through the Central Valley and then Orange County, cutting across to San Diego, then all the way up much of the western coastline toward San Jose and beyond. We can do this."</p>
        <p>After Mr. Bush decided he could not carry California in 1992 and abandoned plans to campaign here, not only did Mr. Clinton win the state but, in the absence of a major effort by the top Republican on the ticket, Republican candidates for Congressional and state offices found their campaigns more difficult.</p>
        <p>"It's great to know that this time around we've got a candidate who won't abandon us," said Gov. Pete Wilson, one of Senator Dole's national campaign co-chairmen. "I'm very optimistic about Bob's chances. And when he does win, he'll carry the rest of the ticket along with him, especially our legislative and Congressional candidates."</p>
        <p>According to the Governor, among the most prominent Republicans who have been urging Mr. Dole to go all-out in California has been House Speaker Newt Gingrich.</p>
        <p>"Newt's been telling Bob," Mr. Wilson said, "that if he carries California, California's big Republican Congressional delegation will remain intact -- and with it Newt's control of the House."</p>
        <p>POLITICS: THE STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
