<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7 'Dead' Bosnians Alive, But Just Who Are They?</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA &amp; HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2D81139F934A15756C0A960958260" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7 'Dead' Bosnians Alive, But Just Who Are They?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>ZVORNIK, Bosnia and Herzegovina, May 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been two weeks since American peacekeeping troops on an artillery exercise on the outskirts of town heard bursts of automatic weapons fire, then saw seven men running up to surrender to them.</p>
        <p>Since then, some of the men, who were turned over to the Serbs, have been tortured by Serbian interrogators into confessing to murder, United Nations officials say, and have become the center of the latest controversy over how wisely NATO is carrying out the peace accord.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been two weeks since American peacekeeping troops on an artillery exercise on the outskirts of town heard bursts of automatic weapons fire, then saw seven men running up to surrender to them.</p>
        <p>Since then, some of the men, who were turned over to the Serbs, have been tortured by Serbian interrogators into confessing to murder, United Nations officials say, and have become the center of the latest controversy over how wisely NATO is carrying out the peace accord.</p>
        <p>But the passing days have only deepened the mystery about who the men are and whether their stories are true or they crashed onstage as part of some conspiracy by one side or the other.</p>
        <p>Their appearance has brought back to life Muslim men whose families long thought they were victims of the Serbian massacre at Srebrenica last year. It has also given new life to previously dubious Serbian claims that the Bosnian authorities are sending armed groups into Serbian territory. What it has not done is provided a complete, satisfactory answer to who the men are.</p>
        <p>The men, who were carrying two pistols, some hand grenades and a small amount of explosives, said they were fleeing the gunfire as they tried to make it to Bosnian Government territory about four miles away. They said they had been hiding in the mountains for the last 10 months after escaping Srebrenica, about  20 miles to the southeast.</p>
        <p>But what the Americans saw made them suspicious, said Maj. Scott Keefer, the  senior officer at the scene. The men looked far too fit to have spent a Bosnian  winter in the wilderness, he said. Their clothing, though motley, was in good shape, their hair was freshly cut and some of them had shaved that morning, although no razors were found in their gear.</p>
        <p>When the men were interviewed separately, their accounts sounded too similar  to be true, the major said. "They all remembered the same details," he said. "But even two people who go through something like that remember things differently."</p>
        <p>As the major explained it, they seemed to be civilians with illegal arms, and the peace agreement required that the weapons be turned over to the local authorities -- in this case, the same authorities whom the men said they had escaped.</p>
        <p>The accord allows NATO forces to hold civilians for up to 72 hours for investigation, but the Americans released the men to Serbian police custody after about two hours.</p>
        <p>The men did not plead for sanctuary, American soldiers and United Nations police monitors present said. Almost nonchalantly, they said, the seven men, who were not handcuffed, climbed into a Serbian police van and left with only two officers. The ease of the transfer made NATO officers suspect that they were agents of the Bosnian Serbs.</p>
        <p>"If they were Srebrenica survivors, they should have been terrified, but they were O.K.," said an American officer.</p>
        <p>They were not O.K. for long. And suspicions that they were posing as Muslim marauders on Serbian territory as part of a Serbian plot faded.</p>
        <p>United Nations officers said the men had told them that the Serbian police had begun to torture them almost as soon as they had been alone with them in the police station here. The men were beaten on and off throughout the night, sometimes with metal bars, say United Nations officials who examined them. By morning, several of the men had signed confessions saying they had killed four Serbian villagers who disappeared recently.</p>
        <p>NATO officers dismissed the confessions as obviously unreliable, but a senior Bosnian Army officer who reviewed two of the confessions immediately pronounced them valid.</p>
        <p>"We didn't know what to think," a NATO officer said. "Our intelligence people tell us the Bosnian Government is running a number of operations on the Serb side. These guys could have been on a mission and ran into trouble, and so the Bosnian Army was trying to throw them to the wolves."</p>
        <p>Then, just as American officers had accepted the idea that the seven were really part of a covert Bosnian Government operation, and that the Americans had been correct in turning them over to the Serbs, the International Committee of the Red Cross determined that the men probably were really survivors of Srebrenica.</p>
        <p>United Nations officials who have been interviewing the men concur, and American military officers now say they agree.</p>
        <p>Further evidence came from the family of one of the men. When the Serbs separated men of fighting age from the women and children in Srebrenica, and expelled the women and children to Bosnian Muslim territory, many of the men fled for their lives. Muharem Hasanovic and his father escaped over the mountains.</p>
        <p>The young man's mother said, "We thought he was lost to us forever, that he had been killed in the mountains by the Serbs."</p>
        <p>But they were wrong. They received a letter via the Red Cross from Mr. Hasanovic, who with the others walked into the arms of the Americans and is now  in the Serbian jail in Bijeljina. His father remains missing.</p>
        <p>The letter asks about his family and then says, imploringly, "Write to me, the one who came back from the dead."</p>
        <p>His wife, Mevlija, said: "It is in his handwriting. We have no doubts of that."</p>
        <p>But a NATO officer said many questions remain. "What I think we know for sure is this," the officer said. "Ten months ago these men were in Srebrenica and today they are in jail, and that's about it. If someone asked me what they have  been doing in the meantime, I'd try to change the subject."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
