<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall Street; Add Aircraft to the Ailing-Asset List</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="470695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENRIQUES, DIANA B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB173EF932A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall Street; Add Aircraft to the Ailing-Asset List</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Diana B. Henriques</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HENRIQUES, DIANA B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the big lessons of the 80's is that trouble travels. Shrinking real estate values in New England can cause bank stocks to fall on Wall Street. Deteriorating junk bonds on Wall Street can send insurance companies into bankruptcy in California. Declining prices at art auctions in New York can leave Tokyo tycoons short of cash.</p>
        <p>With that lesson in mind, two analysts at Fitch Investors Service, a Wall Street credit-rating agency, have spent a good part of the summer tracking the travels of weakening commercial aircraft loans. With unsold and unleased aircraft going begging, Nancy Stroker and Valerie Gerard suspect that many of those idle planes will ultimately be written down -- or written off -- with unhappy consequences for the profitability of the companies that financed them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the big lessons of the 80's is that trouble travels. Shrinking real estate values in New England can cause bank stocks to fall on Wall Street. Deteriorating junk bonds on Wall Street can send insurance companies into bankruptcy in California. Declining prices at art auctions in New York can leave Tokyo tycoons short of cash.</p>
        <p>With that lesson in mind, two analysts at Fitch Investors Service, a Wall Street credit-rating agency, have spent a good part of the summer tracking the travels of weakening commercial aircraft loans. With unsold and unleased aircraft going begging, Nancy Stroker and Valerie Gerard suspect that many of those idle planes will ultimately be written down -- or written off -- with unhappy consequences for the profitability of the companies that financed them.</p>
        <p>Indeed, they warn, in a draft of a report to be released tomorrow, that airplane loans and leases are about to join third world debt, real estate lending and leveraged takeover loans as "hot spots in the loan portfolios of financial institutions over the next several years."</p>
        <p>Of course, direct investments in commercial aircraft have been going sour for the past 18 months, as the airline industry's health has worsened and several leading carriers have filed for bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Aircraft limited partnerships, the speculative investment pools set up to purchase airplanes and lease them out to carriers, have cut their dividends and declined sharply in value. Equipment trust certificates, which are publicly traded notes secured by specific airplanes, have also done a nosedive, and hundreds of millions of dollars worth of them have gone into default.</p>
        <p>The culprit has been an old-fashioned glut. There are too many aircraft for sale or lease at a time when air travel is down and ailing carriers are cutting back on their plane-buying plans. The partnerships that planned to pay dividends from lease income are finding their planes are unrented. Noteholders who thought they could recoup their principal by selling their airborne collateral are finding few buyers.</p>
        <p>Seeing all this, Ms. Stroker said, "we began to wonder where the pain is going to be felt next." She added, "So we decided to look at the finance companies that Fitch rates to see what we could find."</p>
        <p>What they found was that the aircraft trouble too had traveled: Commercial finance companies whose loan portfolios include significant levels of debt secured by aircraft are getting caught up in the dizzying collapse in aircraft prices.</p>
        <p>The companies, each of which has issued publicly traded debt or commercial paper that is rated by Fitch, include Chrysler Financial, Concord Leasing, Foothill Capital, General Electric Capital, Greyhound Financial, Household Finance, McDonnell Douglas Finance and Westinghouse Credit. All told, these units have issued about $45.2 billion in public debt; aircraft loans make up about $3.4 billion of their total portfolios.</p>
        <p>The analysts' first stop was at the used aircraft flea market itself, where they checked to see just how bad things are these days. Very bad, it turns out. "Recent market activity has demonstrated an alarming 50 percent increase in the number of commercial aircraft available for sale or re-lease," the Fitch report says. There were 840 planes offered for buyers or renters in June, up from 545 at the end of 1990.</p>
        <p>"Concurrently, there has also been a 50 percent decline in the number of actual completed transactions," the report continues. This suggests that the glut of commercial jet aircraft is likely to remain a fact of life for finance companies for some time to come.</p>
        <p>This trend is having the same effect on the value of finance company assets as the slump in auction prices is having on the estimated net worth of art collectors. Even conservative estimates of probable resale values now look dubious, at least for the short term, the Fitch report warned.</p>
        <p>If aircraft cannot be resold or re-leased, their owners face the same choices as any collector: to let the assets sit idle until the market recovers, to write the assets down to more realistic values or to retire the assets and not wait for a recovery.</p>
        <p>The result of each option, however, is likely to be that the companies Fitch examined will experience near-term increases in their nonperforming assets and in the related carrying costs, the analysts predicted. That, in turn, is likely to put pressure on those companies' profitability.</p>
        <p>The impact will be uneven, she said, depending on the amount of aircraft lending a company has done, and the age and condition of the various aircraft in its portfolio.</p>
        <p>The companies that are expected to feel the most impact going forward, the Fitch report says, are Chrysler Financial, a unit of Chrysler; Concord Leasing, a subsidiary of the Hongkong and Shanghai Banking Corporation; General Electric Credit, the appliance maker's financial arm; McDonnell Douglas Finance, a unit of the aircraft builder, and Westinghouse Credit, part of Westinghouse Financial Services. Fitch notes that "parent ownership and support" for these subsidiaries could mitigate the damage "in different degrees."</p>
        <p>Except for Concord Leasing, however, these same units are already feeling heat from two other hot spots in the financial community: commercial real estate and loans to heavily indebted companies, called "highly leveraged transaction loans." So the worsening aircraft market simply turns up the voltage a bit, according to Fitch.</p>
        <p>But the aircraft glut is not yet likely to put pressure on those companies' credit ratings, the analysts said. "Ratings are usually projected over a three-year period, and we perceive this glut to be a short-term problem," said Ms. Stroker. "So we don't see a likelihood of any immediate rating changes. But we wanted to warn investors who have a shorter-term horizon that they may be incurring some short-term profitability risks."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
