<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schroder Acts To Explore Compensating Slave Workers</title>
    <meta content="Y20SLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Other Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Class-Action Suits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schroeder, Gerhard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slavery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EED6173DF933A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schroder Acts To Explore Compensating Slave Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Oct. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Germany's Chancellor-elect Gerhard Schroeder, in sign that new Government may be willing to set up fund to compensate those forced into slave labor under Nazis, will meet with top industrial executives to discuss options for resolving growing number of lawsuits; meeting comes at time when German industrial companies are increasingly worried about spate of new class-action suits brought by American lawyers on behalf of former factory workers during World War II (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a sign that Germany's new Government may be willing to set up a fund to compensate people forced into slave labor under Hitler, Gerhard Schroder, the Chancellor-elect, plans to meet with top industrial executives to discuss options for resolving a growing number of lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Several German companies said today that they had received invitations for a meeting on the issue with Mr. Schroder in the next several days. The companies are believed to range from auto makers like Daimler-Benz and BMW to chemical companies like Hoechst and BASF and the giant electronics company Siemens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a sign that Germany's new Government may be willing to set up a fund to compensate people forced into slave labor under Hitler, Gerhard Schroder, the Chancellor-elect, plans to meet with top industrial executives to discuss options for resolving a growing number of lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Several German companies said today that they had received invitations for a meeting on the issue with Mr. Schroder in the next several days. The companies are believed to range from auto makers like Daimler-Benz and BMW to chemical companies like Hoechst and BASF and the giant electronics company Siemens.</p>
        <p>The meeting comes at a time when German industrial companies are increasingly worried about a spate of new class-action suits brought by American lawyers on behalf of former factory workers during World War II.</p>
        <p>German companies increasingly fear that the lawsuits could cost them billions of dollars and would expose them to torrents of horrifying publicity. Some companies are also worried about boycotts of their products, particularly in the United States, if the disputes fester.</p>
        <p>Many industrial companies listed in the lawsuits admit they used forced laborers, but insist they were forced by the Nazis to do so.</p>
        <p>Several companies, including Daimler-Benz and BMW, have argued for some time that the German Government needed to take the lead in creating a fund to compensate former workers and have volunteered to contribute toward it. Volkswagen, which is also being sued, recently announced plans to set up its own $20 million fund to compensate claims by former slave workers.</p>
        <p>But Chancellor Helmut Kohl, who was defeated for re-election last month and hands power over to Mr. Schroder on Oct. 27, adamantly rejected proposals for a Government fund. Mr. Kohl said the German Government had already paid out tens of billions of dollars in various forms of compensation for the Holocaust, and did not want to pay more.</p>
        <p>But pressure has been building to work out some kind of agreement.  ''The Government needs to seriously recognize the pressure on German companies, which could find themselves abandoned in the U.S.A. as a result of the class-action suits,'' said Manfred Gentz, Daimler-Benz's chief financial officer, in an interview with the German Press Agency.</p>
        <p>Several months ago, Switzerland's biggest banks agreed to pay $1.25 billion to settle a class-action suit over unreturned money and property that belonged to Holocaust victims.  That suit was brought by the same lawyers, led by Edward Fagan in New York City, who are now suing the industrial companies.</p>
        <p>John Gilardi, a spokesman for the chemical company BASF A.G., said it had received an invitation to the meeting with Mr. Schroder. BASF, one of three companies spun off from the old I. G. Farben chemical conglomerate, contends that its portion of the old company never used slave labor but is willing to take part in the discussions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
