<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>October Fans Join Summer Fanatics on Yankee Bandwagon</title>
    <meta content="20FANS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Diego Padres</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kleinfield, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DD143DF933A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>October Fans Join Summer Fanatics on Yankee Bandwagon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kleinfield, N R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>As New York Yankees prepare for Game 3 of World series against San Diego Padres, with New York ahead two games to none, people who earlier paid scant attention to game have become caught up in interest in team that is nothing less than victory machine; fans are going to extremes to display World Series allegiance in city where sense of entitlement to baseball sovereignty is almost primal; suddenly, most important thing seems to be whether team that has already won 23 championships in 75 years will win one more; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nothing else matters. Nothing else, it seems, is permitted to matter: only the nine-inning tallies and intervening dramas of a handful of  baseball games.</p>
        <p>Face it, either you're into baseball these days or you're totally out of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nothing else matters. Nothing else, it seems, is permitted to matter: only the nine-inning tallies and intervening dramas of a handful of  baseball games.</p>
        <p>Face it, either you're into baseball these days or you're totally out of it.</p>
        <p>Over the last few weeks, and especially over the weekend when the reality of the World Series finally manifested itself on the field of Yankee Stadium, disparate strands of New York have been transformed into that idiosyncratic and much-studied taxonomic group known as the fan. Suddenly the most important thing in the world seems to be whether a team that has already won a preposterous 23 championships in 75 years will insist on one more.</p>
        <p>As the Yankees prepare for Game 3 tonight against the Padres in San Diego, with New York ahead two games to none and the scent of sweep in the air, people who all year long have paid incidental attention to batters swatting balls and pitchers throwing smoke have become caught up in mass homage to a team that is nothing less than a victory machine.</p>
        <p>It is something that baseball does, especially in New York, where a sense of entitlement to baseball sovereignty is almost primal, and especially in this magical year enlivened by the enthralling pursuit of a ghost's home run record and the voracious accumulation of victories by a Yankee team striving to be engilded as the greatest of all.</p>
        <p>People in the area have been absorbed into this deliberate, elegant,  endlessly complex pastime almost against their will, unable to resist the ceaseless murmurings about the Series and the mighty Yankees.</p>
        <p>That is how it unfolded for Marla Rodriguez, who up until now has unapologetically loathed baseball. She is 32 and works in sports media relations at Rutgers University. Football is her abiding passion, entranced as she is by its savage aggression and that ''people are always hitting each other.''</p>
        <p>''I normally hate baseball,'' she said. ''It's very boring. Nothing ever happens. It's too slow.'' Whenever someone turned a baseball game on the television, she became angry.</p>
        <p>But every day in the last few weeks, wherever she went, the banter was about the Yankees and the Series. Almost hypnotically, she has become a full-throated Yankee rooter. Now she turns the baseball games on. When she speaks about the team, she refers to it as ''we.''</p>
        <p>''I don't know what it is,'' she said, perplexed herself. ''It's exciting now. It's close to home. I'm starting to relate, wow, what it's like playing for the World Series. Until a few weeks ago, I didn't know who David Wells was. Now I know he's a big guy and he throws a mean fastball.''</p>
        <p>The voice of baseball seems to speak even louder this time around than two years ago, when the Yankees returned after a ludicrously long lapse to reclaim the world championship and when baseball was still in such disfavor from the  players strike of 1994-95. The temperate days have been spectacular baseball weather.</p>
        <p>And, in part, the consuming and comforting divertissement of baseball has been seen as something of a mercy gift. So many people are by now fully spent from hearing salacious tales of misbehavior in Washington and hyperventilating about the capricious stock market. They would rather dwell on who is batting .401 than their own 401.</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Marshall, 30, a special education teacher from Queens, who openly admitted to her ''sunshine fan'' status (she watches when the going gets good), spoke of this exorcism from daily entanglements. Not only is she tired of learning of plane crashes and the Washington soap opera, but there have been frailties closer to home. This summer, a former student of hers was charged with assaulting a man on Long Island. ''It feels good to watch baseball,'' she said. ''It's good news for a change.''</p>
        <p>For some people, side dramas have resonated, like Darryl Strawberry's somber confrontation with cancer. ''When I heard he had cancer, I could relate, because my wife had cancer of the lymph nodes, though she's in remission now,'' said Jim Williams, 24, an auto mechanic in Poughkeepsie, N.Y., who is not usually into baseball. ''That's when I started watching. The way his teammates reacted really brought me in.''</p>
        <p>By now, it seems, people have grown somewhat more accustomed to players who perpetually put on new uniforms in pursuit of Gross National Product-like salaries. It is hard not to adore a team of so much harmony and so little swagger, with frolicsome players named Boomer and El Duque. And what else are you going to watch?</p>
        <p>''This has been a good baseball season and this Yankee team has been very good,'' said the author David Halberstam, who has written about baseball. ''And it's an appealing team. It's fun watching this team.</p>
        <p>''And there's nothing else out there. You don't have very good football teams. You don't have a basketball season in place. There's a vacuum. It's bad enough that the stock market is going down without your football teams going down.''</p>
        <p>Baseball and the World Series have this consciousness-altering effect in a way that other sports do not. The Super Bowl is big, but it is a solitary game, not the elastic, emotional unfolding that the World Series is, and it is not local. There is no home team.</p>
        <p>''Baseball's older,'' said Roger Angell, the New Yorker editor who often writes about the sport. ''It has an echo, a ring to it. It's a series. It's not one game.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''One of the things about baseball is it really is continuous. There's a game today and the next day there's another game. And fans who are not fans, when they notice the game, there's a game right away to see. And when your home team wins, a lot of people who never are baseball fans, or who call themselves baseball fans but really aren't, pay attention to the game and say, 'This is great.' ''</p>
        <p>Most of the October idolators are of this distinctly different subspecies from the true fan, the highly emotive, coarse-talking enthusiast who ingests the sport on a daily basis. The true fan knows the players, knows their averages, knows who hits in the clutch and who chokes. Most of all, of course, the true fan knows much more than the manager does.</p>
        <p>But come World Series time, anybody and everybody puts on the cap and talks the talk. Anybody can give advice to Joe Torre and expect him to take it.</p>
        <p>Even Pablo Oviedo, 33, of Kings Park, N.Y. He came to the United States a few years ago from Colombia. He found out who Jackie Robinson was only when the Interboro Parkway changed its name in his honor. No matter. Though he continues to feel the World Cup is more exciting, Mr. Oviedo is on the Yankee express these days. He's talking the plays, getting his grounding. He needs Mr. Torre's phone number.</p>
        <p>Darren Clay, the manager of the Lids baseball cap store in the Poughkeepsie Galleria Mall, was deluged with business for Yankee headgear during the weekend. ''It's crazy,'' he said. ''We get people who didn't watch a ballgame all year coming in here now and they know the exact rotation of the players and the time of each game.''</p>
        <p>Jennifer Dwork, 33, lives in Manhattan and is the senior brand manager for Tic-Tac breath mints at Ferrero USA. ''I've been to two baseball games in my life and they were corporate functions, which means I didn't watch,'' she said. She doesn't have an inkling of what or who a designated hitter is. The players' names lie somewhere on the periphery of her consciousness.</p>
        <p>''Cone is a pitcher,'' Ms. Dwork said. ''There's another one they've been talking a lot about, I just can't remember the name. Then there's some guy with a K who did that bad thing on first base during the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>Details, details. She has been swept up by the mania and is watching the games, gaining an education along with enjoyment. ''The whole city is buzzing about this,'' she said. ''I have friends who have never had baseball come out of their mouth and they're talking about the players like they're household names. I guess it's baseball is all America. I used to work on a root beer and we tried to tie in baseball all the time. Baseball is everybody.''</p>
        <p>The mood of it all suits her. ''We are having entire luncheon conversations about baseball,'' she said. ''It is such a relief from the Starr report. And a lot of my friends in the financial world have been really bummed. They're more up this week.''</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, a friend of hers who is a portfolio manager shrugged off her own investment doldrums and gave a World Series party for about 50 people, Ms. Dwork included, in the rooftop common room of her Manhattan high rise. The innings, in their slow and ordered fashion, crept by. And, oh, the taut drama of it all. The Yankees led, the Padres led, the Yankees led. Ms. Dwork sort of gave up with the Yankees down 5-2. Then she was introduced to the grand slam. ''I didn't realize that games could have such high scores,'' she said. Life was good. Runs were up, what matter if stocks were down.</p>
        <p>There is no escaping, though, that the swelling ranks of Yankee fans in October is not easy on the adherents who follow the team intensely all season long. While they welcome the magnified support that arrives this time of year, they also resent that so many of the latecomers seem to get the box seats to the Series games while they are stuck on their couch at the biggest moment of all.</p>
        <p>Marisa Levine's friends worry about her mental health, her fealty to the Yankees is so complete. She is 20, a senior at Columbia University, studying psychology. She makes it to virtually every home game, settling into the harsh discomfort of the bleachers. ''I'm a bleacher creature,'' she said proudly. She checks into the Yankee Web site at least 10 times a day, seeing what's up. ''When the Yankees lose, I cry,'' she said. ''I'm not kidding.''</p>
        <p>Her room is a shrine to the Yankees. Its walls are adorned with Yankee posters. Its shelves are crammed with Yankee souvenirs. She is nourished by the numbers and exploits of one baseball team. ''You should see my credit card bills,'' she said. ''It's all Yankee tickets, Yankee food, Yankee tickets, Yankee food, maybe a Love's drugstore.''</p>
        <p>Last week, she skipped classes for three days and spent 30 hours outside Yankee Stadium in the hope of acquiring World Series tickets, but got none. She is bitter about the interlopers who will be there. ''I think it's awful,'' she said. ''I know the players, I know their wives' names, I know their kids' names. Tino's wife is Marie. Andy's wife is Laura. They have a son Josh.''</p>
        <p>She sighed. ''It takes a lot of work not to have a life,'' she said. ''It's an everyday thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
