<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 'Sunset Boulevard,' It's the End of the Road</title>
    <meta content="04SUNS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="906454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lloyd Webber, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Close, Glenn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sunset Boulevard (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DB113DF937A35751C0A961958260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 'Sunset Boulevard,' It's the End of the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sunset Boulevard, $12 million Andrew Lloyd Webber musical that won a Tony for best musical in 1995 and made musical star of Glenn Close, will close on March 22; investors will recoups 85 percent of their money; London production of the show is also closing; American road company, now in Minneapolis, will continue its tour; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A theatrical titan has toppled. ''Sunset Boulevard,'' the $12 million Andrew Lloyd Webber musical that won a Tony for best musical in 1995 and made a musical star of Glenn Close, will close on March 22 after 977 regular performances and 17 previews at the Minskoff Theater.</p>
        <p>The London production of the show is also closing, its producers announced. A Canadian production, now playing in Vancouver, British Columbia, had already announced that it would close in April. The American road company, now in Minneapolis, will continue its tour, and there are productions in Germany and Australia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A theatrical titan has toppled. ''Sunset Boulevard,'' the $12 million Andrew Lloyd Webber musical that won a Tony for best musical in 1995 and made a musical star of Glenn Close, will close on March 22 after 977 regular performances and 17 previews at the Minskoff Theater.</p>
        <p>The London production of the show is also closing, its producers announced. A Canadian production, now playing in Vancouver, British Columbia, had already announced that it would close in April. The American road company, now in Minneapolis, will continue its tour, and there are productions in Germany and Australia.</p>
        <p>Of the long-running British megamusicals that have dominated Broadway for the last decade, ''Sunset Boulevard'' is the first to fall. Its demise has a symbolic importance, suggested by Lord Lloyd Webber himself when he proclaimed last year, in reference to his new musical, ''Whistle Down the Wind,'' that the era of the big musical was over. ''Whistle,'' a $10 million production, is small only by Lord Lloyd Webber's standards, but the recent success of smaller-scale, tightly budgeted musicals like ''Bring In da Noise, Bring In da Funk,'' ''Rent'' and ''Chicago'' has lent credence to his assertion.</p>
        <p>''Sunset Boulevard'' proved to be heavily dependent on the star power of the actress playing Norma Desmond, the aging silent-film star at the center of the musical. Ms. Close, who opened the show on Broadway, delivered a highly praised performance that drew sellout audiences.</p>
        <p>After she left, in June 1995, her successors, Betty Buckley and Elaine Paige, both veterans of the London production, won respectful reviews but did not pull in audiences in the same numbers.</p>
        <p>''Sunset Boulevard'' has been struggling for months, with about a third of the theater empty. For the week of Jan. 20 to 26, the show, with weekly running costs of about $500,000, grossed $404,005, according to Variety, the entertainment weekly. The theater has a potential gross of about $830,000.</p>
        <p>''Sunset Boulevard'' has paid back about 75 percent of its investment, with one more disbursement to come, said a spokesman for the show. In the end, investors will recoup 85 percent of their money.</p>
        <p>Lord Lloyd Webber has two musicals remaining on Broadway, ''Cats'' and ''Phantom of the Opera.'' ''Cats'' opened in October 1982 and ''Phantom'' in  January 1988.</p>
        <p>The history of ''Sunset Boulevard'' is nearly as volatile as the temperament of its central character, played by Gloria Swanson in the film on which the musical is based.</p>
        <p>The show opened in London, with Patti LuPone in the starring role and apparently poised to repeat the role in New York when ''Sunset'' opened on Broadway.</p>
        <p>It was not to be. Ms. Close, after winning rave reviews for her performance in the Los Angeles production of the musical, got the nod from Lord Lloyd Webber to take over as Norma Desmond on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Lord Lloyd Webber, after buying out Ms. LuPone's Broadway contract for a reported $1 million, hired Faye Dunaway to replace Ms. Close in Los Angeles, then abruptly dismissed her, saying her voice was not up to the role. He closed down the Los Angeles show, sold the scenery to the Toronto production and moved many in the cast to the New York production.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dunaway, who described the closing of the show as ''yet another capricious act by a capricious man,'' turned around and filed a $6 million lawsuit against Lord Lloyd Webber for breach of contract. The case was settled out of court.</p>
        <p>Ms. Close remained silent throughout the turmoil, but she had plenty to say later. In April 1995, it was reported that the Really Useful Group, Lord Lloyd Webber's American production company, had provided Variety with inflated figures for the period when Ms. Close was on vacation, apparently in an attempt to minimize Ms. Close's impact on the show.</p>
        <p>In a two-page, single-spaced letter addressed to Lord Lloyd Webber, she said she was ''furious and insulted'' and that ''if I could leave 'Sunset' tomorrow, I would.''</p>
        <p>The letter continued: ''I don't think it's an exaggeration to say that my performance turned 'Sunset Boulevard' around. I made it a hit.''</p>
        <p>The London ''Sunset,'' currently starring Petula Clark, opened at the Adelphi Theater in July 1993 at a cost of $7 million. It will close on April 5.</p>
        <p>''Andrew Lloyd Webber has scripted one of the most demanding female roles ever in musical theater,'' said James Thane, the managing director of the Really Useful Theater Company, Lord Lloyd Webber's production company in Britain. ''This makes casting incredibly difficult. The public expect a certain stature of artist in this role, and to continue beyond Petula's contract would risk compromising an extraordinary series of bravura performances.''</p>
        <p>The Vancouver production closes on April 9.</p>
        <p>''Sunset Boulevard'' won seven Tony awards in 1995, two of them by default. Because it was the only musical with an original book up for consideration that year, it would obviously win in the categories of best book, by Don Black and Christopher Hampton, and best score, by Lord Lloyd Webber. Ms. Close was named best actress in a musical and George Hearn best featured actor in a musical for his performance as Max, Norma Desmond's butler. The show also won for scenery and lighting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
