<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rediscovering Glorious Past Pays Off for Some Retailers</title>
    <meta content="09SHOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/09/business/09shop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040410T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1572854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">May Department Stores Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federated Department Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Limited Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Costco</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aeropostale</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chico's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kohl's Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sears Roebuck &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DA1238F93AA35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rediscovering Glorious Past Pays Off for Some Retailers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rediscovering Glorious Past Pays Off for Some Stores</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>America's department stores have spent much of last year ripping themselves apart, reaching back into their own Gilded Age--when stores were beautiful, clothes magnificent and serve smiling--to entice shoppers; department store companies post their best combined monthly performance in more than seven years; May Co reports comparable sales for March that were 10.1 percent higher, company's best results in decade; Federated Department Stores reports strong 6.8 percent gain; aggregate retail sales in March were about 6.8 percent higher than year ago; standouts include Limited, up 15 percent, Costco, 11 percent, Aeropostale, 14.2 percent and Chico's 18.9 percent; Kohl's was down 0.9 percent, Sears, Roebuck rose only 0.1 percent, and Wal-Mart Stores came in 6 percent higher; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America's department stores have spent much of the last year and a half ripping themselves apart, reaching back into their own Gilded Age -- when the stores were beautiful, the clothes magnificent and the service smiling -- to entice fickle shoppers back through their doors. Last month, those efforts started to pay off.</p>
        <p>After struggling for a decade with disappointing sales, department store companies yesterday posted their best combined monthly performance in more than seven years. The March sales figures, compared with results one year ago for stores open at least a year, surprised even industry analysts, who credited renovations and marketing changes, along with more colorful fashions, for the upswing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>America's department stores have spent months ripping themselves apart. Last month, those efforts started to pay off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America's department stores have spent much of the last year and a half ripping themselves apart, reaching back into their own Gilded Age -- when the stores were beautiful, the clothes magnificent and the service smiling -- to entice fickle shoppers back through their doors. Last month, those efforts started to pay off.</p>
        <p>After struggling for a decade with disappointing sales, department store companies yesterday posted their best combined monthly performance in more than seven years. The March sales figures, compared with results one year ago for stores open at least a year, surprised even industry analysts, who credited renovations and marketing changes, along with more colorful fashions, for the upswing.</p>
        <p>The May Company, which owns Lord &amp; Taylor and Filene's, reported comparable sales for March that were 10.1 percent higher -- the company's best results in a decade. Federated Department Stores, which owns Macy's and Bloomingdale's, reported a strong 6.8 percent gain, and yesterday raised its earnings projections for the year. ''We're just getting traction now,'' Terry J. Lundgren, Federated's chief executive, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Over all, March was a retail success almost across the board, with aggregate retail sales, excluding drugstores, coming in about 6.8 percent higher than last March. Standouts included the Limited, up 15 percent; Costco, 11 percent; Aéropostale, 14.2 percent; and Chico's, 18.9 percent.</p>
        <p>Yet there were those that did not do well. Kohl's, the big-box bargain department store, was down 0.9 percent. Sears, Roebuck rose only 0.1 percent. Wal-Mart Stores, the country's biggest retailer, came in 6 percent higher.</p>
        <p>While the overall retail average sales gain remained higher than the department store average, it was the department store numbers that sent the statisticians to the record books.</p>
        <p>''We really started to see improvement in the department stores in the first three months of the year,'' said Michael Niemira, the chief analyst for the International Council of Shopping Centers. ''We've also seen the closing of the gap between department stores and the rest of the industry. They're really picking up.''</p>
        <p>Yet the optimism that followed yesterday's sales releases may not last, as analysts pointed out that the high numbers were basically ''easy comps,'' meaning that, compared with last year's dismal sales, it was easy for this year's numbers to look good.</p>
        <p>Todd D. Slater, an analyst with Lazard, predicted that ''the best comp numbers for the year are now behind us,'' adding that an early Easter gave a boost to March shopping and that rising gasoline prices would keep shoppers watching television instead of strolling through the mall.</p>
        <p>Other analysts were more optimistic. ''My vote is that they will stay strong,'' said Robert F. Buchanan, a retail analyst for A.G. Edwards in St. Louis who is known for his pessimistic pronouncements. ''The department stores have been revving things up. The whole pendulum is swinging from casual to dressy, and department stores are bound to win because they sell dressier clothes.''</p>
        <p>The resurgence began last year at the high end, with luxury stores like Neiman Marcus coming back stronger and faster. ''Our luxury buyer never went away,'' said Burt Tansky, the chief executive. The Neiman Marcus Group, which includes Bergdorf Goodman, was up 25.7 percent in March. Saks Fifth Avenue was also strong, with 9.5 percent growth. Nordstrom, which raised its profile in 2003, did even better, at 15.9 percent.</p>
        <p>In the wake of the luxury chains, the midlevel department stores decided they could not compete on price with mass-market discounters like Wal-Mart on standard-issue khakis and nylon tank tops. To get people to shop again in their urban and mall-based anchors, the department stores knew they had to offer something different, something perceived to have more cachet -- and that might include a distinctive shopping bag or thank you notes for a purchase.</p>
        <p>Over the last 18 months, stores like Lord &amp; Taylor, Marshall Field's and Bloomingdale's, have been gutting their stores; cleaning up their aisles, crowded with sale racks, not customers; and bringing in new midprice lines, called ''better sportswear'' in the industry, by Ralph Lauren, Calvin Klein, Tommy Hilfiger and others. They have also redesigned private label clothes -- featuring truckloads of pink for spring.</p>
        <p>Lord &amp; Taylor is a good example of what looks like a turnaround. While the May Company does not break out the numbers for its individual chains, analysts say that Lord &amp; Taylor's comparable sales, which were rocky for the last five years, started to take off this January -- when analysts estimated the chain was 5 percent ahead of the previous January -- in large part because of the drastic overhaul undertaken by its chief executive, Jane Elfers.</p>
        <p>Last year, Ms. Elfers announced she would jettison fully one-third of the Lord &amp; Taylor mall anchor stores, taking the chain entirely out of some states, including Texas and Florida. (The chain has already closed 14 stores.)</p>
        <p>Then the chief executive ordered a house-cleaning in the stores she kept, sweeping away messy racks and introducing dozens of new brands. Yesterday, the newly designed second floor in the Fifth Avenue flagship was awash with color: private-label Pucci look-alikes (for one-tenth the price) were displayed next to fresh-looking clothes from big-name designers.</p>
        <p>Only a year ago, Lord &amp; Taylor was still running advertisements that looked like supermarket ads: ''We ran 6 to 10 cuts on a page,'' Ms. Elfers said, referring to the number of photographs. ''Now we're down to one or two.''</p>
        <p>She also pared the stock. ''The customer does not want to see 25 green sweaters; reduce the choice to 3 and let them see outfits on the models and on the tables.'' The chain even improved amenities like restaurants. ''We replaced a boring tea shop with Larry Forgione's American Place,'' Ms. Elfers said of the Fifth Avenue flagship.</p>
        <p>She also upgraded the existing merchandise, adding more exotic brands. A year ago, shoppers could not find Vera Wang dresses. The chain did not sell Kate Spade bags or Diesel shoes or Nars cosmetics or Anna Sui or Betsey Johnson or Eileen Fisher. The lingerie department was ''a sea of Playtex and Maidenform and Warners,'' Ms. Elfers said, referring to the preponderance of the more mainstream suppliers. In the last six months, Lord &amp; Taylor has added 54 brands.</p>
        <p>Other chains have joined the rush for new, differentiated brands. Bloomingdale's has added a shopping bag full of new brands in the last year; Marshall Field's has added dozens of newly leased boutiques.</p>
        <p>Steve Sadove, the chief operating officer at Saks Inc., whose holdings include Saks Fifth Avenue and Profitt's, said department stores were increasingly recapturing some of the idea of the historic department stores: a bigger range of products. Department stores now, he explained, have largely turned into clothing and cosmetics merchants. ''Department stores used to be one-stop shopping,'' he said, ''full of different categories, where shoppers could find lots of new things.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday's department store sales numbers -- the best of three strong months -- come at a good time for Target, which is trying to sell Marshall Field's; that chain reported a hefty gain of 9.9 percent yesterday. Mervyn's, the other chain that Target is also trying to sell, came in at only 0.8 percent.</p>
        <p>Target has invested $200 million in a glittering restoration of the Marshall Field Chicago flagship. A very private offering memorandum is going out soon to interested parties, and the price is expected to be higher than it would have been a year ago. According to Gilbert W. Harrison, the chairman of Financo, an investment banking firm in New York, both May and Federated are expected to bid hotly, with a selling price that Mr. Harrison predicted would be more than $2 billion.</p>
        <p>While giving a nod to the efforts of her competitors, including Field's, Ms. Elfers is not ready to trumpet a department store renaissance -- nothing so sweeping. ''We're realists,'' she said. ''We don't want to paint a rosy picture: 'everything is fine.''' She paused. ''But right now, things are looking pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 10, 2004, Saturday  An article in Business Day yesterday about improved financial results for department store chains misstated the increase in March sales at Saks Fifth Avenue stores open at least a year. It was 20.6 percent, not 9.5. (The parent company, Saks Inc., posted a 9.5 increase in March sales.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 10, 2004, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about improved financial results for department store chains misstated the increase in March sales at Saks Fifth Avenue stores open at least a year. It was 20.6 percent, not 9.5. (The parent company, Saks Inc., posted a 9.5 increase in March sales.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
