<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Safety Panel Urges NASA To Examine Shuttle Escape</title>
    <meta content="Y26NASA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/26/national/nationalspecial/26NASA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1475430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Michael P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccool, William C (Cmdr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Husband, Rick D (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Laurel Salton (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramon, Ilan (Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chawla, Kalpana (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, David M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Keefe, Sean (Admr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6D91330F935A15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Safety Panel Urges NASA To Examine Shuttle Escape</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Safety Panel Urges NASA to Examine Shuttle Escape</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA Aerospace Safety Advistory Panel says NASA should seriously study crew escape systems for space shuttle and deploy them or re-examine high risk of human space flight; repeats earlier calls to study methods to allow crew to escape crippled shuttle at any point; Sean O'Keefe, NASA administrator, says that agency is working to make space flight safer but that only way to eliminate risk entirely is to stop flying (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NASA safety advisers said today that the agency should seriously study crew escape systems for the space shuttle and deploy them or re-examine the high risk of human space flight.</p>
        <p>In releasing its annual report to the space agency, the experts, the NASA Aerospace Safety Advisory Panel, repeated earlier calls to study methods to allow a crew to escape a crippled shuttle at any point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NASA safety advisers said that the agency should seriously study crew escape systems for the space shuttle and deploy them or re-examine the high risk of human space flight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NASA safety advisers said today that the agency should seriously study crew escape systems for the space shuttle and deploy them or re-examine the high risk of human space flight.</p>
        <p>In releasing its annual report to the space agency, the experts, the NASA Aerospace Safety Advisory Panel, repeated earlier calls to study methods to allow a crew to escape a crippled shuttle at any point.</p>
        <p>The panel, which finished the report before the Columbia accident on Feb. 1 that killed seven astronauts, generally praised NASA as putting safety first. But it criticized the agency for moving slowly on recommendations that it made in two previous reports to commit to building escape systems.</p>
        <p>''In past years, the panel has been very concerned about the lack of crew escape systems appropriate to all regions of powered flight on board the space shuttle,'' the nine-member committee said. ''It is clear that such systems will significantly increase the chance for crew survival in case of a major mishap.''</p>
        <p>The 106-page report covers the year immediately preceding the Columbia accident and did not comment on it directly or the investigation into its cause.</p>
        <p>In a meeting with the NASA administrator, Sean O'Keefe, the committee noted significant and inherent risks in flying the shuttle. The agency is considering upgrades to systems that will improve safety, including new power systems, advanced electronics and new tires for the landing gear. But, the panel said, the risk of losing another shuttle and its crew would remain high.</p>
        <p>Sidney M. Gutierrez, a panel member who is a former shuttle astronaut and a former Air Force colonel, said the risk of flying in the shuttle was significant on launching and returning. To meet the agency's stated safety goals for human space flight, Mr. Gutierrez said, ''the answer would be a full crew escape system.''</p>
        <p>He said that the agency conducted early studies on an escape capsule that would enclose a entire crew and that the military had demonstrated that group and individual escape pods could be built that worked with high-speed military aircraft. Noting that the shuttle had a demonstrated rate of catastrophic failure of one in 75 flights, Mr. Gutierrez added, the agency could lose one or more of the three remaining shuttles if it continued to fly them until 2020.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Keefe said that the agency was working to make space flight safer and that the only way to eliminate the risk entirely was to stop flying.</p>
        <p>''A question to ask is, Can we tolerate the risk inherent in space exploration?'' he said. ''Is the risk, which is high, acceptable as a consequence of being in an early phase of space exploration?''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Keefe cautioned against prematurely choosing one way of improving safety like escape pods. NASA officials noted that the proposed Orbital Space Plane, which would carry crews but not cargo to and from the International Space Station, is supposed to be much safer than the shuttle. But early design requirements specify the desired levels of safety, not ways to achieve it like escape pods, the space officials said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernard A. Harris Jr., another former astronaut who is a consultant to the safety panel, said NASA needed to change its view of crew safety. Dr. Harris agreed with Mr. Gutierrez that the approach had been returning the crew safely by landing the spacecraft safely. The focus, he said, should be on crew safety, even if it means sacrificing the spacecraft.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
