<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raiders Reach New England On Garner's Swollen Foot</title>
    <meta content="16RAID$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/16/sports/football/16RAID.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1359824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Gregg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garner, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Garner, Charlie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D91338F935A25752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raiders Reach New England On Garner's Swollen Foot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Raiders Reach New England on Garner's Swollen Foot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREGG BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Gregg</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Jan. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Raiders running back Charlie Garner makes crucial play in defeat of New York Jets in wild-card playoff game; Garner played with severely injured foot; his tenacity praised; career highlights noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>His performance was not quite like Willis Reed's limping into Madison Square Garden to lead the Knicks in Game 7 of the 1970 N.B.A. finals, but Charlie Garner, the diminutive Oakland running back, provided plenty of playoff heroics last Saturday night in a 38-24 victory over the Jets.</p>
        <p>His season-high 158 rushing yards, including an 80-yard touchdown run, was a big reason why the Raiders are preparing for an American Football Conference divisional playoff game Saturday night against New England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charlie Garner, the diminutive Oakland running back, is a big reason why the Raiders are preparing to play New England on Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>His performance was not quite like Willis Reed's limping into Madison Square Garden to lead the Knicks in Game 7 of the 1970 N.B.A. finals, but Charlie Garner, the diminutive Oakland running back, provided plenty of playoff heroics last Saturday night in a 38-24 victory over the Jets.</p>
        <p>His season-high 158 rushing yards, including an 80-yard touchdown run, was a big reason why the Raiders are preparing for an American Football Conference divisional playoff game Saturday night against New England.</p>
        <p>Garner, who stands 5 feet 9 inches and weighs 187 pounds, missed all but the Raiders' last two light practices before last week's wild-card game. His foot was so painful that team doctors ordered an M.R.I.  exam to ensure that it was not cracked.</p>
        <p>''Oh, it was hurting,'' Garner said, adding that the foot remains swollen ''but much better now than at this time last week.''</p>
        <p>The 29-year-old Garner, who has not missed a game in three seasons, was all legs on a 3rd-and-11 play at the Raiders' 20-yard line with 1 minute 40 seconds left in the game. The Jets had used their last timeout and needed one more defensive stop to set up a final chance to tie the score.</p>
        <p>Coach Jon Gruden had called ''98 Bunch Crunch,'' a toss play to Garner tight off right end designed against a full blitz. Garner wanted no part of the play.</p>
        <p>''It just hadn't been productive all year,'' Garner said. ''I just didn't think that was going to work.''</p>
        <p>The Jets sent everyone but Weeb Ewbank into the Raiders' backfield. Garner drove at his guard Frank Middleton, darted outside the sealing block of right tackle Lincoln Kennedy, and dashed untouched down the sideline for the clinching touchdown.</p>
        <p>Gruden has known Garner since the 1995 season, when he was the Eagles' offensive coordinator. A year earlier, Garner failed a drug test for marijuana before the draft and dropped into the second round out of the University of Tennessee. He overcame these setbacks to become only the seventh running back in N.F.L. history to rush for more than 100 yards in his first two league games.</p>
        <p>While in Philadelphia, linebacker Willie Thomas pulled Garner aside and advised him not to run straight at menacing linebackers. ''I told him: 'Run around them. With speed like yours, you'll kill 'em,' '' said Thomas, now with the Raiders.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco 49ers signed Garner, now wiser, as a free agent in 1999. That season, he was fifth in the National Football Conference with 1,229 yards rushing.</p>
        <p>Gruden remembered Garner's tenacity when the 49ers chose Garrison Hearst over Garner in a salary-cap-cutting move after Garner made his first Pro Bowl team last January.</p>
        <p>The difference between the Garner who played in Philadelphia and the one who plays in Oakland?</p>
        <p>''He's a man now,'' Gruden said. ''He's a much more professional player. He got married. Has a daughter. He's a more mature, more complete player than we had in Philadelphia.''</p>
        <p>The Raiders, eager to replace the power runner Tyrone Wheatley with a more versatile player, signed Garner to a four-year, $10 million contract last April.</p>
        <p>The Raiders' focus on the pass, however, had come at the expense of Garner's rushing totals. He rushed for 839 yards in the regular season, his fewest in four years, but he has caught a career-high 75 passes, behind only Tim Brown's 94 and Jerry Rice's 90 on the team.</p>
        <p>Oakland led the N.F.L. with 2,470 yards rushing in 2000. This season, the Raiders gained 1,654 on the ground while throwing 103 more times than running. The Raiders agree they focused too much on the passing game in the final six games of the regular season, finishing 2-4.</p>
        <p>Quarterback Rich Gannon said the Raiders were at their best when Garner ran more. That may be a good idea Saturday night against the Patriots, whose defense had 22 interceptions this season, second most in the A.F.C. behind Cleveland (33).</p>
        <p>New England, which was the surprising A.F.C. East champion after winning 11 of its last 14 games, is 2-3 when an opposing back rushes for more than 100 yards in a game.</p>
        <p>That makes Garner a bigger threat.</p>
        <p>''You look at me and you think you're going to run me over,'' Garner said. ''But I may run you over. You never know.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
