<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buyout Offer For Legent Is Extended</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="775815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LEGENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMPUTER ASSOCIATES INTERNATIONAL INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZUCKERMAN, LAURENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D81E31F93BA25754C0A963958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buyout Offer For Legent Is Extended</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ZUCKERMAN, LAURENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Locked in negotiations with the Justice Department, Computer Associates International extended its $1.74 billion tender offer for Legent Corporation for a second time yesterday. The offer, which was set to expire at midnight last night, was extended 48 hours, until midnight on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The extension gives Computer Associates and the Justice Department more time to try to reach a settlement regarding the Government's concerns that Computer Associates' acquisition of Legent would enable the company to monopolize certain lines of computer software for mainframe computers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Locked in negotiations with the Justice Department, Computer Associates International extended its $1.74 billion tender offer for Legent Corporation for a second time yesterday. The offer, which was set to expire at midnight last night, was extended 48 hours, until midnight on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The extension gives Computer Associates and the Justice Department more time to try to reach a settlement regarding the Government's concerns that Computer Associates' acquisition of Legent would enable the company to monopolize certain lines of computer software for mainframe computers.</p>
        <p>If the two sides cannot agree, the Government could challenge the deal in court. According to the terms of its takeover agreement with Legent, Computer Associates is compelled to defend any antitrust lawsuit.</p>
        <p>"We're just trying to work it through with them," said a spokesman for Computer Associates, referring to the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>The announcement of the extension lifted the shares of both companies yesterday. Shares of Computer Associates jumped $2.375, to $76, on the New York Stock Exchange, while Legent shares rose 50 cents, to $44 in Nasdaq trading.</p>
        <p>When Computer Associates first announced its cash offer of $47.95 a share for Legent in May, the company's top executives dismissed the notion that the deal might attract Government scrutiny.</p>
        <p>Computer Associates, which is based in Islandia, L.I., has used a strategy of aggressive acquisition to become the second-largest independent computer software company after the Microsoft Corporation. But Computer Associates did not use an investment banker on the deal and used a relatively obscure local law firm for its first filing with the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>The company's confidence proved misplaced when the Government, responding to worries raised by several of Legent's customers, decided to review the takeover, requesting information from both companies about scores of products, many more than analysts believe are overlapping.</p>
        <p>Since then, Computer Associates has hired Richard Rosen, an antitrust specialist at the law firm of Arnold &amp; Porter in Washington, to handle the case. The company has resisted requests that it divest itself of certain software, according to lawyers and analysts familiar with the case.</p>
        <p>"I think C.A. has been playing hardball," said Frank Dzubeck, president of Communications Network Architects, a Washington consultant. "It was using the tactic of standing pat until the 11th hour. Only now it is getting closer to 12th hour."</p>
        <p>Mr. Dzubeck added that he did not believe that Computer Associates would walk away from the deal, noting that the company was interviewing Legent employees at its Herndon, Va., headquarters last week.</p>
        <p>But he also said that separating overlapping software offered by both companies was no easy task. Many of the offending programs, which manage data storage, scheduling and security for mainframe computers, are offered on more than one operating system.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
