<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks With the Bills Leaving Smith Bitter</title>
    <meta content="17NFLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="951287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DC103FF934A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks With the Bills Leaving Smith Bitter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Smith, defensive star of Buffalo Bills, is unhapping with team's failure to come to terms on new contract; has reportedly rejected offer worth $22 million over five years, including a $5 million signing bonus; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What seems strange about the hard stance the Buffalo Bills have taken with Bruce Smith, their biggest star and one of the most influential defensive players in modern football, is that they always take care of their own. That is why the Bills have long been viewed as one of the classiest teams in the National Football League.</p>
        <p>But for months, the Bills have been in a contractual dispute with their star, and the 6-foot-4-inch, 273-pound Smith made it clear in a recent interview that while he would like to stay with the team for the rest of his career, he is extremely angry, and his bitterness toward the organization may never go away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What seems strange about the hard stance the Buffalo Bills have taken with Bruce Smith, their biggest star and one of the most influential defensive players in modern football, is that they always take care of their own. That is why the Bills have long been viewed as one of the classiest teams in the National Football League.</p>
        <p>But for months, the Bills have been in a contractual dispute with their star, and the 6-foot-4-inch, 273-pound Smith made it clear in a recent interview that while he would like to stay with the team for the rest of his career, he is extremely angry, and his bitterness toward the organization may never go away.</p>
        <p>''When everything is said and done, I will try to put all of this behind me,'' Smith, a 14-year veteran, said. ''But it will be hard to do so, because it has left a bad taste in my mouth. The whole thing that got to me is the fact I have been loyal my entire career to the Bills and I feel they are not being loyal to me.''</p>
        <p>Smith's agent, Leigh Steinberg, met with the team at its Orchard Park, N.Y., facility Monday and Tuesday to try to rework a previously rejected offer reportedly worth $22 million over five years, including a $5 million signing bonus. (Smith said the offer was for less money.)</p>
        <p>Steinberg said that if he met with Bills officials face to face, more progress would be made. He was right; progress was made. But how much progress is unclear. Right now it seems as if it could go either way: a deal could get done soon or one may not get done at all.</p>
        <p>''There was a time when I definitely thought we would work things out,'' Smith said. ''But the way they are making me wait, I don't know anymore.''</p>
        <p>This contract squabble shows that making promises, even honorable ones, can be dangerous.</p>
        <p>Last August, Ralph Wilson, the Bills' owner, made a promise to Jim Kelly, his former quarterback, that he would take care of his contract. Kelly was in a similar situation as Smith is in now.</p>
        <p>The Bills did eventually reward Kelly, but when the quarterback went public with the promise, it set a precedent for the Bills. It also prompted the N.F.L. Management Council to have a conversation with Wilson to caution him against making such promises. So when it was time for Smith's negotiations, the Bills took a more deliberate approach.</p>
        <p>That is the reason Smith is so angry. Kelly's contract situation was quickly resolved, while Smith, just as big a contributor in getting the Bills to four consecutive Super Bowls as Kelly was, is forced to wait.</p>
        <p>But the Bills, who are no longer commenting on the negotiations, had to be more careful because the Kelly situation blew up in their faces and they didn't want a repeat.</p>
        <p>The 34-year-old Smith, still one of the best-conditioned athletes in the game, is in the final year of a contract scheduled to pay him $2.2 million this season, the same amount he made last season. Despite being named the defensive player of the year last season, he was the 19th highest-paid player in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>What also angered Smith was his feeling that the Bills leaked erroneous information to the news media during the negotiation process.</p>
        <p>''I am being portrayed as greedy,'' said Smith, who held out of training camp for three weeks and was fined $105,000 by the Bills. ''It's unfair. This has been a very frustrating experience for me.''</p>
        <p>Smith explained that he got so frustrated with the negotiations that he once even considered asking for a trade.</p>
        <p>''That was a thought that crossed my mind,'' he said. ''If they would have brought a trade up, I would have given it some serious thought. But I want to see where these negotiations go before we reach that point.''</p>
        <p>If Smith did become a free agent, one team that might be interested is the Carolina Panthers.</p>
        <p>Would Smith be interested in playing for Bill Parcells, a coach Smith has a lot of respect for, and the Jets, a team that could challenge for a Super Bowl in several years?</p>
        <p>''If it came to that, yes, I would play for him,'' Smith said. ''The saying is, 'Where there is a will, there is a way.' I think the Jets may have a chance to play in the Super Bowl sooner rather than later, and if I didn't come back to the Bills I want to play for a team that has a chance to play in the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>''But my goal was always to try and stay with the Bills. I play for a great coach now in Marv Levy, who I respect a great deal and is like a father figure to me. I guess what I'm saying is that if the Bills don't want me, there are other teams that will.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, if Smith did become a free agent, he would probably be the most attractive player on the market. That is one of the things Smith's close friend, the Green Bay defensive lineman Reggie White, told him.</p>
        <p>White, who this season could become the first player in league history to have 11 seasons with 10 or more sacks, told Smith, who also has a shot at achieving that feat, to stick to his beliefs.</p>
        <p>Though the contract situation has taken a lot of his attention, Smith said he was able to stay focused on football. He said he thought the Bills have as good a chance as any team in the American Conference East to win the division.</p>
        <p>''We are going through a phase in our division and maybe the league where a lot of teams have a very dominant offense and not that great a defense,'' Smith, a nine-time Pro Bowl player, said.</p>
        <p>''If the Patriots had a dominant defense, they would have won the Super Bowl. If you look at the division, any team can win it, and we have just as good a chance as anybody because we have one of the best defenses in the division.''</p>
        <p>Rivals Off the Field, Too</p>
        <p>The Jets could not believe their eyes when they saw the figures from the four-year, $12 million contract of Jason Sehorn that made the talented young Giants player the seventh-highest-paid cornerback in the league.</p>
        <p>Why do the Jets care what a Giants player received? By signing Sehorn to such a lucrative contract, the Giants may have all but halted contract extension talks between the Jets and their cornerback Aaron Glenn.</p>
        <p>Glenn is represented by Jimmy Sexton and Kyle Rote Jr., the same agents who represent Sehorn. They have been talking to the Jets about an extension for Glenn and apparently feel that because Glenn has started in more games than Sehorn, Glenn may deserve just as much, if not more, money than Sehorn.</p>
        <p>But it would be difficult, if not impossible, for the Jets to sign Glenn to that kind of money unless the Jets release several players, restructure several contracts or both.</p>
        <p>The team's salary cap situation would not allow for that kind of contract -- although the release of Marvin Washington saves about $1 million on the cap for this year and is a starting point.</p>
        <p>Canada Waiting in the Wings</p>
        <p>While many in the league agree that Toronto would be a perfect candidate for an expansion team, it will probably be at least five years before the N.F.L. puts a franchise in Canada. League executives are committed first to putting a team back in Cleveland, then probably in Los Angeles. After that, Houston, Mexico City and Toronto ''will get extensive consideration,'' said Neil Austrian, the N.F.L. president.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the league continues to pour millions of dollars into Canadian football. Earlier this year the N.F.L. and the Canadian Football League formed a marketing and promotional partnership that is scheduled to lead to a World Classic Bowl next June between the Grey Cup champion and the winner of the World League title.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
