<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Sin Is Taken Seriously</title>
    <meta content="17PLUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="951230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satanism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plunket, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helms, Jesse (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weld, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7DB133FF934A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Sin Is Taken Seriously</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Plunket</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Plunket, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>SARASOTA, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Author Robert Plunket Op-Ed article discusses Jesse Helms's opposition to William Weld's nomination as ambassador to Mexico because of Weld's support for legalizing marijuana for medicinal use as example of Southern politician's concern with fighting devil; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you live in the South, then you immediately recognize that there is another player involved in this Jesse Helms-William Weld-Richard Lugar struggle over the soul of the Republican Party. That player is the devil. He occupies a much different place in Southern life than he does in the rest of the country. He is a living presence here, not just a concept. I have no idea how he got here; for that information you'll have to consult the works of William Faulkner or Billy Bob Thornton. But, as Jesse Helms knows, he is here, and as a neighbor he takes a little getting used to.</p>
        <p>True, the devil does have his fun side. Night life in the South is marvelously seedy and there is a very palpable sense of sin. The biker bars are rougher, the gay bars are gayer (the South is the home of drag), the nudie bars are nudie-er. And ah, the parking lot of a Southern bar on a muggy Saturday night. That truly is the devil's playground. With any luck you'll find drugs, prostitution, gambling and firecrackers, not to mention the town's leading minister and a county commissioner or two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you live in the South, then you immediately recognize that there is another player involved in this Jesse Helms-William Weld-Richard Lugar struggle over the soul of the Republican Party. That player is the devil. He occupies a much different place in Southern life than he does in the rest of the country. He is a living presence here, not just a concept. I have no idea how he got here; for that information you'll have to consult the works of William Faulkner or Billy Bob Thornton. But, as Jesse Helms knows, he is here, and as a neighbor he takes a little getting used to.</p>
        <p>True, the devil does have his fun side. Night life in the South is marvelously seedy and there is a very palpable sense of sin. The biker bars are rougher, the gay bars are gayer (the South is the home of drag), the nudie bars are nudie-er. And ah, the parking lot of a Southern bar on a muggy Saturday night. That truly is the devil's playground. With any luck you'll find drugs, prostitution, gambling and firecrackers, not to mention the town's leading minister and a county commissioner or two.</p>
        <p>That is the best thing about sin in the South: the devil still makes you do it. When Jimmy Swaggart made his famous confession on TV, Northerners saw the ruined shell of a man, his life destroyed by addictive behaviors. Southerners saw a minor slip that should be all cleaned up by next week. You're allowed a slip every now and then. The South is the only place left where you can get drunk regularly and not be considered an alcoholic.</p>
        <p>But some of the devil's little schemes are not as entertaining as televanangelism. The South -- and here, as a Southerner by birth and heritage, I'm defining the South as anywhere they automatically serve grits with your eggs -- certainly is the land of strange crimes. People are always disappearing and then being found six months later in the woods by a hound dog, all decomposed. And there is a serious devil-worshiping problem among the young. Just yesterday a group of teen-agers were put on probation for listening to Marilyn Manson and then going out and turning over tombstones.</p>
        <p>The cemetery vandals I can live with. It's the cat killers that get to me. Twice in the past 10 years I've had to live through these Son of Sam type sieges of people who capture house cats and then kill them in Satanic rituals. You try telling my cat that he can't go out tonight because the devil might get him.</p>
        <p>Naturally, anyone with a high moral purpose must make his stand against the devil. Every year at Halloween there is a great civic debate in many towns as to whether the holiday should be abolished for glorifying Satan and his works. And any sports team with the word ''devil'' in the title is a constant target. I have a friend who owned a store called Cult Video -- he specialized in hard-to-find classic and foreign films -- who finally changed the name of the business because of all the harassing calls.</p>
        <p>Jesse Helms (as far as I know) isn't this extreme but like any good Southerner, he knows a devilish scheme when he sees one, and you have to admit that legalizing marijuana for medicinal purposes does sound exactly like something the devil would come up with. Of course he must be opposed. Any Southern politician knows he must always stand up to the devil, unless, of course, the two of them already have a pre-arranged pact, i.e., tobacco.</p>
        <p>And not just any politician. The other day I was in that agora of Southern life, the 7-Eleven, and when the woman in front of me had her purchases totaled up, they came to $6.66. She became hysterical. The whole store became hysterical. We all had to chip in and give her enough money to buy another pack of cigarettes -- anything to undo that terrible number. So watch out, William Weld and Richard Lugar: I wouldn't want to get into a fight over the soul of anything with Jesse Helms. He's been taught by experts.</p>
        <p>Robert Plunket is the author of two novels, ''My Search for Warren Harding'' and ''Love Junkie.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Plunket is the author of two novels, ''My Search for Warren Harding'' and ''Love Junkie.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
