<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capturing Qaddafi's Gun-Toting Women on Film</title>
    <meta content="14PROF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/14/nyregion/14profile.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1581600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Libya</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">RANIA AJAMI</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Lynda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ajami, Rania</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Qaddafi, Muammar El- (Col)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Qaddafi's Female Bodyguards: Shadows of a Leader (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Libya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Qaddafi, Muammar El-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E2DC1F3CF937A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capturing Qaddafi's Gun-Toting Women on Film</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Capturing Qaddafi's Gun-Toting Women on Film</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richardson, Lynda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Rania Ajami, New York University graduate film student, whose documentary, Qaddafi's Female Bodyguards: Shadows of a Leader, has been shown at several world film festivals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is anyone's guess what will become of Rania Ajami's filmmaking career. But Ms. Ajami, who is 25 and a New York University graduate film student, certainly knows how to get attention. Her first feature documentary, spun out of a class assignment, is about the elite female corps of bodyguards assigned to Col. Muammar el-Qaddafi of Libya.</p>
        <p>You might have seen the guards; the eye-catching, gun-toting women in paramilitary uniforms. Some are knockouts. And they will knock you out, too, if you mess with their supreme leader. Some wear lipstick, jewelry, polished nails, even high heels. Last month, the Western world got a few glimpses of them as they backed up Colonel Qaddafi when he visited European Union officials in Brussels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rania Ajami, who is 25 and a New York University graduate film student, certainly knows how to get attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is anyone's guess what will become of Rania Ajami's filmmaking career. But Ms. Ajami, who is 25 and a New York University graduate film student, certainly knows how to get attention. Her first feature documentary, spun out of a class assignment, is about the elite female corps of bodyguards assigned to Col. Muammar el-Qaddafi of Libya.</p>
        <p>You might have seen the guards; the eye-catching, gun-toting women in paramilitary uniforms. Some are knockouts. And they will knock you out, too, if you mess with their supreme leader. Some wear lipstick, jewelry, polished nails, even high heels. Last month, the Western world got a few glimpses of them as they backed up Colonel Qaddafi when he visited European Union officials in Brussels.</p>
        <p>The mind conjures up all sorts of fantastical images, like the Libyan dictator as the singer Robert Palmer, the suave pop Romeo whose hit ''Addicted to Love'' had him backed by a band of deadpan sleek women in little black dresses.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Ajami, who is of Lebanese origin, will have none of this nonsense during a chat the other day. She hopes to dash simplistic ideas with her new film, ''Qaddafi's Female Bodyguards: Shadows of a Leader.'' The documentary, which is yet to be sold or distributed, is an official selection at the Montreal World Film Festival, the Avignon/New York Film Festival and the Festival du Film de Strasbourg.</p>
        <p>''It's showing the notion of the female bodyguard as being these women who are liberated and how it extends to all sectors of society,'' she says in a soft British accent, mellowed perhaps by her undergraduate years at Princeton, where she majored in English literature and minored in theater and dance. ''Bodyguards are really a symbol of this new feminism that exists. One wonders, once Qaddafi is no longer there, will the women still have this future? Do they have a future without him?''</p>
        <p>She says that while the bodyguards may exude sexuality, it demonstrates modern views on gender equality and family life under the Qaddafi regime. ''They present themselves well. The girls are trained in weaponry, but at the same time they want to look good. I really felt it was more about their pride and confidence. Most of the women who go into it are married with children.''</p>
        <p>In talking to Ms. Ajami, one quickly gets a sense of how she pulled off this documentary; obtaining what she describes as unprecedented access to female bodyguards during two trips to Libya last year. She wrote to the Libyan authorities for two years seeking permission.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ajami, who wears low-rise blue jeans and a black top, is driven and quietly confident. All right. She can be a bit pushy, too. She does not want the interview taking place in her apartment. She says it is messy, filled with boxes and visiting relatives. She prefers to meet 10 blocks away in the Upper East Side apartment of a publicist who also appears as the lead actor in one of her recent short films, a futuristic love story set in a surveillance-controlled society. (She is eager to show it on her Mac PowerBook laptop, and hands over headphones.)</p>
        <p>That brings up another point. She is insistent that she not be labeled an Arab filmmaker. She says the bodyguard documentary is not representative of her entire body of work, which includes films like the science fiction short, and experimental plays, including one inspired by the paintings of Balthus.</p>
        <p>And, uh, Ms. Ajami, did you say you were 25?</p>
        <p>She attends N.Y.U. on an Alberto Vilar Global Fellowship, two years of fully paid study modeled after the Rhodes scholarship. She graduates in 2005. The bodyguard film originated in a documentary directing course. ''I was going more as a student without a political agenda, and that way they felt more comfortable,'' she says.</p>
        <p>It also did not hurt that she was able to convey sensitivity to Arab culture. Her father is a Lebanese-born Muslim and the chairman of a London-based investment company; her mother a Lebanese Christian. Ms. Ajami speaks Arabic, French and Spanish. She was born in Ann Arbor, Mich., but grew up mostly in London.</p>
        <p>IN Libya, she says she had an opportunity to meet Colonel Qaddafi but decided against it. ''I didn't want to fall into the cliché. It was more important to see life under him. I knew already what his views are.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ajami has soft features and wavy, shoulder-length hair. Her smile is quick and wide. She holds up a video remote control, flicking through the documentary's scenes of women training with firearms. ''It's very progressive,'' she says. ''You don't get this in any other country.'' One officer jokingly mimics a Pantene commercial, caressing her long hair. A female bodyguard in a leather coat gently pushes girls away from Colonel Qaddafi, a cult figure in his homeland.</p>
        <p>And yes, Ms. Ajami has heard the speculation of hanky panky between the dictator and his bodyguards. ''The sexual thing makes me mad,'' she says, bristling. ''It's always the thing that people pounce on, and it just didn't exist.''</p>
        <p>She will not discuss her own views on the Libyan leader, or her politics. The same goes for her private life. When asked if she is seeing anyone, she replies: ''There's someone, but that's as far as it goes. And no, it's not Qaddafi.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
