<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restaurants</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANT REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LA COTE BASQUE (NYC RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7103BF930A15751C0A966958260" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restaurants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bryan Miller</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, BRYAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: After four recent visits to La Cote Basque, still one of New York City's most sumptuous dining spots, I came away with several lingering memories. One is of an awestruck young couple (my guess was high school prom age) trying to act so worldly as they struggled with the all-French menu and puzzled over the surfeit of silverware.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: After four recent visits to La Cote Basque, still one of New York City's most sumptuous dining spots, I came away with several lingering memories. One is of an awestruck young couple (my guess was high school prom age) trying to act so worldly as they struggled with the all-French menu and puzzled over the surfeit of silverware.</p>
        <p>After four recent visits to La Cote Basque, still one of New York City's most sumptuous dining spots, I came away with several lingering memories. One is of an awestruck young couple (my guess was high school prom age) trying to act so worldly as they struggled with the all-French menu and puzzled over the surfeit of silverware. It was one of those terrifyingly wonderful evenings they surely will never forget. Another is the timeless charm of the dining room with its seaside murals, red leather banquettes and profusion of fresh flowers. A third is a splendid bottle of Meursault enjoyed one evening.</p>
        <p>You may notice that food is not one of the top three impressions, a fact that is disturbing. The cooking these days at Jean-Jacques Rachou's 32-year-old restaurant is pleasing overall, sometimes uplifting, but too rarely memorable. Since last October Michel Fitoussi, who has had a varied career since his days at the Palace in the late 1970's, has been running the kitchen while Mr. Rachou tends to the dining room. La Cote Basque has never been a place to go for culinary revelation. Its strength was its faithful execution of classic French cuisine in this era of gastronomic free-for-alls. In this role, however, it seems to have slipped a notch.</p>
        <p>A wide-ranging sampling of the current menu found that while a little more than half of the dishes continue to uphold French tradition proudly, the rest are flawed. A .500-plus average may keep a baseball team on top of the league, but not a restaurant.</p>
        <p>A striking example is La Cote Basque's once-splendid assortment of cold shellfish with vegetables. On two recent occasions, the crabmeat was ice cold and tasteless. The lobster was pleasing, but the garnish was more appealing to look at than to taste. Vegetables here are a problem across the board, but especially with entrees, where they often have the limp appearance of having come from a steam table.</p>
        <p>Among the recommended starters is a ballotine of salmon, studded with lobster, carrots and peas, and surrounded by pretty turned cucumbers and sweet peppers in a sparkling parsley sauce. Another good choice is roasted sea scallops, a special, which are set over tart sauteed endives in a lemony herb butter sauce. And one day the chef proposed delicious quails stuffed with forcemeat, mushrooms and caramelized onions, with a clean, sharp sauce of lingonberries and Madeira. One preparation I have enjoyed over the years is the regally presented casserole of shellfish - in this case scallops and lobster - in a light ginger-spiked, cream-thickened shellfish stock. It was well cooked this time, but unbalanced, tasting mostly of ginger.</p>
        <p>It takes a large crew of captains and waiters to run this sprawling ship, and the experienced professionals here have it down to a poised routine. Several captains are knowledgeable about the well-stocked wine list and can be helpful, at least among reds, of which Bordeaux is best represented (at fairly elevated prices). A restaurant of this caliber, however, should not omit the vintages of whites like Meursaults, Chablis and all Alsace selections.</p>
        <p>La Cote Basque has always turned out picture-perfect classics like grilled Dover sole a la meuniere, roasted chicken with herbs, and rack of lamb - and it still does. Cassoulet is still a winner, too -crusty, rich but not too heavy, and replete with buttery duck confit, garlic sausage and pork. A hint of cinnamon and cumin in the sauce does wonders for rosy lamb medallions, which come with raisin-flecked couscous. Venison, though, came out gray and bland, although the peppery sauce with roasted chestnuts was invigorating. Fans of sweetbreads should be satisfied with the big, firm and well-browned version here, accompanied by a sturdy sauce of veal stock, mushrooms and cauliflower.</p>
        <p>Overall, seafood was less successful. A special of three fillets - snapper, salmon and sea bass - arrived well cooked, but the salmon and bass needed seasoning. So, too, did the insipid mound of pasta in the center, garnished with chopped tomatoes. Another time a salmon steak, said to be cooked with thyme, came out devoid of any seasoning; only the good hollandaise saved it. One evening when the kitchen did turn out a fine grilled snapper, perfectly cooked and flavorful, the deep-fried parsley promised on the menu was missing.</p>
        <p>This is a good place to sample a classic skate a la Grenobloise. Delicate skate wings are cooked to perfection and enhanced with brown butter, parsley, lemon and capers.</p>
        <p>One area in which La Cote Basque has not lost pace is desserts. Individual apple tarts are superb, especially with vanilla ice cream ringed by a coulis of apricots and Calvados. Souffles are heavenly, too, whether made with Grand Marnier or seasonal fruits, and ile flottante comes under a dome of spun sugar that resembles a bird cage. Another visual stunner is the green apple of lacquered sugar that holds whipped cream flavored with applejack brandy.</p>
        <p>La Cote Basque, which received three stars in 1986, is still one of the grandest of the old-guard French restaurants, and regulars who know the menu can have a transcendent experience there. Others run a small but significant chance of being disappointed - and that is not the definition of a three-star restaurant. Two stars seems more fitting for La Cote Basque today.</p>
        <p>La Cote Basque</p>
        <p>**</p>
        <p>5 East 55th Street, 688-6525.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Old World charm in a comfortable dining room wrapped in seaside murals.</p>
        <p>Service: Experienced professionals keep a steady cadence.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Ballotine of salmon, roasted sea scallops with endives and herb butter, stuffed quails, grilled Dover sole, rack of lamb, cassoulet, sweetbreads, skate a la Grenobloise, souffles, ile flottante, apple tart.</p>
        <p>Wine: Extensive list, especially among Bordeaux, but pricey. Many whites lack vintages and producers.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch prix fixe at $32 (with several supplements); dinner prix fixe at $55 (with supplements).</p>
        <p>Credit cards: All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours: Lunch: noon to 2:30 P.M. Monday to Saturday; dinner: 6 to 10:30 P.M. Monday to Friday, until 11 P.M. Saturday. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Suggested, especially on weekends.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: One small step up at entrance; everything on one level. ----</p>
        <p>What the stars mean:</p>
        <p>(None)Poor to satisfactory</p>
        <p>*Good</p>
        <p>**Very good</p>
        <p>***Excellent</p>
        <p>****Extraordinary</p>
        <p>These ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service considered.</p>
        <p>Prices and menus are subject to change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
