<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late Selloff Pushes Dow 8.79 Points Lower</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="329056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WIGGINS, PHILLIP H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DE143DF930A15751C0A966958260" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late Selloff Pushes Dow 8.79 Points Lower</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILLIP H. WIGGINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WIGGINS, PHILLIP H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Stocks fell broadly yesterday, depressed by late selling, and after being nearly 30 points higher than its opening level about 2 P.M., the Dow Jones industrial average finished 8.79 points lower, at 2,574.77.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Stocks fell broadly yesterday, depressed by late selling, and after being nearly 30 points higher than its opening level about 2 P.M., the Dow Jones industrial average finished 8.79 points lower, at 2,574.77.</p>
        <p>Stocks fell broadly yesterday, depressed by late selling, and after being nearly 30 points higher than its opening level about 2 P.M., the Dow Jones industrial average finished 8.79 points lower, at 2,574.77.</p>
        <p>Declining issues on the New York Stock Exchange, which had trailed advances by nearly 2 to 1, finished ahead of gaining ones, 753 to 715.</p>
        <p>Volume on the Big Board jumped to 184.3 million shares, many of which changed hands in the last hour of trading, from 159.2 million shares on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Early Session Action</p>
        <p>''Near the beginning of the session, a lot of traders realized that what happened in Japan earlier in the week, when the Nikkei 225-stock index plunged 1,161.19 points, or 3.15 percent, to 35,734.33, was influenced by index-arbitrage sell programs, not just by interest rate concerns or institutions unloading stocks,'' said Peter G. Grennan, the head of stock index futures trading at Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc.</p>
        <p>The early market was also influenced positively by the Federal Reserve Board chairman, Alan Greenspan, who told the Senate Banking Committee yesterday that rises in food and energy prices last month would reverse and that there was no evidence of expanding inflation.</p>
        <p>The traders said the stock market began to weaken in the afternoon when a firm using the strategy known as ''tactical asset allocation'' - the switching between stocks and bonds - executed a large sell program about 2 P.M.</p>
        <p>''Such shifting of exposure is usually done through the futures market, which is the fastest and most efficient way to accomplish the switch,'' Mr. Grennan said.</p>
        <p>Although American stocks ended on a negative note, some experts remained optimistic.</p>
        <p>''The stock market is consolidating from an oversold condition,'' said Harold A. Mackinney, the head of the investment policy committee at the Fleet/Norstar Financial Group in Providence, R.I. ''January's inflation results are now behind us, and they will represent the worst numbers for 1990. The bond market has overreacted to the recently released Producer Price Index and Consumer Price Index results, and significantly lower interest rates should be evident soon.''</p>
        <p>Broader Gauges Fall</p>
        <p>In the broader market yesterday, the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks dropped by 1.97 points, to 325.70, while the New York Stock Exchange composite index slipped by 0.79 point, to 180.28.</p>
        <p>Among individual issues, UAL fell by 5 3/4, to 126 1/2. The parent of United Airlines, based in Elk Grove Village, Ill., said its board had not received an acquisition proposal from its employee groups or any other party.</p>
        <p>Honeywell edged up by 3/4, to 77 3/8. Analysts attributed the rise to a conclusion by investors that the recently released earnings of the company for the fourth quarter showed that it was benefiting from a restructuring begun last year.</p>
        <p>Pfizer plunged by 4 1/2, to 59 1/4. The company, whose artificial heart valves by its Shiley unit have been the subject of lawsuits, will appear on Monday at a Congressional hearing in Washington on regulation of the medical-device industry.</p>
        <p>Active Blue Chips</p>
        <p>In other active blue-chip trading, Philip Morris rose by 1/2, to 38 1/8; I.B.M was off by 1 5/8, to 103 1/4, and A.T.&amp; T. fell by 5/8, to 38 1/8.</p>
        <p>On the American Stock Exchange, the Amex market-value index rose by 0.40 point, to 353.35, while in over-the-counter trading, the Nasdaq composite index gained 1.23 points, to 422.75.</p>
        <p>In over-the-counter trading, Apple Computer dropped by a point, to 33. The analysts said they expected more layoffs and price cuts on products than the company, based in Cupertino, Calif., has announced in recent days as it tries to lower costs to increase earnings and revenues.</p>
        <p>Lin Broadcasting dropped 3 points, to 109. The traders said a Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette analyst, Dennis Leibowitz, had removed the New York-based company from his list of recommended stocks, cutting his rating to ''moderately attractive.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
