<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>5 School Districts Will Undergo Review for Progress on Failings</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="518535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ORANGE (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, WAYNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIS, JOHN (COMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE113EF931A35757C0A964958260" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>5 School Districts Will Undergo Review for Progress on Failings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE KING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KING, WAYNE</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, April 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five urban school districts in New Jersey will be reviewed this spring to determine whether they are making adequate progress toward correcting serious educational deficiencies and a sixth, Orange, will be considered for a more comprehensive review that could lead to a state takeover, according to education officials.</p>
        <p>Education Commissioner John Ellis outlined the more stringent monitoring process at a State Board of Education meeting at which he and Assistant Education Commissioner Larry Leverett briefed the board on progress under the state's Quality Education Act and described a "carrot and stick" approach to upgrading schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five urban school districts in New Jersey will be reviewed this spring to determine whether they are making adequate progress toward correcting serious educational deficiencies and a sixth, Orange, will be considered for a more comprehensive review that could lead to a state takeover, according to education officials.</p>
        <p>Education Commissioner John Ellis outlined the more stringent monitoring process at a State Board of Education meeting at which he and Assistant Education Commissioner Larry Leverett briefed the board on progress under the state's Quality Education Act and described a "carrot and stick" approach to upgrading schools.</p>
        <p>The carrot, in this case, is greatly expanded state aid, particularly for 30 "special needs" urban districts that have many poor and minority students and serious educational deficiencies.</p>
        <p>The stick is stricter monitoring and what Commissioner Ellis called a "no excuses are acceptable" approach to insuring quality education for all students in the state, regardless of their districts' abililty to pay. Team to Assess Districts</p>
        <p>In outlining the monitoring process, Commissioner Ellis said five urban districts would receive formal assessments by an external review team that would be "thorough, comprehensive and prescriptive."</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, one district "will be considered for comprehensive compliance investigation, which is the process that can result in a proposed state takeover of a district."</p>
        <p>He did not name the district, but another education official confirmed that it was Orange, a 4,000-student district that is already being monitored for educational deficiencies.</p>
        <p>Orange is one of eight urban districts that are subject to what is called Level III monitoring, which means that it is operating under conditional certification, and must make monthly reports on its progress toward correcting deficiencies to allow full certification.</p>
        <p>The other districts in that category are Asbury Park, Camden, Hoboken, Jersey City, Newark, Union City and Paterson.</p>
        <p>Two of them, Jersey City and Paterson, have been taken over by the state but remain in the Level III monitoring category as they continue to correct deficiencies.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Ellis said today that "significant progress is occurring in the two state-operated school districts" but that "clearly, the minimum of five years assumed under the takeover law is required to begin to achieve the systemic reform required."</p>
        <p>However, Mr. Ellis and Assistant Education Commissioner Leverett also pointed to an array of new programs and physical improvements in the 30 "special needs" districts. For example, in Newark, the state's largest district with 50,000 students, computers have been placed for the first time in some sixth- seventh- and eighth-grade classrooms, a program for gifted students has been expanded to 5 more elementary schools, summer remedial programs have been offered at 26 schools and interactive television instruction has begun at 5 schools.</p>
        <p>In addition, virtually every one of the district's 59 elementary schools, 13 senior high schools and 9 special schools are undergoing some kind of physical upgrading, from extensive window replacements to new roofs, gym floors and boiler rooms to asbestos removal.</p>
        <p>Similar programs were undertaken in all of the "special needs" districts. The current 1991-92 school year is the first to benefit from the Governor's Quality Education Act, which originally appropriated $1.1 billion in new assistance to the state's schools, heavily weighted to poor urban districts. Later revisions and caps on spending cut the figure to about half that amount.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
