<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cooking Up Some Ideas For Negative Campaigns</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA173AF934A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cooking Up Some Ideas For Negative Campaigns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"EVER notice Bill Clinton when he runs?" asked Sean Fitzpatrick, an advertising executive who recently parted with the Bush campaign's ad team. "He looks like a duck."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzpatrick turned that concept into a proposal for a television commercial: a waddling mechanical duck dissolves into images of the hefty Arkansas Governor jogging. The announcer says Mr. Clinton claims he is "not like those Democrats in Congress who like to tax and spend, tax and spend." Then, after the duck has quacked, he says: "We say, if it talks like a duck, walks like a duck, it must be a Democrat."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"EVER notice Bill Clinton when he runs?" asked Sean Fitzpatrick, an advertising executive who recently parted with the Bush campaign's ad team. "He looks like a duck."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fitzpatrick turned that concept into a proposal for a television commercial: a waddling mechanical duck dissolves into images of the hefty Arkansas Governor jogging. The announcer says Mr. Clinton claims he is "not like those Democrats in Congress who like to tax and spend, tax and spend." Then, after the duck has quacked, he says: "We say, if it talks like a duck, walks like a duck, it must be a Democrat."</p>
        <p>Though that spot has not been made, the season of the attack ad has arrived. Last week, the Clinton and Bush campaigns officially began using paid-for airtime to fling mud.</p>
        <p>The Clinton camp fired first; its commercial interspersed clips of President Bush making predictions of a recovery with black-and-white frames showing rising jobless figures.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign tried humor; it used hick music and fast-forward video in an ad that portrays Mr. Clinton as a Governor of a small, backward state who did little but raise taxes.</p>
        <p>It will only get nastier, and the toughest ads can be expected to come from the Republicans as long as Mr. Bush is stuck in second place in the polls.</p>
        <p>"The resistance to Bush is akin to the resistance that mosquitoes have developed to DDT -- people are resisting any and all advances from him," said Douglas Watts, the advertising director for the 1984 Reagan campaign who is now in public relations. "The only way to truly overcome that is to start beating up the other guy."</p>
        <p>Killer commercials have inherent risks, but they are often the only way candidates can break through to voters whose only exposure to political discourse is on "Murphy Brown," not the evening news.</p>
        <p>The most important decision facing the Republicans in coming weeks is not whether to attack but how hard and on what issues: If Mr. Bush jumps from family values to the draft to pollution in Arkansas, he risks confusing voters and undermining his own credibility.</p>
        <p>Most analysts agree that reviving tales of womanizing would only cast the Republicans as purveyors of sleaze. And while the Bush campaign has prepared advertising implying that Mr. Clinton evaded the draft, many Republican strategists questioned whether that issue "has legs" because of the public's ambiguity about the Vietnam War. Pick One Bull's Eye</p>
        <p>"They have to throw darts at one bull's eye," said Don Sipple, an advertising consultant in Mr. Bush's campaign earlier this year. "It has to be Clinton's credibility. I would deal with it very explicitly. Just frame it there at the top of the commercial: How much can we really trust Bill Clinton?"</p>
        <p>As long as the criticisms are accurate, Mr. Sipple has no qualms about nasty ads. "You're going to take the hit for going negative," he said, "so you might as well land the blow."</p>
        <p>But officials in both the Bush and Clinton camps are nervous because it is getting harder to dodge media "truth squads" -- greater efforts by reporters to look into the claims made in the advertisements. They also know some voters have grown sophisticated about commercials and may not want to elect someone they think is too vicious.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush is still accused of race-baiting with the Willie Horton ad in 1988. A reminder of the danger to the messenger is Elizabeth Holtzman's attacks on Geraldine A. Ferraro in New York's Democratic Senate primary. The ads may have cost Ms. Ferraro the race, but Ms. Holtzman came in fourth, and many voters disliked the tone of her campaign.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign's use of humor and the Clinton campaign's attempts to hang the President using only his own words and numbers from his own Bureau of Labor Statistics may have been attempts to avoid sharing Ms. Holtzman's predicament.</p>
        <p>Republicans say their television assault will move into higher gear this week, and the Clinton campaign is not known for shrinking from a brawl. Neither camp will disclose what it has in the works, but several political consultants were asked what they would do under the circumstances. Mr. Fitzpatrick's answer was the duck ad.</p>
        <p>Tony Schwartz, a Democratic consultant, said he would reprise his 1968 "A Heartbeat Away" commercial that sought to make voters nervous about Spiro Agnew, Richard M. Nixon's running mate. "The ad should say, 'Which of these two men do you want a heartbeat away from the Presidency: Quayle or Gore?' " Mr. Schwartz said. "It is very meaningful when you talk about how many of the last Vice Presidents became President."</p>
        <p>Joseph Napolitan, who also helps Democratic candidates, says they should exploit the idea that Mr. Bush is out of touch with ordinary Americans.</p>
        <p>A script he dreamed up opens with scenes from the Depression, cuts to a preppie emerging from a limousine with his school books, and then to Mr. Bush emerging from Air Force One and into a limousine. The announcer says "Some people never come into contact with the realities of life," recalls that young George Bush was chauffeured to school in Greenwich, Conn., and says he still doesn't understand poverty, hunger or unemployment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Napolitan, who has been in the business for decades, counsels subtlety to his younger peers.  "We tried to sneak in with a stiletto," he said.  "Today, they're hitting with a sledgehammer."  THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
