<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Markets; Where Does Britain Go From Here?</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EUROPEAN MONETARY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D91438F934A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Markets; Where Does Britain Go From Here?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard W. Stevenson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE British equity market last week got what it has been praying for all year: a drop in interest rates and the promise of more to come.</p>
        <p>Having abandoned its commitment to keeping the value of the pound stable against other European currencies, the British Government did a monetary policy about-face, cutting its benchmark lending rate by one point, to 9 percent, and leaving open the possibility that rates could fall by as much as another point by the end of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE British equity market last week got what it has been praying for all year: a drop in interest rates and the promise of more to come.</p>
        <p>Having abandoned its commitment to keeping the value of the pound stable against other European currencies, the British Government did a monetary policy about-face, cutting its benchmark lending rate by one point, to 9 percent, and leaving open the possibility that rates could fall by as much as another point by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>After several years in which the Government had forgone opportunities to stimulate the battered economy because of its pledge to prop up the pound in the face of high German interest rates, the rate cut provided investors with new hope that the recession would end and corporate profits would grow again.</p>
        <p>"The market's been off to the races," said Richard Davidson, an investment strategist at Morgan Stanley International in London.</p>
        <p>By the end of the week the Financial Times-Stock Exchange index of 100 leading stocks stood at 2,601.0, up 34 points this week and up 222.7 points in the 11 days since Britain pulled out of the European Exchange Rate Mechanism. After hitting an all-time high of 2,737.8 in May just after the Conservative Government of Prime Minister Major won re-election, the market had slid steadily to a low for the year of 2,281.0 on Aug. 25.</p>
        <p>"The floating of sterling and the cut in interest rates has persuaded most people that some sort of recovery is now on schedule for next year, which is precisely what the market had grown to doubt during the summer," said George Hodgson, chief equity strategist here at S. G. Warburg &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The British market looks particularly attractive compared with the Paris, Milan and Frankfurt markets. The French Government's decision last week to push up interest rates to defend the value of the franc dashed hopes for quick monetary easing in that country. Italy's economic and monetary policies remain in turmoil after the devaluation of the lira and the nation's departure from Europe's monetary system earlier this month. The prospects for the Frankfurt market had seemed to brighten when the Bundesbank nudged interest rates down two weeks ago, but the central bank now seems inclined to maintain its tight money policy.</p>
        <p>But analysts said they were cautioning investors in the London market not to become overoptimistic and not to ignore the problems still facing Britain. They said that pulling out of the Exchange Rate Mechanism gave the nation new flexibility in promoting growth through lower rates, but also increased the likelihood of inflation since the devalued pound will make imports more expensive. And they said that it would take many companies a long time to recover from Britain's worst recession since the 1930's.</p>
        <p>"Where we go from here remains not so clear," said Carolyn J. F. Moses, the head of research at Lehman Brothers International in London. "So what I see fund managers doing is sticking with big stocks. This is not the kind of market where smaller companies or companies with big debt positions are going to be bailed out."</p>
        <p>Andrew Bell, director of European equity strategy at Barclays de Zoette Wedd in London, said: "The market is anticipating more of a springback of corporate earnings than it would get in an E.R.M. environment. But we'd be cautious about chasing the market through 2,600 without signs of a recovery."</p>
        <p>Still, analysts see a number of sectors and particular companies whose earnings and stock prices could benefit from the lower interest rates.</p>
        <p>Among the biggest winners will be those British companies that have large operations in the United States. They will benefit from the sharp slide in the value of the pound against the dollar since Britain started allowing sterling to float in value. The pound, which was worth more than $2 less than a month ago, is now worth about $1.70, meaning that earnings in dollars will be worth 15 percent more when expressed in pounds.</p>
        <p>Two of those that will benefit the most, analysts said, are Imperial Chemical Industries, which last year did 31 percent of its sales in North and South America, primarily the United States, and Hanson P.L.C., the British-American conglomerate that derives nearly half its sales from the United States.</p>
        <p>But the analysts said investors should approach even the biggest dollar earners with some caution. "Earnings in dollar terms are going to be relatively flat for some time, given the weakness in the U.S. economy," said Mr. Hodgson of Warburg.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that it was probably too soon to bet on earnings turnarounds from companies that rely primarily on the British economy. The news from British industry last week, in fact, was almost uniformly gloomy. British Aerospace P.L.C., for example, posted a large loss, said it would cut 3,000 jobs and saw its share price plunge by 43 percent.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Moses of Lehman Brothers said that Pearson P.L.C. and Reed International P.L.C., both publishing and media companies, could be attractive buys. She also said the Boots Company P.L.C., a consumer products and retailing concern, would be the kind of company that will see sales and earnings improve early in any recovery.</p>
        <p>"A company like Boots is safe even if the consumer spending pattern remains only modestly up," Ms. Moses said. "There's a little touch in the market of being ready for a consumer upturn, but not a willingness to make big plays into cyclical sectors and definitely not into heavy industry cyclical stocks."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
