<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Fresh Can You Get? Ask the Devotees of the Fish Farm</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH FARMING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MULTI AQUACULTURE SYSTEMS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROMANO, JAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCENERY, MARIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALENIT, BOB</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DB133CF935A15754C0A964958260" item-length="1339" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Fresh Can You Get? Ask the Devotees of the Fish Farm</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROMANO, JAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LINDA DRASHEFF and Abby Bluestone sat on an empty lobster box, dipping jumbo shrimp into a paper cup filled with cocktail sauce.</p>
        <p>Behind them, in rows of round concrete tanks filled with water, thousands of lobsters, crabs, shrimp and oysters quietly waited for the moment when they, too, would be plucked from their tanks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LINDA DRASHEFF and Abby Bluestone sat on an empty lobster box, dipping jumbo shrimp into a paper cup filled with cocktail sauce.</p>
        <p>Behind them, in rows of round concrete tanks filled with water, thousands of lobsters, crabs, shrimp and oysters quietly waited for the moment when they, too, would be plucked from their tanks.</p>
        <p>Nearby on a cloudless summer afternoon, in what has become an weekend ritual in East Hampton, a steady stream of hungry vacationers arrived to carry away theshellfish.</p>
        <p>The site was the Fish Farm, an assortment of ramshackle buildings and huge outdoor tanks that serve as temporary home for millions of fish and crustaceans headed for dinner tables from Hoboken to Hong Kong.  More than a few, however, never make it off Long Island.</p>
        <p>"I like the place because it's funky," Ms. Drasheff, 36, of Manhattan, said.</p>
        <p>She, along with Ms. Bluestone, had bicycled to the farm from their nearby summer rental to buy that night's lobster dinner. "You feel like you're getting the fish right off the boat," Ms. Drasheff added.</p>
        <p>Ms. Drasheff and Ms. Bluestone, 28, a talent agent from New York City, were among hundreds of vacationers and year-round residents who travel each day from the fashionable enclaves of the Hamptons to the dusty farm on Cranberry Hole Road just off Route 27 in Amagansett. 22 Tanks of 18,000 Gallons Each</p>
        <p>"It's really the only place to go for an emergency lobster," Ms. Bluestone said.</p>
        <p>When abundant, the price of lobsters can fall as low $3.25 a pound.</p>
        <p>The proprietor and founder of the farm is Bob Calenti, 48, with a quick smile, a fisherman's tan and a permanent patina of fish stains on his faded jeans. And oh yes, a Ph.D. in marine biology from New York University.</p>
        <p>For five years Mr. Calenti worked at the New York Ocean Science Laboratory in Montauk, which has closed.  "Then I decided that commercial fish farming would be easier than constantly applying for grant money," he said. "Boy, was I naive."</p>
        <p>Mr. Calenti's original idea was to establish a working fish farm, a breeding plant that would use high-technology equipment and procedures to produce abundant quantities of striped bass, northern blowfish, sea bass, fluke and winter flounder. He established the Fish Farm in 1976, building 22 outdoor tanks of 18,000 gallons each.</p>
        <p>But obtaining the necessary government permits proved to be a four-year pilgrimage through a bureaucratic maze. "I should have gone into teaching instead," he said. "By the time it was over, I was broke. I had a brand new shiny fish farm with no money. It was like having a Cadillac with no gas."</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Calenti began breeding fish. "We struggled for eight years," he said. "Then we lucked into lobster and live fish."</p>
        <p>Rather than breed fish, he found that it was easier to buy them live from nearby fisheries, keep them healthy in the tanks and sell them to restaurant suppliers in the United States and overseas.</p>
        <p>"We're a wholesaler to wholesalers," Mr. Calenti said. "Nearly every Chinese and Korean restaurant in New York City ultimately gets our product."</p>
        <p>Distributors go to the Fish Farm, whose corporate name is Multi Aquaculture Systems Inc., to pick up live seafood and return to the city to distribute it.</p>
        <p>"Most of our business is in live fish," he said.  "Something that sells for $1 dead will sell for $4 live. The prices that the end customer will pay for live product is astounding."</p>
        <p>A substantial part of the business is exporting live fish and shellfish to countries like Italy, Spain and Japan. The farm, Mr. Calenti said, is the largest live-seafood holding operation of the handful on the East End.</p>
        <p>"We ship about a million and a half pounds of lobster a year," he said.  "There are always lobsters coming in and going out. We usually keep a minimum of about 6,500 of them in the tanks."</p>
        <p>When the lobsters from the waters of Montauk and Long Island Sound arrive at the farm, Mr. Calenti said, they are sorted by weight and placed in the concrete outdoor tanks. Other shellfish are also kept in the outdoor tanks. Live flounder, fluke, blackfish and sea robin are stored in fiberglass tanks in the buildings.</p>
        <p>"We operate seven days a week 12 months a year," Mr. Calenti said.  "That's the problem with live product. You turn your back for a minute, and something will go wrong." Sweet Smell of Success</p>
        <p>Although retail sales account for just a small part of the business, the lobster, shrimp, clams and oysters that he sells by the piece attract hundreds of shoppers like Lisa Pincus, 28, a medical social worker from Manhattan, every weekend.</p>
        <p>"It's just a great place," Ms. Pincus said. "You drive up this dirt road. There's this dog that greets you, and the whole place smells like fish.</p>
        <p>"Whatever you want, they'll go in the back and chop it up. There's this woman wearing galoshes scaling fish. The scales are flying all over the place. She looks like she just got off a fishing boat."</p>
        <p>The woman in galoshes is Marie McEnery, who happens to be an owner of the farm and happens to be married to Mr. Calenti. She, too, wears faded stained jeans. And, oh yes, she, too, has a Ph.D. in marine biology from N.Y.U.</p>
        <p>"When I first met her she didn't know how to fillet fish," Mr. Calenti said. "She was a microbiologist. But then she made a mistake. She married me. Now she fillets fish."</p>
        <p>Ms. McEnery works seven-day weeks at the farm. But she says she has no regrets about leaving her research job at City University.</p>
        <p>"It was a nice life," she said on a break from scaling and filleting. "But this is rather nice, too, because we're outdoors all the time. And every day there's a wonderful sunset here." Litany of the Monger</p>
        <p>When asked what fresh fish were in stock that day, Ms. McEnery brushed a wisp of strawberry-blond hair from her forehead with the back of her hand and recited a litany familiar from 10 years of repetition.</p>
        <p>"I have flounder, I have halibut, I have mako shark, mahi-mahi, and I think I've got some bluefish, too," she said, feeling around in a fiberglass tank.</p>
        <p>She wiped her hands on her jeans.</p>
        <p>"I guess I would have become a different person if I were living in the city, clean all the time, and having my life nicely scheduled," she said.  "But I think I would have been a little bit boring, too."</p>
        <p>And she has come to know many customers, even though some visit just on summer weekends. "This is my social life," Ms. McEnery said. "I know these people by their first names. I even know a little about their families."</p>
        <p>Susan Fillichio, 28, a lawyer from Manhattan, bicycled up to the small gray building that is the front office.  She emerged a few minutes later with a bag of "chickens," small lobsters that weigh about a pound and a quarter.</p>
        <p>"We come here every weekend," she said. "I know I'm getting the freshest lobster on the Island, and it's a lot less expensive than anywhere else. It's the principle of the thing."</p>
        <p>Ms. Fillichio placed the bag in the basket on her bicycle, waved goodbye to Ms. McEnery and pedaled down the driveway past a small flock of noisy chickens. Real chickens. 'Being Dirty All the Time'</p>
        <p>The Fish Farm is also an orphanage of sorts for a number of animals that have found their way onto the property, including three dogs, four ducks, four geese, scores of chickens and a new baby deer.</p>
        <p>"One of the fellows went out on a delivery," Ms. McEnery said. "He calls from Montauk and says, 'Guess what, we have a new pet.' It's like having children. You wonder what they're going to bring in next."</p>
        <p>Ms. McEnery, who does not have children, said owning the farm and "being dirty all the time" had not made her life easier, "but it has made it a whole lot richer."</p>
        <p>She started work the day after she married and has not taken a real vacation, she said, adding, "This has been my honeymoon."</p>
        <p>Ms. McEnery looked down at her high galoshes and her torn jeans and then looked up, brushed her hair from her forehead with the back of her hand, and smiled, saying, "I guess I'm still on it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
