<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mobster, 67, Changes Plea To Guilty In Rao's Killing</title>
    <meta content="13RAO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/13/nyregion/13rao.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1596358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rao's (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Luchese Crime Family</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saulny, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barone, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Circelli, Albert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Serial Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rao's</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D81E3BF930A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mobster, 67, Changes Plea To Guilty In Rao's Killing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mobster, 67, Changes Plea to Guilty in Rao's Killing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Louis Barone changes plea to guilty in murder of Albert Circelli in Rao's restaurant, Manhattan, last December; will face 15 years in prison; other terms noted; both men have ties to Luchese crime family; sentencing is set for August (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The small-time mobster who had been accused of fatally shooting a fellow patron last year at Rao's, a famously exclusive Italian restaurant in East Harlem, in a dispute over singing pleaded guilty yesterday to manslaughter and assault in a deal that spares him the possibility of life in prison.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Louis Barone, appeared before Justice Budd G. Goodman in State Supreme Court in Manhattan and withdrew the plea of not guilty he had entered in January to two counts of second-degree murder, two counts of assault and a single charge of criminal possession of a weapon. If he had been found guilty of murder, he could have faced a prison term of 25 years to life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The small-time mobster who had been accused of fatally shooting a fellow patron last year at Rao's, a famously exclusive Italian restaurant in East Harlem, in a dispute over singing pleaded guilty yesterday to manslaughter and assault in a deal that spares him the possibility of life in prison.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The small-time mobster who had been accused of fatally shooting a fellow patron last year at Rao's, a famously exclusive Italian restaurant in East Harlem, in a dispute over singing pleaded guilty yesterday to manslaughter and assault in a deal that spares him the possibility of life in prison.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Louis Barone, appeared before Justice Budd G. Goodman in State Supreme Court in Manhattan and withdrew the plea of not guilty he had entered in January to two counts of second-degree murder, two counts of assault and a single charge of criminal possession of a weapon. If he had been found guilty of murder, he could have faced a prison term of 25 years to life.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the plea deal announced by Justice Goodman, Mr. Barone, 67, will face 15 years in prison for killing Albert Circelli, a concurrent five-year term for assaulting Albert W. Petraglia and three years of post-release supervision. He is scheduled to be sentenced on Aug. 12.</p>
        <p>Gary Fishman, an assistant in the Manhattan district attorney's office, told the court that the deal was the result of ''extensive negotiations,'' and that he had been in contact with Mr. Circelli's family. ''They are O.K. with the sentence,'' Mr. Fishman told Justice Goodman.</p>
        <p>Efforts to reach the Circelli family by telephone yesterday were unsuccessful. An answering service responding to the family's phone number was not accepting messages in the afternoon, and in the evening the number was no longer in service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barone was rolled into the courtroom in a wheelchair yesterday, and Mr. Fishman said that he had been suffering for at least a month from an old injury to his back.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barone said little during the proceeding. He answered yes when Justice Goodman asked if Louis Barone was his real name and if he had intended to seriously injure Mr. Circelli. Mr. Barone also answered yes when asked if he had assaulted Mr. Petraglia, who was shot in the foot.</p>
        <p>Investigators have said that Mr. Barone was a bookmaker for the Luchese crime family.</p>
        <p>After the proceeding, Thomas J. Lee, Mr. Barone's lawyer, said that he had no comment.</p>
        <p>The confrontation at Rao's, a restaurant where reservations can be hard to come by, happened on Dec. 22 when Mr. Barone objected to Mr. Circelli's criticism of the live entertainment, a rendition of ''Don't Rain on My Parade'' by Rena Strober, a musical actress whose credits include ''Les Misérables'' on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barone asked Mr. Circelli, who also had ties to the Luchese crime family, a couple of times to quiet down, unleashing a string of profanity from Mr. Circelli, the police said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Circelli, 37, rose from his seat to leave, Mr. Barone pulled out a gun and shot him in the back, the police said.</p>
        <p>In a handwritten statement to the police dated Dec. 23, Mr. Barone wrote that he had grown so angry that ''I had blood in my eyes.''</p>
        <p>''I shot him in the back,'' he wrote. ''The guy fell down face first near the doorway to the kitchen. While the guy was falling down I fired another shot at him. I snapped at that point, I went ballistic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Petraglia was apparently wounded unintentionally.</p>
        <p>In the statement, Mr. Barone said he had been carrying a gun because of the orange national security alert, referring to the government's color-coded system of terrorism warnings.</p>
        <p>Just after the shootings, according to papers released by prosecutors this year, Mr. Barone said to the police: ''I didn't do it! Did the guy die?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
