<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sehorn Being Sought By Falcons' Reeves</title>
    <meta content="23NFLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sehorn, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5DC123BF930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sehorn Being Sought By Falcons' Reeves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Falcons reportedly are considering signing New York Giants cornerback Jason Sehorn, restricted free agent, to offer sheet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants may soon have to fight off someone who knows them extremely well. What's at stake? One of the best young cornerbacks in the league, that's all.</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Falcons this week had internal discussions about signing Giants cornerback Jason Sehorn, a restricted free agent, to an offer sheet, according to several people within the Falcons' organization and other N.F.L. sources. Although the Giants have the right of first refusal and vow they will match any offer to keep Sehorn, the former Giants and current Falcons Coach Dan Reeves knows as well as anyone what it would take to keep Sehorn and what would make General Manager George Young blink.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants may soon have to fight off someone who knows them extremely well. What's at stake? One of the best young cornerbacks in the league, that's all.</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Falcons this week had internal discussions about signing Giants cornerback Jason Sehorn, a restricted free agent, to an offer sheet, according to several people within the Falcons' organization and other N.F.L. sources. Although the Giants have the right of first refusal and vow they will match any offer to keep Sehorn, the former Giants and current Falcons Coach Dan Reeves knows as well as anyone what it would take to keep Sehorn and what would make General Manager George Young blink.</p>
        <p>It is still a longshot for the Falcons to get Sehorn because he wants to stay in New York. But the Falcons spent this weekend thinking of ways to get him and one of the possibilities is something that truly irks Young -- voidable years. When a certain incentive is put in a contract, and if that incentive is reached, then years can be chopped off the back end of the deal and the player -- in this case, Sehorn -- would be an unrestricted free agent sooner.</p>
        <p>What the Falcons may do is what San Francisco did with running back Rodney Hampton at the end of last season. That is, compose a deal that would make it tough for the Giants to match and, if they did match, cost them tons of cap room.</p>
        <p>Sehorn has exploded into a top cornerback the last two seasons. Last year, he led the Giants with five interceptions (one returned for a touchdown). He is worth the millions he will get in the coming years either from the Giants or the Falcons or any other team. But don't think Reeves wouldn't want to steal him and thus stick it to his old team.</p>
        <p>Drastic Talk</p>
        <p>No team in Los Angeles means less money in the pockets of the National Football League. So, drastic times call for drastic actions. Or at least drastic talk.</p>
        <p>That is why the N.F.L. is considering the unprecedented use of its own resources to start up a team, in order to then sell it.</p>
        <p>Normally, a zillionaire would buy a franchise from the league for millions of dollars and build a team as he or she pleases. But in this latest scenario, the N.F.L. would hire a general manager, a coach, the staff, everyone. It would set up the team, run it for a short period of time and then sell it to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>The idea is that the league, by setting everything up, could ease any concerns a potential investor might have about buying a team in the Los Angeles area. The idea was discussed among some owners and league executives as recently as last week, but it probably will not happen for one reason: the lousy stadium situation. One need look no further than dusty Memorial Coliseum.</p>
        <p>Los Angeles is the second-largest market in the country, but it may have the worst stadium situation of any big market. When the N.F.L. Stadium Committee recently examined the issue there, it found that none of the existing facilities in the greater Los Angeles area were up to N.F.L. standards. That is one of the big reasons why no pro football team played in Los Angeles last season for the first time in 50 years.</p>
        <p>So, basically, Los Angeles will not get a team until it straightens out the stadium situation, even if the league wants to present a team to a prospective buyer with a red bow around it.</p>
        <p>Pace Puts On a Show</p>
        <p>Ohio State offensive tackle Orlando Pace worked out for N.F.L. teams earlier this month, and some scouts expected to see a player with a bad knee. There had been talk for weeks that Pace had damaged ligaments in his knee and that his draft value would plummet.</p>
        <p>But what the league got was a view of the best player in the draft. By far.</p>
        <p>Pace, at 300 pounds, was able to run about a 4.9-second 40-yard dash. That is extremely fast for an offensive lineman. All signs currently point to Pace being the first offensive lineman taken No. 1 over all since Southern Cal's Ron Yary in 1968.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to say where he will go,'' Giants General Manager George Young said. ''It all depends on a team's need. But he's a very good player.''</p>
        <p>Not Your Average Scout</p>
        <p>When Dallas Cowboys coaches and scouts work out free-agent wide receivers this off season, they are going to have an extra pair of eyes -- and one of the best throwing arms ever -- with them.</p>
        <p>In an unusual move, Dallas Coach Barry Switzer has asked quarterback Troy Aikman to help him work out receivers, even when it means traveling. And Aikman is all for it. Receiver is a critical position for the Cowboys, because they lack depth there and one never knows what lies ahead for Michael Irvin.</p>
        <p>And who knows, maybe some road trips and chats over nachos and beer might improve what has been a strained relationship between Switzer and Aikman.</p>
        <p>Just Business in New Orleans</p>
        <p>The New Orleans Saints' coach and team czar, Mike Ditka, recently hired the former NBC executive Terry O'Neil as his salary cap expert. Since O'Neil, a friend of Ditka's, has never worked with the salary cap before, some observers have speculated that O'Neil is really there to figure out how he and Ditka can put together a group and eventually buy the team. Certainly, O'Neil and the other cap generals have plenty to deal with, starting with the increasing disparity among the players between the haves and have-nots. One league official recently estimated that on half of the teams in the N.F.L., about 10 players make 50 percent of the team's payroll. The ratio is even worse for teams like Dallas that are full of superstars.</p>
        <p>The former Giants assistant George Henshaw turned down an offensive coordinator position with San Diego to take a job as co-offensive line and tight ends coach with the Houston Oilers. Henshaw did not want to move his family across the country. . . . The St. Louis Rams recently hired the former Philadelphia running back Wilbert Montgomery as a special assistant to baby-sit the troubled running back Lawrence Phillips. Then, a few days before he was to start the job, Montgomery was arrested in connection with an altercation with his wife at his house in Clementon, N.J.</p>
        <p>The former Giants linebacker Lawrence Taylor continues to make it known to teams that he wants a job working with players. Because of his past off-the-field troubles, however, few teams are willing to take a chance on him. . . . Soon after Bill Parcells departed, Bobby Grier was promoted from director of pro personnel to vice president of the Patriots. He is now one of the league's highest-ranking black executives.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
