<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chilling Balance Of Love And Evil</title>
    <meta content="23ROTH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FILM VIEW: After 25 Years, a Family Saga for the Ages" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FILM VIEW: After 25 Years, a Family Saga for the Ages"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Copola, Francis Ford</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Godfather, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6DA1038F930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chilling Balance Of Love And Evil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment by Edward Rothstein on digitally remastered release of 1972 film The Godfather; focuses on balance of love and evil in the film; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE ARE SOME MEMBERS of the Corleone crime family whose offers we couldn't refuse. Who could deny Clemenza a favor after watching him make spaghetti sauce?  Or turn down a request from Tom Hagen after seeing the empathy on his face as an old family friend is led away for his last limo ride?</p>
        <p>While watching Frances Ford Coppola's ''Godfather,'' we even feel sympathy for the thuggish Luca Brasi as an ice pick goes through his hand. And there is something charming in the way Clemenza keeps an errand for his wife in mind as he completes a particularly bloody job. ''Leave the gun,'' he calls to his colleague. ''Take the cannoli.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE ARE SOME MEMBERS of the Corleone crime family whose offers we couldn't refuse. Who could deny Clemenza a favor after watching him make spaghetti sauce?  Or turn down a request from Tom Hagen after seeing the empathy on his face as an old family friend is led away for his last limo ride?</p>
        <p>While watching Frances Ford Coppola's ''Godfather,'' we even feel sympathy for the thuggish Luca Brasi as an ice pick goes through his hand. And there is something charming in the way Clemenza keeps an errand for his wife in mind as he completes a particularly bloody job. ''Leave the gun,'' he calls to his colleague. ''Take the cannoli.''</p>
        <p>But as the 25-year-old film based on the Mario Puzo novel returns to theaters with a digitally remastered soundtrack and freshly minted prints, its juxtaposition of heartfelt loyalty and horrific vengeance, its mix of ethnic charms and coldblooded calculations can also cause chills. We may have learned the first time around what it means to sleep with the fishes and what lies under the Hollywood mogul's silk sheets, but we watch with ambivalent compulsion, covering the eyes while peering through the fingers.</p>
        <p>The film's mixture of family values and Family values, its combination of blood relations and relations based on blood, sent a shock through the somnolent movie business when it was first released in 1972. Despite Paramount's early support for Mr. Puzo, the studio got cold feet when it came time to make the movie. Then, Costa-Gavras, Peter Yates and Otto Preminger refused to direct.</p>
        <p>And when Mr. Coppola finally agreed (without a single moneymaking hit to his credit), he cast his old friends James Caan and Robert Duvall, a young unknown named Al Pacino and a volatile eccentric (Marlon Brando) as he worked on the screenplay, long-distance, with Mr. Puzo. As Harlan Lebo points out in his new book, ''The Godfather Legacy,'' which traces the making of the movie, Mr. Coppola and Mr. Pacino kept expecting to be dismissed as the filming went on.</p>
        <p>Then, of course, it became the  highest-grossing film of its time. The film seemed an extension of the era's headlines. As it was being made, one prominent mob leader, Joe Colombo, was shot; as it was shown, another, Joseph Gallo, was gunned down. Then life started imitating art in earnest: according to F.B.I. informants, members of the mob began to mimic the hand-kissing and dialogue of the fictional Corleones.</p>
        <p>The Godfather even spawned its own filmic Family. Mr. Coppola created a ''Godfather Part II'' in 1974 and a ''Godfather Part III'' in 1990. He repackaged the first two films into a ''Saga,'' for television, an expanded ''Epic'' for home video, and, finally, a chronologically remodeled ''Trilogy'' for laser disk and video release, each with its own insertions and deletions from original footage. The Italian mobster genre, in which wine and blood tend to flow freely, flourished with films like ''Prizzi's Honor,'' ''Goodfellas,'' ''Casino'' and most recently, ''Donnie Brasco,'' in which Mr. Pacino inverts the status of his ''Godfather'' role, playing a mob loser.</p>
        <p>The Italian-American Civil Rights League, founded by Joe Colombo, originally worried that ''The Godfather'' would engage in ethnic slurs. But as it turned out, at the heart of the movie is a forthright assertion of  ethnic identity as a source of strength. That is where we find the human side of the mob, its warmth and loyalty, its love of cannolis. Aside from the nature of the family business, the plot could be about an immigrant family trying to preserve its ethnic traditions. The Corleone family values are stalwart, asserting that security is not to be found in the chaos of the New World but in the Sicilian customs of the Old. Blood is a tighter bond than any other, the family a haven in a heartless world.</p>
        <p>The classic American gangster movie actually grew out of similar ethnic universes. The gangster, as in ''Little Caesar'' or ''The Public Enemy,'' is typically a second-generation American -- at that time, Irish or Italian -- who breaks away from Old World family ties. But instead of Americanization he chooses criminalization, creating his own world of allegiances. The traditional movie would then show the error of his ways, the disastrous consequences of rejecting the social compact.</p>
        <p>''The Godfather'' rejects that pattern. The Don's youngest and brightest son, Michael, returns from World War II in an Army uniform, full of hopes, determined to avoid the family business and its Sicilian origins. With his WASP fiancee, he watches supplicants enter his father's office, vowing to have no part of it. He will rebel into respectability and Americanization.</p>
        <p>But the Old World asserts its claims. The Don once objected to Michael's going off to war to risk his life for strangers; only the Family (or family) could merit such sacrifice. Michael finally seems to feel the same way. So do other Family members. ''I believe in America'' are the first words of the movie, spoken by the heavily-accented Italian undertaker to the Don. ''I went to the police like a good American.'' Still, like  Michael, he learns that blood is thicker than citizenship. In this gangster film, the rebel returns home and  Americanization is a failure.</p>
        <p>This cynical take on the American dream is closely connected to the period in which the film was made. While ''The Godfather'' was being filmed, the Vietnam War was going on, protests raged, and countercultural ideas were in full force. America was portrayed as unjust, morally  bankrupt. Mr. Coppola's twist was in turning an immigrant family into America's nemesis: the Corleones often take on a heroic cast.</p>
        <p>The movie's sequels go even further. Family life may not be all Michael expected, yet the surrounding world is even worse. In ''The Godfather, Part II,'' senators and businessmen are just varieties of American mobsters. In ''The Godfather, Part III'' even the Vatican is rotten with graft and murder.</p>
        <p>MR. COPPOLA GOES TOO  far, of course, so everything becomes a mob-ridden morass. But the first movie is so powerful because he creates an uneasy balance: without dismissing this family romance, he laces it with horrific burdens. The family promises to protect, defend and preserve its members against all disruptions from outside and at all costs.</p>
        <p>In crime as in life, however, it is impossible; generations change; the cost is too high, the pressures too great; rot seeps in. Respect can become just a currency upon which one's life depends; obedience and loyalty can become the requisites of love. Those warm bonds of the Corleone families hide jealousies and lies, betrayals and transgressions. Under the sentimental surfaces roil barely controlled forces; the haven can seem a hell.</p>
        <p>This doesn't turn us against the family because we seem too close to them, as if they were our own relations. They are also, in part, right about the dangers they face. Mr. Coppola keeps contradictory feelings swirling about, so the film becomes what its producer, Albert S. Ruddy, initially envisioned: ''an ice-blue terrifying movie about people you love.</p>
        <p>The terror is the terror of betrayal; the love keeps asserting that there is hope. And in this, ''The Godfather'' hit upon one of the great themes of American life in this century the challenge of becoming American. This challenge lies underneath the plots of many gangster films; it is even one of the issues lying behind the formation of ethnic gangs in immigrant communities. How is the passage to be made from family to society, from ethnic culture to American life, from the bonds of blood to bonds of citizenship?</p>
        <p>Michael thinks he can do it, but he fails. Mr. Coppola eventually seems to argue that it isn't worth doing. And the movie shows us, again and again, the tragedy implicit in trying and in not trying, the tenuous nature of any social order, the evils that can erupt whether rushing ahead or desperately trying to remain behind.</p>
        <p>FILM VIEW: After 25 Years, a Family Saga for the Ages</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
