<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Red Sox May Be Classified as a Lost Cause Before the Start of the Season</title>
    <meta content="23BASE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vaughn, Mo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canseco, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDE123BF930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Red Sox May Be Classified as a Lost Cause Before the Start of the Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boston Red Sox first baseman Mo Vaughn expresses concern about direction in which team is headed after losing Roger Clemens and Jose Canseco; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mo Vaughn tries hard to shackle his thoughts, but sometimes they just happen, like a home run that he doesn't try to hit.</p>
        <p>Vaughn is the cornerstone of a Red Sox team that is like a lost soul, meandering through life with no sense of direction. If Point A is where they are and Point B is where they want to be, the Red Sox seem to have no clue how to get there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mo Vaughn tries hard to shackle his thoughts, but sometimes they just happen, like a home run that he doesn't try to hit.</p>
        <p>Vaughn is the cornerstone of a Red Sox team that is like a lost soul, meandering through life with no sense of direction. If Point A is where they are and Point B is where they want to be, the Red Sox seem to have no clue how to get there.</p>
        <p>The suggestion that the organization seems to go out of its way to do weird things and undermine the cohesiveness of the team elicited insight into the thinking that Vaughn is trying not to exhibit publicly.</p>
        <p>''What you see is an observation that many people have made,'' the bulky first baseman said recently in Bradenton, Fla. ''That's for the general manager to clear up and if he can't, that's the way things look, that's the way things are.''</p>
        <p>Are the Red Sox heading into what they know will be a lost season? ''You never view it as a lost cause,'' he said, ''but you know the facts.''</p>
        <p>One fact is the Red Sox plan to use Wilfredo Cordero in left field. The Red Sox acquired him as a shortstop from Montreal 14 months ago, switched him to second base and discovered he couldn't play it. Now, when he has recovered from a muscle strain, he will be the left fielder, the latest in the Red Sox lineage of Ted Williams to Carl Yastrzemski to Jim Rice to Mike Greenwell.</p>
        <p>Another fact is the belated, though long-planned, decision to bump John Valentin to second base so that Nomar Garciaparra, a good-looking rookie, can play shortstop. The mid-training-camp move led to a two-day cooling-off period and a $500 fine for Valentin. It could also result in a trade, with the Yankees being an interested party and the No. 1 team in Valentin's heart. If he has to play second, he figures, it might as well be somewhere he wants to be.</p>
        <p>But Boston General Manager Dan Duquette said Valentin would be the team's opening-day second baseman. Furthermore, he said in response to questions about potential trouble: ''We've had a good work atmosphere in camp. We're making pretty good progress on putting our team together.''</p>
        <p>After their winter moves, the Red Sox needed reconstruction.</p>
        <p>''You lose Roger Clemens, you lose Jose Canseco, you take away Mike Greenwell,'' Vaughn said, reciting the absentees from 1996. ''In 1995, we won the pennant. It seemed as if we were two, three players away from being right there. All of a sudden you look back and we're going in a different direction. I don't know which direction this team is going to go in, but I can't worry about that as a ballplayer. I have to go out and do my job.</p>
        <p>''It's a tough situation, no doubt about it. As a professional, you know you have a job to do and you go and do it. What you can control, you control. What you can't, you can't. We've got a lot of question marks, things that have to be answered. I don't think as a professional you can let uneasiness affect you. You have to go out and do the job. That's what I'll try to do.''</p>
        <p>Valentin has no control over his career because he is two years from eligibility for free agency. His days with the Red Sox are certain not to exceed that time, because of the way they have taken his position away and because of their refusal to offer him a multiyear contract.</p>
        <p>Duquette has said he does not like multiyear contracts because players' performances tend to slack off. But Vaughn followed his most-valuable-player performance of 1995 by signing a three-year, $18.6 million contract -- and achieved career highs in nearly every offensive category last season.</p>
        <p>Valentin and his lawyer, Richard Moss, who has filed a grievance over the $500 fine, have taken the position that they will no longer negotiate with the Red Sox. They said they would go to salary arbitration next winter and free agency the following winter.</p>
        <p>Asked if he would rather not be with the Red Sox, Valentin said: ''I played shortstop my whole career. I still think I can play shortstop for anybody, but it doesn't look like I'm going to go anywhere else at this point. Once I put on my uniform, it's more being a professional. I have a lot of pride. So I'm going to do whatever I can to try to win and try to help this club win. As long as I'm here, I'm going to do that. That's the approach I'm taking. Forget about what has happened. Kind of turn the page and go from there.''</p>
        <p>That's what Clemens, who signed with Toronto as a free agent, said when he was asked about the place he called home for 13 years. ''As my wife says, it's time to move on,'' the pitcher said. ''We're not living in anybody else's misery.''</p>
        <p>Fregosi's Forecast for Giants</p>
        <p>Jim Fregosi, dismissed after last season as the Phillies' manager, is scouting in spring training for the San Francisco Giants. He apparently has grander ambitions, however.</p>
        <p>A scout for another team said Fregosi has been telling his counterparts with other teams that he is going to become the Giants' manager by June 1. That's the job Dusty Baker has held for the last four seasons and the one he is under contract to perform the next two seasons.</p>
        <p>But the Giants have finished in last place in the National League West the last two years, and their prospects do not look good for a higher finish this year. Because of injuries and personnel, those finishes might be beyond Baker's control. But Fregosi has firsthand knowledge of what happens to managers who finish last.</p>
        <p>Fregosi may have additional reason to expect a change. Brian Sabean, the Giants' new general manager, traded Matt Williams, a Baker favorite, and Baker did not publicly endorse the deal. Baker was the choice of the owner, Peter Magowan, who preferred him over Tom Trebelhorn, the choice of Bob Quinn, then the general manager. But Fregosi is said to be close with Magowan.</p>
        <p>The Writing on the Wall</p>
        <p>The words are not exactly written in stone, but they are posted on the cement-block wall of Cincinnati's spring clubhouse:</p>
        <p>''Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa at the annual baseball writers' dinner: 'I guarantee you we will not relinquish the Central Division.'</p>
        <p>''Then, at a luncheon the next day, he said: 'Everybody here from the media . . . you're going to be covering a championship club in 1997.' ''</p>
        <p>Ray Knight, the Reds' fiercely proud manager, said he did not take La Russa's admittedly foolish bravado personally, but he acknowledged: ''I didn't like it. It gave me a flash of anger because of the respect factor. They're a good ball club, but they're certainly not a club that scares me, that is so dominant that they can't be beaten.''</p>
        <p>La Russa said he got caught up in the enthusiasm of the moment, or moments, and did not need long to realize he overdid it.</p>
        <p>''I'm not saying it was a real bright thing to do,'' La Russa said. ''The only thing I didn't like about it is I've made a career of respecting the game and opponents, and that to me was disrespectful. If somebody had said that, I would have said, 'What about us?' That's the only thing that bothered me. That's more disrespectful than I think is right.''</p>
        <p>Knight said he and La Russa have spoken about the impromptu remarks. ''I told him he made it real easy for me,'' Knight said, alluding to his opening spring training address to the players. ''I had a theme and it went right along with it.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''It sends the same signal as a knockdown pitch or taking someone out at second base. It's just a challenge: 'We're the champions. We're challenging you to come get us.' Well, let's pack it up and get ready to go after it. And we're going to go after it.''</p>
        <p>Players to Be Named Later</p>
        <p>Doug Brocail has been named the opening-day starter for the pitching-poor Detroit Tigers. He holds another distinction. He was the only player involved in the two biggest trades in decades, the 12-player swap between San Diego and Houston in 1994 and the 9-player deal between Houston and Detroit last December.</p>
        <p>For his trouble, he gets a pop quiz. Can Brocail name all of the players in both trades?</p>
        <p>''Can I name them? I can name them,'' Brocail said confidently, then began with the first trade. ''There's me, Craig Shipley, Phil Plantier, Ricky Gutierrez. . . .'' Uh-oh.</p>
        <p>''I can't name them,'' he conceded, having omitted Derek Bell and Pedro A. Martinez from the group that went to Houston. Then he tried the players who went to San Diego. ''Ken Caminiti, Steve Finley, Roberto Petagine -- that's all I can remember over there.'' He forgot Andujar Cedeno, Brian Williams and Sean Fesh.</p>
        <p>Then he tried the recent trade. ''I know Brad Ausmus went. The other guys, I think -- did C. J. Nitkowski go? I have a hard enough time remembering who came over here.</p>
        <p>''We were going through it the other day. Me, Jonesy, that's bad . . . I don't remember . . . oh, Brian Hunter and, uh, I'm really . . . oh, Orlando Miller, yeah. Now how many guys went over to Houston? Six?''</p>
        <p>No, five. Ausmus, Nitkowski, Jose Lima, Trever Miller and Daryle Ward. Going with Brocail to Detroit were Hunter, Orlando Miller and Todd Jones along with cash.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't hit you that wow, this is one of the biggest trades in the last umpteen years,'' Brocail said. ''Then you sit down and look at it and say, man, I've been involved in something that's absolutely huge.''</p>
        <p>Twice.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
