<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slow Start, But the Devils Roll in the End</title>
    <meta content="23DEVI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOCKEY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Penguins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Modoono, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DF133BF930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slow Start, But the Devils Roll in the End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL MODOONO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Modoono, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, March 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils defeat Pittsburgh Penguins, 3-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A game that threatened to be dominated first by the Pittsburgh Penguins and then by their public address announcer, wound up being taken over -- and won -- by the Devils today at the Civic Arena.</p>
        <p>A standing-room-only crowd of 17,261 showed up early, but the Devils did not, falling behind by two goals before rallying in the third period, and winning by 3-2. The victory put the Devils in a first-place tie with Philadelphia in the Eastern Conference, ended a two-game streak without a victory and might have sent a message.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A game that threatened to be dominated first by the Pittsburgh Penguins and then by their public address announcer, wound up being taken over -- and won -- by the Devils today at the Civic Arena.</p>
        <p>A standing-room-only crowd of 17,261 showed up early, but the Devils did not, falling behind by two goals before rallying in the third period, and winning by 3-2. The victory put the Devils in a first-place tie with Philadelphia in the Eastern Conference, ended a two-game streak without a victory and might have sent a message.</p>
        <p>''We're a team to be reckoned with,'' Devils defenseman Dave Ellett said.</p>
        <p>Actually, by Coach Jacques Lemaire's reckoning, early in the game the Devils looked less like a Stanley Cup contender than a harried commuter forced to wake up on a Monday morning after a long, sweet weekend. ''You don't want to go to work,'' Lemaire said. ''That's how we looked. Everybody had a tough time at the start.''</p>
        <p>The Devils paid for their early lethargy, falling behind, 1-0, on a goal by Dave Roche at 9 minutes 13 seconds of the first period.</p>
        <p>Greg Johnson made the game 2-0 at 2:01 of the second, after Stu Barnes embarrassed New Jersey center Bobby Holik by going around him to set up Johnson. ''I just got caught flat-footed,'' Holik said. ''It was not a good play by me.''</p>
        <p>But Lemaire had no interest in blaming Holik, who wound up scoring the game-winning goal at 11:58 of the third period after a Penguin defensive breakdown. To Lemaire, just about every Devil ''didn't start that good.''</p>
        <p>The Penguins, who were playing without Jaromir Jagr and Petr Nedved, were looking for their third consecutive victory at home, after playing through a bad couple of months that culminated in General Manager Craig Patrick's replacing Eddie Johnston as coach.</p>
        <p>''I thought when we were up in the third period, we should have been able to come out with the 2 points,'' said Mario Lemieux, who very likely played his last regular-season game against the Devils today, a team he has scored more against than any other in his National Hockey League career. ''But that's a great team with a great system and a great coach. They're tough to beat.''</p>
        <p>But neither team could beat the replay rule, which dominated the second period and nullified one goal for each team. The Devils lost a Randy McKay goal when it was determined he was in the crease too soon, while a possible Barnes goal by Pittsburgh was not allowed because no camera angle could show whether the puck had crossed the goal line before Martin Brodeur smothered it.</p>
        <p>The Devils had no problem with either decision. Their complaint was with the way the goals were reviewed. ''A player can't ask for a replay,'' Devils defenseman Scott Stevens said. ''It's a referee's decision.''</p>
        <p>The Devils decided the matter on their own with a second-period goal by Dave Andreychuk (his 25th), and third-period scores by Ellett and Holik. By that time, however, their early tendencies had long since disappeared.</p>
        <p>''We were a little cautious at the beginning,'' Andreychuk said. ''We picked up a bit in the second, and we took the play to them in the third.''</p>
        <p>That is not something the Devils can necessarily count on doing if the two teams meet in the playoffs. Without Jagr, Nedved and goalie Ken Wregget, the Penguins are not nearly as fearsome as they might be later this spring.</p>
        <p>''We were a little short today, especially offensively,'' said Lemieux, who was kept off the scoreboard by the Devils. ''The makeup of the team was short of talent and when you are, you make mistakes like we made in the third period.''</p>
        <p>The Penguins are a team able to compensate for mistakes by great individual offensive play. Today, that was not possible, with their biggest threats being Barnes, Johnson and Ed Olczyk.</p>
        <p>''They're totally different with Jagr there,'' Stevens said. ''We've got to understand that.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
