<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Windowsill Friends, Awesome in the Tropics</title>
    <meta content="CNGARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="GARDENING" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEFDA173BF930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Windowsill Friends, Awesome in the Tropics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NORTHERN gardeners who head to tropical climates for a time should have no problems identifying many of the plants growing there. The reason? Most of the popular tropical landscape plants have become house plants in New England.</p>
        <p>This fact should give home gardeners vital clues as to the culture of the tropicals when they are confined to a pot. Some take more kindly to indoor life than others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NORTHERN gardeners who head to tropical climates for a time should have no problems identifying many of the plants growing there. The reason? Most of the popular tropical landscape plants have become house plants in New England.</p>
        <p>This fact should give home gardeners vital clues as to the culture of the tropicals when they are confined to a pot. Some take more kindly to indoor life than others.</p>
        <p>There is schefflera, for instance,  probably one of the easiest to grow. Schefflera, often called umbrella plant, thrives indoors in minimum light, and really takes off when it is given brighter light and frequent watering and feeding.</p>
        <p>Even with the roots confined, those who grow this indoor tree at home tend to find within a year or two that the plant is too huge for its space. One house plant reference states that the tree can grow almost a foot a year. When this happens, the schefflera is either tossed out in search of a smaller specimen or given to a friend who has a home with a high ceiling. In another popular use, mall shoppers quite often see these fast-growers providing greenery.</p>
        <p>However, when this plant, which originated in Australia, is grown outdoors in warmer climates, it flourishes to the point of liability. It spreads its root system hither and yon, like a willow tree, finally arriving at a size where digging it up is the only answer. Also, it grows so tall, frequent cutting back is needed.</p>
        <p>Those who are quite used to seeing the trailing vines of the all too common philodendron at home can sometimes be taken back when confronted with the huge treelike form of Philodendron selloum in warmer climates. When this rather elegant big leaved plant, which hails from the forests of Brazil, has enough room to spread out its deeply lobed foliage, it provides a junglelike effect.</p>
        <p>Northern growers are generally confined to the smaller growing philodendrons that thrive in pots. The greenhouse trade has developed many such plants which suit interior decor needs. Philodendron means tree loving, which provides important clues for successful growing: moderate light and adequate air moisture.</p>
        <p>In the North, lilacs and daphnes are often planted near the door because the scent from these lovely shrubs can fill the air and waft into the home. New Englanders just put them in the ground and let them go.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Northern gardeners must coddle gardenias, keeping them cool and misting them every once in a while to bring on the reward of flowers. By contrast, those in tropical climes grow gardenias as shrubs, hedges or even specimen plants. They bloom freely with a little modest care, provided they have a generous amount of fertilizer once a year. Gardenias thrive so well, the plants have to be pruned just to keep them in line and in extreme cases, alleviate what can become an overwhelming aroma.</p>
        <p>Two other popular shrubs used in the tropical climates for landscape effect are podocarpus and pittosporum. These excellent plants with their good foliage have become popular in the North as well, since they  take kindly to pot culture and can even be pruned judiciously.</p>
        <p>Another well-known tropical plant, croton, is choice for the color of its foliage. In the tropics and in New England alike, this plant proves to be rather difficult. In New England,  mealybugs have a fine time feeding on it, trapped as it is in a pot. In the tropics, croton grows too well and eventually becomes a long-stemmed, leaf-poor landscape liability.</p>
        <p>All members of the vast and versatile dracaena clan can be utilized North or South for indoor culture.  The plants adapt exceedingly well to a long life growing indoors as a house plant. The only facet of their life that possibly changes when they are set outdoors is their ability to attain considerable size.</p>
        <p>In a tropical setting, dracaenas fit in nicely outside and become landscape assets. In the home, all dracaenas adapt well, even to low light levels, provided they are not neglected.</p>
        <p>All of this comparison is just another way of saying that it is the nature of plants to grow. If a plant becomes too big for the pot, it is merely indicating that it is thriving naturally and wants to be more of what nature intended it to be: a full-grown plant.</p>
        <p>Too often house plant hobbyists in the North complain that their plants have grown too big. Or they lament that the lovely specimen purchased three years ago is beginning to wane, the leaves are getting yellow and ''I just have no luck with plants.''</p>
        <p>Remember where many of these popular plants came from. Then think through why they are outgrowing their spaces. Fortunately, greenhouse growers have done much of the needed research and have been able to provide some excellent foliage plants that can do quite well when confined to pot culture.</p>
        <p>But it is not always fair to blame the grower for inabilities. Quite often plants are just doing what they are supposed to do: grow.</p>
        <p>GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
