<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q. &amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="23QAQA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2DD163BF930A15750C0A961958260" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q. &amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Housing questions and answers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rejecting Too-Smart Tenant</p>
        <p>Q. A Feb. 23 opinion essay in The City section of The New York Times entitled ''No Dogs, or Lawyers, Need Apply'' indicates that it is common practice for New York City landlords to refuse to rent to lawyers. The article says that although the city's Administrative Code bans housing discrimination based on occupation, a 1977 court decision allows a landlord to refuse to rent to ''intelligent persons, aware of their rights, who may give him trouble in the future.''  Is this really the law? . . . Brooke Tawkins, the Bronx.</p>
        <p>A. Sherwin Belkin, a Manhattan lawyer who specializes in landlord-tenant matters, said that New York's housing discrimination laws prohibit discriminatory practices that are predicated upon certain ''suspect classifications'' of people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rejecting Too-Smart Tenant</p>
        <p>Q. A Feb. 23 opinion essay in The City section of The New York Times entitled ''No Dogs, or Lawyers, Need Apply'' indicates that it is common practice for New York City landlords to refuse to rent to lawyers. The article says that although the city's Administrative Code bans housing discrimination based on occupation, a 1977 court decision allows a landlord to refuse to rent to ''intelligent persons, aware of their rights, who may give him trouble in the future.''  Is this really the law? . . . Brooke Tawkins, the Bronx.</p>
        <p>A. Sherwin Belkin, a Manhattan lawyer who specializes in landlord-tenant matters, said that New York's housing discrimination laws prohibit discriminatory practices that are predicated upon certain ''suspect classifications'' of people.</p>
        <p>Generally, Mr. Belkin said, an owner will run afoul of anti-discrimination laws if rental decisions are predicated upon race, creed, color, national origin, gender, age, disability, sexual orientation, marital status, citizenship status or the presence of children.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Belkin said, the New York City Administrative Code prohibits discrimination on the basis of occupation -- a prohibition promulgated subsequent to the case referred to by the letter-writer.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, while a landlord may not refuse to rent to a person simply because that person is a lawyer, there does not appear to be any prohibition against a landlord's refusing to rent to a person simply because that person is smart.</p>
        <p>''An owner does not lose all decision-making authority or discretion over the leasing of his or her apartments,'' Mr. Belkin said. ''The owner's decision can even be illogical or foolish.''</p>
        <p>Status of Diplomats In Business in City</p>
        <p>Q. A foreign diplomat and his wife want to rent a store from me in Manhattan for the purpose of conducting a jewelry business there. Do diplomats and their spouses have immunity in cases where they engage in commercial activities unrelated to diplomacy? . . . Deborah T. Vanz, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A. ''Foreign diplomats should not be moonlighting in the host country,'' said Bradford Trebach, a Bronx lawyer who concentrates in international affairs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trebach said that pursuant to the 1961 Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations, diplomats have a duty to abstain from practicing for personal profit any professional or commercial activities in the host country.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, he said, the broad immunity that foreign diplomats typically enjoy does not extend to civil cases related to their operation of a professional or commercial enterprise in this country.</p>
        <p>''If a foreign diplomat and his wife rent a store in Manhattan so they can operate a private business they would be subject to the same civil process as anyone else who engages in such activity,'' Mr. Trebach said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trebach noted that the Vienna Convention did not prohibit a member of a foreign diplomat's family from engaging in remunerative work here. However, he said, if such activities are being performed without the prior consent of the United States Government, they would be viewed as an abuse of the family member's visa status.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, if a family member of a foreign diplomat has been authorized to work in this country, that individual should be able to produce an authorization document issued by the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
