<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four-Day Prescription: Europe's Workweek Debate -- A special report.; Europeans Ponder Working Less So More of Them Can Have Jobs</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="651586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORKING HOURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIRING AND PROMOTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LARROUTUROU, PIERRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF123BF931A15752C1A965958260" item-length="2691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four-Day Prescription: Europe's Workweek Debate -- A special report.; Europeans Ponder Working Less So More of Them Can Have Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COHEN, ROGER</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Nov. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>France, it is sometimes said, has little inclination for reform and a penchant for revolution. True to its reputation, the country has suddenly become obsessed by a revolutionary idea: a wholesale switch to a four-day workweek that would, its proponents insist, slash unemployment, improve family life and bring new hope to a disenchanted society.</p>
        <p>The proposal's chief advocate, Pierre Larrouturou, 29, a consultant for the accounting firm Arthur Andersen, has achieved such fame in recent weeks that he is now known simply as "le gourou." Swept from Elysee Palace to Government offices to television talk shows, Mr. Larrouturou has tapped what appears to be a thirst for a radical solution at a time of political torpor and economic recession in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>France, it is sometimes said, has little inclination for reform and a penchant for revolution. True to its reputation, the country has suddenly become obsessed by a revolutionary idea: a wholesale switch to a four-day workweek that would, its proponents insist, slash unemployment, improve family life and bring new hope to a disenchanted society.</p>
        <p>The proposal's chief advocate, Pierre Larrouturou, 29, a consultant for the accounting firm Arthur Andersen, has achieved such fame in recent weeks that he is now known simply as "le gourou." Swept from Elysee Palace to Government offices to television talk shows, Mr. Larrouturou has tapped what appears to be a thirst for a radical solution at a time of political torpor and economic recession in Europe.</p>
        <p>"The four-day week can create two million jobs without sacrificing competitiveness," Mr. Larrouturou said in an interview. "The alternative, more and more people in Europe perceive, is creeping despair." Resonance Beyond France</p>
        <p>Although the debate has been most intense in France, the four-day week has also struck a deep chord in Germany and other Western European countries reeling from high unemployment.</p>
        <p>Companies like Volkswagen see the shorter workweek as an emergency measure to save thousands of jobs, while some politicians promote it as a "New Deal" to transform and inspire societies beset by economic insecurity.</p>
        <p>In Italy, unions are pushing the slogan "Lavorare meno, lavorare tutti" -- "Work less, and everyone works."</p>
        <p>The Larrouturou gospel in France is based on a switch, proposed for 1996, from the nation's current five-day, 39-hour workweek to a four-day, 33-hour week; an average 5 percent reduction in salary; a 10 percent increase in the private work force to create two million new jobs, and tax cuts and incentives to compensate companies for the added costs. It also offers a rosy vision of the plan's economic effects, from lower absenteeism and higher productivity to a more motivated society. It May Seem a Dream</p>
        <p>With Western Europeans working fewer hours than their competitors in the United States and Japan, let alone South Korea and Singapore, the four-day week may seem a wistful dream rather than a serious model for change in French or European society.</p>
        <p>Germans already work a 37-hour week with six weeks of paid vacation -- "by far the shortest working hours among industrialized nations," Klaus Friedrich, chief economist for Dresdner Bank, said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, politicians of varying political stripes are jumping on the bandwagon. A French parliamentary committee voted last week in favor of experimenting with a 33.3-hour workweek at companies that increase their staffs by 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Despite talk of a progressive New Deal, some workers fear that companies will use the four-day week to exploit employees without creating any new jobs. Others dismiss Mr. Larrouturou's plan as illogical. "The 32-hour week is a utopia and a joke," said Gerard Grannec, 39, a technician at the A.M.P. electronics plant in the northwestern Paris suburb of Pontoise. "You reduce working time and wages. But what is the worker going to do with his extra leisure time if he has no money? And where's this supposed boost to consumption going to come from if people are broke?" The Challenge  Desperate People Look for Answers</p>
        <p>Behind the growing fascination with a shorter workweek is a combination of economic pressure and psychological angst.</p>
        <p>A long recession and a steady surge in European unemployment have made many people insecure. At the same time, the inexorable advance of technology, global competition and leaner production methods has created what the French sociologist Edgar Morin called "a crisis of the future in which people no longer believe things will get better and are looking desperately for alternatives."</p>
        <p>Computers, robots and other machines, workers and executives say, will go on replacing people, European companies will go on moving to Singapore or India, where labor is much cheaper, and instant global communications will keep on showing up the high cost of doing business in Europe, with its costly social welfare programs.</p>
        <p>More than 1.5 million people in the European Community have lost their jobs in the last year in a process that a leading Gaullist, Philippe Seguin, has called "a social Munich." More than 11.3 percent, or 19.1 million people, in the 12 European Community countries are unemployed.</p>
        <p>In France, the jobless rate stands at 11.8 percent, almost double the rate in the United States. In Germany, the council of economic advisers told Chancellor Helmut Kohl this month that unemployment would rise to four million, or 10 percent of the work force, next year, from the current level of 3.5 million or 9.2 percent.</p>
        <p>With the drumbeat of layoffs from such industry giants as Philips, Daimler-Benz and Michelin continuing, any consultant giving a European politician advice for a campaign today could be very succinct: "It's jobs, stupid."</p>
        <p>"Jobs are disappearing so fast, people are saying we must look for new solutions," said Alain Touraine, a French political scientist. "The French could not give a damn today if they are governed by the left or the right; what matters is unemployment."</p>
        <p>In Germany, too, a conviction has taken hold among many people that Europe's emergence from recession, repeatedly postponed and now projected for the second half of 1994, will not restore the lost jobs. Most economists estimate that with 3 percent growth, few if any jobs would be created. With 4.5 percent growth, new jobs would result, but no one expects such an economic spurt in the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>"I am skeptical that jobs will come back," said Berthold Huber, the chief wage negotiator for the the huge I. G. Metall labor union, representing 3.2 million German metalworkers. "About four million unemployed are going to remain in Germany, and that is a major problem for democracy. So we have to at least look at the shorter working week." Some Answers In an Ill Wind, Different Tacks</p>
        <p>Behind the four-day idea lurk a lot of different notions. They range from emergency steps like Volkswagen's recent proposal to avoid mass dismissals by switching to a four-day week with 20 percent less pay to idealistic visions of societies turning their backs on the scourge of frenetic global competition in favor of a more balanced way of life. In between those extremes, many companies have already acted.</p>
        <p>At the Regensburg plant of the German automaker B.M.W., for example, a four-day, 36-hour week has existed since 1990.</p>
        <p>The idea behind the plan was for individuals to work less but more flexibly, enabling machinery to operate for longer periods. Thus a Saturday shift, generally taboo in Germany, was introduced and weekday shifts were extended from eight to nine hours. Although wages were unchanged, productivity gains more than offset the cost of hiring more people, B.M.W. says.</p>
        <p>"I was skeptical at first, particularly about working Saturday, because that is when I play soccer for my local team," said Otto Sollner, a production line worker. "But now I appreciate the advantages, particularly the intermittent long weekends."</p>
        <p>Similar changes have taken place this year at the French subsidiaries of the American computer manufacturers Digital Equipment and Hewlett-Packard. Hit by the recession and squeezed margins in the worldwide computer market, they faced the alternatives of layoffs or a sweeping reorganization of working schedules.</p>
        <p>"The choice we put to workers at our Grenoble plant was simple: either change working habits, or we relocate to Singapore and all the jobs will be lost," said Marese Cosseron, a spokeswoman for Hewlett-Packard.</p>
        <p>The result was an entirely new work structure that has tripled production at the plant, which produces microcomputer components. No employee works more than four days a week, but the plant is kept open 24 hours a day, seven days a week, instead of the previous five days.</p>
        <p>Working weeks now vary from 26 hours and 50 minutes for employees working night and weekend shifts, 33 hours and 30 minutes for those on afternoon shifts and 34 hours and 40 minutes for those on morning shifts. All 250 employees, including 40 new ones, are paid on the basis of the plant's former week of 37 hours and 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>"We are pleased by experiments like Hewlett-Packard," said Gilbert Fournier, a senior official of the French Confederation of Democratic Labor, a moderate union. "We are convinced that shorter working weeks that also leave machinery functioning as long or longer represent a key to creating employment in Europe."</p>
        <p>The Communist union, the General Labor Confederation, opposes such flexibility on the basis that it would institutionalize night and weekend work without overtime. "Flexibility is often just a code word for companies to cut wage costs by getting people to work when they like without overtime," Chantal Rey, a union official, said.</p>
        <p>Digital introduced a different plan earlier this year involving salary cuts averaging about 7 percent for people choosing a four-day week. With 530 employees of a total of 4,000 opting for the plan, 90 jobs that were to have been cut were saved.</p>
        <p>"A large number of people were interested in working less and being paid less," Robin Ashmore, a Digital spokeswoman, said. "Young people want to divide their lives differently and have more leisure time."</p>
        <p>Digital says its productivity has not suffered. The Message  Some Buy Idea, Others Don't</p>
        <p>Martine Dessemond, a personnel manager at Digital who opted for the four-day week, said she was now spending more time with her grandson and had started a small consulting business in her spare time.</p>
        <p>"I am more efficient in my work, less stressed and speedy outside it, and have not seen my life style much affected by the pay cut," she added. "But I am convinced the four-day week must be negotiated business by business rather than be the object of some grand reform or government diktat."</p>
        <p>The idea has stirred far less interest among British companies, which are wary of managed solutions to unemployment and generally convinced that excessive regulation lies at the core of Europe's economic problems.</p>
        <p>But in France, Michel Rocard, who will be the Socialist Party's presidential candidate in 1995, sees the germ of a social revolution in the four-day week, a means, as he has said, "to jump-start society."</p>
        <p>In this vision, the four-day week would be a way to live differently, an exchange of slightly lower pay for greater personal freedom, a means to enjoy the benefits of automation rather than suffer its ravages, a vote for solidarity over ever more grueling economic competition, a fresh start for a disaffected Continent.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Larrouturou has carried this message to Anne Lauvergeon, the economic adviser to President Francois Mitterrand. The President later spoke favorably of the four-day week. The "gourou" suggests that the reform be put to the French in a referendum or as a theme of the 1995 presidential election. Pro and Con  The Numbers: Do They Add Up?</p>
        <p>As envisaged in Mr. Larrouturou's 54-page manifesto, everything goes swimmingly. After national legislative approval, French companies move to a four-day week in 1996 and take on 10 percent more staff. Wages cuts vary from 3 percent for the lowest paid to 8 percent for higher salaries, with an average of 5 percent.</p>
        <p>Young technocrats from the best French state schools would help companies prepare their reorganization, including the introduction of profit-sharing schemes that would eventually help compensate for pay cuts.</p>
        <p>To offset increased corporate costs, the state assumes the financing of unemployment insurance, suppressing the 8.8 percent payroll tax. On top of the 5 percent wage cut and an estimated 5 percent productivity gain through the reorganization of work shifts, this should make the revolution "cost neutral" for companies, Mr. Larrouturou estimates.</p>
        <p>Paradoxical as it may seem, the theory is that companies will not actually face higher costs if more people work less.</p>
        <p>Equally miraculously, the state does not suffer financially from abolishing the unemployment payroll tax, which is expected to bring in $21.8 billion this year. Rather, with two million fewer people unemployed, the state would save about $27.5 billion in payments that would have gone to people without jobs, and thereby come out ahead. With more people working, the economy would supposedly rebound, widening the tax base.</p>
        <p>Yet among five workers interviewed at the A.M.P. electronics plant in Pontoise, only one worker, Michel Angard, said he would support the idea -- "providing it means a guaranteed end to layoffs and my salary cut does not exceed 1 percent."</p>
        <p>Mr. Grannec, the technician, said: "Companies will just keep a smaller staff and make employees work more. Or they'll use short-term contracts with no benefits, promotions or bonuses to pay."</p>
        <p>Management seems far more open to the four-day week. "We are on the eve of a revolution in the way work is organized in Europe," said Jean-Pierre Nannio, personnel director at U.A.P., the big state-owned insurance group in Paris.</p>
        <p>A seeming majority in the French Parliament now backs the notion of a shorter workweek, despite warnings from several economists and former President Valery Giscard d'Estaing that if France is to remain competitive, a 32-hour week would mean an 18 percent cut in wages.</p>
        <p>Certainly the management of Germany's Volkswagen believes that a 20 percent cut in work time only makes sense if accompanied by a 20 percent cut in wages. That is what it has proposed, as an alternative to dismissing 31,000 people by 1995. Discussion of the proposal began last week.</p>
        <p>"The four-day week could be useful in crisis management, as at Volkswagen, Mr. Friedrich of Dresdner Bank said. "But as a medium-term policy, it is a great craziness. You do not resolve a problem by working less.</p>
        <p>"The basic question in Europe should be how to make our economies flexible enough to create jobs with low growth," he said. "In other words, get rid of the regulations, like no weekend work in Germany. The machinery is not Catholic or Protestant." Assessment Critics Lay Blame On Rigid Rules</p>
        <p>Opponents of the four-day week, particularly in Britain, say the solution to Europe's unemployment crisis lies in doing away with regulations and costly welfare programs that add considerably to wage costs and have made the European job market the most inflexible in the world. Since 1970, real economic growth in the 12 countries that now form the European Community has totaled 73 percent, but employment has risen only 7 percent.</p>
        <p>"Unemployment is proportional to the degree of state involvement and rigidity in an economy," said Alain Madelin, France's conservative Economic Development Minister. "When Europe grows, unlike the United States, it does not create jobs, because we are overregulated."</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there are signs that European workers have run out of patience with arguments based on the global market. When Air France workers went on strike last month against proposed job cuts, surveys showed that 70 percent of French people supported them, despite the disruption. The French Government retreated, aware that people saw the strikers not as vandals but as crusaders for the security of everyone's jobs.</p>
        <p>"The lesson of Air France is that people have had enough," Mr. Touraine, the sociologist, said.</p>
        <p>He said the French now appeared to be saying, "Look, my plumber can't fix the bathroom anymore, so I'm damn well going to change plumber."</p>
        <p>"And, for all its current vagueness," Mr. Touraine said, "the only real recipe for change they see is the four-day week."</p>
        <p>Mr. Huber, the wage negotiator for the I.G. Metall union, said he was tired of German executives telling him that one German worker now costs as much as 70 Russian workers and that some benefits would have to be abandoned if Germany was to remain competitive.</p>
        <p>"Where are the cuts supposed to stop?" he asked. "At the Czech level? Or the Thai? Or the Russian?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
