<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City's Immigration Restrictions Go on Trial</title>
    <meta content="13hazleton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/13/us/13hazleton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hazleton (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Civil Liberties Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Preston, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2DF1131F930A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City's Immigration Restrictions Go on Trial</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">City’s Immigration Restrictions Go on Trial</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA PRESTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Preston, Julia</byline>
      <dateline>SCRANTON, Pa., March 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Municipal restrictions against illegal immigration in Hazleton, Pa, are being challenged as discriminatory and overreaching in federal trial that just opened; Hazleton's city officials are first in country to adopt ordinances intended to drive away illegal immigrants by punishing local landlords for renting to them and employers for giving them jobs; restrictions, which have not yet taken effect, have been imitated by at least 80 towns and cities; lawsuit brought by American Civil Liberties Union and Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund claims ordinances encourage discrimination against Hispanic residents; this is first challenge to municipal ordinances across country to be heard in federal trial; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a test case about the power of cities to crack down on illegal immigration, a federal trial opened here Monday in which municipal restrictions in Hazleton, Pa., are being challenged as discriminatory and overreaching.</p>
        <p>City officials in Hazleton were the first in the country to adopt ordinances intended to drive away illegal immigrants by punishing local landlords for renting to them and employers for giving them jobs. The restrictions, which have yet to take effect, have been imitated by at least 80 towns and cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>City officials in Hazleton, Pa., adopted ordinances intended to drive away illegal immigrants by punishing local landlords for renting to them and employers for giving them jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a test case about the power of cities to crack down on illegal immigration, a federal trial opened here Monday in which municipal restrictions in Hazleton, Pa., are being challenged as discriminatory and overreaching.</p>
        <p>City officials in Hazleton were the first in the country to adopt ordinances intended to drive away illegal immigrants by punishing local landlords for renting to them and employers for giving them jobs. The restrictions, which have yet to take effect, have been imitated by at least 80 towns and cities.</p>
        <p>''The city has responded rationally to a very real threat,'' Kris W. Kobach, a law professor at the University of Missouri-Kansas City, said in the opening statement on behalf of Hazleton. Mr. Kobach described a surge in violent crime and gang warfare since 2005 that city officials attribute to a growing population of illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>The trial, before Judge James M. Munley of Federal District Court, is the result of a lawsuit by the American Civil Liberties Union and the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund. It is the first challenge to the municipal ordinances across the country to be heard in a federal trial.</p>
        <p>The rights groups say the ordinances encourage discrimination against Hispanic residents, violate federal and state housing laws, and overstep the powers of a local government to deal with immigration, which has been almost exclusively a federal matter.</p>
        <p>Witold Walczak, the legal director for the Pennsylvania A.C.L.U., said Hazleton did not have the authority to inquire into its residents' immigration status. ''Law regarding immigration can and must be passed only by Congress,'' Mr. Walczak said in an opening statement, warning that the ordinances could unleash racial vendettas in which neighbors would make complaints about Hispanic residents based on their appearance.</p>
        <p>Judge Munley's ruling could be a major marker of how far local governments can go to limit illegal immigration. In another closely watched case, a state court judge in St. Louis on Monday struck down similar employment and housing laws adopted by Valley Park, Mo., a suburb of St. Louis.</p>
        <p>In that case, the blunt ruling by the judge, Barbara W. Wallace, means that ''as a matter of state law, no city in Missouri should be doing this,'' said Linda M. Martínez, one of the lawyers who brought the challenge.</p>
        <p>Most of the ordinances that followed Hazleton's have faced state and federal challenges. So far, not one of the tougher measures has gone into effect, according to a roster compiled by the Puerto Rican rights group.</p>
        <p>After first adopting the ordinances last July, Hazleton revised them several times in response to questions raised by opponents. City officials announced another revision on Monday, saying they would eliminate two words that appeared to leave open the possibility that complaints could be brought against tenants solely on racial grounds.</p>
        <p>Hazleton's mayor, Louis J. Barletta, the driving force behind the laws, said his basic purpose remained the same: to make Hazleton hostile territory for illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''Illegal is illegal,'' Mr. Barletta said in an interview. ''There is no race in illegal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barletta said he was spurred to action last year by the daytime shooting death of a Hazleton man, Derek Kichline, in which two illegal immigrants have been accused.</p>
        <p>One ordinance withholds business licenses from employers who knowingly hire illegal workers. Another requires all tenants to register with City Hall, presenting proof of identification that the authorities can check against federal databases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barletta said that some Hispanic businesses had complained of losing customers and that some immigrants had moved away.</p>
        <p>''We witnessed many people leaving in the dark of night,'' he said. ''We have to assume they were illegal aliens.''</p>
        <p>Testifying against Hazleton, José Luis Lechuga, a legal Mexican immigrant who said he had lived in the city for 16 years, recounted how his grocery specializing in tortillas and chorizo and his restaurant with home-cooked tacos had failed in recent months. ''Many people did not want to come to Hazleton anymore because they did not feel safe,'' Mr. Lechuga testified. Hazleton residents ''look at us as enemies now.''</p>
        <p>Under cross-examination by a Hazleton lawyer, Harry G. Mahoney, Mr. Lechuga confirmed that his financial troubles had started well before the ordinances were passed, and he acknowledged that many of his customers might have been illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>Still, the court testimony left an impression of a harsh social change in Hazleton for some Hispanic residents.</p>
        <p>''I saw a lot of fear'' after the laws were adopted, said one resident, Agapito López, a retired ophthalmologist. ''It was hurting my people. Latinos are a family.''</p>
        <p>Judge Munley ruled Friday that the illegal immigrants who were plaintiffs in the case did not have to appear in court but could present their depositions as evidence, meaning they would not face cross-examination.</p>
        <p>Last year, Hazleton also adopted an ordinance making English the city's official language. That law is the subject of a temporary restraining order issued by Judge Munley, but it is not at issue in this trial.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
