<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barricades to Storm, Whether or Not Any Guards Were on Them</title>
    <meta content="13ceci" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/13/arts/music/13ceci.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070317T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1832628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Taylor, Cecil</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Zorn, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3D71031F930A25750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barricades to Storm, Whether or Not Any Guards Were on Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Barricades to Storm, Whether or Not Any Guards Were on Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was a superficial electricity ahead of last weekend's double bill at the Rose Theater at Jazz at Lincoln Center: Cecil Taylor's new trio and John Zorn's Masada. It was conducted further by some critics and through the nervous conversations of the audience before the show. It had to do with the notion that a pugnacious jazz avant-garde was being invited inside the gates of a dull and powerful establishment.</p>
        <p>The jazz avant-garde is a problematic notion: everybody knows roughly what it means, but nobody knows where it begins and ends. And if you accept Mr. Taylor and Mr. Zorn as avant-gardists, you're too easily forced to consider Wynton Marsalis -- Jazz at Lincoln Center's artistic director -- as a mainstreamer. He's not. His bands don't sound like anyone else's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever ponderous metathoughts about jazz the weekend’s shows promised, they happily delivered something much more specific: the end of one great band and the beginning of another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was a superficial electricity ahead of last weekend's double bill at the Rose Theater at Jazz at Lincoln Center: Cecil Taylor's new trio and John Zorn's Masada. It was conducted further by some critics and through the nervous conversations of the audience before the show. It had to do with the notion that a pugnacious jazz avant-garde was being invited inside the gates of a dull and powerful establishment.</p>
        <p>The jazz avant-garde is a problematic notion: everybody knows roughly what it means, but nobody knows where it begins and ends. And if you accept Mr. Taylor and Mr. Zorn as avant-gardists, you're too easily forced to consider Wynton Marsalis -- Jazz at Lincoln Center's artistic director -- as a mainstreamer. He's not. His bands don't sound like anyone else's.</p>
        <p>But above all, the experimental composers and bandleaders whose work refers to, argues against and engages with different parts of jazz -- the putative jazz avant-garde -- just don't need Jazz at Lincoln Center anymore. Their interests and audiences don't extend there. They've built their own festivals, their own record companies. (Mr. Zorn has created his own Lower East Side club, the Stone, with music six nights a week.) The MacArthur Foundation has honored almost all the major figures of the jazz avant-garde with fellowships. Academic presses are pumping out books about their achievements. What's the big deal, for them, about a gig at the Rose Theater?</p>
        <p>Since it began presenting concerts in 1988, Jazz at Lincoln Center has never before contracted Mr. Taylor or Mr. Zorn for a concert. (Oops.) Now, toward the end of a season called ''Innovations in Jazz,'' they were packaged together as a twofer. But whatever ponderous metathoughts about jazz the weekend's shows promised, they happily delivered something much more specific: the end of one great band and the beginning of another.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zorn distrusts institutional authority and has mastered the language of the outsider-scourge. Onstage with Masada on Friday, he righteously cudgeled the institution.</p>
        <p>''Let's hope this is the beginning of a trend of enlightened programming here,'' he yelped. ''There are more young faces in the audience here than there have been since the inception of this place!'' The remark ennobled the scattering of mostly white and schlumpy student hipsters among the old subscription audience, but that didn't make it true.</p>
        <p>Speeches delivered, the quartet started up, and of course it didn't sound out of place; it sounded great. Nobody got up and left. The older subscriber types around me weren't put off by the aggression in the music. They liked it.</p>
        <p>Masada's music is logical, comic, athletic; it rides on a strong groove from Greg Cohen's bass and Joey Baron's speeding drums. It never sounds comfortable or settled, which fits with the rest of Mr. Zorn's artistic temperament. It uses Jewish scales, early Ornette Coleman melodic shapes and hardcore-punk energy, and both Mr. Zorn and the trumpeter Dave Douglas feed off the rhythm section's rush: Mr. Douglas's solos are harmonically engaged; Mr. Zorn's are gestural.</p>
        <p>Like all of Mr. Zorn's best projects, Masada is an airtight system. It has also barely changed since its first records in 1994, and Tzadik.com, the Web site of Mr. Zorn's label, Tzadik, announced that the Lincoln Center shows would be two of Masada's last concerts.</p>
        <p>What is it, at this point, that's so important in Cecil Taylor's music? Rhythm. He plays some interesting chords, but it isn't so much how he gets from one to the next, or the melodic shapes he traces; it's all in the movement. As with any innately charismatic actor or dancer, witnessing it is infinitely better than trying to explain it. It's in the millions of choices that make a flowing gesture.</p>
        <p>There's plenty of alluring stuff in Mr. Taylor's phrasing: funk, 6/8 grooves and very familiar bits and pieces of blues. It's just that a lot of it happens almost simultaneously, one strand merging into the next before the completion of a single measure. His new trio, AHA 3, had Henry Grimes on bass, who confirmed the music's shifting key centers with his low-end rumble. But it was the drummer Pheeroan AkLaff, playing with technical detail and plenty of funk, who made it all clear for you.</p>
        <p>In a handful of pieces, some becoming impossibly dense and clotted, too much for a sizable chunk of the audience -- was this why the Rose Theater technical crew made the idiotic decision to bring up the house lights before the show was over? -- the three musicians careered through agitated pantonal improvisations, bass and drums tightly aligned to Mr. Taylor's phrasing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor's music doesn't draw on a body of consensual, practical knowledge; he is the single source of his art, and his sidemen got as close to it as any Taylor group I've seen in 20 years.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 17, 2007, Saturday  A review on Tuesday of Cecil Taylor's trio and John Zorn's Masada, at the Rose Theater, misstated the year that Lincoln Center began regularly presenting jazz concerts. It was 1987, not 1988.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 17, 2007, Saturday</p>
        <p>A review on Tuesday of Cecil Taylor's trio and John Zorn's Masada, at the Rose Theater, misstated the year that Lincoln Center began regularly presenting jazz concerts. It was 1987, not 1988.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
