<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Rises by 4.21; I.B.M. Drops Further</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="431576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEED8173DF932A15750C0A967958260" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Rises by 4.21; I.B.M. Drops Further</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day after its worst session in more than five months, the stock market brushed itself off yesterday and posted a small gain in nervous trading.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average rose 4.21 points to close at 2872.03. Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was fairly heavy, at 196.8 million shares, and advances led declines by a small amount.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One day after its worst session in more than five months, the stock market brushed itself off yesterday and posted a small gain in nervous trading.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average rose 4.21 points to close at 2872.03. Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was fairly heavy, at 196.8 million shares, and advances led declines by a small amount.</p>
        <p>The Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks closed up 1.33 points, to 367.92, and the Nasdaq composite index rose 3.28 points, to 466.09.</p>
        <p>In early trading, stocks moved within a narrow range as bargain hunters sought values after Tuesday's 62-point Dow selloff.</p>
        <p>Investors and traders kept a wary eye on I.B.M., which was a big factor in Tuesday's decline after it announced lower expected earnings. Shares of the computer maker closed down 1 yesterday, to 114 1/8, on four million shares traded.</p>
        <p>"Basically, the market stabilized after the trauma of yesterday," said Ronald J. Hill, investment strategist for Brown Brothers Harriman Inc. Investors searched for safety, he added, "as they continue to sell high-tech issues and move money toward consumer nondurable stocks like foods, drugs and tobaccos."</p>
        <p>Utilities showed some strength yesterday, he noted, reflecting the lower inflation fears in the bond market, and possibly the decision by the Illinois Supreme Court to allow the Commonwealth Edison Company to put into effect an already approved rate increase over the objections of consumer groups. The utility's stock was up 5/8, to 39 1/4.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hill said yesterday's "real strength came from a reversal in bonds, indicating that inflation expectations are not getting worse, providing a base of confidence to retain stocks."</p>
        <p>Concern over first-quarter earnings continued to worry the market, however. Some traders felt early in the session that I.B.M.'s stock price could hold and that the worst of Tuesday's decline was over. But others remained skeptical, and declining issues took an early 5-to-1 lead over stocks advancing.  Other Computer Stocks</p>
        <p>Among the personal computer stocks following I.B.M. down were Compaq Computer, down 1 3/4, to 59 1/2, and Apple Computer, down 1 3/4, to 67 3/4. Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing fell 2 1/8, to 87 1/2, also on a poor earnings outlook.</p>
        <p>In Tokyo, the stock market was closed today for Spring Equinox Day. Yesterday, the Nikkei index slipped 557.31 points, or 2 percent, to close at 26,449.35.</p>
        <p>Toward noon, the New York market made a small run on bargain hunting, with advances taking a slight lead over declines. But by early afternoon, the Dow had slipped into the negative side in directionless trading.</p>
        <p>Choppy trading persisted into late afternoon, with stocks moving toward their highs as bonds posted further gains. "The market has room to rebound further," Mr. Hill said. "You had more volume on a slightly up day like today than the lighter volume on a bad day like yesterday."</p>
        <p>Among the stocks posting gains was NCR, up 3 1/4, to 98, after A.T.&amp; T. said it would increase its offer for the computer company to $100 a share if NCR removed its board next week. But traders and analysts noted that shares stopped short of that price, an indication that investors were unconvinced that A.T.&amp; T. would clinch the deal. A.T.&amp; T. shares slipped 3/8, to 34.</p>
        <p>In the health-care sector, C.R. Bard, principally engaged in hospital and surgical specialties, rose 1 1/4, to 21 1/4, on speculation of favorable first-quarter results. The company is awaiting Food and Drug Administration approval of its Probe III angioplasty catheter</p>
        <p>Other health-sector stocks that performed well were Pfizer, up 3 3/8, to 104; Schering-Plough, up 1 1/8, to 50 1/8; Merck, up 2 1/4, to 103 3/4, and American Cyanamid, up 1 1/2, to 53 1/4.</p>
        <p>Warner Lambert rose 3, to 74, following a buy recommendation from a Dean Witter analyst, Jerome Brimeyer, who said the company's Cognex drug for Alzheimer's disease could be approved by the end of 1991.</p>
        <p>Airlines were narrowly mixed, while auto stocks were down. Chrysler slipped 3/8, to 14 1/2, and General Motors fell 1 1/4, to 37 3/8.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
