<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Housing Organization Finds Itself in Another Cuomo's Hands</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="590668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSING AND URBAN DEVELOPMENT DEPARTMENT (HUD)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSING ENTERPRISE FOR THE LESS PRIVILEGED (HELP)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENESIS HOMES (BROOKLYN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EQUITY HOMES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, ANDREW M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLE, MARIA CUOMO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D81230F936A25751C0A965958260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Housing Organization Finds Itself in Another Cuomo's Hands</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sam Roberts</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBERTS, SAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIVE years ago, as the first 25 homeless families moved into an imaginative prefabricated housing project in Brooklyn, Andrew M. Cuomo pondered a future political career and reflected on his father's.</p>
        <p>He said he would be reluctant to run for office from New York while his father was still Governor. Suppose Mario M. Cuomo happened to be holding office someplace else?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIVE years ago, as the first 25 homeless families moved into an imaginative prefabricated housing project in Brooklyn, Andrew M. Cuomo pondered a future political career and reflected on his father's.</p>
        <p>He said he would be reluctant to run for office from New York while his father was still Governor. Suppose Mario M. Cuomo happened to be holding office someplace else?</p>
        <p>"He will be in New York State if he's serving in elective office," Andrew Cuomo said.</p>
        <p>Since then, Governor Cuomo was re-elected again and passed up two opportunities to run for President. He is still in New York and if Washington beckons, it will most likely be for an appointive post. As of two weeks ago, though, Andrew Cuomo was in Washington as President Clinton's nominee for Assistant Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for Community Planning and Development.</p>
        <p>The position will give him wide discretion and visibility to replicate nationally the policies his commission on the homeless recommended last year to Mayor David N. Dinkins. It will also give him a chance to lobby for the construction of homes for the homeless similar to the ones built in Brooklyn and elsewhere by Housing Enterprise for the Less Privileged, or H.E.L.P., an organization Mr. Cuomo founded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's title has been retired, but his organization has been placed in good hands. The executive vice president will be Ilene Margolin, who is currently the associate executive director for operations of the Federation Employment and Guidance Service, and formerly an adviser to the Governor on homelessness. The unsalaried chairwoman will be Maria Cuomo Cole, Andrew's younger sister. Ms. Cuomo Cole, who was a partner in a public relations firm until this year and a H.E.L.P. board member, is married to Kenneth Cole, the shoe designer.</p>
        <p>"We could have either really let go or try to continue and fulfill Andrew's agenda and his dream, which is to continue on a national level," Ms.  Cuomo Cole said. "We want to keep a family commitment."</p>
        <p>Critics complained sometimes that Mr. Cuomo was able to keep that commitment only because he is the Governor's son. No matter. Plenty of progeny never even try to emulate powerful parents.</p>
        <p>"We feel confident that other cities will be able to implement this formula without their having any familial relation," said Ms. Cuomo Cole.</p>
        <p>"The H.E.L.P. concept was to provide immediate homes for homeless families and support services to find permanent homes. That was our covenant with homeless families. They, in turn, participated in the program by staying off drugs and committing themselves to drug treatment and cooperating with the support staff in training and counseling."</p>
        <p>With eight sites serving more than 4,000 people a year in the Bronx, Brooklyn, Albany, Westchester and Suffolk, H.E.L.P. has evolved into what it describes as the largest private provider of housing for homeless in the nation. New projects are pending on 14th Street in Manhattan and in Harrison in Westchester.</p>
        <p>Last year, H.E.L.P. itself graduated into becoming an innovative provider of permanent housing. Genesis Homes, a visually striking sanctuatuary in Brooklyn's East New York, houses 150 families evenly divided between the working poor who pay monthly rent of $500 to $700 and the formerly homeless whose rent is federally subsidized. Tenants share any savings if the time and effort they invest in clerical, maintenance or security duties pare the project's annual budget. Welfare mothers who join job-training classes will receive free day care for their children.</p>
        <p>The agenda for Genesis and its suburban counterpart, Equity Homes, is simple: to create public-private partnerships that increase the supply of housing for low-income and lower- middle-income families in low-density economically mixed projects in which vital social services are available to provide "prevention before intervention."</p>
        <p>Equity Homes plans to sell subsidized two-family homes for about $160,000 to homeowners who agree to lease the second apartment to a low-income tenant eligible for Federal rent subsidies.</p>
        <p>Genesis, with Ms. Cuomo Cole at the helm, marks another beginning for a concept that defies partisan politics and ideology. Its first principle is work, not welfare, which to be achieved requires an investment in education, training and child care and that jobs be available. Its second principle promotes independence because "government programs which treat a person as a mere recipient of entitlements can destroy one's sense of pride, value and control." And it limits government's role to planning, financing and regulating while private providers develop and operate the housing and other services.</p>
        <p>Those principles are economically and politically sound if advocates for the homeless succeed in melding conscience with the plight of the poor with the middle-class self-interest that predominates in Washington and New York. After the Board of Education ousted Schools Chancellor Joseph A. Fernandez last week to protest his social agenda, Governor Cuomo, who raised his family in Queens, reminded the rest of New York that it might well have been the Chancellor rather than the board that had lost touch.</p>
        <p>"There has been a syndrome for a long time if you're in Manhattan to see things a little bit different than you see them in Staten Island, Queens and Brooklyn. And I think the 4-to-3 vote -- right, wrong, for better, for worse -- probably reflects where that population is."  METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
