<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gonaives Journal; A City With Grit Keeps Aristide's Banner Flying</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GONAIVES (HAITI)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D61F31F935A35752C1A967958260" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gonaives Journal; A City With Grit Keeps Aristide's Banner Flying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>GONAIVES, Haiti, Nov. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although only 90 miles away by heavily cratered road, judging by its temperament this rugged port town can seem very distant from Haiti's capital, Port-au-Prince, where debates rage over the merits and misdeeds of the country's deposed President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide.</p>
        <p>From downtown streets to the dusty neighborhoods of Gonaives, the simple mention of Father Aristide's name can set crowds to chanting for the exiled President's return. The month since he was overthrown by soldiers has only served to brighten the reverence in which he is held here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although only 90 miles away by heavily cratered road, judging by its temperament this rugged port town can seem very distant from Haiti's capital, Port-au-Prince, where debates rage over the merits and misdeeds of the country's deposed President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide.</p>
        <p>From downtown streets to the dusty neighborhoods of Gonaives, the simple mention of Father Aristide's name can set crowds to chanting for the exiled President's return. The month since he was overthrown by soldiers has only served to brighten the reverence in which he is held here.</p>
        <p>"His return is urgent so that everything can be good again," said one man, who called the deposed President the Messiah. "When we had Titid, there were no problems," said another, affectionately using Father Aristide's nickname.</p>
        <p>While much of Haiti seems to have lapsed into a sort of dejected resignation over Father Aristide's overthrow by the army, Gonaives's 80,000 residents boast of a long tradition of resistance and say they are willing to endure anything to restore their leader.</p>
        <p>In what many said recalled the start of a series of popular demonstrations that began here in 1985 and ultimately led to the uprooting of the Duvalier family dictatorship in 1986, 300 to 400 youths ended a week of silent protests and prayer in Gonaives on Friday with the nation's first march to demonstrate against Father Aristide's overthrow. Priest Gives a Warning</p>
        <p>Under the nervous watch of soldiers who participants say peacefully cut the march in two after a time to hasten its breakup, the youths, who had gathered that morning in the town's high-arching concrete-and-tile cathedral, filed through the streets chanting slogans like "Aristide or death!"</p>
        <p>"The people are ready for a repeat of 1985," said the Rev. Anick Joseph, a 30-year-old Roman Catholic priest, whose heated political oratory and calls for active "self-defense" echo the liberation theology of Father Aristide. "If I had not asked the youths to restrain their passions a bit, they would be in the streets every day."</p>
        <p>Like many others who spoke to a visitor here, Father Joseph called on the world to come in and disarm the Haitian military so that Father Aristide could be restored to power. Failing that, he warned, the people will eventually take justice in their own hands.</p>
        <p>Asked about the appropriateness of popular violence, like Pere Lebrun, the name given to street lynchings with burning tires, Father Joseph said, "Faced with a military that has weapons of death in its hands, the people must have something to defend themselves with."</p>
        <p>The determination to do away with a military-backed Government that replaced the country's first democratically elected President seemed no less real among the ordinary people of Gonaives than among members of an active church that has long played an important role in Haitian politics. Embargo Is Applauded</p>
        <p>As teen-age girls danced playfully in circles, rhythmically repeating Father Aristide's name, a 34-year-old market vendor who gave her name only as Elizabeth applauded the international embargo even though she said the economic uncertainty it created had ruined sales of the toothpaste, artificial hair, and laundry soap crowding her market stall.</p>
        <p>"When Aristide comes it will be just like God coming," Elizabeth said, speaking in a staccato Creole. "We can wait, but we can't wait forever."</p>
        <p>A passer-by in his 40's who stopped immediately when he heard a discussion of the deposed President said: "I'm keeping one eye open at night to look out for the soldiers and one eye closed to pray for Aristide's urgent return. Gonaives will never be calm until he comes back."</p>
        <p>As a crowd quickly gathered, anxious to hear news of Father Aristide's return from a foreigner, a 15-year-old girl said of the army: "They don't want us to listen to the radio, and they don't want us to read the paper. They don't even want us to go outside."</p>
        <p>In addition to the anxiety of those hoping for his return, tension in the town could also be seen among the few people who cautiously identified themselves as non-supporters of Father Aristide.</p>
        <p>"The authors of this coup did what they did to save the Constitution," a man in his early 30's said, almost whispering, wary of youths standing a few feet away. When asked what he meant, he replied: "I don't feel free to express my view. It risks compromising my life. All around us are Aristide partisans."</p>
        <p>Aware of the passionate support that endures for Father Aristide and the town's reputation for political ferment, soldiers guard all entrances to the city.</p>
        <p>In an often-repeated story that has heightened emotions against the army since the coup on Sept. 30, residents said a man was shot after being told to remove a roadblock. They said two men who tried to carry the wounded man off to the hospital were themselves shot, as was a fourth man who asked the soldiers why they had attacked.</p>
        <p>"When we had Titid, we didn't have problems like this," a man said of the killings. "Aristide's victory was for us, and his return will give us deliverance. Once and for all we must get rid of these animals."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
