<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; Calvin Klein Teases With Longer Skirts</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PERRY ELLIS (CO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BERNADINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, CALVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACOBS, MARC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRENNER, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DE163AF935A35752C1A967958260" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; Calvin Klein Teases With Longer Skirts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNADINE MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BERNADINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY did it seem as if Calvin Klein was taking up the cudgels for longer skirts? Other designers had presented calf-length styles for spring and split them up the front or sides to make them look more seductive. Other designers had introduced longer skirts in sheer fabrics that allow the legs to show.</p>
        <p>Most of those designers offered disclaimers like "we think women should have options: we're showing short skirts, too." So did Mr. Klein. Still, it seemed he paid more than cursory attention to the long skirt at his show yesterday in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY did it seem as if Calvin Klein was taking up the cudgels for longer skirts? Other designers had presented calf-length styles for spring and split them up the front or sides to make them look more seductive. Other designers had introduced longer skirts in sheer fabrics that allow the legs to show.</p>
        <p>Most of those designers offered disclaimers like "we think women should have options: we're showing short skirts, too." So did Mr. Klein. Still, it seemed he paid more than cursory attention to the long skirt at his show yesterday in New York.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, Mr. Klein decided that the scales had tilted in favor of short skirts, and that he would concentrate on them. Perhaps he is now tired of short and ready to push long styles?</p>
        <p>The designer didn't sound too militant. "Longer clothes can be charming, especially when they are printed," he said. "But they can also be sexy."</p>
        <p>Mull this over and it seems that he is an advocate of coexistence. But when he adds, "Clothes have to change: they have to look new, they have to evolve," you may feel he is throwing his weight behind long hemlines.</p>
        <p>It is certainly true that both short and long are represented in his spring collection, along with trousers for those women who want no part of the hemline controversy. And it would seem that the short skirts with a little graceful flip to them are almost always successful. But that is what the viewers, as well as the designer, are most accustomed to seeing.</p>
        <p>The batting average for the longer skirts is not quite so high. The best are narrow skirts slashed to show the legs. When the skirt is too full or not translucent enough, it can seem heavy. And the addition of a wool jacket does not help much: the dresses look better alone.</p>
        <p>Heaviness goes against the grain of this collection, in which colors are pale and subtle: there is every variety of beige, plus light washes of coral, apricot or lilac. Patterns are pale checks or plaids plus a few gently abstract flower prints.</p>
        <p>Loose, ribbed sweaters are pulled over some of the calf-length full skirts. Sweaters baring the midriff, stretch unitards that cling to the skin and stretch dresses take the eye off the hemlines.</p>
        <p>Weightlessness is emphasized for evening in ankle-length slender columns in satin georgette the designer calls tunics. They are split to show the narrow sheer pants underneath. A peach tunic over apricot pants is a wonderful combination.</p>
        <p>Even the hint of color is eliminated in the full-length white evening dresses. Some are touched with crystal beading at the slip-top or one-shoulder neckline. These show the designer as a minimalist, but it is a rich minimalism.</p>
        <p>The collection as a whole represents a gentle approach to spring. The clothes are clean-looking and, except for the beading, there is no extraneous decoration. It makes a strong case for calf-length skirts, but it offers alternatives. The uncluttered look is its strong suit.</p>
        <p>In his show on Monday night, Marc Jacobs cast his lighthearted separates for Perry Ellis against the backdrop of a fantasy western. Cowboy boots decorated with poppies or palm trees, leather skirts with fringe hanging from the waist, peasant blouses and midriff-baring sweaters were some of the lively ingredients in a show that did not take itself too seriously.</p>
        <p>Bandana prints embroidered in white beads were made into tight short skirts that shared the runway with short bouffant styles, including a black and white checked skirt worn with a red petticoat.</p>
        <p>Button-front dresses opened over swimsuits and swim dresses were beaded and had cowl necklines. Most jackets barely cleared the waistline, leather vests accompanied ruffled skirts, and big long skirts were printed with cactus for a desert scene and patio chairs for a poolside scene.</p>
        <p>It was all a little zany and not every combination worked. But the show was filled with imagination and good cheer. It offered a choice of hem lengths and kicky patterns, like awning stripes and overscale flowers. The ruffle-edged skirts and sailor pants each had a different kind of appeal. What they shared was a sense that fashion can be fun. Not too many shows convey that feeling.</p>
        <p>Eleanor Brenner opened her show yesterday morning with the bicycle pants, cotton sports jackets in two or three colors and tennis sweaters women like to wear during their leisure hours. Then she moved into the tailored suits and trench coats suitable for work.</p>
        <p>She ended with snazzy bead-embroidered evening jackets, which were paired with georgette pleated shirts and sequin-embroidered or quilted plastic skirts. The many pleated shorts, plastic separates and bright colors lightened the mood of the compact collection, which touched many fashion bases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
