<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parolee's Arrest Spurs Calls for Tougher Laws</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATTACKS ON POLICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JENKINS, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMEON, WILLIAM (POLICE OFFICER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REEHIL, MICHAEL(POLICE OFFICER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DC1E39F933A15752C0A960958260" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parolee's Arrest Spurs Calls for Tougher Laws</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moments before he was sentenced to prison for a fatal stabbing in 1991, Charles Jenkins, 16, apologized to his victim's family and pledged that he would shun violence and crime.</p>
        <p>"I know this situation caused many people to feel sorrow," Mr. Jenkins wrote  in a letter his lawyer read in court. "I'm just writing this letter to let everybody know I have a heart and I'm not a killer."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moments before he was sentenced to prison for a fatal stabbing in 1991, Charles Jenkins, 16, apologized to his victim's family and pledged that he would shun violence and crime.</p>
        <p>"I know this situation caused many people to feel sorrow," Mr. Jenkins wrote  in a letter his lawyer read in court. "I'm just writing this letter to let everybody know I have a heart and I'm not a killer."</p>
        <p>But on Thursday, just five months after he was paroled, Mr. Jenkins was again charged with a crime of violence, the shooting of two Bronx police officers.</p>
        <p>Officer Michael Reehil of the 42d Precinct in Melrose was in serious condition at Jacobi Hospital, where he underwent surgery for five bullet wounds  to the abdomen. Officer Reehil and Officer William Simeon were both struck as they responded to a call reporting a "man with a gun" at the Forest Houses on East 166th Street. The other officer was not wounded because a bullet struck the handcuff case on his belt.</p>
        <p>The police said Mr. Jenkins, who was wounded by police but is expected to survive, admitted the shootings and said he fired his .380 automatic because he  was "mad at my mother."</p>
        <p>As doctors tended to Officer Reehil, officials from City Hall to Albany were  using the incident as a rallying cry in their efforts to toughen New York's juvenile offender laws.</p>
        <p>Jim Flateau, a spokesman for the State Department of Corrections, said that if Gov. George E. Pataki's proposals for juvenile offenders had been the law when Mr. Jenkins was sentenced, Thursday's shooting would not have occurred.</p>
        <p>"He would have still been incarcerated," Mr. Flateau said.</p>
        <p>The Governor is seeking to have juveniles who are charged as adults sentenced to longer terms, and once they reach age 16, to have them serve those terms in adult prisons. He also is advocating longer terms before parole is considered.</p>
        <p>On Thursday at 6:30 P.M., Mr. Jenkins's mother called the police to report that he had become violent and had sprayed her with a tear gas, said First Deputy Commissioner John F. Timoney. Two housing police officers responded to her 13th-floor apartment, but Mr. Jenkins was already armed and downstairs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenkins opened fire almost immediately, detectives said, and police officers wounded him.</p>
        <p>"He admitted the shooting," said a detective, who spoke on condition of anonymity. "He said he was mad about his mother."</p>
        <p>A friend of Mr. Jenkins said yesterday that since his release in August, Mr.  Jenkins had been trying to readjust to life on the outside. The friend, Jose Gomez, said he spoke with Mr. Jenkins 30 minutes before the shooting, and tried  to help him calm down. "He was a very quiet kid," Mr. Gomez said. "He was just looking for somebody to talk to."</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said he was angered to learn that Mr. Jenkins had been paroled after serving four years for a homicide. State court records show Mr. Jenkins was convicted of a slaying that occurred on Aug. 20, 1990 on East 166th Street and Tinton Avenue.</p>
        <p>According to police and prosecutors, Mr. Jenkins approached Arturo Zamura and demanded his money, pretending to have a gun. When Mr. Zamura, 36, pulled out a  knife, Mr. Jenkins beat him so he would drop the knife. Mr. Jenkins then used the knife to stab Mr. Zamura once in the chest, according to court records.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenkins was originally charged with second-degree murder and pleaded guilty to manslaughter, with a sentence agreement of 39 months to nine years in  prison. Bronx prosecutors said yesterday that they concurred because their witnesses "had credibility problems."</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Jenkins was tried as an adult, he served his sentence at the Brookwood Secure Center for youths in Brookwood, Mr. Flateau said. In July 1993, the Parole Board rejected Mr. Jenkins's first application for release, noting the seriousness of the crime. But his next application was granted, and he was released on Aug. 17, 1995.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
