<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Labor Officials See Little to Fear in a Combination</title>
    <meta content="Y08UNI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1015420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SHAPING A GLOBAL GIANT: THE UNIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimler-Benz Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Automobile Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ig Metall (German Union)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EED61231F93BA35756C0A96E958260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Labor Officials See Little to Fear in a Combination</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Giant labor unions representing auto workers in US and Germany see little to fear in Daimler-Benz AG's acquisition of Chrysler Corp; union officials see little prospect of consolidation and layoffs because there is little overlap in production of two companies; some union leaders predict that combination will bring more opportunities than worries; I G Metall represents German auto workers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Labor unions often cringe at mergers because such combinations frequently portend large-scale layoffs. But the giant unions representing auto workers in the United States and Germany see little to fear in Daimler-Benz A.G.'s acquisition of the Chrysler Corporation.</p>
        <p>The reason: There is little overlap in the production of the two companies, and as a result, union officials see little prospect of consolidation and layoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Labor unions often cringe at mergers because such combinations frequently portend large-scale layoffs. But the giant unions representing auto workers in the United States and Germany see little to fear in Daimler-Benz A.G.'s acquisition of the Chrysler Corporation.</p>
        <p>The reason: There is little overlap in the production of the two companies, and as a result, union officials see little prospect of consolidation and layoffs.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some union leaders predicted that a combination would bring more opportunities than worries. For instance, officials with the United Automobile Workers predicted that the acquisition would open the door to the union's organizing workers at a new Mercedes plant just outside Tuscaloosa, Ala., a plant with 1,500 workers that has until now fought unionization.</p>
        <p>And labor experts also said the deal could result in strong cross-Atlantic ties between the U.A.W. and I. G. Metall, the powerful union representing German auto workers -- perhaps creating a more formal alliance between a European union and an American one than has ever existed before.</p>
        <p>At a news conference yesterday in Detroit, Stephen P. Yokich, president of the U.A.W, sounded anything but worried. ''I don't believe it weakens us -- not at all,'' Mr. Yokich said. ''We really don't see any layoffs and the company didn't see any when we spoke to them.''</p>
        <p>Even if the two unions have some major objections to the merger, some labor union officials acknowledged that such objections were unlikely to result in walkouts anytime soon because the two unions have pending contracts with Chrysler and Daimler.</p>
        <p>In an interview with a German radio station, Walter Riester, vice president of I. G. Metall, which represents about 160,000 auto workers at Daimler-Benz, said his first reaction was to check whether the merger endangered production or jobs in Germany.</p>
        <p>''To begin with, there is convincing proof that this is not the case,'' Mr. Riester said. ''The range of products at Chrysler and Daimler and Mercedes-Benz is very, very different and both operate in different markets.''</p>
        <p>Philippe Houchois, an automobile analyst with Standard &amp; Poor's/DRI in London, agreed. ''The official line is there will not be any job losses or redundancies,'' he said. ''It's a believable line because there is no product overlap.''</p>
        <p>An outgrowth of the Chrysler-Daimler deal could be the formation of the strongest cross-Atlantic alliance ever between two unions, several labor analysts said. Officials from the U.A.W. and I. G. Metall already compare notes and discuss strategies about coming problems, but as a result of the merger, that cooperation is expected to increase vastly.</p>
        <p>''This merger is good for business and good for labor,'' said Lowell Turner, a professor of comparative labor relations at Cornell University. ''It will also be a good stimulus for growing international collaboration among unions as they struggle to counterbalance the enormous power of capital in the global economy.''</p>
        <p>Several analysts predicted that the deal, by having the unions looking over each other's shoulders, could prompt the U.A.W. to begin demanding some of the goodies received by their German counterparts. ''Americans haven't really paid attention that the Germans get six weeks' vacation because they see Germany as a different universe,'' Professor Turner said. ''But when they get pulled more closely together because of a merger like this, it's likely to affect bargaining demands.''</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Yokich said yesterday that it would be good if American unions could win the same rights that German unions have. German law gives unions half the seats on the supervisory board of many companies and requires many corporations to have works councils, which are groups of union officials who can block some of management's moves, like layoffs, but not others, such as installing new technologies.</p>
        <p>Indeed, several labor experts suggested that since under German law, I. G. Metall has half the seats on Daimler's supervisory board that could make life easier for the United Automobile Workers in future negotiations or in future corporate decisions on plant closings. For example, if Daimler-Chrysler had a showdown with the U.A.W. over wages in American negotiations, Metall might be able to pressure Daimler, both on the supervisory board and on the factory floor, to give their American co-workers a better deal.</p>
        <p>But Karl E. Ludvigsen, chairman of Ludvigsen Associates, an automobile consulting firm in London, said he doubted the merger would strengthen either union's hand. ''After all the international mergers I've seen, none of the labor unions have really moved the need in being able to go to the headquarter country to try to get a better deal,''he said. ''There's much talk among the unions trying to use their leverage across international boundaries, but they haven't succeeded.''</p>
        <p>Diane C. Swonk, an economist with the First Chicago NBD Corporation, said that as result of the merger, the United Automobile Workers would be more likely to select Chrysler as its strike target in next year's round of bargaining. The union might conclude it could get a better deal from a German-owned Chrysler, she said.</p>
        <p>''This,'' she said, ''makes them a target because the union will think there's a tendency that Daimler will roll over and play dead with the U.A.W. more than Chrysler would have.''</p>
        <p>SHAPING A GLOBAL GIANT: THE UNIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
