<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hunting 2 Outlaws, They Find Skeletons</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="501008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CEMETERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOLIVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARKER, ROBERT LEROY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LONGBAUGH, HARRY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUTCH CASSIDY AND THE SUNDANCE KID (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF1330F934A25752C0A964958260" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hunting 2 Outlaws, They Find Skeletons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of forensic experts and historians has exhumed a pair of skeletons in Bolivia that may be those of two famous American outlaws, Butch Cassidy and "the Sundance Kid."</p>
        <p>One of the expedition's members, Dan Buck of Washington, said a trail of documentary clues discovered in various parts of South America led the group last month to a cemetery in San Vicente, Bolivia, a remote mining village where the outlaws supposedly died in a 1907 gun battle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of forensic experts and historians has exhumed a pair of skeletons in Bolivia that may be those of two famous American outlaws, Butch Cassidy and "the Sundance Kid."</p>
        <p>One of the expedition's members, Dan Buck of Washington, said a trail of documentary clues discovered in various parts of South America led the group last month to a cemetery in San Vicente, Bolivia, a remote mining village where the outlaws supposedly died in a 1907 gun battle.</p>
        <p>The scientific leader of the expedition, Dr. Clyde Collins Snow, a forensic anthropologist, has taken the skeletons to his laboratory in Norman, Okla., where he plans to subject them to the same analytical techniques that he and other scientists used in identifying the skull of the Nazi concentration camp doctor Josef Mengele. Fled U.S. in 1901</p>
        <p>The lives of Butch Cassidy and "the Sundance Kid" were romantically portrayed in a movie starring Paul Newman and Robert Redford, but the real careers of the outlaws are shrouded in mystery. The two bandits, whose real names were Robert LeRoy Parker and Harry Longbaugh, carried out so many successful bank and railroad robberies in the late 1800's that large rewards were offered for their capture. Hotly pursued by Pinkerton agents, they fled the United States in 1901 with Longbaugh's mistress, Etta Place.</p>
        <p>After arriving in Buenos Aires, the trio began robbing banks and trains all across South America, but at some point, their documented histories faded into romantic legend. According to one theory, they returned to the United States and lived happily ever after. But other evidence suggests that Cassidy and Longbaugh fought a final battle in 1907 with the Bolivian police at San Vicente near Tupiza and were buried in unmarked graves in a mining cemetery, the one visited last month by Dr. Snow and his colleagues.</p>
        <p>The historians of the group, Dan Buck and his wife, Anne Meadows, combed through documents of old mining companies, consulates and police departments in Bolivia, Chile and other countries, and the clues pointed to the cemetery in San Vicente, Mr. Buck said. Mr. Buck, who is administrative assistant to Representative Patricia Schroeder, a Colorado Democrat, formerly served with the Peace Corps in Bolivia, where he began to gather information about the outlaws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buck said that witnesses to the 1907 gun battle had died, but that the son of one of them was able to identify not only the house where the two Americans died but the graves where they were buried.</p>
        <p>Dr. Snow has determined that one of the skulls he disinterred has entry and exit holes from a bullet that passed through the temples, and the other has a smashed forehead, consistent with the head-on impact of a projectile. This evidence, he said, would tally with an account that both outlaws were badly wounded in a shootout after their robbery of the mine payroll, and that realizing they were lost, Cassidy shot the Kid and committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Snow is widely known for his work identifying victims of political executions in Latin America.</p>
        <p>He and his colleagues hope to extract DNA from the San Vicente bones for comparison with possible remnants of hair or other genetic material from the bandits. "We can't yet be sure what we've got," he said, "but I really believe we've got Butch and the Kid."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
