<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seton Hall's Dehere Hurt In Victory Over Rutgers</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="493542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SETON HALL UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF1E31F931A25751C1A967958260" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seton Hall's Dehere Hurt In Victory Over Rutgers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN,</byline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY, N.J., Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Seton Hall Pirates had to face some questions about themselves following an embarrassing 29-point defeat to North Carolina last week. Tonight, having to cope with the harsh and overwhelming noise of the Rutgers Athletic Center, the Pirates thought they found several solutions in their inspired 77-72 victory over the Scarlet Knights.</p>
        <p>But at the end of a late night created by a national cable telecast, Seton Hall was still left with a serious question -- the condition of Terry Dehere's right wrist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Seton Hall Pirates had to face some questions about themselves following an embarrassing 29-point defeat to North Carolina last week. Tonight, having to cope with the harsh and overwhelming noise of the Rutgers Athletic Center, the Pirates thought they found several solutions in their inspired 77-72 victory over the Scarlet Knights.</p>
        <p>But at the end of a late night created by a national cable telecast, Seton Hall was still left with a serious question -- the condition of Terry Dehere's right wrist.</p>
        <p>Dehere, a junior guard who was held to 9 points on 3-for-11 shooting, fell on the wrist in the final seconds. John Levitt, the Seton Hall trainer, said Dehere, who will be examined in the morning, may have suffered tendon damage. A Few Steps Forward</p>
        <p>The possibility of a serious injury to the most important of the Pirates was the only troubling factor on a night of significant progress. "We took three or four or five steps forward tonight," said P. J. Carlesimo, the Seton Hall coach. "That's what we've been looking for. That's one of the better wins we've had in a while."</p>
        <p>The Pirates, 4-1 and ranked 12th in the latest Associated Press poll, overcame the noise and heat from the crowd of 8,966, the second-largest in Rutgers history. Rutgers (3-1) built upon the passion of its overtime victory over Nevada-Las Vegas last Saturday, but could not come closer than 1 point in its second-half comeback.</p>
        <p>Gordon Winchester, a senior forward who averaged 7.4 points a year ago, tied his career high with 18 on 8-of-11 shooting. Jerry Walker, a junior forward, scored 15 points, the biggest coming on consecutive baskets after the Knights had come within 1 point with 8:06 to play.</p>
        <p>Thanks to Walker, the Knights -- and the relentless crowd -- never had a chance to take the lead. Walker's 10-foot jumper from the right side gave the Pirates a 3-point lead. Then after Steve Worthy missed a 3-point shot -- one of the disappointments in a 4-for-15 shooting night -- Walker scored inside for a 64-59 lead.</p>
        <p>Worthy then missed a jumper in traffic and Winchester, who was responsible for much of Worthy's frustration, scored from inside for a 66-59 lead.</p>
        <p>Seton Hall's lead was built and preserved by new and suddenly important faces. Danny Hurley, a freshman guard, came off the bench with Bryan Caver struggling against the Rutgers pressure defense, and found enough slim openings to the basket to score 13 points. Hurley, who was kicked in the ribs by Walker on a defensive sequence in the second half, is also expected to be examined.</p>
        <p>And John Leahy, a second-year freshman who missed last season with a fractured ankle, scored 13 points and became an essential factor down the stretch.  Leahy Arrives</p>
        <p>Leahy's behind-the-back pass to Winchester, down the lane, led to a basket for a 5-point lead with 3:35 to go. His drive and foul shot gave the Pirates a 6-point lead with 2:58 to play. And with 17 seconds to go, the Knights still within 3 and the crowd refusing to give up, Leahy went to the foul line and made two free throws for the final margin.</p>
        <p>"John Leahy arrived tonight," Carlesimo said. "I just think we saw the real John Leahy for the first time."</p>
        <p>Leahy smiled at the idea that not every first-year player, in the fifth game of the season, before a national cable audience and a hostile crowd, would attempt a behind-the-back pass down the lane in the final minutes of a 3-point game.</p>
        <p>"It was just one of those things," he said. "That was the only pass I could get off. If I made a straight pass it would have been deflected. Whatever gets the ball to the guy."</p>
        <p>"We were hanging on by our fingers," Carlesimo said, "but we hung on."</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
