<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyers More Willing To Discuss Their Fees</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Your Money Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="LAW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL PROFESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEES (PROFESSIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWYERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANSNERUS, LAURA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED81F3CF933A05752C0A965958260" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyers More Willing To Discuss Their Fees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laura Mansnerus</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MANSNERUS, LAURA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAWYERS are not blase about money these days, which means that they are not blase about clients. While still not very amenable to negotiation -- lawyers have fairly firm rates, like surgeons or baby sitters -- they are increasingly receptive to requests to keep costs down.</p>
        <p>Clients can minimize rude surprises by asking questions at the outset about fees. Since the advent of computerized billing systems, they can also monitor statements more easily. And increasingly, experts on billing say, clients are doing both.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAWYERS are not blase about money these days, which means that they are not blase about clients. While still not very amenable to negotiation -- lawyers have fairly firm rates, like surgeons or baby sitters -- they are increasingly receptive to requests to keep costs down.</p>
        <p>Clients can minimize rude surprises by asking questions at the outset about fees. Since the advent of computerized billing systems, they can also monitor statements more easily. And increasingly, experts on billing say, clients are doing both.</p>
        <p>The subject "is in the public eye more than when lawyers weren't allowed to discuss fees publicly," said George Kuhlman, ethics counsel for the American Bar Association. Mr. Kuhlman said advertising had impressed upon people who need lawyers that they are shoppers of a sort.</p>
        <p>For new clients, the general practice, urged but not required by most state ethics codes, is to send an "engagement letter" confirming billing terms. Usually a retainer, or down payment, is required; this will be worked off and is sometimes a nonrefundable minimum.</p>
        <p>For tasks that are discrete and predictable, like a simple will or real estate closing, most lawyers charge a flat fee that is not likely to exceed $1,000. In personal injury cases, plaintiffs' lawyers work on a contingency basis. Otherwise, billing by the hour, usually in units of 6 or 15 minutes, is the norm. It is also the source of most trouble and suspense.</p>
        <p>The hourly rate is disclosed in the first consultation and on each bill. But a firm might have several people working on one matter, including an associate at $100 an hour and a partner at twice that rate. Most clients do not know who is working or how many hours are being rung up.</p>
        <p>"People are concerned that the meter is running when the taxi isn't moving," said Richard C. Reed, a lawyer in Bellevue, Wash., who headed an A.B.A. task force on billing.</p>
        <p>Nearly all lawyers say, however, that there is no such thing as an estimate -- at least not the kind an auto mechanic gives.</p>
        <p>"I'm not an apologist for the profession, but it's almost impossible to say what the bill is going to be," said Daniel R. White, author of "What Lawyers Do . . . and How to Make Them Work for You" (E. P. Dutton, 1987). He added, however: "They will bill as much as they think they can get away with."</p>
        <p>So what should a client ask? First, seek a probable range of costs, which is better than no estimate. The client can also worry aloud and in advance about expenses.</p>
        <p>"I would say, 'I want you to understand that I'm not a deep pocket,' " Mr. White said. "I have definitely heard lawyers at firms say, 'This client is concerned about the bill.' " For associates doing research, "that means you yuk it up less in the library."</p>
        <p>It is certainly legitimate to set an upper limit, although some say that encourages the lawyer to reach it. And no lawyer would argue with a request to notify the client when the tab hits a certain point.</p>
        <p>Even with a fixed fee, it's advisable to ask exactly what it covers: How many consultations are included? How many times can the beneficiaries in the will be changed? What if the adoption is contested?</p>
        <p>And sometimes neither an hourly nor a flat fee covers photocopies and overnight mail, which can add costs at astonishing speed.</p>
        <p>Finally, the client should know the policy on telephone consultations. Almost all lawyers bill them; as for the two-minute call, some record a minimum charge and others don't.</p>
        <p>Clients should be aware that conversation costs. Mr. Kuhlman said, "If you want to spend time talking about things that don't require a lawyer, call your sister-in-law."  LAW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
