<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Congo Vote, Neglect and Scandal Still Reign</title>
    <meta content="28congo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/world/africa/28congo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Congo</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kindu (Congo)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kinshasa (Congo)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gettleman, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shariff, Ahmed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Congo (Formerly Zaire)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kabila, Joseph</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bemba, Jean-Pierre</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DC1330F93BA15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Congo Vote, Neglect and Scandal Still Reign</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After Congo Vote, Neglect and Scandal Still Reign</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFFREY GETTLEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gettleman, Jeffrey</byline>
      <dateline>KINDU, Congo</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on neglect and corruption that continue in Congo six months after historic election that cost UN $500 million and was billed as end of free fall; decades of misrule have reduced 60 million people in mineral-rich country to among poorest in world as ceaseless rebellions destabilize enormous chunk of central Africa and claim estimated four million lives; fledgling government is now trying to stitch country together but recent 1,200-mile trip shows huge obstacles; once-prosperous Kindu in interior has lost its roads, railroad and river barges so all goods are flown in by plane; photos; map; capital Kinshasa has streets of rubble and shells of once-elegant buildings; World Bank president Paul Wolfowitz visits to discuss $1.4-billion aid program and fighting corruption; UN official Ahmed Shariff notes theft of millions of dollars given by West to disarm militias; dire plight of country with 900,000 square miles and only 300 miles of paved road described (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The highway out of town is a single dirt motorcycle track. The colonial-era railroad has finally broken down. The last of the mighty river barges lies rotting on shore with weeds shooting up through its ribs.</p>
        <p>And so Kindu, a once prosperous city here in Congo's interior, is now so cut off that everything is flown in by plane: bottled water, panes of glass, cookies, cucumbers, even gasoline, at $12 a gallon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six months after a historic election, the fledging government is struggling to put Congo back together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The highway out of town is a single dirt motorcycle track. The colonial-era railroad has finally broken down. The last of the mighty river barges lies rotting on shore with weeds shooting up through its ribs.</p>
        <p>And so Kindu, a once prosperous city here in Congo's interior, is now so cut off that everything is flown in by plane: bottled water, panes of glass, cookies, cucumbers, even gasoline, at $12 a gallon.</p>
        <p>This is Congo six months after a historic election, the most expensive in Africa and one that was billed -- by the Congolese and the United Nations officials who paid half a billion dollars for it -- as the end of a free fall.</p>
        <p>Decades of misrule have reduced the 60 million people of this mineral-rich country to among the poorest in the world. Ceaseless rebellions have destabilized an enormous chunk of central Africa and claimed an estimated four million lives.</p>
        <p>Congo's fledging government is now trying to stitch the nation back together, as if it ever existed meaningfully at all. But a recent 1,200-mile trip across the country -- by plane, truck, motorbike, hiking boots and dugout canoe -- shows the Congo-size obstacles that are not going away.</p>
        <p>Kinshasa, the unruly capital at the western edge of the country, looks as if a war has been fought in its streets. There has been some violence there, like the periodic clashes between the presidential guard and a militia loyal to Jean-Pierre Bemba, a tycoon, former warlord and unsuccessful candidate for president.</p>
        <p>But it is not tanks and bombs that have turned the streets into bone-jarring rubble and many elegant buildings into teetering shells. It is neglect and corruption, which persist despite the election.</p>
        <p>In early March, when it came time to form the first truly democratic government in the country's history, a political party connected to President Joseph Kabila submitted the name André Kasongo Ilunga for trade minister. The problem, government officials later acknowledged, was that there was no such man.</p>
        <p>Naturally, when the government appointed Mr. Ilunga to the cabinet, he did not show up. The president's advisers soon discovered that the name had been submitted as a ruse to ensure that another politician got the post.</p>
        <p>''It was very embarrassing for all of us,'' said Kikaya bin Karubi, a member of Parliament and a confidant of President Kabila.</p>
        <p>A few days later, Congo's top nuclear official was charged with making an unauthorized deal with a British company to sell the country's copious supply of uranium.</p>
        <p>That all happened just a few days before Paul D. Wolfowitz, president of the World Bank, arrived in Kinshasa to discuss a $1.4 billion aid program. He said fighting corruption was the ''foundation of all the other things that need to be done in this country,'' but he warned that ''it took many years to bring the country to this point.''</p>
        <p>''It is not going to be fixed overnight,'' Mr. Wolfowitz said. Mr. Kabila has vowed to do his best, and his advisers say he has a stronger hand after defeating Mr. Bemba in a runoff election with 58 percent of the vote. Before that, Mr. Kabila was president of a transitional government in which power was awkwardly divided among him and four vice presidents, two of them warlords.</p>
        <p>That system was partly to blame for the disappearance of millions of dollars meant for the disarmament of militias. In 2004, Western donors gave Congo more than $200 million to get 330,000 militiamen out of the killing business. The plan was to provide each militia member who voluntarily disarmed with $25 a month and job training. But last summer the money suddenly ran out, after helping only a fraction of the gunmen.</p>
        <p>''The money got stolen,'' said Ahmed Shariff, the top official in Kindu for the United Nations, which has 17,000 peacekeeping troops in Congo. ''It was used to build houses and buy cars.'' The government has yet to revive the program, leaving tens of thousands of former militiamen angry, armed and in the bush.</p>
        <p>Sabuni Bokota is one of them. He is a 5-foot-tall tomato farmer and former militia commander, with three wives and 15 children. They all live in a string of mud brick huts along the east bank of the Congo River in an isolated village called Lotangi, a day's paddle from Kindu past 100-foot-tall stalks of bamboo and baseball-size spiders.</p>
        <p>During Congo's recent wars, Mr. Sabuni commanded 2,000 militiamen called the Mai-Mai, who greased themselves with palm oil, hung ivory amulets around their necks and chewed antibiotic pills they thought would give them magical powers.</p>
        <p>The Mai-Mai were a surreal dimension to the chaos that exploded in Congo in the late 1990s after the fall of Mobutu Sese Seko, the longtime dictator of Congo, which he renamed Zaire. Troops from six neighboring countries poured across the borders to plunder minerals. In Lotangi, local people like Mr. Sabuni fought back.</p>
        <p>The Mai-Mai were supposed to be part of the national disarmament plan, but since they lived in far-off places, many heard about the $25 monthly salaries only over crackly radios and never saw a dime.</p>
        <p>Now they are getting impatient. Recently, Mr. Sabuni greased himself up again, threw on his amulets and led a contingent of Mai-Mai to Kindu to protest. ''We've been waiting five years,'' he said. ''But they keep telling us it will take time.''</p>
        <p>Time has not been especially kind to Lotangi. It used to be part of a network of sun-baked river towns connected by barges, railways and roads built during the Belgian colonial era to cart away as much gold, ivory, produce and timber as possible. The old palm oil plantations and banana warehouses are still there, but they are sinking into the riverbanks, more jungle-eaten evidence of Mobutu's kingdom of rot.</p>
        <p>''We used to have electricity,'' said Germain Musombo, 38, who lives here in Kindu, a city of 250,000 lighted by candles. ''We used to have a movie theater. We used to have decent roads and a train that could take us to Lubumbashi in three days,'' a distance of 600 miles.</p>
        <p>Now that ride takes an entire month.</p>
        <p>Congo is spread across more than 900,000 square miles, but it has only 300 miles of paved roads. The lack of infrastructure keeps the people poor. Kindu's farmers used to export bananas, wood, rice and peanuts. Now much of their land, among the most fertile in Africa, lies fallow because they cannot get crops to market.</p>
        <p>''''There's only so much you can carry on your head,'''' said the acting governor, Katharina Aziza Sadiki.</p>
        <p>Farther east, the antigovernment frustrations intensify. Kichanga, a little town about 1,000 miles from Kinshasa, lies clearly outside Mr. Kabila's control. It is reachable by a 60-minute United Nations flight from Kindu to Bukavu, a two-hour speedboat ride from Bukavu to Goma and then a three-hour slog up a steep, muddy road.</p>
        <p>The last government checkpoint is in the market town of Sake. After that, boy soldiers in unmarked uniforms march along the roads with rocket-propelled grenades and knee-high rubber boots. Villagers pay taxes not to the Democratic Republic of Congo but to Laurent Nkunda, the local warlord.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nkunda is built like a letter opener -- long, sharp and thin. He is a Tutsi nationalist, and with Hutu death squads still roaming the countryside, Mr. Nkunda sees himself as all that stands between Congolese Tutsis and genocide.</p>
        <p>''The Tutsis who were killed in Rwanda were my friends,'' he said. ''I cannot accept it here.''</p>
        <p>Eastern Congo is probably the most beautiful part of the country, but also the most brutalized and the most confusing. Thousands of lives there have been lost to disease, starvation and a shifting mix of rebel groups.</p>
        <p>The trouble began in 1994, when Rwanda's Hutu ethnic majority turned on the Tutsi minority and 800,000 people were killed. Ever since, Rwanda's Hutu-Tutsi violence has continued to play out across the border in Congo, where both communities have lived for decades.</p>
        <p>But something new is happening, which could help bring stability. The Kabila government, empowered by the elections and freed from having to gain the approval of four rival vice presidents for every decision, is striking deals with a number of warlords, including Mr. Nkunda.</p>
        <p>Sometimes Mr. Kabila has little choice. In November, Mr. Nkunda's forces humiliated government soldiers and advanced to within 10 miles of Goma, one of the biggest cities in eastern Congo. They would have seized it if United Nations peacekeepers had not sent in helicopter gunships.</p>
        <p>''Our national army is a joke,'' said Aloys Tegera, the manager of an aid organization in Goma. ''It's a serious problem. Everybody is celebrating this big moment of democratization, but we're building on sand.''</p>
        <p>In Kichanga, government troops have been placed in an uneasy chain of command under Mr. Nkunda's officers, but it is hard to know whether warlords like Mr. Nkunda are part of the problem or the solution.</p>
        <p>The town of Sake was occupied first by Mr. Nkunda's soldiers, who basically left it alone, and then by government troops, who summarily looted it, residents said. Yet Congolese officials continue to accuse Mr. Nkunda of war crimes, including massacring prisoners of war, though many residents here seem to like him, for obvious reasons.</p>
        <p>''If you're sick, he gives you money,'' said Sesaga Nzabonimba, a farmer near Sake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nkunda said he would rather join the government than strike out on his own. And that may be one of Congo's greatest mysteries -- how after decades of brutal colonial rule, kleptomaniacal dictatorship, ethnic fighting and regional isolation, a faint pulse of nationalism still survives.</p>
        <p>''I am a Tutsi, but more than that, I am Congolese,'' Mr. Nkunda said. ''I truly hope that one day I'll be part of the national army. They need the help.''</p>
        <p>Hundreds Killed in Kinshasa</p>
        <p>KINSHASA, Congo, March 27 (Reuters) -- More than 200 people were killed last week in fighting between the army and a former rebel leader's forces, European Union ambassadors said Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Fighting erupted in Kinshasa on Thursday after troops loyal to Mr. Bemba refused an order to disarm. The clashes continued for two days before his forces were routed.</p>
        <p>''There are fairly clear indications coming from the hospitals and morgues that are giving the number at between 200 and 600,'' said the German ambassador, Karl-Albrecht Wokalek.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
