<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Butcher With Tables Behind the Counter</title>
    <meta content="28unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/28/dining/reviews/28unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20070404T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1836154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DD1330F93BA15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Butcher With Tables Behind the Counter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Butcher With Tables Behind the Counter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meehan, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAS Americas, a carnicería in Sunnyside, Queens, has been serving the meat needs of the Colombian, and greater Latino, communities for nearly 30 years.</p>
        <p>After splitting with his partners in New York's first Colombian butcher shop on Roosevelt Avenue, Libaniel López opened Las Americas on 45th Street in 1978. He and his family moved the shop, now run by Ricardo López, Libaniel's grandson, around the corner to its current location, on Greenpoint Avenue, in 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Las Americas, a carnicería in Sunnyside, Queens, offers a modest restaurant in the back with an inexpensive and tasty menu of trencherman’s fare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAS Americas, a carnicería in Sunnyside, Queens, has been serving the meat needs of the Colombian, and greater Latino, communities for nearly 30 years.</p>
        <p>After splitting with his partners in New York's first Colombian butcher shop on Roosevelt Avenue, Libaniel López opened Las Americas on 45th Street in 1978. He and his family moved the shop, now run by Ricardo López, Libaniel's grandson, around the corner to its current location, on Greenpoint Avenue, in 1999.</p>
        <p>The butcher's counter in the front is certainly the primary concern of the business. But in the back there's a modest restaurant: a few booth tables, a line of stools along a wall and a big, fully equipped open kitchen, with a rotisserie and deck ovens (leftovers from the location's previous incarnation as a pizzeria).</p>
        <p>Las Americas serves an almost impossibly inexpensive menu of trencherman's fare, prepared with a surprisingly light hand. Unlike plenty of other Colombian kitchens in the city, the cooks at Las Americas don't hide behind fat and salt.</p>
        <p>Instead of pizza, the deck ovens at Las Americas are pressed into service for special orders of roast whole pigs -- including lechona tolimense, a baby pig stuffed with rice and peas -- and other celebratory Colombian preparations of the pig, especially popular around the holidays but also on demand for any party.</p>
        <p>And when a cook fries a pounded chop, it's a chuleta de cerdo empanizado ($7.50), not a Milanese. The one at Las Americas is fried until the breading is crisp and nutty brown; the meat is about as tender as you'd expect a pounded and fried piece of meat to be. It's served with a wedge of lime and, like all the main courses at Las Americas, with generous portions of a small salad, a tower of rice rising out of a lagoon of soupy beans and your choice of tostones (the starchy green plantain preparation) or maduros (the more banana-y sweet plantains browned on a grill).</p>
        <p>A cilantro-heavy, loose hot sauce (look for it in a small ceramic crock on the counter) with a chipotle-like kick and smokiness kept me eating the ginormous chop even well after I was no longer hungry. Once you get started, it's difficult not to use it to anoint anything within spoon's reach, and there's almost nothing it won't improve.</p>
        <p>The short Las Americas menu is reliable and cheap; nothing is more than $8. The long Colombian-style empanadas ($1), especially the beef ones, stuffed with a sturdy mix of mashed potatoes and way-tender meat, are a must, more so on weekends when they're hot and fresh.</p>
        <p>Las Americas is hopping on Saturdays, when the butchers get a workout from a sizable cast of locals. It's a convivial atmosphere, where the workers know the customers and the customers seem to know each other.</p>
        <p>For drinks, there's a cooler (the kind that's emptied over a coach's head after a big victory) behind the counter holding the supersweet, lemon-spiked sugarcane juice called aguapanela ($1).</p>
        <p>Since there's no booze at Las Americas, my go-to beverage was a brand of sparkling water called Güitig from Ecuador. The label promised ''Exotic Andean Magic'' and 2 percent of my daily calcium. Added electrolytes have nothing on that.</p>
        <p>In a phone conversation, Mr. López stressed the restaurant's commitment to keeping things affordable at Las Americas. Backing up that claim is the especial del día, always $6 to $8, about as good a deal as any. It changes daily -- on a recent Wednesday afternoon, a dryish but not unlovable quarter chicken, with all the aforementioned sides and a bowl of simple, comforting potato and corn soup, spiked with cilantro, was $6.50 -- but Thursdays and Saturdays are always the same.</p>
        <p>Bandeja Paisa, a platter of grilled steak, fried pork belly, rice, beans, a fried egg and an arepa, is the Thursday special. Mr. López's cooks keep the price nice at $7 by omitting expensive avocado, which you'd probably find on a bandeja plate in Paisa, the northwestern Colombia region that Mr. López's family hails from.</p>
        <p>Saturday is sancocho time. A $7.50 order gets you a bowl of the rustic potato- and cassava-thickened corn and short rib soup called sancocho first. A platter of guiso -- cross-cut short ribs cooked in a meltingly soft and sweet sauce of onions, scallions, tomatoes, garlic and more -- follows. As does satisfaction. And, in the best scenario, maybe a nap.</p>
        <p>Restaurante Las Americas  45-12 Greenpoint Avenue, Sunnyside, Queens; (718) 784-0284.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES Beef empanada; sancocho; corn and potato soup; guiso; fried pork cutlet.  PRICE RANGE Antojitos and other small dishes, $1 to $3.50; main courses, $6 to $8. No alcohol.  CREDIT CARDS Cash only.  HOURS 11:30 a.m. to 7:30 p.m. Monday through Saturday. Sunday 11:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS All on one level; restrooms inaccessible.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 4, 2007, Wednesday  The $25 and Under column last Wednesday, about the Colombian restaurant Las Americas in Queens, referred incorrectly to a region of Colombia that is home to a dish called bandejas Paisa. People who live in Antioquia and other northwestern provinces are colloquially known as Paisas, and the area is known as the Paisa region, but the area is not called Paisa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 4, 2007, Wednesday</p>
        <p>The $25 and Under column last Wednesday, about the Colombian restaurant Las Americas in Queens, referred incorrectly to a region of Colombia that is home to a dish called bandejas Paisa. People who live in Antioquia and other northwestern provinces are colloquially known as Paisas, and the area is known as the Paisa region, but the area is not called Paisa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
