<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharing Space, Saving Identity For Three Faiths</title>
    <meta content="21LIRELI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/21/nyregion/21LONG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031228T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1545018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Protestant Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protestant Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E6DD133FF932A15751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharing Space, Saving Identity For Three Faiths</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sharing Space, Saving Identity for Three Faiths</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on some Protestant churches on Long Island that are sharing their sanctuaries with Jewish and Muslim congregations; Protestant congregations, burdened with high costs ofmaintaining churches, rent out space to other faiths or, more commonly, to other Protestant denominations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE cross, the central symbol of Christianity, will be on the communion table at the Cutchogue Presbyterian Church on Christmas Eve as the small congregation joins Christians around the world in celebrating the birth of Jesus with carols and prayers.</p>
        <p>But soon thereafter, the brass cross, over two feet high, will be tucked away while another small congregation, the North Fork Reform Synagogue, holds Shabbat services in the same sanctuary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Churches have been renting or giving space to Jewish and Muslim congregants for worship services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE cross, the central symbol of Christianity, will be on the communion table at the Cutchogue Presbyterian Church on Christmas Eve as the small congregation joins Christians around the world in celebrating the birth of Jesus with carols and prayers.</p>
        <p>But soon thereafter, the brass cross, over two feet high, will be tucked away while another small congregation, the North Fork Reform Synagogue, holds Shabbat services in the same sanctuary.</p>
        <p>Members of the Jewish congregation will move an ark containing two Torahs, one saved from the Holocaust, from the rear to the center of the chancel for their services, which are the first and third Fridays of each month. In the narthex, the vestibule of the 151-year-old church, they will temporarily replace a large Presbyterian denominational wall hanging with a Star of David quilt.</p>
        <p>''As they say, they transform the church into a synagogue, and when they leave they reverse the process,'' said the Rev. Lynda Clements, the church pastor. ''They do all the schlepping.''</p>
        <p>''We find it a wonderful place to meet, and we do cooperate with each other,'' said Merle Levine of East Marion, the president of the 50-member Reform congregation, which has paid rent to use the church for six years. Recently the two congregations joined in raising funds for a new church organ.</p>
        <p>In a sharing of sanctuary that goes beyond the ecumenical to cross lines of faith, Cutchogue Presbyterian is among a handful of Protestant churches on Long Island that have opened their doors to Jewish congregations.</p>
        <p>For Protestant congregations burdened with high costs of maintaining churches, renting out space -- to other faiths, or, more commonly, to other Protestant denominations -- has become crucial to making ends meet. ''We are so small, and we have such limited resources, it is important to us from a practical point of view,'' Pastor Clements said.</p>
        <p>But the arrangements, particularly when they involve different faiths, are also building bridges of understanding. ''Nobody seems to have any trouble with it,'' Pastor Clements said. ''Everybody feels that it is God's grace in our midst.''</p>
        <p>Others point out that sharing sacred space means it is less often empty. ''Increasingly, people in our churches are saying that they should be used more than just one hour a week,'' said the Rev. Thomas Goodhue, the executive director of the Long Island Council of Churches, a predominantly Protestant group in Hempstead, and a United Methodist minister.</p>
        <p>In Sag Harbor, the First Presbyterian Church, also known as the Old Whalers' Church, has shared space with the Conservative Synagogue of the Hamptons for about five years. ''They use the chapel and we use the sanctuary,'' said the Rev. Susan McKeegan-Guinn, the pastor. ''It's a very close relationship. They are welcomed as friends; we don't think of them as people just renting space.''</p>
        <p>In a typical story for Protestant churches on Long Island whose congregations are dwindling, a sanctuary that seats 700 to 900 people is far more than big enough for the Presbyterians. The chapel, which seats 100, usually suits the needs of the Jewish congregation, which includes about 65 families.</p>
        <p>It is also a space they have come to cherish. ''That chapel is one of the most beautiful, prayerful places I have ever worshiped in,'' said Rabbi Jan Uhrbach, who presides over services held Saturday mornings and many Friday nights.</p>
        <p>As in Cutchogue, the chapel cross is put away when the congregation meets. Two arks, one portable and stored in a church closet and the other stationary in a corner of the chapel, are used.</p>
        <p>''We are blessed with an opportunity for each of us to worship in the way that we do, respectful of each other's traditions but maintaining our own identity,'' Rabbi Uhrbach said, explaining why the cross is removed. ''A cross is a Christian symbol, not a Jewish symbol. It is inappropriate for our worship.''</p>
        <p>On High Holy Days, when the congregation was too large for the chapel, Rabbi Uhrbach said that it met across the street at St. Andrew Roman Catholic Church, where services were held in the social hall.</p>
        <p>At the Brookville Reformed Church, a Protestant church founded by Dutch settlers and located in the same place since 1732, the sharing goes further.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Allan B. Ramirez, the pastor, said the Jewish Congregation of Brookville, a Reform synagogue, had been holding Shabbat services and celebrating bar mitzvahs and bat mitzvahs in the sanctuary for more than six years. About a year ago, he said, the church invited in the Muslim Reformed Movement Organization, which meets on Sunday afternoons.</p>
        <p>All three congregations' names appear on the sign in front of the church. ''It has the names of all three together so they are not the stepchildren, not just somebody who comes in,'' Pastor Ramirez said. ''They have access to all the facilities like anyone else, whether it's the kitchen, the sanctuary or the parish hall.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramirez, the pastor since 1983, said he knew of no parishioners who left his church as a result of the arrangement. ''If they did I would have been glad,'' he said. ''Obviously they don't belong here.''</p>
        <p>He said the Jewish and Muslim groups were free to make voluntary donations but were not charged rent. ''We have never given them an amount, and as long as I am here we never will,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Steven H. Moskowitz, the rabbi of the 150-family Jewish Congregation of Brookville, said it was in its eighth year and had plans to build a synagogue. He said the congregation used the Brookville church for Shabbat services and Hebrew school, but gathered at the C.W. Post campus of Long Island University on the High Holy Days.</p>
        <p>''We are the wandering Jews in some regard, which is not how we plan to stay, but we understand this is how our people started,'' he said. ''But we could not have grown without someone saying, 'Here, use my home.' And Reverend Ramirez has said his home is our home, and that is a wonderful example to all, and to my congregation in particular, of what Christian charity truly means.''</p>
        <p>Pastor Ramirez said the Muslim group, unlike the Jewish congregation, did not remove the cross when it met. ''To them it wasn't even an issue,'' he said. Jesus and Mary are prophets in Islam.</p>
        <p>He said he saw no problem sharing space with a Jewish congregation that did not believe in Christ or with a Muslim group for whom Mohammed was the greatest prophet.</p>
        <p>''I was born and raised within the context of Christianity, which allows me to see that as the revelation of God,'' he said. ''But had I been born a Muslim, or a Jew or a Buddhist, my understanding would have come through their traditions.</p>
        <p>''We are all the children of God. I hope I will never be so arrogant as to think I am the only child of God.''</p>
        <p>Pastor Ramirez said a caretaker removed the Baptismal font and the cup and plate used in communion out of respect for the Jewish congregation at times when it used the church. Rabbi Moskowitz said the Jewish congregation covered the communion table with a Jewish tapestry and used it in services when Cantor Marcey Wagner chanted from the Torah.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Moskowitz, who travels frequently to Israel, spoke of the disbelief he encountered when he told Israeli acquaintances his congregation met in a church. ''They say, 'Oh no, impossible,''' he said. ''And then they say, 'Only in America,' and I say, 'Yes, you are right, that is the power and the beauty of America.'''</p>
        <p>Pastor Ramirez said the sharing went beyond words about interfaith understanding. ''We can either talk about ecumenicalism or we can actually live it out by sharing space, by worshiping together, by working on projects together, and that is ultimately when you come to a better understanding of each other,'' he said. ''I say to the Jews, 'When you are here it is a temple,' and I say to the Muslims, 'When you are here it is a mosque, you don't have to worry about us.'''</p>
        <p>Members of the three congregations joined in the meeting hall in November for prayers and fellowship and to assemble 60 baskets for distribution to needy families on Thanksgiving. In the past, the Jewish congregation has invited the Christian congregation to Passover Seder and in turn has been invited to Christmas Eve services. More recently, the Muslims invited the Jewish and Christian congregations to a dinner breaking the fast of Ramadan.</p>
        <p>A gathering of the three faiths has also taken place at the Cutchogue Presbyterian Church. After the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, the members of the church, the North Fork Reform Synagogue and Muslims invited by Pastor Clements filled the sanctuary for an interfaith service.</p>
        <p>In Sag Harbor, Episcopal, United Methodist and Presbyterian pastors, two rabbis and a priest performed an interfaith Thanksgiving service this year in the chapel at Old Whalers'.</p>
        <p>Joanne Navarro, a spokeswoman for the Roman Catholic Diocese of Rockville Centre, said parish churches on Long Island sometimes opened temporarily to other denominations. ''It doesn't happen frequently here because other denominations are able to build their own churches,'' she said. When sharing occurred, she said, it was usually with Episcopal and Lutheran congregations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Navarro said that when St. Andrew's, a Catholic church in Syosset, burned down several years ago, Faith Lutheran Church, also in Syosset, offered the Catholic parish space for weddings and funerals while the parish rebuilt.</p>
        <p>Protestant churches often make space for one or more other Protestant denominations. The Episcopal Church of the Nativity in Mineola, which has about 60 members, provides a home for Korean Presbyterian and Seventh-day Adventist congregations, said the church organist, Daniel W. Mason of Hempstead.</p>
        <p>Nativity is also part of ELP, an interdenominational group formed four years ago whose name is an acronym for Episcopal, Lutheran and Presbyterian. Nativity and the two other members, the Lutheran Church of Our Savior in Mineola and the First Presbyterian Church of Mineola, operate a food pantry and work together in other community programs.</p>
        <p>''We recognize that society is in a tailspin in terms of morality,'' Mr. Mason said. ''At least we are trying to take baby steps to meet some of the needs in our own community.''</p>
        <p>Different faiths routinely work together in charitable pursuits. Jean Kelly, the executive director of the Interfaith Nutrition Network in Hempstead, a network of 19 church soup kitchens, said volunteers learned much from one another.</p>
        <p>At a soup kitchen in Huntington, she recalled, two women, one a Catholic and the other a Baptist, struck up a friendship while buttering bread. ''Afterward,'' Ms. Kelly said, ''the Catholic woman told me: 'I just found out she was a Baptist and I was always told to be afraid of Baptists. But we buttered our bread the same way, out to the edges.</p>
        <p>''We are all coming from the same place. Ultimately, we are all the same.''</p>
        <p>Long Island  Correction:  December 28, 2003, Sunday  An article on Dec. 21 about houses of worship that are shared by congregations of different faiths misidentified a Roman Catholic church in Syosset that burned several years ago. It is St. Edward's, not St. Andrew's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 28, 2003, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Dec. 21 about houses of worship that are shared by congregations of different faiths misidentified a Roman Catholic church in Syosset that burned several years ago. It is St. Edward's, not St. Andrew's.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
