<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>US. LEADS NATIONS IN SURPRISE BUYING TO PROP UP DOLLAR</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="766033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CURRENCY MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUBIN, ROBERT E (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DF1639F932A35755C0A963958260" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>US. LEADS NATIONS IN SURPRISE BUYING TO PROP UP DOLLAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration and a dozen foreign countries took the currency markets by surprise today, buying billions of dollars in an intervention that appeared to have stopped yet another slump in the dollar.</p>
        <p>After several days of sliding slowly down toward its record lows of mid-April, the dollar bounced back sharply today against the Japanese yen and the German mark. But when trading ended, the dollar had not quite reached the levels that traders said would signal a new stability.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration and a dozen foreign countries took the currency markets by surprise today, buying billions of dollars in an intervention that appeared to have stopped yet another slump in the dollar.</p>
        <p>After several days of sliding slowly down toward its record lows of mid-April, the dollar bounced back sharply today against the Japanese yen and the German mark. But when trading ended, the dollar had not quite reached the levels that traders said would signal a new stability.</p>
        <p>Still, the dollar's recovery contributed to a sharp rally on Wall Street. The Dow Jones industrial average posted its biggest percentage gain in a year, surging 86.46 points, or nearly 2 percent, to a record high of 4,465.14. [Page D1.]</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin issued a statement this morning that described the currency market intervention as consistent with a commitment in April by the United States and six other leading industrial nations to bring about an orderly reversal of the dollar's fall this year.</p>
        <p>"We acted in the exchange markets this morning consistent with the exchange rate objectives expressed in the April 25 G-7 Communique," he said, referring to the Group of Seven nations. "We are prepared to continue to cooperate in exchange markets as appropriate."</p>
        <p>American officials said privately that the Administration also wanted to make clear that it would not use a weak dollar as a weapon in the negotiations with Japan in the contentious trade dispute over American automobiles and auto parts. They also indicated that the White House was leaning toward moving up the date of the next round of talks.</p>
        <p>Previous trans-Pacific trade disputes have produced sharp drops in the dollar that have made Japanese goods more expensive and less salable in the United States.</p>
        <p>But the fall in the dollar has result ed this year in a steady rise in the prices of imported goods. The resulting threat of possible inflation has made it somewhat harder for the Federal Reserve to consider a reduction in interest rates, even though the American economy appears to be slowing.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have also been watching with concern the growing number of indications that the economy may be weak during the 1996 election campaign. Propping up the dollar in currency markets, if successful, allows the  Administration to continue confronting Japan while also leaving the Federal Reserve with the option of lowering interest rates at some point.</p>
        <p>Lawrence B. Lindsey, a governor of the Federal Reserve Board, predicted in an interview this afternoon that the economy was continuing to slow from the torrid growth of late 1994, but would not slip into a recession. "We're going to see continued moderation in the pace of growth, but we're going to have growth," he  said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindsey also acknowledged some concerns about the effect of rising import prices on inflation, but emphasized that imports accounted for only a fraction of the goods and services sold in the United States. "I think it is a matter of  concern but I think the numerical effects are relatively small," he said.</p>
        <p>Currency traders said that if the Administration had not acted to support the dollar, it would have continued its recent decline. "You can characterize today  as a pre-emptive strike before the dollar could test its lows again -- that was  the direction that market sentiment had been building," said Stephen Flanagan, a currency trader at Credit Agricole in New York.</p>
        <p>The dollar settled in New York late this afternoon at 84.54 yen, up 1.68 yen  from Tuesday, after trading as high as 85.28 yen around 9 A.M. after the Federal Reserve and Japanese and European central banks entered the currency markets. It also jumped to 1.4157 marks today from 1.3905 marks. [The dollar showed little change in Asian trading by mid-afternoon on Thursday.]</p>
        <p>Because the dollar did not end trading in New York above 85 yen and 1.42 marks, two key psychological levels, traders said the dollar might still be vulnerable to further attacks by speculators.</p>
        <p>Still, traders cited several reasons why the Administration succeeded in pushing up the dollar today after previous interventions in currency markets this year had failed.</p>
        <p>David F. DeRosa, the director of foreign exchange trading at the Swiss Bank Corporation in New York, said traders were reluctant to bet against the success  of Government purchases of dollars because many traders' profits and losses were calculated today, the last day of the month. That makes traders eager to protect the profits they have already made or minimize the losses they have already suffered.</p>
        <p>Kevin J. Lawrie, a foreign exchange manager at the Mellon Bank in Pittsburgh, said traders were also content to let the dollar rise because they feared that today's currency market intervention might be part of a coordinated international strategy that could include a cut in German interest rates when the top council of the German Bundesbank meets on Thursday. Lower German interest rates would make it less attractive for international investors to put  money there and more attractive for them to buy dollars and invest here.</p>
        <p>For every dollar won in foreign exchange trading, somebody else loses a dollar, and traders said that losses today were probably heavy. The heaviest damage probably was in Asia, where markets were closed when the intervention took place and some traders might not have been able to undo their bets against  the dollar, said Neal M. Soss, a hedge fund manager in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>European money managers may also have had trouble selling other currencies and buying dollars within seconds so as to avoid losses. "It happened today at a time when many Europeans were probably thinking more about lunch than about their positions," Mr. Soss said.</p>
        <p>The decision to intervene in currency markets is made by the Treasury Secretary, Mr. Rubin. But the Federal Reserve actually buys the dollars in exchange for yen and marks from its own reserves and from the Treasury's Exchange Stabilization Fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin used to direct currency trading at Goldman, Sachs and has a reputation as a savvy market strategist. But until now, his record in directing  currency interventions had been mixed.</p>
        <p>Traders had more respect for Mr. Rubin today. "A lot of people have criticized Rubin and his predecessors for not carrying out skillful interventions -- this time they did a pretty good job," Mr. DeRosa of the Swiss  Bank Corporation said.</p>
        <p>CURRENCY MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
