<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax Delinquencies in New York Rising Again</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="465906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROPERTY TAXES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARTLETT, SARAH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DI LORENZO, ALEX 3D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MACKLOWE, HARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB153FF93AA3575BC0A967958260" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax Delinquencies in New York Rising Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BARTLETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARTLETT, SARAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Property-tax delinquencies in New York City are rising again, as they did during the 1970's, when the city last underwent an economic crisis. But city officials do not expect a recurrence of the wave of the abandonments that destroyed neighborhoods across the South Bronx the last time around.</p>
        <p>Many of the new delinquencies are in commercial properties in Manhattan, including a number of buildings owned by some of New York's leading real-estate families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Property-tax delinquencies in New York City are rising again, as they did during the 1970's, when the city last underwent an economic crisis. But city officials do not expect a recurrence of the wave of the abandonments that destroyed neighborhoods across the South Bronx the last time around.</p>
        <p>Many of the new delinquencies are in commercial properties in Manhattan, including a number of buildings owned by some of New York's leading real-estate families.</p>
        <p>City officials see the increase -- 38 percent in the 12 months ended June 30 -- as a result of the real-estate slump and the reluctance of banks to lend to developers. Landlords unable to pay their bills are in effect using the city as a bank: "borrowing" money by not paying property taxes.</p>
        <p>According to the Department of Finance, between June 1990 and June 1991 property-tax delinquencies rose by $86 million, to $315 million, or 3.64 percent of the total tax levy. That is the highest level since 1980, but still a long way from the postwar peak of 7.5 percent that was reached in 1976.</p>
        <p>Of that $86 million increase, 70 percent is owed by owners of commercial buildings, and nearly 20 percent of the total is owed by owners of Manhattan office buildings.</p>
        <p>The finance department's list of those who are delinquent on their property taxes, water or sewage charges includes some well-known names: real-estate developers like Alex di Lorenzo 3d and Harry Macklowe; the Barbizon Hotel; the Prince George, the former welfare hotel, and Bob Guccione, the publisher of Penthouse magazine.</p>
        <p>"It says something about the state of the economy," said Carol O'Cleireacain, the city's Commissioner of Finance. "The real-estate market is in dreadful shape."</p>
        <p>The fact that the city's list of delinquencies includes prominent business organizations has Ms. O'Cleireacain relatively unconcerned by this increase in delinquencies. She views it primarily as a cash-management issue. Others are less sanguine: they see the increase, and the big names involved, as a sign of desperation.</p>
        <p>"This is further evidence that New York is hurting badly," said Steven Spinola, president of the Real Estate Board of New York.</p>
        <p>During the Manhattan real-estate boom of the 1980's, many property owners were sufficiently optimistic about the future to refinance their buildings, taking out larger mortgages on the assumption that property values and rents would keep on rising. But with 20 percent vacancy rates now common in Manhattan properties, and property taxes escalating, many owners are not getting enough cash from their buildings to cover their mortgage, maintenance and tax bill.</p>
        <p>"The cash flow is no longer there on which millions of dollars were lent," said Joel Picker, a lower Manhattan leasing agent for the Galbreath Company. A recent survey by the consulting firm of Hamilton, Rabinovitz &amp; Alschuler found that the number of buildings where operating costs exceeded income increased by 70 percent last year, to almost 10 percent of the 560 buildings that were studied.  Vacancies Surge</p>
        <p>"Every owner has a problem building," said Mr. Spinola, of the Real Estate Board, which paid for the consulting firm's study.</p>
        <p>Consider the problems that have plagued 2 South William Street, the elegant nine-story office building that was built in 1892 and is home to Delmonico's restaurant. In the last 18 months, the vacancy rate has soared over 30 percent, as a law firm, an executive search firm, a brokerage firm and a computer company have all either moved to cheaper quarters in Brooklyn, gone under or taken space in newer office buildings in Manhattan, the building's rental agent said.</p>
        <p>Although a representative of the owner, J. D. Branmaur Inc. refused to comment, the agent, Richard Marcus, said that a building like 2 South William Street can only command rents in the range of $15 a square foot, but has operating costs of $5 to $6 and taxes of $3 to $4 a square foot. When financing costs are thrown in, there is precious little left. According to the Department of Finance, the building's taxes went unpaid for more than a year and the arrears were only cleaned up in June.</p>
        <p>Landlords facing temporary cash shortgages used to ask their banks for short-term lines of credit. But these days few banks are willing to lend to the real-estate industry. An Alternative Banker?</p>
        <p>In the absence of bank loans, the city often becomes the only alternative. Unlike commercial banks, which foreclose on properties fairly promptly, the city waits at least 12 months before initiating foreclosure proceedings. There is then a four-month grace period during which owners who come up with the money can get their buildings back. And the city is willing to negotiate a return of the property to an owner for another 20 months after that.</p>
        <p>As a reward for its patience, the city has been charging a hefty 19 percent interest rate. But many property owners are willing to pay the price.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Cleireacain says the city generally collects about 95 percent of what it is owed within two years.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Mr. Macklowe said that within the last two weeks, the developer settled a $2 million delinquent tax bill that dated to January. The city said it has no record of that payment but acknowledged that there is a delay in its processing.</p>
        <p>And Joseph Neumann, who is reckoned to be the third-largest owner of rentable office space in Manhattan, recently paid back $1.8 million on a building that had been in arrears for more than a year. A spokesman for the company said that in the last two weeks Mr. Neumann had also repaid $2.357 million on two downtown buildings that the city said had been delinquent since January. The city's records do not yet reflect those payments.</p>
        <p>"We've been cutting our costs left, right and center," said Charles Herzka, a vice president at Broadway Management, which manages Mr. Neumann's properties. "We saved up the money and we paid our taxes."</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Cleireacain said the rise in delinquencies has not heightened the city's own financial problems. For starters, the city is collecting handsome interest payments -- albeit not all upfront. But Ms. O'Cleireacain says this does not pose a serious cash-management problem for the city. The numbers are small in relation to a $29 billion budget.</p>
        <p>And since there are always a certain number of slow payers, she simply builds that factor into her revenue forecasts. At the same time that there are new delinquents, the city is collecting payments from old ones who are finally ready to settle their debts.</p>
        <p>Still, not everyone views this new trend with quite so much equanimity. Mr. Spinola says it is hardly a healthy sign when some of New York's most prominent real-estate developers have no choice but to borrow at 19 percent from the city.</p>
        <p>"Other buildings could go into default," he said, "and the city could end up owning office buildings."</p>
        <p>Such a dire scenario seems unlikely, because banks that hold the mortgages on those buildings are likely to intervene rather than let those properties revert to the city. The Glick Organization, for instance, recently defaulted on a property on East 14th Street and the bank which repossessed it, Fidelity New York Federal Savings Bank, is now responsible for repaying $626,624 in delinquent taxes.  814 Buildings Claimed</p>
        <p>Still, the finance department's records indicate that nearly 80 percent of the 48 largest delinquent properties are overdue by more than one year. And the number of buildings that the city has actually been forced to take over rose to 1,586 in 1990, from 930 in 1989. So far this year, the city has claimed 814.</p>
        <p>And many real-estate experts are not optimistic about a quick recovery in the office market. David Shulman, a real-estate analyst at the Wall Street firm of Salomon Brothers, forecasts that when discounted rents for sublet space are taken into account, the "true" vacancy rate could rise to as high as 25 percent in the future.</p>
        <p>Property taxes are also likely to aggravate building owners' problems. The Dinkins administration already has built into its financial plan for the next three years property-tax increases of about $1.6 billion. And some real-estate experts think if the finance department re-assesses buildings to reflect the decline in property values, real tax-rates will have to be raised again to compensate for the shortfall that would otherwise result.</p>
        <p>Typically, when the city raises property-tax rates, as it did recently, commercial property owners are insulated because they can pass those increases directly onto their tenants.</p>
        <p>But in a market where owners are having to offer rent-free periods, generous renovation allowances and other inducements just to attract tenants, many owners have had no choice but to absorb the tax increases themselves. Ms. O'Cleireacain thinks that is one reason the Real Estate Board became such a vociferous opponent of the city's latest round of tax-rate increases.</p>
        <p>"I think it was coming out of their own pockets," she said of owners.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
