<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>She Chases a Life of Wind and Water and Sail</title>
    <meta content="29PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/29/nyregion/29PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1320891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Samantha Heyman</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heyman, Samantha</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson River</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lehigh University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">John, Chris</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5D81730F93AA1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>She Chases a Life of Wind and Water and Sail</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">She Chases a Life of Wind and Water and Sail</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles Samantha Heyman, captain of boat that tours Hudson River to educate those aboard on river's glories and ecology; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SURE, Samantha Heyman runs a tight ship, but the Hudson River sloop Clearwater is hardly an autocracy. ''I don't wear epaulettes,'' says Ms. Heyman, who is, nevertheless, the captain. There is no saluting. Never has there been a mutiny on, or off, the bounty. And no one has ever walked the plank. ''We don't have a plank,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Yet Ms. Heyman is firmly in command as the 32-year-old sloop casts off from the dock at Newburgh, N.Y., on a recent afternoon, poised to make its way upriver against wind and current on a jaunt to Poughkeepsie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Samantha Hyman is a laid back boat captain, but she still runs a tight ship</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SURE, Samantha Heyman runs a tight ship, but the Hudson River sloop Clearwater is hardly an autocracy. ''I don't wear epaulettes,'' says Ms. Heyman, who is, nevertheless, the captain. There is no saluting. Never has there been a mutiny on, or off, the bounty. And no one has ever walked the plank. ''We don't have a plank,'' she says.</p>
        <p>Yet Ms. Heyman is firmly in command as the 32-year-old sloop casts off from the dock at Newburgh, N.Y., on a recent afternoon, poised to make its way upriver against wind and current on a jaunt to Poughkeepsie.</p>
        <p>''Ease your bow!'' she says, and the sloop gains way. Ms. Heyman has been a Clearwater captain since September, one of two skippers who guide the sloop during its sailing season of April through November. She works alternate weeks with John Chris Parker, because this is definitely one of those 24/7 jobs.</p>
        <p>A handful of women command sail-training boats these days on the world's oceans. There are far fewer female captains on the Hudson, but Ms. Heyman knows of at least two ''because I've heard them on the radio.''</p>
        <p>At 5-foot-3, she has a big voice, and there's this resemblance to Jodie Foster as she strides the scarred pine deck in crisp white Old Navy shirt and lived-in jeans. They're accessorized with a knife and a marlinspike (for untangling knots). ''Touch right!'' she calls to the tiller crew, which aims the sloop directly into the five-knot wind. With its 108-foot mast of stained Douglas fir and its 3,000-square-foot mainsail, the Clearwater is designed after the Dutch cargo vessels that once sailed the river's waters.</p>
        <p>It carries 17 crew members and 50 day-trippers on its perpetual educational mission: each year exposing 20,000 ladies, gentlemen and children of all ages to the glories of the Hudson River and the mysteries of its ecology.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the nonprofit Clearwater trains its future crews: every week the sloop gets six new landlubber volunteers. As a result, at the age of 30, Ms. Heyman is not only maximum leader but also den mother for young volunteers and interns, all of whom eat and sleep aboard with the crew. Ms. Heyman's rank has its privilege: she lives in the snug captain's cabin to the left of the main cabin.</p>
        <p>Despite the relentless current, the sloop is making forward progress courtesy of the boat's rebuilt Cummins diesel engine, which powers it majestically beneath the Newburgh-Beacon Bridge under the way-high whoosh of traffic.</p>
        <p>A QUARTER left,'' Ms. Heyman says to the tiller crew, steering to the center of the ancient 40-foot-deep Hudson channel. But the river isn't all sun, fun and puffy Hudson Valley clouds. There is unpredictable traffic. There are tricky shoals and lightning squalls. ''And the wind can get weird,'' she said. ''It can get so nasty so fast.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Heyman grew up in Newton, Mass., where her father was a construction project engineer and her mother was in real estate. At 10, she learned to sail on a Sunfish, but didn't become a hopeless sailophile until 1993, when she delivered her twin brother, Leigh, to his job as a deckhand on the three-mast, 177-foot-long Gazela of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>''I saw this beautiful boat -- how amazing that something so large could be carried by the wind -- and I said, 'I have to do this.' '' So. There she was, a political-science graduate from Lehigh University, signing on as a volunteer in New Orleans, working beside her brother on a return voyage to Philadelphia. ''I loved everything about it, but most of all, I realized I loved being out at sea.''</p>
        <p>Soon she was filling the highly competitive slots on sail-training vessels. In the summer of 1994 she became an apprentice on the Clearwater, eventually rising to bosun, the watery equivalent of maintenance man. She shipped out on the Roseway, a two-masted schooner, helping to sail it down to St. Thomas, weathering Hurricane Gordon.</p>
        <p>Hurricane, you say? ''I like a thrill,'' she said. ''I was always a tomboy when I was a kid.'' You get the picture: skiing since age 7, lacrosse and cross-country skiing teams in high school. Not to mention that stint as a ski instructor in Utah, until she tore up her knee.</p>
        <p>Then she joined the Pride of Baltimore II, a square-topsail schooner, crewing a seven-month trip to Ireland, England, Copenhagen, Stockholm, Oslo and Lisbon. After a return to the Clearwater as first mate (second in command) in 1997, she rejoined the Pride of Baltimore II for its sail to China, Taiwan and Korea.</p>
        <p>Ms. Heyman is boyfriend-free right now. She is committed to making a career in the ''education-based sailing'' universe. ''My dream is to have a program for young girls -- they'd learn about challenges, and the sea.''</p>
        <p>After nearly three hours and roughly 18 miles on the river, she reaches the dock in Poughkeepsie, yells ''Full right,'' and winds it all up with a brisk ''Make 'em all fast!'' Mission accomplished. Any regrets? ''Just a small one, that I don't have a chance to get out to sea,'' she says. ''You miss the freedom of it. The community of it. The challenge of it. Sailing for 24 hours a day.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
