<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nothing Like the Suns, Thomas Mixes It Up</title>
    <meta content="10suns" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/10/sports/basketball/10suns.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1846312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/San Antonio Spurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Phoenix Suns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Phoenix Suns</org>
        <org class="online_producer">San Antonio Spurs</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Kurt</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nash, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Duncan, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D61731F933A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nothing Like the Suns, Thomas Mixes It Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nothing Like the Suns, Thomas Mixes It Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Phoenix Suns ran a footrace against one another in practice, Kurt Thomas might well finish last.</p>
        <p>Steve Nash could probably lap him. Leandro Barbosa could possibly beat him with his shoelaces tied together. Even Eric Piatkowski would have an edge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Knick Kurt Thomas gives Phoenix some semblance of balance  a little defense to complement the offense, a little strength to go along with the speed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the Phoenix Suns ran a footrace against one another in practice, Kurt Thomas might well finish last.</p>
        <p>Steve Nash could probably lap him. Leandro Barbosa could possibly beat him with his shoelaces tied together. Even Eric Piatkowski would have an edge.</p>
        <p>''I really don't think I'm as slow as people say,'' Thomas said.</p>
        <p>He has made the mistake of surrounding himself with the swiftest players in the National Basketball Association. At 6-foot-9, 245 pounds, Thomas does not seem to fit on the Phoenix roster. He is too big, too quiet and he absorbs too much heavy contact.</p>
        <p>The Suns are all about offense; Thomas is known for defense. The Suns love the fast break; Thomas is most comfortable in the halfcourt. The Suns score with a flurry of 3-pointers and reverse dunks; Thomas makes his living with a bunch of 15-foot jumpers.</p>
        <p>''He is one of those guys you can definitely say puts his hard hat on,'' Nash said.</p>
        <p>In Phoenix, where hard hats are about as common as ski caps, Thomas does not dress like most of his teammates. Clad in basic jeans and a buttoned-down work shirt, Thomas said, ''The guys here mess with my outfit all the time.''</p>
        <p>If the Suns were looking out for Thomas's best interest, they would probably ship him to some Eastern Conference team, maybe back to the Knicks, and let him perform his dirty work in an environment where it is truly appreciated.</p>
        <p>But the Suns need Thomas, if only because he represents everything they are not. Thomas gives Phoenix some semblance of balance -- a little defense to complement the offense, a little strength to go along with the speed.</p>
        <p>Against most teams, the Suns can win as normally constituted, without a bruiser in the paint. But against the San Antonio Spurs, small ball does not necessarily run smoothly. For years, the Spurs have pushed around the Suns like a scrawny younger brother.</p>
        <p>When Phoenix Coach Mike D'Antoni put Thomas into the starting lineup for Game 2 against the Spurs on Tuesday night, he was basically abandoning his trademark system before the most important game of the season.</p>
        <p>D'Antoni knew that Thomas's presence would slow down the Suns, but he also believed that Thomas could slow down the Spurs' best player, Tim Duncan. As usual, Thomas's contribution in the game was hard to quantify, but impossible to ignore.</p>
        <p>With Thomas guarding Duncan man-to-man, the Suns were able to put Shawn Marion on San Antonio's Tony Parker, holding him to 13 points. The Suns were also able to free Amare Stoudemire from Duncan duty, enabling him to collect 27 points.</p>
        <p>Duncan still managed 29 points, but he was in foul trouble by the end of the first half and looked worn down late in the game. He scored only two points in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>''I think it helped Amare,'' Duncan said. ''They decided to let Kurt deal with me.''</p>
        <p>Phoenix beat the Spurs, 101-81, evening this second-round series at one game apiece, with a three-day layoff before Game 3 in San Antonio. In one night, the Suns' entire strategy for the series seemed to switch.</p>
        <p>The Suns won the game by going big, toughening their defense and relying on a player who is unlike the rest of them. Phoenix is composed mainly of talented young wings who like to take a lot of shots, score a lot of points and get the proper glory.</p>
        <p>Thomas, who spent seven seasons with the Knicks, is used to sliding out of the limelight. He and Jalen Rose, another former Knick, have tried to persuade their young teammates to think less about individual status and more about overall success.</p>
        <p>''When you've got a bunch of guys going through the same stage at the same time, they can step on each other's toes,'' Rose said. ''You get everybody shooting for the same thing and it becomes oversaturated. Someone like Kurt shows you how to accept a role.''</p>
        <p>The Suns acquired Thomas from the Knicks in 2005, as part of the Quentin Richardson deal, in part because they needed a big body for Duncan and the Spurs. When Thomas arrived in Phoenix, he felt as though he were going back to his college days at Texas Christian, when the Horned Frogs treated games like 40-minute wind sprints.</p>
        <p>At T.C.U., Thomas fed off the frenetic pace, once leading the nation in scoring. The Suns, however, are significantly faster than the Horned Frogs, and Thomas could not always keep up with them in practices or in games.</p>
        <p>He spent much of last season on the injured list, along with Stoudemire, depriving the Suns of any interior threat. But now that Thomas and Stoudemire are both in the lineup, small ball seems to be changing slightly.</p>
        <p>The Suns are not about to turn into the Spurs or the Pistons, halting tempo and holding teams to 75 points. But they may slow down this series enough to enjoy it.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
