<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WINNERS, BY KNOCKOUT</title>
    <meta content="23VECS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/23/sports/baseball/23VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1336420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pettitte, Andy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DC1731F930A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WINNERS, BY KNOCKOUT</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fans Hope the Party Continues</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses outlook for New York Yankees in World Series against Arizona Diamondbacks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The older Yankees notice, and so does the mayor. Through all the rollicking postseason times of the past seven years, it has never been quite this loud, never quite this happy.</p>
        <p>Strangers were high-fiving strangers as they walked down the ramps of the old ballpark last night. They were chortling and skipping and singing along to Sinatra's upbeat version of ''New York, New York'' as if they had inhaled pure oxygen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fans have shown a need for release ever since the city took the big hit on Sept. 11. The Yankees have been providing it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The older Yankees notice, and so does the mayor. Through all the rollicking postseason times of the past seven years, it has never been quite this loud, never quite this happy.</p>
        <p>Strangers were high-fiving strangers as they walked down the ramps of the old ballpark last night. They were chortling and skipping and singing along to Sinatra's upbeat version of ''New York, New York'' as if they had inhaled pure oxygen.</p>
        <p>The giddiness level seems higher than it has ever been after the Yankees dispatched the Mariners, 12-3, at Yankee Stadium to win yet another American League pennant.</p>
        <p>''I've never heard the crowd this enthusiastic,'' said Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who has been a real hero in the important business of keeping the city going.</p>
        <p>''There's no question this city needs a lift,'' the mayor said in the clubhouse with just the slightest reek of Champagne. ''The World Series is going to be played here.''</p>
        <p>The Series is coming here because the old guys and the young guys who had seemed suspect a month ago were now doing exactly what Yankee teams have done in other Octobers, but this time it seems like pure joy.</p>
        <p>The fans have shown a need for release ever since the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11. Nobody has called for the Yankees to win for the city because that would be a burden the players do not need, but there is definitely a link between the performers and their audience.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees and the NY we wear on our cap when we play the games, we feel we are representing more than the Yankees now, with what New York and the rest of the country have gone through since the 11th of September,'' Joe Torre said before last night's game.</p>
        <p>Then he added, ''I don't think it would be fair for me to say that that's been our motivation because we've done this before this tragedy, and we've always been a highly motivated team.''</p>
        <p>''But for sure they are in our thoughts regularly,'' Torre said of the uniformed workers at the center of the horror.</p>
        <p>Even for the fans who may be a degree or two removed from ground zero, these games have presented a potential for momentarily forgetting.</p>
        <p>''New York needs this,'' George Steinbrenner, the owner, said Sunday night. ''This is good for the city, but we haven't won this yet.''</p>
        <p>He would not be complacent last night, even with the fans making the Stadium rock with their feet and their voices. By winning at home, the Yankees gave their best starters a few days to rest up before matching the buzz saw of Curt Schilling and Randy Johnson.</p>
        <p>The World Series against Arizona will come soon enough. In the past, Yankee fans greeted each October victory with a swagger. All those gloomy legends amassed in the monuments behind center field and all those booming pregame history film clips seem to induce a bristling sense of entitlement.</p>
        <p>''It's not the uniform,'' Lou Piniella of the Mariners asserted before last night's game. ''You can put purple and green on this bunch over there, and they are going to play well.''</p>
        <p>The poor Mariners won 116 games during the regular season, then had the misfortune of running into three-quarters of a century of tradition, plus one extremely talented team in the present tense.</p>
        <p>And afterward, Piniella volunteered that in the middle of the whipping he was taking, he had looked around at the happy fans and felt good for the city where he used to play.</p>
        <p>The Yankees imposed their real or imaginary mystique in only three of their six postseason games in the Stadium, but Alfonso Soriano's game-ending homer on Sunday and last night's early cluster of runs touched off a lighthearted celebration.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's the balmy weather. The Stadium turns more ominous when true fall sets in. The feet and hands are colder. The first couple of beers turn people sour and aggressive. The extra layers of clothing cause people to bump into each other in the narrow alleyways built back in 1923, when people were smaller and, dare one say it, more self-controlled.</p>
        <p>Now that the Yanks have settled it in front of the home folks, the ever-present Challenger, the nonreleasable American bald eagle, can point toward next Tuesday's third game and the Sunshine Boys tandem of Yogi Berra and Phil Rizzuto can store up their energy for their nightly stint of throwing out the first pitch.</p>
        <p>They've got the big-game routine down pat in the Bronx. Once you get through the barricades, there is the feeling of a city that hopes this happy little party has no curfew.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
