<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Influence in Gardens</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="188620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="INSPIRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DB1530F935A25753C1A96E948260" item-length="1685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Influence in Gardens</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allen Lacy; Allen Lacy's anthology, ''The American Gardener: A Sampler,'' was published last spring by Farrar Straus and Giroux.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: If James van Sweden and Wolfgang Oehme have their way, the American residential landscape is in for some major changes by the time the 21st century rolls around. Already, their landscape architecture firm, Oehme, van Sweden &amp; Associates, founded in 1975 and based in Washington, has won kudos for its fresh style of garden design.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: If James van Sweden and Wolfgang Oehme have their way, the American residential landscape is in for some major changes by the time the 21st century rolls around. Already, their landscape architecture firm, Oehme, van Sweden &amp; Associates, founded in 1975 and based in Washington, has won kudos for its fresh style of garden design.</p>
        <p>If James van Sweden and Wolfgang Oehme have their way, the American residential landscape is in for some major changes by the time the 21st century rolls around. Already, their landscape architecture firm, Oehme, van Sweden &amp; Associates, founded in 1975 and based in Washington, has won kudos for its fresh style of garden design. Dramatically unlike anything ever seen in America, theirs is truly a garden for all seasons, marked by lush plantings of decorative grasses and massed bold-colored perennials that blend with the landscape and can be viewed with interest all year long.</p>
        <p>Oehme and van Sweden are in the forefront of a horticultural movement that has received many labels, among them the ''new American garden,'' the ''new romantic garden,'' and the ''American garden revolution.'' The word ''American,'' however, is not entirely apropos, considering that van Sweden studied in the Netherlands and that Oehme was born and educated in Germany. The European - and especially German - influence on their thought about what a garden should be and what it should contain is strong. Nowhere is it more obvious than in the heavy use of ornamental grasses, which the Germans have held in high favor for most of this century, a predilection for pools and fountains and the downplaying of the importance of lawns.</p>
        <p>Of the sizable body of work carried out over the past decade by the firm, about half of their commissions are private. (Public commissions include an eight-acre park of rolling meadows and athletic fields planned for Battery Park City on the Hudson River in Manhattan.) Their approach is a direct challenge to the established ideas about residential gardens set forth in the late 19th century by such figures as Frank J. Scott. In his highly influential book, ''The Art of Beautifying Suburban Home Grounds of Small Extent'' (1870), Scott successfully advocated the American garden as a lawn open to the street, with foundation plantings of evergreens tightly corseting the house, and a minimum of herbaceous flowering plants. The paradoxical result has been that private property became virtually public space, and that grounds required a high level of maintenance, since, to look their best, lawns must be weeded, mowed, fertilized and watered, and foundation plantings pruned, so they do not block windows and plunge interiors into gloom.</p>
        <p>Oehme and van Sweden have challenged this well-established approach with ideas of their own. They have, in essence, reclaimed the garden as a private space for its owners. One of the first steps Oehme usually takes when beginning a new project, he says, is to remove the foundation plantings around the house, transferring the taller shrubs such as yews toward the street, where they may grow in their natural shape, unclipped, and where they help provide a screen for privacy. In their view, the garden is not meant to be seen from the road, nor is it desirable that it be taken in at a single glance. It should be a place, according to van Sweden, where there are constant surprises - an unexpected little fountain around the corner, for example, a fine collection of ferns or an immense clump of Hosta sieboldiana, with its dramatically large, slightly bluish leaves.</p>
        <p>Other surprises may take place with the passage of time. ''I think of a garden as a three-dimensional sculpture,'' observes van Sweden. ''But it's designed in the dimension of time as well as the other three. You're looking at it under constantly changing conditions of light and shadow on any day, and you're also looking at it throughout the entire year.''</p>
        <p>In keeping with their goal of a landscape that has interest all year round, Oehme and van Sweden's plant ''vocabulary'' is strong in decorative grasses and other plants that change with the seasons. The ornamental grasses that they favor are beautiful throughout the year. They are also quite diverse, ranging in size from the six-inch mounds of dwarf blue fescue (Festuca ovina glauca) to the giant miscanthus (Miscanthus floridulus), capable of exceeding 12 feet. Some are the shade of green one expects of grass, but others have striped foliage, or leaves that tend toward purple or blue or that are tipped with scarlet. Their plumes, on close inspection, may have a pink, silver or bronze cast. The one thing that may be said of all these grasses is that they're constantly changing, from late spring, when they first begin dramatic growth, to winter, when their plumes, now faded to tan and parchment, rustle in the wind.</p>
        <p>Another technique that distinguishes the designs of this firm is their highly visible use of herbaceous perennials, planted in bold masses of each kind to exploit every possible contrast in form, texture and color and achieve aesthetic unity. These too are chosen for their ever-changing forms and colors. A fine example is the Sedum telephium 'Autumn Joy' (hybridized in Germany), which they frequently select. This tall perennial has attractive succulent, grayish-green leaves from its first appearance in early spring. In midsummer, flattened pale-green clusters of flower buds appear. By August they open, showing creamy ivory blossoms, the first color in a progression that moves to pale pink, deep rose, russett, copper and, finally, the dark mahogany of the seed heads, which remain handsome in winter, especially against a background of snow. Another example is Rudbeckia fulgida 'Goldsturm,' a kind of black-eyed Susan, which blooms for a period of about three months and then develops dark-colored seed heads that last through the winter. Among the woody plants favored by the firm is the hybrid Chinese witch hazel 'Arnold Promise,' which blossoms in January or February, producing bright bursts of highly fragrant tiny yellow flowers.</p>
        <p>A final concern of Oehme and van Sweden's is that of reducing the work of the gardener. While the grasses require only an annual cutting back in late winter, the other plants they choose must be tough, able to withstand the stress of drought, tolerate a moderate degree of neglect and call for a low level of annual maintenance. But the two reject the notion of a ''no-maintenance'' garden.</p>
        <p>''There's no such thing,'' van Sweden says flatly. ''All gardens require care and tending, or they cease to be gardens. What is possible, through careful plant selection, is to reduce the level of maintenance to something that a homeowner can take care of himself, in his spare moments, without having to hire someone to come in to mow and weed every week and do a lot of trimming and pruning.''</p>
        <p>Asked about future trends in American residential landscaping, Oehme and van Sweden unhesitatingly say, ''Water.'' Ninety percent of the gardens their firm has recently completed or has on its drawing boards involve water, and in 60 percent it is something other than a swimming pool - such as a fountain, a small pool or even a large pond. (Van Sweden returned from a recent trip to Japan with the conviction that a pool should be big, ''the bigger the better.'') Of utmost importance, naturally, are the plantings surrounding them, and here again grasses and perennials are in evidence as well as those plants particularly suited to the site. Oehme points out that the fastest-growing segment of the nursery business in the United States is that which specializes in aquatic and bog plants for the edges of ponds. ''I go to Germany every year to look for new plants,'' he says, ''and among the aquatics there are some recent introductions that are very exciting.'' These include, among others, dwarf cattails, double marsh marigolds, which bloom in spring, and pickerelweed, which flowers in the summer months.</p>
        <p>Visitors to West Germany and its private gardens know that gardeners there who don't already have a pond in their backyard, designed in such a way that it contains a natural balance of life (plants, fish, snails, beneficial bacteria and other micro-organisms), are most likely planning to install one. In this regard, in our own country, James van Sweden and Wolfgang Oehme, with their belief that the landscape should reflect the natural order of things, are probably in the vanguard. Where the lawn once was, we may, in time, have a surface of water to mirror our gracefully waving grasses and great masses of colorful perennials.  A SELECT SAMPLING OF PLANTS</p>
        <p>In addition to Sedum telephium 'Autumn Joy' and Rudbeckia fulgida 'Goldsturm,' other perennials and ornamental grasses that frequently appear in the gardens of Oehme, van Sweden &amp; Associates include the following:</p>
        <p>Astilbe x arendsii 'Deutschland': fine dark-green foliage, with plumes of creamy white flowers in summer, followed by handsome seed heads</p>
        <p>Calamagrostis acutiflora 'Karl Foerster': a medium-sized (up to five feet in height) ornamental grass, with erect stalks of light tan flowers fading to ivory in the autumn</p>
        <p>Ceratostigma plumbaginoides: a low ground cover with lustrous green foliage tinged with bronze and attractive sapphire flowers</p>
        <p>Hosta sieboldiana 'Elegans': one of the largest of all hostas, eventually reaching three or more feet in height and as much across, with handsome, immense, puckered leaves toned blue until midsummer</p>
        <p>Hypericum hidcote: drought tolerant, a continuous bloomer until frost, bearing single golden flowers</p>
        <p>Liriope muscari: a tough and undemanding ground cover with straplike, glossy evergreen foliage and purple spikes of bloom in early fall</p>
        <p>Miscanthus sinensis 'Gracillimus': a medium-sized ornamental grass, somewhat rounded in form, with unusually graceful and delicate plumes</p>
        <p>Stachys byzantina (Lamb's Ears): a low, sprawling ground cover, with velvety silver leaves (also known as Stachys lanatus)</p>
        <p>Yucca filamentosa: an American native evergreen plant, notable for its huge rosettes of sharp leaves and tall stalks of cream-colored blooms in early summer Two mail-order nurseries that carry these and other plants with year-round interest: Kurt Bluemel, 2740 Greene Lane, Baldwin, Md. 21013 (catalog: $2), and Andre Viette Farm and Nursery, Route 1, Box 16, Fishersville, Va. 22939 (catalog: $2).</p>
        <p>INSPIRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
