<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Restoring a Forest Goes Slowly, and Advocates Seethe</title>
    <meta content="04FORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/04/science/earth/04FORE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1469512"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDE163FF937A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Restoring a Forest Goes Slowly, and Advocates Seethe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Restoring a Forest Goes Slowly, and Advocates Seethe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <dateline>MISSOULA, Mont.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the summer of 2000, fires roared through the tinder-dry Bitterroot National Forest, cloaking the valley in dense smoke for weeks, blackening more than 300,000 acres and destroying 70 private homes in a valley that is a bedroom community for this university town.</p>
        <p>Now the restoration of the forest has become the focus of a dispute between environmental groups and the United States Forest Service. A coalition of local and national environmental groups say the agency is breaking a promise to move the restoration along quickly. The Forest Service acknowledges that the work has been delayed by budget shortages but insists that it will be completed in three to five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The restoration of Montana's Bitterroot National Forest has become the focus of a dispute between environmental groups and the United States Forest Service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the summer of 2000, fires roared through the tinder-dry Bitterroot National Forest, cloaking the valley in dense smoke for weeks, blackening more than 300,000 acres and destroying 70 private homes in a valley that is a bedroom community for this university town.</p>
        <p>Now the restoration of the forest has become the focus of a dispute between environmental groups and the United States Forest Service. A coalition of local and national environmental groups say the agency is breaking a promise to move the restoration along quickly. The Forest Service acknowledges that the work has been delayed by budget shortages but insists that it will be completed in three to five years.</p>
        <p>An analysis by the environmental groups found that of 33,150 acres planned for reforestation, only 4,000 acres had been planted, and that watershed and road restoration was going even more slowly. The Forest Service has completed just 13 of 500 miles of road upgrades to accommodate increased timber hauling and prevent runoff from substandard roads. The agency has obliterated just half a mile of the 45 miles of roads planned for elimination.</p>
        <p>''The Forest Service always says we have to trust them,'' said Robert Ekey, who, as Northern Rockies regional director for the Wilderness Society, was a party to negotiations last year that produced the agreement on restoration. ''This illustrates why we don't trust them. They always break their promise.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists also say the agency's three- to five-year time frame is too long. The longer the restoration work goes undone, some scientists say, the greater the effects on forest ecosystems -- especially to two species of trout, the west slope cutthroat and the federally protected bull trout. Heavy silt in streams can also suffocate fish eggs and kill adult fish by blocking their gills.</p>
        <p>''Some of these roads are generating tremendous concentrations of runoff,'' said Dr. Chris Frissell, a fisheries biologist and watershed scientist with the Pacific Rivers Council, a conservation group. ''I've never seen streams muddier.''</p>
        <p>The Forest Service replies that it is under severe budget constraints, largely as a result of last year's destructive wave of forest fires in other states. The fires cost the agency $1.2 billion, more than four times its annual firefighting budget. The agency shifted $919 million from other uses to fires, including $25.5 million for restoration on the Bitterroot.</p>
        <p>''Those funds were withdrawn to protect life and property,'' said Spike Thompson, a deputy forest supervisor on the Bitterroot. ''We understand that.''</p>
        <p>Congress's 2003 spending bill included just $636 million in reimbursement, so many restoration and research projects around the country will get less than planned. Officials also warn that another record fire season this year may mean even less money for such projects.</p>
        <p>The roots of the Bitterroot dispute can be traced to the three-way tug-of-war between environmentalists, the Forest Service and the timber industry. Environmentalists say one reason the Bitterroot is so carefully watched is that the forest has a long history of abuse, including years of clear-cutting and extensive networks of logging roads that have compromised many forest ecosystems.</p>
        <p>The year after the fires here, Bitterroot forest officials proposed to sell 41,000 acres of burned timber, equivalent to 10 years' worth of logging. Calling the sale and associated restoration a ''burned area recovery plan,'' they said removing dead trees was important to head off future fires.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists maintained that the burned area recovery plan was just an old-fashioned timber-salvage sale with a new spin. The Forest Service replied that forest health, including the removal of roads to prevent stream sedimentation, was first and foremost.</p>
        <p>''It is imperative that we move forward with the project to help restore the land and prevent further environmental degradation,'' Dale Bosworth, the chief of the Forest Service, said last year.</p>
        <p>Timber companies said the longer the burned trees stood, the lower their value. When the Forest Service tried to hasten logging by shortcutting a public appeals process, environmental groups responded by filing a lawsuit.</p>
        <p>A federal judge ruled in the environmentalists' favor, forcing the two sides to talk. Last year, Chief Bosworth and Mark Rey, an under secretary of agriculture who is a former timber lobbyist, agreed to about 14,000 acres of timber cutting, down from the Forest Service's original proposal of 41,000 acres.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frissell, of the Pacific Rivers Council, says the logging has generally had minimal effect on streams. But Larry Campbell, a spokesman for another environmental group, Friends of the Bitterroot, said the salvage logging now taking place had cut far too many big trees, which the Forest Service said it would leave.</p>
        <p>''Ecologically they are the most valuable,'' Mr. Campbell said. ''The only moisture available in a burned forest is inside these nurse logs'' -- the logs in which new trees and other plants establish themselves.</p>
        <p>Grasses have come back after the fire, but vast swaths of blackened trees that look like burned matches are still the most dominant feature of the forest in many places where the fires burned.</p>
        <p>The Forest Service acknowledged last month that it had accidentally allowed the cutting of 10 large trees that were important to shading a creek in the burned area. Rather than allow timber companies to take them, the agency ordered them left on the ground.</p>
        <p>The salvage sale, which started last summer and is still going on, is being conducted under a microscope. The Bitterroot is one of the state's most watched forests because it lies close to the ecologically minded town of Missoula.</p>
        <p>''If they can't get it right on the Bitterroot, where everyone is watching and the chief and under secretary are involved,'' said Matthew Koehler, the director of the Native Forest Network, an environmental group critical of last year's negotiations, ''they can't get it right anywhere.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
