<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>So Many Knots, Inspector, And Time Is Running Out</title>
    <meta content="22WERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/22/arts/22WERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1272615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thaw, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mystery! (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Remorseful Day, The: The Inspector Morse Finale (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Last Morse, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">robberies_and_thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">police_brutality_and_misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oxford</location>
        <org class="online_producer">PBS</org>
        <org class="online_producer">aid</org>
        <org class="online_producer">uses</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DD1439F931A15751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>So Many Knots, Inspector, And Time Is Running Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews The Remorseful Day: The Inspector Morse Finale, which is preceded by The Last Morse, documentary in which John Thaw and others associated with series look back upon it; they are part of PBS's Mystery! series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Why it that Chief Inspector Morse never seems to smile?</p>
        <p>''He's just saddened and disturbed and upset by the fact that a fellow human being could do this,'' says John Thaw, the actor who has portrayed Morse, the English detective, through 33 cases since 1988. What Morse's fellow human beings do, of course, is kill one another. Eighty-one residents of Oxford and environs have gone to their rewards on Morse's watch, which ends, alas, tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Why it that Chief Inspector Morse never seems to smile?</p>
        <p>''He's just saddened and disturbed and upset by the fact that a fellow human being could do this,'' says John Thaw, the actor who has portrayed Morse, the English detective, through 33 cases since 1988. What Morse's fellow human beings do, of course, is kill one another. Eighty-one residents of Oxford and environs have gone to their rewards on Morse's watch, which ends, alas, tonight.</p>
        <p>The final drama, ''The Remorseful Day,'' part of ''Mystery!'' on PBS, is preceded by an hourlong documentary, ''The Last Morse,'' in which Mr. Thaw and others associated with the series look back upon it with appropriately wistful affection.</p>
        <p>Calling Morse ''a poor policeman but a good detective,'' Mr. Thaw seems genuinely sad (albeit with a properly Morseian reserve) to bid farewell to his alter ego, that crossword-solving snob who works his way through the knottiest problem with the aid of generous helpings of alcohol and Wagner. That sadness is shared by Kevin Whately, who plays Morse's long-suffering assistant, Sergeant Lewis, and admits that he never expects to enjoy another assignment as much.</p>
        <p>The documentary proudly notes that the Morse series has been seen by 85 percent of the British population and has had a total worldwide audience of a billion viewers. So why end it now? The answer, such as it is, comes from Colin Dexter, who created Morse and sent him trailing all those evildoers in a string of novels (and who has a Hitchcockian walk-on in each of the television films).</p>
        <p>''I think we killed enough people in Oxford,'' Mr. Dexter says with a scampish grin.</p>
        <p>A few more will succumb in tonight's mystery, which finds the inspector seriously ill and just weeks from retirement. Ignoring the advice of his doctor to stop drinking and of his boss, Chief Superintendent Strange (James Grout), to take it easy, Morse plunges into the task of revisiting an unsolved case that is reopened by an anonymous letter implicating a man about to be released from prison.</p>
        <p>The plot, filled with the usual serpentine twists and all-too-flawed characters, casts a tantalizing bit of light on Morse's personal life. Though he is facing the ultimate deadline, Morse uses his superior intelligence to sort things out.</p>
        <p>But guessing whodunit has never been the point with Morse's cases. The satisfaction here, as in the past, comes from watching Mr. Thaw put the detective through his paces, locating that kernel of believability in the man to make yet another far-fetched tale seem real.</p>
        <p>As before, Morse finds solace not only in Wagner and beer but in his favorite poet, A. E. Housman, whom he quotes in his despair:</p>
        <p>Past touch and sight and sound</p>
        <p>Not further to be found,</p>
        <p>Now hopeless under ground</p>
        <p>Falls the remorseful day.</p>
        <p>Those who have watched the relationship of Morse and Lewis over the years will note its changes as the two approach their professional parting, a shift handled deftly by both actors. At this late date, Lewis is still trying to please Morse, even as the younger man hopes the older one's retirement may open the way for a long-delayed promotion.</p>
        <p>''I'll be an inspector soon, if there's any justice in the world,'' Lewis says with a just bit of hope.</p>
        <p>Morse replies, ''I'm not sure there is.''</p>
        <p>Sigh. If there were, this would not be Morse's last case.</p>
        <p>THE REMORSEFUL DAY  The Inspector Morse Finale  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>Chris Burt, producer; written by Stephen Churchett, based on the novel by Colin Dexter; Jack Gold, director; Ted Childs, Rebecca Eaton and John Thaw, executive producers; Barrington Pheloung, composer.</p>
        <p>WITH: John Thaw (Chief Inspector Morse), Kevin Whately (Sergeant Lewis), James Grout (Chief Superintendent Strange), Meg Davies (Yvonne Harrison), Eddie Webber (Harry Repp), Anna Wilson-Jones (Sandra Harrison), Paul Freeman (Frank Harrison), James Benson (Paddy Flynn), Clare Holman (Dr. Laura Hobson), T. P. McKenna (Sir Lionel Phelps), Helen Pearson (Debbie Repp), Jesse Birdsall (John Barron), Aidan J. David (Roy Holmes), Simon Hepworth (Simon Harrison), Barbara Lott (Mrs. Bayley), Annette Ekblom (Mrs. Holmes), Sharon Maiden (Linda Barron), Alisa Bosschaert (Josie Flynn) and Barrington Pheloung (Choir Master).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
