<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Primer for Back-to-School Furnishings</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="785839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DF153CF932A0575BC0A963958260" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Primer for Back-to-School Furnishings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY JACK WARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DROVES of parents and school-age children (in small, medium and large sizes) are now preparing for earlier bedtimes, school bus schedules and -- groan -- homework.</p>
        <p>By choosing age-appropriate furnishings tailored to the right size, parents can help young people create personalized places for studying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DROVES of parents and school-age children (in small, medium and large sizes) are now preparing for earlier bedtimes, school bus schedules and -- groan -- homework.</p>
        <p>By choosing age-appropriate furnishings tailored to the right size, parents can help young people create personalized places for studying.</p>
        <p>Ikea shines when it comes to small-size designs for children. The self-serve home-furnishings chain has an enormous inventory of furniture that it is diminutively scaled and cartoonlike. Even the names are likely to please: there's Jussi, a cheerful green dining table ($79), and Roberto ($39), a Tuscan-styled chair with a rush seat that could have come from "Beauty and the Beast" and is a perfect for a 6-year-old's first desk. Parents can turn a drawback -- Ikea's do-it-yourself assembly -- into an advantage by making it a family activity. Telephone orders: (800) 434-4532.</p>
        <p>Quick -- what's the capital of New Jersey? Even children who know their geography may appreciate an update of a classic decorating device: a map. Hagstrom, at 57 West 43d Street (near Avenue of the Americas) sells a six-panel world map measuring 118 inches by 88 inches for $90. Information: (212) 398-1222.</p>
        <p>Caldor discount stores offer black wrought-iron "baker's racks" ($119) that can easily be transformed into child-size escritoires with some 22-inch-long pine shelves. (At the Home Depot store in Danbury, Conn., for example, three shelves cost about $10.) The desk's curved lines brought an approving smile to Rebecca Blum, 10, who will be a fifth grader at the Grafflin Elementary School in Chappaqua, N.Y.</p>
        <p>For students returning to college, Knoll's new SoHo ergonomic desk chair with arms made of recycled plastic bottles is serious good design and one of the best values around. It is about $399 at 105 Wooster Street (near Spring Street); (212) 343-4000.</p>
        <p>At Caldor in Mt. Kisco, N.Y., last weekend, there was an ad-hoc reunion of some of the Class of 1995 from Horace Greeley High School, all college bound, in the appliance aisles. "Everyone's concern is making the dorm room feel like home," said Lauren Foster, 18, five days away from the start of her freshman year at Union College in Schenectady, N.Y. She said she chose a sleek new iron ($39) along with her "very first box of laundry detergent."</p>
        <p>One befuddled looking Syracuse University-bound teen-ager headed for the "50 percent off" Rubbermaid Roughneck display to find a heavy-duty plastic garbage can, which he cheerfully loaded into a shopping cart. "This will make a slammin' beer cooler," he confided, out of his mother's earshot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
