<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Tag Along for a While But Bulls Make Plans to Split</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="507212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHICAGO BULLS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, CLIFTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE1731F931A25751C0A964958260" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Tag Along for a While But Bulls Make Plans to Split</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWN, CLIFTON</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Feb. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Things looked good for the Nets tonight for three quarters. It didn't last. It rarely does for teams that visit Chicago.</p>
        <p>Beginning the fourth quarter with a 14-2 run, the Bulls broke open a close game and dumped the Nets, 133-113, at Chicago Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Things looked good for the Nets tonight for three quarters. It didn't last. It rarely does for teams that visit Chicago.</p>
        <p>Beginning the fourth quarter with a 14-2 run, the Bulls broke open a close game and dumped the Nets, 133-113, at Chicago Stadium.</p>
        <p>It was the eighth consecutive loss for the Nets (19-29), their longest losing streak of the season. And they learned tonight that their starting point guard, Mookie Blaylock, will miss another 10 days to two weeks with an injury to his right knee, a partly torn medial meniscus. Blaylock was injured on the Nets' West Coast trip earlier this month.</p>
        <p>For the Bulls (40-9), tonight was the beginning of what they hope will be a strong finish to their season. They have the best record in the National Basketball Association, but they lost four of their last six games before the All-Star Game break. Playoff Advantage for Bulls</p>
        <p>Chicago's main goal is to finish with the league's best record, which would give the Bulls the homecourt advantage throughout the playoffs. With that in mind, they had no intention of losing a home game to New Jersey, although the Nets made it difficult.</p>
        <p>The Bulls who are 22-2 at home, were led by Michael Jordan (34 points) and Scottie Pippen (23). Drazen Petrovic (23 points), Sam Bowie (22) and Chris Morris (20) led the Nets, who have lost 15 consecutive games at Chicago Stadium.</p>
        <p>"Three-and-a-half quarters does not a game make," said Nets Coach Bill Fitch. "If we had finished the game better, we may have had a shot."</p>
        <p>It was almost as if the Bulls were on cruise control for three quarters, because they dominated the final period from the outset. They started the fourth quarter with a 7-0 run, turning a 94-93 deficit into a 100-94 lead.</p>
        <p>The catalyst was neither Jordan nor Pippen, but backup point guard B. J. Armstrong, who scored 10 of his 15 points in the fourth quarter. Armstrong started the run with a jumper and a driving layup. Then after Kenny Anderson missed a jumper, Will Perdue made a lane hook shot while being fouled by Bowie. Not Done Yet</p>
        <p>Chicago was far from finished.</p>
        <p>With the Bulls leading, 102-96, Armstrong stole the ball from Derrick Coleman (14 points, 10 rebounds), forcing Petrovic to commit a breakaway foul to prevent Armstrong's layup. Armstrong made both free throws, then Craig Hodges made a 3-point jumper from the corner, giving the Bulls a 107-96 lead with 9 minutes 32 seconds left. New Jersey never threatened thereafter.</p>
        <p>"We knew sooner or later, we'd get our burst," Pippen said. "New Jersey had their confidence way up there tonight. They played with a lot of intensity and a lot of energy."</p>
        <p>With Blaylock out, Anderson (11 points, 6 assists) started at point guard for the second consecutive game and played 36 minutes with poise. Anderson looked relaxed and confident, knowing he would get playing time even if he made mistakes. Anderson figures to play often until Blaylock returns.</p>
        <p>"As far as running the team, that was the best I've seen of him," Fitch said of Anderson. "He's always going to able to drive and dish. It's the other parts of the game that he has to learn. But he's still learning on the job. I can't be too critical of what he did with the ball tonight."</p>
        <p>As for Blaylock, the Nets do not believe his injury will require surgery, but he is far from ready to play. Fitch indicated before the game that New Jersey was unlikely to sign another player to replace Blaylock.</p>
        <p>"By the time we sign someone to a 10-day contract and they started playing for us," said Fitch. "Mookie would probably be ready to come back." Press Bothers Nets</p>
        <p>One thing that bothered the Nets tonight was the Bulls' fullcourt press. At times, the Nets reacted to it as if they had seen a ghost.</p>
        <p>"We work on that every day, it was ridiculous," Fitch said. "Some of the turnovers were like shooting yourself in the foot. They weren't forced by the press. With Mookie out, we're going to see more pressure, so we better get used to it."</p>
        <p>Right now, the Nets are used to losing. And it does not feel good.</p>
        <p>"We played pretty well tonight, but we still lost," Bowie said. "We need a win badly." REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Nets visit Philadelphia on Wednesday night. The Bulls' next game is Thursday at Madison Square Garden against the Knicks.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
