<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Graduation Rates For Athletes Rise</title>
    <meta content="03COLLEGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/03/sports/ncaafootball/03college.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1516764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brand, Myles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EEDB1338F930A3575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Graduation Rates For Athletes Rise</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Educators Encouraged as Graduation Rates Rise</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NCAA report contends that graduation rates for student-athletes are highest since 1984, when statistics were first tracked (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sixty-two percent of all scholarship athletes who entered Division I colleges for the 1996-97 academic year graduated in the six-year window established by the Department of Education, a rate 3 percentage points higher than that of the overall student body, according to a report released yesterday by the N.C.A.A.</p>
        <p>The graduation rates for students and student-athletes are the highest since the Department of Education began tracking those statistics in 1984, and the gap between athletes who earn their degrees and the general student body's graduation rate is the largest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The graduation rates for students and student athletes are the highest since the Department of Education began tracking those statistics in 1984.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sixty-two percent of all scholarship athletes who entered Division I colleges for the 1996-97 academic year graduated in the six-year window established by the Department of Education, a rate 3 percentage points higher than that of the overall student body, according to a report released yesterday by the N.C.A.A.</p>
        <p>The graduation rates for students and student-athletes are the highest since the Department of Education began tracking those statistics in 1984, and the gap between athletes who earn their degrees and the general student body's graduation rate is the largest.</p>
        <p>While drastic improvement was shown in many categories, especially among African-American athletes, the gains in high-profile sports were more modest. In Division I football, 54 percent of all players graduated within six years, compared with 53 percent in last year's report. Forty-four percent of Division I men's basketball players graduated, also up 1 percent from last year.</p>
        <p>''Academic reform in intercollegiate athletics is taking root,'' Myles Brand, president of the National Collegiate Athletic Association, said during a conference call. ''We cannot say that the job is complete. It's a great step forward, but much remains to be done.''</p>
        <p>The only declines were slight. The graduation rates for white male basketball players (52 percent) and white football players (61 percent) dropped by 1 percentage point from last year's report.</p>
        <p>Female athletes had a 70 percent graduation rate, a 1 percent increase from last year's. Male athletes were at 55 percent, also a 1 percent increase.</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. report broke down the numbers in other categories.</p>
        <p>$(6$)African-American male athletes climbed to a 48 percent graduation rate, 5 percentage points better than last year's. The combined graduation rate of male and female African-American athletes was 52 percent, 4 percentage points higher than last year's.</p>
        <p>$(6$)The difference between African-American men who are athletes and their counterparts in the rest of the student body also reached a new high (48 percent to 35 percent).</p>
        <p>$(6$)African-American female athletes graduated at a much higher rate (62 percent) than did African-American women in the student body (46 percent) and showed an increase of 2 percentage points over last year's rate.</p>
        <p>$(6$)After years of discouraging rates, African-American men playing Division I basketball, the highest level, graduated at a 38 percent rate, 10 percentage points higher than the year before.</p>
        <p>Brand said the improvement was welcome, if not totally unexpected, because the 2002 class was the first to graduate under stricter academic requirements.</p>
        <p>''A one-year snapshot is not a real conclusive picture of college sports, but it's a real good sign,'' said Richard Lapchick, director of the Institute for Diversity and Ethics in Sport at the University of Central Florida. ''I believe that universities have learned to put the resources into academic support for athletes and have discovered that their chance of classroom success is greatly enhanced.''</p>
        <p>In his own studies over the previous 10 years, Lapchick has found far more alarming results, including that more than 50 Division I basketball programs failed to graduate even one black player.</p>
        <p>A look at the top 10 football teams in the current Associated Press poll shows both improvement and decline in graduation rates, as well as the incomplete way they are calculated.</p>
        <p>Top-ranked Oklahoma, for example, recorded the highest one-year increase in athletes' graduation rates -- 74 percent, up from 40 percent -- and its 65 percent graduation rate for football players made it one of only two teams in the top 10 (Kansas State is the other) to outpace the graduation rate of the general student body, which is 54 percent.</p>
        <p>Jeff Long, the newly named athletic director at Pittsburgh, said graduation numbers were deceptive. In the new report, No. 10 Pittsburgh is credited with graduating only 16 percent of its football players. Long pointed out that 19 players entered for the 1996-97 season, the last for Johnny Majors as coach, but 14 of them transferred. No. 6 Texas also had a rush of transfers after Coach Mack Brown took over in 1998.</p>
        <p>Under the current system, transfers count against the graduation rate even if athletes subsequently earn degrees elsewhere. Likewise, athletes who transfer in and graduate are also not counted. ''When you're dealing with a change of a coaching staff, there's instability and it causes transfers in and out,'' said Long, who was previously had been senior associate athletic director at Oklahoma. ''We're now in our seventh year under Coach Walt Harris and we have strong academic support systems in place, and you're going to see those numbers improve dramatically.''</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A.'s incentive/disincentive plan, to be put into effect incrementally from 2005 to 2008 to hold institutions accountable for their graduation rates, will not penalize them for transfers. But teams that do not perform well academically could lose scholarships and be barred from postseason play. Teams that perform well in the classroom may be entitled to additional revenue through the N.C.A.A.'s distribution formula and to pick up more scholarships, among other benefits.</p>
        <p>''We should have no subgroup graduating below the graduate rate of the general student body on their campus,'' Brand said. ''Academic reform cannot be considered a real success until we have reached that bar.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
