<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I Got Millions For Writing This Article</title>
    <meta content="01instincts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/01/business/01instincts.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASIC INSTINCTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunleavey, M P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DE1530F932A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I Got Millions For Writing This Article</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">I Got Millions for Writing This Article</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. P. Dunleavey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunleavey, M P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M P Dunleavey column on price droppers, people who are so price-proud that they go beyond social convention and comment on what they paid for things without being asked (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I CAN'T decide if this is a new trend, or an old one that has become a lot more irritating. Call it price dropping: the annoying habit some people have of oh-so-casually letting you know how much they paid for that Weber grill, new digital camera, their Marc Jacobs shoes or the swish hotel they stayed at on Mikonos.</p>
        <p>These aren't the bargain hunters who can't wait to tell you the steal they found at a certain sample sale, or what they bought for a song on eBay. Nor are these the people who might sport a Patek Philippe or set their table with Frette, and let you draw your own conclusions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Call it price dropping: the annoying habit some people have of oh-so-casually letting you know how much they paid for that Weber grill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I CAN'T decide if this is a new trend, or an old one that has become a lot more irritating. Call it price dropping: the annoying habit some people have of oh-so-casually letting you know how much they paid for that Weber grill, new digital camera, their Marc Jacobs shoes or the swish hotel they stayed at on Mikonos.</p>
        <p>These aren't the bargain hunters who can't wait to tell you the steal they found at a certain sample sale, or what they bought for a song on eBay. Nor are these the people who might sport a Patek Philippe or set their table with Frette, and let you draw your own conclusions.</p>
        <p>No, I'm talking about people who are so price-proud they're willing to elbow past social convention to tell you what they paid for things, even when you'd much prefer they didn't. In fact, you didn't even ask.</p>
        <p>Colleen Mastro, who works in film production in New York, said she once worked for a compulsive price dropper. Her boss would flaunt the cost of anything from suits to shoes to restaurant bills. ''And it wasn't just because I was an employee,'' Ms. Mastro said. ''I'd hear him dropping numbers into all his phone conversations.''</p>
        <p>There's nothing new about ostentatious behavior, of course; ''conspicuous consumption'' existed for eons before the economist Thorstein Veblen coined the term about 100 years ago. But a once-formidable taboo against talking about money, and specifically the price of things, seems to be eroding in America -- at least in certain circles.</p>
        <p>When I spoke to Joan Caraganis Jakobson, a woman familiar with high society and author of ''And One More Thing  a Mother's Advice on Life, Love and Lipstick'' (WarnerBooks, 2005), she felt that those accustomed to wealth were more likely to rely on certain codes than to discuss actual prices. ''You would never say what you paid for a car''; people tend to know how much a Jaguar set you back.</p>
        <p>Alas, in other circles some people seem comfortable shrugging off these distinctions -- perhaps because we live in an era in which bling is king and the price tags of the lifestyles of the rich and famous are frequent TV fodder.</p>
        <p>Erik Kolbell, a psychotherapist and author of ''Lifescripts for Family and Friends: What to Say in 101 of Life's Most Troubling and Uncomfortable Conversations'' (Pocketbooks, 2002), points to this trickle-down effect of affluence as one reason price-dropping behavior may be more common. Price droppers ''are becoming more brazen in their behavior,'' he said. ''The need they feel to let you know what something costs is more urgent'' because it's a way of broadcasting how well you're doing, at least financially.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a frank exchange about price has its place, especially when the information can help someone make a better choice or find a better deal -- whether on insurance rates, baby-sitting fees or furniture.</p>
        <p>But price droppers, like name droppers, aren't interested in offering financial insight. ''They're pulling rank,'' said Shekaiba Bennett, a photographer in New Canaan, Conn., who has a friend who manages to weave the price and pedigree of whatever she's wearing into a conversation -- sometimes even with people she doesn't know.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bennett attributes this woman's behavior to a deep-seated insecurity about her appearance, whereas Mr. Kolbell feels that in many cases price dropping is about hubris. What the person bought ''is an extension of their ego, and the price is a measuring rod for that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PRICE droppers are frustrating because so often the hapless listener has no idea how to parry the unwanted financial poke.</p>
        <p>''It's embarrassing,'' said Olivia Mellan, a psychologist and the author of several books and a new audio CD set, ''The Secret Language of Money'' (MoneyHarmony, 2006). ''There's a subtext, but you don't know what it is.''</p>
        <p>Some price droppers aren't trying to be competitive; they may simply lack the appropriate social filter, Ms. Mellan said. Others may have developed the habit because they fear being judged. ''Let's say that person was a spender, but had a parent who was a hoarder. They may be looking for some approval that they didn't get. They want someone to say, 'It's O.K., you deserve it.' ''</p>
        <p>Is there a comfortable way to cope with this?</p>
        <p>''The kindest thing you can do is to validate the person,'' perhaps by offering a compliment, Ms. Mellan suggested.</p>
        <p>And when you can't say something nice, as your mother might have told you, the next best thing would be ''breathing deeply, looking pleasant and not saying a damn thing,'' Ms. Mellan added.</p>
        <p>BASIC INSTINCTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
