<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Generic Drugs: The Window Has Loopholes</title>
    <meta content="01nocera" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/01/business/01nocera.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1772977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Merck &amp; Company Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Nocera, Joseph</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DC1530F932A35754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Generic Drugs: The Window Has Loopholes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Generic Drugs: The Window Has Loopholes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE NOCERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nocera, Joseph</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WEEK ago yesterday, Zocor's United States patent protection expired. Zocor, of course, is Merck's big cholesterol-lowering drug, which last year generated $4.4 billion for the company. As Alex Berenson pointed out in The New York Times, that makes Zocor ''the largest-selling drug yet to be opened to generic competition.''</p>
        <p>Not long ago, a big pharmaceutical company like Merck would have rolled over and played dead once its ''branded'' drug lost patent protection. For the first six months after the patent's expiration, the company would probably have maintained its old monopoly price, while a single generic drug maker, which had gained the right to sell its version exclusively for 180 days, undercut it by, say, 20 percent. After the six months were up, and half a dozen generic companies started making their own versions of the drug, the price would ''fall off the cliff,'' in the words of the generic drug expert Tim Van Biesen of Bain &amp; Company. At which point, the branded drug would fade into oblivion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A drug maker can license what has come to be called an "authorized generic" of its drug once its patent is broken.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WEEK ago yesterday, Zocor's United States patent protection expired. Zocor, of course, is Merck's big cholesterol-lowering drug, which last year generated $4.4 billion for the company. As Alex Berenson pointed out in The New York Times, that makes Zocor ''the largest-selling drug yet to be opened to generic competition.''</p>
        <p>Not long ago, a big pharmaceutical company like Merck would have rolled over and played dead once its ''branded'' drug lost patent protection. For the first six months after the patent's expiration, the company would probably have maintained its old monopoly price, while a single generic drug maker, which had gained the right to sell its version exclusively for 180 days, undercut it by, say, 20 percent. After the six months were up, and half a dozen generic companies started making their own versions of the drug, the price would ''fall off the cliff,'' in the words of the generic drug expert Tim Van Biesen of Bain &amp; Company. At which point, the branded drug would fade into oblivion.</p>
        <p>But in recent years, Merck and all the big drug companies have started to fight fire with fire, as Zocor nicely illustrates. Teva Pharmaceutical Industries, the Israeli generic drug company, has the exclusive 180-day window. But instead of having the period all to itself -- and thus being able to keep all the profits -- it finds itself facing a generic competitor. That company, Dr. Reddy's Laboratories, has been granted a license to produce generic Zocor from none other than Merck.</p>
        <p>As it happens, there is nothing that prevents a drug maker from licensing what has come to be called an ''authorized generic'' of its drug during the 180-day window. So now they all do it and get a nice piece of the generic profits. With two competitors, the price of the generic drug drops more like 30 percent or 40 percent instead of 20 percent. So it's good for consumers as well.</p>
        <p>Merck has added a new wrinkle: it decided to sell Zocor itself at a generic-style price, by cutting special deals with certain health care companies, including UnitedHealth. Clearly, generic Zocor is going to be very cheap very quickly.</p>
        <p>With health care costs so high, you would think the development of authorized generics would be worth applauding. And in some quarters, it is. General Motors is happy: its cholesterol drug costs could drop to $82 million a year from $200 million a year, according to Bloomberg News. Besides, who can be against more competition? As John E. Calfee of the American Enterprise Institute puts it, ''If you tried to count the times aggressive pricing has hurt the marketplace, it's hard to get beyond zero.''</p>
        <p>But it turns out that the rise of authorized generics has lots of critics. Their theory is that authorized generics are a sinister plot by the pharmaceutical industry to deprive generic drug makers of what is rightfully theirs: the rich profits they should be reaping during their exclusive 180-day window. ''It's the new scam in town,'' said Kathleen Jaeger, the president of the Generic Pharmaceutical Association, a trade group. Senator Charles E. Schumer of New York told me: ''It is a form of predatory pricing. They are trying to put a dagger through the heart of the generic industry.''</p>
        <p>Oh, I'm not so sure about that.</p>
        <p>FOR all practical purposes, the generic drug industry was born in 1984, when Congress passed a law, the Hatch-Waxman Act, that established the rules of the road. Wanting to infuse low-priced generic competition into the high-priced prescription drug business -- yet not wanting to strip Big Pharma of its incentive to bring new drugs to market -- Hatch-Waxman devised an ingenious solution.</p>
        <p>Patent-protected drugs that won approval from the Food and Drug Administration still won monopoly status, which meant high prices, just as they always had. But after a certain amount of time passed, generic companies were permitted, indeed encouraged, to file an application with the agency for a generic version while also mounting a legal challenge to the drug's underlying patents. If a generic company succeeded in having a patent invalidated, it could then immediately market the drug, with no generic competitors, for 180 days.</p>
        <p>Even if it failed to break the patent, though, if the company was first in line with its drug application and legal challenge, it still got the right to market the drug exclusively for six months, though it had to wait for the patent to expire. (A drug patent has a 20-year life. By the time a drug gets to market, the patents usually have 12 to 14 years remaining.) The lure of the 180-day window was the generic drug industry's incentive to bring patent challenges and hence get lower-priced drugs to the market sooner. ''When a generic company has an exclusive,'' said Michael Krensavage, an analyst at Raymond James, ''it is a fantastic business.'' But once the 180 days expire, the drug becomes a low-cost commodity with very little profit margin.</p>
        <p>Why didn't Big Pharma start rolling out authorized generics from the start? Two reasons. First, the 1980's and especially the 1990's were an extraordinary time in the drug industry, with one blockbuster drug after another brought to market. With profits rolling in, the giant pharmaceutical companies didn't feel the need to pick up every nickel on the street.</p>
        <p>Secondly, though, many of the more aggressive pharmaceutical companies spent most of their efforts gaming the system to keep their patents alive, rather than worrying about what would happen after the patent expired. Like any law, Hatch-Waxman had loopholes and unintended consequences that the companies quickly learned to exploit and that could extend the life of the patent for years, despite the legal challenges.</p>
        <p>By 2003, though, things had changed. Congress closed many of the loopholes. Secondly, though, many of the 1990's-era blockbusters were facing patent expiration or successful challenges. And the drug pipelines of the pharmaceutical companies were drying up. With companies facing profit squeezes, those nickels suddenly seemed worth bending over to get.</p>
        <p>To hear the big drug companies tell it, jumping into the authorized generic business was nothing more than a sensible response to a business predicament. Why shouldn't they try to grab a piece of the generic profits if it was legal to do so? Isn't that how capitalism is supposed to work?</p>
        <p>''We believe that the actions we've taken are good for consumers, good for those who pay for medicine and good for us as a company,'' said Ian Spatz, Merck's vice president for public policy. ''We're acting rationally.''</p>
        <p>As for whether Big Pharma is consciously trying to hurt its generic competition, Hank McKinnell, the chief executive of Pfizer, probably said it best the other day in The Wall Street Journal. Asked whether Pfizer's authorized generic strategy was intended to stick it to the generics or preserve sales for Pfizer, he replied, ''Both are good things.''</p>
        <p>When you talk to the people on the other side, though, you hear that neither is a good thing. Sure, consumers may get lower prices during the 180-day window (though the generic lobby disputes even that), but that short-term benefit pales in comparison to the way Hatch-Waxman is evaded. ''I think this is a loophole in the act that should be closed,'' said David Balto, a lawyer and former Federal Trade Commission official specializing in health care litigation.</p>
        <p>The argument made by Mr. Balto -- and many others, including Senator Schumer -- goes like this. Hatch-Waxman is an attempt to carefully balance incentives for both Big Pharma and the generic drug industry. When a company like Merck introduces a competitorin the form of an authorized generic, it is depriving the generic industry of a big part of the incentive Congress intended. After all, if generic companies can't make as much money during the 180-day window, won't that mean they will have less incentive to challenge Big Pharma's patents? And won't that also mean high-priced drugs will stay on the market longer than they would otherwise?</p>
        <p>There is a fair amount of rumbling on Capitol Hill that an effort will be made to outlaw authorized generics, but I'm not convinced that is a good idea. True, generic companies are making less money now that Big Pharma has figured out how to compete during the 180-day period. But so far, there appears to be no evidence that generic companies are holding back on patent challenges as a result. (The F.T.C., however, is conducting its own study, which is expected to be completed next year.)</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Pfizer's antidepressant, Zoloft, lost its patent protection -- and the company immediately rolled out an authorized generic to compete with Teva for the next six months. David Woodburn, an analyst with the Prudential Equity Group, estimated that even with the competition, Teva would generate $200 million in sales of generic Zoloft in the next six months. That's not as much as it once would have made, but it's not terrible, either. Outlawing authorized generics would mainly be a boon to the stock prices of the generic drug companies, which hardly seems like something Congress should worry about.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the one person on the generic side of the divide who sounded positively sanguine about the new competition was George Barrett, the president of Teva North America. Although he told me that authorized generics ''undermine the intent of the law,'' he quickly added that his company expected such competition now. ''This is part of the landscape,'' he shrugged.</p>
        <p>Then he added, ''When you see the number of major drugs that are coming off patent, it would be unreasonable to expect a brand company to just stand still.''</p>
        <p>Not that I was surprised by his remarks. After all, he is a capitalist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
