<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chess</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="420465"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D61131F936A35751C0A967958260" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chess</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BYRNE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The narrow victory by the Hungarian team over the Soviet Union's in the Women's Olympiad in Novi Sad, Yugoslavia, hinged on matches with the Czechoslovakians. And at the center of the action was one player, the 14-year-old Hungarian superstar, Judit Polgar.</p>
        <p>As the next to last round started on Dec. 3, the Hungarians -- the two older Polgars, Zsuzsa and Zsofia, as well as Judit and a fourth player, Ildiko Madl -- trailed the Soviet team of Maya Chiburdanidze, Nona Gaprindashvili, Alisa Gallyamova and Ketevan Arakhamia by 1 1/2 points. But in the match with Czechoslovakia, Gallyamova was upset by J. Hajkova-Maskova and, when Chiburdanidze drew with Eliska Klimova-Richtrova and Arakhamia defeated P. Polakova-Kisova, the three-board match ended in a tie. At the same time, Hungary rolled over Argentina, 3-0.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The narrow victory by the Hungarian team over the Soviet Union's in the Women's Olympiad in Novi Sad, Yugoslavia, hinged on matches with the Czechoslovakians. And at the center of the action was one player, the 14-year-old Hungarian superstar, Judit Polgar.</p>
        <p>As the next to last round started on Dec. 3, the Hungarians -- the two older Polgars, Zsuzsa and Zsofia, as well as Judit and a fourth player, Ildiko Madl -- trailed the Soviet team of Maya Chiburdanidze, Nona Gaprindashvili, Alisa Gallyamova and Ketevan Arakhamia by 1 1/2 points. But in the match with Czechoslovakia, Gallyamova was upset by J. Hajkova-Maskova and, when Chiburdanidze drew with Eliska Klimova-Richtrova and Arakhamia defeated P. Polakova-Kisova, the three-board match ended in a tie. At the same time, Hungary rolled over Argentina, 3-0.</p>
        <p>In the final round the next day, both the Soviet Union and Hungary won their matches, 3-0, and Judit Polgar took the swing point by winning sharply from Hajkova-Maskova. Of course, that put the two teams even at 35-7, but the Hungarians took the gold medals on tiebreak points. There were 64 teams.</p>
        <p>When one plays 6 . . . Bb4 in the Four Knights Variation of the Sicilian Defense, one looks toward 7 a3 (7 Nd6?! Ke7 8 Nc8 Rc8 yields Black rapid development) Bc3 8 Nc3 d5 9 ed Nd5 10 Bd2 Nc3 11 Bc3 Qd1 12 Rd1 f6, with the intention of working gingerly for a draw in the endgame despite White's bishop pair. The alternative that Polgar chose, 7 Bf4, is generally shunned as leading to a gambit that is not sound for White. Obviously, she had different ideas.</p>
        <p>The position after 11 bc has long been judged inadequate to produce anything worthwhile for White -- for several reasons. Supposedly 11 . . . e5 is strong because 12 Nd5 Ng5 13 Bg5 Qg5 14 Kb2 gives White doubled, isolated c pawns that are not compensated for by Black's retarded mobilization and uncomfortable king placement. But observe that 14 . . . Bg4 15 Qg3 Qh5 16 f3 may not be so easy for Black, whose forces lack coordination. Moreover, the alternative, 11 . . . g5, which Hajkova-Maskova chose, is thought to be reliable for Black because 12 Na8?! would produce a powerful counterattack for Black with 12 . . . Qa5! and because 12 Bg3 Ng3 13 Qg3 Rb8, the course this game followed, is advocated for Black in The Encylopedia of Chess Openings, Vol. B, second edition.</p>
        <p>But Polgar put on pressure at once with 14 Bb5, threatening 15 Bc6 bc 16 Nd5! Hajkova-Maskova might have tried 14 . . . Bd7, but then 15 c4!? cannot be met by 15 . . . dc? since 16 Bc6 bc 17 Qd6 wins a piece. Also, 15 . . . d4 16 Bc6 Bc6 17 Qe5 Rg8 18 Rd4 Qc8 (18 . . . Qe7? 19 Ne6! wins rook for knight) 19 Qc5 Kg7 20 Qg5 Kh8 21 Qf6 Rg7 22 Rhd1! Qc7 23 Rd8 Be8 24 Rb8 Qb8 25 Rd8 wins for White.</p>
        <p>Against this hypothetical 14 . . . Bd7 15 c4!?, Black might try a counterattack with 15 . . . Qf6, yet 16 cd Qa1 17 Kd2 Qd4 18 Ke2 Qe4 (or 18 . . . Qe5 19 Qe5 Ne5 20 Bd7 Nd7 21 de, winning a decisive pawn) 19 Kf1 Qc2? 20 Be2! Ne7 (20 . . . ed? 21 Qd6 costs Black his bishop) 21 Ne6! fe 22 Qb8 is overwhelming for White.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, Hajkova-Maskova tried 14 . . . Qe7, which gave up the exchange to 15 Bc6 bc 16 Ne6 Be6 17 Qb8 Kg7 18 Qg3 but at least kept a reasonably compact position.</p>
        <p>On 21 Kd2, it would have been a horrible blunder to capture with 21 . . . Qa2? because of 22 Re6! fe 23 Qc7, which wins more material.</p>
        <p>Just as soon as Hajkova-Maskova attempted to attack with 22 . . . Bf5, Polgar struck with 23 Qe5! Kg6 24 Rb8!, a mating attack that came first. After 24 . . . Bd3 25 Rg8 Kh5 26 f3 f5 27 Qg3, there was nothing to do about the threat of 28 Qh3 mate because 27 . . . g4 28 fg fg allows 29 Qg4 mate. Hajkova-Maskova gave up.  SICILIAN DEFENSE</p>
        <p>White</p>
        <p>Black</p>
        <p>Polgar</p>
        <p>Haj.-Mas.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>e4</p>
        <p>c5</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>Nf3</p>
        <p>Nc6</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>d4</p>
        <p>cd</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Nd4</p>
        <p>Nf6</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Nc3</p>
        <p>e6</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Ndb5</p>
        <p>Bb4</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Bf4</p>
        <p>Ne4</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Qf3</p>
        <p>d5</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>O-O-O</p>
        <p>Bc3</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Nc7</p>
        <p>Kf8</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>bc</p>
        <p>g5</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Bg3</p>
        <p>Ng3</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Qg3</p>
        <p>Rb8</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Bb5</p>
        <p>Qe7</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>Bc6</p>
        <p>bc</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Ne6</p>
        <p>Be6</p>
        <p>17</p>
        <p>Qb8</p>
        <p>Kg7</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>Qg3</p>
        <p>Rd8</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>Rhe1</p>
        <p>h6</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Rd3</p>
        <p>Qa3</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Kd2</p>
        <p>Rd6</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Rb1</p>
        <p>Bf5</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Qe5</p>
        <p>Kg6</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Rb8</p>
        <p>Bd3</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Rg8</p>
        <p>Kh5</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>f3</p>
        <p>f5</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Qg3</p>
        <p>Resigns</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
