<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Babel of Programs, Translation</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="420461"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="PERIPHERALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFTWARE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SYSTEMS COMPATIBILITY CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHANNON, L R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB1131F936A35751C0A967958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Babel of Programs, Translation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By L. R. SHANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHANNON, L R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU have a problem. Assigned to prepare a major report, you must gather information from the accounting department's spreadsheets, the sales department's databases and memos from branch offices, some of which were prepared with a word-processing program different from the one you use.</p>
        <p>Perhaps someone in system support knows how to translate such diverse kinds of data into a form that your word processor can understand. Then again, perhaps the expert in file conversions, is on vacation. It looks as though you are in for a lot of retyping, subsequent proofreading and inevitable errors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU have a problem. Assigned to prepare a major report, you must gather information from the accounting department's spreadsheets, the sales department's databases and memos from branch offices, some of which were prepared with a word-processing program different from the one you use.</p>
        <p>Perhaps someone in system support knows how to translate such diverse kinds of data into a form that your word processor can understand. Then again, perhaps the expert in file conversions, is on vacation. It looks as though you are in for a lot of retyping, subsequent proofreading and inevitable errors.</p>
        <p>To the rescue comes Outside In. This program will take documents created with any of more than 50 MS-DOS programs, as well as 3 Macintosh ones, and bring them virtually intact into your word-processing program. It doesn't even lose what are called character attributes -- things like italicized, underlined or bold words or sections.</p>
        <p>The list of programs is too long to give here. It looks like an honor roll of both the most popular, and some of the less-heralded word processors, spreadsheets and databases. The list is printed on the box, so you can check before you buy, but be warned that the list in the manual adds the version numbers that Outside In can deal with, so you might want to inquire further if you are still using an older version of a piece of software, or one that just came out.</p>
        <p>Not having a large amount of information created with a variety of programs, I was not able to put Outside In to a full test. But it certainly installed easily enough, and the opening screen is straightforward. The program uses the function keys to accomplish most of its tasks, and a listing of what each key does is at the bottom of the screen.</p>
        <p>Working through a 27-page tutorial chapter in the manual, I brought into my word-processing program a variety of simple files created by other word-processing, spreadsheeting and database programs, both in whole and in part. They came across in good shape, even taking on the formatting characteristics I had selected from the ones offered by my word-processing program.</p>
        <p>The tutorial assumes your word processor is Microsoft Word. If you are using something else, you will have to translate the commands.</p>
        <p>Outside In is a memory-resident program. That is, when you start it up either manually or automatically at the beginning of a session, it remains available while you go on to something else. When you come to that part of the report where you need a list of customers in Dayton, Ohio, press two keys and the program pops up. Then you scroll through directories and files looking for Dayton, find it, select the part you need and insert it into your document with the press of one key. Each file is shown on the screen in its original format.</p>
        <p>Two important distinctions should be made between Outside In and other "file importing" programs. You do not have to have access to the program the file was originally created with, and there is no intermediate step, like the clipboard in Windows and on the Macintosh that temporarily holds information that is going from one program to another.</p>
        <p>Outside In comes on a 5.25-inch and 3.5-inch disk, and works on any MS-DOS computer with at least 70 kilobytes of free memory. A hard disk is not required, but is close to essential. The single-user version has a suggested retail price of $99. Network versions are also available.</p>
        <p>Outside In is a product of Systems Compatibility Corporation, 401 North Wabash, Suite 600, Chicago, Ill. 60611; telephone (312) 329-0700.</p>
        <p>PERIPHERALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
