<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shackled Convict Leaps to Death in Hudson</title>
    <meta content="15ESCA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rensselaer (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evans, Gary C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED8113AF936A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shackled Convict Leaps to Death in Hudson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gary C Evans, convicted thief charged in three killings, kicks out side of police van, hobbles in shackles to edge of bridge in Rensselaer County, and leaps 65 feet to his death in Hudson River; 43-year-old convict was sentenced earlier in day to 24 months in prison for violating probation and was being taken by US marshals from Federal court in Albany to county jail in Troy; photos; he had escaped from county jail in 1980, and is recalled as exceptionally strong and determined; authorities say Evans, who was living in Vermont when arrested in May, confessed to killing five men over 13-year period when he led gang of jewelry and antiques thieves (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A convicted thief recently charged in three killings kicked out the side window of a police van yesterday morning, hobbled in shackles to the edge of a bridge in Rensselaer County and leapt 65 feet to his death in the rocky shallows of the Hudson River, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The thief, Gary C. Evans, 43, had been sentenced earlier that morning to 24 months in prison for violating probation, and was being taken by United States marshals from the Federal courthouse in Albany to the Rensselaer County Jail in Troy. Considered an escape risk, he had been closely guarded and was shackled at the feet, waist and hands before being placed alone in the back of the van, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A convicted thief recently charged in three killings kicked out the side window of a police van yesterday morning, hobbled in shackles to the edge of a bridge in Rensselaer County and leapt 65 feet to his death in the rocky shallows of the Hudson River, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The thief, Gary C. Evans, 43, had been sentenced earlier that morning to 24 months in prison for violating probation, and was being taken by United States marshals from the Federal courthouse in Albany to the Rensselaer County Jail in Troy. Considered an escape risk, he had been closely guarded and was shackled at the feet, waist and hands before being placed alone in the back of the van, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans kicked out the window and jumped from the van as it was crossing the Troy-Menands bridge, on the outskirts of Troy at about 11 A.M., the authorities said. The two deputy marshals riding in front and two other deputies following in a second van jumped out of their vehicles and tried to grab Mr. Evans. But before they could reach him, he had leapt over the bridge's railing, landing on the rocks at the river's edge where the water is only a foot deep, officials said.</p>
        <p>The four deputies scrambled down the banks and found the body of Mr. Evans, who apparently had been killed instantly, said Chris Clauss, a deputy marshal in Albany. While the escape was being investigated by Federal marshals and the New York State Police, ''there isn't much to investigate,'' Mr. Clauss said. Mr. Evans, who escaped over the wall of the Rensselaer County Jail in 1980, was exceptionally strong and extremely determined, he said.</p>
        <p>''In prison he would be walking around on his hands,'' Mr. Clauss said.</p>
        <p>Described by his lawyer Randolph F. Treece, as a ''very rugged, solitary man,'' Mr. Evans was living in a tent in northeastern Vermont when he was arrested in May on a Federal probation charge connected to a theft. By July, the authorities said, Mr. Evans had confessed to killing five men over a period of 13 years during which he was leading a gang of jewelry and antiques thieves.</p>
        <p>At his death, Mr. Evans was under indictment in Rensselaer County in three of the killings.</p>
        <p>The victims, who had been his friends and associates, were Timothy W. Rysedorph, 39, of Saratoga Springs, N.Y., who was shot in the head in 1997; Damien Cuomo, 28, of Troy, who was killed in 1989, and Michael Falco, 30, also of Troy, who was shot to death there in 1985 and whose body was recently found in Lake Worth, Fla.</p>
        <p>After his arrest, Mr. Evans led the police to the bodies of Mr. Falco, Mr. Rysedorph in Brunswick, N.Y., and Mr. Cuomo in a wooded area in Troy, the authorities said. He told the police that he had killed the three men because they were witnesses to some of his crimes.</p>
        <p>In an interview last month with The Times-Union of Albany, Mr. Evans said he had confessed after a state police investigator described the anguish of the 9-year-old son of Mr. Rysedorph. He said he had felt ''empathy for an innocent kid who needed to know the truth.''</p>
        <p>If convicted of killing Mr. Rysedorph, Mr. Evans could have faced the death penalty. The other two men were killed before capital punishment was reinstated in New York in 1995.</p>
        <p>The authorities said Mr. Evans also confessed this summer to the killings of two jewelry shop owners: Gregory Jouben, 36, of Herkimer County, who was shot to death in 1991, and Douglas Berry, 63, who was killed in his sleep in 1989. He told the police that he killed the two shopkeepers during robberies. Those killings had not yet been brought up before a grand jury.</p>
        <p>Growing up in the blue-collar neighborhood of South Troy, Mr. Evans was a troubled and troublesome teen-ager and a convicted bicycle thief, according to newspaper reports. One childhood acquaintance recalled that he had a reputation for jumping off bridges into a canal leading into the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Later, he became a thief with rarefied tastes. Among his many convictions were ones for thefts of antique stores in Vermont: $85,000 worth of antique toys, coins and jewelry and a leather-bound book of lithographs by John James Audubon titled ''The Birds of America.''</p>
        <p>In St. Johnsbury, Vt., where he was captured in May, he was a vegetarian living the rugged life of a survivalist, Mr. Treece said.</p>
        <p>''I think he wanted to determine his own fate,'' he said, reflecting on his client's suicide. ''He wasn't going to allow others to make decisions for him.''</p>
        <p>In a suicide note that Mr. Evans left for Mr. Treece shortly after his sentencing yesterday morning, he made it clear that he preferred a death he could control over a life he could not. ''On to a better place now,'' he told his lawyer, who opened the note shortly after hearing of the suicide. ''Stars surround me and peace and love are mine. They cannot be taken or touched.</p>
        <p>''I win.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
