<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRESIDENT PICKS A SPECIAL ENVOY TO REBUILD IRAQ</title>
    <meta content="07POST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/07/international/worldspecial/07POST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1486965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="AFTEREFFECTS: POSTWAR PLANNING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iraq-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bremer, L Paul 3d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garner, Jay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Tommy R (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Colin L (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Defense Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Garner, Jay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED71E3CF934A35756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRESIDENT PICKS A SPECIAL ENVOY TO REBUILD IRAQ</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">President Picks a Special Envoy to Rebuild Iraq</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO and ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James; Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush names L Paul Bremer III, retired diplomat and counterterrorism expert, as his special envoy to Iraq; makes him senior civilian in charge of rebuilding Iraq's government and infrastructure; Bremer will take charge of effort currently led by Gen Jay Garner, who reports to Gen Tommy R Franks; will report directly to Defense Sec Donald H Rumsfeld; Bush administration officials say shift underscores Bush's intention to speed transition from military occupation toward civilian administration; say Garner, although largely being supplanted by Bremer, to whom he will report, will not resign; Garner confirms he will stay for while; Bush move seeks to resolve sharp dispute between State Department and Pentagon over control of reconstruction project, with Bush, Rumsfeld and State Sec Colin L Powell all involved in hashing out details of Bremer's appointment, responsibilities and reporting chain; diagram of reporting chain; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush today announced the appointment of L. Paul Bremer III, a retired diplomat and counterterrorism expert, as his special envoy to Iraq, making him the senior civilian in charge of rebuilding the country's government and infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bremer will take charge of a multibillion-dollar enterprise currently run by a retired lieutenant general, Jay Garner, who reports to Gen. Tommy R. Franks, the commander of allied forces in Iraq. Mr. Bremer will report directly to Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, administration officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>L Paul Bremer III will take charge of a multibillion-dollar enterprise currently run by a retired lieutenant general, Jay Garner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush today announced the appointment of L. Paul Bremer III, a retired diplomat and counterterrorism expert, as his special envoy to Iraq, making him the senior civilian in charge of rebuilding the country's government and infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bremer will take charge of a multibillion-dollar enterprise currently run by a retired lieutenant general, Jay Garner, who reports to Gen. Tommy R. Franks, the commander of allied forces in Iraq. Mr. Bremer will report directly to Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>The shift underscores the White House's intention to speed the transition from a military occupation toward civilian administration, senior administration officials said. Although he is largely being supplanted by Mr. Bremer, to whom he will report, the officials said General Garner would not resign, even as his role was still being worked out. In Iraq today, General Garner confirmed as much, saying: ''I'll stay awhile. There's got to be a good handoff.''</p>
        <p>By announcing the appointment himself, and by elevating Mr. Bremer to the level of presidential envoy, Mr. Bush sought to resolve a sharp dispute over the last several days between the State Department and the Pentagon for control of the reconstruction project. The State Department has argued that a civilian with diplomatic skills and foreign policy experience should coordinate reconstruction, while Pentagon officials have insisted that the project remain under the military's control.</p>
        <p>The move has been so contentious that Mr. Bush, Mr. Rumsfeld and Mr. Powell were all personally involved in hashing out details of Mr. Bremer's appointment, his responsibilities and his reporting chain, top administration officials said.</p>
        <p>''He's a man with enormous experience,'' Mr. Bush said of Mr. Bremer in an Oval Office event attended by Mr. Rumsfeld, Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and the national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice. ''The ambassador goes with the full blessings of this administration and the full confidence of all of us in this administration that he can get the job done.''</p>
        <p>In asserting that Mr. Bremer was popular throughout the administration, Mr. Bush tried to paper over those differences by choosing a retired diplomat who has 23 years of Foreign Service experience, but who is also close to leading neoconservatives in the Pentagon. By making Mr. Bremer, who is 61, a presidential envoy, Mr. Bush also placed him more clearly under White House control and less under the aegis of the Defense Department.</p>
        <p>But the infighting may have only just begun. Because Mr. Bremer and General Franks will both report to Mr. Rumsfeld, the appointment sets up possible conflicts between the military and civilian administrators that Mr. Rumsfeld will have to adjudicate.</p>
        <p>For all the infighting, which held up the announcement of the appointment for several days, officials at the State Department and Pentagon insisted today that they were satisfied.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bremer will report to Mr. Rumsfeld, a senior State Department official said, ''it's a transition from a predominantly military structure to a more civilian structure.</p>
        <p>''Rumsfeld chose him, checked it with Powell, we're fine with it,'' the official said. ''We know Jerry well, and we can work with him.'' (Mr. Bremer is known to his friends as Jerry.)</p>
        <p>At the Pentagon, senior officials said Mr. Rumsfeld had long envisioned that Mr. Bremer would ultimately fill the role of overall civilian administrator for Iraq.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld has known Mr. Bremer for years, one official said, adding that General Garner was notified in January of the plan to bring in Mr. Bremer.</p>
        <p>Another reason Mr. Rumsfeld may have been willing to go along with Mr. Bremer's appointment was that even the general's supporters in the administration acknowledged that the blunt-spoken former three-star Army officer could be politically tone deaf.</p>
        <p>Last week, for example, General Garner scolded reporters traveling with Mr. Rumsfeld in Baghdad for dwelling on the shortcomings of the effort to restore civilian order and services to Iraq.</p>
        <p>''We ought to look in a mirror and get proud, and stick out our chests and suck in our bellies and say, 'Damn, we're Americans!' '' General Garner said.</p>
        <p>Disputing accusations that the Pentagon was resisting Mr. Bremer, Defense Department officials insisted today that it might have been Mr. Rumsfeld's intention all along to bring in Mr. Bremer, but that it was not explained clearly when General Garner was appointed.</p>
        <p>''What we had here was a failure to articulate what the big guy had in mind,'' said one defense official.</p>
        <p>Sean McCormack, the spokesman for the National Security Council, said Mr. Bremer, who may leave for Iraq as soon as this weekend, would guide overall reconstruction policy while General Garner would handle day-to-day reconstruction work.</p>
        <p>''General Garner will continue doing what he's been doing, getting the lights turned on, the water flowing, the sewers working,'' Mr. McCormack said.</p>
        <p>Zalmay Khalilzad, who has been the White House liaison to former Iraqi opposition groups, will also stay on to advise Mr. Bremer on Iraqi politics and assist in starting a representative government, Mr. McCormack said.</p>
        <p>During 23 years in the Foreign Service, Mr. Bremer was an ambassador to the Netherlands and a senior aide to six secretaries of state before retiring as President Ronald Reagan's ambassador at large for counterterrorism in 1989.</p>
        <p>After leaving government, he became managing director at Kissinger Associates, the global consulting firm run by former Secretary of State Henry A. Kissinger, who remains close to Mr. Rumsfeld.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bremer is also considered acceptable to many neoconservatives, including Deputy Secretary of Defense Paul D. Wolfowitz, in large part because he has taken hawkish positions on fighting terrorism, as well as on containing Iran and Syria, officials said.</p>
        <p>While administration officials described the appointment as a compromise, some analysts said the Pentagon had still come out on top because Mr. Bremer would still take his orders from Mr. Rumsfeld.</p>
        <p>''My sense is that no one can claim this is a Powell victory,'' said Ivo Daalder, a former National Security aide in the Clinton administration who now works at the Brookings Institution. ''The person you report to is the key, and while Bremer reports to the president, he does it through Rumsfeld, not Powell.''</p>
        <p>While the administration wrangled over reconstruction, two senior Republican lawmakers complained today that the administration had left them in the dark about the postwar organization structure for Iraq.</p>
        <p>''Those of us who have responsibilities in foreign policy at the moment don't have a lot of facts,'' Senator John W. Warner, a Virginia Republican who heads the Armed Services Committee, said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Warner praised General Garner and warned the administration to ensure that ''it's made clear to Bremer, don't throw any roadblocks down to Garner to continue to perform his duties.''</p>
        <p>Senator Richard G. Lugar, an Indiana Republican who heads the Foreign Relations Committee, said: ''The president or Mr. Bremer or others will have to explain that to all of us. I'm not quite sure how to interpret the organizational charts or the dynamics of this.''</p>
        <p>''It's fairly obvious that a desire for some management plan is evolving,'' he added. ''It's occurring if not on the run, sort of day by day.''</p>
        <p>AFTEREFFECTS: POSTWAR PLANNING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
