<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ways That Maazel Knows His Mahler</title>
    <meta content="24PHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/24/arts/music/24phila.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1682539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maazel, Lorin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Maazel, Lorin</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mahler, Gustav</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DA1F3BF937A15755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ways That Maazel Knows His Mahler</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Ways That Maazel Knows His Mahler</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews New York Philharmonic concert conducted by Lorin Maazel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Lorin Maazel completes his third season as music director of the New York Philharmonic, debate continues about his artistic impact on the Philharmonic, on culture in New York City and on the overall state of the American orchestra. But if you want to understand why the Philharmonic players and many concertgoers in the city so value Mr. Maazel, report to Avery Fisher Hall for his performance of Mahler's Symphony No. 6 in A minor. The final program of the subscription season is devoted to this single work of nearly 90 minutes. The first performance on Wednesday night was deeply impressive and continuously exciting.</p>
        <p>This symphony has been dubbed by some the ''Tragic.'' But the tragedy is defiant, not pitiable, and that is the quality Mr. Maazel conveyed in this incisive, radiantly colorful and never maudlin performance. The work essentially hews to the four-movement classical structure. Yet the music has a narrative subtext, though Mahler was always ambivalent about ascribing stories to his symphonies. In this one a hero marches willfully into the morass of life, fiercely determined, yet prone to bouts of wistfulness and depression. By the end he is struck down by hammer blows of fate. The danger in conducting the work is to treat it too much like a tone poem or a film score.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lorin Maazel's performance of Mahler's Symphony No. 6 in A minor on Wednesday was deeply impressive and continuously exciting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Lorin Maazel completes his third season as music director of the New York Philharmonic, debate continues about his artistic impact on the Philharmonic, on culture in New York City and on the overall state of the American orchestra. But if you want to understand why the Philharmonic players and many concertgoers in the city so value Mr. Maazel, report to Avery Fisher Hall for his performance of Mahler's Symphony No. 6 in A minor. The final program of the subscription season is devoted to this single work of nearly 90 minutes. The first performance on Wednesday night was deeply impressive and continuously exciting.</p>
        <p>This symphony has been dubbed by some the ''Tragic.'' But the tragedy is defiant, not pitiable, and that is the quality Mr. Maazel conveyed in this incisive, radiantly colorful and never maudlin performance. The work essentially hews to the four-movement classical structure. Yet the music has a narrative subtext, though Mahler was always ambivalent about ascribing stories to his symphonies. In this one a hero marches willfully into the morass of life, fiercely determined, yet prone to bouts of wistfulness and depression. By the end he is struck down by hammer blows of fate. The danger in conducting the work is to treat it too much like a tone poem or a film score.</p>
        <p>In the opening movement, a crazily insistent march, Mr. Maazel focused on making everything lucid, energetic, full of character and accurate. His tempo had drive, but it was held in check just enough to allow the musical intricacies to come through. By coaxing the players into crisp articulation of the accents that proliferate in the thematic lines and rhythms, Mr. Maazel brought to this march a jumpy, jerky surface quality that kept you off guard.</p>
        <p>When the first section gave way to the reflective second theme, Mr. Maazel balanced and voiced the soft chords for winds and brass so that the music seemed like an unearthly chorale drifting in from afar. In the impassioned theme that Mahler named for his wife, Alma, Mr. Maazel drew burnished sound and impetuous lyricism from the Philharmonic strings. He brought a strange beauty to the development section of this long movement, which is like the hero's vision of some now-impossible bucolic life, full of amorphous harmonies, mystical harps and rustic cow bows.</p>
        <p>The middle movements of the symphony are a Scherzo and an Andante, originally conceived (and published) by Mahler in that order. But he had second thoughts and reversed the order in a later published edition. Still, he dithered and never settled the question. Most conductors perform the Scherzo first. Mr. Maazel started with the Andante and made it seem the only choice. After the relentlessness of the first movement, the pensive, soulful Andante was a welcome balm. This in turn gave more freshness to the Scherzo -- a bitter parody of the first movement's march.</p>
        <p>The epic finale had breadth and urgency. As the hero forges ahead with mindless determination, the first hammer blow (made by a percussionist pummeling a great wooden box with a fearsome-looking felt-covered wooden hammer) knocks him loopy. Crazed and wild-eyed, he tries to go on, or so it seems from the frantic outbursts of counterpoint that are scattered in the orchestra. But the second hammer blow levels the hero, and the bucolic music comes back, this time, as performed here, in some unhinged, dissipating state. Imagine a ''Star Wars'' character being slowly vaporized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maazel can be a cool interpreter. But that coolness, combined with his musical exactitude, prevents his Mahler from seeming melodramatic -- always a danger with this all-embracing composer. One of the highlights of Mr. Maazel's tenure so far was his Mahler Third, which ended last season. Clearly, he should keep the Mahler coming.</p>
        <p>The program is repeated tonight and tomorrow night at 8; (212) 875-5656.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
