<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gang Attacks 3 And Yells Slurs On West Street</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="371904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSAULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREENWICH VILLAGE (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYS, CONSTANCE L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMALL, IRVING</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEWART, GERARUD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAHAM, GARRETT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLANVING, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANABY, RONALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREEN, FRANK (ALLEGED ASSAILANT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRISON, DERRICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ, TONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, RAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC113DF934A15754C0A966958260" item-length="392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gang Attacks 3 And Yells Slurs On West Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYS, CONSTANCE L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Three men were attacked early yesterday by a gang that shouted anti-homosexual slurs at them in Greenwich Village, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Three men were attacked early yesterday by a gang that shouted anti-homosexual slurs at them in Greenwich Village, the police said.</p>
        <p>Three men were attacked early yesterday by a gang that shouted anti-homosexual slurs at them in Greenwich Village, the police said.</p>
        <p>Seven men were arrested when police officers who were driving a victim of another bias-related attack to his home heard the suspects' car described on the police radio and then saw it in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The attack began at 2 A.M. on West Street. Two victims were walking near Christopher Street, and the third was in a car, when the seven men shouted anti-homosexual taunts, Sgt. Philip Banks Jr. of the bias-incident investigative unit said.</p>
        <p>The seven men stopped, demanded money from the victim in his car, and had a fight in which one victim was slashed on the face and another suffered cuts, the police said, adding that the third victim was not physically hurt, but was traumatized when gang members picked him up and threatened to throw him in the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>One victim, Irving Small, 21 years old, was admitted to St. Vincent's Hospital in satisfactory condition. Gerarud Stewart, 17, who was slashed in the face and neck, and Garrett Graham, 21, whom the gang threatened to throw in the river, were treated at St. Vincent's and released, Sergeant Banks said.</p>
        <p>Beaten Outside a Bar</p>
        <p>The seven men, all from the East New York section of Brooklyn, were arrested on charges of second-degree assault, robbery and criminal possession of a weapon. They were identified as Anthony Blanving, 28, of 1114 Decatur Street; Ronald Canaby, 26, of 240 Wortman Avenue; Frank Green, 26, of 547 Hinsdale Street; Derrick Harrison, 24, of 295 Cozine Avenue; Raymond Little, 23, of 285 Cozine Avenue; Tony Perez, 27, of 250 Wortman Avenue, and Ray Simpson, 30, of 195 Cozine Avenue.</p>
        <p>The police recorded 55 bias-related crimes against homosexuals in the first six months of the year, compared with 47 all of last year, the commander of the bias unit, Inspector Paul M. Sanderson, said.</p>
        <p>The other bias incident was at 8 P.M., when a gang of whites beat a black man, Derreck Empatge, 28, a peddler, outside the Black Rock Cafe at 410 Avenue of the Americas, near Ninth Street, the police said.</p>
        <p>Three people, all from Queens, were arrested. They were identified as Brian Kish, 30, of 157-11 Sanford Avenue, Flushing; William Kish, 24, of 147-26 Jasmine Avenue, Flushing, and Thomas Hladek, 25, of 50-28 207th Street, Bayside.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
