<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance;   A Message About Women</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="371818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DANIELS, BRENDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D7123AF934A15754C0A966958260" item-length="376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance;   A Message About Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The ingredients were good in Brenda Daniels's new ''Irises,'' presented last Friday night at the Merce Cunningham Studio. Ms. Daniels's dream of a dancer's body is long, slender and impressively lithe, with an amusingly blank, slightly insolent face topped by a spiky punk haircut. She has assembled a group of seven witty and able female dancers who occupy the stage with a teasing boldness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The ingredients were good in Brenda Daniels's new ''Irises,'' presented last Friday night at the Merce Cunningham Studio. Ms. Daniels's dream of a dancer's body is long, slender and impressively lithe, with an amusingly blank, slightly insolent face topped by a spiky punk haircut. She has assembled a group of seven witty and able female dancers who occupy the stage with a teasing boldness.</p>
        <p>The ingredients were good in Brenda Daniels's new ''Irises,'' presented last Friday night at the Merce Cunningham Studio. Ms. Daniels's dream of a dancer's body is long, slender and impressively lithe, with an amusingly blank, slightly insolent face topped by a spiky punk haircut. She has assembled a group of seven witty and able female dancers who occupy the stage with a teasing boldness. And her new three-part piece has its promise.</p>
        <p>''Irises'' begins with a solo in which Ms. Daniels, wearing a long purple velvet dress, stands almost motionless at the top of a pedestal-like flight of stairs. A woman's voice speaks lines from a poem filled with episodic imagery of a woman whose slow undressing is observed almost voyeuristically. The scene then shifts to four deliciously dowdy housewives making lime Jell-O as four gum-chewing women in tight mini-dresses and spike heels shift lazily from pose to pose before them. In the closing section, the women, dressed in unitards in shades of purple, might be shifting, elongated trees in a thicket of light and dark created by Nicole Werner.</p>
        <p>Marc Farre's electronic and acoustic score keeps Ms. Daniels sensitive company all the way, from a rising and falling hum of iridescent sound for the solo to noodling, restful little repeated melodic phrases and imperceptibly driving piano music. Mr. Farre strikes just the right balance of the artful and the incidental with his Cageian incorporation of strange, dry little screams and an answering-machine message from Kate Raley, whose poem forms the core of ''Irises.''</p>
        <p>It was difficult, however, to understand how the parts fit together and what together they expressed. Dedicated to Susana Hayman-Chaffee, Shelley Lee and Mary Seidman and to Ms. Daniels's mother, Marie, ''Irises'' seemed to have something to say about women. But the message was unclear, as if Ms. Daniels had come up with the components before the whole. And it was disturbing to see very similar choreography for Ms. Daniels, her body folding into origami shapes, in ''Damages,'' the recent group piece that completed the program.</p>
        <p>The compelling company also included Mary Lisa Burns, Kristina Harvey, Calla Jo, Amy Schwartz, Connie Sullivan, Paula Swiatkowski and Henrika Taylor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
