<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deals</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="371936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DA173CF934A15754C0A966958260" item-length="250" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deals</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Baseball</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Baseball</p>
        <p>Baseball</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI (NL) - Recalled Keith Brown, pitcher, from Nashville of the American Association. Optioned Tim Birtsas, pitcher, to Nashville.</p>
        <p>METS (NL) - Recalled Kevin Brown, pitcher, from Tidewater of the International League. Optioned Todd Hundley, catcher, to Jackson of the Texas League.</p>
        <p>TEXAS (AL) - Activated Jeff Kunkel, shortstop, from the 15-day disabled list. Sent Cecil Espy, outfielder, outright to Oklahoma City of the American Association.</p>
        <p>Football</p>
        <p>NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE -Named Reggie Roberts director of information. Promoted Leslie Hammond from public-relations assistant to publications coordinator.</p>
        <p>BRITISH COLUMBIA (CFL) - Signed Lorenzo Graham, running back.</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (NFC) - Signed Mike Tomczak, quarterback, to a two-year contract.</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI (AFC) - Agreed to terms with David Fulcher, safety.</p>
        <p>DENVER (AFC) - Waived Chris Allen, defensive lineman.</p>
        <p>DETROIT (NFC) - Signed Dan Owens, defensive end, to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>INDIANAPOLIS (AFC) - Signed Tony Walker, linebacker; Ken Clark, running back, and Harvey Wilson, defensive back.</p>
        <p>GIANTS (NFC) - Signed Rodney Hampton, running back, and Aaron Emanuel, fullback. Released Scott Underwood, defensive lineman.</p>
        <p>JETS (AFC) - Announced the retirement of Joe Kohlbrand, linebacker.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO (NFC) - Signed Anthony Shelton, safety, and Odell Haggins, nose tackle.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY (NFC) - Announced that Terry Blackmon, defensive back, and Terry Fleming, linebacker, had left camp.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
