<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Film Tribute to Clinton Focuses on Simple Values</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Campaign" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATIC TICKET -- BIG-SCREEN SALUTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC NATIONAL CONVENTION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIMES, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8173AF934A25754C0A964958260" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Film Tribute to Clinton Focuses on Simple Values</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRIMES, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How many old-fashioned American values can fit into a 14-minute film? Nearly 57 varieties, when it is by Linda Bloodworth-Thomason, the television producer who made "The Man From Hope," an intimate portrait of Gov. Bill Clinton, with commentary by Mr. Clinton and members of his family.</p>
        <p>From beginning to end, the film sought to portray Mr. Clinton not as a charismatic, dynamic political leader, but rather as a man with a modest, small-town background, no stranger to adversity, who matured into a man who believes deeply in family and country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How many old-fashioned American values can fit into a 14-minute film? Nearly 57 varieties, when it is by Linda Bloodworth-Thomason, the television producer who made "The Man From Hope," an intimate portrait of Gov. Bill Clinton, with commentary by Mr. Clinton and members of his family.</p>
        <p>From beginning to end, the film sought to portray Mr. Clinton not as a charismatic, dynamic political leader, but rather as a man with a modest, small-town background, no stranger to adversity, who matured into a man who believes deeply in family and country.</p>
        <p>The film wasted no time in sounding its main themes. As the camera pulled back from a railroad depot, Mr. Clinton began his narration with the words, "I was born in a little town called Hope, Ark.," and almost immediately cited his grandparents' opposition to segregation and their deep belief in education.</p>
        <p>But Oxford, which Mr. Clinton attended as a Rhodes Scholar, did not come up. In the great log-cabin tradition, the film included the information that Mr. Clinton was born into a home with an outhouse in the back, and dwelt on the family's financial struggles after the death of Mr. Clinton's stepfather, an alcoholic.</p>
        <p>In one of the more emotional moments, Mr. Clinton's mother, Virginia Kelley, recalled the night her son intervened to prevent his stepfather from mistreating her. Mr. Clinton, in other words, could be counted on to stand up for what was right. But he bore no ill will. In reflecting on his stepfather, he said he regarded him as a good man, more to be pitied than blamed.</p>
        <p>When not providing a voice-over, Mr. Clinton, dressed casually in a blue shirt open at the neck and a blazer, spoke directly into the camera. The use of tight camera close-ups, particularly when Mr. Clinton spoke on emotional subjects, like the birth of his daughter, Chelsea, communicated a recurrent subliminal message: here is a man who has nothing to hide, who can look Americans straight in the eye and bare his soul.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bloodworth-Thomason, the creator of the television programs "Designing Women" and "Evening Shade," scored a coup in finding film of Mr. Clinton shaking hands with President John F. Kennedy at a Rose Garden ceremony in 1963, and she used it twice, presenting the image as a kind of laying on of hands.</p>
        <p>The political genealogy also included the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and Robert F. Kennedy, whose assassinations Mr. Clinton referred to as two of the crucial events of his generation. Although the 45-year-old nominee mentioned the nation's anguish after the King slaying and the ensuing urban riots, he did not mention the Vietnam war as an emotionally wrenching experience for Americans of his age.</p>
        <p>The first mention of the word "leadership" occurs not in a political context, but when Mr. Clinton's half-brother said, "My brother took over the leadership role in our family when he was just a kid."</p>
        <p>In the end, the film painted a portrait not of a political candidate, a potential world leader or policy thinker, but a fine, decent American, manly but sensitive, firm in his ideas of right and wrong yet compassionate, a devoted husband and doting father, a man who has had his share of troubles in life but prefers to talk about the troubles of others. Bill Clinton, the film seemed to say, represented the best that small-town America can produce.</p>
        <p>In its final sequence, the film came back to Hope. "All I am or ever will be came from there," Mr. Clinton said, and then reaffirmed his faith in the American dream.</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATIC TICKET -- BIG-SCREEN SALUTE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
