<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="607330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">METRO DIGEST (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC1530F934A35756C0A965958260" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>METRO DIGEST  FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WARNS INSURER</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has notified Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield that its handling of $1.7 billion in Medicare claims for doctors' services has been so poor for the last three years that Empire's contract with the Government may be canceled, government officials said. A1. DEPORTEE FROM ISRAEL CHARGED IN BLAST</p>
        <p>A 27-year-old Palestinian, Mohammad Ahmad Ajaj, who was deported from Israel as a suspected terrorist was charged yesterday with conspiring in the World Trade Center bombing by traveling into the United States with another suspect and carrying manuals that told how to construct the kind of bomb used in the February 26 explosion. A1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>METRO DIGEST  FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WARNS INSURER</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has notified Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield that its handling of $1.7 billion in Medicare claims for doctors' services has been so poor for the last three years that Empire's contract with the Government may be canceled, government officials said. A1. DEPORTEE FROM ISRAEL CHARGED IN BLAST</p>
        <p>A 27-year-old Palestinian, Mohammad Ahmad Ajaj, who was deported from Israel as a suspected terrorist was charged yesterday with conspiring in the World Trade Center bombing by traveling into the United States with another suspect and carrying manuals that told how to construct the kind of bomb used in the February 26 explosion. A1.</p>
        <p>Mahmud Abouhalima, in the first public statements by any of the World Trade Center suspects, said that he knew five other men who have been arrested in the case, but he denied any involvement in the attack. B3. NEW YORK CITY  A CONTROVERSY DREW FEW VOTERS</p>
        <p>Despite the most vigorously disputed campaign in two decades, only about 9.4 percent of New York City voters cast ballots in Tuesday's community school board elections, according to tentative figures released yesterday. B2. DINKINS NAMES PRODUCTIVITY PANEL</p>
        <p>After being criticized for months for not securing productivity gains from municipal workers, Mayor Dinkins announced the formation of a panel to study how to get more out of the city work force. B3. The explosion at an East Side power plant, the Waterside plant, last November occurred in part because Con Edison failed to drain steam pipes, a Federal safety agency said. B3. REGION  COURT FINDS SEX BIAS</p>
        <p>The state's highest court ruled in Albany that drug treatment programs cannot exclude pregnant women as a matter of policy, saying the practice is sexually discriminatory. Lawyers in the case said the ruling was the first of its kind by a top court in any state. B2. 4th TROOPER CHARGED IN TAMPERING</p>
        <p>In a growing scandal that has shaken the New York State Police, a fourth trooper was charged with tampering with evidence. David M. Beers pleaded not guilty in Broome County Court in Binghamton. B4. FLORIO AIDE HAS POWERHOUSE FIRM</p>
        <p>The financial firms that Governor Jim Florio's chief aide, Joseph C. Salema, and another Florio ally established eight years ago have grown to become major bond firms. B4. POLICE OFFICERS CHARGED IN BEATING</p>
        <p>A Federal grand jury in White Plains charged two Yonkers police officers with violating the civil rights of two men and a woman by beating them during arrests. B5. The Grumman Corporation in Garden City, L.I., announced that it was closing a major electronics plant in Suffolk County. B4.  The Connecticut General Assembly passed the first half of an $8.6 billion state budget. B5. Our Towns by James Barron B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
