<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="607300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DB1531F934A35756C0A965958260" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The productivity of American factories soared in the first quarter, helped by production of computers and cars, but productivity in the entire private economy fell at an annual rate of 0.1 percent.  [ Page D1. ]  Shoppers cut back on visits to stores in April, depressing sales growth for most retailers.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>The Labor Department says that it overstated by 540,000 the number of jobs created in the late 1980's and how many jobs disappeared in the recession.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The productivity of American factories soared in the first quarter, helped by production of computers and cars, but productivity in the entire private economy fell at an annual rate of 0.1 percent.  [ Page D1. ]  Shoppers cut back on visits to stores in April, depressing sales growth for most retailers.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>The Labor Department says that it overstated by 540,000 the number of jobs created in the late 1980's and how many jobs disappeared in the recession.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Administration officials are considering alternatives to the investment tax credit to spur the economy, including small-business tax breaks and a smaller corporate income tax increase.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>How one young lobbyist preserved the tax-deductibility of airline and hotel club dues offers insight into Washington.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>The Senate voted to make lobbyists report on who hires them to sway public policy and what they spend doing it.  [ A18. ]</p>
        <p>Legislation to revamp the nation's health-care system will be delayed further before going to Congress.  [ A18. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield was told by the U.S. that its handling of $1.7 billion in Medicare claims was so poor that its contract with the Government might be canceled.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Some of the nation's biggest newspapers are forming a research consortium to explore new ways to use computers and telecommunications to deliver news.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Carl Icahn offered to buy out holders of E-II Holdings' senior notes and take control of the company in a deal worth about $820 million.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Chrysler named a new executive vice president and chief financial officer to replace Jerome York, who joined I.B.M.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Computer makers and phone companies questioned the new U.S. plan to encode advanced electronic communications.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Leslie Fay replaced BDO Seidman with Arthur Andersen as the auditor for its restated results for 1991 and 1992.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>OSHA wants to fine Con Edison $247,000 for a power plant explosion last November that killed one man and burned two.  [ B3. ]</p>
        <p>Grumman will close a major electronics plant on Long Island, along with others in Texas and Maryland.  [ B4. ]</p>
        <p>The firms built by Gov. Jim Florio's chief aide and another ally have become the biggest and most influential advisory concerns in New Jersey's municipal bond business.  [ B4. ]</p>
        <p>The largest law firms grew hardly at all last year, continuing layoffs and hiring freezes because there is not enough work.  [ B16. ] International</p>
        <p>China has been on an American shopping spree in recent months, ordering more than $1 billion of goods. Driving the deals is the June deadline by which President Clinton must decide whether to extend China's most-favored-nation trade status.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>The French economy is in far worse straits than the previous Socialist Cabinet suggested, according to a report cited as a factor in the suicide of former Prime Minister Pierre Beregovoy.  [ A9. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks traded in a narrow range for much of the day, then turned down in the last hour. The Dow slipped 7.20.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>The Treasury's shift in its borrowing mix away from long-term debt is a bet that inflation will remain at low levels.  [ D12. ]</p>
        <p>Copper fell to five-and-a-half-year lows.  [ D14. ]  The dollar ended lower against other leading currencies.  [ D14. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Herbalife, the food-supplement company that nearly went bankrupt, appears to have the worst behind it. Market Place.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Good Housekeeping is drawing fire from homosexuals over ads dealing with family values. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D15. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
