<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rink Exchanges Pucks for Big Bird</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="638451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAUPPAUGE (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RINX (HAUPPAUGE, LI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDC1E3EF930A35753C1A965958260" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rink Exchanges Pucks for Big Bird</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the New York Islanders trained at the Rinx at Hidden Pond Park in Hauppauge, coaches and executives gathered around a conference table in a room above the ice to discuss roster moves, salaries and logistics.</p>
        <p>As soon as camp ended, however, the personality of the room changed quickly. Workers decorated the walls with large pictures of Big Bird and the Cookie Monster. A rocking horse and toddlers' toys took over part of the space as a preschool set up shop. Children visited to see where they would spend the next nine months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the New York Islanders trained at the Rinx at Hidden Pond Park in Hauppauge, coaches and executives gathered around a conference table in a room above the ice to discuss roster moves, salaries and logistics.</p>
        <p>As soon as camp ended, however, the personality of the room changed quickly. Workers decorated the walls with large pictures of Big Bird and the Cookie Monster. A rocking horse and toddlers' toys took over part of the space as a preschool set up shop. Children visited to see where they would spend the next nine months.</p>
        <p>The new center is growing, and the Rinx is carving out recreational and business niches.</p>
        <p>Gerry Hart, the former Islander defenseman, operates the building. It is one of nine skating centers in Nassau and Suffolk Counties and the only one with two skating surfaces and one preschool. "We've made a profit from Day 1," Mr. Hart said. 'They Treat Us Like Kings'</p>
        <p>The Islanders' coach, Al Arbour, said the Rinx was "the finest facility on Long Island by a country mile." Don Maloney, the general manager of the team, said when he left:</p>
        <p>"We're totally spoiled now. It's first class. It's clean and bright. This is a state-of-the art facility. They treated us like kings."</p>
        <p>The reasons why the Islanders are not using the Rinx for practices throughout the season long involve money, schedules, personalities and the distances of traveling around suburbs. Last season, when the $4.5 million center opened, Mr. Maloney was in his first year as general manager and Mr. Hart was a rookie at running a rink.</p>
        <p>They negotiated at length. But, both said, they could not agree on a rental fee and guaranteed ice time. There might have also been a personality conflict, Mr. Hart said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Islanders were concerned that the location was too far from the Nassau Veterans Memorial Coliseum in Uniondale, where they play their home games, and La Guardia Airport, which they use for most of their road trips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart was faced with the problem of using the buildings on weekdays, when children are at school and parents are at work.</p>
        <p>Maryann Dertinger, who worked part-time at the Rinx in a summer camp, proposed the Rinx Preschool Academy. Ms. Dertinger, with 20 years' experience with preschools and four years running a school in Ronkonkoma, proposed to combine activities in three classrooms with ice skating.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart said he accepted that idea, thinking that it might entice the parents to use the exercise room, with its 24 training machines. Rotation on the Ice</p>
        <p>"It's very different," Ms. Dertinger said. "It's new. I don't think anyone has tried it like this before. If you are going to make something succeed in this field, it helps to come up with a new concept. I did my thesis on rotating classrooms. We will use three rooms. The fourth rotation is to the ice."</p>
        <p>The school opened on Sept. 20 with room for 185 students. It has two two-and-a-half-hour sessions a day, one in the morning and one in the afternoon.  A three-day-a-week program costs $95 a month, and the two-day program is $80 a month. Skating lessons are included. With 100 children enrolled, Ms. Dertinger said, her staff includes three teachers, three aides and a secretary.</p>
        <p>"We can bring in the mothers for the aerobics and the fitness room and the skating," she said. "It becomes a family center." To Be Open 24 Hours a Day</p>
        <p>But the heart of the Rinx is hockey.  Mr. Hart said the ice surfaces were used for hockey half the time, with open skating about 25 percent and the rest filled by lessons and parties. In the peak winter months, he added, the building will be open 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>The major hockey tenants are the Police Athletic League and the Suffolk County High School League.  There is also a house league, for which teams pay $6,000 each for a winter season that lasts 20 games.</p>
        <p>"We have tried to implement a couple of things with the Long Island Waves, a women's team," Mr. Hart said. "They have a team in Freeport, and we'd like to have one here, too. So far, there isn't a great deal of interest, but we would be very receptive."</p>
        <p>The building has 23 full-time employees and a part-time staff that varies from 30 to 45, Mr. Hart said. The large lobby features television sets suspended from ceilings, a row of video-game machines, a large snack bar and a shop that sells hockey gear beneath posters of Pat LaFontaine and Gordie Howe.</p>
        <p>Behind one net are the flags of the United States and Canada. Although few Canadians will use the Rinx, such binational displays are common at rinks in Massachusetts, Minnesota and Michigan, where the sport is most popular in the United States.</p>
        <p>Despite the proximity of the Islanders, Mr. Hart said, Ranger paraphernalia outsells that of the "home" team by 4 to 1. Moving to the Rinx full time would help the Islanders "from a public-relations and marketing standpoint," Mr. Hart said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maloney said the team would practice again this season at the Long Island Skating Academy in Syosset.  Double Rinks in Manitoba</p>
        <p>In the past, the shortage of ice and quality competition on the Island have led some players like the Ferraro twins of Sound Beach to move out of state. The Ferraros now play for the United States Olympic team and have been drafted by the Rangers.</p>
        <p>"I come from Flin Flon, Manitoba," said Mr. Hart, who also played with Detroit, Quebec and and St. Louis in his 15-year career. "In my hometown, we had two rinks for 7,000 people."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart took over ownership of the Rinx in May 1992, after the builders had financial problems. Fred Young, who operates the men's hockey league, said the delay lasted three years.</p>
        <p>"When you have 32 teams looking to play and there's no place to skate, it's an eternity," Mr. Young said. Along with night league, where games extend long after midnight, Mr. Young offers daytime leagues for shift workers, "the cops, the firemen, the air-traffic controllers."</p>
        <p>The director of the Police Athletic League, Bill Hall, said he supervised 10 travel teams out of the Rinx and 26 teams in house leagues. "I just wish there were more rinks," he said. "We'd be able to fill them."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall has the help of six fellow Suffolk County police officers and volunteers. The traveling teams play in cities like Boston, Washington and Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart said that he leased the land from the Town of Islip, which owns Hidden Pond Park, and that the arena pays the town 5 to 10 percent of its revenue. He said the town had the option of taking over the building after 20 years or leasing it again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart's concern also operated the adjacent town pool in the summer. "We're testing the water," he said. "Towns cannot make money on these kinds of swimming operations.' Trend to Private Operation</p>
        <p>Even as a private venture, Mr.  Hart said, he is not sure that an outdoor pool can make a profit, because it is limited to warm weather.</p>
        <p>Supervisor Pete McGowan said converting recreational activities to private businesses on public land was "a trend of the future." The operations at Hidden Pond Park, he added, "are not costing a dime of taxpayer money."</p>
        <p>"And after the lease expires in 20 years," Mr. McGowan said, "we get the facility back, and it will be owned by the taxpayers."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
