<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jurors Find Couple Guilty In Bank Fraud</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="727015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMORED CAR SERVICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REVERE ARMORED INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCARETTA, ROBERT J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCARETTA, SUSANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFD61E31F931A15752C1A962958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jurors Find Couple Guilty In Bank Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Nov. 21 -</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal jury today found Robert and Susanna Scaretta guilty of using their armored car company to defraud several major banks of more than $30 million to pay off the couple's Atlantic City gambling debts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scaretta, who had been free on $500,000 bail, was ordered to jail immediately by Judge Arthur D. Spatt of Federal District Court here, pending sentencing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal jury today found Robert and Susanna Scaretta guilty of using their armored car company to defraud several major banks of more than $30 million to pay off the couple's Atlantic City gambling debts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scaretta, who had been free on $500,000 bail, was ordered to jail immediately by Judge Arthur D. Spatt of Federal District Court here, pending sentencing.</p>
        <p>The judge said that there was evidence that Mr. Scaretta had "a serious gambling problem" and that "gamblers were a poor risk and likely to flee."</p>
        <p>"There is also evidence that a large amount of the missing money was never recovered, and that could give him a means of flight," said Judge Spatt, who permitted Mrs. Scaretta to remain free on bail until sentencing to care for the couple's four children.</p>
        <p>The missing money was taken between April 1990 and February 1993 from bank cash deposits that were stored by the Scarettas' armored car company, Revere Armored Inc. of Bohemia, L.I, said prosecutors, who accused the Scarettas of using Revere "like it was their own piggy bank."</p>
        <p>Testimony by several Revere employees during the eight-week trial indicated that the Scarettas, both 40, skimmed millions of dollars from bins of cash, then covered it up by falsifying or destroying records.</p>
        <p>The jury, which began its deliberations on Friday afternoon and worked through the weekend, delivered its verdict shortly after noon.</p>
        <p>The jurors found Mr. Scaretta guilty of defrauding several banks, including National Westminster, the North Fork Bank &amp; Trust Company, Key Bank of New York, and Marine Midland. He was also found guilty of using wire fraud to mislead underwriters at Lloyd's of London, which insured Revere.</p>
        <p>The scheme began to unravel when Lloyd's withdrew its coverage of Revere after a competitor raised questions about the company and its ability to underbid other armored car companies. Federal investigators and bank auditors initially estimated the loss as high as $76 million, then reduced it to $38 million. Judge Spatt indicated today that as much as $11 million may still be unaccounted for.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scaretta, a former auto mechanic who began his business with an armored truck he bought after its owner could not pay for repairs, could be sentenced to more than 10 years in prison, said the chief prosecutor, Michael Considine, an assistant United States attorney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Considine told the court that on Oct. 28, 21 months after Mr. Scaretta's arrest and in the midst of his trial, Mr. Scaretta had again returned to Atlantic City, where gaming officials reported that he spent $3,000 playing the slot machines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scaretta's lawyer, Francis X. Casale, said that he had accompanied his client and that the trip was "to gather information and help in his defense."</p>
        <p>Judge Spatt appeared to be taken aback by Mr. Scaretta's return to gambling. He admonished Mr. Casale for not informing him about the trip and for failing to seek the court's permission.</p>
        <p>"There is evidence that Mr. Scaretta was the No. 1 roller at Caesar's Palace," Judge Spatt said, "placing hundreds of thousands of dollars in bets. And that's a lot of wagering for a man who is said to have a modest income."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Scaretta, who was Revere's president, was found guilty of five counts of bank fraud and ordered confined to her home pending sentencing.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. and Mrs. Scaretta sat motionless and without expression as the jury delivered its lengthy verdict. When the judge ordered Federal marshals to take Mr. Scaretta into custody, Mr. Scaretta emptied his suit pockets, gave his keys, cash and personal jewelry to his wife and kissed her goodbye.</p>
        <p>The jury also convicted a third defendant, Vincent Graff, a Revere employee, of three counts of bank fraud. He remained free on bond. Another employee charged with bank fraud, Peter Lysohir, was acquitted by the jury.</p>
        <p>Judge Spatt set a hearing for Dec. 15 on pending motions for dismissal. He said he would schedule sentencing at a later date.</p>
        <p>Lawyers representing all three convicted defendants denied their clients had taken any money and said they planned to file motions to have the verdicts set aside. Should the judge reject their motions, they said, they plan to appeal the jury's decision.</p>
        <p>On leaving the courthouse this afternoon, two jurors, who insisted on anonymity, said they had taken time to consider all the many counts on each of the four defendants.</p>
        <p>"The prosecution clearly proved its case against the Scarettas," one of the jurors said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
