<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; As Kemper's crown jewel fades, so do hopes of a high sale price.</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="727013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KEMPER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EATON, LESLIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D61E31F931A15752C1A962958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; As Kemper's crown jewel fades, so do hopes of a high sale price.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Eaton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EATON, LESLIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO, Conseco Inc. could not raise the cash to buy the Kemper Corporation for $60 a share, much less the $67 Conseco originally bid. So what?</p>
        <p>After all, General Electric offered $55 a share last March, and other insurance companies are said to be interested. All an investor has to do is wait for the white knight, right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO, Conseco Inc. could not raise the cash to buy the Kemper Corporation for $60 a share, much less the $67 Conseco originally bid. So what?</p>
        <p>After all, General Electric offered $55 a share last March, and other insurance companies are said to be interested. All an investor has to do is wait for the white knight, right?</p>
        <p>Wrong, according to many analysts and observers who have watched the Conseco-Kemper courtship. One big reason: The jewel in Kemper's crown -- its mutual fund business -- is rapidly losing its luster, which means that any new suitor is unlikely to pay a lot for Kemper.</p>
        <p>That certainly seems to be the stock market's view. On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, shares of Conseco rose $3, to $40.375, even while the overall market fell sharply. Shares of Kemper plunged $6.375, to $42.25, on the Big Board.</p>
        <p>The merger, which was announced in June, fell apart when it became clear that the deal could not be financed. Citibank, which had agreed to lend $1.22 billion to help finance the original transaction, said yesterday that it did not back away from its commitment to the original deal.</p>
        <p>But, a spokeswoman for the bank said, a new approval would have been needed if the terms of the acquisition were changed, as Conseco had told Kemper it wanted to do. People connected with Conseco and Kemper said they had concluded that such a new deal would not be financed, given Kemper's deteriorating situation.</p>
        <p>Mutual funds have always been the key to Kemper's allure. Last year asset management was the only one of Kemper's divisions to contribute to pretax earnings, according to the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation. The other divisions -- life insurance, securities brokerage, real estate and corporate -- were losers.</p>
        <p>And until this year, the mutual fund industry had boomed. "They all got accustomed to 20 percent-plus levels of growth of assets as well as of earnings," said Guy Moszkowski, an analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, which conducts research for institutions and manages money.</p>
        <p>Because investment companies charge their fees as a percentage of the assets they manage, they benefit when markets rise and investors give them more money.</p>
        <p>But rapid growth has come to a screeching halt at many firms. Indeed, Mr. Moszkowski said that over all, the assets in mutual funds grew by just 5 percent this year through September.</p>
        <p>And that increase was not spread evenly among all kinds of funds; while those that specialize in international investments soared by 44 percent, those that specialize in bonds shrank by 5 percent. Rising interest rates have caused huge losses in bond funds, and frightened investors have bailed out.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Kemper's shareholders, the company missed out on the recent boom. During the last five years, its fund assets dropped by about 2 percent, while those of its competitors that also sell mutual funds through brokers more than doubled, according to the Financial Research Corporation.</p>
        <p>Kemper, however, has participated in the recent bust -- and in spades. Figures from AMG Data Services show that the assets in Kemper's bond funds have fallen by 15 percent since early March, equity funds have fallen 7 percent, and even money market funds have edged down 1 percent.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, bond fund assets at Putnam Investments, a similar firm, have fallen just 10 percent, equity fund assets have risen 20 percent, and money market fund assets have soared by a third.</p>
        <p>Kemper officials say that over all, their funds have not contracted much more than the offerings of other companies this year. Still, Kemper is taking steps to improve and broaden its stock offerings, for example, by hiring several international analysts, said Steven A. Radis, a spokesman for Kemper Financial Services.</p>
        <p>The company is now making less money from mutual funds than it did a year ago -- operating earnings from asset management have fallen 15 percent in the first nine months of 1994 and margins are smaller.</p>
        <p>But pretax margins in the company's mutual fund operation still top 25 percent, which makes executives in other industries swoon. The firm's funds are sold through many outlets, including banks, which in the fund business is very valuable.</p>
        <p>And for an acquirer, buying a troubled company can be very attractive, because rapid growth is easier to achieve than in a more stable, profitable operation.</p>
        <p>But anyone interested in Kemper "will probably try to play hardball," said Michael Lewis, an analyst for Dean Witter. "They have not done well in a good environment, and their prospects are not what they were; $60 is now the ceiling, not the floor."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
