<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Novel Kind Of Computing: Calculation With DNA</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19941123T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="727090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEOXYRIBONUCLEIC ACID (DNA)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCE (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLATA, GINA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADLEMAN, LEONARD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5DC1F31F931A15752C1A962958260" item-length="1680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Novel Kind Of Computing: Calculation With DNA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLATA, GINA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a bold experiment that is provoking investigators to reconsider what a computer is and what it means to compute, a researcher has used DNA, the genetic material, as a sort of personal computer. Exploiting the extraordinary efficiency and speed of biological reactions, he translated a difficult mathematical problem into the language of molecular biology and solved it by carrying out a reaction in one-fiftieth of a teaspoon of solution in a test tube.</p>
        <p>Conventional computers perform operations on logical symbols, which are represented inside the machine by the flow of electrons. Dr. Adleman's idea is to set up a system of symbols whose tangible expression is not electrons but the chemical units of DNA. The idea is not so far fetched given that DNA is a rich repository of information and that living cells are processing the information all the time. In Dr. Adleman's test tube system, he sets up a problem by synthesizing particular molecules of DNA, and he processes the information through the chemical reactions that take place when the molecules are mixed together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a bold experiment that is provoking investigators to reconsider what a computer is and what it means to compute, a researcher has used DNA, the genetic material, as a sort of personal computer. Exploiting the extraordinary efficiency and speed of biological reactions, he translated a difficult mathematical problem into the language of molecular biology and solved it by carrying out a reaction in one-fiftieth of a teaspoon of solution in a test tube.</p>
        <p>Conventional computers perform operations on logical symbols, which are represented inside the machine by the flow of electrons. Dr. Adleman's idea is to set up a system of symbols whose tangible expression is not electrons but the chemical units of DNA. The idea is not so far fetched given that DNA is a rich repository of information and that living cells are processing the information all the time. In Dr. Adleman's test tube system, he sets up a problem by synthesizing particular molecules of DNA, and he processes the information through the chemical reactions that take place when the molecules are mixed together.</p>
        <p>The experiment's designer, Dr. Leonard Adleman of the University of Southern California in Los Angeles, discovered a way to use DNA to solve a problem that involves finding possible paths linking seven cities. This is one of a class of famously hard mathematical problems that have no simple solutions and can, in general, only be solved by trying out all possibilities. Dr. Adleman described his experiment in the Nov. 11 issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>A DNA-based system of computing, Dr. Adleman said, are breathtakingly fast and efficient, and they have unheard of storage capacities. He said that molecular computers can perform more than a trillion operations per second, which makes them a thousand times as fast as the fastest supercomputer. They are a billion times as energy efficient as conventional computers. And they can store information in a trillionth of the space required by ordinary computers.</p>
        <p>Whether or not such molecular computing will prove practical, the experiment is tantalizing, computer scientists said.</p>
        <p>"It's a very intriguing idea," said Dr. Ronald L. Graham, adjunct director of information science at A.T.&amp;T. Bell Laboratories in Murray Hill, N.J. "It's more than just cute. It makes you think in a different direction."</p>
        <p>Dr. David Jefferson, a computer scientist at the University of California at Los Angeles, said: "I am incredibly impressed. This is the first attempt to my knowledge of an undeniable computational problem solved by molecular methods. It shows a deeper unity between computational science and life science than was ever demonstrated before. I think it's fantastic."</p>
        <p>Dr. David Gifford, a computer science professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said: "It's quite exciting. It's a completely new way to think about computing. Our minds are prejudiced to think about computing in terms of computers we build ourselves. But it's important to free our minds to think about how computing might occur naturally."</p>
        <p>In addition, Dr. Gifford said, the experiment at least raises the question of whether biological systems actually compute in a more deterministic fashion than had been imagined. In evolution, for example, it is supposed that changes in DNA occur at random and lead, by the process of natural selection, to new organisms. "But there is a question of whether random events can be guided along productive paths," Dr. Gifford said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Adleman, he added, used DNA segments to help direct a search process, finding the best solution to his problem from trillions of wrong solutions. "It's conceivable that there are similar mechanisms at work in evolution," Dr. Gifford said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jefferson said that another way to look at the evolution question is to ask whether there are some computational problems that are best handled by molecular computers and others that are not. Then, he said, scientists can ask whether evolution favors mechanisms that are easy to handle with molecular computations?</p>
        <p>Besides its provocative implications, Dr. Jefferson said, the new experiment is the first example of technology on an atomic scale.</p>
        <p>"We certainly know in general that some form of molecular computation will be feasible in the coming decades," said Dr. Ralph Merkle, a computer scientist who studies nanotechnology at Xerox's Palo Alto Research Center in California. The DNA experiment "illustrates that we're in an era now where unexpected advances are not only possible but probable," he said. "It's quite possible that the route taken will be quite surprising."</p>
        <p>Dr. Adleman said his DNA experiment grew out of a year he spent in a molecular biology laboratory satisfying his curiosity about the burgeoning field of molecular genetics. "It was always in my mind that molecular biology has computational aspects to it," he said. "A computer scientist quickly learns that any sort of system where you can have organized, predictable actions or reactions can be parlayed into a computational system."</p>
        <p>He explained that the heart of ordinary computers consists of chips, and chips perform very simple operations involving 0's and 1's. "If you look at the basic operations in a computer, you find them very unimpressive," Dr. Adleman said. "But you can parlay these simple operations into much more complicated things."</p>
        <p>But it is one thing to get a notion that biological molecules might be exploited to do computations and another to figure out how to do it. Dr. Adleman said he thought for six months before figuring out a simple experiment that would use DNA as a computer.</p>
        <p>The problem, finding a path to connect seven cities when routes exist between only some of them, can only be solved in general by testing every possibility to see if a path exists. For example, if a traveler wanted to start in Baltimore, travel to six other cities and end the trip in Chicago, would a path exist? Dr. Graham said that although it is not hard for modern computers to do a problem involving seven cities, the number of possible paths grows so quickly as the number of cities increases that larger problems are simply impossible. He said that 100-city problems are challenging and that if there were 1,000 cities in the path, no computer could at present solve the problem.</p>
        <p>Dr. Adleman began by assigning each city a name in the form of a specific sequence of letters represented by chemical units of DNA. Each city had a first name that consisted of a string of 10 arbitrarily selected DNA letters and a last name that consisted of a different configuration of 10 DNA letters. Translating the names into DNA letters, he said, is analogous to the first step an ordinary computer would take, which would be to translate the city names into strings of 0's and 1's. In a sense, it is using the language of DNA rather than the language of computers to label the cities.</p>
        <p>Next Dr. Adleman gave each city a set of "flight numbers." A flight number for a flight between Baltimore and Chicago, for example, would consist of the last name of Baltimore in the DNA code appended to the first name of Chicago in the DNA code, except that these sequences of DNA would be expressed in their mirror opposites of the sequences for the cities. (In the four-letter alphabet of DNA, A is the opposite of T and has a strong chemical affinity with it, and C is the opposite of G.)</p>
        <p>Dr. Adleman then ordered the synthesis of DNA molecules corresponding to the cities and to the flight tags representing all the permissible flights between one city and another. Then he mixed all the DNA segments together. What happened then was that each flight tag started pairing with the DNA for its two cities, building up longer and longer chains of DNA representing flights between more and more cities.</p>
        <p>As the DNA segments sloshed through the solution and bumped into one other, they almost instantaneously created all the permitted paths linking the seven cities. Using well-established techniques of molecular biology, Dr. Adleman could then look for the molecule, if any, that represented the solution. The molecule would contain one sequence each of all the designated cities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Adleman said he did not do the study to make a commercially applicable computing system, but instead to show that it is possible to exploit the computational power of biological systems.</p>
        <p>"All of this comes from the fact that if you hold up, say, a tablespoon of water, you have something like 1023 molecules," he said. "It's just a huge number. If you can orchestrate and choreograph them to do something all at once, you can execute operations thousands of times faster than the fastest supercomputers..</p>
        <p>"The energy efficiency is just stunning," Dr. Adleman added. He explained that a joule, a unit of energy, is the amount of energy that is needed to burn a 100-watt light bulb for one second. Thermodynamic theory, he says, predicts that one joule can fuel 34 times 1019 operations. A cell can perform 2 times 1019 operations. But a supercomputer can only do 1010 operations, making a cell 1010 times more efficient.</p>
        <p>The same goes for information storage, Dr. Adleman said. Cells can store one bit of information in one nanometer of space. A videotape stores one bit in 1012 nanometers, taking a trillion times more space than is used in cells.</p>
        <p>"For me, the main point is not that DNA can compute so well, it's that it can compute at all," Dr. Adleman said.</p>
        <p>When computer scientists start to view DNA as a computer, he said, "we have a chance to look at a system of computation that's evolved for millions of years," adding, "We might reasonably expect that it has evolved computational tricks that would be of great interest to a computer scientist."</p>
        <p>Dr. Gifford said that for him, it is these philosophical issues that make the work so intriguing.</p>
        <p>"Some might say, 'Well, it really isn't practical,' " Dr. Gifford said. But, he added, the new finding, "is like a stake in the ground," marking what he expects will be the start of a new era.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 23, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about an experiment using DNA, the genetic material, as a form of computer referred incorrectly in some copies to a problem solved that way. It was to find a path connecting seven cities, passing through each once, when routes exist between only some of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 23, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about an experiment using DNA, the genetic material, as a form of computer referred incorrectly in some copies to a problem solved that way. It was to find a path connecting seven cities, passing through each once, when routes exist between only some of them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
