<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knowing when you're being seduced by powerful persuasive techniques.</title>
    <meta content="29TECH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="983850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY: DIGITAL COMMERCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sun Microsystems Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, Denise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fogg, B J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6D71731F93AA15751C1A961958260" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knowing when you're being seduced by powerful persuasive techniques.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Denise Caruso</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caruso, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of thinkers and researchers are studying computers and software as tools of persuasion, both to help industries that use them and to protect consumers from their unscrupulous use; B J Fogg, Sun Microsystems Inc researcher, studies how persuasive technology actively campaigns to change behavior (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE messages that unfold on the many screens of our lives -- televisions, automated teller machines, computers and their offspring -- have become so integral to our routine that we often overlook their extraordinary ability to influence our behavior.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of thinkers and researchers recognize that this ability is at once wondrous and spectral. They believe that a broad understanding of computers and software as tools of persuasion may not only help the industries that use them but may also protect the rest of us from their unscrupulous use.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE messages that unfold on the many screens of our lives -- televisions, automated teller machines, computers and their offspring -- have become so integral to our routine that we often overlook their extraordinary ability to influence our behavior.</p>
        <p>But a growing number of thinkers and researchers recognize that this ability is at once wondrous and spectral. They believe that a broad understanding of computers and software as tools of persuasion may not only help the industries that use them but may also protect the rest of us from their unscrupulous use.</p>
        <p>The idea of persuasive technology is not new; veteran computer users have long known that hardware and software were changing their behavior, from the first time they had to memorize a string of arcane commands to get something done.</p>
        <p>Though some of us came to appreciate the new capabilities that computer software gave us, we were also aware that these capabilities were not of our choosing. They were bestowed upon us by some programmer in some fusty cubicle who decided how we would draw our digital pictures, calculate our digital net worth, write our digital novels.</p>
        <p>This is the kind of persuasion that the author and editor Steven Johnson explicates in his book, ''Interface Culture: How New Technology Transforms the Way We Create and Communicate'' (Harper San Francisco, 1997). Where some might feel manipulated by software designers, Mr. Johnson sees them as creators, and their creations as metaphors for a new mode of human thought.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson's premise is that software interfaces -- the connection point where the interactivity between people and technology actually takes place -- are persuasive precisely because they force us to think differently, however subtle the change may be.</p>
        <p>But we are also confronted by much less subtle persuaders.</p>
        <p>B. J. Fogg, a researcher at Sun Microsystems Inc. and a visiting scholar and lecturer in Stanford University's departments of computer science and communications, has just finished teaching the first course ever on a subject he calls ''captology'' -- an acronym for computers as persuasive technology.</p>
        <p>Moving beyond the ambient effects of interface on the way we think and communicate, Mr. Fogg's captology research explores how persuasive technology actively campaigns to change our behavior. (He has  compiled a resource base, available at http://www.captology.org.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Fogg puts persuasive technology into three categories: tools, media and social actors. Among the most compelling examples of the last category are the Baby Think It Over doll and some software that Hewlett-Packard ships with its color printers.</p>
        <p>The doll is part of the Baby Think It Over program intended to combat pregnancy among teen-agers. This ''infant simulation'' -- i.e., chips and software inside a realistic doll -- cries whenever the baby needs to be fed, is in the wrong position, is treated roughly or is neglected.</p>
        <p>Equally remarkable in its own way is the software screen saver called MOPy (for ''multiple original prints'') that Hewlett-Packard makes available to people who buy its color printers.</p>
        <p>This virtual pet for the computer desktop (available at http:// www.hp.com/go/fish) encourages users to make multiple original copies on the printer instead of duplicating the original printout on a color copier. This, in turn, keeps them buying more of Hewlett's color inks.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is easy to dismiss these examples as insignificant; they are so persuasive that they barely register in our conscious minds. But if we really look around us, it is somewhat astonishing how certain kinds of technology do actually affect our behavior.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most interesting area of persuasive technology is what Mr. Fogg calls seductive computing -- the products that vamp from across the room (or across the Web), crooning, ''Try me, buy me, use me . . .''</p>
        <p>For example, the GTE Airfone's screen flashes, ''Call home! Check your voice mail! Log on! Here's how!'' Or those gaudy ''attract mode'' screens that seduce quarters from gamers in a video arcade.</p>
        <p>Seductive computing could become a crucial component in interactive design on the Internet if someone figures out how to use its techniques to attract visitors to a Web site, rather than to annoy them. At present, an animated banner ad on a Web page comes on much more like a boor than a seducer; it demands your attention but does not know when to shut up.</p>
        <p>Many ideas and methodologies of persuasion have the potential to put interactive design on a fresh and much steadier course, taking the voodoo out of a process that is needlessly mysterious today.</p>
        <p>The larger question, of course, is whether persuasive technology is a good idea at all -- especially when  talking about turning a machine as soulless as a computer into what is essentially a propaganda engine.</p>
        <p>We probably do not mind being persuaded to be responsible and healthy. But what happens when those with bad intentions deploy persuasive techniques? As Mr. Fogg says, with tongue only slightly in cheek, how can we be sure that ultra-gory video games like Mortal Kombat were not designed to make children blase about violence?</p>
        <p>Giving people the knowledge to protect themselves from manipulation is the reason that Mr. Fogg says he studies captology and would have others recognize its importance. Because interactive technology is, by its very definition, more engaging than other types of media, he says, it has the potential to be the most persuasive of all.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY: DIGITAL COMMERCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
