<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bell's Two Homers Leave Yanks in Rut</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TORONTO BLUE JAYS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DC1231F936A15755C0A966958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bell's Two Homers Leave Yanks in Rut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A good trip? A bad trip? It was a little of both. In the late afternoon today, the Yankees gathered their belongings and returned home, satisfied that they had won four of seven games on the road but unsettled by the last two dizzying days, which left them with losses and with the familiarity of their position in the cellar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A good trip? A bad trip? It was a little of both. In the late afternoon today, the Yankees gathered their belongings and returned home, satisfied that they had won four of seven games on the road but unsettled by the last two dizzying days, which left them with losses and with the familiarity of their position in the cellar.</p>
        <p>A good trip? A bad trip? It was a little of both. In the late afternoon today, the Yankees gathered their belongings and returned home, satisfied that they had won four of seven games on the road but unsettled by the last two dizzying days, which left them with losses and with the familiarity of their position in the cellar.</p>
        <p>When the day was done, George Bell had hit two home runs and driven in four runs, and the Toronto Blue Jays had dispatched the Yankees, 8-3, under the Skydome roof. By the end of their weeklong trip, the Yankees were no better off than when they started.</p>
        <p>''We're still in last place,'' said Steve Sax, ''and we have a lot of ground to make up. But I see some good things. We're scoring runs, and the young guys we brought up are contributing.''</p>
        <p>The giddiness of Friday is gone now. After taking the first two games here, the Yankees slashed their deficit in the American League East to 12 games. Now, after the four-game split, it is back to 14, just a half-game better than when they left New York last week.</p>
        <p>Catching Up Gets Tougher</p>
        <p>At this rate, they will catch the first-place Blue Jays by the first snowfall of winter.</p>
        <p>They were done in by Bell, who rapped three more hits despite a bruise at the base of his right thumb. He hit .550 in the series, going 11 for 20 with 5 home runs, 2 doubles, 9 runs scored and 9 runs batted in.</p>
        <p>Today, Bell hit homers in his first two times at bat against Chuck Cary, who started for the Yankees but couldn't get past two batters in the third. How to pitch to Bell? ''I tried going away; I tried going in,'' Cary said. ''Then I tried going away again and I tried going in. You're asking the wrong guy. He's well protected in the lineup, so he's going to see a lot of good pitches. But he's good enough to hit bad pitches.''</p>
        <p>Bell, whose average rose from .283 to .302 in the series, offered no real reason for his surge.</p>
        <p>''I don't even try to figure it out myself,'' he said. ''I'm just going up there and hitting. I'm swinging the bat pretty good, and that's it.''</p>
        <p>Fast Start by Blue Jays</p>
        <p>By the time the fourth inning was complete, the Blue Jays had 7 of their runs and 9 of their 13 hits.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had gotten a bases-empty home run by Bob Geren in the third, and in the fifth they got one big chance but didn't capitalize.</p>
        <p>They had two runs in against John Cerutti, the Toronto pitcher, and loaded the bases with one out after Sax and Don Mattingly hit singles and Jesse Barfield was hit on the left foot by a pitch. But Mel Hall struck out swinging and Jim Leyritz, the rookie, drove a two-strike pitch to left that was caught at the wall by Bell.</p>
        <p>''I thought it had a chance,'' Leyritz said, ''especially because the ball carries so well here. I just didn't get enough of it.''</p>
        <p>In the sixth, they had runners at first and second with two out, but Mattingly hit a fly ball to right. The Yankees had 49 hits in four games, but Mattingly went just 3 for 21, a .143 average, and dropped to a season-low .257.</p>
        <p>Mattingly Is Frustrated</p>
        <p>''I feel frustrated, obviously,'' he said. ''If you watch the games and see my numbers, you know I'm frustrated.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, so are all the Yankees, even though they had their best road trip since the middle of May. In their previous two trips, they went 3-12.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't a bad trip,'' said Hall, ''but we really didn't gain anything. We're still in last place, and we're still behind six teams. We can't worry about catching the leader until we catch the other five teams ahead of us. Going 4-3 doesn't really help us. It's a sign we're playing better baseball, but it's not going to get you back in it.''</p>
        <p>Not Ready</p>
        <p>Mike Witt, who was eligible to come off the disabled list Sunday, threw for 10 minutes off a mound before the game but is apparently no closer to being activated than he was several days ago. Witt said he would probably receive a cortisone shot for his inflamed right elbow Monday after the Yankees returned home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
