<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wanted: A Little Less Respect</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="454669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="ARCHITECTURE VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHITECTURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALK INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAHN, LOUIS I (1901-74)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERGER, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DA103BF930A15755C0A967958260" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wanted: A Little Less Respect</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Goldberger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERGER, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>LA JOLLA, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is time, once again, to ponder the fate of a building by Louis Kahn. It's only a little more than a year since a coalition of architects, architectural historians and others joined forces to defeat a plan by the trustees of the Kimbell Museum in Fort Worth to expand that Kahn masterwork in a way that would have done serious damage to it. Now the focus shifts to the Salk Institute for Biological Studies on the California coast, where plans are now afoot to construct an addition to another Kahn masterpiece: after the Kimbell brouhaha, it should come as no surprise that the news has sent Kahnophiles into a tizzy.</p>
        <p>The Salk Institute is a building that makes you want to caress concrete. Here, in this laboratory complex overlooking the Pacific Ocean, the profound magic Louis Kahn exerted over materials, space and light can be felt in its purest form. To come here is to see at once great power and immense restraint; this</p>
        <p>is</p>
        <p>architecture, as glorious, as magnificent, as awesome as in any cathedral.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is time, once again, to ponder the fate of a building by Louis Kahn. It's only a little more than a year since a coalition of architects, architectural historians and others joined forces to defeat a plan by the trustees of the Kimbell Museum in Fort Worth to expand that Kahn masterwork in a way that would have done serious damage to it. Now the focus shifts to the Salk Institute for Biological Studies on the California coast, where plans are now afoot to construct an addition to another Kahn masterpiece: after the Kimbell brouhaha, it should come as no surprise that the news has sent Kahnophiles into a tizzy.</p>
        <p>The Salk Institute is a building that makes you want to caress concrete. Here, in this laboratory complex overlooking the Pacific Ocean, the profound magic Louis Kahn exerted over materials, space and light can be felt in its purest form. To come here is to see at once great power and immense restraint; this</p>
        <p>is</p>
        <p>architecture, as glorious, as magnificent, as awesome as in any cathedral.</p>
        <p>The laboratory consists of two identical four-story wings of concrete with inset panels of teak, set parallel to each other across a court paved in travertine. At one end of the austere court, where visitors arrive, is a grove of trees, and at the other end is an open vista down the cliffs to the sea and the setting sun. The concrete has been crafted with the perfection of rich stone, and the warm teak is its perfect counterpoint: the relationship between these two materials is a metaphor for the whole building, which is nothing so much as an essay in balance.</p>
        <p>The Salk Institute has only one true peer in America, and that is Thomas Jefferson's campus for the University of Virginia at Charlottesville. At Charlottesville, too, parallel structures face each other across an open space, that one looking toward the the Blue Ridge Mountains. The Jefferson campus is a statement on the subtle balances between the individual and the community and between nature and the city, and we might well say the same of the Salk Institute -- which its founder, Dr. Jonas Salk, has called "architecture as a crucible for creativity."</p>
        <p>At La Jolla, the form of the building, in which Kahn gave scientists private studies that jut out from the main laboratory wings, expresses the equilibrium between solitary thought and communal work in research. The private studies and the larger, more flexible laboratories come together to make a kind of village, set around the piazza of the paved central court; this urban gesture is framed by the grove of trees at one end and by the stunning vista to the Pacific at the other.</p>
        <p>The Salk Institute was finished in 1965, the product of one of the most remarkable collaborations between architect and client in modern times. Dr. Salk, the inventor of the polio vaccine, was widely quoted as having told Kahn that he wanted him to design a building that would not only be a properly functioning laboratory but would also be a structure to which he could feel comfortable bringing Picasso. The two men worked closely, so much so that when Dr. Salk confessed to second thoughts about the design on the eve of the start of construction, Kahn did not fight his client; instead, he completely redesigned the project into the form it has today.</p>
        <p>Kahn died in 1974. Dr. Salk lives on, no longer in day-to-day charge of his institute but as proprietary about it as ever. Indeed, even more so lately, since he, along with the institute's board of trustees, has been seeking approval for a substantial addition, the first significant change planned for the building since its construction. The addition would be placed at the head of the central court, roughly 120 feet from the Kahn structure; it would occupy much of the landscaped area through which visitors and employees pass as they arrive at the institute, and it would change irrevocably the experience of approaching and entering Kahn's building.</p>
        <p>The design is by two architects who worked with Kahn on the original building, Jack MacAllister and David Reinhart, now with the Los Angeles firm of Anshen &amp; Allen. To say that this new proposal has had a mixed response is an understatement: there are those who feel it could not be more respectful of the original Kahn building, and there are others who believe that, if built, it will defile a masterpiece.</p>
        <p>The truth is somewhere in between. Emotions run deep where Kahn is concerned: his major buildings are more deeply beloved than any other architecture created in our time. The Salk plan is not this year's Kimbell, in which Kahn's design was going to be literally reproduced in an extension, an act of mimicry that would have turned the Kimbell Art Museum into the architectural equivalent of a stretch limousine. The Salk addition does not copy Kahn's design literally, and it would be separated from the original buildings, connected only by an underground passageway. But the question still remains: shouldn't a building as extraordinary as the Salk Institute be preserved in its original form, its greatness uncompromised by the tinkerings of lesser architects?</p>
        <p>That the addition is the tinkering of lesser architects is beyond argument: Anshen &amp; Allen have produced ersatz Kahn, imitative of his style but ultimately not nearly as respectful of Kahn as it purports to be for the simple reason that one does not honor a great architect best by mimicking him. As a pure building, the Salk addition calls to mind the sad imitations of Frank Lloyd Wright produced by the architects of Taliesin, inheritors of Wright's practice who continue to design weak work in the style of their master.</p>
        <p>But the actual architecture is less the issue here than the placement of the building. Kahn's structure is a kind of acropolis; it sits, templelike, above the sea, and an essential part of the way in which this piece of architecture is experienced comes from the way in which it is approached and entered.</p>
        <p>There is now a strikingly ordinary parking lot at the far end of the site, providing a banal first impression; after parking, one passes through the grove of trees (now rather sparse and run-down, it should be said), a landscaped intermezzo intended to serve as a buffer between the world of the automobile -- a world Kahn despised -- and the refined land of stone that Kahn had made. From the car to nature's embrace, then from the trees to the scientific village: all a sequence, ordered and intended. It was a sequence not only from the man-made to the natural and back again but from Cartesian order to softer lines and back again.</p>
        <p>As Anshen &amp; Allen originally designed the addition, this sequence was destroyed. The new building all but obliterated the grove of trees, and would have made the procession from car to Kahn one of ever-increasing order and monumentality. The breathing space, conceptual as much as ecological, that the grove of trees represented would have been lost.</p>
        <p>But then, responding to criticism from several critics including Sue Ann Kahn, the architect's daughter (and one of the leaders of the Kimbell battle), the plan was revised slightly -- enough to make a glimmer of possibility that it could evolve still further into something that would not undo all that Kahn was trying to achieve. As the plan now stands, the building has been moved another 30 feet back from the Kahn buildings, which puts it 150 feet away, and a central walkway that was to have connected the new wing with the original by bisecting the grove of trees has been eliminated. A semblance of the grove now remains, and it will be possible to meander through a landscaped area, approaching Kahn's building not on a formal axis but through trees, as he intended us to.</p>
        <p>But the building is still large, and monumental; I fear that beside it, Kahn's serene and gentle buildings will appear modest, almost too understated. Mr. MacAllister and Mr. Reinhart have given their building a central rotunda, open to the sky, that if built will become the entrance not only to their new wing but to the entire complex; it is Kahnian to a fault, oozing respect for the master's style. This is the architecture of obsequiousness, and it does not, in the end, serve Kahn well. Indeed, it makes you wish for a different building altogether -- something less like Kahn in style, something with more of its own integrity, something with a bit less grandiosity.</p>
        <p>It isn't too late. The adjacent City of San Diego, which has jurisdiction over planning for this site, gave rough approval to the project last month, but opponents have filed an appeal, and the debate is likely to go on for some time yet. Dr. Salk and the architects seem genuinely eager to respond to objections, especially given the speed with which they made the two important changes I mentioned, moving the building back and eliminating the monumental central walkway.</p>
        <p>The truth is that it is not impossible to add to the Salk Institute, nor is it reasonable to suggest that a facility built in 1965 is adequate to the needs of the 1990's. (Incidentally, the laboratories have proved to be remarkably flexible, and are much more suited to contemporary research needs than many structures built even a few years later; the problem now is not in Kahn's original design but in the fact that there simply wasn't enough of it, and it lacked such amenities as meeting and conference facilities.) If the architects and Dr. Salk can continue to edit this design, they may yet manage to prove that you can save an icon and expand it, too.  ARCHITECTURE VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
