<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confessions of a Video Glutton</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="672353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIMES, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D9103AF937A35750C0A962958260" item-length="1908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confessions of a Video Glutton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRIMES, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STOP me before I rent again.</p>
        <p>The last several weeks have been especially bad. Snow and bitter cold have sent New Yorkers rushing to the video stores, desperate to stock up on tapes and wait out the weather with nonstop triple features. The carcass was picked clean. One grim evening, my hand hovered over the box of "Stop, or My Mom Will Shoot."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STOP me before I rent again.</p>
        <p>The last several weeks have been especially bad. Snow and bitter cold have sent New Yorkers rushing to the video stores, desperate to stock up on tapes and wait out the weather with nonstop triple features. The carcass was picked clean. One grim evening, my hand hovered over the box of "Stop, or My Mom Will Shoot."</p>
        <p>I am a video addict. In the mid-1980's, when I finally acquired a VCR, I would routinely rent seven or more movies a week. It didn't look like deviant behavior at the time, because so many others were doing the same thing. But in recent years, Americans have cut back sharply. The five-movie-a-week renter now rents one or two films, if that many. Not me. The 10-film weekend binges have become rarer, but I continue to rent three to five films a week.</p>
        <p>Night after night, I creep down the aisles, elbowing my way through tight little groups of 12-year-olds, trying to justify the rental of "Beastmaster II," an exercise that requires more bogus reasoning than the program notes to a Russ Meyer film festival.</p>
        <p>There are moments of bliss, of course. Many art films and independent films come and go rather quickly. If it weren't for video I would never have seen small gems like "Dogfight," "Blood and Concrete," "Flash of Green," "Parents," "Don's Party" or "Flirting."</p>
        <p>Video has allowed me to take a walk down memory lane and revisit hard-boiled classics like "Double Indemnity" and "The Killing," to check out the pre-code Barbara Stanwyck in "Baby Face" and to verify that "Breakfast at Tiffany's" and "Butterfield 8" were as unwatchable as I remembered them being.</p>
        <p>Yes, films should be seen on the big screen. And Shakespeare should be seen on the stage, but that doesn't stop most of us from reading him. Besides, I don't like lines; the presence of fellow viewers irritates me, and I enjoy hurling abuse at the screen, small though it may be.</p>
        <p>If ever there was an action movie meant for the big screen, "Cliffhanger" is it. I enjoyed it immensely, even with its Alpine vistas shrunk to 15 inches. Stretched out on the couch, with a firm grip on a cold beer, a magazine and several books close by in case the action should give way to a mushy romantic scene, I was in home-viewing heaven. This is the way a movie should be seen. Just make a mental correction for scale. Or not, if it's too much trouble.</p>
        <p>Life is cruel, however. Convenience in one part of the equation has to be paid for somewhere else. In video, the problem comes on the supply side.</p>
        <p>As noted above, I probably rent an average of four films a week, or about 200 films a year. (Is this possible? I only remember eight of them.) That far outstrips the total annual output of all Hollywood studios combined.</p>
        <p>Consequently, the trend lines point steeply down. At a rate of 200 films a year, I must inevitably descend the ladder of taste, talent and, eventually, self-respect. How long will it be before I rent "The Pickle"? I don't know the answer (in fact, I resent the question), but rest assured that the day will come. An Expert's Secrets</p>
        <p>To slow the rate of descent, I have evolved strategies for operating at peak efficiency in the video store, for maximizing viewing opportunities and for separating the merely bad from the irredeemable. What's more, I am willing to share some of these secrets.</p>
        <p>First, I make it my business to know the store. Like supermarkets, all video stores are the same, only different. They have the basic layout of New Releases, Comedies, Classics, Dramas, Horror, Sci-Fi and Fantasy, Action, Martial Arts and Adult, with clever little sub-categories like Staff Favorites (stone-cold losers that no one has rented in about five months) or special sections devoted to, say, John Wayne or Alfred Hitchcock.</p>
        <p>Commit the layout, and the categories, to memory so you can sight a new offering on the shelves with a fast cruise, picking up visual cues out of the corner of your eye. This approach saves hours of fruitless study. Trust your peripheral vision.</p>
        <p>This won't work for new releases, of course, where close examination of the wares can be rewarded. When paying for my rentals, I look up at the list of release dates posted behind the cash register so I'll be prepared to move quickly when a hot title comes out. Know No Shame!</p>
        <p>But how to prevail over the miserable hordes also hellbent on renting "The Fugitive"? Through patience and cunning. Don't head straight to the shelves. Instead, see whether the stack of returned tapes has reached critical mass and will shortly emerge from behind the counter.</p>
        <p>Then, like a basketball player poised for a rebound, stake out turf near the New Releases shelves. Assume a relaxed pose. Appear to be staring straight ahead but keep the stack of tapes in sight. The moment the tape reaches the shelf, strike instantly, plucking it free. Be prepared not only to administer a subtle hip check to anyone trying the same move, but to ignore their stares of outrage as well.</p>
        <p>Some video stores stack the processed returns on a counter. Scan it several times while in the store.</p>
        <p>I've been referring to "the" store, but in fact, any committed video renter must rely on two, three or even more sources of supply. With time, you end up anticipating buying patterns and quirks in the cataloguing scheme.</p>
        <p>A video store that used to be around the corner from me, for example, had trouble assigning foreign films to their proper spot. I soon learned that it paid dividends to cruise just about every section except Professional Wrestling. On day, among the splatter films, I ran across "Celia," a sensitive, beautifully acted film about a young girl growing up in Australia in the 1950's. The blurb on the box mentioned an act of violence at the end of the film, thereby consigning it to the company of "Slumber Party Massacre" and "Bloodsucking Pharaohs in Pittsburgh." (It also pays to remember that many video-store clerks are shaky on alphabetizing, so coveted titles often end up several boxes, or even shelves, away from their proper positions.)</p>
        <p>Another store, near Times Square, offered standard fare in every category but for some reason had nearly all of Paul Verhoeven's early films. Most American moviegoers have seen "Basic Instinct," "Robocop" and "Total Recall." Hipper viewers recall "Soldier of Orange," "Spetters" and the stylish, slightly kinky "Fourth Man," Mr. Verhoeven's last Dutch film. I was able to enjoy "Turkish Delight," starring a very young Rutger Hauer as a rake on the loose, and even "Keetje Tippel," a naturalistic drama set in 19th-century Amsterdam.</p>
        <p>At yet a third store, the manager, a recent arrival from Russia, took a while to learn that in America, film means "Hard Target," not "Alexander Nevsky." For a month or two, I cleaned up on all manner of terrific foreign films, while the store remained empty. It couldn't last, of course. Now the manager carefully pastes little promotional notes like "steamy erotic thriller" on his latest buys. Redefining 'Choice'</p>
        <p>We video maniacs learn not to reason why, but to grab fast. My local Blockbuster does not have "I'm All Right, Jack," but it does have another early Peter Sellers, "Only Two Can Play." It does not have more than three or four Fellinis, but one of those is "The White Sheik," not that easy to find.</p>
        <p>Don't ask. Be grateful. Because the choice is usually not between early and late Fellini, but between "Meatballs" I, II, III or IV.</p>
        <p>This is the reality we're dealing with here. Video addicts inhabit a sleazy twilight world in which actors like Wings Hauser, Brigitte Nielsen, and Shannon Tweed count as major box-office draws, and all films, no matter how wretched, are "two thumbs up!"</p>
        <p>It's a world in which "Relentless" can shed the star power of Judd Nelson and still live on for two more incarnations, in which Sylvie Kristel, the original Emmanuelle, is now Emmanuelle's mother, and Richard Roundtree is never out of work.</p>
        <p>Ever wonder what happened to Linda Blair, Sally Kellerman or Erik Estrada? Scan the shelves of your video store and trace the downward progress. It's not easy to go downhill from "Sheena," but Tanya Roberts managed it. The Genre Frontier</p>
        <p>Not until I began to haunt the video stores did I realize that while snobby cineastes were lining up for Wim Wenders retrospectives, the rest of America was feasting on inexhaustible genres like the slumber party-sorority house-slumber party-summer camp massacre film, a highly efficient cinematic form that allows viewers to get slice-and-dice action, horror, suspense and lots of young women running around in their underwear.</p>
        <p>The "babes behind bars" genre, it turns out, is at least as rich as film noir. It dates to the 1957 film "Girls in Prison" and runs full speed up to last year's "Chained Heat 2" (with the superstar Brigitte Nielsen).</p>
        <p>Do not despair. Faithful searching and a willingness to roll the dice often lead to unexpected finds. My favorite example is "Cross Country," a losers-on-the-run tale, Canadian yet, that went straight to video in 1983. The stars are Richard Beymer and Nina Axelrod. It's atmospheric, exuberantly sleazy and eminently watchable. I will probably rent it again, either intentionally or because I forgot I saw it (this seems to happen more and more frequently).</p>
        <p>"Vampire's Kiss," starring Nicolas Cage, went nowhere at the box office. I hereby declare it a masterpiece. Liner-Note Lies</p>
        <p>How to separate the wheat from the chaff?</p>
        <p>First, do not be seduced by the snappy production values on the front of the box. Flip the box over and look at the little pictures on the back. Is the lighting garish? Do the interiors seem to have a lot of plywood paneling? Is Karen Black in the cast?</p>
        <p>Also look with suspicion on the term "erotic thriller," which generally means that the main character has a girlfriend who is a topless dancer, that he is investigating the murder of a topless dancer or that he routinely finds his best sources of information in topless bars.</p>
        <p>Handicap the blurbs. A film that's described as "intriguing" may not be the ticket. Two thumbs up from The Abilene Post-Dispatch-Leader-Citizen makes you think that the video distributor may be reaching a little far for an endorsement. Raves from Rolling Stone have to be deeply discounted. At this point, I will respond to nothing short of an actual cash offer from Jann Wenner.</p>
        <p>Beware the clones. Every "Basic Instinct" spawns a "Primal Instinct" and a "Basic Motive." Sometimes the boxes look pretty good. The movies look pretty bad.</p>
        <p>Try to draw the line. I can rent "Weekend at Bernie's" with a clear conscience. I have actually seen all of the "National Lampoon Vacation" movies. But standards must be maintained. I refuse to put my money on the counter for any film with Barbra Streisand, Dudley Moore or Sean Young, or one in which Richard Gere looks intense. I pass by anything advertised as "the feel-good movie of the year."</p>
        <p>Stick to these principles and, after the last credit has rolled, you will always be able to say, "Gee, that could have been a lot worse."</p>
        <p>My Personal List of Shame:</p>
        <p>1.  "Milo and Otis."</p>
        <p>2.  "Drop Dead Fred."</p>
        <p>3.  "Revenge of the Nerds" (Parts 1 and 2, possibly 3 as well, I can't remember).</p>
        <p>4.  "Bill and Ted's Excellent Adventure."</p>
        <p>5.  "The Adventures of Ford Fairlane" (but I ripped it out of the VCR, honest).</p>
        <p>6.  "Point Break."</p>
        <p>7.  "Caligula."</p>
        <p>8.  "Howard Stern's Butt Bongo Fiesta."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
