<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; New Beginnings Near the End of Life</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637623"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIDDER, TRACY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OLD FRIENDS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D7143BF933A0575AC0A965958260" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; New Beginnings Near the End of Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Old Friends  By Tracy Kidder  352 pages. Richard Todd/Houghton Mifflin. $22.95.</p>
        <p>"It was not the place itself but the visions of the life to come that got her down," Tracy Kidder writes about Ruth, a volunteer at the nursing home he describes so touchingly in his new book, "Old Friends."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Old Friends  By Tracy Kidder  352 pages. Richard Todd/Houghton Mifflin. $22.95.</p>
        <p>"It was not the place itself but the visions of the life to come that got her down," Tracy Kidder writes about Ruth, a volunteer at the nursing home he describes so touchingly in his new book, "Old Friends."</p>
        <p>He continues: "The visible decline of residents who came to her Literary Hour -- that woman who seemed so sprightly last week on her cane, appearing this week in a wheelchair, bravely trying to smile -- and glimpses Ruth had of the nearly comatose laid out in their bedrooms, and of the demented wandering the halls. Once when she was on her way out, a nice-looking resident approached her and asked if she wouldn't please give him a ride home. She left in tears that day, feeling sorry both for the man and for the fact that her own father now resided among people who seemed consigned to live no kind of life at all."</p>
        <p>Feelings similar to Ruth's are what make it so often painful to read "Old Friends." Not only deterioration and death pervade its pages, but also the depressing revelation that there is really no rest in a rest home. The struggle for attention continues. People living in too-close quarters find themselves squabbling, and yet, despite all the community, they are afflicted with an inescapable feeling of separateness. As the legend on one resident's baseball cap puts it, "We Are All in This Alone."</p>
        <p>Still, if no one suffers these feelings more sharply than the residents of Linda Manor, near Northampton, Mass., then no one fights against them more bravely. As Lou Freed, Ruth's father, remarks, "It's a great life, if you don't weaken."</p>
        <p>Lou is 92, blind ("I could read if I could see"), a widower, suffering from occasional bouts of angina and assailed by old memories that he has to curb himself from rambling on about. He likes the poems of Robert Service, and he can't think of anything in his life he feels guilty about. Even at 92 he remains endlessly curious ("If vultures ate tainted meat, why didn't they get sick?" "What kind of wood were George Washington's teeth made from?"), and although as a Jew he is not particularly religious, he sometimes wonders who began the universe.</p>
        <p>Lou is assigned to a room with Joe Torchio, 72, still married, a former probation officer from Pittsfield, victim of a stroke at 54 that led him eventually to give up heavy drinking. Joe admires the bitterly ironic poetry of Stephen Crane, although, as Mr. Kidder writes, "ever since his stroke, he couldn't get through more than a sentence before the words seemed to scatter in front of him like pigeons in a park." Embittered by the loss of a son to leukemia and the birth of a retarded daughter, Joe has given up his Catholicism. He hopes there's an ice storm when he dies. "I want my ashes spread on the sidewalk. So nobody will slip."</p>
        <p>Clearly Lou and Joe are opposites in most respects. But they have in common a deep generosity, a thoughtfulness toward others and a wacky sense of humor. "We're the best!" Joe exclaims. "God help the others if we're the best," Lou says. "I have half a brain, and you can't see," Joe says. "And so betwixt us both, we licked the platter clean," Lou says. They come to admire and even love each other. They make themselves counselors and elder statesmen at Linda Manor.</p>
        <p>Their lives are touching, funny and inspiring in Mr. Kidder's graceful prose. So a reader keeps reading "Old Friends" despite dreading the inevitable deaths of Joe and Lou. Yet mercifully the author allows them to survive in these pages. It is through another character's story that he poignantly dramatizes dying in a rest home, just as through still other lives he depicts rebellion, submission, vacant withdrawal and successful accommodation, like allegorical figures in some medieval tapestry. Joe and Lou, meantime, go on and on.</p>
        <p>This eventually becomes one of the problems with "Old Friends." Beyond a certain point, a static quality sets in. Part of the difficulty is that the author never reveals himself in the text. Yet he is clearly present in the way some of the people express themselves. "He's a good scout," the wife of the dying man is reported thinking out loud. "He's puzzled by these things that are happening to him." So a kind of black hole develops in the narrative toward which the characters contort themselves. On the other hand, Mr. Kidder too rarely steps outside his story and speaks in general terms about the problems of growing old in America. Along with stasis, claustrophobia sets in.</p>
        <p>Or maybe the trouble is that beyond a certain point, our anxiety over what will inevitably happen to Lou and Joe overcomes our curiosity. In any case, Mr. Kidder sustains their story a few pages longer than he did this reader's attention.</p>
        <p>Still, "Old Friends" leaves a powerful impression. Mr. Kidder writes gracefully, particularly in descriptive passages, as he has shown again and again in books like "House," "Among Schoolchildren" and "The Soul of a New Machine," which won the National Book Award and the Pulitzer Prize for nonfiction in 1982.</p>
        <p>Dusk coming to the Berkshires, the lights inside Linda Manor beginning to reflect in the windows, the faint pastels of dawn perceptible to sleepless residents, crows gathering in a dead maple tree on a Sunday morning, as if holding their own church service: such images impress themselves sweetly and indelibly on feelings concentrated on death by these pages.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Kidder captures most movingly is the candle dancing up before guttering. Of Joe Torchio he writes: "One might have thought such a fiery temperament would expend itself in fury at the irritations and confinements of this place. But when his powers to act had greatly diminished, Joe had taken control of his life. He'd done so by gaining a greater control of himself. . . . He had entered a little society founded merely on illness, and, accepting it for what it was, realizing it was all there was for him, he had joined it and improved it. He had made a lot of friends in here, and one friend for life."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
