<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viacom Gets Help From Blockbuster</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARAMOUNT COMMUNICATIONS INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BLOCKBUSTER ENTERTAINMENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">VIACOM INTERNATIONAL INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">QVC NETWORK INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REDSTONE, SUMNER M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE1130F933A0575AC0A965958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viacom Gets Help From Blockbuster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though he still has a ways to go before he can match a rival $9.8 billion bid for Paramount Communications Inc., the chairman of Viacom Inc., Sumner Redstone, yesterday found a way to raise an additional $600 million that can be used to sweeten his offer, currently valued at $7.6 billion, or $64.77 a share.</p>
        <p>The Blockbuster Entertainment Corporation, the video rental company based in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., agreed yesterday to invest the $600 million in exchange for convertible preferred stock in Viacom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though he still has a ways to go before he can match a rival $9.8 billion bid for Paramount Communications Inc., the chairman of Viacom Inc., Sumner Redstone, yesterday found a way to raise an additional $600 million that can be used to sweeten his offer, currently valued at $7.6 billion, or $64.77 a share.</p>
        <p>The Blockbuster Entertainment Corporation, the video rental company based in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., agreed yesterday to invest the $600 million in exchange for convertible preferred stock in Viacom.</p>
        <p>The proceeds would allow Mr. Redstone to raise the cash portion of his bid for Paramount to roughly $14 a share, from $9.10 a share, if he chooses.</p>
        <p>Currently, the shareholders of Paramount prefer a competing $9.8 billion offer from QVC Network Inc. because it is higher, and especially because it would entitle them to $30 a share in cash. More Work Ahead</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Redstone seemed pleased with the Blockbuster deal, but understood that he had more work ahead to close the gap. Even with the infusion from Blockbuster, Mr. Redstone must come up with an additional $1.6 billion to match the total value of QVC's cash and stock offer. If he felt obligated to match the cash portion of the QVC bid dollar-for-dollar, he would need to raise another $1.9 billion in new financing.</p>
        <p>"Events will evolve that relate to us in the next several days, if not sooner," Mr. Redstone said, indicating that another equity investment would probably be announced by Monday.</p>
        <p>In an era where just about every media company is searching for strategic mergers, companies appear prepared to explore linking up with Viacom in some way. And bankers said they would be willing to lend Viacom big sums of money on the right terms to help Mr. Redstone realize his ambitions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redstone is known to have strong feelings against taking on unnecessary debt and is intent on finding equity partners instead. He acknowledged yesterday that Viacom had been "talking to telephone companies" and that "a cable company would be welcome" as another possibility.</p>
        <p>Sources close to Mr. Redstone have said he was in talks with Southwestern Bell and Cox Enterprises. A potential deal could yield as much as $1 billion that he could use to buy Paramount. Analysts said they expected he could then make up the remaining $900 million difference through borrowing.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Redstone still needs an additional $2 billion, if that is his goal," said David Londoner, a media analyst at Wertheim Schroder. "He does not have to get equity investors for the entire $2 billion. If he gets a portion of that and borrows the remainder, the combined Viacom-Paramount balance would not be excessively leveraged."</p>
        <p>As of yesterday, Mr. Redstone was still playing cat and mouse about whether he would use the proceeds from Blockbuster to raise his bid for Paramount. But in a promise to his shareholders, he said, "We will have maximum flexibility that does not leverage our company."  A Move to Diversify</p>
        <p>For Blockbuster, the arrangement is only the latest effort aimed at helping the company diversify out of the home video business. Many industry experts project that the video rental business will be eclipsed by newer technologies that will allow consumers to view videos on demand at home.</p>
        <p>Blockbuster has been in talks with Viacom regarding an investment since April, well before it became aware of Mr. Redstone's designs on Paramount.</p>
        <p>One investment banker, who requested anonymity, said of the Blockbuster infusion, "It looks like a good deal for Viacom." He was impressed because Mr. Redstone had managed to raise a lot of money and strengthen his balance sheet without sacrificing any control.</p>
        <p>The deal would entitle Blockbuster to receive cumulative preferred shares in Viacom paying a 5 percent cash dividend each year. The shares would be convertible into nonvoting Viacom stock at $70 a share. (Viacom's class A stock fell $1.50, to $59.50, and itsclass B stock fell 75 cents, to $55.25, on the American Stock Exchange yesterday.) A Saving of Face</p>
        <p>The clever structure of the deal allows Mr. Redstone to save face on at least one front. Last week, he claimed he would be able to buy Paramount without having to take on equity partners even in the face of a higher bid by QVC.</p>
        <p>Because Blockbuster is accepting securities that lack voting rights, Mr. Redstone can say he did not back down on his pledge. His aversion to partners is another reason analysts said they suspected he might be lining up several minority partners rather than a large investor to share the burden.</p>
        <p>Getting an interest in Paramount is clearly part of the allure for Blockbuster. In fact, if the deal with Paramount does not go through, Blockbuster has negotiated the right to cut its investment in half. Either way, H. Wayne Huizenga, the chairman and chief executive of Blockbuster, will get a seat on the Viacom board.</p>
        <p>As Viacom's betrothed, Paramount officials approved the Blockbuster deal late Tuesday, a source close to Paramount said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huizenga said in an interview that there were tremendous synergies between the two companies, given that Viacom owns movie theaters and Blockbuster owns video stores.</p>
        <p>"You can have Paramount make the movies," he said, "and basically you have most of the windows of movies covered."</p>
        <p>Blockbuster has been interested in the movie business, and several executives close to QVC said Blockbuster had also talked to them about an investment in that company, but that the talks were only preliminary.</p>
        <p>Asked why he was willing to sign a deal that gave him no voting rights, Mr. Huizenga said the dividend made it worthwhile. "It is a heck of a deal," he said.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
