<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolution in Europe;   Bonn Opposition Chief Stabbed at Campaign Rally</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MENTAL HEALTH AND DISORDERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAFONTAINE, OSKAR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STREIDEL, ADELHEID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD8103EF935A15757C0A966958260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolution in Europe;   Bonn Opposition Chief Stabbed at Campaign Rally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</byline>
      <dateline>BONN, April 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Oskar Lafontaine, the candidate for Chancellor from the opposition Social Democratic Party, was stabbed in the throat today by a German woman carrying a knife concealed in a bouquet of flowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Oskar Lafontaine, the candidate for Chancellor from the opposition Social Democratic Party, was stabbed in the throat today by a German woman carrying a knife concealed in a bouquet of flowers.</p>
        <p>Oskar Lafontaine, the candidate for Chancellor from the opposition Social Democratic Party, was stabbed in the throat today by a German woman carrying a knife concealed in a bouquet of flowers.</p>
        <p>A spokesman at the hospital to which Mr. Lafontaine was taken from the campaign rally in Cologne said after a two-hour operation that he had lost a considerable amount of blood and that his condition was critical.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Heinz Pichelmaier, chief of surgery at the University Clinic of Cologne, added that doctors hoped that ''the worst danger was past,'' and that if the 46-year-old Mr. Lafontaine pulled through, there was a good chance he would have no lingering effects. The doctor said a full evaluation was not possible until morning.</p>
        <p>It remained to be seen whether Mr. Lafontaine would be able to carry on his campaign for the national elections on Dec. 2. But doctors who heard the initial medical reports said the chances seemed good that he would recover.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lafontaine was tapped as the Social Democratic Party's standard-bearer earlier this year after he was re-elected Premier of the state of Saarland with an impressive majority.</p>
        <p>A quick-witted and hard-driving politician of a new generation, Mr. Lafontaine was generally acknowledged to be facing an uphill battle against Chancellor Helmut Kohl, who has the advantage of being the leader in Bonn when the two Germanys are rapidly moving toward unification.</p>
        <p>Assailant Identified</p>
        <p>The police identified Mr. Lafontaine's attacker as Adelheid Streidel, 42 years old, from Bad Neuenahr, a town southwest of Bonn. There was no immediate information on her motive, though Deutsche Presse-Agentur, the principal West German news agency, quoted Government security services in Bonn as saying that the assailant had no known links to extremist groups.</p>
        <p>ZDF, the West German television network, reported that she had a history of mental illness and had once been arrested for arson.</p>
        <p>The chaotic aftermath of the attack was captured on television, which showed several men crouching over the prostrate and bloody figure of Mr. Lafontaine alongside a table on the stage of the municipal hall.</p>
        <p>At the edge of the stage, the attacker, a short, stocky woman with short black hair, wearing a white dress, white stockings and bright red lipstick, sat with her arms pinned by guards. She gave no answer to shouted questions from reporters, and showed little emotion then, or when she was taken away by the police.</p>
        <p>Officials said the woman sat in the second row during the rally and had repeatedly tried to mount the stage, but that the guards turned her back. When the rally was over, however, a guard let her through, thinking she was only seeking an autograph.</p>
        <p>Witnesses and the police said the woman, carrying one bouquet of roses and another of carnations and a book by Mr. Lafontaine, mounted the stage about 8:45 P.M. and asked for the candidate's autograph. As she approached him, she pulled a long knife from one bouquet and stabbed him.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pichelmaier said Mr. Lafontaine was initially treated for about half an hour at the scene by a doctor who had been in the audience. He said that contrary to early reports, the attacker did not cut Mr. Lafontaine's carotid artery, a principal artery in the neck. But, the surgeon said, Mr. Lafontaine had lost much blood and arrived at the clinic with ''zero circulation.'' He said 20 doctors took part in the emergency operation.</p>
        <p>Chancellor Kohl was on a visit to Paris at the time of the attack and was notified of it during a banquet gfiven by President Francois Mitterrand. A spokesman for the Christian Democratic Chancellor said he was ''profoundly shocked'' and sincerely hoped that Mr. Lafontaine would survive.</p>
        <p>Should Mr. Lafontaine prove incapable of continuing with the race, immediate speculation for his replacement centered on Hans-Jochen Vogel, the 64-year-old chairman of the Social Democratic Party, who was its unsuccessful candidate for Chancellor against Mr. Kohl in 1983.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vogel was among early visitors at the hospital, where he called for an immediate investigation. ''We all feel especially close to him in this hour,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The attack on Mr. Lafontaine came the day after a political rally in Cologne addressed by Mr. Kohl turned violent. Radical demonstrators pelted him and Norbert Blum, the Christian Democratic candidate for state Premier, with tomatoes, eggs and pouches of paint.</p>
        <p>Despite a history of radical terrorism in West Germany over the last 20 years at the hands of the Red Army Faction, sometimes known as the Baader-Meinhof group, the country's politicians have been relatively untouched.</p>
        <p>The most prominent politician to be assassinated in Western Europe in recent years was Olof Palme, the Prime Minister of Sweden, who was shot and killed on a Stockholm street four years ago.</p>
        <p>Aldo Moro, a former Prime Minister of Italy, was killed in 1978, after being kidnapped by terrorists of the Red Brigades. In 1973, Luis Carrero Blanco, the Prime Minister of Spain, was assassinated by Basque separatists.</p>
        <p>The most recent attack on a politician in West Germany occurred in September 1988, when Red Army Faction terrorists fired at Hans Tietmeyer, State Secretary in the Finance Ministry. He escaped untouched. In October 1986, Gerolf von Braunmuhl, director of the political department of the Foreign Ministry, was shot to death in Bonn by the Red Army Faction.</p>
        <p>Most terrorist attacks have been against businessmen. On Nov. 30, a bomb killed Alfred Herrhausen, chairman of West Germany's largest bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
