<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New U.S. Aid Sought For High Technology</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="347338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE ADVANCED RESEARCH PROJECTS AGENCY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKOFF, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1E3FF935A15757C0A966958260" item-length="764" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New U.S. Aid Sought For High Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKOFF, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Proponents of increased financial support for the development of advanced technologies, concerned that the Bush Administration is reducing its commitment to research sponsored by a Pentagon agency, are scrambling to find new sources of money outside the military budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Proponents of increased financial support for the development of advanced technologies, concerned that the Bush Administration is reducing its commitment to research sponsored by a Pentagon agency, are scrambling to find new sources of money outside the military budget.</p>
        <p>Proponents of increased financial support for the development of advanced technologies, concerned that the Bush Administration is reducing its commitment to research sponsored by a Pentagon agency, are scrambling to find new sources of money outside the military budget.</p>
        <p>The efforts have been intensified because of the removal last week of Craig I. Fields, the director of the Pentagon agency, the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, or Darpa, in a dispute over what the agency's role should be. The agency has played a vital role in the development of technologies that proved to have important commercial as well as military applications, including advanced computers and aerospace materials.</p>
        <p>Several executives of the agency said Dr. Fields had been transferred to a new post because he had advocated high-technology initiatives that some high Administration officials opposed as smacking of advocating the development of certain industries - a de facto industrial policy.</p>
        <p>A Variety of Proposals</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that they have little hope of either restoring Dr. Fields to his old position or forcing the Administration to direct the Pentagon agency toward nonmilitary research, proponents of increased financial support have shifted their attention to a variety of proposals. But they concede that the prospects for such proposals are dimmed by the Administration's ideological opposition to such concepts.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the proposals:</p>
        <p>* A new plan by the National Advisory Committee on Semiconductors, a Government-industry advisory group, to set up a private $5 billion to $10 billion fund, backed by Federal loan guarantees, to create an Electronics Capital Corporation. It would provide money for important technology projects.</p>
        <p>* A bill introduced by Senator Albert Gore Jr., Democrat of Tennessee, that would provide $1.75 billion for the development of advanced computers, software and computer networks.</p>
        <p>* A bill to be introduced soon by Representative Mel Levine, Democrat of California, to establish a corporation, known as the Technology Corporation of America, that would support joint ventures with $50 million a year.</p>
        <p>* A bill by Senator John Glenn, Democrat of Ohio, that would allocate $100 million annually for applied research financed by a new organization, the Advanced Civilian Technology Agency, a civilian counterpart to Darpa within the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>* The expansion of Federal financing for the Advanced Technology Program, created this year at the National Institute for Standards and Technology and currently receiving $10 million annually.</p>
        <p>But the Bush Administration's position has left supporters pessimistic that significant Federal programs will emerge soon to underwrite important research in areas including high-definition television, advanced semiconductors and computers.</p>
        <p>''Even many of the initiatives that were started under the Reagan Administration are on the chopping block,'' said Robert Reich, a Harvard economist who favors the development of Government programs that foster advanced technologies.</p>
        <p>'An Industrial Outcry'</p>
        <p>But proponents of increased support for such research argue that the Administration's opposition to new spending initiatives is breeding intense criticism even from Republican strongholds.</p>
        <p>''There's an industrial outcry building up,'' said Robert Cohen, a New York economic consultant. ''Normally conservative corporate executives are extremely upset about the way the country is moving away from promoting industrial innovation.''</p>
        <p>One difficulty facing those concerned about a growing gap between the United States and Japan in terms of capital investment is how to match the historically effective style of the Pentagon agency in supporting leading-edge research.</p>
        <p>The agency spends about $1 billion annually in areas including advanced computing, exotic materials and future manufacturing techniques. By spending in a freewheeling fashion, often backing academic and corporate research ventures before they are ready for commercial financing, the agency has had an enormous influence over the course of the computer industry, many executives say.</p>
        <p>Some industry executives and Government officials point out that it will not be easy to duplicate the Pentagon agency's style. ''The big issue is who are you going to trust to make the investment?'' said Robert Kahn, a former official of the agency who left it to found the Corporation for National Research Initiatives. ''Setting up a brand new organization and bringing in new people entails its own risks.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
