<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For White Sox, All Eyes Are on Thomas's Elbow</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="638993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHICAGO WHITE SOX</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TORONTO BLUE JAYS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D71430F936A35753C1A965958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For White Sox, All Eyes Are on Thomas's Elbow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As dominating a hitter as he has been this season, Frank Thomas would have elbowed his way into prominence in the American League Championship Series one way or another. But today he was the primary topic of conversation because of his elbow.</p>
        <p>Gene Lamont, the Chicago White Sox manager, and the team's talented trainer, Herman Schneider, left no doubt that Thomas, the heavy favorite to win the league's most valuable player award, would be in the lineup against the Toronto Blue Jays in the playoff opener Tuesday night. But Lamont left open the question of where Thomas would play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As dominating a hitter as he has been this season, Frank Thomas would have elbowed his way into prominence in the American League Championship Series one way or another. But today he was the primary topic of conversation because of his elbow.</p>
        <p>Gene Lamont, the Chicago White Sox manager, and the team's talented trainer, Herman Schneider, left no doubt that Thomas, the heavy favorite to win the league's most valuable player award, would be in the lineup against the Toronto Blue Jays in the playoff opener Tuesday night. But Lamont left open the question of where Thomas would play.</p>
        <p>"I'd like Frank to play first base, but I'm a little hesitant," Lamont said as his team followed the Blue Jays in a Comiskey Park workout. "The swelling went down from Saturday to Sunday. Yesterday you could see his elbow for the first time. If I had to say right now, I'd say he'd probably d.h." A Struggle and Then the Sidelines</p>
        <p>Thomas is the White Sox's regular first baseman, but in trying to catch a foul pop Sept. 19 he suffered a bruised left triceps. The injury rendered him unproductive as a hitter, and he finally sat out five games before the season finale Sunday.</p>
        <p>"I was worried," Thomas acknowledged. "My arm was so big and tight I was concerned about playing tomorrow night. You have a great year and then you're thinking your season could be over."</p>
        <p>But, Thomas added, his arm is 100 percent better than it was three days ago. He also was heartened by his ability to rap a single and a double and drive in two runs against Cleveland Sunday.</p>
        <p>"I slept with my arm in a sling for three nights," he said. "It was uncomfortable, but it helped. I think I'll be 100 percent hitting." Fear of Aggravating Injury</p>
        <p>Schneider, who was responsible for restoring Bo Jackson to playing condition after hip surgery, confirmed Thomas's thinking, saying, "I don't think it's going to hurt him swinging at all."</p>
        <p>Playing first base could be another matter. After he initially hurt his arm, Thomas aggravated it by diving for balls, and that's what the White Sox want to avoid in this four-of-seven-game series.</p>
        <p>"We need Frank's bat in the lineup," Lamont said. "If he dives for a ball and it puffs up, we won't have him."</p>
        <p>Thomas, with a .317 batting average, 41 home runs and 128 runs batted in, clearly is the focal point of the White Sox lineup. The Blue Jays, in contrast, have a multitude of reliable hitters, including Joe Carter, the leading run producer, and John Olerud, Paul Molitor and Roberto Alomar, who finished 1-2-3 in the batting race, the first time in 100 years one team has had the top three hitters. Pasqua Might Play at First</p>
        <p>If Thomas is the designated hitter, Lamont said that Dan Pasqua would play first base. Pasqua batted only .205 in 78 games this season, but he hit .294 (5 for 17) against the Blue Jays, compared with .065 (2 for 31) for George Bell and .048 (1 for 21) for Bo Jackson.</p>
        <p>Whoever plays for the White Sox, they will face Juan Guzman, a right-hander with a 14-3 record. The Blue Jays will see Jack McDowell, a 22-game winner who struggled against them this season, losing both of his starts with a 5.68 earned run average.</p>
        <p>"He made some bad pitches and our hitters jumped on those pitches," Cito Gaston, the Toronto manager, said of McDowell. "He might come out tomorrow night and not make any of those pitches."</p>
        <p>It remained to be seen what kind of pitches Guzman and the other Toronto pitchers would throw to Thomas. There was speculation that they would not give him anything good to hit, preferring to make the other White Sox hitters beat them. 'A Smart Hitter'</p>
        <p>But Gordon Lakey, the Blue Jays' super scout who scrutinized the White Sox the last several weeks of the season, said no one can pitch around Thomas all the time.</p>
        <p>"I saw Kansas City try to pitch around him," Lakey said. "They were successful early in the game, but late in the game he was up with men on base and they couldn't pitch around him and he beat them."</p>
        <p>To defuse Thomas's bat, Lakey explained, pitchers have to vary the way they pitch him.</p>
        <p>"He's a smart hitter," the scout said, "a great long-ball hitter. He uses the whole field, he's a big-game hitter and a good situation hitter."</p>
        <p>The elbow ailment, Lakey added, would add an unknown factor to the pitchers' confrontations with Thomas.</p>
        <p>"We just don't know what he can do," Lakey said. "We have to see and adjust accordingly. I saw him yesterday and I don't say it was indicative. Our people saw him when he was healthy. You have to adjust to what you see the first few times at bat. You might be able to get away with things you couldn't earlier this year. It's an at-bat to at-bat monitor."</p>
        <p>In 11 games against the Blue Jays this season, Thomas batted .289, hit 4 home runs and drove in 10 runs. Toronto also walked him 9 times in 47 plate appearances. INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>GENE LAMONT was asked about his reputation as a laid-back manager, a trait that has prompted criticism from some quarters. "There are a lot of managers at home today," he said. "I don't know if they're fired up there or what. I'm glad to be here."</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
