<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sex Scandal Threatens House Leader In Virginia</title>
    <meta content="Y11VIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/11/national/11VIRG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1399707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Virginia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilkins, S Vance Jr (Speaker)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Virginia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Virginia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wilkins, S Vance Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DA1E3DF932A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sex Scandal Threatens House Leader In Virginia</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sex Scandal Threatens House Leader in Virginia</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>RICHMOND, Va., June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia House Speaker S Vance Wilkins Jr comes under severe pressure from fellow Republicans to resign leadership post following publication of accusations that he sexually harassed two women and paid one $100,000 for her silence; has denied harassing women but not publicly discussed payment, prompting increasing number of Republicans to criticize him openly and estimate that his days in post are numbered; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Speaker S. Vance Wilkins Jr. was under severe pressure from fellow Republicans today to resign his leadership post after the publication of accusations that he had sexually harassed two women and paid one of them $100,000 for her silence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkins has denied harassing women but has not publicly discussed the payment, prompting an increasing number of Republicans in the House of Delegates to criticize him openly and estimate that his days as leader are numbered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Speaker S. Vance Wilkins Jr. was under severe pressure from fellow Republicans today to resign his leadership post after the publication of accusations that he sexually harassed two women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Speaker S. Vance Wilkins Jr. was under severe pressure from fellow Republicans today to resign his leadership post after the publication of accusations that he had sexually harassed two women and paid one of them $100,000 for her silence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkins has denied harassing women but has not publicly discussed the payment, prompting an increasing number of Republicans in the House of Delegates to criticize him openly and estimate that his days as leader are numbered.</p>
        <p>''I deny the allegations categorically,'' Mr. Wilkins said tonight after a three-hour meeting that anxious Republicans pronounced unsatisfactory and unlikely to turn the tide running against him.</p>
        <p>''He's going to have to come clean,'' said Delegate Vincent F. Callahan Jr., the senior House Republican. ''He just can't say, 'I didn't do it' after paying $100,000 in hush money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Callahan said that the speaker denied the accusations to him but that skepticism was widespread in the Republican caucus.</p>
        <p>The Virginia speakership is one of the nation's most powerful, with Mr. Wilkins in firm control of the agenda and of all committee assignments. Mr. Wilkins was also the architect of his party's 1999 victory in the House, the first time in Virginia's history the Republicans won majority status in the lower house.</p>
        <p>''He accomplished one of the major feats of party-building in the South,'' said Robert D. Holsworth, director of the Center for Public Policy at Virginia Commonwealth University, describing how Mr. Wilkins spent a decade in turning around the Republicans' statehouse fortunes. ''He almost single-handedly created this majority, personally recruiting the lawmakers who are judging him. And now he's squandered it.''</p>
        <p>The speaker's standing tumbled after The Washington Post reported on Friday that Mr. Wilkins paid $100,000 in an out-of-court settlement last year to Jennifer L. Thompson. She is a 26-year-old clerical worker at his former construction company who complained that he groped her and pinned her against office furniture last year, the newspaper said.</p>
        <p>Then, a second woman, Elizabeth P. Massie, a 45-year-old flight attendant active in Republican politics, told a Lynchburg television station, WSET, that at a party last year the speaker began rudely caressing her.</p>
        <p>Asked if that encounter occurred, Mr. Wilkins, who is married and 65, told The Associated Press, ''I have no idea.'' He added, ''I don't remember 'if' or 'what.' I know I was at a party.''</p>
        <p>Privately, Republican lawmakers said Mr. Wilkins told them that he paid the $100,000 to Ms. Thompson and signed a joint confidentiality agreement not as an admission of guilt but to protect the party from notoriety during the 2001 campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkins met with the Republican House caucus here in the Capitol tonight to try to calm the party turmoil. But even before the closed meeting, Republican lawmakers and political analysts were estimating that the speaker, for all his power, would harm his party's chances in the legislative election next year if he decided to remain as leader.</p>
        <p>''We've learned over the years from Bill Clinton on down that when a powerful person chooses to hang on, even when guilty, he can often survive,'' said Larry J. Sabato, director of the Center for Politics at the University of Virginia. ''But he would cost his party a ton of votes.''</p>
        <p>The sex scandal follows a controversy involving the speaker's office in which statehouse Republicans were accused of eavesdropping on conference calls by Democrats who were planning their strategy on legislative redistricting. Speaker Wilkins's chief of staff, Claudia D. Tucker, is under investigation.</p>
        <p>Democrats, outnumbered 65 to 34 in the lower house, have sought to exploit the speaker's problems.</p>
        <p>''Virginians deserve to know whether Republican legislators were aware of such reprehensible behavior when they elected Vance Wilkins as speaker,'' Senator Louise Lucas said in a Democratic news release that featured criticism from the party's female legislators.</p>
        <p>Considering the Democrats' defense of President Clinton during impeachment over his sex scandal, they had better be careful with their criticism of Mr. Wilkins, Professor Sabato warned, but added that the Republicans also had a problem.</p>
        <p>''They viciously attacked Bill Clinton and other Democrats for similar offenses,'' he said, ''and if they let Wilkins stay, they'll add hypocrisy on top of these latest troubles.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Wilkins were to step down, a special session of the General Assembly would be required to name a replacement. Republicans seemed to be preparing for this in admitting that Mr. Wilkins had compromised his ability to lead and besmirched the party's stand on family values.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
