<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now That's a Riddle: A Dancing Sphinx</title>
    <meta content="04SPHI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/04/arts/dance/04SPHI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1330582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dance Theater of Harlem</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tetley, Glen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Dance Theater of Harlem</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Tetley, Glen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1D6113DF937A35753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now That's a Riddle: A Dancing Sphinx</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Riddle of the Dancing Sphinx</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Dance Theater of Harlem's performance of Sphinx, Glen Tetley ballet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dance Theater of Harlem's first production of ''Sphinx,'' a ballet that Glen Tetley created in 1977 for American Ballet Theater, is downright splendid. With a fantastic set (huge wings flanking a platform), a turbulent score and its distilled drama, the work has grown in theatrical impact.</p>
        <p>Ballet Theater no longer performs it, but it is tailor-made for the Dance Theater of Harlem cast: Caroline Rocher gives this sphinx with human desires an astounding sensuality; Ramon Thielen is particularly intense as Anubis, the jackal-headed God of the Dead, and Duncan Cooper is the macho Oedipus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dance Theater of Harlem's first production of "Sphinx," a ballet that Glen Tetley created in 1977 for American Ballet Theater, is downright splendid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dance Theater of Harlem's first production of ''Sphinx,'' a ballet that Glen Tetley created in 1977 for American Ballet Theater, is downright splendid. With a fantastic set (huge wings flanking a platform), a turbulent score and its distilled drama, the work has grown in theatrical impact.</p>
        <p>Ballet Theater no longer performs it, but it is tailor-made for the Dance Theater of Harlem cast: Caroline Rocher gives this sphinx with human desires an astounding sensuality; Ramon Thielen is particularly intense as Anubis, the jackal-headed God of the Dead, and Duncan Cooper is the macho Oedipus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tetley's storytelling is hardly linear, and it has been filtered through his inspiration, Jean Cocteau's 1934 play, ''La Machine Infernale.'' There, in true Cocteau style, the mythical was played out in the realm of the ordinary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tetley's sphinx thus assumes human form. She would normally kill travelers who cannot solve the riddle she asks, but she falls in love with Oedipus. He, for his part, treats their encounter as sex without strings after she reveals the answer to the riddle. Mr. Tetley's Oedipus is supposed to raise several fingers to symbolize his reply to the riddle. This detail seemed missing on Sunday afternoon at City Center. But it was clear that the sphinx, once betrayed, lost her power. Mounting the platform, Ms. Rocher's creature expired grandly in a spiraling fall.</p>
        <p>The fall comes from Martha Graham's idiom, and the ballet has a Grahamesque structure. Anubis is a one-man chorus: when the sphinx prepares to make love to Oedipus and thus risks losing her power, Mr. Thielen's frenzied solo sounds the alarm.</p>
        <p>Yet ''Sphinx'' is not a modern-dance piece, and its use of toework for the ballerina and of ballet bravura for the two men exemplifies the skill with which Mr. Tetley absorbs modern-dance movement into classical technique. Ms. Rocher dances big, with a bold classical shape, and Mr. Cooper's masculine vigor complements her seductiveness.</p>
        <p>The score, conducted by Tania Léon, is Martinu's Double Concerto for Two String Orchestras, Piano and Tympani. The set is by Rouben Ter-Arutunian, and the stylized leotard costumes by Willa Kim.</p>
        <p>Another production of theatrical impact on Sunday's program was ''Firebird,'' which left its audience delirious. John Taras's treatment of Stravinsky's music would look persuasive in any context, and in this case, the blaze of color in Geoffrey Holder's exotic sets transports a Russian-inspired folk tale to a tropical clime.</p>
        <p>Bethania Gomes, small, sharp and dazzling, rightly stressed the birdlike aspects of the title role, while Kip Sturm looked properly entranced by her and his princess, the lissome Rejane Duarte.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
