<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>150th Anniversary: 1851-2001; The Reporter's Reporter</title>
    <meta content="20MOHR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Special Section" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/14/specials/onefifty/20MOHR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Guiding Hands"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halberstam, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mohr, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Luce, Henry III</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DE1F38F937A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>150th Anniversary: 1851-2001; The Reporter's Reporter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Reporter's Reporter</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID HALBERSTAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halberstam, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Halberstam profiles Charles Mohr, a 'reporter's reporter,' who worked for New York Times from 1964 until his death 25 years later; notes that Mohr covered every major story in world during those years, most notably wars in Middle East and in Vietnam; photo (L) (Special section marking New York Times' 150th birthday)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOTHING changed the nature of print journalism quite like the force of television. In the 1960's and 70's, the encyclopedic, omniscient style that had defined The Times was no longer enough. There had to be room for a subtler style of reporting, one that greatly enhanced the influence and judgment of the reporter on the ground. Reporters had to be able to go places that television's bulky cameras couldn't go, and produce stories that television, with its inherent limits of time and space, could not match.</p>
        <p>If any one reporter's career reflected the changes in these two very different eras, it was that of Charles Mohr of Loup City, Neb., who worked for the paper from January 1964 until his death 25 years later. In those years, he covered every major story in the world -- most notably wars in the Middle East and in Vietnam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 60's and 70's, Charles Mohr covered every major story in the world  most notably wars in the Middle East and in Vietnam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOTHING changed the nature of print journalism quite like the force of television. In the 1960's and 70's, the encyclopedic, omniscient style that had defined The Times was no longer enough. There had to be room for a subtler style of reporting, one that greatly enhanced the influence and judgment of the reporter on the ground. Reporters had to be able to go places that television's bulky cameras couldn't go, and produce stories that television, with its inherent limits of time and space, could not match.</p>
        <p>If any one reporter's career reflected the changes in these two very different eras, it was that of Charles Mohr of Loup City, Neb., who worked for the paper from January 1964 until his death 25 years later. In those years, he covered every major story in the world -- most notably wars in the Middle East and in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>We met in Saigon in 1963 when I was working for The Times and he for Time magazine. I came to think he was the best all-around reporter of my generation. No one could cover such a wide range of stories with such skill, and no reporter had such an ability -- in the field, under difficult circumstances -- to create an instantaneous connection with his subjects and to inspire such remarkable trust. He was, his colleague Tom Wicker wrote at his death, ''the outstanding combat reporter of the war -- militarily knowledgeable, unafraid to reach his own conclusions, unflinching under fire, filing stories of sensitivity and compassion that matched their brilliance.''</p>
        <p>Mohr got his start at Time. He was a favorite of Henry Luce, the magazine's publisher, who called him ''a reporter's reporter.'' But in Vietnam, Mohr's relationship with Time quickly unraveled. His integrity put him in direct conflict with his editors in New York, who in those days loved the war even more than senior officials in the Pentagon did. In the fall of 1963, Mohr filed an article that began, ''The war in Vietnam is being lost.'' His editors reversed the thrust of the piece, making it seem that the war was being won. Mohr resigned and promptly went to The Times. ''Charles Mohr of The New York Times,'' his wife, Norma, said when he joined the paper. ''Sounds good, doesn't it?''</p>
        <p>Had he come a generation earlier, Charley Mohr might not have fitted in. The Times in the 50's still practiced the journalism of Adolph Ochs era -- bland and nonjudgmental, and tilted, some of the better reporters believed, toward official versions of events. The paper's immense influence derived from a kind of encyclopedic journalism. In any big story it always had the ability to flood the scene with more reporters than anyone else.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1960's, however, that sort of reporting was becoming vulnerable. The pace of life had sped up. Other sources of information arrived to deliver news faster -- and with more drama. Many Times reporters, especially younger ones, found the paper's reporting too stiff and bland, bearing the stamp of far too much officialese.</p>
        <p>Thus there was an escalating conflict between the paper's best reporters, who wanted to extend their mandate on a story, and its editors, who saw themselves as the keepers of the Ochs tradition. Those who tried to write well, it was said, did so at their own risk. The battles were particularly sharp between New York and Washington, where the bureau chief, Scotty Reston, had consciously set out to collect a generation of younger reporters, emphasizing their literary abilities as much as their journalistic  ones -- Russell Baker, Max Frankel, Tom Wicker and Anthony Lewis, among others.</p>
        <p>The battle was so intense that in 1961, when Orvil Dryfoos made his first trip to the bureau as publisher, he was stunned by the alienation he found. Dryfoos turned to Baker, The Times's leading stylist and perhaps the most fair-minded person in the bureau. ''Russell, is it really that bad?'' he asked. ''Orvil,'' Baker answered, ''some days when you get up and look at what they've done to your copy, you just don't want to go to work.''</p>
        <p>By the time Mohr arrived, the paper was changing.  Reporters were getting broader authority to construct their stories and to explain the underlying meaning of events. It was a paper designed for Charley Mohr. Within a year, he was back in Saigon as chief of an unusually distinguished bureau (with Neil Sheehan and Johnny Apple), writing stories that always had something no one else had -- a wonderful quotation from an interview, a glistening insight, an exceptional human touch.</p>
        <p>Dove? Hawk? Neither</p>
        <p>He was aware that he was a beneficiary of the paper's changes. Once during his Saigon years he had a conversation with Jack Laurence, then of CBS, about whether to keep old notebooks. Laurence had saved his, while Mohr hadn't. For a moment Mohr seemed to regret his decision. Then he reconsidered. ''You know,'' he said, ''when you're working on a good story, so much of it gets in the paper that your notes get preserved that way.'' It was the highest compliment a reporter could pay his paper.</p>
        <p>As a sign of how good Mohr was, there was always a debate about his sympathies -- was he a covert war lover, or was he a secret dove? He was neither. He was an honorable and straightforward man. On his own, he was probably somewhat conservative -- the sons of dentists from small towns in Nebraska are rarely flaming liberals. But he was always open-minded.</p>
        <p>Neil Sheehan thought he got on so well with the best combat officers because he was so much like them -- he was from a small town, had hunted and fished as a boy and had hungered to get out and find adventure. ''If Charley had not been a great journalist he might have been a great combat officer,'' Sheehan said. ''I think the men he covered recognized that in him immediately.''</p>
        <p>Sheehan remembered a moment in the fall of 1965 when Mohr rushed to Plei Me in the Central Highlands to visit a Special Forces team commanded by Maj. Charles Beckwith that had been under assault from a North Vietnamese regiment for several days. Reporters drew lots to get on a helicopter loaded with ammunition and medical supplies, and Mohr won. As the copter landed under heavy fire, Mohr got out and immediately started loading wounded G.I.'s into it. Beckwith, who was also helping, first took him for a medic. Then he realized it was Mohr. ''I need you like I need a case of the clap!'' he shouted. ''Get the hell out of here. Now.''</p>
        <p>''Can't,'' Mohr said. ''There's no room on the chopper. It's filled with the wounded.'' He stayed on. The camp was not overrun. And Mohr, as Sheehan noted, almost immediately bonded with Beckwith, who became one of the war's most celebrated combat officers.</p>
        <p>Mohr always understood who the real heroes of the war were. ''No sensible reporter deludes himself that he is being heroic in this war,'' he once wrote. ''The heroics are reserved for the troops who do not enjoy the supreme privilege that any reporter can exercise at any time. That is the chance to say, 'I'd love to stay, fellas, but I've got to get back to Saigon to file.' ''</p>
        <p>A President's 'Mohr Problem'</p>
        <p>If military men admired Mohr, politicians were puzzled by him. They searched for his politics, and could not quite find them. Sometimes they sought his friendship, and received instead his irreverence and toughness of mind. In 1976, when Jimmy Carter found himself under increasing scrutiny on his march to the presidential nomination, he suggested through his aide Jody Powell that perhaps he and the reporters who covered him could sit down and find out how they might improve relations.</p>
        <p>Carter started the meeting by saying he wanted to find a way to get on better. Mohr's hand went up immediately -- after all, if a likely presidential nominee felt he had a problem with media coverage, that was news. ''This meeting is on the record, right, Governor?'' he asked. The meeting stayed on the record, and Carter later complained that he had a ''Charley Mohr problem.''</p>
        <p>Mohr liked to say that he hoped to go down in history as the White House correspondent who asked questions that produced classic answers from two different presidents. As a reporter for Time, he famously asked President Dwight D. Eisenhower to enumerate any decisions that Vice President Richard M. Nixon, then running for president, had made or helped with during their two terms in office. Eisenhower, ill prepared for the question, answered that if you gave him a week he might be able to think of one. It was a throwaway line that dogged Nixon for the rest of the campaign.</p>
        <p>The second question came in an interview with President Lyndon B. Johnson. To help Times colleagues who were preparing a special story on education, Mohr asked the president a general question on the topic. Johnson's reaction was immediate and emphatic: ''Here you have a chance to ask a question of the president of the United States and the leader of the entire free world and you ask a'' -- here the president used what The Times liked to call a barnyard epithet -- ''question like that.''</p>
        <p>Generally journalism is considered a young person's business. That was not true of Mohr. He covered dangerous, difficult stories for more than three decades, and he never tired of it. But in the 1980's, his body began to break down. He suffered from diabetes and then had a heart bypass operation. ''At the end he had a young man's mind in an old person's body,'' his friend Johnny Apple noted. In 1989, on his 60th birthday, Charley Mohr died of a heart attack. He was much loved and respected by his peers; more than that, he was a reflection of the kind of great reporter The Times was now hiring.</p>
        <p>Guiding Hands</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
