<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cause Is Sought In Fatal Crash Of Airplane On Casino Trip</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="683742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SIKORSKY MEMORIAL AIRPORT (STRATFORD, CONN)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">STRATFORD (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ACTION AIR CHARTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JUDSON, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DA1430F93AA15757C0A962958260" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cause Is Sought In Fatal Crash Of Airplane On Casino Trip</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JUDSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JUDSON, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>STRATFORD, Conn., April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Emergency workers at Sikorsky Memorial Airport stood outside their firehouse Wednesday night and watched a small charter plane descend out of thick fog, speed by and disappear again before crashing into an embankment at the end of the runway and bursting into flames. Tonight, Federal officials said they did not yet know whether fog played a role in the crash, which killed eight people and critically injured a ninth.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board found skid marks only 545 feet from the end of the 4,677-foot runway, suggesting that the plane nearly overshot the airport in attempting a landing. But readings from the control panel in the burned-out cockpit, fragments of the pilot's records and witnesses' accounts of shifting weather conditions did not add up to an explanation, they said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Emergency workers at Sikorsky Memorial Airport stood outside their firehouse Wednesday night and watched a small charter plane descend out of thick fog, speed by and disappear again before crashing into an embankment at the end of the runway and bursting into flames. Tonight, Federal officials said they did not yet know whether fog played a role in the crash, which killed eight people and critically injured a ninth.</p>
        <p>Investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board found skid marks only 545 feet from the end of the 4,677-foot runway, suggesting that the plane nearly overshot the airport in attempting a landing. But readings from the control panel in the burned-out cockpit, fragments of the pilot's records and witnesses' accounts of shifting weather conditions did not add up to an explanation, they said.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they did not know whether the pilot of the charter plane, carrying home Connecticut gamblers who had spent the day on a trip to Atlantic City, was trying to land by sight or with the aid of instruments.  Returning From Atlantic City</p>
        <p>They also said they did not know whether the pilot had overshot the runway and slammed into the embankment or had tried to bring his craft up for a second attempt before it crashed into a solid steel wall atop the embankment, which was erected just months ago to protect a road behind it from the prop wash of planes taking off.</p>
        <p>The plane, a Piper Chieftain owned by Action Air Charter of Groton, was returning from Atlantic City, where it had taken passengers for a day of gambling. The authorities today released the names of only two of the people aboard the plane. The survivor was Paul Hagopian, 37, of the Mystic, Conn., area, said officials at Bridgeport Hospital, where he was being treated for severe burns. Authorities said he was a dispatcher for Action Air and had been riding in the copilot's seat. One of the victims, who died shortly before 8 A.M. today at Bridgeport Hospital, was identified as Joseph Williams, 41, of New Haven.</p>
        <p>Gerald Grover, the fire chief of Bridgeport, which owns the airport, said that the families of the people listed as passengers had been notified, but that identities of the burned victims were being double-checked to make certain that no unlisted passengers had boarded for the return trip. He said all were from Connecticut, including three from Bridgeport. The plane had begun the day by picking up people at Brainard Airport in Hartford before stopping at Sikorsky on the way to Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagopian may have survived because he was thrown from the plane, beyond the fence, officials said. Of the five men and three women found in the plane, seven died almost instantly.</p>
        <p>"The cabin in the front was fully incinerated," Chief Grover said. "You couldn't be in the plane and not be a fatality."</p>
        <p>The fire was so intense that everyone died even though the airport's emergency crew was spraying water and foam on the flames within 60 seconds of the crash and had extinguished them 30 to 60 seconds later, said the airport manager, John Ricci.</p>
        <p>"They were listening to the chatter on the radio frequency and paid particular attention to this plane coming in because of the weather," Mr. Ricci said of the emergency crew, Kurt Sendlein and George Lainis. "I was told they couldn't see 100 feet in the fog."</p>
        <p>The crashed occurred a few minutes before 11 P.M., nearly an hour after the Sikorsky control tower closed for the night. Heavy ground fog rising from the salt marshes around the airport may have affected the pilot, Mr. Ricci said, who may have been trying to abort the landing and rise for a second try when the plane hit the fence. No Recording Device</p>
        <p>Officials said the plane speeded past the emergency crew members a few hundred yards from the end of the 4,677-foot runway. The top of the fence stands 10 to 12 feet above the runway, which stops just a few feet from the embankment leading to the lower end of South Main Street in Stratford, where the Housatonic River enters Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>National Transportation Safety Board investigators told The Associated Press that there was no device on the plane to record what happened before it went down.</p>
        <p>"This type of aircraft is 20 years old," one investigator, Jim Hall, said.  "This plane did not have a black box or a cockpit voice recorder or flight data recorder. Obviously, had that been the case, it would make our investigation much easier."</p>
        <p>While the weather may have been a factor in the crash, aviation officials said there was nothing unusual about planes landing at small commuter and corporate airports like Sikorsky after the control tower had closed for the night.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of the 18,000 airports in the United States do not even have control towers, said Anthony Willett, a Federal Aviation Administration spokesman in Boston. "It's all a very, very safe, articulated procedure. The reason we're discussing this is because what occurred is so uncommon."</p>
        <p>The general manager of Action Air Charters, Dennis Piscitello, would not comment today except to confirm that his company owned the Piper Chieftain, a twin-engine turboprop. Mr. Ricci said Action Air made frequent stops at Sikorsky on its charter runs to and from Atlantic City. The company also flies out of Brainard and MacArthur Airport on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Gamblers flying to Atlantic City casinos aboard charter flights made up 40 percent to 45 percent of the 885,000 travelers at Atlantic City International Airport in 1993, and Connecticut provides a large share of those, said the airport's manager, Kevin Willis.</p>
        <p>The Action Air plane that crashed was chartered by Merv Griffin's Resorts Hotel Casino, said Carmen Gonzalez, a spokeswoman for the casino, and the victims included the casino's junket representative in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>Representatives bring business to casinos by arranging package trips that offer gamblers reduced room rates, free dinners and other complimentary items. Ms. Gonzalez said Resorts arranges about 50 junkets by air travel each month, using several carriers. 'Pilot's Responsibility'</p>
        <p>Kenneth Roach, a veteran flier and the manager of the F.A.A.'s Flight Standards Office in Windsor Locks, said pilots of such flights have several ways to check on the weather, starting with the regional weather reports that are available before they take off. But, he said, "It's always the pilot's responsibility."</p>
        <p>En route, Mr. Roach said, pilots can check conditions with a flight service station. When visibility is so poor that Federal Aviation Administration rules for a visual landing cannot be met, pilots can ask for the nearest airport with visibility.</p>
        <p>A pilot planning to land visually, following an airport's lights, should not be surprised by fog as he begins to land, Mr. Roach said, but if he is, the procedure again is clear. The pilot would have to pull up for a second approach and ask for clearance from the nearest control tower to land using instruments.</p>
        <p>At Sikorsky, Mr. Ricci said, decision time comes at an altitude of 257 feet, three-fourths of a mile from the runway. Officials estimated that the Piper Chieftain was traveling 100 miles an hour when it struck the embankment and fence.</p>
        <p>Cloud conditions were changing rapidly Wednesday night after thunderstorms moved across Fairfield County. While visibility was near zero at the time of the crash, an hour or two later the moon was shining brightly through patchy clouds. But the marshes that surround this part of Stratford, known as Lordship, are known for heavy ground fog.</p>
        <p>"When it's foggy down here, you can't see a thing," said Jennifer Bonne, who was working at her parents' South Main Street bar, the Windsock Inn, when the crash occurred nearby. "And that's the way it was last night."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
