<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clothes That Make the Star, the Cast and the Show They're On</title>
    <meta content="29WINE0AE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="COVER STORY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="898295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DB1430F93AA15751C1A960958260" item-length="1391" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clothes That Make the Star, the Cast and the Show They're On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on how clothes set the style for a television series; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS he maneuvers his 1971 yellow Barracuda through the hilly streets of San Francisco, Don Johnson exudes a kind of don't-mess-with-me cool that has been as carefully conceived as the color of his car, which he admits had to be repainted several times until just the right shade was achieved. In the CBS police detective drama ''Nash Bridges,'' he said he felt it was important to come up with the right look, as he did for ''Miami Vice'' in the 1980's. So Mr. Johnson, who is also the show's executive producer, and Richard van Ernst, a San Francisco costume designer, created a uniform for Nash: he wears a T-shirt under a vest (one of them always brightly colored), khaki pants or bluejeans, a blazer (often with an unusual detail like  plaid shoulders) and, of course, his signature wire-rimmed sunglasses.</p>
        <p>''I noticed in San Francisco everyone wears layers because the weather's so unpredictable,'' Mr. Johnson said recently. ''It's a functional look. But more importantly, I wanted the actors to wear a certain amount of color so they popped against the gray-and-beige background of the city.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS he maneuvers his 1971 yellow Barracuda through the hilly streets of San Francisco, Don Johnson exudes a kind of don't-mess-with-me cool that has been as carefully conceived as the color of his car, which he admits had to be repainted several times until just the right shade was achieved. In the CBS police detective drama ''Nash Bridges,'' he said he felt it was important to come up with the right look, as he did for ''Miami Vice'' in the 1980's. So Mr. Johnson, who is also the show's executive producer, and Richard van Ernst, a San Francisco costume designer, created a uniform for Nash: he wears a T-shirt under a vest (one of them always brightly colored), khaki pants or bluejeans, a blazer (often with an unusual detail like  plaid shoulders) and, of course, his signature wire-rimmed sunglasses.</p>
        <p>''I noticed in San Francisco everyone wears layers because the weather's so unpredictable,'' Mr. Johnson said recently. ''It's a functional look. But more importantly, I wanted the actors to wear a certain amount of color so they popped against the gray-and-beige background of the city.''</p>
        <p>Executive producers like Mr. Johnson as well as costume designers on many of today's television series have begun to sound like architects when explaining the wardrobes they choose for a show: like the silhouette of a new building, clothes, they say, must be sensitive to the place. Series that are set on the West Coast tend to have far more colorful wardrobes, reflecting the way people dress in cities like Los Angeles and San Francisco. Those on the East Coast tend to echo fashion trends in places like New York, where black is everyone's favorite color and women these days are seen wearing skinny-legged pants and men are in Gap-style casual classics.</p>
        <p>Mr. von Ernst said his choice of clothes reflected the show's overall design concept: deconstructivism, or a departure from original classic forms and shapes. He prefers asymmetry,  clothes that are just a bit offbeat, like jackets with slanted pockets and unusual, often strong colors. ''I take elements from different periods of American 20th-century fashions from the late 20's through the 50's and then mix them with elements that are common in clothes today,'' he said.</p>
        <p>All of Mr. Johnson's jackets are custom-made by a tailor in Los Angeles. Many of the vests are specially made too, others are from vintage clothing stores and some are bought off-the-rack. ''I do something with color in every episode,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The cast of ''Clueless,'' another series set on the West Coast, never wears black, brown or gray. Mona May, the costume designer who created the clothes for the movie as well as for the ABC series, said she had tried to bring  back sweet dressing for teen-agers. ''Away with grunge!'' Ms. May proclaimed. ''This show is not about fashion but about style, about taking what's out there and making the girls young and pretty.'' Because the story line calls for teen-age schoolgirls who, by definition, are preoccupied with clothes, the parade of outfits is as important as the characters themselves. But since Ms. May has about 60 changes to worry about each week, she does not have time to have everything specially designed. Instead, she studies European fashion magazines and constantly shops showrooms, researching what's hip and new. This results in a mix of clothes from everywhere. There are outfits from high-end designers like Donna Karan, Gianni Versace and Dolce &amp; Gabbana, and ones from little-known manufacturers in the United States and abroad.</p>
        <p>''Everything is custom fit, even a $12.99 shirt,'' she said. ''and I like to show things before they hit the stores.'' But she is careful to stay away from making the girls to obvious. ''No cleaverage, no high heels, nothing too tight,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Accessories are as important as the clothes themselves, with matching hats, handbags and coats. And in scenes where there are many teen-agers, everyone is coordinated with one another. ''I rarely repeat an outfit,'' Ms. May said. ''And most fo the clothes are in vibrant shades: pinks, yellows and lime greens.'' On the question of whether the show is making an effort to set fashion trends, Ms. May said definitely not. ''If you see the show five years from now I think it will still look pretty and stylish, not dated.''</p>
        <p>The costume designers who have created the hip look for the cast of ''Moesha'' like the idea of setting tends. ''That's No. 1 for us,'' said Yolanda Braddy, the costume designer for this UPN series about a girl growing up in the Leimert Park section of Los Angeles. ''We want to be the first out there with fashion, style and color.''</p>
        <p>Susan Moses, who does the singer and actress Brandy Norwood's dressing for her part as Moesha Mitchell as well as for her personal appearances, describes herself as a constant shopper. ''I get clothes everywhere, from designers like Moda, Gaultier, Moschino and Todd Oldham to Esprit and Gues, and then I mix it all up.'' Chocolate brown and black are Moesha's favorite colors, and Ms. Moses says she likes to pair them with hot colors like a brigth orange velour sweater or hot green boots. ''We try to keep it bright; the look is everything from Afro-eccentric to urban wear,'' she said. The character of Q. Moesha's boyfriend, played by Fredro Starr, is the show's one East Coast character; Ms. Braddy has dressed him in camouflage, but not your typical green camouflage. Q ears a gray and blue combination with a matching bandana tied in different ways. ''Whenever I go to New York I'm always watching the kids on the streets,'' said Ms. Braddy. ''I take a Polaroid so I can remember what I've seen.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Braddy said viewers notice how everyon e on the show dresses. Every week there are calls and mail asking where to get some of the clothes, she added.</p>
        <p>Debra McGuire, the costume designer for ''Friends,'' says that NBC show is also besieged by viewers. ''They want to know where to get the socks and V-neck T-shirts; often they ask for the oddest things,'' said Ms. McGuire. Since the show is set in New York but filmed in Los Angeles, Ms. McGuire always has to tone things down. ''I design about 30 percent of the girls' wardrobes myself. The rest comes from all over, thrift shops and some designers. Each character has her own style and personality. Phoebe, because of her eccentric nature, tends to wear more color and jewelry. Color is played down because the sets are so vibrant. Monica's apartment has so many things in it. I want the characters to look soft.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McGuire said she also tried to make sure the characters' clothes reflected what is happening in their lives. ''When they were unemployed they dressed one way; but now, for instance, Monica and Rachel are getting proper jobs,'' she said. ''With Jennifer working in a department store, I wanted to create a look that's not out there. She's a working girl, but with a sense of humor, to show off her body without being obnoxious.''</p>
        <p>''I've seen these characters evolve and change and that's been a big factor in the way they dress,'' she said. ''I'm more motivated by the script than by fashion. And by the fact that the show is very much about New York. Fortunately, I'm from New York, so I know what the look is.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
