<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zedillo Tells Mexico Painful Economic Policies Are Farsighted</title>
    <meta content="Y02MEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DA123FF931A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zedillo Tells Mexico Painful Economic Policies Are Farsighted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Ernesto Zedillo makes his first major statement about effects of world financial crisis on Mexico; he acknowledges that plunging oil prices had forced painful budget cuts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Ernesto Zedillo tonight made his first major statement about the effects of the world financial crisis on Mexico. Mr. Zedillo acknowledged that plunging oil prices had forced painful budget cuts and urging Mexicans to be patient and work hard to help the country continue to grow.</p>
        <p>''I must be the first to warn that the circumstances in which our economy will operate in the near future will be difficult,'' Mr. Zedillo said in his annual state of the union address. But Mexico can expect to average 4 percent growth for the two years that remain in his six-year term, he said, ''as long as we keep our spirits high and work hard.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Ernesto Zedillo tonight made his first major statement about the effects of the world financial crisis on Mexico. Mr. Zedillo acknowledged that plunging oil prices had forced painful budget cuts and urging Mexicans to be patient and work hard to help the country continue to grow.</p>
        <p>''I must be the first to warn that the circumstances in which our economy will operate in the near future will be difficult,'' Mr. Zedillo said in his annual state of the union address. But Mexico can expect to average 4 percent growth for the two years that remain in his six-year term, he said, ''as long as we keep our spirits high and work hard.''</p>
        <p>In an hourlong speech that defended his Government's efforts to solve everything from surging crime to illiteracy, Mr. Zedillo devoted the most time to explaining his often-painful economic policies, arguing that they had so far helped Mexico to bend, but not break, with the global financial pressures.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary recent losses in the Mexican financial markets after  Russia's de facto devaluation of the ruble surrounded Mr. Zedillo's report to Congress with an air of crisis.</p>
        <p>Politicians and analysts of all stripes delivered their own assorted report cards on the President's performance in his four years in office.</p>
        <p>''A quick look at the economic indicators reveal that our country is sustaining itself on the pillars of deceit and the people's poverty,'' Senator Gabriel Jimenez Remus of the opposition National Action Party told the Congress hours before Mr. Zedillo's address. ''Falling per capita income, rising inflation, the devaluation of our currency, ever rising unemployment -- all are shoving our country toward the third world.''</p>
        <p>''Fifth Year Begins in Financial Crisis'' was the headline today in the newspaper Reforma. The paper featured a poll that showed that 51 percent of Mexicans approved Mr. Zedillo's Presidency, down from 60 percent in December.</p>
        <p>''Zedillo's approval ratings have begun to decline,'' the newspaper reported, ''and the President's fall has been caused by the poor pace of the economy.''</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Zedillo is more popular than the opposition Mayor of Mexico City, Cuauhtemoc Cardenas, and about half the 31 state governors.</p>
        <p>The 1994 peso devaluation, during Mr. Zedillo's first month in office, provoked a worldwide financial crisis and plunged Mexico into recession. But the tight-money policies and fiscal discipline that he imposed  after that brought the broad economic indicators back to healthy growth in two years.</p>
        <p>The new economic turbulence, originating in Asia, has been washing over Mexico since July, when plunging world oil prices forced Mr. Zedillo to preside over the third severe budget cut this year. Soon the peso, which opened the year worth 12.4 American cents, began to slide. At the close of trading on Monday the peso was worth 10.03 cents.</p>
        <p>Interest rates have climbed, to 38 percent in the secondary markets.</p>
        <p>Mexican markets were closed today for a national holiday, the Day of the Presidential Report.</p>
        <p>''People are saying that the President is weakened,'' Sergio Sarmiento, news director of the TV Azteca network, wrote in a newspaper column. ''They say, with a certain degree of truth, that the international financial crisis is eroding the only point about which Zedillo could claim success, his handling of the macroeconomy.</p>
        <p>''Everything else seems to be in disaster. But this isn't the first time Mr. Zedillo has been portrayed erroneously as defeated.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
