<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Nightmare for Most Shareholders, but a Dream Come True for Short-Sellers</title>
    <meta content="02SHOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1043412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKET TURMOIL: HAPPY BEARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Short Selling</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abelson, Reed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3D8123FF931A3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Nightmare for Most Shareholders, but a Dream Come True for Short-Sellers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REED ABELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abelson, Reed</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>While many investors lost in August 31 stock market selloff, when Dow Jones industrial average tumbled 512 points, those who stayed on sidelines with cash over past few weeks or made astute bets in Treasury market racked up gains; those who profited are most likely short sellers, who borrow shares that they later sell and hope to replace with cheaper issues as stock prices decline (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not everyone is lamenting the stock market's steep selloff. While many investors are still licking their wounds, even after yesterday's rally,  some are celebrating. They may have stayed on the sidelines with cash, for example, immune to the damage in the last few weeks, or made astute bets in the Treasury market and racked up some gains.</p>
        <p>Some of those with the widest grins are most likely those people who bet on a market downturn, selling stocks short by borrowing shares that they sell and hope to replace with cheaper shares as stock prices decline. The short-sellers are the ultimate bears, cheering any decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not everyone is lamenting the stock market's steep selloff. While many investors are still licking their wounds, even after yesterday's rally,  some are celebrating. They may have stayed on the sidelines with cash, for example, immune to the damage in the last few weeks, or made astute bets in the Treasury market and racked up some gains.</p>
        <p>Some of those with the widest grins are most likely those people who bet on a market downturn, selling stocks short by borrowing shares that they sell and hope to replace with cheaper shares as stock prices decline. The short-sellers are the ultimate bears, cheering any decline.</p>
        <p>''We're making money in quite a few places,'' said David W. Tice, the manager of the Prudent Bear Fund, a mutual fund that specializes in shorting stocks. Prudent Bear posted a gain of about 30 percent in August. Among the areas that Mr. Tice has found most profitable for short sales are technology and banking stocks.</p>
        <p>Most short-sellers seem to be making out handsomely. According to Michael R. Long, the principal of Rockbridge Research, a Charlotte, N.C., firm that specializes in analyzing short-selling trends, the short- sellers he follows are up about 25 to 30 percent so far this year.</p>
        <p>These investors ''have done phenomenally well, based on the current they are swimming in,'' said Mr. Long, who estimates short-sellers as a group had an average return of about 12 percent last year, even though the market was surging.</p>
        <p>Even if their victory is short-lived and stocks resume their climb, short-sellers say the drop demonstrates that their strategy offers some protection to investors.</p>
        <p>The short-sellers have had no trouble finding opportunities in recent weeks. And Mr. Tice says the market could drop much further because global deflationary forces will severely depress the earnings of American companies.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, James S. Chanos, a longtime short-seller and  president of Kynikos Associates, a money management firm, is agnostic on the outlook for the market. While the United States seems to be enjoying a strong economy, which would be positive for stocks, investors could refuse to come to the stock market's rescue and the country could slide into a recession. If that happens, ''all bets are off,'' he said. ''The downside is enormous.''</p>
        <p>THE MARKET TURMOIL: HAPPY BEARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
