<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Remembering Hepburn, Floppy Pants and All</title>
    <meta content="02ROSS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/02/opinion/02ROSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1501505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Lillian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hepburn, Katharine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tracy, Spencer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hepburn, Katharine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tracy, Spencer</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Ross, Lillian</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D8123AF931A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Remembering Hepburn, Floppy Pants and All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Remembering Hepburn, Floppy Pants and All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lillian Ross</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ross, Lillian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lillian Ross Op-Ed tribute to Katharine Hepburn on her death at age 96; lauds way she handled her long-time affair with Spencer Tracy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Katharine Hepburn, who died on Sunday at the age of 96, had an oddly subtle influence on women, one that has been felt, perhaps most keenly by moviegoers, well into the present day. It was widely known that she had a 27-year-long personal life with Spencer Tracy, outside of a formal marriage. Having grown up watching the films they made together, I -- along with scores of other women -- found them to be a romantic and appealing couple, on screen and off. The New York Times, in its obituary, quoted her as saying in her television biography: ''I have no fear of death. . . . It's how you live that really counts.''</p>
        <p>To me, how she lived was pretty classy, and it should put all the petty, catty, would-be diminishers around us in their place. Miss Hepburn was morally instructive. I never met her, but it was heartening to see her in movies and the theater, and on the streets of New York. She seemed to be speaking directly to me by her example.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her affectations notwithstanding, Katharine Hepburn had a kind of pure Puritan strengthsure of herself, sure of her life, sure of her love.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Katharine Hepburn, who died on Sunday at the age of 96, had an oddly subtle influence on women, one that has been felt, perhaps most keenly by moviegoers, well into the present day. It was widely known that she had a 27-year-long personal life with Spencer Tracy, outside of a formal marriage. Having grown up watching the films they made together, I -- along with scores of other women -- found them to be a romantic and appealing couple, on screen and off. The New York Times, in its obituary, quoted her as saying in her television biography: ''I have no fear of death. . . . It's how you live that really counts.''</p>
        <p>To me, how she lived was pretty classy, and it should put all the petty, catty, would-be diminishers around us in their place. Miss Hepburn was morally instructive. I never met her, but it was heartening to see her in movies and the theater, and on the streets of New York. She seemed to be speaking directly to me by her example.</p>
        <p>Her affectation of wearing so many floppy pants suits may have been occasionally disquieting, and not everybody responded patiently to that forceful New England Brahmin accent. My own report card registered an unqualified A++ for her, with Humphrey Bogart, in ''The African Queen,'' as well as automatic A's for her in ''Woman of the Year,'' ''State of the Union,'' ''Adam's Rib,'' ''Pat and Mike'' and even ''Guess Who's Coming to Dinner?'' -- as well as everything else she did with Tracy. It was simply fun watching the two of them together.</p>
        <p>There was an extra perk one always got with Miss Hepburn, too, whether it was watching her go shoulder to shoulder with John Wayne, Peter O'Toole, Henry Fonda or Warren Beatty. In her presence, even behind the fancy accent, she had a kind of true Puritan strength. She emanated courage, decency, generosity and independence. She demonstrated all of these in how she lived, and in how she loved, in her life with Tracy.</p>
        <p>In her book ''Me,'' she revealed how, at the age of 33, she discovered what ''I love you'' ''really means.'' She called her life with Tracy ''absolute bliss.'' ''I loved Spencer Tracy,'' she wrote. ''He and his interests and his demands came first. . . . I really liked him -- deep down -- and I wanted him to be happy.'' The night he died, in 1967, she called his family, and his wife, Louise, came over. ''She was in a peculiar spot,'' Miss Hepburn wrote. ''She could never bear to admit failure. Now he was dead. And he would never come back. She had dreamed -- hoped -- imagined that he would. . . . She just could not settle for the fact that her marriage had been a failure.'' Miss Hepburn also addressed Tracy in the book: ''You were still married to Louise. . . . You couldn't leave her if she didn't want to be left.''</p>
        <p>For years before Miss Hepburn wrote her book, she gave print and television interviews. Invariably, she would be asked about Tracy. To my knowledge, she never whined or protested about her life with him. It seems clear now that she tried to protect him from, among other things, being torn apart by his dilemma.</p>
        <p>I remember watching a couple of Miss Hepburn's television interviews years back. In one, the interviewer tried to imply that she was trying to take the place of Tracy's wife. ''Oh, no!'' she replied, indignantly. ''Mrs. Tracy is his wife, and I would never try to do that. I have great respect for Mrs. Tracy.''</p>
        <p>The way she responded, to give Mrs. Tracy what she asked for, left Miss Hepburn's mark on me forever. She was sure of herself, sure of her life, sure of her love. Because she lived that way -- with pure, Brahmin generosity -- it counted.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Lillian Ross, a staff member at The New Yorker, is author, most recently, of ''Here but Not Here'' and ''Reporting Back: Notes on Journalism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lillian Ross, a staff member at The New Yorker, is author, most recently, of ''Here but Not Here'' and ''Reporting Back: Notes on Journalism.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
