<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neglected Verdi Opera Is Heard Again in Paris</title>
    <meta content="02VERD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/02/arts/music/02VERD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1501477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paris National Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verdi, Giuseppe (1813-1901)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conlon, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Les Vespres Siciliennes (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Paris National Opera</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DC123AF931A35754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neglected Verdi Opera Is Heard Again in Paris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Neglected Verdi Opera Is Heard Again in Paris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on revival of long-neglected Verdi opera Les Vespres Siciliennes by Paris National Opera; work of music director James Conlon in reviving opera in original French version described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly 150 years after its premiere, a long-neglected opera by Verdi, ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes,'' has finally been revived in its original French version with nine performances by the Paris National Opera through July 15.</p>
        <p>The revival comes thanks to James Conlon, music director of the Paris Opera, who at age 23 first heard its music while attending James Levine's recording of ''I Vespri Siciliani'' -- an Italian-language version -- in London in 1973. Years later, having studied the original French-language version of Verdi's ''Don Carlos'' (the better known Italian version is called ''Don Carlo''), Mr. Conlon became intrigued by ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes.'' Last month at the Bastille Opera he conducted it for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly 150 years after its premiere, "Les Vêpres Siciliennes" has finally been revived in its original French version by the Paris National Opera.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly 150 years after its premiere, a long-neglected opera by Verdi, ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes,'' has finally been revived in its original French version with nine performances by the Paris National Opera through July 15.</p>
        <p>The revival comes thanks to James Conlon, music director of the Paris Opera, who at age 23 first heard its music while attending James Levine's recording of ''I Vespri Siciliani'' -- an Italian-language version -- in London in 1973. Years later, having studied the original French-language version of Verdi's ''Don Carlos'' (the better known Italian version is called ''Don Carlo''), Mr. Conlon became intrigued by ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes.'' Last month at the Bastille Opera he conducted it for the first time.</p>
        <p>Describing it as ''an opera of unique beauty,'' Mr. Conlon argued in a program note that it was important for it to reach a wider audience. And he added, ''Above all, it is important that it be presented in French so that in the future it can awaken the same interest as 'Don Carlos.' ''</p>
        <p>Still, there are good reasons why this opera barely features in the Verdi canon. The composer's collaborator on the work was Eugène Scribe, an immensely popular dramatist as well as a successful librettist. When Verdi was contracted to write his first major work for the Paris Opera in 1852, Scribe seemed like a natural partner. But it was not a happy association. Scribe borrowed from a libretto that he and Charles Duveyrier had written in 1839 for Donizetti's ''Duc d'Albe'' and moved it from 16th-century Flanders to 13th-century Sicily. The new plot introduced two key elements that Verdi feared would upset both Italian and French audiences: a Sicilian hero betrays his own people, and in the story's climax French occupation forces are massacred by Sicilian patriots.</p>
        <p>Verdi requested changes but was ignored. ''Writing an opera for the Opera is like killing a bull,'' he complained. When his chosen soprano, Sophie Cruvelli, disappeared with a lover in the middle of rehearsals, Verdi tried to cancel his contract. But the diva just as suddenly reappeared, and with Scribe's libretto largely untouched, Verdi's first French-language opera finally opened here on June 13, 1855.</p>
        <p>The troubles that accompanied the birth of the opera have plagued it ever since. Performed in French in Paris and Brussels until 1864, it was then forgotten, its fate blamed on Scribe's libretto. The Italian-language version fared marginally better in the 20th century, even being performed here in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Written when Verdi was in his early 40's, ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes'' (Sicilian Vespers) is often considered a transitional piece, coming after the triumphs of ''Rigoletto,'' ''Il Trovatore'' and ''La Traviata,'' and immediately before ''Simon Boccanegra'' and ''Un Ballo in Maschera.'' But it was arguably Verdi's most political opera to date, a large-canvas epic in which love is disrupted by competing patriotic and filial loyalties.</p>
        <p>With Sicily under French occupation, the nationalist leader Procida returns from exile to lead a rebellion. His lieutenant, Henri, who is in love with Hélène, learns that he is the illegitimate son of the French governor, Montfort. When Henri saves his father from assassination, the rebels condemn him as a traitor, but he persuades Montfort to pardon them and allow him to marry Hélène. As the French gather unarmed for the wedding, they, along with Henri and Hélène, are slain by the Sicilians.</p>
        <p>In accepting a commission from the Paris Opera, something of a rite of passage for 19th-century European composers, Verdi also accepted the prevailing rules for grand opera, notably a five-act spectacle that included a ballet interlude. But while the version being performed here omits the 30-minute ballet (it still runs 3 hours 10 minutes), Andrei Serban's modern dress production cannot disguise the dramatic weaknesses in the libretto.</p>
        <p>The set, designed by Richard Hudson, is dominated by a large white wall riven in two, which presumably symbolizes the unhappy coexistence of the Sicilians and their French occupiers. But while the opera opens with choruses of French soldiers and Sicilian peasants, during much of the narrative there is little to link the masses with the parallel political and romantic drama involving Henri, Hélène, Procida and Montfort.</p>
        <p>Musically, though, along with several luscious choruses, the opera also includes stirring solos, duets and quartets that are vintage Verdi. With the Paris Opera orchestra and chorus in fine form and Mr. Conlon clearly enjoying his first public encounter with ''Les Vêpres Siciliennes,'' however, it soon became apparent that Verdi had his diva Sophie Cruvelli principally in mind when he wrote this opera.</p>
        <p>In the Cruvelli role of Hélène, the American soprano Sondra Radvanovsky dominated the stage with her beautiful and dramatic voice, one large enough to fill the cavenerous Bastille Opera. She was well supported by the richly toned English baritone Anthony Michaels-Moore as Montfort and the powerful Ukrainian bass Vitalij Kowaljow as Procida. But as Henri, arguably the most difficult role, since he only reacts to events, the Italian tenor Marcello Giordani disappointed as he struggled with both high notes and volume.</p>
        <p>Singling out Ms. Radvanovsky for specially warm applause, the first-night audience obligingly overlooked the detail that none of the lead singers in this rare French-language production were actually French. But the Bastille Opera's public is unforgiving of most modern directors, and when Mr. Serban and Mr. Hudson made their appearance, they were loudly booed. In response Mr. Serban smiled bravely and waved a small French flag used in the final scene. Perhaps he was consoled by thinking that the heckling was aimed at a man who was not onstage: Eugène Scribe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
