<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keep It Simple</title>
    <meta content="18FRIE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Affairs" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Foreign Affairs"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iraq-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5DC113AF93BA2575AC0A960958260" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keep It Simple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says Clinton Administration is wise in toning down its rhetoric and stepping back from brink of all-out war with Iraq; says US has no vital interests, or allies or regional strategy that would justify trying to break apart Iraq or singlehandedly going to war against it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When trying to assess the long-term implications of Saddam Hussein's recent ''victory'' in northern Iraq, keep in mind the following fact: The Kurds whom Saddam wooed away from the U.S., and forged a partnership with in an effort to reassert his authority in northern Iraq, are the same Kurds whom Saddam bombarded with mustard gas and cyanide in 1988. This is not a relationship with a long future. The relationship between Saddam and the Barzani Kurdish faction has about the same shelf life as an Elizabeth Taylor marriage.</p>
        <p>That's why it's actually reassuring to see the Clinton Administration, belatedly, toning down its rhetoric, taking a deep breath and stepping back from the brink of all-out war against Saddam. Yes, the new Kurdish-Saddam alliance is a setback for American policy, but probably only a temporary one and certainly only a limited one. It doesn't change the fact that the U.S. still has Saddam in a strategic box. Washington has no vital interest, no allies and no regional strategy that would justify now trying to break apart Iraq or singlehandedly going to war against it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When trying to assess the long-term implications of Saddam Hussein's recent ''victory'' in northern Iraq, keep in mind the following fact: The Kurds whom Saddam wooed away from the U.S., and forged a partnership with in an effort to reassert his authority in northern Iraq, are the same Kurds whom Saddam bombarded with mustard gas and cyanide in 1988. This is not a relationship with a long future. The relationship between Saddam and the Barzani Kurdish faction has about the same shelf life as an Elizabeth Taylor marriage.</p>
        <p>That's why it's actually reassuring to see the Clinton Administration, belatedly, toning down its rhetoric, taking a deep breath and stepping back from the brink of all-out war against Saddam. Yes, the new Kurdish-Saddam alliance is a setback for American policy, but probably only a temporary one and certainly only a limited one. It doesn't change the fact that the U.S. still has Saddam in a strategic box. Washington has no vital interest, no allies and no regional strategy that would justify now trying to break apart Iraq or singlehandedly going to war against it.</p>
        <p>The vital United States interests are to keep Saddam boxed in, to prevent him from threatening the oilfields in Kuwait and Saudi Arabia, to prevent him from savaging the Kurds and to support all reasonable attempts to dispatch him to the next world. All those goals can be accomplished with the current basic U.S. force deployment. Saddam is a chronic rash -- ugly, itchy, occasionally painful, but in his present condition no longer fatal, let alone worth radical, messy surgery with unpredictable results.</p>
        <p>The Republicans, desperate to score some points against President Clinton, have been hyperventilating that he squandered the great gulf war coalition. Nonsense. That coalition was held together by two things: oil and nukes. It was not a coalition to protect Kurds. It was not a coalition to take apart Iraq. It was a coalition to protect the oilfields of Kuwait and Saudi Arabia from Iraqi attacks and it was a coalition to prevent Saddam from developing nuclear weapons. That coalition still exists. But a coalition for doing more than that -- like punishing Saddam for maneuvering in northern Iraq -- never existed. The French, the Arabs, the Russians would never sign on to that. So we acted alone. So what? That's the price of leadership. It's also why God created cruise missiles -- for operations without allies.</p>
        <p>But the Clinton Administration is also wise to stick to this limited approach because the United States has no larger vision or strategy for the Middle East, and neither does anyone else. There is a strategic vacuum in the Middle East today. In 1991 the end of both the cold war and the gulf war, coupled with a new global emphasis on economic growth, gave the region a new agenda. That new agenda was crystallized in former Israeli Prime Minister Shimon Peres's vision of a ''new Middle East,'' in which Arab-Israeli and Arab-Arab economic development and cooperation would replace confrontation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Peres's vision was a romantic one, and everyone liked to poke fun at it. But it actually produced a moderate center in the Middle East and provided a strategic framework for much of what Israel, the Arabs and the U.S. were doing in the region. Everyone reacted to it. Some by opposing it, some by trying to modify it, some by trying to nurture it.</p>
        <p>Today the Peres vision is no longer the dominant trend. Yet it has not been replaced by any new vision or agenda. The Arabs have none. The new Israeli Government has none. The new Islamic Government in Turkey has none, and the Clinton Administration has hung an ''Out to Lunch, Back on Nov. 6'' sign. In this vacuum all the old rivalries and habits are reasserting themselves. There is an all-against-all free-for-all in the Middle East today. Syria and Israel were even reported mobilizing some troops on their common border. We haven't heard that story in years.</p>
        <p>When you don't know where you're going, any road will get you there. Right now, no one in the Middle East seems to know where he is going, and everyone is on a different road. In such a moment, the U.S. would be wise to keep its policy toward Iraq simple and tightly focused. It doesn't have the allies, vital interests or road map for anything more.</p>
        <p>Foreign Affairs</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
