<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Staten Island Cheerleader, With an O, Not an I</title>
    <meta content="08PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/08/nyregion/08PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1525554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Borough Presidents</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">James P. Molinaro</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molinaro, James P (Boro Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Conservative Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Molinari, Susan</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bloomberg, Michael R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6D8113CF93BA35753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Staten Island Cheerleader, With an O, Not an I</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Staten Island Cheerleader, With an O, Not an I</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Kifner Public Lives column discusses Staten Island (NYC) Borough President James P Molinaro, who is known as enthusiastic and statistic-citing public fixture in city's most Republican borough; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ENSCONCED in the wood-paneled office on the second floor of Staten Island's Borough Hall that for years was the power base of Guy V. Molinari and his family, the current borough president, James P. Molinaro, contemplated Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's approval ratings.</p>
        <p>''Horrible,'' he said. ''His numbers are horrible, there's no question.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>James P. Molinaro, the borough president of Staten Island, can unleash a torrent of statistics and a barrage of civic pride.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ENSCONCED in the wood-paneled office on the second floor of Staten Island's Borough Hall that for years was the power base of Guy V. Molinari and his family, the current borough president, James P. Molinaro, contemplated Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg's approval ratings.</p>
        <p>''Horrible,'' he said. ''His numbers are horrible, there's no question.''</p>
        <p>In one poll taken last month, 32 percent of New Yorkers approved of the way the mayor is handling his job, while 57 percent disapproved.</p>
        <p>But in the last election, Mr. Bloomberg won Staten Island, the most Republican of the five boroughs, more than four to one in the last election, and it is vital to his re-election prospects. That puts Mr. Molinaro in an enviable position.</p>
        <p>''He has to carry Staten Island at least the same as last time,'' said Mr. Molinaro, 72, a jovial longtime Conservative Party official. ''But his popularity has gone down because of the real estate tax increase. He's got work to do.''</p>
        <p>Unbidden, Mr. Molinaro began spewing out numbers, as he is wont to do.</p>
        <p>''He got 78 percent here; we gave him 85,000 votes,'' he said. ''Seven percent of the total vote came out of Staten Island. He carried Queens 52 to 43; there were 380,000 people voted in Queens. He lost Brooklyn 45 to 55, the Bronx 42 to 58 and he was 45 to 55 in Manhattan. He never really got clobbered anywhere, but you've got to protect your base.''</p>
        <p>And so the urbane mayor has become somewhat of a fixture in relatively bucolic Staten Island these days. He was just there announcing grandiose plans for a park on a longtime sore spot, the Fresh Kills dump, er, landfill. He caught and released a fish at the new Ocean Breeze pier. He even flew to Wisconsin for the christening of a new Staten Island ferry named after -- who else? -- Guy V. Molinari.</p>
        <p>''I like it when he comes over, because he makes these great announcements,'' Mr. Molinaro fairly chortled at the announcement of the Fresh Kills plans.</p>
        <p>''Bloomberg's done a lot for Staten Island,'' Mr. Molinaro said, mentioning another new park and approval for a shopping center which is to include a Home Depot and a Target store on a site that will also have a retirement village, ball fields, a wetlands park and 15 acres reserved for future school construction. ''He's come through for me.''</p>
        <p>Ask Mr. Molinaro about the state of Staten Island and brace yourself for a torrent of statistics and a barrage of civic pride.</p>
        <p>''It's a suburban community in a city,'' he said. ''The community feels very safe. It's like being in a small town. We have grown 18 percent since 1990, a population of 445,000. We have the highest standard of living of any borough, a per family median income of $58,000. We have 36,000 acres of which 9,000 are parks. You can find almost anything here, gun ranges, riding stables, three beautiful golf courses. We have the highest percentage of children who graduate high school, the highest percentage that go to college. We have more Little Leagues than any other borough; there's a Little League on every corner. Most people own their own houses. You can buy a house from $250,000 to $5 million. Snug Harbor is gorgeous, the Chinese Garden is unique in America.''</p>
        <p>''History, you can't beat our history,'' he hurtles on, turning to a particular point of pride, the Depression-era Works Progress Administration murals scattered through Borough Hall, recently restored after years of accumulated grime. ''Our history is very historical.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Molinaro's immigrant parents never learned to speak English, but raised five children in a three-room apartment on Crosby Street, back when SoHo was sweatshops and tenements. He vividly remembers his father, who pushed a cart laden with vegetables and fruit from the old Washington Market to downtown restaurants, wrapping newspapers under his long underwear before he went off to work on a cold winter day.</p>
        <p>Murray Hill High School was the end of Mr. Molinaro's formal education, and then he went to work.</p>
        <p>''They call it recycling now,'' he said. ''Then it was called the junk business. I was 23 years in the junk business.''</p>
        <p>He married -- his wife, Carol, died in 1990 -- and moved to Staten Island 39 years ago -- a month before the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge opened -- buying the house he still lives in ''brand new'' for $17,000. He still has the same telephone number.</p>
        <p>MR. MOLINARO joined the Conservative Party, becoming county chairman in 1974, socializing often with Mr. Molinari, a staunch Republican.</p>
        <p>''In 1980, Guy ran for Congress,'' Mr. Molinaro said. ''And when he won, he asked me to run his local office. Two years later he asked me to be his chief of staff and I was for three terms.''</p>
        <p>He was also the deputy when Mr. Molinari was borough president (his daughter Susan Molinari also represented Staten Island on the City Council and in Congress).</p>
        <p>Was the fact that he is but one vowel removed from Staten Island's best-known citizen an electoral plus?</p>
        <p>''It does no harm, does no harm at all,'' Mr. Molinaro said. ''I'm sure there were people who thought they were voting for Guy again.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
