<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dangers And Jitters Of Life in Sarajevo</title>
    <meta content="26WELC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sarajevo (Bosnia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrelson, Woody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tomei, Marisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillane, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholson, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winterbottom, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Welcome to Sarajevo (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DF173AF935A15752C1A961958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dangers And Jitters Of Life in Sarajevo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews film Welcome to Sarajevo, directed by Michael Winterbottom and based on book by Michael Nicholson; Stephen Dillane, Woody Harrelson and Marisa Tomei star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unlike more exotic and elliptical films that have tried to depict the chaos of war in the former Yugoslavia, such as ''Before the Rain'' and ''Underground,'' Michael Winterbottom's ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' tackles its subject head on. Set in 1992 and based on a memoir by an English journalist, Michael Nicholson, ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' plunges directly into pandemonium.</p>
        <p>Peril and jitters are everywhere as Mr. Winterbottom presents a gonzo guided tour of life under fire.  Yet this film, for all its apparent immediacy, winds up less affecting than a more poetic or roundabout approach might be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unlike more exotic and elliptical films that have tried to depict the chaos of war in the former Yugoslavia, such as ''Before the Rain'' and ''Underground,'' Michael Winterbottom's ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' tackles its subject head on. Set in 1992 and based on a memoir by an English journalist, Michael Nicholson, ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' plunges directly into pandemonium.</p>
        <p>Peril and jitters are everywhere as Mr. Winterbottom presents a gonzo guided tour of life under fire.  Yet this film, for all its apparent immediacy, winds up less affecting than a more poetic or roundabout approach might be.</p>
        <p>In part, that happens because the film walks a thin line between flippancy and passion. War correspondents surely do the same as a way of  hanging on to their sanity, but the film's apparent detachment is strong and cavalier enough to create a chill.  So does its way of intermingling real images of wartime with patently manufactured ones, as when Marisa Tomei, very much the actress, turns up as a relief worker helping orphaned children. The near-documentary feeling of much of the film is undercut by such intrusively dramatic touches.</p>
        <p>As played with understated expertise by the English actor Stephen Dillane, the film's quiet hero (called Michael Henderson) enjoys a sparring friendship with Flynn (Woody Harrelson), a wisecracking American hotshot who is a star of television news. Tensions between these two and their entourages provides a lively counterpoint to the real terror that these reporters face every day.</p>
        <p>In the film's volatile atmosphere, it's possible to be standing with a friend at one moment, turn your back and then find him shot dead. The main characters draw their gallows humor from this awareness of hair-trigger danger lurking everywhere in Sarajevo. (Mr. Winterbottom bravely shot the film in the midst of that rubble-strewn city in 1996, just after a cease-fire took effect.)</p>
        <p>And yet, however closely they mirror the real experience of Mr. Nicholson and others, some of the shocks here are too sadly predictable. A bride and her wedding party dress gaily and prepare to cross a Sarajevo street in broad daylight: can there be much surprise in what the film will show next? Or is there doubt that when the journalists are in a particularly playful mood, they will suddenly stumble onto a grisly massacre?</p>
        <p>Even the truth here loses some of its authenticity, thanks to overly convenient contrasts, an exaggeratedly flippant tone, Mr. Winterbottom's taste for ironic pop songs (''Don't Worry, Be Happy'' linked to images of wounded orphans) and excessive fancy footwork with the camera.  Jazzy faux-documentary images only keep the material's real anguish farther away.</p>
        <p>Much of ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' is concerned with Henderson's efforts to rescue a tough young girl (played unsentimentally by Emira Nusevic, who grew up experiencing the war firsthand) and has a simple, impressive decency. There's more sparkle from Mr. Harrelson, who brings offhanded charm to the role of a nonchalant blowhard capable of real courage under fire.</p>
        <p>But the film's best moments are its smallest ones, the casual contrasts between the lives of interloping journalists and those of people watching their homeland torn apart.  As a Sarajevan driver working with the British crew, Goran Visnjic gives a gently affecting performance and best illustrates the civilians' plight.</p>
        <p>When the newsmen playfully hand him a few eggs to use as a hangover remedy, he saves the eggs gratefully for his Sarajevan friends. One man's joke is another's precious omelet in the shaky, tumultuous climate that ''Welcome to Sarajevo'' wants so much to understand.</p>
        <p>''Welcome to Sarajevo'' is rated R  (under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes mild profanity, abrupt violence and gore.</p>
        <p>WELCOME TO SARAJEVO</p>
        <p>Directed by Michael Winterbottom; written by Frank Cottrell Boyce; based on the book ''Natasha's Story'' by Michael Nicholson; director of photography, Daf Hobson; edited by Trevor Waite; music by Adrian Johnston; production designer, Mark Geraghty; produced by Graham Broadbent and Damian Jones; released by Miramax Films. Running time: 100 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Stephen Dillane (Henderson), Woody Harrelson (Flynn), Marisa Tomei (Nina), Emira Nusevic (Emira), Kerry Fox (Jane Carson), Goran Visnjic (Risto) and Emily Lloyd (Annie McGee).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
