<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ripley, Believe It or Not, Has a Secret, and It's Not Pretty</title>
    <meta content="26ALIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryder, Winona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weaver, Sigourney</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeunet, Jean-Pierre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Alien Resurrection (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED6163AF935A15752C1A961958260" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ripley, Believe It or Not, Has a Secret, and It's Not Pretty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews Alien Resurrection, film directed by Jean-Pierre Jeunet and starring Sigourney Weaver and Winona Ryder; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps it counts as a compliment among those who appreciate the dripping, throbbing, drooling intensity of the ''Alien'' movies to say that the series' latest installment is its most freakish and macabre to date. But ''Alien Resurrection,'' the fourth installment and the one that comes closest to suggesting there may be rain-slicked dark alleys in space, also offers the most buff and sexily insolent incarnation of the aliens' favorite antagonist, Sigourney Weaver's Ripley. And this time it's personal: much of Ripley's new swagger comes from the fact that she now apparently has alien blood, or slime, or ooze, or whatever it is, coursing through her veins.</p>
        <p>Ripley is a clone now, but at least that's an improvement over what she was at the end of David Fincher's third installment: dead. As ''Alien Resurrection'' begins, scientists are growing a test-tube Ripley aboard the Auriga, a big ship with mysterious mission. Ripley interests the scientists mostly because she is host to an alien embryo, which makes for a squishy surgery scene almost before the opening credits are over. Relieved of the monster spawn, Ripley is manacled and mistreated, and it takes her a while to begin understanding who, what and where she is all over again. Though she has been dormant a lot longer than Rip van Winkle, Ripley must still face the same nagging alien issues that dogged her formulaically through the first three films.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps it counts as a compliment among those who appreciate the dripping, throbbing, drooling intensity of the ''Alien'' movies to say that the series' latest installment is its most freakish and macabre to date. But ''Alien Resurrection,'' the fourth installment and the one that comes closest to suggesting there may be rain-slicked dark alleys in space, also offers the most buff and sexily insolent incarnation of the aliens' favorite antagonist, Sigourney Weaver's Ripley. And this time it's personal: much of Ripley's new swagger comes from the fact that she now apparently has alien blood, or slime, or ooze, or whatever it is, coursing through her veins.</p>
        <p>Ripley is a clone now, but at least that's an improvement over what she was at the end of David Fincher's third installment: dead. As ''Alien Resurrection'' begins, scientists are growing a test-tube Ripley aboard the Auriga, a big ship with mysterious mission. Ripley interests the scientists mostly because she is host to an alien embryo, which makes for a squishy surgery scene almost before the opening credits are over. Relieved of the monster spawn, Ripley is manacled and mistreated, and it takes her a while to begin understanding who, what and where she is all over again. Though she has been dormant a lot longer than Rip van Winkle, Ripley must still face the same nagging alien issues that dogged her formulaically through the first three films.</p>
        <p>We know most of the aliens' tricks by now, even if ''Alien Resurrection'' gives them the chance to chase human prey through garbage-strewn waters and swish their tails like marauding raptors. They still invade human hosts and burst out horribly at inconvenient moments; they still enjoy some of the most stomach-turning breeding habits imaginable.  The new wrinkle this time is that neo-Ripley finds herself strangely sympatico with these creatures, even to the point of experiencing maternal stirrings late in the story.  A new queen alien has appropriated some of Ripley's reproductive system and can now produce live, skeletal, screeching, glop-covered offspring. Maybe that tells you more than you want to know.</p>
        <p>As directed by Jean-Pierre Jeunet, half of the duo behind ''Delicatessen'' and ''City of Lost Children,'' ''Alien Resurrection'' has an eerie grunge look (with cinematography by the inventive Darius Khondji) and a sometimes ghastly sideshow atmosphere. The characters this time, with a cast including Dan Hedaya, Brad Dourif and Ron Perlman, tend to be surly miscreants, and the story has more kinks. Winona Ryder wears Army boots as a crew member of the Betty, a small ship that docks with the Auriga to engage in illicit business and stays long enough to fight the evil beasts. Tauntingly flirtatious scenes between Ms. Ryder and Ms. Weaver give this film a sexual boldness that the others' action-adventure spirit lacked.</p>
        <p>Fierce, beautiful and sardonic, Ms. Weaver makes an impressive linchpin for this series, even if she can't make it palatable for the faint of heart. When Mr. Jeunet's well-established taste for the grotesque yields an episode worthy of a circus sideshow, with hideously malformed creatures floating in glass containers and a grisly secret about Ripley's past ready to emerge, not even Ms. Weaver and her flamethrower can triumph over the sequence's extreme nastiness. The filmmaker's ghoulishly fecund imagination makes this tale (a definite change of pace for the screenwriter Joss Whedon, who also wrote ''Toy Story'') so murky that even the screen's toughest woman warrior remains largely stuck in the mud.</p>
        <p>Ms. Weaver's acting prowess is, however, enhanced by her wicked skill with a basketball in one of the film's better scenes. And perhaps it will carry what looks like an inevitable fifth film in the offing, with a major change of scenery in store.  Alien slime atop the Empire State Building looks like a distinct possibility next time around.</p>
        <p>''Alien Resurrection'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian) for an endless parade of repellent and violent reasons.</p>
        <p>ALIEN RESURRECTION</p>
        <p>Directed by Jean-Pierre Jeunet; written by Joss Whedon; director of photography, Darius Khondji; edited by Herve Schneid; production designer, Nigel Phelps; produced by Bill Badolato, Walter Hill, David Giler and Gordon Carroll; released by 20th Century Fox. Running time: 105 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Sigourney Weaver (Ripley), Winona Ryder (Annalee Call), Dominique Pinon (Vriess), Ron Perlman (Johner), Dan Hedaya (General Perez), J. E.Freeman (Wren), Brad Dourif (Gediman) and Michael Wincott (Elgyn).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
