<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gambino Crime Boss or Not, Peter Gotti Gets 9-Year Term</title>
    <meta content="16GOTT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/16/nyregion/16gotti.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1574591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Block, Frederic (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotti, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gambino Crime Family</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gotti, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDF123BF935A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gambino Crime Boss or Not, Peter Gotti Gets 9-Year Term</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gambino Crime Boss or Not, Peter Gotti Gets 9 Years in Prison</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Gotti is sentenced in federal court, Brooklyn, to nine years in prison for racketeering and money laundering; Judge Frederic Block says that even though Gotti does not exhibit leadership characteristics, he is indeed leader of Gambino crime family; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Gotti, the older brother of the deceased mobster John J. Gotti and the reputed acting head of the Gambino crime family, was sentenced yesterday to nine years and four months in federal prison for money laundering and racketeering.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti's lawyer, Gerald L. Shargel, asked Judge Frederic Block of United States District Court in Brooklyn to impose a lighter sentence because Mr. Gotti, 64, a retired garbageman, was at most a mob boss in name only and is in poor health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Gotti, the older brother of the deceased mobster John J. Gotti and the reputed acting head of the Gambino crime family, was sentenced for money laundering and racketeering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Gotti, the older brother of the deceased mobster John J. Gotti and the reputed acting head of the Gambino crime family, was sentenced yesterday to nine years and four months in federal prison for money laundering and racketeering.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti's lawyer, Gerald L. Shargel, asked Judge Frederic Block of United States District Court in Brooklyn to impose a lighter sentence because Mr. Gotti, 64, a retired garbageman, was at most a mob boss in name only and is in poor health.</p>
        <p>But Judge Block said that while the record ''strongly suggests that Peter Gotti did not exhibit leadership characteristics,'' he was ''indeed a leader,'' whose position required a stiff sentence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shargel said that with credit for time already served and other reductions, Mr. Gotti could finish his sentence in as little as six years. Mr. Gotti, however, is also facing up to 70 years in prison on separate federal charges that he took part in an unsuccessful 1999 plot to kill the Mafia turncoat Sammy Gravano. That case is scheduled to go to trial in June in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The sentencing came two weeks after a woman linked to Mr. Gotti, Marjorie Alexander, 43, killed herself in a Long Island motel. While Mr. Gotti's lawyers have said he was devastated by the woman's death, Mr. Shargel referred to it only indirectly.</p>
        <p>''He doesn't have a visitors' list that's very long,'' Mr. Shargel said. ''He is, your honor, very much alone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti declined to speak before the sentence was imposed.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said he took the reins of the Gambino family in 1999 after his brother's son and successor, John A. Gotti, pleaded guilty to extortion.</p>
        <p>Peter Gotti and six others, including another brother, Richard V. Gotti, were indicted in 2002 on charges that included corrupt control of a longshoremen's union local, illegal gambling and extorting money from the movie star Steven Seagal.</p>
        <p>Peter Gotti was accused of meeting regularly with a Gambino soldier who gave him the proceeds of the family's illegal activities. In March 2003, all the defendants were convicted in what prosecutors described as a heavy blow to an already weakened Gambino organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shargel told Judge Block that Mr. Gotti is blind in one eye and suffers from thyroid goiter, sciatica, emphysema, rheumatoid arthritis, postconcussion syndrome and depression, and that a long prison stay could be further ruinous to his health.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Gotti's stewardship of the mob, Mr. Shargel said: ''Peter Gotti may have had the title of acting boss, but I don't think there's anyone who knows Peter Gotti who thinks he has managerial capacity, if you will. I don't think there's anyone who knows Peter Gotti who thinks he was making important decisions, if you will.''</p>
        <p>Some law enforcement officials have said that the Gotti family's role in the Gambino family is on the wane. But J. Kevin McGowan, assistant police chief of the Waterfront Commission of New York Harbor, said that Mr. Gotti remains the boss.</p>
        <p>''Whatever show there is left,'' Chief McGowan said, ''he still runs it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
