<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clams, Tailpipes and Other Harvests</title>
    <meta content="16FACTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1582000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gustin, Georgina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DF1E3CF935A25756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clams, Tailpipes and Other Harvests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGINA GUSTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gustin, Georgina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>List of summer facts about Connecticut; drawings (Special Issue: Summer Life) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE drive, we try to stay cool, we take off our ties during the summer. And we get lots of guests. Here are a few summer facts about the state.</p>
        <p>ON THE LAST FRIDAY IN JULY, STAY HOME -- Interstate 95 has been chronically crowded since it reached its capacity in the 1970's, according to the Department of Transportation. These days, travel on the road is even heavier than it was three decades ago, especially in the summer. In 2003, the busiest day of the year on I-95 -- measured at a counting station in Branford -- was the last Friday in July when 104,469 vehicles passed in both directions. That day, and all of the Fridays last July, surpassed even the day before Thanksgiving, traditionally one of the heaviest travel days in the country.</p>
        <p>IT TAKES MORE EFFORT TO KEEP COOL -- Connecticut residents use more energy trying to keep cool in the sticky months of July and August than they do staying toasty in the winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE drive, we try to stay cool, we take off our ties during the summer. And we get lots of guests. Here are a few summer facts about the state.</p>
        <p>ON THE LAST FRIDAY IN JULY, STAY HOME -- Interstate 95 has been chronically crowded since it reached its capacity in the 1970's, according to the Department of Transportation. These days, travel on the road is even heavier than it was three decades ago, especially in the summer. In 2003, the busiest day of the year on I-95 -- measured at a counting station in Branford -- was the last Friday in July when 104,469 vehicles passed in both directions. That day, and all of the Fridays last July, surpassed even the day before Thanksgiving, traditionally one of the heaviest travel days in the country.</p>
        <p>IT TAKES MORE EFFORT TO KEEP COOL -- Connecticut residents use more energy trying to keep cool in the sticky months of July and August than they do staying toasty in the winter.</p>
        <p>On a typical spring day, residents might consume about 4,000 megawatts of power. On a peak day in the summer, when air conditioners are blasting, that number has surpassed 6,000 megawatts.</p>
        <p>HERE TODAY, GONE TOMORROW -- Connecticut residents love seafood, but much of what is caught along the shoreline is actually shipped elsewhere. The state, in fact, is the one of the largest producers of farmed oysters in the country, according to the Department of Agriculture.</p>
        <p>Right now, the largest catch from the state is hard clams, which last year weighed in at 3.4 million pounds, outdoing oysters, which have been troubled by disease and have dropped to 247,000 pounds in 2002 from five million pounds in 1995.</p>
        <p>Also hurt by disease has been the lobster harvest. In 1997, there were 3.7 million lobster ''landings'' here, while in 2002, after a massive lobster die-off in Long Island Sound, there were just under one million lobsters hauled in.</p>
        <p>STAY A WHILE -- The most popular summer destinations in the state are on the shoreline, from Greenwich to Stonington. Summer accounts for 40 percent of the tourism take in Connecticut, while the fall accounts for 30 percent, said Ed Dombroskas, director of the state's tourism division.</p>
        <p>According to figures compiled by the Connecticut East Convention and Visitors Bureau, the southeastern part of the state, primarily the Mystic area, draws about two-thirds of the state's visitors every year.</p>
        <p>The state's 100 parks also are popular in the summer, pulling in about four million to five million visitors. Thomas Morrissey, chief of the Bureau of Outdoor Recreation, said Hammonasset in Madison is the most popular.</p>
        <p>HI, MAY WE HELP YOU? -- Over the past decade manufacturing jobs in Connecticut have dropped by about 54,000 employees, while jobs in the service industry have increased by about 17,000. In the summer those service jobs reach their peak.</p>
        <p>Employment in restaurants last year jumped from 84,500 in January to 93,600 in June. In the arts, entertainment and recreation fields, the number jumped from 17,800 in January to nearly 28,000 in July.</p>
        <p>''Hotels and restaurants certainly pick up,'' said Salvatore DiPillo, a statistician with the state's Department of Labor. ''Amusement and recreation, too.''</p>
        <p>''We don't have the tourism of Massachusetts or southern Maine, but people do pass through,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SUMMER ON THE FARM -- Most Connecticut residents don't think of their state as an agricultural hotbed, but it actually posts some impressive statistics and the summer growing season is a busy one for many of the state's 3,800 farms.</p>
        <p>The state grows premium cigar leaf wrappers, second only in production to Cuba, according to the Department of Agriculture. (Anyone who has driven to Bradley International Airport north of Hartford has seen the red cigar-leaf barns along the highway.)</p>
        <p>Connecticut is also the fifth-largest grower of mushrooms and has been called the ''Bedding Plant Capital of the World,'' said Rick Macsuga of the state agriculture department. Thousands of people from Connecticut and beyond, Mr. Macsuga said, line up at the Hartford regional summertime market for impatiens, begonias, fuchsia and other bedding plants.</p>
        <p>The state also has a booming egg industry. ''There are as many egg-laying chickens in the state as there are people,'' said Mr. Macsuga, noting a human population of 3.8 million and a chicken count of about 3.7 million. ''So that's a chicken for every pot.''</p>
        <p>Altogether, Connecticut's farms, with more than 360,000 acres in production, generate $2 billion every year.</p>
        <p>CASUAL FRIDAYS AND THE HABERDASHER -- Richard's of Greenwich and Mitchells, in Westport, two clothing stores, sell millions of dollars in ties every year, but in the summer, sales plummet.</p>
        <p>''We do 70 percent of our neckwear sales in the fall and on holidays,'' said Dan Farrington, a merchandise manager for the stores. ''The work dress code gets a little more casual in the summer, and people go on vacation. The business definitely drops.''</p>
        <p>BOATS, BOATS AND MORE BOATS -- A surge of boat registrations floods the Connecticut Department of Motor Vehicles between March and May. Over the past decade, though, that surge has grown more intense as recreational boating has become more popular. In 2003 there were 111,489 registered vessels in the state, the vast majority of which were recreational. In 1994, there were only 100,653 registered boats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
