<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Early, but the Mets Must Find an Identity</title>
    <meta content="01BASE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/01/sports/01BASE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1289778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Flushing</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Norfolk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle</location>
        <org class="online_producer">AAA</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Valentine, Bobby</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Phillips, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Piazza, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Agbayani, Benny</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Payton, Jay</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED81638F932A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Early, but the Mets Must Find an Identity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses problems besetting New York Mets; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mets Manager Bobby Valentine sauntered toward a group of reporters at Shea Stadium last night like an eager gunfighter, a small smile creasing his face. ''I'm ready for you,'' Valentine bellowed. When a reporter chuckled, Valentine feigned incredulity and said, ''You sound like you don't believe me?''</p>
        <p>Valentine knew what to expect, as did Mets General Manager Steve Phillips. Five minutes earlier, Phillips leaned against a black cinder-block wall beside the Mets' clubhouse and answered questions like a defense lawyer whose client had just berated the judge. Somehow, Phillips had to make that embarrassing client sound appealing again. That was arduous since the Mets have been unappealing for a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mets Manager Bobby Valentine sauntered toward a group of reporters at Shea Stadium last night like an eager gunfighter, a small smile creasing his face. ''I'm ready for you,'' Valentine bellowed. When a reporter chuckled, Valentine feigned incredulity and said, ''You sound like you don't believe me?''</p>
        <p>Valentine knew what to expect, as did Mets General Manager Steve Phillips. Five minutes earlier, Phillips leaned against a black cinder-block wall beside the Mets' clubhouse and answered questions like a defense lawyer whose client had just berated the judge. Somehow, Phillips had to make that embarrassing client sound appealing again. That was arduous since the Mets have been unappealing for a month.</p>
        <p>The Mets can keep saying it is early in the season, but this has been ugly. April or not, the Mets have pitched horrendously, fielded poorly and hit terribly. Six months ago, they had just finished losing to the Yankees in the World Series. But the confused Mets were home last night and had to explain why what was supposed to be a splendid year has shown signs of deterioration.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to lose,'' Mike Piazza said. ''It's another to lose the way we're losing. That's what makes it frustrating.''</p>
        <p>Phillips met with Valentine and his coaches yesterday and searched for reasons the Mets, the National League champions, had lost 15 of their first 24 games. Phillips asked two important questions over lunch: ''What can we do with what we have? What else can we consider?''</p>
        <p>While Phillips and Valentine would not reveal specifics about the meeting, they obviously believe the Mets will get improved starting pitching and some timely hits. The Mets had better.</p>
        <p>For one night, there was relief in Flushing because the Mets received both. Steve Trachsel tossed six reliable innings, three players had two-out run-scoring singles and Piazza belted a three-run homer to power the Mets to an 8-2 victory over the Astros last night. It was one victory, but it was a start for a team that should not be playing this raggedly.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot better to win,'' Valentine said. ''It was a good-looking game. Lord knows we've had some bad-looking games. This was a nice, well-played game I think we can build on.''</p>
        <p>The Mets needed this after a brutal 3-6 road trip during which they were bruised for more than nine runs a game in the losses and had three hits in their previous 31 at-bats with runners in scoring position. They had four in their first seven at-bats in that situation last night. Phillips minimized the importance of the meeting and said that the Mets did this often. Still, the timing of Phillips's session and his divulging it to the news media was noteworthy. Even Phillips is wondering what is awry.</p>
        <p>''It's one that I look at it and say, ''Who are we right now?' '' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>Indeed. Who are these Mets? Phillips went on to explain that Benny Agbayani and Timo Perez were on the disabled list before the season was even a week old, and Al Leiter and Robin Ventura have also been injured. He does not know who the Mets are at this point because they have been incomplete during a troubling month. Jay Payton laughed while conceding that the Mets had been consistent, as in ''consistently bad.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have talked about promoting Alex Escobar, their premier prospect, who was hitting .299 with four homers at Class AAA Norfolk before last night. But they are hesitant to do so because they do not want Escobar to feel he is being viewed as a savior. That is foolish. If Escobar can boost the Mets by providing power, he should be here now.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Mets spoke of trusting their player evaluations and waiting for this team to jell. Even if that happens, the Mets should know that the last team to make the postseason after being more than four and a half games out of a playoff spot at the end of April was the 1987 Tigers. Today, the 10-15 Mets are four and a half games out of first place and a wild-card spot.</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt this team is a lot better than this record,'' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>Surroundings. That was the all-purpose word Valentine used to describe why he is sure the Mets will reverse themselves. They play the next five at Shea, their players are getting healthy and they have not played even one-sixth of the schedule. They are in a division that does not have any team running away with first place, the way the Seattle Mariners are in the American League West, and they still have 64 games left against N.L. East teams.</p>
        <p>''I have no fear at all,'' Valentine said, ''and I have total confidence in every team I've ever been with, including this one.''</p>
        <p>The Mets insisted that this slump would not last, deflecting dozens of questions about what is wrong and whether they need to make changes. Of course, the Mets should be playing much better and they have five months to gather themselves. They began regrouping last night, but there is one omen circling over them. During a memorable 2000, when the Mets won 94 games, they never had a streak where they stumbled through 15 of 24. Recall that when someone claims it is only May.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
