<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The End of the Battle in Belgium</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="156455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOCIETE GENERALE DE BELGIQUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MONTGOMERY, PAUL L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DE BENEDETTI, CARLO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDA143FF936A15755C0A96E948260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The End of the Battle in Belgium</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL L. MONTGOMERY, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MONTGOMERY, PAUL L</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, June 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Carlo de Benedetti ended his five-month battle for Societe Generale de Belgique today, making a deal with his rivals to reduce his holdings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Carlo de Benedetti ended his five-month battle for Societe Generale de Belgique today, making a deal with his rivals to reduce his holdings.</p>
        <p>Carlo de Benedetti ended his five-month battle for Societe Generale de Belgique today, making a deal with his rivals to reduce his holdings.</p>
        <p>In return, he will be one of the company's three vice chairmen, as well as a director and a member of the executive committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. de Benedetti and his companies Cerus and Europe 92 will sell 7.75 million shares of Societe Generale, cutting their stake from about 45 percent to about 16 percent. Mr. de Benedetti said the sale would bring in $1 billion.</p>
        <p>A French-Belgian alliance led by Compagnies Financieres de Suez of France gained control of Belgium's largest company during a bidding war that at one point quadrupled the stock price. The stock price is currently about double what it was when Mr. de Benedetti began buying shares. Questions on Profit</p>
        <p>Mr. de Benedetti, the chairman of Ing. C. Olivetti &amp; C. S.p.A., and his forces have said that they paid $1.5 billion for their entire stake.</p>
        <p>Some analysts questioned whether Mr. de Benedetti had made any profit from his failed bid. Mr. de Benedetti would not give any details of his bookkeeping. An independent accounting of the transaction is impossible because Belgian law does not require disclosure of purchases of stakes in companies, and it is not clear at what average price Mr. de Benedetti built his holding.</p>
        <p>In return for ending the takeover battle, Cerus will increase its stake in Suez, a French holding company, to more than 4 percent. It now owns about 1 percent.</p>
        <p>When Mr. de Benedetti began his campaign in January he said his ambition was to hold about 25 percent of the shares and to have a hand in the day-to-day management of the company.</p>
        <p>Societe Generale controls 25 to 30 percent of the economy of Belgium in one way or another, and Mr. de Benedetti had said the holding company was in an ideal position to take advantage of the ending of market barriers within the European Community, which is scheduled to occur in 1992.</p>
        <p>The two other vice chairmen who will serve with Mr. de Benedetti will be Renaud de la Geniere, president of Suez, and Maurice Lippens, managing director of the Belgian insurer Compagnie Financiere et de Reassurance du Groupe A.G. One of 26 Directors</p>
        <p>Mr. de Benedetti will be one of 26 directors and will have a place on the nine-member executive committee. The French banker Herve de Carmoy was elected Tuesday at the annual shareholders meeting to head the executive committee.</p>
        <p>In the end Mr. de Benedetti was outmaneuvered by the Suez group, which assembled a 51 percent majority from investors in France, Belgium, Switzerland and Luxembourg.</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. de Benedetti was scaling back his ambitions, the British publisher Robert Maxwell appeared on the scene.</p>
        <p>In a series of conferences here today, Mr. Maxwell said discussions with Societe Generale were at an ''advanced stage'' about creating a joint venture called Maxwell Generale that would have assets of at least $350 million. It would combine, under the management of the Maxwell Communication Corporation, some of Societe Generale's cable television and information system holdings with Mr. Maxwell's print and electronic publishing interests.</p>
        <p>The end of Mr. de Benedetti's takeover attempt unblocks 10 million new shares of Societe Generale that had been tied up in the courts. Mr. Maxwell said he would like to buy some of the shares ''if the terms are right.'' He declined to elaborate beyond saying, ''If I become a shareholder you can be sure I will become a director,'' implying that any purchases would be for large amounts of stock.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
