<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuffle That Deck: Here Come the Jets</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="790364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA FALCONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D9123EF930A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuffle That Deck: Here Come the Jets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I., Sept. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not even Coach Rich Kotite, who backed up the truck and dumped half the team when he arrived, could have anticipated the drastic changes the Jets will unveil Sunday at Atlanta. Essentially, Kotite has brought in a second truck.</p>
        <p>The game against the Falcons marks the end of the team's first quarter. By now, players should be familiar with one another. But because of injuries and other factors, there are 10 Jets starters who weren't even penciled in to be first-string when training camp began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not even Coach Rich Kotite, who backed up the truck and dumped half the team when he arrived, could have anticipated the drastic changes the Jets will unveil Sunday at Atlanta. Essentially, Kotite has brought in a second truck.</p>
        <p>The game against the Falcons marks the end of the team's first quarter. By now, players should be familiar with one another. But because of injuries and other factors, there are 10 Jets starters who weren't even penciled in to be first-string when training camp began.</p>
        <p>The cynics could say that this latest shuffling is merely an indication that the players who were here before couldn't perform and that any change is an improvement. Or, the way Kotite sees it, a collection of younger, hungrier players has helped improve the team.</p>
        <p>Three of the first-stringers against Atlanta weren't even on the team at the start of camp: Charles Wilson at wide receiver, Wilber Marshall at weakside linebacker and Carlton Haselrig at right guard.</p>
        <p>Others who didn't figure as starters at their positions when camp began were wide receiver Wayne Chrebet, Kyle Brady at tight end, Ronald Moore at running back, Matt Brock at defensive left tackle, Mo Lewis at middle linebacker, Otis Smith at right cornerback and Ron Carpenter at free safety.</p>
        <p>And when quarterback Boomer Esiason takes the opening snap at the Georgia Dome, he will be the only player on offense who will be in the same spot he was when last season ended. Only three defenders are lined up in the same place: left end Marvin Washington, weakside linebacker Bobby Houston and left cornerback Aaron Glenn.</p>
        <p>Over all, the Jets have 11 rookies or first-year players on the roster, with starters in Brady and Chrebet. Hugh Douglas is the designated pass rusher and Don Silvestri is the team's long kicker. Carl Greenwood sees considerable action in the nickel and dime defenses that require extra cornerbacks.</p>
        <p>"I've never had a group of so many young guys who are contributing," Kotite said today. "They got to where they are because they worked for it."</p>
        <p>A 1-2 record -- with that one victory last Sunday's 27-10 decision over the expansion Jacksonville Jaguars -- does not indicate anything special. Losing records never do. But the Jets believe they should be 2-1, that they should never have blown their 24-3 lead over the Indianapolis Colts and lost, 27-24, in overtime.</p>
        <p>Actually, the Jets have not played that badly: they were even with the Miami Dolphins for virtually the first half in the season opener; they were trouncing the Colts into the final quarter, and they manhandled the Jaguars the entire game.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
