<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confrontation in the Gulf: TV Critic's Notebook;   Iraq's Leader Entertains 'Guests,' Not 'Hostages'</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="379026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD123BF937A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confrontation in the Gulf: TV Critic's Notebook;   Iraq's Leader Entertains 'Guests,' Not 'Hostages'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly, yesterday at noon, viewers of CNN's ''News Hour'' were presented with President Saddam Hussein, in civilian suit and shiny tie, sitting amid some two dozen people, most of them under 21 and dressed for kicking a ball around.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Suddenly, yesterday at noon, viewers of CNN's ''News Hour'' were presented with President Saddam Hussein, in civilian suit and shiny tie, sitting amid some two dozen people, most of them under 21 and dressed for kicking a ball around.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, yesterday at noon, viewers of CNN's ''News Hour'' were presented with President Saddam Hussein, in civilian suit and shiny tie, sitting amid some two dozen people, most of them under 21 and dressed for kicking a ball around.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi leader had not been seen in public for several weeks, and it was not clear where or when the pictures shown on Iraqi television had been taken. Yesterday's appearance, however, must have been taped recently, after the announcement that Westerners would be dispersed to the vicinity of potential targets. The where was evidently the living quarters of some of the Britons whom he called guests and whom observers in the West have taken to calling hostages. They seemed a bit startled at first; at least one man, bare-chested, may have been summoned from the shower.</p>
        <p>What accounts for President Hussein's attraction to home video? From the choice of setting, you do not have to be an expert to deduce that a public relations adviser had discerned that he has not been coming across outside his own precincts as a man who is all heart. It follows that he must be placed among children, whose hair could be tousled and shoulders massaged on camera, as he explained to his guests for about 45 minutes that ''your presence here is meant to avoid war.'' Rudimentary perhaps, but then, what is someone known on Western television as the ''beast of Baghdad'' to do?</p>
        <p>Not Waiting for Answers</p>
        <p>It was a tossup whether President Hussein or the two boys in shorts with whom he made small talk at the outset about milk and cornflakes and volleyball were the more uncomfortable. Chitchat was plainly not his strong suit. ''How are you occupying your time?'' the President asked his guests, who were now his hosts, and did not pause for a reply.</p>
        <p>Instead, he went on to explain, through the translator seated beside him, that owing to a deliberate or inadvertent mistranslation, the interned Westerners had been described as ''a shield'' when they should have been described as ''prevention.'' He assured one of the boys that he will one day be happy over the part he was playing in preventing war, and he sympathized with their parents that the enemy might ''strike despite your presence.'' They were all ''heroes of peace.''</p>
        <p>If there were lessons here about the uses of television on the world stage, they were that a forceful personality comes through almost in spite of itself, and that there is more than one audience to consider. President Hussein's script, no doubt suited to stirring emotions in his own country and elsewhere in the Middle East, seemed slightly whacky as an appeal to Westerners. It would take a remarkably amenable Briton, concerned about his fellow countrymen's being prevented from leaving Iraq and Kuwait, to take much comfort from their captor's tributes.</p>
        <p>While the President rattled on, one of the two officers behind him kept tousling the smaller boy's hair. A nice man like that could never pick on the Kurds. CNN's Reid Collins broke in to explain to viewers that they were watching a propaganda film. But he must have been in error, because Mr. Hussein said, ''I am not speaking for propaganda purposes.''</p>
        <p>A Lesson in History</p>
        <p>Although the point of the exercise was not so much what President Hussein said as where he was and with whom, he invited questions. The first came from a woman who was concerned that her children were missing school. He promised to send experts to assist with schooling and used the next 10 minutes for a history lesson: that Kuwait had been taken from Iraq by British colonialists and that ''we can smash and crush any aggression that may be perpetrated.'' His manner remained subdued, but he seemed periodically to lose track of the purpose of the show, at least for part of the audience.</p>
        <p>His other responses, too, were mixtures of solicitude, truculence and piety. In answer to a man's friendly remark, ''Your last initiative was quite reasonable, we all think,'' he discoursed on how God is on the side of initiatives. He promised that ''Arabs will teach Bush how to be closer to God.'' He seemed to be going for the avuncular but slipping now and then into the messianic or even the menacing.</p>
        <p>Where had we seen such a performance before? Perhaps it was the mustache and the children, but wasn't there a resemblance to Uncle Joe Stalin playing Mr. Nice Guy?</p>
        <p>The climax was a group photo op, the President and his guests together. He urged them to send copies to relatives to show how well they were getting on. He was sorry that he could not stay for lunch, which must have come as a relief to the much-tousled boy. And there were handshakes all around. None of the Britons declined to shake the presidential hand. Some viewers may take that as evidence of abiding good will. But some may see it as the sort of courtesy that is quickly learned by guests in Saddam Hussein's Iraq.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
