<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mother's Experience Upstages Woods</title>
    <meta content="15anderson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/15/sports/golf/15anderson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1687444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">St Andrews</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Woods, Tiger</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D61330F936A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mother's Experience Upstages Woods</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">His Mother's Experience Upstages Woods's Start</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <dateline>St. Andrews, Scotland</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN an air horn screeched at the 134th British Open to begin two minutes of silence yesterday to honor the victims of last week's London bombings, the tournament and the golfers stopped. Atop the grandstands to the right of the first fairway and behind the 18th green, only the flags were moving, fluttering in the cloudy breeze off the North Sea as the gold hands on the clock on the Royal and Ancient clubhouse crept past noon.</p>
        <p>On the Old Course, on the mounds in front of the green on the 618-yard No. 14, Tiger Woods stood still, his black cap off, his head bowed, his mind on his mother, Tida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiger Woods has preferred to keep his family and his private life separate from his golf, until he learned of his mother's close call in London.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN an air horn screeched at the 134th British Open to begin two minutes of silence yesterday to honor the victims of last week's London bombings, the tournament and the golfers stopped. Atop the grandstands to the right of the first fairway and behind the 18th green, only the flags were moving, fluttering in the cloudy breeze off the North Sea as the gold hands on the clock on the Royal and Ancient clubhouse crept past noon.</p>
        <p>On the Old Course, on the mounds in front of the green on the 618-yard No. 14, Tiger Woods stood still, his black cap off, his head bowed, his mind on his mother, Tida.</p>
        <p>''For me, personally,'' he was saying now when asked what his thoughts had been during the silence, ''I was more thankful than anything else because my mom was in the building right across the street from where the bomb blew up. It very easily could have been tragic for me personally. I can only imagine what everyone else who was involved, where they lost a loved one or had a loved one hurt, what they might have been going through.''</p>
        <p>Woods shot a six-under-par 66, but suddenly his mother's experience had upstaged his opening-round play and opened a window into his heart.</p>
        <p>In a current American Express advertisement, he is shown hugging his mother sweetly, and at tournaments, he has occasionally spoken fondly of his mother and his father, Earl, his wife, Elin, his caddie, Steve Williams, and his golf guru, Hank Haney.</p>
        <p>But mostly he has preferred to keep his family and his private life separate from his golf, until he learned of his mother's close call last week.</p>
        <p>''She was vacationing in London,'' he said, smiling. ''I don't know why. Maybe because the weather is so great. I don't know. She just had a bunch of friends and family there. She was kind of touring Europe before she came over here.''</p>
        <p>His mother, a Thai who met his father when he was an Army officer in Vietnam, was in a hotel when the bomb went off, but Woods didn't know any details or which of the four bombing sites she was near.</p>
        <p>''I've talked to her, but she really hasn't said a whole lot,'' he said. ''Typical mom, you know. You know my mom: 'Are you O.K.?' 'Yeah good. What are you going to do today on the course?' That kind of thing. She likes to change the subject real fast.''</p>
        <p>Woods said he didn't know about his mother's incident until Haney told him about it Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''She doesn't tell me anything,'' he said. ''That's kind of how our family is. If you're injured or you're hurt or you're sick or anything, you don't tell anyone. You just deal with life and move on.''</p>
        <p>But she hadn't mentioned anything to him about it?</p>
        <p>''My family doesn't do that,'' Woods said. ''When my dad had cancer, he didn't say anything. When I had my knee surgery, I didn't say anything. It's one of our deals of probably being a Woods, I guess. Kind of deal with things and move on.''</p>
        <p>Had his mother returned home to the Orange County area in California?</p>
        <p>''She's here, so everything is good to go,'' Woods said. ''She's out here following,'' he added, referring to her being in his gallery. ''I heard a couple of 'Nice putts' from her.''</p>
        <p>But when play resumed, how had he been able to switch gears from his mother to his next shot?</p>
        <p>''I had a tough shot, so my focus went right to that,'' he said. ''I was trying to hit a low-skipping spinner where it hit on top and grabbed and released on down.''</p>
        <p>Woods got his par 5 there, bogeyed the 423-yard No. 16 but putted out of the Valley of Sin in front of the green at the 357-yard finishing hole for a birdie and 66.</p>
        <p>''That's the left part of the swale,'' he said later, referring to the huge left-to-right break involved on his long putt after he had nearly driven the green. ''Actually, ironically, I practiced that putt quite a bit Wednesday because for three straight days I kept hitting the ball in the same spot. I didn't hit it any further, didn't hit it any shorter. I just thought I'd hit a few putts from there for the hell of it.''</p>
        <p>One of sport's oldest truisms: the harder you work, the luckier you get. And yesterday, Woods's tee shot on No. 18 provided him with that same putt.</p>
        <p>''I knew the speed,'' he said, smiling. ''It was a matter of getting the line. And obviously, I didn't get quite enough break, but I had the speed right.''</p>
        <p>But for all of what Tiger Woods learned from those practice putts Wednesday, the most important thing he learned that day was how his mother had been so close to one of the London bombings. Even if he had to learn of it from Hank Haney.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
