<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leading Indexes Continue To Climb to Record Levels</title>
    <meta content="Y20STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russell 2,000 Stock Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DF1638F933A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leading Indexes Continue To Climb to Record Levels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stock market's leading indexes rise to record highs again despite new earnings warnings from several companies; Dow Jones industrial average increases by 27.65 points, to 8,803.05, fourth new high in row; Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index climbs 4.22 points, to 1,089.75, fourth consecutive new high; Russell index of 2,000 smaller-company stocks sets new high, rising 2.12 points to 474.30; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stock market's leading indexes rose to record highs again yesterday despite new earnings warnings from several companies. Investors, it appears, are continuing to focus on what good news there is while ignoring -- or discounting -- any negative vibrations.</p>
        <p>Both the Sunbeam Corporation and Rockwell International said yesterday that their first-quarter earnings may be less than expected, adding their names to a growing list of recent corporate warnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stock market's leading indexes rose to record highs again yesterday despite new earnings warnings from several companies. Investors, it appears, are continuing to focus on what good news there is while ignoring -- or discounting -- any negative vibrations.</p>
        <p>Both the Sunbeam Corporation and Rockwell International said yesterday that their first-quarter earnings may be less than expected, adding their names to a growing list of recent corporate warnings.</p>
        <p>The shares of Sunbeam declined by 4 11/16, or 9.4 percent, to 45 3/8, after it said that orders for appliances were lower than the company had forecast. This is the second consecutive quarter that Sunbeam has disappointed expectations. Rockwell International said price cuts would trim its earnings. Its stock retreated 6 1/16, or 10 percent, to 54 7/16.</p>
        <p>But the overall environment for stocks remains favorable. Interest rates still remain low, which makes stocks a more attractive investment for investors and helps give the economy a boost.</p>
        <p>Inflation is restrained, as indicated by the Consumer Price Index for February, which rose only one-tenth of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>While the growth in earnings appears to be slowing, the economy seems more resilient this quarter than many economists had expected.</p>
        <p>The expected drag from the Asia financial turmoil has yet to appear in a major way. The Federal Reserve seems to have little leeway at the moment to consider either raising or lower interest rates.</p>
        <p>While some doubts may have been formulating about the earnings outlook, Abby Joseph Cohen, the co-chairwomen of the investment policy committee at Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, helped reinforce the positive view by announcing Tuesday that she had raised her 1998 target  for the Dow to 9,300 and for the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks to 1,150.</p>
        <p>In this atmosphere, the Dow Jones industrial average has increased by 27.65 points, to 8,803.05, its fourth new high in a row and its first trip over 8,800. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index climbed 4.22 points, to 1,089.74, its fourth consecutive new high, while the Nasdaq composite index finished at 1,799.98, up 11.70, to its second consecutive new high. The Amex Composite increased by 4.04 to close at 726.80.</p>
        <p>The Russell index of 2,000 smaller- company stocks also hit a new high -- its second consecutive -- rising 2.12 points, to 474.30.</p>
        <p>It was a day of below-average volume, with 598.2 million shares traded. Advancing stocks led stocks that declined by 1,660 to 1,253.</p>
        <p>A rise in the price of crude oil for the second consecutive day helped push some oil stocks higher. Oil, which had fallen to a nine-year low Tuesday, could not hold its gains and ended the day down slightly.</p>
        <p>But oil stocks held on. Exxon Corporation, which was up as much as  3/8, finished 3/16 higher at 64 13/16.</p>
        <p>Oil service stocks, which are more vulnerable to a price collapse, fared better. The S.&amp; P. index of six oil service companies climbed 58.31 points, to 4,104.91, lead by Schlumberger.</p>
        <p>It rose 1 3/8, to 71 5/8, after having surged on the oil price rebound Wednesday. Before that, the stock had fallen in eight of the previous 10 trading days.</p>
        <p>Banking shares climbed further, helped by low interest rates and speculation about mergers. J. P. Morgan, which is a possible target, led the Dow higher, rising 3 3/8, to 135 3/8. First Union rose 1 15/16, to 58 1/4,  and Nationsbank climbed 15/16, to 72 7/16. But Chase Manhattan Bank fell 2 7/8, to 135 1/4, after rising Wednesday on new rumors about its possible acquisition of Merrill Lynch. When the rumor lost its steam, Merrill Lynch, which jumped 7 1/4 Wednesday, fell 3 15/16 yesterday to 83 1/16.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
