<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Stall Bill on Education Tax Breaks</title>
    <meta content="Y20EDU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003476"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Filibusters and Debate Curbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Savings Accounts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0DD1638F933A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Stall Bill on Education Tax Breaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats, in first confrontation over education agenda in an election year, block Republicans' centerpiece proposal, with each party questioning the other's commitment to schoolchildren; Democrats are able to continue filibuster on bill to provide parents with tax breaks for education costs; photo of Pres Clinton, who has threatened to veto plan for education savings accounts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first confrontation over the education agenda in an election year, Democrats blocked the Republicans' centerpiece proposal today, with each party questioning the other's commitment to schoolchildren.</p>
        <p>By a strictly party-line vote, Democrats, including one who is a chief co-sponsor of the bill to provide parents with tax breaks for education costs, were able to continue a filibuster. The vote was 55 to 44 to end the filibuster, but it takes 60 votes to break a filibuster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first confrontation over the education agenda in an election year, Democrats blocked the Republicans' centerpiece proposal today, with each party questioning the other's commitment to schoolchildren.</p>
        <p>By a strictly party-line vote, Democrats, including one who is a chief co-sponsor of the bill to provide parents with tax breaks for education costs, were able to continue a filibuster. The vote was 55 to 44 to end the filibuster, but it takes 60 votes to break a filibuster.</p>
        <p>Immediately after the vote, the two Senate leaders said that they expected to work out their disagreements and would try to bring the bill to establish education savings accounts to the floor next week. If the two sides remain at loggerheads, there will be another effort on Tuesday to cut off the filibuster. The bill, a version of which has already passed in the House, is supported by several Democrats, but President Clinton has threatened to veto it.</p>
        <p>The dispute centered on the decision this week by Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader, to limit the number of amendments -- many of which he says are irrelevant to education -- on what is technically a tax bill.</p>
        <p>Outraged over the tactic, Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the Democratic leader, rallied support for the filibuster among his colleagues on the ground that Mr. Lott was simply trying to stifle Democratic education initiatives. He even convinced one of the bill's chief co-sponsors, Senator Robert G. Torricelli, Democrat of New Jersey, to vote to block his own legislation today.</p>
        <p>Senator Paul Coverdell, the Georgia Republican who wrote the bill,  criticized Democrats for wanting too much. ''This is not a dream list,'' he said after the vote.</p>
        <p>Education is a favorite topic on the campaign trail for lawmakers who know that it captivates voters and highlights the two parties' philosophical differences. For decades, Democrats have waved the education banner, using the topic successfully as one of their party's strongest platforms. Hoping to do the same, Congressional Republicans have recently seized on the education issue,  pushing a number of initiatives in both chambers.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clinton has said he will veto their showcase proposal on the ground that it favors wealthier parents, who can use the savings to pay for private and parochial schools. Poor parents of public school children, the President maintains, would scarcely benefit.</p>
        <p>In a recent study, the Joint Committee on Taxation in Congress found that the bill would most benefit parents with children in private schools. For the average family with a child in public school, the tax benefit would be minuscule, $7 in five years, the committee concluded.</p>
        <p>The bill would raise the limits on annual contributions to existing education savings accounts from $500 to $2,000 a year. The money would grow with interest. Withdrawals, as long as they are used for education expenses, such as tuition, books and tutoring, would be tax-free. Parents could use the money for children in kindergarten through 12th grade, as well as for college. Supporters say that 14 million families would benefit from the expansion of the savings accounts.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Coverdell and Mr. Torricelli say the accounts would give those parents disillusioned with public schools an alternative and encourage the parents of public school students to save and help them pay for their school-related expenses.</p>
        <p>''It is true that some statistically insignificant number, several thousands of families would use their accounts, with their money in it, to change schools, from a public to a private school,'' Mr. Coverdell said. ''But that is their total point and concern of the opposition.''</p>
        <p>The bill has several Democratic provisions, including one to spur school construction through private bonds and another to make pre-paid tuition plans tax-free. But Democrats said they want to offer more proposals to address class sizes, child care and early childhood development.</p>
        <p>Despite the veto threat, members from both parties say they have been eagerly anticipating what could be the only full-blown education debate of the year on the Senate floor. If nothing else, it will give senators a chance to discuss their differing positions on education: Giving parents an alternative to public schools or keeping the focus strictly on public schools.</p>
        <p>''Education has become the focus of a national debate,'' Mr. Torricelli said. ''I think Republicans recognize the problem. The Democratic Party is overwhelmingly identified with the issue of education. And Republicans ignore it at their peril.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
