<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FILM IN REVIEW</title>
    <meta content="RV011036" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Leading Man, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0D81638F933A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FILM IN REVIEW</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews film The Leading Man (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'The Leading Man'  Directed by John Duigan  99 minutes</p>
        <p>Felix Webb, arguably Britain's  foremost living playwright, has three beautiful children, a fine home and Elena, a lovely wife at the breaking point.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'The Leading Man'  Directed by John Duigan  99 minutes</p>
        <p>Felix Webb, arguably Britain's  foremost living playwright, has three beautiful children, a fine home and Elena, a lovely wife at the breaking point.</p>
        <p>With a gleaming pair of scissors, she angrily snips his neckties; she snips his hair while he sleeps and heaven knows what she intends to snip next.</p>
        <p>The cause of her fury? Felix (Lambert Wilson) has a comely young mistress, Hilary Rule (Thandie Newton), pressing him for marriage while he is advancing her career by arguing her case for a role in his latest play, ''Hit Man,'' a drama of politics and morality, which is about to enter rehearsals in London.</p>
        <p>Between the tortured women in his life, his sensitive children and the demands of production, Felix is a man under stress. Enter Robin Grange (Jon Bon Jovi), the handsome young devil from Hollywood who is to play the title role in ''Hit Man.'' Robin causes teen-age girls to drop their jaws, while their bold, leggy older sisters drop by his spacious apartment after he has accepted their invitations to inscribe their taut thighs with his phone number.</p>
        <p>Robin, a self-described mercenary, makes Felix an offer: In exchange for expenses and perhaps the return of the favor in the future, Robin will seduce Elena (Anna Galiena), thereby leveling the playing field in the Webb household, lowering tensions and clearing the way for divorce.</p>
        <p>So begins ''The Leading Man,'' a densely plotted drama of domestic and backstage duplicity, directed by John Duigan (''Flirting,'' ''Sirens'') and written by Virginia Duigan, his sister, in her screenwriting debut under a grant from the Women's Film Fund in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the delicate chemistry of success eludes ''The Leading Man,'' which is watchable without being gripping. The London locations beckon; the sets, backstage and in various homes and pubs,  catch the eye; the supporting cast,  with such accomplished performers as David Warner, Barry Humphries and Patricia Hodge, provides mischievously good company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Galiena and Ms. Newton give convincing performances, but Mr. Bon Jovi, the rock star, seems more smug than seductive in the crucial role of Robin, who has an agenda of his own as he presses his favors on both Elena and Hilary. And the conflicted Felix seems a bit too bright and a little too short on passion to let matters proceed as far as they do before he realizes the full toll of his pact with the handsome young devil.</p>
        <p>''The Leading Man'' is rated R (under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes partial nudity, sexual foreplay and some strong language.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
