<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 4-Lane Highway to Love (It's Easy on the Feet)</title>
    <meta content="Y10ROA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/10/international/asia/10ROAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1526052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Machangping Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guizhou Province (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guixin Highway (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DA173FF933A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 4-Lane Highway to Love (It's Easy on the Feet)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A 4-Lane Highway to Love (Its Easy on the Feet)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>MACHANGPING, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China has created network of highways that totaled 875,000 miles two years ago and is projected to reach 1.06 million miles in 2010; Guixin Highway, which opened several years ago, illustrates how national ambitions do not always translate into local realities; few people in Guizhou Province can afford cars, so broad superhighway is being used more by villagers on foot than by cars or trucks; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every morning, Liu Qianlin and his wife, Guo Yuanhong, both 29, load up with cabbage, beans and chives from their farm and hop onto the new Guixin Highway to head to work. As they weave around the lush landscape of tiered rice paddies against spindly mountains in this slice of southern China, they merge seamlessly with the rush-hour convoy of farmers and construction workers.</p>
        <p>The trip, from their village of Xiapu to the town here, takes an hour, though the distance is only three miles, the asphalt is perfectly smooth and traffic jams are unheard of. But such is life when a new road is used by local residents mainly for walking, not driving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new Guixin Highway in China is used by local residents mainly for walking, not driving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every morning, Liu Qianlin and his wife, Guo Yuanhong, both 29, load up with cabbage, beans and chives from their farm and hop onto the new Guixin Highway to head to work. As they weave around the lush landscape of tiered rice paddies against spindly mountains in this slice of southern China, they merge seamlessly with the rush-hour convoy of farmers and construction workers.</p>
        <p>The trip, from their village of Xiapu to the town here, takes an hour, though the distance is only three miles, the asphalt is perfectly smooth and traffic jams are unheard of. But such is life when a new road is used by local residents mainly for walking, not driving.</p>
        <p>In recent years, transportation has become a near-obsession in China. What the official New China News Agency calls a ''nationwide fever of highway construction'' has created a network of highways that totaled 875,000 miles two years ago and is projected to reach 1.06 million miles in 2010. In congested cities like Beijing and Shanghai, the number of personal vehicles has soared.</p>
        <p>In the rugged west, Beijing has been pumping billions of dollars into road, railway, pipeline and water projects, seeing roads especially as a magic bullet to reduce poverty and connect more rural communities to social services. A legion of newly minted highways, tracks and bridges are altering the look, feel and prospects of many locales.</p>
        <p>But the Guixin Highway, which opened a couple of years ago, illustrates how national ambitions do not always translate into local realities.</p>
        <p>In Guizhou, the country's poorest province, Guiyang, the capital, and Kaili, about three hours to the east, teem with cars, new skyscrapers and department stores. But in the villages few people can afford cars.</p>
        <p>Farmers and workers walk along the clean asphalt shoulder of the four-lane highway. They carry scythes and straw baskets, fruits and vegetables on wooden shoulder poles. They haul heavy equipment, overnight bags, infants.</p>
        <p>There are occasional trucks or tour buses.</p>
        <p>Every day, residents estimate, as many as 100 or 200 people travel a three-mile stretch between the villages of Xiapu and Wangjiayuan, and the town of Machangping. The number triples on the one day a week or so that Machangping's sprawling farmer's market offers other goods, like trinkets and crafts.</p>
        <p>Many residents remain impressed, even intimidated, by the highway, preferring to call it the ''Old Eagle's Nest Road,'' after the dirt road it replaced. And even though the highway has little connection to the villages it slices through -- no rest stops, no roadside businesses, no signs advertising local attractions -- most residents have only good things to say about how the highway has saved them time and money.</p>
        <p>Lei Zhirong and his wife, Xu Huixiang, said the road to Machangping, over tricky and mountainous terrain, used to take two hours. Now it is a one-hour jaunt.</p>
        <p>''It's better for my feet,'' said Mr. Lei, who takes the highway at least twice a day to get to his fields. ''More comfortable.''</p>
        <p>A young mother, her ailing infant strapped onto her back, said she was taking her child to the clinic in Machangping for some shots. The hour walk each way saved her the round-trip bus fare of 40 cents.</p>
        <p>The traffic fluctuates. Between 5:45 p.m. and 6 p.m. on a recent Tuesday, there were four trucks, one bus, two cars, one bicycle and seven pedestrians. But that volume could not compare to the numbers from the next morning.</p>
        <p>At 4:30 a.m., two people could be heard chatting in the dark. An hour later, in a light rain, there were clusters of three, four, five pedestrians. A car came through every 5 or 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>By 6 a.m., there were perhaps 20 people within a couple of hundred yards of one another. The crowd passed a half a dozen coal miners on a reverse commute from their overnight shift. A smattering of trucks and tour buses rumbled by.</p>
        <p>Accidents are few. But ''whenever a car hits someone, everyone will come out from the villages and surround the car,'' said a miner, Li Zhihua.</p>
        <p>The miners passed Mr. Liu and Ms. Guo, the young Xiapu farmers, on their morning walk to market. He was carrying a shoulder pole with two straw baskets stocked with 50 pounds of produce. She was carrying the weight measure and other tools of their trade. They were walking very fast.</p>
        <p>''It's not tiring,'' Mr. Liu said. ''We're used to it.''</p>
        <p>They arrived at Machangping's market, around 7 a.m. and found supreme luck. They sold everything by 7:45 a.m. -- their earliest time ever -- for a total of about $4.</p>
        <p>It was time to hit the road again, to return to the fields. But the commute home is usually more leisurely.</p>
        <p>''If we run into friends, then we'll stop and talk,'' Ms. Guo said. ''We can take our time on the way back.''</p>
        <p>Machangping Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
