<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Is Counting on Month's Delay to Dull Criticism of Nominee for Surgeon General</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="743425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGEON GENERAL (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEHL, DOUGLAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, HENRY W JR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D9103AF936A25751C0A963958260" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Is Counting on Month's Delay to Dull Criticism of Nominee for Surgeon General</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEHL, DOUGLAS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The White House will not ask the Senate to begin hearings on the nomination of Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. as Surgeon General until at least mid-March, a timetable that Administration officials believe will leave the nominee in better shape to confront his critics.</p>
        <p>The four-week delay was described by White House aides today as necessary to let the Federal Bureau of Investigation complete its check into Dr. Foster's background. But they also made clear that they were not at all unhappy about such a waiting period.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The White House will not ask the Senate to begin hearings on the nomination of Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. as Surgeon General until at least mid-March, a timetable that Administration officials believe will leave the nominee in better shape to confront his critics.</p>
        <p>The four-week delay was described by White House aides today as necessary to let the Federal Bureau of Investigation complete its check into Dr. Foster's background. But they also made clear that they were not at all unhappy about such a waiting period.</p>
        <p>Indeed, aides to President Clinton made clear that they believed that Dr. Foster's prospects for winning Senate confirmation would improve with time. Some said Dr. Foster, a 61-year-old obstetrician-gynecologist, would benefit by gaining distance from episodes that had raised questions about his candor concerning abortions he has performed. These aides suggested that the lag would also help the White House portray his Senate critics as captives of the anti-abortion movement.</p>
        <p>No Republicans and only a handful of Senate Democrats have voiced support for Dr. Foster since President Clinton announced the nomination nearly two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Today, the White House chief of staff, Leon E. Panetta, said he believed that more senators were now "keeping an open mind" about Dr. Foster, who has acknowledged performing abortions but who has also given conflicting accounts of their numbers. Mr. Panetta said a White House-orchestrated campaign in which Dr. Foster sought to defend his record had "helped turn some of the momentum around."</p>
        <p>That view was echoed by Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the Democratic leader, who said that he and other supporters were "becoming more upbeat each day."</p>
        <p>While the White House has not yet formally sent its nomination of Dr. Foster to the Senate, officials emphasized that the President was determined to do so. They also said that they would not press the F.B.I. to hurry its background check, which must be completed before confirmation hearings can begin.</p>
        <p>As Dr. Foster prepared to pay courtesy calls in the Senate on Wednesday, White House officials said they would take their time trying to build support. They said they would schedule no more than six meetings between Dr. Foster and individual senators this week.</p>
        <p>And even as he begins his door-to-door quest for more support, Dr. Foster's only visits on Wednesday will be with two declared champions: Mr. Daschle and Senator Patty Murray, Democrat of Washington. The next day Dr.Foster is to move on to meet individually with Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts, the ranking Democrat on the committee that will consider the nomination, and with the committee's chairman, Senator Nancy Landon Kassebaum, Republican of Kansas, who has criticized the White House handling of the nomination.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Senator Kassebaum said today that she had requested "a very candid and open discussion" with Dr. Foster and that the White House had agreed. Several Republican senators have said that Dr. Foster's performance of abortions should disqualify him as Surgeon General, but Senator Kassebaum, who supports abortion rights, has said she will withhold judgment until after the meeting. But she has expressed anger at what she says was misleading information initially provided to her about Dr. Foster's abortion record.</p>
        <p>As the White House gathered representatives of several dozen medical, educational and business groups today for a meeting in which Dr. Foster asked for their backing, aides made clear that President Clinton would take the fight to the Senate, even if his nominee might be defeated. "This is a nomination you take to a vote," Mr. Panetta said. "I think that's important."</p>
        <p>The team that has been working to rescue the nomination is headed by Erskine Bowles, the deputy chief of staff, and includes Patrick Griffin, the President's liaison to Congress, and two other top-ranking White House officials who are working nearly full time in the effort, Mark D. Gearan, the communications director, and John Podesta, the staff secretary. They have come to be known within the White House as "the Dalmatians" in recognition of their being called upon to fight political fires ignited by the Whitewater affair and other crises.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
