<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="28QNA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/28/living/28QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1305373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DA1F30F93BA15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Delphinium Blues</p>
        <p>Q.  A year ago, I bought five yellow delphinium seedlings at a plant sale. They didn't grow large or bloom, but they seemed healthy, and I thought they would flower this year. Instead, they all died. Delphiniums usually do well here in western Connecticut (my others are fine). Do you have any idea what happened? Is the problem likely to spread?</p>
        <p>A.  Winter is what happened. And although it won't go away for good, it is no threat to those delphiniums that are most commonly planted.</p>
        <p>Whether they are tall Pacific hybrids, midsize Connecticut Yankees or short grandiflorum, whether they are light or dark blue, purple, pink or white, they are all hardy even when temperatures dip well below zero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Delphinium Blues</p>
        <p>Q.  A year ago, I bought five yellow delphinium seedlings at a plant sale. They didn't grow large or bloom, but they seemed healthy, and I thought they would flower this year. Instead, they all died. Delphiniums usually do well here in western Connecticut (my others are fine). Do you have any idea what happened? Is the problem likely to spread?</p>
        <p>A.  Winter is what happened. And although it won't go away for good, it is no threat to those delphiniums that are most commonly planted.</p>
        <p>Whether they are tall Pacific hybrids, midsize Connecticut Yankees or short grandiflorum, whether they are light or dark blue, purple, pink or white, they are all hardy even when temperatures dip well below zero.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the yellow one, Delphinium semibarbatum, also known as D. zalil, is a more tender creature. Temperatures below 10 degrees will do it in. If it's any consolation, the yellowness doesn't stay constant from plant to plant. Some flowers are a wan cream color, others have an orange cast.</p>
        <p>If you want to try again, treat the plant as an annual. Start fresh seeds indoors in December. Give the seedlings bright sun, moderate temperatures (55 to 65 degrees) and monthly doses of half-strength fertilizer. Make sure they have plenty of root room.</p>
        <p>Established plants set out in early May should send up spikes of loosely packed flowers in summer.</p>
        <p>I have been able to find only one source for seeds, Thompson &amp; Morgan, P.O. Box 1308, Jackson, N.J. 08527; (800) 274-7333; free catalog.</p>
        <p>Beet Bonanza</p>
        <p>Q.  I am having trouble planting beets correctly. Last year, they were too crowded, and thinning them took forever. This spring I spaced the seeds much farther apart, almost two inches. There are a few empty spots, but in general, the plants are still as thick as weeds. How do I prevent this?</p>
        <p>A.  You don't, because beet fruits are built like pineapples, as clusters of single-seeded units.</p>
        <p>They don't come apart even after they dry, which means the things in the seed packet are clusters, not separate seeds.</p>
        <p>Not every seed in every cluster will sprout (when none do, you get empty spots), but usually enough come through to make thinning unavoidable.</p>
        <p>Mulch Invaders</p>
        <p>Q.  What are those little sprouts that are growing all over my new mulch? My husband thinks something has infested it. I think the problem is related to the massive pollen surge we have had here in Chatham, N.J., and that the sprouts are maple seedlings. Any ideas?</p>
        <p>A.  Armies of Norway maples are indeed invading many areas, but even these aggressive spreaders have to start with seeds; pollen alone doesn't generate anything but allergies.</p>
        <p>And baby maples develop maple leaves right after the initial pair of seed leaves has fully opened. They are a plague, but they aren't confusing. You know them when you see them.</p>
        <p>If the mulch is straw, your sprouts are probably oats. Stir the straw around to uproot them, and let them perish in place.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, there is no telling what the sprouts might be. Whatever they are, it is unlikely that pulling them up one by one will solve the problem. It would be better to remove the mulch and start over with fresh.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
