<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dreams Of Glory Unraveling In Chaos</title>
    <meta content="30KAKU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/30/books/30kaku.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1630952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Naipaul, V S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Magic Seeds (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Naipaul, V S</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Magic Seeds (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA103EF933A05752C1A9629C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dreams Of Glory Unraveling In Chaos</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dreams of Glory Unraveling in Chaos</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews book Magic Seeds by V S Naipaul; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Magic Seeds'  By V.S. Naipaul  280 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Magic Seeds,'' the title of the latest novel by the Nobel laureate V.S. Naipaul, refers to the beanstalk seeds for which fairy tale characters trade away their livelihood; the seeds sprout into a giant beanstalk that leads to the palace of an ogre, who will threaten to wreak destruction upon the puny humans who have dared disturb his peace. In Mr. Naipaul's telling, the magic seeds represent the dreams of revolution planted in the souls of the poor and the lost -- seeds that will sprout not into promises of glorious liberation, but into a nightmare of blood and chaos and upheaval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The protagonist of V. S. Naipaul' s novel allows himself to be bullied by his strident sister into joining a Maoist revolutionary group in India.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Magic Seeds'  By V.S. Naipaul  280 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Magic Seeds,'' the title of the latest novel by the Nobel laureate V.S. Naipaul, refers to the beanstalk seeds for which fairy tale characters trade away their livelihood; the seeds sprout into a giant beanstalk that leads to the palace of an ogre, who will threaten to wreak destruction upon the puny humans who have dared disturb his peace. In Mr. Naipaul's telling, the magic seeds represent the dreams of revolution planted in the souls of the poor and the lost -- seeds that will sprout not into promises of glorious liberation, but into a nightmare of blood and chaos and upheaval.</p>
        <p>Although ''Magic Seeds'' is meant to be the sequel to Mr. Naipaul's 2001 novel ''Half a Life,'' the two novels could not be more different. ''Half a Life'' was a keenly observed, richly imagined portrait of a writer named Willie Chandran, whose rootless life served as a mirror for the author's vision of the 20th century as an age of exile, dislocation and postcolonial confusion. ''Magic Seeds,'' in contrast, is less a full-fledged novel than a didactic thesis featuring characters who deliver speeches instead of conversation, and who seem less like real people than mouthpieces for the author's own sour opinions about everything from colonialism to multiculturalism to the English welfare state. The book should have been written as a series of essays or op-ed pieces, not poorly disguised as a would-be work of fiction.</p>
        <p>Willie himself hardly seems like the same man we met in ''Half a Life.'' Yes, he's still infuriatingly passive and adrift, but the author's sympathetic understanding of Willie's crippling sense of alienation has been replaced by ill-tempered disdain. In fact, Mr. Naipaul now appears to regard his hero as a fool: a stupid, self-absorbed idiot who not only allows himself to be bullied by his strident sister into joining a Maoist revolutionary group in India, but who remains with this group for years, despite his almost immediate realization that he has ''fallen among the wrong people,'' joined ''the wrong revolution.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Naipaul has frequently written about his impatience with third-world revolutionaries in thrall to borrowed ideologies and radical chic Westerners with round-trip tickets to troubled lands, and he tries to attach to Willie's story a cut-and-dried moral about these sorts of people. ''It is wrong to have an ideal view of the world,'' he has Willie think at the end of the novel. ''That's where the mischief starts. That's where everything starts unraveling.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Naipaul also tells us that Willie initially decided to become a revolutionary because his sister convinced him that devotion to such a cause would be ennobling, and he found that his new mission made him feel superior to ''everything around him.'' In other words, ideals for Willie are simply illusions designed to feed his own ego; they have virtually nothing to do with a larger moral or social vision of the world.</p>
        <p>The other revolutionaries Willie meets in India have similarly petty reasons for joining the ill-defined antigovernment guerrilla group. These people all seem meant to serve as illustrations of the novel's thesis that personal problems -- neurosis, resentment or out-and-out psychosis -- drive individuals to join political movements. One is a former math student who became obsessed with correcting Einstein, and who after losing his university job ''dreamed of destroying the world.'' Another is a killer who likes ''being important'' and who likes ''browbeating villagers.'' And a third is a former student who says that ''sexual rage'' led him to join the movement.</p>
        <p>Willie's years among the revolutionaries are depicted in highly perfunctory terms. There are few of the piercing details that have animated Mr. Naipaul's best writings about distant places in the past; few conjurings of mood and place and time. Instead, we are given a tired litany of repetitious scenes: Willie and his comrades waiting for orders in small, foul-smelling rooms; Willie and his comrades engaging in pointless, random killings; and Willie and his comrades trying desultorily to cover their tracks before they move on to their next meaningless assignment.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Willie turns himself in, is charged as an accessory to the murder of three men and is sentenced to 10 years in prison. In a particularly preposterous development, he is granted a special amnesty, when the authorities realize that he is no ordinary guerrilla, but a writer -- ''a pioneer of modern Indian writing'' -- who many years ago published a book in England.</p>
        <p>In short order Willie returns to London, where he is soon safely ensconced in the guestroom of his friend Roger's house. Willie begins an affair with Roger's wife, Perdita, starts hanging out with Roger's rich friends and quickly acquires a job at an architectural magazine. The people Willie meets in London are every bit as loathsome as the revolutionaries he met in India. They are all narcissistic snobs, obsessed with status and class, and their own agendas of revenge and oneupsmanship.</p>
        <p>In fact ugly, contemptuous remarks pop out of the mouths -- like small, poisonous toads -- of all of the characters in this book. The revolutionaries condescendingly describe the peasants as ''cricket people, matchstick people,'' whose ''minds have gone after the centuries of malnourishment.'' And the rich Londoners say things like, ''most people in this country have a streak of commonness.'' Their contempt for others makes these characters seem like bitter, bigoted caricatures. And Mr. Naipaul's contempt for all the people he has created in this novel makes for a mean, stingy book -- a book full of judgmental pronouncements and free-floating rage, and sadly bereft of insight, compassion or wisdom.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
