<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freud Would Recognize This Family</title>
    <meta content="27LYALL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/weekinreview/27lyall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050306T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1653210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Growing Up Royal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Charles, Prince of Wales</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elizabeth Ii, Queen of Great Britain</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diana, Princess of Wales (1961-97)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parker Bowles, Camilla</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Charles, Prince of Wales</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bowles, Camilla Parker</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6D8143DF934A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freud Would Recognize This Family</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Freud Would Recognize This Family</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Lyall article notes that Queen Elizabeth will skip Prince Charles's wedding; says their relationship has been uneasy since childhood; holds that Elizabeth has been upset at his treatment of his first wife, Diana, and at his decades-long relationship with Camilla Parker Bowles because of harm she feels romance has done to monarchy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are many possible explanations for Queen Elizabeth's decision to skip the wedding of her eldest son in April. Maybe she dislikes civil ceremonies. Maybe she is distressed by the prospect of crossing the street, like some sort of common person, for the service.</p>
        <p>Or maybe she and Charles just don't get along.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much of what the British royal family does can be attributed to timeless family stresses like hurt feelings, sibling rivalry and parental disapproval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are many possible explanations for Queen Elizabeth's decision to skip the wedding of her eldest son in April. Maybe she dislikes civil ceremonies. Maybe she is distressed by the prospect of crossing the street, like some sort of common person, for the service.</p>
        <p>Or maybe she and Charles just don't get along.</p>
        <p>While the British royal family's behavior is strictly prescribed by precedent, law and the (unwritten) English constitution, much of what its members actually do can be attributed to timeless family stresses like hurt feelings, sibling rivalry and parental disapproval.</p>
        <p>This is nothing new; things were, in fact, much more extreme in the old days. Queen Elizabeth I imprisoned and executed her own cousin, Mary Queen of Scots. Queen Victoria took such a dim view of her extravagant and hedonistic son, the future Edward VII, that she refused to grant him any political powers, even though she lived in widowed seclusion and made him take her place at most royal occasions.</p>
        <p>As early as the 14th century, questionable royal companions were causing familial trouble. Edward of Caernarfon, England's first Prince of Wales (later King Edward II), provoked endless grief over his friendship with the dissipated Piers Gaveston, a foppishly handsome young squire who, rumor had it, was his lover. His manly father, King Edward I (the Hammer of the Scots), did not approve. Grabbing his son's hair and tearing it out in tufts , Edward sent Gaveston into exile.</p>
        <p>The way Charles and his remote mother have dealt with each other has not been as bad as all that. Elizabeth does not appear to be the hair-seizing type. But their relationship has been uneasy in a more modern sort of way and dates, as these things always do, to childhood.</p>
        <p>A shy and lonely child raised mostly by governesses and nannies, Charles celebrated his fifth birthday without his parents (he was in London; they were in one of their out-of-town houses). Less than a week later, they left Britain, and their son, for a six-month trip abroad.</p>
        <p>The queen has always deferred to her stern husband, Prince Philip, in family matters, and, at least in Charles's version, Philip has always considered him a spineless wimp in need of toughening up. When Charles wrote plaintive letters home describing the ''absolute hell'' of boarding school -- where other students ridiculed his ears, hit him with pillows so he couldn't sleep, and erupted into choruses of slurping, sucking noises when boys tried to befriend him -- his father just urged him to buck up, stop moaning and take it on the chin.</p>
        <p>Later, Charles tried to gain public sympathy by disclosing these details to his biographer, Jonathan Dimbleby. But his parents saw the subsequent book, ''The Prince of Wales,'' as a shockingly whiny betrayal of the upper-class principle that one never reveals one's feelings (to the extent that one has any) in public.</p>
        <p>Charles, whose reputation as a self-pitying introvert only grew as a result of the book, has struggled for years to gain his mother's acceptance. The queen was reportedly upset at his treatment of his first wife, Diana, the Princess of Wales; she has been even more upset at his decades-long relationship with Camilla Parker Bowles, first his mistress, then his live-in lover, and now his fiancée, in large part because of the harm she feels the romance has done to the monarchy.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Elizabeth skipped her son's 50th birthday party, because Mrs. Parker Bowles was there. Four years later, Charles gingerly broached the subject to his mother at dinner. ''The queen said she never wanted to talk about that wicked woman and wanted nothing to do with her,'' a ''highly placed confidant of the prince'' told the Daily Mail columnist Richard Kay. ''He was devastated.'' Meetings since then have been one degree above frosty. The first time Elizabeth agreed to be in the same place as her son's lover -- a party for the exiled King of Greece -- she put out her hand, Mrs. Parker Bowles curtsied, and the queen moved on without saying a word.</p>
        <p>Like a youth whose parents make his live-in girlfriend sleep in a separate bedroom when they visit, Charles, who is 56 years old, has since then occasionally been allowed to bring his 57-year-old paramour to royal functions -- but only if they don't sit together.</p>
        <p>Nor has the queen met recently with Camilla, who, after all, is the bride; she seems determined to hold the wedding reception (which she is paying for) her way. It is hardly on a par with sending Camilla into exile. But the most recent rumor to trickle out of the leaky royal palaces is that, thwarting the couple's dream of having a lavish sit-down dinner, the queen plans to hold a modest buffet and serve finger food.</p>
        <p>Growing Up Royal</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 6, 2005, Sunday  An article last Sunday about strains between Prince Charles and his mother, Queen Elizabeth II, misstated the year in which she failed to attend his 50th-birthday party. It was 1998, not 1994. The article also misstated the relationship between Queen Elizabeth I and Mary Queen of Scots. They were half-sisters, not cousins.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 13, 2005, Sunday  An article on Feb. 27 about strains between Prince Charles and his mother, Queen Elizabeth II, misstated the year in which she failed to attend his 50th-birthday party. It was 1998, not 1994. A correction on that point in this space last Sunday mistakenly retracted the Feb. 27 article's statement of the relationship between Queen Elizabeth I and Mary, Queen of Scots. The article was correct: they were cousins, not half-sisters. (Elizabeth I was a half-sister of Queen Mary I of England.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 6, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about strains between Prince Charles and his mother, Queen Elizabeth II, misstated the year in which she failed to attend his 50th-birthday party. It was 1998, not 1994. The article also misstated the relationship between Queen Elizabeth I and Mary Queen of Scots. They were half-sisters, not cousins.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: March 13, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 27 about strains between Prince Charles and his mother, Queen Elizabeth II, misstated the year in which she failed to attend his 50th-birthday party. It was 1998, not 1994. A correction on that point in this space last Sunday mistakenly retracted the Feb. 27 article's statement of the relationship between Queen Elizabeth I and Mary, Queen of Scots. The article was correct: they were cousins, not half-sisters. (Elizabeth I was a half-sister of Queen Mary I of England.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
