<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joint Tenderness; * Fever; * Discolored Toes</title>
    <meta content="WLN115411" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/27/magazine/27DIAGNOSIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1653033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 2-27-05: DIAGNOSIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanders, Lisa (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Diagnosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DC163DF934A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joint Tenderness; * Fever; * Discolored Toes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Joint Tenderness, Fever, Discolored Toes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Sanders, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanders, Lisa (Dr)</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diagnosis article on symptoms that seem to indicate trauma or frostbite, but actually are condition called pernio, caused when body overreacts to cold; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. Symptoms  A ''13-year-old with swollen toes'' read the hasty scrawl on the chart outside the exam-room door. The pediatrician glanced through it quickly, knocked and then entered the room. The patient sat with her head resting on her mother's shoulder. Tall and slender, she had the look of an athlete. Her face was tan, but her eyes looked heavy and tired. She wore a red U.S.C. sweatshirt and soft flannel pants -- appropriate enough given the cool Northern California winter. But on her feet, flimsy sandals revealed her bloated, purple toes.</p>
        <p>''Whoa,'' the doctor exclaimed. ''What's with the toes?'' He pulled up a chair and gave her feet a good, hard look. ''That looks like frostbite. Where have you been?'' Nowhere, they assured him. The family went skiing two weeks earlier, but this problem started only a few days ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This young athlete didn't recall injuring herself on the court or the ski slopes. What could it be  if not trauma or frostbite?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. Symptoms  A ''13-year-old with swollen toes'' read the hasty scrawl on the chart outside the exam-room door. The pediatrician glanced through it quickly, knocked and then entered the room. The patient sat with her head resting on her mother's shoulder. Tall and slender, she had the look of an athlete. Her face was tan, but her eyes looked heavy and tired. She wore a red U.S.C. sweatshirt and soft flannel pants -- appropriate enough given the cool Northern California winter. But on her feet, flimsy sandals revealed her bloated, purple toes.</p>
        <p>''Whoa,'' the doctor exclaimed. ''What's with the toes?'' He pulled up a chair and gave her feet a good, hard look. ''That looks like frostbite. Where have you been?'' Nowhere, they assured him. The family went skiing two weeks earlier, but this problem started only a few days ago.</p>
        <p>At first, her toes were just sore and slightly swollen, the patient explained. ''I play a lot of soccer, and I've injured my toes before, so I wasn't that worried.'' But the day before, when she removed her shoes after volleyball practice, they were purple. This morning they were so tender she couldn't even put on her sneakers.</p>
        <p>The doctor grinned, revealing a dimple in one cheek. ''Don't you think you'd remember if someone drove a truck over your foot?'' he asked. The girl smiled. ''Did you fall or do anything to your feet during your volleyball game?'' She shook her head.</p>
        <p>She had been feeling feverish and achy for a few days, though nothing serious enough to keep her from school. She had also recently noticed some pain in her right hip. The pediatrician, Dr. Wolffe Nadoolman, asked the patient to move to the examining table, then watched as she walked the couple of steps and boosted herself effortlessly onto the waist-high table. Her head, neck, heart and abdomen were completely normal. She had no rashes or swollen lymph nodes. She had some pain when he pressed on the joint where the femur connected to her right hip and when her leg was rotated outward.</p>
        <p>2. Investigation  At last, the doctor turned his attention to her strangely discolored toes. Both feet were cool to the touch. On the left, the four smaller toes were the color of eggplant, then darkened so their tips were almost black. Where the toes joined the foot there was a band of deep red. The rest of the skin on her foot was normal. The line between the purple and red was sharp -- almost as if her toes had been dipped in ink. On the knuckle of the big toe there was a dark nodule the size of a dime. There were smaller nodules on the second and third toes as well. The right foot was much less affected, but it had some swelling, and one toe looked bruised.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nadoolman sat back in his chair and ran a hand through his thinning blond hair. The dark toes combined with a fever and sore hip were worrisome. Were they connected or coincidental? His first thought had been frostbite. He had never seen a patient with it, but her purple digits were right out of a documentary he'd seen about a mountain expedition gone bad. Yet he couldn't make it fit -- the ski trip was too long ago. Her toes looked badly bruised, so trauma was certainly possible. But with this much damage, it would have to have been a significant injury -- one that most people would remember.</p>
        <p>What about her fever? Certain infections will sometimes produce this type of lesion in response to cold; mononucleosis can do it, and some pneumonias, too. But she didn't have symptoms of either. She had a painful hip -- if she had an infection in that joint, could tiny pieces of infected tissue have escaped into her bloodstream? Septic emboli, as they're called, can block off the smallest blood vessels and cause this kind of blackening. But embolic lesions are usually patchier than this, and her hip was not as painful as he would expect if there was active infection there. Still, overlooking this type of infection could be fatal.</p>
        <p>There are also a number of serious systemic diseases, as varied as lupus, leukemia and hepatitis C, that can cause this injury. In each of these cases, the body overproduces cells or proteins that can, in turn, damage the small blood vessels and cause this bruised appearance.</p>
        <p>He ordered blood tests to tell him if there was an infection or a systemic disease, an X-ray of her foot to see if it was trauma and one of her hip to look for an infection. In the meantime, he started her on antibiotics. Before she left, he took a pen and drew a thin line between the dark toes and the normal part of her foot so that he could tell if the disease, whatever it turned out to be, was spreading. Then he arranged to visit his patient at home the next day, Sunday, since the office was closed.</p>
        <p>That evening, Nadoolman reviewed the results of the tests he'd ordered. Both X-rays were normal. The blood tests were unremarkable, with one exception: her white-blood-cell count was slightly low. Normally, an infection causes the white count to go up. In very significant infections, though, it can actually decrease as fighter cells are destroyed. But in that case, there's usually an increase in immature white cells -- known as bands -- as the body ramps up its defenses. This patient had no evidence of more bands.</p>
        <p>The next afternoon he paid his house call. The patient looked better than she had the day before: her eyes were bright, and she laughed easily at his banter -- an unofficial but useful gauge. Her toes were unchanged. Her fever and aches had disappeared, but it remained a mystery whether they had something to do with her foot injury. He told her to continue taking the antibiotics and to follow up at the office the next day.</p>
        <p>3. Resolution  As Dr. Nadoolman drove away, he considered the case once more. She looked far too healthy to have the kind of severe infection that causes the white count to go down. So what did that leave? A cold injury? He still couldn't figure out how to connect the ski trip with what she had now. He headed to the hospital library. He needed to know more about injuries caused by cold. One in particular came to mind: pernio, also known by its medieval-era moniker, chilblains, from the Anglo-Saxon for cold sore. Historically, this was a torment of infantrymen. These days it's common in skiers. But could pernio really take this much time to show up? As he read, he felt the sudden thrill of recognition: ''Pernio lesions have an insidious onset,'' appearing ''several days or weeks after exposure to wetness and cold.''</p>
        <p>When the patient arrived the next day, she was using crutches, but otherwise she felt fine. When the doctor described pernio to the girl and her mother, they nodded in agreement. The dermatologist he referred them to agreed -- she had pernio. The body's normal response to cold is to limit blood flow to the extremities in order to preserve the warmth of the inner organs. In some individuals, the body overreacts; the vessels clamp down, and the amount of blood that gets through to nourish the tissue is inadequate. Ultimately that leads to pain, swelling and a bruised appearance. Her toes would heal in a few weeks, the dermatologist told them, but only if she bundled up. His prescription was simple -- wool socks and warm clothes. Having had pernio once, however, she would be at risk for it again. Skiing was probably not going to be her sport.</p>
        <p>When I spoke to the patient a couple of days ago, she was no longer on crutches and had a large supply of socks. The purple had faded, and though her toes remained a little tender, they were getting better. She had given up skiing for the season. I asked about next winter. ''Oh, who knows?'' she told me. ''That's a long way off.'' Then she left for volleyball practice.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 2-27-05: DIAGNOSIS If you have a solved case to share with Dr. Sanders, you can e-mail her at LSanders@pol.net. She is unable to respond to all e-mail messages.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">If you have a solved case to share with Dr. Sanders, you can e-mail her at LSanders@pol.net. She is unable to respond to all e-mail messages.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
