<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scream-Along Punk That's Enough to Wilt Mohawks</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="804189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RANCID (MUSIC GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRAUSS, NEIL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DD1238F93BA15753C1A963958260" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scream-Along Punk That's Enough to Wilt Mohawks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRAUSS, NEIL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Thursday night at Roseland, Rancid played pop music as it shouldn't be played. It was too fast, too sloppy, too venomous. In other words, it was perfect punk, and Rancid delivered it in a sweaty, 20-song show that had the mohawks on two of its members wilting by the end.</p>
        <p>If pop songwriters strive to create the most unforgettable sing-along, Rancid aspired to perform the ultimate scream-along. The quartet ripped and blistered through storylike verses until a single slash of Tim Armstrong's guitar signaled a switch into chorus mode. Here, the guitars and drums united in a single driving rhythm, propelling short, simple, catchy refrains that two or three band members spit out as fast and as frequently as possible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Thursday night at Roseland, Rancid played pop music as it shouldn't be played. It was too fast, too sloppy, too venomous. In other words, it was perfect punk, and Rancid delivered it in a sweaty, 20-song show that had the mohawks on two of its members wilting by the end.</p>
        <p>If pop songwriters strive to create the most unforgettable sing-along, Rancid aspired to perform the ultimate scream-along. The quartet ripped and blistered through storylike verses until a single slash of Tim Armstrong's guitar signaled a switch into chorus mode. Here, the guitars and drums united in a single driving rhythm, propelling short, simple, catchy refrains that two or three band members spit out as fast and as frequently as possible.</p>
        <p>Rancid, which has the dubious distinction of being the second-most popular punk band in the country, next to Green Day, believes in the power of a good song. "When the music hits, I feel no pain at all," Mr. Armstrong sang in "Radio," a song with a melody that sounds like a speeded-up version of Marvin Gaye's "Sexual Healing."</p>
        <p>Where Green Day sings about its own alienation and boredom, Rancid prefers to look outside at class differences, political problems and street conditions its members blame for those feelings. "When you're brought up, you're caught up in a system that is going," it sang in its addict's lament, "Junkie Man."</p>
        <p>Roughly half the songs Rancid performed were from its third and latest album, ". . . And Out Come the Wolves" (Epitaph), which peaked on the pop charts at No. 45. The album is partly a nostalgic look back at the Berkeley, Calif., scene that produced the band, and it includes several ska songs in the style of Operation Ivy, a band two of Rancid's members used to be in. Nostalgia, however, is nothing new for Rancid. Its music sounds as if it came straight from England circa 1977, the time of the Clash, another band that let Jamaican ska influence its class-conscious punk-rock. And the concert itself ended on a historical note when Mike Ness of the influential pop-punk band Social Distortion, which wanted to be the Clash of the 1980's, joined Rancid for a version of "Telling Them."</p>
        <p>The Bouncing Souls, who opened the show, also played on the crowd's memory. Performing fast, brash, bratty songs, they had the audience yelling lines from John Cusack films in their hilarious stop-and-go punk-rock song, "These Are the Quotes From My Favorite 80's Movies."  POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
