<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In 'Slavs!' Kushner Creates Tragic Burlesque</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="731814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK THEATER WORKSHOP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUSHNER, TONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGULIES, DONALD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SLAVS! (PLAY)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WHAT'S WRONG WITH THIS PICTURE? (PLAY)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FLYING KARAMAZOV BROTHERS DO THE IMPOSSIBLE, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1D81F39F93BA25751C1A962958260" item-length="2075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In 'Slavs!' Kushner Creates Tragic Burlesque</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vincent Canby</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HEAVEN THAT TONY Kushner envisions in the epilogue of "Slavs!," his bracing, rational 80-minute new fantasia at the New York Theater Workshop Off Broadway, is a dark, gloomy place designed to look like a city after an earthquake. The landscape is barren. Snow falls lightly. Huddled in their overcoats, two old Russian Bolsheviks sit on wooden crates and play cards, when a little girl named Vodya arrives. "Welcome to Nevermore," says one of the old men. The other asks how she died.</p>
        <p>"Cancer," says Vodya, who was a victim of a nuclear spill. She is impassive but not at a loss for words that bewitch: "A wild profusion of cells; dark flowerings in my lungs, my brain, my blood, my bones; dandelion and morning-glory vine seized and overwhelmed the field; life in my body ran riot. And here I am."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HEAVEN THAT TONY Kushner envisions in the epilogue of "Slavs!," his bracing, rational 80-minute new fantasia at the New York Theater Workshop Off Broadway, is a dark, gloomy place designed to look like a city after an earthquake. The landscape is barren. Snow falls lightly. Huddled in their overcoats, two old Russian Bolsheviks sit on wooden crates and play cards, when a little girl named Vodya arrives. "Welcome to Nevermore," says one of the old men. The other asks how she died.</p>
        <p>"Cancer," says Vodya, who was a victim of a nuclear spill. She is impassive but not at a loss for words that bewitch: "A wild profusion of cells; dark flowerings in my lungs, my brain, my blood, my bones; dandelion and morning-glory vine seized and overwhelmed the field; life in my body ran riot. And here I am."</p>
        <p>In this way, the body blooms even as it dies.</p>
        <p>In much the same fashion, even as Mr. Kushner evokes the death of Russia's Leninist-Stalinist revolution in "Slavs!," he has created a rambunctiously funny, seriously moving stage piece that is part buffoonish burlesque and part tragic satire. From beginning to end, it's also shot through with the kind of irony virtually unknown in today's theater, movies and television, where sarcasm passes for wit. There were hints of this exaggerated style in his epic "Millennium Approaches" and "Perestroika," collectively titled "Angels in America," both in the images of angels and icebergs and in the mesmerizing portrait of Roy Cohn.</p>
        <p>"Slavs!," which carries the subtitle "Thinking About the Longstanding Problems of Virtue and Happiness," is less complex though equally adventurous. Mr. Kushner not only possesses one of the freshest, most original talents in the American theater, but he also has the kind of historical reach more often found in novelists. His interests are wide-ranging, his responses hallucinatory. Here is an extended revue sketch that mercilessly catalogues the failures of the Soviet experiment while also mourning the loss of the idealism that gave it birth. "Slavs!" isn't chauvinist; the dismal triumph of mediocrity and opportunism is not an exclusively Russian problem.</p>
        <p>Why is good always defeated by evil and why does justice never win? In "Slavs!" one answer is provided by Aleksei Antedilluvianovich Prelapsarianov, "the world's oldest living Bolshevik," the memorable figure Mr. Kushner briefly introduced in "Perestroika." As played to frail perfection by Joseph Wiseman, he stays around somewhat longer in "Slavs!" Says the ancient ideologue in a spasm of terrible clarity, "God is a Menshevik!" His reasoning: an indifferent God must be reactionary. Progressive people are His political enemies.</p>
        <p>"Slavs!" features the fading figure of Aleksei and his grandly humane speech to the Chamber of Deputies, both taken directly from "Perestroika," but it is otherwise an entirely different work. Its characters are leaders of the Communist Party, apparatchiks, minor functionaries, technicians, babushkas, dropouts and victims. They come and go and reappear, though the play has no conventional narrative. The new work is a series of scathingly funny and grotesque variations on a sorrowful theme: the absolute end of a transforming belief. It also eschews the note of hope that so tidily and arbitrarily brings the seven hours of "Angels in America" to a close. "Slavs!" offers no solutions for man's problems; it simply repeats the eternal question: What is to be done?</p>
        <p>Not much, it would seem, though that doesn't necessarily invalidate the efforts to find solutions. Mr. Kushner has emphasized that "Slavs!" is not intended to be taken as the work of a historian. Rather, it's a work of a brilliant and restless imagination.</p>
        <p>The play starts off in Moscow on the day in March 1985 when Mikhail Gorbachev succeeded Konstantin Chernenko as General Secretary of the Communist Party. As two old peasant women sweep snow from the steps of the Hall of the Soviets in the Kremlin, earnestly debating Marxist dialectics, two tired party chiefs inside the hall sip tea and discuss the passing of the old order. One of them is already fed up with the new era, especially with all of the debating and voting. "I am a true apostle of the old scientific creed," he says wistfully, "geriatrical materialism. Our motto: stagnation is our only hope. Our sacred text: silence."</p>
        <p>In this way begins Mr. Kushner's whirlwind examination of the Russian psyche during the last years of the U.S.S.R. and the first years of its successor, the Commonwealth of Independent States. Among the people who come into view is, most spectacularly, Katherina (Marisa Tomei). She's the pretty, self-consciously butch night security guard at the facility where the party has stored the brains of its departed leaders, "an unbroken line of brains," she says, "stretching back to Red October."</p>
        <p>Lenin's brain, Stalin's brain, they're all there, "except for those which got flushed in the notorious dead-brain purges of 1937." Katherina is a very young, aggressive lesbian, courted ineffectually by Popolitipov (John Christopher Jones), a romantic if meanspirited apparatchik. She is heedlessly in love with Bonfila (Mary Shultz), a doctor whose great-grandfather was one of the fathers of the revolution.</p>
        <p>In addition there are also the horse-faced Rodent (David Chandler), a timid apparatchik who does his best to say yes to the right people but always fails; Serge (Gerald Hiken), a Bolshevik almost as old as Aleksei, who continues to believe in the future and leaps into it with fatal results, and Vodya (Mischa Barton), the doomed little girl who goes to heaven. She's first seen as an apparition in the mind of a drunk, then alive but mute in Siberia in 1992, where Bonfila, accompanied by Katherina, is trying to deal with the human debris in a country she describes as "a radioactive swamp."</p>
        <p>The New York Theater Workshop production, directed by Lisa Peterson, has a jolly, go-for-broke attitude that embraces the slapstick and the lunatic as well as the unspeakably cruel and the sad. One eerie and rollicking sequence occurs when Katherina and Bonfila, in a boozy haze, pray for a bottle of vodka as they kneel before an old icon, whose saint's face has been replaced by Lenin's. Do they get it? (Are you kidding?) But you have to see "Slavs!" to appreciate how the miracle is effected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kushner's words dazzle, sting and prompt belly laughs. In them are also echoes of the kind of Russian mysticism that can be detected in Chekhov, though these echoes are now filtered through minds shaped by, or reacting to, party dogma. Listen to Katherina's vision of the future: "I will be in a heavy metal band! There will be surprises, most of them unpleasant, but at least unanticipated, and the Great Gray Age of Boredom will finally lift." The smarmy Rodent predicts the coming of a strong new leader, "a man of iron and will." The romantic Popolitipov continues to believe in the party. "It dispenses miracles," he says. He remembers when it "electrified Russia, milled steel, built railways, abolished distance, suspended time, became eternal." Poor Poppy.</p>
        <p>All of the performers are good, and some are extremely good: Mr. Wiseman, Mr. Hiken, Ms. Shultz, Mr. Jones, Mr. Chandler, even the tiny, chillingly authoritative Ms. Barton. For someone who has only seen Ms. Tomei on the screen, where she won an Oscar for her priceless performance in "My Cousin Vinny," her work here will be another astonishment. She looks no more than 18, and her theatrical power and range are true and very funny.</p>
        <p>In his written directions to the cast, Mr. Kushner suggests that "the actors should probably use very, very mild Russian accents -- standard American accents, really, lightly perfumed with something Slavic. But intelligibility is paramount -- so don't eliminate diphthongs or replace too many 'W's with 'V's." There are times when the accents do become oppressive, unintelligible really, though slight accents are required to italicize the play's burlesque nature.</p>
        <p>As the director, Ms. Peterson clearly responds to the varying demands of the playwright. Together they have created a very singular, grown-up production. "Slavs!" uses cartoon figures to suggest that man's ability to bear up under the unbearable isn't limitless. After being flattened by a steamroller, it suggests, people don't pop back into shape like Bugs Bunny. "Slavs!" is essentially grim, but it's also irresistible.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>'What's Wrong With This Picture?'</p>
        <p>Donald Margulies's "What's Wrong With This Picture?," at the Brooks Atkinson Theater on Broadway, is a little too weird to be a sitcom but far too conventional to be a seriously dark comedy. The play isn't one thing or the other, like Shirley (Faith Prince). She's the Jewish mother who, a week after choking to death on moo shu pork, bolts from the grave to reassert her dominion over her adoring husband, Mort (Alan Rosenberg), and her conflicted son, Artie (David Moscow).</p>
        <p>Shirley is neither alive nor dead: she's the obsessive, immortal spirit of the stereotypical Jewish wife and mother. The idea has various comic and sick possibilities, but every one of them is either realized or introduced and then sidestepped in the first of the play's two acts.</p>
        <p>Before Shirley returns, there's a peculiar moment when Mort persuades his son to model one of Shirley's dresses, only to become turned on by the sight. Nothing happens, but at that moment the members of the Brooks Atkinson audience with whom I saw the play began to disengage themselves from the performance. As Mr. Margulies demonstrated last season with his "Loman Family Picnic," he has the ability to uncover nasty truths within the ordinarily harmless comedy of wisecracks. There are no revelations here.</p>
        <p>Joe Mantello (currently represented by Terrence McNally's "Love! Valour! Compassion!") directed this latest version of the play, earlier drafts of which were presented at the Jewish Repertory Theater in 1990 and the Manhattan Theater Club in 1985. The new production can't be faulted in any obvious way. The cast is good, especially Jerry Stiller, who plays Sid, Shirley's senile father-in-law, and Florence Stanley, as Bella, her sharp-tongued mother-in-law. Says the cheerfully disconnected Sid on meeting the dead woman on her return, "By the way, Shirley, I was sorry to hear what happened." That's about as good as it gets.</p>
        <p>The show is scheduled to close today.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>'The Flying Karamazov Brothers Do the Impossible!'</p>
        <p>The Flying Karamazov Brothers, the four-man group that has been a juggling-and-joking show-biz phenomenon since 1973, is back in New York at the Helen Hayes Theater. The title of the new piece ("The Flying Karamazov Brothers Do the Impossible!") prompts a philosophical discussion among them about the latent contradiction within it: if they do the impossible, what they are doing, of course, is possible, which means they fail. This kind of joshing seems to take up far more of the performance than the juggling, which is the way the men (Paul Magid, Howard Jay Patterson, Michael Preston and Sam Williams) most blithely express themselves.</p>
        <p>There are two good sequences. In a number called "The Gamble," they invite the audience to give Ivan Karamazov (Mr. Patterson) items to juggle, though he won't accept live animals or anything bigger than a breadbox. Good fun. Also fine is a demonstration of spectacular juggling near the end when the four men, with what seem to be several dozen pins flying through the air, each move one place to the left or right without missing either a catch or a toss. It's their way of square-dancing.</p>
        <p>Warning: Don't send anyone to see this without explaining what and who the Flying Karamazovs is and are. At intermission the night I went, a puzzled woman approached another woman out front to ask what she thought of the show. The second woman returned the question. "Oh, I don't like it," said the first with a frown. "I thought they were going to be Russian dancers." SLAVS!  Tony Kushner's words dazzle and sting in a go-for-broke production that embraces the slapstick and the lunatic as well as the unspeakably cruel and the sad.  WHAT'S WRONG WITH THIS PICTURE? Out of focus and overexposed.  THE FLYING KARAMAZOV BROTHERS DO THE IMPOSSIBLE!  Go back a step. Would less joshing and more juggling be possible?  SUNDAY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
