<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Pair of Saints Who Refuse To Stay Dead</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="731813"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="ART VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INSTITUTE OF CONTEMPORARY ART (BOSTON, MASS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, VICKI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRESLEY, ELVIS (1935-77)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MONROE, MARILYN (1926-62)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6D81F39F93BA25751C1A962958260" item-length="2158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Pair of Saints Who Refuse To Stay Dead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vicki Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, VICKI</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ELVIS WAS A HIP replacement, a shaky premise, a groined vault. He put the male pelvis right where belly dancers and stripteasers had already put the female's: up front in the spotlight. This made some people nervous. What's more, he was vulgar, his hair was full of goo, he had a pink stripe on his black pants, and his music borrowed freely from black gospel, blues, and rhythm and blues. Numerous disk jockeys burned stacks of his records. Ministers preached against him. Police and district attorneys held him responsible for juvenile delinquency. Pravda gleefully declared him proof of Western decadence, and many Americans agreed. He just wanted to play house in the Heartbreak Hotel. He just wanted you to love him tender.</p>
        <p>Marilyn was the promise of pneumatic bliss and the power to cloud men's minds. She was the blondest woman in America, a bombshell made of custard, the ecstatic answer to your mother's injunction to have a good time, dear. She had a smile as bright as cloudless skies while inside she rained tears, but at the moment that the Pill became available she let women know that sex was more fun than the married women's instruction manuals let on, thereby helping prepare the ground for sexual revolution. Baseball greats and playwrights married her; men in high office bedded her. She just wanted someone to love her true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ELVIS WAS A HIP replacement, a shaky premise, a groined vault. He put the male pelvis right where belly dancers and stripteasers had already put the female's: up front in the spotlight. This made some people nervous. What's more, he was vulgar, his hair was full of goo, he had a pink stripe on his black pants, and his music borrowed freely from black gospel, blues, and rhythm and blues. Numerous disk jockeys burned stacks of his records. Ministers preached against him. Police and district attorneys held him responsible for juvenile delinquency. Pravda gleefully declared him proof of Western decadence, and many Americans agreed. He just wanted to play house in the Heartbreak Hotel. He just wanted you to love him tender.</p>
        <p>Marilyn was the promise of pneumatic bliss and the power to cloud men's minds. She was the blondest woman in America, a bombshell made of custard, the ecstatic answer to your mother's injunction to have a good time, dear. She had a smile as bright as cloudless skies while inside she rained tears, but at the moment that the Pill became available she let women know that sex was more fun than the married women's instruction manuals let on, thereby helping prepare the ground for sexual revolution. Baseball greats and playwrights married her; men in high office bedded her. She just wanted someone to love her true.</p>
        <p>Wendy McDaris, a curator who lives in Elvis's hometown, Memphis, has had the clever idea of examining the impact of these two on the arts in "Elvis + Marilyn: 2 x Immortal" at the Institute of Contemporary Art in Boston (through Jan. 8, then traveling to institutions in nine cities, including the New-York Historical Society next October with a well-illustrated and sometimes thoughtful catalogue from Rizzoli). This very large show includes the work of 107 artists, among them Robert Arneson, Joseph Cornell, Keith Haring and Claes Oldenburg.</p>
        <p>Rather arbitrarily divided into images of cultural, heroic, mythic and religious significance, it suffers from the usual problem of theme shows: some work is here simply because it is about the title. But many pieces are smart and amusing, and some are important. In Jeff Bourgeau's "You Are the One," Marilyn, in low resolution, tantalizingly, maddeningly blows a kiss over and over on tiny monitors while a scratchy male voice sings. Ralph Burns's report on pilgrims to Graceland includes an amazing photograph of a fat woman in a bedroom contemplating an Elvis mannequin stiffly at rest on the bedspread. Ashley Bickerton's "Seascape: Floating Costume to Drift for Eternity" -- a strapped-up trunk, equipped to float and enclosing a jeweled white Elvis jump suit -- is a ghostly high-tech message in a bottle.</p>
        <p>The strongest section is on religion, especially the Elvis cult. Elvis considered himself a healer, and people with sick children trooped to his concerts as if to Lourdes -- and that was before he died. Joanne Stephens's "Homage to Elvis" enshrines a jeweled and crowned singer in a golden splendor of musical putti atop a gutted television set, within which a diorama shows Elvis belting it out for an attentive group of animals. Marilyn has an altar, too. Mark Solomon Dennis serves up Elvis's severed head on a platter with some salmon, Conrad Atkinson and Alexander Guy both produce crucified Elvis suits.</p>
        <p>Our saints today, such as they are, survive a certain amount of torture at the hands of cruel lovers, an inquisitorial public and private demons. Then, lacking executioners, they have to finish the job themselves with neglect or overdoses or whatever. Performers and artists are good candidates to become cult figures, musicians especially, for they promise transcendence, initiating their followers into ecstatic mysteries where reason cannot reach.</p>
        <p>YOU MIGHT OVERDOSE ON Elvis and Marilyn in the midst of the I.C.A. extravaganza, but you will certainly be convinced that artists believe, with the rest of us, that these two are cultural icons. Marilyn and Elvis are as undead as vampires and return more often, not being afraid of sunlight. Their images are everywhere and have been from the moment they died. A photograph of Elvis in his coffin was said to be the first picture of a dead celebrity on a front page; it sold six million copies of The National Enquirer.</p>
        <p>Yet Elvis has refused to lie still; he is sighted more often than endangered species. Christopher Walken, in "Him," a play now at the Public Theater, proposes that Elvis did not die but went into hiding disguised as a waitress. Marilyn, theatrical in her lifetime, after her death was also turned into theater in Arthur Miller's "After the Fall." Madonna resurrected her via the sincerest form of flattery in music videos and magazine spreads. Elvis crossed the country on a postage stamp; Marilyn became one, too, but only in St. Vincent, in the West Indies.</p>
        <p>It is a safe bet that very few artists make the yearly pilgrimage to Memphis to lay a rose on Elvis's grave and take home a packet of Graceland earth. The myriad images of Elvis and Marilyn that spangle the art-world skies are obviously cultural commentary. Whereas the great painters of altarpieces in the past were no doubt fired by both religious and artistic zeal, contemporary artists, debonair in their unbelief, treat the newer icons as sociology. The dependence on popular figures and media presentations of them is an admonition to pay attention to the modern world.</p>
        <p>But the art world, though its eyes are glued to the television screen and its fingers count the nation's pulse, is actually thinking of something else all the while: itself. It has its own gods, and they are artists. This show is actually about three icons: Elvis, Marilyn and Andy. There are any number of riffs on Warhol's Elvis and Warhol's Marilyn, paintings that are stars themselves. (Warhol's "Shot Red Marilyn" broke an auction record in 1989 by fetching more than $4 million and then brought $3.6 million this fall. Like Marilyn, the picture is worth more because it was "murdered" and lived on; someone shot it in Warhol's studio, and he repaired the bullet hole.)</p>
        <p>Richard Pettibone repeats part of a Warhol Elvis. Jerry Kearns does it again, adding familiar Vietnam images. Frank Xerox, Janice E. Williams and Raymond Saunders rework Warhol's Marilyn, Seymour Howard paints abstractions over Andy's Elvis and his Marilyn. Peter Halley paints a two-panel abstraction of squares and lines, brightly colored on the left, gray on the right, and calls it "Double Elvis" after Warhol's painting of Elvis with a gun. Halley says, rather coyly, that he liked the idea of cloning.</p>
        <p>Then Deborah Kass does Barbra Streisand the way Warhol did Elvis: two double portraits of Yentl side by side, one colored, one not. Barbra is a crasher at this party of Elvis and Marilyn look-alikes; she got in solely by looking like a Warhol. These are in- jokes, winks, knowing references for people in the know. As comments on the media culture, they refer to art as a mass medium on a level art seldom achieves, though Warhol just may have. The pictures here are really art appreciation under the guise of social critique.</p>
        <p>Post-modernism's appropriation of newspaper, film and comic-strip imagery, an acknowledgment that life today lodges in representation, is, in a way, a last gasp of the 19th-century Realists' concentration on contemporary life. Rarely have artists borrowed from art so slavishly as they do now, a practice explained as a bow to the end of originality.</p>
        <p>But borrowing Warhol's silk-screens of commercially distributed photographs -- the experience at second hand in the photograph, at third in Warhol, at fourth in the newest redaction -- points up the inability of art to forge our cultural symbols. For centuries, artists provided forms for society's heroes (or for the heroes governments wanted society to have): statues of Greek athletes or the Marcus Aurelius in Rome; Michelangelo's David, which was understood by the Florentines to represent civic freedom. Photography, film, newsreels and television changed that, and artists now are reduced to playing with images already established in public fantasies, stoked by forces beyond the limits of art.</p>
        <p>Elvis spearheaded the rebellious youth culture that emerged after the silent 50's; Marilyn assured women they could enjoy their own bodies and thus foretold sexual liberation. He was the first big rock star, solidifying the power of popular music on the mores and behavior of the young. She was always larger than life, her oversize invitation pulsing on the big screen before the little screen whittled the stars down and brought them home. It wasn't just his music that made him a star, though he did make black sound available to segregated white ears. It wasn't just her acting, though long after she perfected the sex kitten's purr she proved her talent, particularly at comedy.</p>
        <p>Both of them released something pent up in their audiences: sex. (And to varying degrees, rebellion.) Both of them said, oh, yeah, I know that's dirty, but, baby, let me tell you it's a good time, and I'm not ashamed to say so at the dinner table. The kids gasped, then swooned with delight. Their parents gasped, then said, "Hmm."</p>
        <p>They both embodied enough contradictions to captivate a motley audience. Elvis was a choirboy in punk's clothing. Success bought him Cadillacs, gold pianos, women, pills, but he was a rigorously polite young man and always good to his mamma. Marilyn was a sex goddess with a mortally wounded soul. They would have been stars but not legends had they not both been Horatio Alger and then both died young.</p>
        <p>The climb up from poverty and marginal status -- Norma Jean was an abused child of an insane mother and an unknown father, Elvis merely from the wrong side of the tracks -- gave hope to millions, stirred sympathy in the rest, and reinforced the collective American dream. (She was one of the first stars with a dreadful background so publicly displayed. Her fans, knowing so much about her, felt a thrill of intimacy and an urge to protect her.) Early death is an essential ingredient of martyrdom, and if we can no longer witness martyrs burned at the stake, we can read all about it in the papers and shed a tear to think what we have lost.</p>
        <p>It did not seem to matter that they failed, that his magic dwindled, he got into fights, and his flesh turned to porridge as he aged, or that she fell into the arms of pills and alcohol. They had the grace to be vulnerable and to have won once nonetheless, proving themselves triumphantly human.</p>
        <p>Untold numbers took that to heart and identified with one or the other. Elvis look-alike contests still attract young boys as well as men much older than the King. Few of them can sing, and almost none look like Elvis except for the jewels on their shirts. Marilyn look-alike contests draw every young blonde with a dark lipstick and a passable figure in a bathing suit.</p>
        <p>THIS IS EVIDENCE OF GLOBAL envy. Everyone wants to be somebody else. After Schwarzenegger and Stallone, young men who never flexed a bicep before began to pump religiously. Cyndi Lauper once spawned a rash of cheap dressers; Marilyn boosted peroxide sales; a woman named Cindy Jackson has spent $55,000 on plastic surgery in her quest to look like Barbie, who is a distant relative of Marilyn's. Who is there to look up to? Politicians, doctors, even priests have been dragged off their pedestals; teachers were never on one. We cling to beauty, rebellion and outsiders who made it big in spite of everything -- ourselves, had we but the talent and the breaks.</p>
        <p>Marilyn was killed by a conspiracy. The world conspired against her, poor illegitimate baby, exploited sex symbol, plaything of powerful men, sex object yearning to be a subject. Marilyn conspired to kill herself. Bobby Kennedy conspired to kill her. Jack Kennedy conspired to kill her. Only Lee Harvey Oswald inspired more rumors and theories, and nobody loved Lee Harvey Oswald, but everybody loved Marilyn. (Except some of the big guys who just used her, and Marilyn herself.) Her cherry lips and marshmallow body invite us closer in photo shops and diners across the land. Her creamy voice and breathy delivery still caress us on late-night television, where computer imaging briefly turns a model into la Monroe to tout Chanel No. 5.</p>
        <p>Then there was Elvis. He died on the toilet perusing pornography (or so says a 1991 book), but the ecumenical version now goes that he was reading a text on the Shroud of Turin. Elvis! He died for our sins; he died from our sins -- addictions, prescriptions, success, excess, bad taste. He lives on in parking lots and shopping malls, blessing his aging devotees with visions of Himself between pickup trucks and plastic curlers and inchoate longings. The King must die but still he lives, drawing a bead on his fans with a pistol and crooning on CD's, right here in mass-reproduction heaven.  ART VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
