<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Party Structure In the Soviet Union</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="184060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DE1531F932A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Party Structure In the Soviet Union</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The personnel shake-up in the Soviet Communist Party yesterday was accompanied by a revamping of the party structure. Six Central Committee commissions were created, all headed by secretaries of the Central Committee, to supplant 22 departments as the party's main administrative apparatus. Political power continues to be centered in the Central Committee and the Politburo, where all important decisions are made.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The personnel shake-up in the Soviet Communist Party yesterday was accompanied by a revamping of the party structure. Six Central Committee commissions were created, all headed by secretaries of the Central Committee, to supplant 22 departments as the party's main administrative apparatus. Political power continues to be centered in the Central Committee and the Politburo, where all important decisions are made.</p>
        <p>The personnel shake-up in the Soviet Communist Party yesterday was accompanied by a revamping of the party structure. Six Central Committee commissions were created, all headed by secretaries of the Central Committee, to supplant 22 departments as the party's main administrative apparatus. Political power continues to be centered in the Central Committee and the Politburo, where all important decisions are made.  Communist Party Congress</p>
        <p>Theoretically the highest body, the congress consists of delegates elected by party organizations around the country. It ordinarily convenes at least once every five years, with its next meeting scheduled in 1991. The Congress elects the Central Committee, which is to meet at least every six months.  Central Committee</p>
        <p>Consisting of about 300 voting and 150 nonvoting members, it is picked from among party congress delegates. It acts for the congress between sessions, meeting about twice a year to discuss and approve policies. It formally elects what is, in effect, the highest party body, the Politburo.  Politburo</p>
        <p>It sets the overall policy of the country and now has 12 full (voting) members and 8 candidate (nonvoting) members, all of whom are among the nation's leading political figures. All members have regular duties elsewhere in the party or Government.  Secretariat</p>
        <p>Until now, it has run the nation's day-to-day affairs. It is headed by the General Secretary, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, and composed of nine other Central Committee secretaries and a large permanent staff that is expected to be cut in the months ahead.  The Commissions and Their Chairmen</p>
        <p>Agriculture policy: Yegor K. Ligachev</p>
        <p>Ideology: adim A. Medvedev</p>
        <p>International policy: Aleksandr N. Yakovlev</p>
        <p>Legal policy: Viktor M. Chebrikov</p>
        <p>Party building and personnel policy: Georgi P. Razumovsky</p>
        <p>Social and economic policy: Nikolai N. Slyunkov  All chairmen are secretaries of the Central Committee and all except Mr. Razumovsky, who is a nonvoting member, are full members of the Politburo.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
