<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Relax? I Can't! I'm on Vacation!</title>
    <meta content="13DAVID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="OUT OF ORDER" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="943279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="OUT OF ORDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bouchier, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD1239F930A25754C0A961958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Relax? I Can't! I'm on Vacation!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BOUCHIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bouchier, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Bouchier comment on how stressful planning and taking vacations can be; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE just got back from our vacation. My dictionary defines vacation as ''a period of rest and freedom,'' which just goes to show that you can't trust dictionaries, however fat and impressive they are. Everyone knows that the busiest times of year are just before going away on vacation, just after coming home and the period in between.</p>
        <p>Even a simple trip to the Hamptons this weekend demands the persistence of a Hannibal (to get there) and the ruthlessness of a Genghis Khan (to park and find a place to eat). One can only admire the fortitude of citizens who set off with their families on far longer trips, sometimes even beyond the borders of the United States, in search of that elusive period of rest and freedom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE just got back from our vacation. My dictionary defines vacation as ''a period of rest and freedom,'' which just goes to show that you can't trust dictionaries, however fat and impressive they are. Everyone knows that the busiest times of year are just before going away on vacation, just after coming home and the period in between.</p>
        <p>Even a simple trip to the Hamptons this weekend demands the persistence of a Hannibal (to get there) and the ruthlessness of a Genghis Khan (to park and find a place to eat). One can only admire the fortitude of citizens who set off with their families on far longer trips, sometimes even beyond the borders of the United States, in search of that elusive period of rest and freedom.</p>
        <p>The pressure begins to build as soon as vacation is mentioned in the house. Whose vacation will this be? He wants to go to Las Vegas, she wants to go to Tuscany, the kids want to go to Disney World, except for the teen-ager who wants to go to Colombia. After a long period of secret struggle, reminiscent of the internal battles of the old Russian Politburo, they agree to go to Hawaii. This way, nobody is happy but nobody loses face.</p>
        <p>When the decision has been made, the planning begins. Some people  start organizing their vacations six months ahead. But we follow what I suspect is the more common habit of making the reservations in January, then doing absolutely nothing about it until three days before flight time. We have a vacation planning list saved in our computer. It gets larger every year and threatens to engulf the last few megabytes of  memory. Suddenly, the list springs to life and becomes a timetable with a  very short fuse. All the usual routines of life come to an abrupt halt.  Loose ends stay loose, dishes pile up and the grass grows under our feet.  Everything is subordinated to the monstrous authority of The List.</p>
        <p>If you need a passport and don't have one, it's already too late. Getting a United States passport takes  longer than canonization, and the requirements are tougher. Then there's currency, travelers' checks, maps, guide books, insurance. A hundred years ago, servants would have looked after these details. Now they are doing it for themselves, and they'll probably be on the same flight, traveling first-class.</p>
        <p>But it's the emotional work, not the paperwork, that leaves us exhausted on the first day of vacation. A house can take care of itself. But pets are another matter. Most Americans have pets, but how can the cat/dog/ ferret/goldfish/parrot have a perfect experience while we are away? It's no solution to dump them in kennels, unless we are willing to risk daily anxiety during the trip and reproachful looks for weeks afterward. The alternative is to get a resident pet sitter, and spend the  vacation worrying about the sitter.</p>
        <p>All this organzation has to happen in the space of about two days. On the morning of departure day, things get desperate. Mouldy suitcases are  roused out from the basement and a slow, careful process of packing begins. This gets faster and faster until in the last hour almost anything may be flung in, including small appliances and slow-moving household pets. We leave the house like the typical American traveling couple, with enough stuff to survive a six-month siege in Antarctica, but none of the things that we actually want on the trip.</p>
        <p>Now comes the only truly relaxing part of the whole vacation -- the limo ride to the airport. The flight itself can be relaxing too, at least until we remember in mid-flight, at 30,000 feet, that we left the iron on in the basement. But at least there's nothing to be done, and a brief period of rest and freedom can take place.</p>
        <p>Once the plane touches down, of course, life gets busy again. It would be a crime to waste even a minute of this expensive time. So we create an hour-by-hour timetable of trips, meals, sights that must be seen and even languages and driving styles to be learned.</p>
        <p>At last, shattered and hollow-eyed with the effort of vacationing, and jet-lagged all over again, we return home. The pets are grumpy, the lawn sprinklers sprung a leak and flooded the neighborhood, some very nasty things are lurking in the refrigerator. Usually we've put on weight.  Sometimes, after a bout of food poisoning from some dubious foreign  restauraunt, we arrive home strangely thin and yellow. And there, always waiting, are those intensely irritating neighbors who stayed home. They are are bright, tanned and full of vigor after a couple of weeks relaxing on the deck.</p>
        <p>It takes about a week for us to start feeling human again, and to  begin talking about what a great time we had. Then the credit card bills start to come in. But it was worth it. How can you hope to enjoy a period of rest and freedom if you never go away?</p>
        <p>OUT OF ORDER  David Bouchier of Wading River is an essayist and commentator heard regularly on public radio.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Bouchier of Wading River is an essayist and commentator heard regularly on public radio.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
