<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leveraged Buyout Specialist Resigns His Job at First Union</title>
    <meta content="Y5BANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/05/business/Y5BANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1252694"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Union Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knowlton, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DB143CF936A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leveraged Buyout Specialist Resigns His Job at First Union</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RIVA D. ATLAS</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leveraged buyout specialist and investment banker David Knowlton resigns from First Union Corp (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Knowlton, an investment banker at the First Union Corporation who was co-manager of the bank's effort to finance leveraged buyouts and other private equity investments, is resigning, a spokeswoman for First Union confirmed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knowlton, who was based in New York, is resigning as the bank tries to narrow the focus of its capital markets business. He decided to leave after he was told to report to Kevin Roche, a veteran executive of the bank who last month was named head of leveraged finance, including syndicated lending and high-yield debt. Mr. Knowlton, who had previously reported directly to the heads of investment banking at First Union, was unhappy about the decision, according to one executive at the bank.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Knowlton, an investment banker at the First Union Corporation who was co-manager of the bank's effort to finance leveraged buyouts and other private equity investments, is resigning, a spokeswoman for First Union confirmed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knowlton, who was based in New York, is resigning as the bank tries to narrow the focus of its capital markets business. He decided to leave after he was told to report to Kevin Roche, a veteran executive of the bank who last month was named head of leveraged finance, including syndicated lending and high-yield debt. Mr. Knowlton, who had previously reported directly to the heads of investment banking at First Union, was unhappy about the decision, according to one executive at the bank.</p>
        <p>A veteran of the Chase Manhattan Corporation and Gleacher NatWest, the United States investment banking arm of National Westminster Bank, Mr. Knowlton joined First Union in April 1999, as part of a push by the bank, which is based in Charlotte, N.C., to bolster the profile of its capital markets business. So far, it  has met with mixed success: while it has moved up to 4th place among lenders to leveraged companies, up from 11th place five years ago, according to the Loan Pricing Corporation, it is still a second-tier player in the high-yield bond and merger advisory businesses, where it ranks in 14th and 57th place, respectively, according to Thomson Financial Securities Data.</p>
        <p>First Union is in the midst of refining the scope and size of its capital markets business, after making four acquisitions of midsize investment banks since 1997, and amid a slowdown overall on Wall Street. Last month, First Union laid off seven securities analysts and announced a plan to cut a few investment banking jobs.</p>
        <p>''They are developing a more well- thought-out notion of what their business strategy should be,'' said Susan Roth, an analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston. The bank recently told analysts that it planned to focus on clients in the middle market, which it defines as companies with $200 million to $2 billion in sales, she said. ''First Union can't compete with Goldman, Sachs,'' Ms. Roth said, although she noted that some middle-market companies First Union might work with could be attractive to financial buyers.</p>
        <p>First Union remains committed to working with private equity investors, said the company's spokeswoman, Arati Randolph. The division will continue under the leadership of Edward Imbrogno, a Charlotte-based banker who had led the division along with Mr. Knowlton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Knowlton's deals at First Union included arranging a $225 million financing for an acquisition of the New York Jets. Mr. Knowlton also advised Kohlberg Kravis Roberts &amp; Company on its $125 million investment in NewSouth Communications and the buyout firms Thomas H. Lee Company and Kelso &amp; Company on an investment of more than $400 million in MJD Communications (since renamed FairPoint Communications).</p>
        <p>''David is a terrific person and he understands the capital markets,'' said James H. Greene Jr., a partner at Kohlberg Kravis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
