<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knight Receives Some Barbs</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="410861"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INDIANA UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPERBER, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KNIGHT, BOBBY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDF1530F937A15751C1A966958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knight Receives Some Barbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although he has taught at Indiana University for 20 years, Murray Sperber said he has never had the privilege, if not the pleasure, of an audience with one of the university's most powerful people. No, not the president, but the head basketball coach, Bobby Knight.</p>
        <p>Sperber, who was hired as an English professor in 1971 -- the same year Knight was hired to coach basketball -- said he wanted to talk with the head coach while doing research for his recently published book, "College Sports Inc.: The Athletic Department vs. the University (Henry Holt)."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although he has taught at Indiana University for 20 years, Murray Sperber said he has never had the privilege, if not the pleasure, of an audience with one of the university's most powerful people. No, not the president, but the head basketball coach, Bobby Knight.</p>
        <p>Sperber, who was hired as an English professor in 1971 -- the same year Knight was hired to coach basketball -- said he wanted to talk with the head coach while doing research for his recently published book, "College Sports Inc.: The Athletic Department vs. the University (Henry Holt)."</p>
        <p>"I was on KABC radio in Los Angeles and the guy kept asking me, 'How come you don't know Knight?' " Sperber recalled. "I said, 'Look, my chances of meeting Knight are about as good as yours of meeting Michael Jackson.'</p>
        <p>"Because I was asked that question so much I did a poll in the English department. I asked 32 faculty members who had been here longer than 10 years whether they had ever met Knight, or been in a room smaller than Assembly Hall with him. And only one of them actually had.</p>
        <p>"A man who had been chair of the faculty council had to go to a Trustees meeting and Knight was there. He said that the coach spent about three-quarters of an hour denouncing the faculty."</p>
        <p>Sperber's book certainly won't inspire an invitation from Knight. Among other things, he argues that coaches at big-time programs are not educators but merely yard masters of the commerical entertainment business. He also attempts to show how big-time athletic programs do not enhance but actually drain the university's resources.</p>
        <p>"I understand that he is not happy about my book because I point out his graduation statistics," Sperber said.</p>
        <p>In the book the author said that Knight's graduation rate is 65 percent. "That's a misprint; it should be 56 percent of all his players," he said.</p>
        <p>Indiana's overall graduation rate for incoming freshmen is 59 percent over the same five-year period the N.C.A.A. uses for tracking rates.</p>
        <p>"If you take all of his players from the 1980's and get the N.C.A.A. academic reporting form where they track to see whether those players graduated from the university, his stats for the 1980's are 42 percent," Sperber said. "The most interesting one is that of his black recruits in the 80's, 17 black recruits, of those only two have graduated from Indiana University. It's 11 percent."</p>
        <p>Knight did not return a call asking for his response. 2 Forceful Takeovers</p>
        <p>If Kenny Anderson, Georgia's Tech's super sophomore, and the University of Nevada-Las Vegas continue at their current rate, they might become the first player and team to be drafted into the National Basketball Association at midseason.</p>
        <p>Anderson, 6-foot-3-inch sophomore who early on was trying to devise a way to carry the Yellow Jackets while keeping everyone involved, has apparently found the answer: He's simply taken over.</p>
        <p>Beginning with a 26-point performance in a losing effort at Temple two weeks ago, Anderson has been on a tear. He scored 40 points and played all 55 minutes in a triple-overtime victory over Georgia last Wednesday. On Saturday, Anderson scored a record 50 points as Georgia Tech set a school scoring mark in a 135-94 victory over Loyola Marymount.</p>
        <p>Nearly 2,000 miles away in Las Vegas, the Runnin' Rebels were enjoying a similar collective feast at Thomas and Mack Center. The defending national champions, who routed Princeton on Wednesday, defeated Florida State, 101-69. Afterward, Pat Kennedy, the Florida State coach, said: "I don't think any team in the country can beat them. They're head and shoulders above anybody." More Woes at Syracuse</p>
        <p>Tony Scott, a versatile 6-8 guard/ forward who was an important, but unhappy player for Syracuse last season, has departed for Texas A&amp;M. Now a published report says that a New York City talent scout arranged for Scott's transfer to the Aggies.</p>
        <p>The Syracuse Post-Standard reported last week that Scott said Texas A&amp;M had paid for part of his father's airfare and had paid for the scout, Rob Johnson, to stay at a hotel during one trip. The paper also reported that the public university paid for $1,400 worth of phone calls made by Johnson.</p>
        <p>Syracuse, which seemed to be ridding itself of a problem with Scott's departure, may have taken on an even bigger headache last season when LeRon Ellis, the 6-10 senior center, transferred to Syracuse from Kentucky. According to Post-Standard reports, Ellis's father, Leroy, received a job from a Syracuse alumnus at about the same time his son transferred.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
