<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hunting for Elusive Terrorists Off Somalia's Coast</title>
    <meta content="Y02SOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/02/international/africa/02SOMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: SECURITY PATROLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Somalia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Somalia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bin Laden, Osama</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DD123AF931A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hunting for Elusive Terrorists Off Somalia's Coast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hunting for Elusive Terrorists Off Somalia's Coast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <dateline>OFF THE COAST OF SOMALIA, March 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A tiny blip appeared on the radar screen of a German surveillance plane patrolling the Somali coastline. It was a faint green dot, which meant something small was out there on the water. Was this a boatload of fleeing Al Qaeda fighters?</p>
        <p>The pilot maneuvered the plane for a close look. Two spotters with high-powered binoculars scoured the sea. Another sat inside the plane's nose, which was made of clear plastic. Minutes passed. Nothing. Then, the man in the nose spotted something. But it was not Osama bin Laden or his men.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dozens of ships now ring vast stretches of the Horn of Africa in an attempt to block Al Qaeda fighters from seeking refuge in Somalia or Yemen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A tiny blip appeared on the radar screen of a German surveillance plane patrolling the Somali coastline. It was a faint green dot, which meant something small was out there on the water. Was this a boatload of fleeing Al Qaeda fighters?</p>
        <p>The pilot maneuvered the plane for a close look. Two spotters with high-powered binoculars scoured the sea. Another sat inside the plane's nose, which was made of clear plastic. Minutes passed. Nothing. Then, the man in the nose spotted something. But it was not Osama bin Laden or his men.</p>
        <p>''Dolphins,'' the spotter said, pointing down at a dozen of the mammals frolicking in the sea.</p>
        <p>The German patrol missions are a small part of what defense officials are calling the largest maritime patrol mission since World War II. Dozens of ships now ring vast stretches of the Horn of Africa in an attempt to block Al Qaeda fighters from seeking refuge in Somalia or Yemen. The air patrols assess the situation from above, sending information by radio to the allied ships. But hunting down terrorists in an area so vast is a monotonous task fraught with false alarms. The surveillance flights begin before dawn and go on for 10 hours.</p>
        <p>Even when the radar screen does come to life it can send the plane chasing everything from whales to waves. Actual ships resemble tiny specks on the horizon from afar. Gradually, their outlines appear. When the plane swoops in low near the ship, people on the deck are sometimes visible. The German spotters squint down until they can read the names and home ports on the sides of the vessels. On one recent outing, they spotted four large container ships with the names Tiger River, Colombo, Lucy and Bougainville. All appeared to be legitimate.</p>
        <p>The plane, a cold war-era Breguet Atlantic BR 1150, photographs each boat and sends the identifying information to United States Navy commanders in Bahrain. It becomes part of the intelligence database for the United States war on terrorism.</p>
        <p>The German Parliament set conditions last November when it agreed to allow German forces to take part in the campaign. First, the deployment would last no more than a year without further approval. And second, Germany could not penetrate any national borders without that country's permission.</p>
        <p>In the case of Somalia, that means the air force must operate 12 miles off the coast, in international waters, even though there is no central Somali government. On its recent outing, the surveillance plane took off from a Kenyan airfield and headed straight out to sea. It then flew hundreds of miles to the north in a zigzag pattern, trying to cover a vast expanse of water.</p>
        <p>At one point, the plane flew 15 nautical miles from Mogadishu, the coastal capital of Somalia. Along with the Germans, who use a beachfront hotel in Mombasa, Kenya, as their base, numerous other countries are monitoring stretches of sea. The British recently began operating two surveillance planes out of Mombasa. Farther north, in Djibouti, American forces are working along with colleagues from France, Spain and Germany over the Gulf of Aden, the waterway that divides Africa from the Middle East.</p>
        <p>The Germans have the southernmost stretch of Somalia, an area that stretches 1,000 miles from the Kenyan border to the tip of the horn. This was dangerous water even before the terrorist attacks on Sept. 11. It is known to be a prime route for traffickers in drugs, weapons and illegal immigrants, as well as cash, military officials said.</p>
        <p>From above, however, it is nearly impossible to determine what the ships have aboard. Still, the monitors have their suspicions.</p>
        <p>''They are not wearing T-shirts saying 'Al Qaeda No. 2,' '' said Lt. Col. Udo Schmidt, commander of the German forces in Mombasa. ''But if you see tiny boats 40 to 50 miles off the coast with a bunch of people on them, you have to wonder.''</p>
        <p>Even when they encounter suspicious ships, the German patrol planes are in no position to intercept them. The allied boats patrolling the Somali coastline are spread so thin that they cannot effectively stop most traffic. The mere presence of the patrols is meant to act as a deterrent. ''As you can see, there's a lot of looking and not much finding,'' said the pilot of the German patrol plane, sitting in the cockpit midway through his shift. ''Sometimes you wonder how much good you're doing. But if Al Qaeda is going to cross here, they'll at least know that someone is looking at them.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Pakistani Police Seize 16 Arabs</p>
        <p>ISLAMABAD, Tuesday, April 2 (Agence France-Presse) -- Sixteen mostly Arab men suspected of having links to Al Qaeda were arrested during raids in the eastern Pakistani city of Lahore overnight, the police chief there said today.</p>
        <p>Police Chief Javed Noor said the men ''had been living in Afghanistan'' and were being interrogated ''to find out their identities and their background'' after having been caught ''by surprise.'' No American law enforcement agencies had a role in their capture, he said.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: SECURITY PATROLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
