<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Options In Assault On Smallpox</title>
    <meta content="02DOCS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/02/health/02DOCS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE DOCTOR'S WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smallpox</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/The Doctor's World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Smallpox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Smallpox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anthrax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vaccination and Immunization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smallpox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5D9153AF931A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Options In Assault On Smallpox</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Options in Assault on Smallpox</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN, M.D.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article traces development of smallpox vaccine in light of disclosure that large cache of vaccine is available to control bioterrorist attack; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disclosure that a large cache of smallpox vaccine is available to control a bioterrorist attack has put an unusual focus on the vaccine -- the first effective immunization ever developed.</p>
        <p>Edward Jenner introduced a smallpox vaccine in 1796. Although it took nearly two centuries, Jenner's vaccine was the weapon that health workers used to eradicate the viral disease from the world in 1980. Wiping out a disease that can kill 30 percent of its victims was a public health triumph, and the success eliminated the need for anyone to be vaccinated over the last 22 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disclosure that a large cache of smallpox vaccine is available to control a bioterrorist attack has put an unusual focus on the vaccine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disclosure that a large cache of smallpox vaccine is available to control a bioterrorist attack has put an unusual focus on the vaccine -- the first effective immunization ever developed.</p>
        <p>Edward Jenner introduced a smallpox vaccine in 1796. Although it took nearly two centuries, Jenner's vaccine was the weapon that health workers used to eradicate the viral disease from the world in 1980. Wiping out a disease that can kill 30 percent of its victims was a public health triumph, and the success eliminated the need for anyone to be vaccinated over the last 22 years.</p>
        <p>But the world now faces a quandary: determining the most effective way to use the vaccine to thwart the threat of a bioterrorist attack.</p>
        <p>The United States stopped vaccinations for smallpox in 1972, leaving the youngest Americans with no immunity to it. Older people face uncertainty about the durability of their vaccinations.</p>
        <p>Vaccinating every American now would immediately eliminate the threat of a bioterrorist smallpox attack. But the vaccine can be hazardous, and the available supply of 77 million doses is insufficient to cover the 285 million Americans.</p>
        <p>Widespread vaccination would lead to at least 150 deaths of Americans, and thousands more would suffer brain damage and other serious complications. The risks rise for people with impaired immune systems.</p>
        <p>Such risks were considered acceptable when smallpox was around. But events have changed the ratio of risks and benefits. Incidence of immune deficiency is not precisely known but is estimated to be higher than it was before 1972, especially with the onset of AIDS and new treatments for cancer.</p>
        <p>Because the hazards of smallpox vaccine pose a risk that health officials fear many people do not fully understand, some medical leaders have called for a dialogue to educate people about the issues before an attack occurs.</p>
        <p>One reason the vaccine poses risks is that it is crude by today's standards.</p>
        <p>Smallpox vaccine has traditionally been made by placing a strain of vaccinia, a cousin of the smallpox virus, on the cut skin of a calf, which is killed a week later. Then scientists remove hair and the microbes that normally live on the skin to prepare the vaccine.</p>
        <p>The government has ordered 209 million doses of vaccine that is prepared with that same strain, called the New York Board of Health strain. But calves will not be used. Instead, scientists will grow the vaccinia on cells in test tubes. The vaccine, expected by year's end, presumably will be safer because it is developed by a cleaner method.</p>
        <p>Until then supplies will be insufficient to cover the population, federal officials say. The government owns 15.4 million doses. Those can now be expanded to at least 77 million, based on findings from recent tests showing that the vaccine can be safely diluted five times and still be as potent as the original.</p>
        <p>The newly disclosed cache of up to 90 million doses will be donated by the drug company Aventis Pasteur. Some batches date from 1958, when companies since acquired by Aventis Pasteur made the vaccine the traditional way. The cache could swell the supply to about 167 million doses.</p>
        <p>Rumors have circulated since at least the mid-1990's about the existence of frozen stores of tens of millions of doses of smallpox vaccine. Aventis Pasteur officials said they told the Department of Health and Human Services about its stockpile years ago and had discussed plans to destroy it. But because destroying the cache was not a high priority, the vaccine was saved. Tommy G. Thompson, the department secretary, said Aventis Pasteur officials first approached him office in October after the anthrax attack.</p>
        <p>Whether the cache could be diluted five times to provide 450 million doses in an emergency awaits results of tests that have not begun, government officials said. The tests are to be performed on volunteers and are expected to take two months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said the government still planned to adhere to its policy issued a few months ago: to fight a smallpox attack the way the disease was eradicated. Known as ring containment, the plan calls for vaccinating after an attack occurs and limiting vaccination to people who had contact with a suspected or confirmed case of smallpox.</p>
        <p>THE DOCTOR'S WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
