<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adults Sidestep Serious Talks With Teenagers, Survey Finds</title>
    <meta content="Y09ADU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/09/national/09ADUL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1261457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lutheran Brotherhood</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8123AF93AA35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adults Sidestep Serious Talks With Teenagers, Survey Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Survey commissioned by Lutheran Brotherhood, financial services organization that serves Lutheran families, finds adults avoid talking to youngsters about budgeting, saving and giving to charity in much same way that they recoil from advising them about sex; its findings discussed (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Adults avoid talking to youngsters about budgeting, saving and giving to charity in much the same way that they recoil from advising them about sex, according to a survey released yesterday.</p>
        <p>Their reticence stems partly from a failure to practice what they preach and from a fear of being found out, according to the survey, which was commissioned by Lutheran Brotherhood, a financial services organization that serves Lutheran families, and the Search Institute, a social science research firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Adults avoid talking to youngsters about budgeting, saving and giving to charity in much the same way that they recoil from advising them about sex, according to a survey released yesterday.</p>
        <p>Their reticence stems partly from a failure to practice what they preach and from a fear of being found out, according to the survey, which was commissioned by Lutheran Brotherhood, a financial services organization that serves Lutheran families, and the Search Institute, a social science research firm.</p>
        <p>The survey of 1,425 adults, which was conducted last spring by the Gallup organization, suggests that a host of other meaningful subjects make adults tongue-tied in front of adolescents and young adults, including personal values, cultural differences and community service.</p>
        <p>''The consistent theme I get from parents is, 'I know I haven't done well in this myself,' '' said Nathan Dungan, the vice president of stewardship and brand development for Lutheran Brotherhood, which is based in Minneapolis. ''They're afraid of owning up to their own shortcomings.''</p>
        <p>The survey suggests that the only serious subjects that most adults are comfortable broaching with young people concern being successful in school and having respect for adults.</p>
        <p>The survey leaves no doubt that adults consider the very issues they avoid to be of critical importance. Seventy-five percent of those interviewed said they felt a duty to provide financial guidance to young adults; 77 percent put a premium on ''teaching respect for cultural differences''; and 73 percent said that they had a responsibility to discuss personal values with young people.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to having these conversations, most adults say that they, and other adults they know, do not follow through. Only 36 percent said that they or their acquaintances had tutored young people about money, a similar percentage to those who had counseled children about personal values or instructed them about respecting the qualities that make various cultures unique.</p>
        <p>The figures are largely consistent no matter a person's income, education or racial or ethnic background, the survey found.</p>
        <p>The authors of a study based on the survey, ''Grading Grown-Ups: American Adults Report on Their Real Relationships with Kids,'' say that one reason underlying adults' shyness is age-old and rooted in the disconnect between the generations.</p>
        <p>''There is some discomfort in being in dialogue with young people, because it makes us feel vulnerable,'' said Peter L. Benson, the president of the Search Institute, which is also in Minneapolis. ''There are gaps in language and image and interest.''</p>
        <p>Deborah Harvill-Ash, 43, a part-time actress and humor writer from Coronado, Calif., said that raising issues of money with her 11- and 14-year-old daughters induces as many butterflies in her stomach as talking to them about the ''nuts and bolts'' of conception.</p>
        <p>''I don't know why money would seem as personal as sex, but it does,'' said Ms. Harvill-Ash, who is married to a naval officer. ''I was brought up to believe that you took care of your money, but it was tacky to talk about it. My parents figured they should handle everything.''</p>
        <p>Though she has yet to take the plunge in engaging her daughters on money, Ms. Harvill-Ash said she knew that her advice would be essential at a time of such prosperity, when ''the outside world keeps telling them, 'Buy this, buy this, buy this.' ''</p>
        <p>In contrast, Rich Mahler, 41, a life insurance salesman for Lutheran Brotherhood on Staten Island, said he had forced himself to wade into waters that his parents would not, telling his 15- and 17-year-old sons that they were not too young to engage in financial planning.</p>
        <p>''I talk to them about every penny that they earn,'' Mr. Mahler said. ''I say, 'Give 10 percent to the church, and put away the next 10 percent for savings.' The rest is for expenses, gas money, and if there's anything left over, put that away, too. They practice that, as do I.''</p>
        <p>The authors of the study believe that the key to breaking through to young people on such critical issues is for Americans to grapple with those topics as neighborhoods and communities, with various adults taking on particular issues with groups of young people in a way that sounds almost utopian.</p>
        <p>The study's author's pointed to Mr. Mahler as a role model who has staged free seminars in local churches for 40 or 50 adolescents and their parents on such subjects as the value of a dollar and the many things that can be done with $100.</p>
        <p>''Parents love them,'' Mr. Mahler said. ''A lot of times when kids hear advice from another adult, they listen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
