<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Than an Ocean Separates Two Series</title>
    <meta content="27PRIX$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/27/sports/27PRIX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monaco Grand Prix</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indianapolis 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">North American Sports Car Racing Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Monaco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Austria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indianapolis 500 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Monaco</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Indianapolis (Indiana)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bogotá</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Austria</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Brazil</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Formula One</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Jaguar</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DF143CF934A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Than an Ocean Separates Two Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>MONACO, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times foreign correspondent John F Burns article, on eve of Indianapolis 500 and Monaco Grand Prix, discusses differences between European Formula One competition and auto racing in United States, highlighted by Formula One's dependence on technology and away from skilled driving required by Nascar racers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the first decades of the 20th century, the narrow, twisting harborside streets that are host to the Monaco Grand Prix and the blindingly fast sweeps of the Indianapolis 500 have defined motor racing on opposite sides of the Atlantic -- and mirrored, in their high-octane, ear-splitting way, something of the broader differences that characterize the sporting cultures in Europe and America.</p>
        <p>But if it has been so ever since the first running of the Indy 500 in 1911 and the inaugural Monaco race in 1929, there has rarely been a time when the contrasts have been more marked. When the races start on Sunday, a few hours apart, the technology employed in the cars, the nature of the contests, and even the drivers' racing styles at the two events will be as different as are the yachts, casinos and $2,500-a-night hotel suites of Monaco from the more prosaic environs of Speedway, Ind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since the first decades of the 20th century, the narrow, twisting harborside streets that are host to the Monaco Grand Prix and the blindingly fast sweeps of the Indianapolis 500 have defined motor racing on opposite sides of the Atlantic -- and mirrored, in their high-octane, ear-splitting way, something of the broader differences that characterize the sporting cultures in Europe and America.</p>
        <p>But if it has been so ever since the first running of the Indy 500 in 1911 and the inaugural Monaco race in 1929, there has rarely been a time when the contrasts have been more marked. When the races start on Sunday, a few hours apart, the technology employed in the cars, the nature of the contests, and even the drivers' racing styles at the two events will be as different as are the yachts, casinos and $2,500-a-night hotel suites of Monaco from the more prosaic environs of Speedway, Ind.</p>
        <p>This year, the contrasts are a talking point in Monaco, Formula One's showcase event, in part because of the presence here of Juan Pablo Montoya, the 25-year-old Colombian who won last year's Indianapolis 500 in his first attempt, and who now starts among the favorites at Monaco, again as a rookie. Montoya, whose hard-charging ways electrified spectators and television audiences in two years of Indy-car racing, is having a similar impact in Formula One, which he joined at the end of last year for an annual salary said to be about $8 million.</p>
        <p>Even before he has won a Formula One race, European enthusiasts are comparing the prodigious talent of Montoya -- a Bogotá architect's son with the build, lightning-fast reflexes and aggression of a featherweight boxer -- to Juan Manuel Fangio, the Argentinian who won five world drivers' championships in the 1950's. But beyond that, rave reviews for Montoya's Grand Prix performances have given impetus to a wider debate about the high technology direction of Formula One that is carrying the sport ever further away from the less complex technology, but more open racing, of Indy cars.</p>
        <p>As the Formula One teams geared up for the race here this week, talk in the teams' gleaming motor homes beside the harbor was of the lessons Indy-car racing might have for Formula One. These would include rules changes to restrict the multimillion-dollar technology that critics like Niki Lauda, a three-time Formula One champion from Austria, say is turning Formula One cars into computer-driven rocket ships leaving their drivers little to do but steer and brake.</p>
        <p>The calls for change are mostly from veterans of Indy racing like Bobby Rahal, an Indy 500 winner who now runs Jaguar's struggling Formula One team. Much of the Formula One establishment remains steadfastly opposed, including the Ferrari and McLaren-Mercedes squads that dominate the sport, and the Williams-BMW unit, Montoya's team, which is snapping at the front-runners' heels.</p>
        <p>Formula One's commercial success has made it harder for people like Lauda and Rahal, along with Emerson Fittipaldi, a Brazilian who won the Indy 500 twice and was a double world champion in Formula One, to push their heresy: the idea that Formula One has fallen into a trap by embracing cutting-edge technologies banned in Indy racing, only to find that the resulting spectacle is often less appealing than the less high tech, but often more closely contested, Indy-car races.</p>
        <p>Several top drivers, including Michael Schumacher, the Ferrari driver, and Montoya, have said they would prefer more emphasis on driver skills. But the protests have been low key. Schumacher, a 32-year-old German who dominates Grand Prix racing, is said to earn upward of $100 million a year. But until Montoya came on the scene, many races were high-speed processions, with a handful of lead changes.</p>
        <p>Rahal, 48, is part of the Indy racing establishment, as winner of the 1986 Indy 500 and last year as interim director of the CART single-seater racing series, Formula One's closest equivalent in the United States. In the Jaguar job, he has found himself an outsider, arguing for technology restrictions that other Formula One teams dismiss out of hand.</p>
        <p>''There has always been an elitism in Formula One,'' he said in an interview in the Jaguar motor home. ''It's a very closed society. In America, there's been a much greater recognition of the sporting side of motor racing, whereas here it's much more of a technological exercise. In America, we've tried to put the spectators first. In Europe, the attitude seems to be, 'If you don't like it, it's your problem. We aren't going to change.' ''</p>
        <p>Rahal said recent rules changes will mean that Formula One cars next year will have fully automatic transmissions shifting gears at points on the track preset into on-board computers. Starting earlier this year, teams were allowed to use computer-driven traction control systems that eliminate wheel spin, and launch control systems that reduce starts to a push of a button on the steering wheel.</p>
        <p>In the CART series, even the semiautomatic gearboxes currently in use in Formula One, requiring the driver to initiate gear-change sequences by squeezing a paddle on the steering wheel, are outlawed.</p>
        <p>More than anything else, though, it is Montoya, the Colombian newcomer, who is helping to sweep aside Formula One's assumptions of superiority over Indy racing. For the first time in years, there is a driver who is widely regarded as a potential superstar in the Schumacher mold. After winning the world drivers' championship last year for the third time, Schumacher is only four races short of the highest number of grand prix -- 51 -- ever won by a driver.</p>
        <p>In Monaco, Schumacher will again start as favorite, willed on around the 1.9-mile, 95-mile-an-hour circuit by a sea of supporters with red Ferrari flags. But he faces a new kind of challenge from Montoya, and he does not like it. So far this year, Schumacher has won three races, and Montoya none. But Montoya has thrown down a gauntlet.</p>
        <p>In Brazil last month, he overtook Schumacher going into a diving bend with a maneuver that had Formula One veterans reaching for superlatives. The maneuver came to nothing when a tail-end driver speared Montoya's car from the rear. In Austria two weeks ago, the Colombian again raced wheel-to-wheel with the German until the two cars collided. When the German protested Montoya's racing tactics, the Colombian struck back.</p>
        <p>''Does he think he has a divine grace not to be overtaken?'' Montoya said, when told of Schumacher's complaints. ''Schumacher won't intimidate me because I'm not as psychologically fragile as other drivers.''</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
