<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Starters, Relax, and Then Eat in Style</title>
    <meta content="27DINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vine Bistro (Putnam, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DB133DF934A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Starters, Relax, and Then Eat in Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of Vine Bistro restaurant in Putnam, Conn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the northeast corner of Putnam, antiquing is the name of the game, and after shoppers have exhausted themselves browsing in local shops, they can seek a respite at the Vine Bistro, a stylish cafe in the town center.</p>
        <p>In the last 10 years, this little town has turned itself around. Putnam, once a manufacturing center, was in serious decline until the abandoned stores were revived as antiques shops and marketplaces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the northeast corner of Putnam, antiquing is the name of the game, and after shoppers have exhausted themselves browsing in local shops, they can seek a respite at the Vine Bistro, a stylish cafe in the town center.</p>
        <p>In the last 10 years, this little town has turned itself around. Putnam, once a manufacturing center, was in serious decline until the abandoned stores were revived as antiques shops and marketplaces.</p>
        <p>It seemed only natural that when shoppers came, places to eat followed. But no other place has the smart look and menu of the Vine Bistro. Although its gustatory reach sometimes exceeds its grasp, Vine Bistro offers a delightful reprieve from shopping.</p>
        <p>One dinner starter was eggplant rollatini, two large tubes of paper-thin eggplant in a slightly crunchy batter filled with ricotta, mozzarella and Parmesan cheeses, and surrounded by a refreshingly light sauce of fresh tomatoes and basil. Our second choice was less successful: portobello mushrooms (undercooked to the point of raw) sautéed with spinach, roasted red peppers, garlic and olive oil.</p>
        <p>Our entrées produced better results. Veal piccata consisted of three chewy escalopes, floured, sautéed and served in a delicious thick gravy with lemon and capers. The dish was accompanied by smashed potatoes (skins, lumps and all) and steamed broccoli (undercooked, not al dente).</p>
        <p>Chicken d'vine, our other entrée, was a mélange of artichoke hearts, chicken, tomatoes, mushrooms and sliced black olives (canned) in a pleasing herb-accented broth.</p>
        <p>Before the entrée course, we were served (gratis) a huge salad on a plate too small to hold all the greens and croutons. What was really off-putting was the raspberry vinaigrette, which lacked vinegar and was thick and syrupy, more like a dessert sauce than a salad dressing.</p>
        <p>Most desserts also erred on the side of quantity. Apple-stuffed spice cake, a serving large enough for three, had a thick sugary shell and sliced baked apples. Its freezer coldness set our teeth on edge. The chocolate mud cake was just as gargantuan, also ice cold, but had enough chocolate richness to keep our chocolate fan happy.</p>
        <p>Lunch brought a more consistent experience. The fried mozzarella that two of us shared as an appetizer was lovely. Two delicately fried ovals of cheese in a superlight batter came in an airy, frothy fresh marinara sauce dotted with capers.</p>
        <p>One main courses was vodka rigatoni with Gulf shrimp. The dish consisted of ribbed tubes of pasta and giant juicy shrimp tossed with fresh cooked tomatoes. We asked for the cream sauce on the side, which was a wise decision because the sauce was thin and milky. Without it, the shrimp sang forth loud and clear.</p>
        <p>Our other entrée, firecracker shrimp, was a special: a generous salad of medium-size shrimp, vermicelli, tasty greens and a month's supply of fresh cilantro (which works better as an accent than as the star) in a sassy sauce with a spark of heat -- if not a real firecracker bang. The dish was garnished with two large wings of deep-fried wontons. All in all, it was an agreeable dish.</p>
        <p>Our dessert prize was pumpkin Cognac cheesecake: it was light, creamy and totally rewarding and made on the premise. Frutta di Bosco was also tasty. Touted as imported from Italy, the dessert combined a shortbread base and custard filling, topped with a lavish display of red and black currants, raspberries and blackberries.</p>
        <p>The lunch and dinner menu is the same, with lower prices and marginally smaller portions served at lunch.</p>
        <p>The prices are moderate and the portions are humongous. A three-course dinner for two came to $48, before tax, tip and drinks. The wine list is small, mostly Californian, but we enjoyed a surprisingly attractive local product, a Chardonnay from Sharpe Hill Vineyard in Pomfret for $20 a bottle. The vineyard's red Seraph, also $20, was much less satisfying. Wine is also available by the glass.</p>
        <p>The appealing simplicity of Vine Bistro's decor is sometimes offset by awkwardness in the kitchen. Yet there are enough successes to make this a worthwhile stop for lunch or dinner. It is clearly the best game in town, culinarily speaking.</p>
        <p>The Vine Bistro  85 Main Street, Putnam. (860) 928-1660.</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A low-key, modish cafe with wood floors and tables, comfortable banquettes, soft lighting and two-tone avocado-colored walls with framed art.  NOISE LEVEL -- Subdued and conversational.  SERVICE -- Friendly, but inexperienced staff.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Fresh fried mozzarella, eggplant rollatini, firecracker shrimp, vodka rigatoni, veal piccata, chicken d'vine, pumpkin Cognac cheesecake, frutta di bosco.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch $6.95 to $12.95; Dinner $8.95 to $23.95.  CREDIT CARDS -- Most major cards accepted.  HOURS -- 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Tuesday to Sunday, Dinner, 5 p.m. to 9 p.m. Tuesday to Saturday, 5 p.m. to 7 p.m. Sunday. Closed Monday.  RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Street level.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
