<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/Kansas City, Kan.; A City Builds Its Hopes on New Kansas Speedway</title>
    <meta content="27COMM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1296645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nascar Winston Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kansas City (Kan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas Speedway</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Shirley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EEDF103DF934A15756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/Kansas City, Kan.; A City Builds Its Hopes on New Kansas Speedway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHIRLEY CHRISTIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Christian, Shirley</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Kan.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kansas Speedway, newest stop on Nascar auto racing circuit and new home of Winston Cup race, promises to produce economic development in Kansas City, Kan; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the end of September, on a hillside in the western outskirts of this city, the princes of auto racing will take off in a Winston Cup race before 75,000 fans at the $224 million Kansas Speedway, the newest stop on the Nascar circuit. This explosion of horsepower is expected to produce reverberations of economic development in a struggling city.</p>
        <p>''Imagine a state fair and multiply it a hundred times -- that's what we're bringing here, but more upscale,'' said Jeff Boerger, vice president and general manager of the Kansas Speedway. ''The economic impact will be huge,'' he added, ''like having the Super Bowl and the baseball All-Star Game at the same time and place.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the end of September, on a hillside in the western outskirts of this city, the princes of auto racing will take off in a Winston Cup race before 75,000 fans at the $224 million Kansas Speedway, the newest stop on the Nascar circuit. This explosion of horsepower is expected to produce reverberations of economic development in a struggling city.</p>
        <p>''Imagine a state fair and multiply it a hundred times -- that's what we're bringing here, but more upscale,'' said Jeff Boerger, vice president and general manager of the Kansas Speedway. ''The economic impact will be huge,'' he added, ''like having the Super Bowl and the baseball All-Star Game at the same time and place.''</p>
        <p>But the Winston Cup weekend will happen only once a year. While there will also be other racing events occasionally, city officials and business leaders in this town, the smaller of the two Kansas Citys, decided they wanted more.</p>
        <p>The unified city-county government stepped in and bought a 400-acre tract adjacent to the 1,250-acre speedway grounds and earlier this year announced the first tenants for a planned shopping and commercial development. They predict that residential development will soon follow.</p>
        <p>Incorporated in 1859 by Wyandot Indians displaced from Ohio, Kansas City, Kan., has a colorful history distinct from its Missouri counterpart to the east, across the wide confluence of the Missouri and Kansas rivers.</p>
        <p>A refuge for fleeing slaves during the Civil War, it later grew into a center of railroading, milling and meatpacking. Waves of Mexican and East European immigrants were recruited early in the 20th century to operate the railroads and hoist beef carcasses for Armour, Swift and Cudahy.</p>
        <p>After the end of World War II, the town, known locally as K.C.K., became increasingly viewed as a blue-collar, minority enclave with a serious crime problem, major social needs, a declining tax base and government by cronyism. Shopping for anything but essentials gradually dried up; the only movie theater in business today is an old drive-in. Residents who prosper tend to move across the county line on the south into the booming Johnson County suburbs or elsewhere in the five-county, bistate metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>While K.C.K. has been almost barren of shopping locales in recent years, the rest of the metropolitan area is saturated with malls, so K.C.K. leaders were looking for something beyond the usual mall fare to draw people. They believe they have found that in Nebraska Furniture Mart, an Omaha store that bills itself as the largest volume furniture dealer in the country, and Cabela's, a supplier of fishing and hunting gear with a cultlike following among many of the 75 million people who receive its catalogs.</p>
        <p>ANCHORED by these two stores, the shopping district is expected to be a tourist draw on its own. Coupled with the racetrack, the area is projected to draw five million to six million people a year, not just from around the metropolitan area but from at least six surrounding states. That will help bring back into K.C.K. and its county, Wyandotte, some of the sales-tax revenue that has been soaked up by the surrounding richer communities.</p>
        <p>''The vision for what we are calling the Tourism District started four years ago, after the city had won the speedway competition,'' explained William F. Crandall, vice president the Zimmer Management Company, which will act as the developer for the area adjacent to the speedway. ''The mayor and other people concerned concluded that they should capitalize on this icon -- the racetrack -- so they hired a master developer, our company, to look for a way to make this a tourist destination.''</p>
        <p>Besides Nebraska Furniture and Cabela's, Zimmer has obtained commitments for a 12-screen multiplex by Warren Theaters of Wichita and a 200-seat Applebee's restaurant. It has also reached agreement with a mall developer that will sign smaller tenants.</p>
        <p>Nebraska Furniture Mart, owned by the Berkshire Hathaway Corporation, the company headed by the legendary investor Warren E. Buffett, plans a 450,000-square-foot store and a 130,000-square-foot distribution center. Cabela's, which plans a 175,000-square-foot store, is to start construction this summer and be open in September 2002. Nebraska Furniture Mart and the first part of the shopping mall are to be completed in the fall of 2003. The cost of this first phase of the retail area is an estimated $240 million.</p>
        <p>Douglas G. Bach, special projects manager in the county administrator's office, said that despite the overwhelming size of the retail area, the goal is to achieve ''a real quality development,'' using state bonds to create beauty around the asphalt. ''We want to create a sense of place,'' he said. ''We'll have a grand boulevard, a pleasant walking area with wonderful landscaping, maybe incorporating native limestone.''</p>
        <p>All of this is a long way from the heart of K.C.K. on the riverfront. More than 100 blocks stretch west from the decayed center city to the pastoral speedway site. Along the way are residential areas that gradually grow sparse, then give way to rolling farmland where cattle and horses graze.</p>
        <p>The effort to attract the speedway began as Carol Marinovich, a former teacher who was elected mayor in 1995, was in a campaign to unify the governments of the city and Wyandotte County. After the unification measure passed in 1997, she was elected mayor and chief executive of the combined government, then re-elected this spring.</p>
        <p>The mayor admits she was not a racing fan and had no idea of the growing economic importance of big-time auto racing when she went to the first meeting with representatives of the International Speedway Corporation, the company that, with the opening now of the Kansas Speedway, has 14 tracks around the country. International Speedway was looking for a large site somewhere in the five-county metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the site offered by K.C.K. won against a site on the outskirts of Kansas City, Mo. The Kansas group enjoyed strong support from the state government and Gov. Bill Graves, who hopes the raceway will help move Kansas out of the bottom ranks of states as a tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>The incentive package they offered abates property taxes on the speedway for 30 years as well as state and local sales taxes. The Board of Public Utilities added a $3 million grant toward electricity and water costs.</p>
        <p>City officials argue that the potential payoff made the concessions worthwhile and point out that the speedway helped to attract the big anchor stores. For the commercial area, there is no property tax abatement.</p>
        <p>''The 400 acres was bringing in just $15,000 a year in real estate taxes before we bought the land,'' the mayor said. ''After Phase 1 of the commercial area is completed, it will bring in $5 million a year in real estate taxes. That is money that can be used for services throughout the community. If we don't increase our economic viability, we can't put more dollars into services.''</p>
        <p>The new Kansas Speedway sits at the intersection of two interstate highways: I-70, a major east-west route, and I-435, which circles the greater metropolitan area. Mr. Boerger said this would make it possible to get spectators in and out of the speedway for an event in three and a half hours, even when the grandstand is expanded to its planned eventual size of 150,000 seats.</p>
        <p>The grandstand, painted the blue and yellow of the Kansas state flag, overlooks a 1.5-mile tri-oval track -- an oval that has a bowed-out front stretch -- that handles speeds of 180 to 200 miles an hour. There is free parking on grass for 65,000 cars, plus rental space for recreational vehicles. Race drivers have another area in which to park their million-dollar RV's.</p>
        <p>There is a large open-air space in which entertainers will perform before races, and a freestanding 5,000-square-foot kitchen is to feed up to 150,000 people. Sixty-eight corporate suites were snapped up at annual lease rates ranging from $29,000 for a 601-square foot suite for 32 guests to $70,000 for a 1,245-square-foot suite for 86 guests. Cabanalike ''hospitality chalets'' are available for seasonal rental for large parties. The University of Kansas Medical Center will operate a full trauma unit in a separate building a short distance from the track and grandstand.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boerger says this all adds up to ''the most fan- and driver-friendly track on the circuit.'' And the mayor still laughs when she remembers her initial ambivalence about the speedway.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
