<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sosa Deal Is Getting Closer To Reality</title>
    <meta content="29BASE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/29/sports/baseball/29baseball.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sosa, Sammy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4D6143BF93AA15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sosa Deal Is Getting Closer To Reality</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sosa Deal Is Getting Closer To Reality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Cubs are reportedly close to trading outfielder Sammy Sosa to Baltimore Orioles (S)g</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs are moving closer to achieving their No. 1 goal for the winter -- trading Sammy Sosa.</p>
        <p>A baseball official said the Cubs engaged in serious talks yesterday with the Baltimore Orioles and another team, believed to be the Washington Nationals, but he said that more work needed to be done before they reached agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs are moving closer to achieving their No. 1 goal for the winter - trading Sammy Sosa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chicago Cubs are moving closer to achieving their No. 1 goal for the winter -- trading Sammy Sosa.</p>
        <p>A baseball official said the Cubs engaged in serious talks yesterday with the Baltimore Orioles and another team, believed to be the Washington Nationals, but he said that more work needed to be done before they reached agreement.</p>
        <p>''This is a different kind of deal,'' the official said, asking not to be identified because he did not want to risk undermining a trade. ''There are Major League Baseball issues, union issues and there's potentially more than one club involved.''</p>
        <p>He mentioned the Orioles but would not identify the other team, saying only that the Cubs had ''some fairly serious talks'' with it.</p>
        <p>In any trade the Cubs make, they would probably have to agree to pay most of Sosa's $17 million salary for this season. Commissioner Bud Selig would have to approve the amount of cash in the deal.</p>
        <p>Sosa's contract also has an option for 2006 that becomes guaranteed with an $18 million salary if he is traded. However, the players association has indicated that it would allow Sosa to waive the guarantee.</p>
        <p>The Cubs want to trade the 37-year-old Sosa, the only player in history to hit more than 60 home runs three times, because they have become disenchanted with him. He has had problems with Manager Dusty Baker, and he incurred the wrath of players, club officials and Cubs fans by leaving Wrigley Field without Baker's approval on the last day of last season.</p>
        <p>Red Sox to Get Ball for a Year</p>
        <p>The baseball Doug Mientkiewicz caught for the out that ended the Boston Red Sox' 86-year championship drought is going back to the team -- for one year, anyway.</p>
        <p>The club and Mientkiewicz, its former first baseman, announced yesterday that while no decision had been made on who owns the ball, it would be encased in a special plaque and would join the World Series trophy on its victory tour.</p>
        <p>''Doug was a key part of our stretch run and postseason victories, and he won over our fans in a very short period of time,'' said Larry Lucchino, the Red Sox' president.</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz was traded to the Mets on Wednesday. As a late-inning replacement for Kevin Millar in Game 4 of the World Series in St. Louis, he recorded the final putout of the clinching 3-0 victory. Edgar Renteria hit the ball to pitcher Keith Foulke, who threw to first.</p>
        <p>Mientkiewicz, a 2001 Gold Glove winner with Minnesota, kept the ball. The team asked him for it this month, and the decision was made to let the Red Sox display it.</p>
        <p>''There was never a fight, there was never words exchanged'' over ownership of the ball, Mientkiewicz said this week. ''It was very cordial, and we worked something out. I want the fans to see it, and that's what both the Red Sox and I agreed on. They waited a long time to see that ball and to live it. ''</p>
        <p>He also said he ''probably'' would get the ball back after a year. (AP)</p>
        <p>Criticizing Other Owners</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh Pirates' Kevin McClatchy lashed out at other baseball owners yesterday for a return of free-agent spending that he feared might steer some clubs close to bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>McClatchy is the Pirates' managing general partner, and he serves on baseball's executive council and long-range labor committee. He warned of a growing division between big-payroll and small-market clubs which could lead to contentious owners meetings and a much-harder stance during the next labor negotiations. The current labor deal runs until December 2006.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what happened; maybe they drank some funny water, but they all decided they were back on the binge,'' said McClatchy, whose team has a relatively low payroll. (AP)</p>
        <p>Yankees Add 18 Players</p>
        <p>Outfielder Doug Glanville, utilityman Damian Rolls and the right-hander Brad Voyles were among 18 players who agreed to minor league contracts with the Yankees yesterday.</p>
        <p>Glanville will receive a one-year, $550,000 contract if he is added to the major league roster. Rolls would receive $600,000 and Voyles $350,000.</p>
        <p>Also agreeing to minor league deals were infielder Homer Bush; the left-hander Danny Borrell; the right-handers Aaron Small and Marc Valdes; infielders Russ Johnson and Caonabo Cosme; outfielders Mike Vento, Noah Hall and Colin Porter; and catchers David Parrish, Joe Depastino, Ryan Hankins, Irwil Rojas, Omir Santos and Jon-Mark Sprowl. (AP)</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
