<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Best Fighter in the World? Whitaker Taking a Jab at It</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WORLD BOXING COUNCIL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WISE, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITAKER, PERNELL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGIRT, JAMES (BUDDY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7DC143DF930A35753C1A962958260" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Best Fighter in the World? Whitaker Taking a Jab at It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WISE, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>NORFOLK, Va., Oct. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seth Abraham's roadies were already cleaning up the television cable on Saturday night when his marquee Home Box Office fighter, Pernell (Sweetpea) Whitaker, stepped up to speak.</p>
        <p>"It was as if he were a pitcher, hitting the black of the plate with each pitch," the HBO president said with a genuine look of astonishment, sitting in the second row at the post-fight news conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seth Abraham's roadies were already cleaning up the television cable on Saturday night when his marquee Home Box Office fighter, Pernell (Sweetpea) Whitaker, stepped up to speak.</p>
        <p>"It was as if he were a pitcher, hitting the black of the plate with each pitch," the HBO president said with a genuine look of astonishment, sitting in the second row at the post-fight news conference.</p>
        <p>Whitaker, who had shown his full seven-punch repertory earlier in the evening while punishing James (Buddy) McGirt for 12 rounds and keeping his World Boxing Council welterweight title, did not hear Abraham.</p>
        <p>But he did mention "saving the family," in reference to his promoter, Dan Duva. Two of Duva's Main Events fighters -- Lennox Lewis was one -- had been knocked out in world title fights during the past three weeks, and so Duva and Whitaker shared a laugh over the very thought of Duva's champion surviving as the promoter's meal ticket for the moment. "He carried us on his back again," Duva said.</p>
        <p>Funny, no? Whitaker is lugging boxing around on his sinewy shoulders these days.</p>
        <p>Picking up the flag of HBO, Main Events and a sport short of championship-caliber fighters, Whitaker showed a crowd of 9,158 why he may be the best in his profession. "I hate to brag on myself," Whitaker said after he beat McGirt by a unanimous decision, "but I can say I'm the best, pound for pound."</p>
        <p>It was Whitaker's second unanimous decision victory over the Brentwood, L.I., native in 19 months. While he was asked repeatedly about the prospect of a second fight with Julio Cesar Chavez, Whitaker seemed to realize that his accomplishment no longer needed validation from the Mexican champion.</p>
        <p>"The public wants to see that fight, but I don't beg for anybody," he said, alluding to a controversial draw with Chavez in September 1993. "People can see for themselves who the best in the world is."</p>
        <p>Ringing combinations off McGirt's clean-shaven head, Whitaker improved to 34-1-1, with 15 knockouts. Though he was knocked down once, he dictated the pace with counterpunching that frustrated the challenger in nearly every round.</p>
        <p>McGirt (64-4-1, 44 knockouts) fought as well as he could, standing toe to toe and trading blows with Whitaker in the 11th and 12th rounds, but he didn't mount a serious challenge. McGirt's forehead was bruised afterward, and he fought with a welt under his left eye from the fifth round on.</p>
        <p>"He was more on his p's and q's this time," said McGirt, explaining the difference between their first fight on March 6, 1993, at Madison Square Garden, which also ended with Whitaker winning by decision. "His movement threw me off."</p>
        <p>McGirt had his left arm surgically repaired after the first fight and said he would be a two-armed fighter this time. He used the left hand, but it was no match for Whitaker's right jab.</p>
        <p>Steve Weisfeld of Cedar Grove, N.J., scored the fight 117-110; Chuck Giampa of Las Vegas, Nev., scored it 117-113, and Rudy Ortega of San Francisco had Whitaker winning by 118-112.</p>
        <p>Chants of "Sweetpea! Sweetpea!" were heard throughout the fight, as the Norfolk native treated his following to a fourth straight victory by decision at the Scope. He entered the ring in all-black satin, white tassels swinging from his shoes. McGirt was dressed in velvet.</p>
        <p>By the 10th round, McGirt's welt had a purple tint to it. Before going for broke in the final two rounds, McGirt wandered around the ring with his left eye swollen nearly shut.</p>
        <p>Whitaker's keys to victory were the same that he has been using to unlock HBO's vault -- he made $2.5 million, the second installment on his four-fight deal. They feature quick combinations -- wild flurries, reminiscent of Sugar Ray Leonard in his prime -- and a simple strategy of keeping his opponent off balance by changing styles.</p>
        <p>Early on Saturday night, he slipped in and out of trouble with his movement. In the middle and later rounds, Whitaker began flailing away with unanswered combinations.</p>
        <p>"Every round, he was changing," said Whitaker's trainer, George Benton. "McGirt would go back to his corner and they would tell him something that Pete was doing. By the next round, he was doing something else."</p>
        <p>More embarrassed than hurt by the second-round knockdown, Whitaker got off the canvas and began firing back with left hooks and right crosses, catching McGirt several times.</p>
        <p>"It was just a flash knockdown, it caught me off balance," Whitaker said. "It didn't bother me at all. It made me more aware of what I had to do. I still think I got the round."</p>
        <p>McGirt made $600,000. He and Whitaker both turned 30 in January, and McGirt admitted his career will be better off in another weight division. He had twice tried to tame the world's best 147-pounder, only to walk away with more respect for Whitaker than he had going into each fight.</p>
        <p>But he would not give the champion the pound-for-pound title yet. "The winner of the Roy Jones-James Toney fight gets that label," McGirt said, referring to the Nov. 18 showdown in Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Whitaker rolled his eyes when he asked to respond, then said, "No comment."  BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
