<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Heart of Protests to Con Ed: The Schools</title>
    <meta content="08CONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1060386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buchanan (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lombardi, Kate Stone</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DB163EF93BA35752C1A96E958260" item-length="1871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Heart of Protests to Con Ed: The Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lombardi, Kate Stone</byline>
      <dateline>BUCHANAN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Estimated 800 residents of Buchanan, NY, stage protest against Con Edison's effort to lower property taxes on its Indian Point nuclear reactors; request, if approved, would trim utility's taxes by about $16 million and slice Buchanan's school budget by $9.9 million; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not the first protest march against the Indian Point nuclear power plants here. But for this small village, which is home to three of the four nuclear plants in the state, the 800 or so people who turned out recently were not shouting warnings about radioactive meltdown or demanding that the plants be shut down. Instead, among the slogans shouted and the signs carried were these: ''Con Ed Is a Tax Dodger,'' ''Con Ed -- Con Men,'' ''Don't Nuke Our Taxes'' and ''Con Ed -- Don't Turn the Lights Out on My Education!''</p>
        <p>At issue is Consolidated Edison's effort to lower the property taxes on its Indian Point 1 and 2 nuclear reactors. The utility has filed a certiorari -- or tax reduction request -- in the town of Cortlandt to reduce its $40 million assessment by 65 percent. If successful, Con Edison would trim its taxes by roughly $16 million, a loss that would be absorbed by the village of Buchanan, the town of Cortlandt, the Hendrick Hudson School District and several other government entities. The school district would by far be the most affected -- $9.9 million, roughly a third of its budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not the first protest march against the Indian Point nuclear power plants here. But for this small village, which is home to three of the four nuclear plants in the state, the 800 or so people who turned out recently were not shouting warnings about radioactive meltdown or demanding that the plants be shut down. Instead, among the slogans shouted and the signs carried were these: ''Con Ed Is a Tax Dodger,'' ''Con Ed -- Con Men,'' ''Don't Nuke Our Taxes'' and ''Con Ed -- Don't Turn the Lights Out on My Education!''</p>
        <p>At issue is Consolidated Edison's effort to lower the property taxes on its Indian Point 1 and 2 nuclear reactors. The utility has filed a certiorari -- or tax reduction request -- in the town of Cortlandt to reduce its $40 million assessment by 65 percent. If successful, Con Edison would trim its taxes by roughly $16 million, a loss that would be absorbed by the village of Buchanan, the town of Cortlandt, the Hendrick Hudson School District and several other government entities. The school district would by far be the most affected -- $9.9 million, roughly a third of its budget.</p>
        <p>Residents here said they felt betrayed by the utility, adding that they have long supported the power plants, which sit in their backyard, and expected the utility in turn to support their town.</p>
        <p>''Thirty some odd years ago, when Con Edison came into our community and held public hearings, they talked about all the tax revenues that the municipalities and the school district would receive,'' said Linda D. Puglisi, Supervisor of the town of Cortlandt. ''How can they now come to us and ask for this kind of reduction? We've been good neighbors. When these plants have had problems and have been periodically shut down, we didn't call for their closing, we worked with them. And now this? How can they even consider doing this? It's outrageous.''</p>
        <p>Con Edison maintains that the property at Indian Point is significantly overassessed. The utility argues that as energy deregulation continues, the company needs to cut costs wherever possible. Michael J. Spall, a spokesman for Con Edison, said that for every dollar paid on a Con Edison bill, 20 cents reflects the company's cost for local, county and state property taxes. He added that the utility's tax costs were passed directly to customers, and if Con Ed were successful in lowering its taxes, customers' bills would be reduced. The certiorari filed in the town of Cortlandt is one of seven Con Edison has filed in Westchester. Con Ed has reached a negotiated settlement in three towns, the names of which it would not reveal, and has filed for judicial review in Greenburgh, New Castle and Mount Vernon. The utility has also filed other tax challenges elsewhere in the state.</p>
        <p>''Overassessment of utility property has become an important issue over the last few years,'' Mr. Spall said. ''We believe that property taxes are too high, and it's our obligation to all our customers to reduce them. The overassessments in the town of Cortlandt must be paid by all of our customers. It's simply unfair for those customers in Cortlandt to benefit at the expense of other customers in New York City and Westchester.''</p>
        <p>Residents of Cortlandt are appalled by that position. They say they have long been shouldering the burden of housing the nuclear plants and are now being asked to slash town services and school programs to save customers elsewhere in the state at best a few cents on their monthly bills. They argue that it is Con Edison's presence here that has lowered the property values and limited commercial development in the area. Further, town officials say that because of radioactive contamination, the prime riverfront property will be unusable -- and unable to generate future taxes -- for decades, if Con Edison were to leave the site.</p>
        <p>Also in question is whether nuclear plants should be viewed differently than other commercial property during a tax challenge. At the protest rally, when Mayor Alfred J. Donahue of Buchanan, handed a megaphone to Assemblywoman Sandra R. Galef, Democrat of Ossining, who was next to address the crowd, he inadvertently turned on a siren, which was part of the public address system. After a brief stunned silence, the siren was turned off, and the Mayor quipped, ''Don't worry folks, that was not Con Ed.'' The crowd laughed, but it was a reminder of the anxiety that those who live in the shadow of the Indian Point reactors face daily.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spall said the fact that the plants were nuclear was not relevant to the tax challenge. ''This is not a matter involving nuclear power,'' he said. ''This is a business matter. Taxes are based on the value of a piece of property, not its function.''</p>
        <p>Originally, Con Edison owned all three nuclear power plants in Buchanan. In 1974, the utility sold Indian Point 3 to the New York Power Authority. Because it was sold to a public utility, Indian Point 3 then went off the property tax roles, representing a cumulative loss to date of nearly $100 million in tax revenue, said Richard Levinson, a member of the Hendrick Hudson School Board.</p>
        <p>''We didn't cause Con Ed's financial problems,'' Mr. Levinson said. ''They made promises to us and when they had a problem they sold the plant, and they sold us out with it. Now the market has changed again, and Con Ed wants us to pony up another $17 million a year, so that by five years from now their bill will be $150 million that we will have paid that Con Ed promised to pay. I think we have to tell them, No more broken promises. You owe this community.''</p>
        <p>In a separate action, the town is lobbying to force the New York Power Authority to pay taxes on Indian Point 3, saying that another public utility, the Long Island Lighting Company, pays taxes on its power plants. Under its current ownership, Indian Point 3 was placed in 1994 on the Nuclear Regulatory Commission's watch list of the 10 most troubled reactors in the country. The power plant came off the list last year. Since 1991 the New York Power Authority has been fined more than $1 million for rules violations at both of its nuclear power plants, Indian Point 3 and the James A. Fitzpatrick reactor in Scriba, near Oswego.</p>
        <p>Indian Point 1, the oldest plant, was decommissioned more than 20 years ago. It is still used to store spent fuel rods, another source of contention. The town says Con Edison should be assessed on the property for the storage of radioactive waste on the site, arguing that the utility would have to pay huge amounts to store the rods elsewhere. But Mr. Spall, the company's spokesman, said: ''The spent fuel is considered to be personal property. Property tax is on the values of buildings and property, not personal materials.''</p>
        <p>Indian Point 2 has the best safety record of the plants but has not been without its troubles. Closed in October last year and fined a total of $440,000 by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the plant reopened last September. The plant's license runs until 2013, at which point Con Edison will decide whether to recondition it and apply to extend the license, or close it down. Mr. Spall said that it would cost $650 million to decommission the plant.</p>
        <p>Con Edison filed the tax grievance with the town of Cortlandt in June. The town's Assessment Review Board rejected the utility's request in September. Con Edison then filed an appeal, known as an Article 7, in State Supreme Court in White Plains. The village of Buchanan, the town of Cortlandt and the Hendrick Hudson School District have had continuing negotiations with Con Edison, but if no settlement is reached, the matter  will go to court, Mr. Spall said. He added if Con Edison lost its appeal, customers would see higher electric bills. Town and school officials are projecting the impact of the tax loss. Mr. Levinson, of the school board, said: ''We did some analysis of what we would have to cut if Con Ed was successful. Basically, you'd have to cut out every nonmandated program and raise taxes by 10 percent after that. We're talking about every sport, every club, transportation, all the advanced placement courses, all the remediation, our new early-intervention reading program, all gone. Music, art, gone. It would gut the district.''</p>
        <p>Also affected are the Verplanck Fire District, the Hendrick Hudson Free Library and Westchester County, which would lose more than $3 million in taxes. County Legislator George Oros, Republican of Cortlandt, said that all county residents would face a 1 percent increase on their property taxes. The town says that if Con Edison is granted its request, taxpayers who are paying $2,300 in school taxes would pay $3,500. Those with higher assessments and paying $4,600, for example, would pay $7,000.</p>
        <p>Residents say they cannot afford such increases. ''We moved here to protect ourselves from high taxes,'' said Jimmy Wilson, one of the protesters. ''I retired over a year ago, and if I knew this was going to happen, I wouldn't have. We're running scared. If this goes through, I'll lose my house.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spall said Con Edison would continue to pursue a settlement. ''We continue to negotiate in good faith to find a middle ground that does not have a significant impact on local services, yet fairly represents the value of the Indian Point property. However, we are willing and able to pursue our legal remedies if negotiations aren't successful. We're exercising our right to challenge our taxes like any other property owner.''</p>
        <p>Residents at the protest angrily disagreed. ''A nuclear power plant is not a house,'' Joanne Dyckman of Cortlandt said. ''For 20 years, I have lived within a quarter of a mile of the power plant, and now I get angry every time I drive past. I have two children in the school district, which will be severely affected. It's going to be really hard to pay your tax bill. I think Con Edison has a nerve, I really do. They should pay their tax bill like everybody else.''</p>
        <p>Jeanette Ladue of Montrose, who has two children in the school district, said: ''I didn't see Somers raising their hand when Con Ed wanted to build this plant. I didn't see Scarsdale raising their hand. Buchanan was good enough for Con Edison then. Now they don't want to pay the bill.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
