<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barak Favors Peace Deal That's Slower And in Steps</title>
    <meta content="Y01MID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/01/world/01MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001202T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1251593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D9103DF932A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barak Favors Peace Deal That's Slower And in Steps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Nov. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak says that he now favors incremental peace deal with Palestinians, with immediate handover of more territory and possible recognition of statehood, but a postponement of up to three years of crucial issues of Jerusalem and resettlement of Palestinian refugees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak said today that he now favored an incremental peace deal with the Palestinians, with an immediate handover of more territory and a possible recognition of statehood, but a postponement of up to three years of the crucial issues of Jerusalem and the resettlement of  Palestinian refugees.</p>
        <p>Seemingly abandoning his quest for an all-inclusive ''end to the conflict,'' Mr. Barak suggested in a speech to Israeli newspaper editors that the Palestinians might agree to an Israeli annexation of major Jewish settlements in the West Bank in return for a recognition of independence. Israel would give the Palestinians ''another 10 percent of the territory to create continuity, so they don't have to pass so many roadblocks,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak said today that he now favored an incremental peace deal with the Palestinians, with an immediate handover of more territory and a possible recognition of statehood, but a postponement of up to three years of the crucial issues of Jerusalem and the resettlement of  Palestinian refugees.</p>
        <p>Seemingly abandoning his quest for an all-inclusive ''end to the conflict,'' Mr. Barak suggested in a speech to Israeli newspaper editors that the Palestinians might agree to an Israeli annexation of major Jewish settlements in the West Bank in return for a recognition of independence. Israel would give the Palestinians ''another 10 percent of the territory to create continuity, so they don't have to pass so many roadblocks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials swiftly rejected Mr. Barak's proposal.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians have autonomy in most of the Gaza Strip, but in just 40 percent of the far larger West Bank, with more than a dozen segments separated by land under Israeli control. Making major Palestinian population centers contiguous would require giving the Palestinians control of much more than half of the West Bank.</p>
        <p>At the Camp David talks last summer, Mr. Barak was reported to have considered giving the Palestinians about 90 percent of the West Bank as part of a comprehensive peace pact.</p>
        <p>Today, Saeb Erekat, a leading Palestinian negotiator, said Palestinians would return to the bargaining table only for ''full permanent-status negotiations -- Jerusalem, settlements, refugees and borders.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's feistily delivered speech was not aimed primarily at Palestinians, however. Kicking off what could be a six-month-long re-election campaign, he is seeking to convince potential challengers on his left that he is still pursuing negotiations with the Palestinians, while reassuring the center-right that he does not intend to surrender East Jerusalem, major settlement blocs, or the strategic Jordan Valley.</p>
        <p>''This is a political program, not a diplomatic program,'' Emmanuel Rosen, a prominent television commentator, said tonight.</p>
        <p>Several small settlements in the Gaza Strip are likely to be abandoned in any permanent peace deal, however, a senior cabinet official acknowledged today. Finance Minister Avraham Shochat, visiting Gaza to announce a $5 million grant to underwrite security and ''psychological counseling'' needs for settlers, told residents of the Gush Katif enclave that he believed they would have to be ''evacuated'' in the event of a ''final status'' agreement.</p>
        <p>While Israeli public opinion polls show a solid majority in favor of a peace settlement with the Palestinians, a survey released today by Palestinian pollsters showed a strong majority of Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza opposed to a resumption of talks with Israel.</p>
        <p>The survey, by the Palestinian Center for Public Opinion, also showed more than three-quarters of  those surveyed opposed to attacks on Israeli forces from inside Palestinian residential areas, but favoring ''military action'' in Israel and supporting the terror bombing of the school bus that killed two Israelis and maimed two children in Gaza 10 days ago.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 2, 2000, Saturday  An article yesterday about a peace proposal by Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel misstated the number of Israeli children maimed in the bombing of a school bus in the Gaza Strip on Nov. 20. It was three, not two.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 2, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a peace proposal by Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel misstated the number of Israeli children maimed in the bombing of a school bus in the Gaza Strip on Nov. 20. It was three, not two.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
