<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Estonian Home Boys: Populist Europe Makes Room for Hip-Hop Heritage</title>
    <meta content="22LYON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/22/arts/dance/22lyon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1613277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lyon Dance Biennial</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lyon (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Rhone Valley</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Rhone Valley/Lyon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lyon Dance Biennial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lyon Dance Biennial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Darmet, Guy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6D71239F931A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Estonian Home Boys: Populist Europe Makes Room for Hip-Hop Heritage</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Populist Europe Makes Room for Hip-Hop Heritage</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <dateline>LYON, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Lyon Dance Biennial in Lyon, France, showcase for French and Eastern European break dancers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Europe has become hip-hop nation, or so the Lyon Dance Biennial, one of the world's foremost dance festivals, seemed to announce by replacing its usual gala opening last week with an exuberant showcase for French and Eastern European break dancers.</p>
        <p>More than 4,000 viewers, mainly young, repeatedly stamped their feet in approval in a sports stadium. Renaud Donnedieu de Vabres, the French culture minister, in attendance with Gérard Collomb, the mayor of Lyon, even told journalists that hip-hop is ''part of our heritage.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With its increasingly populist mission, this year's biennial has become a showcase for French and Eastern European break dancers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Europe has become hip-hop nation, or so the Lyon Dance Biennial, one of the world's foremost dance festivals, seemed to announce by replacing its usual gala opening last week with an exuberant showcase for French and Eastern European break dancers.</p>
        <p>More than 4,000 viewers, mainly young, repeatedly stamped their feet in approval in a sports stadium. Renaud Donnedieu de Vabres, the French culture minister, in attendance with Gérard Collomb, the mayor of Lyon, even told journalists that hip-hop is ''part of our heritage.''</p>
        <p>The title of this year's biennial is ''Europa,'' and unlike other major international festivals, the event is again offering an overview of dance in a single country or a theme-related region. Dance in Europe, especially as it includes new members of the European Community, is the ostensible pretext.</p>
        <p>But the real message in this three-week biennial has been its increasingly populist mission. On Sunday 4,500 participants from the Lyon area and nearby towns marched and danced on the left bank of the Rhône River under a blazing sun. Part street dance, part postmodern movement devised by professional choreographers, the festival's parade is a brilliantly conceived community outreach project. Once intended to encourage creative input from Lyon's immigrant suburbs, the parade now attracts diverse social strata.</p>
        <p>Obviously, this year's theme, ''Europe's Great Tales and Legends,'' was interpreted variously. A stylized mass dance for couples embracing on one knee was part of the ''Romeo and Juliet'' entry, and Alice of Wonderland fame was trapped in a plastic cylinder on a float.</p>
        <p>But the nearly 300,000 spectators who saw the marchers and dancers from Vénisseux, considered a tough suburb, saw a focus on a sadder tale: the plight of Europe's Gypsies. Led by a giant puppetlike Gypsy Queen, 270 dancers moved in rhythmic cadence with large framed photographs of Gypsy children strapped to their backs. The photographs come from a registry that the French government established at the beginning of the 20th century to keep track of the Gypsy people, perpetual outsiders.</p>
        <p>But Guy Darmet, director of the biennial since its beginnings in 1984, invited the Cozmesti Gypsy brass band from Romania, which has never been abroad, to open the parade.</p>
        <p>But pop culture and folk dance are only part of Mr. Darmet's programming, which is devoted largely to modern dance with some contemporary ballet. Populism may take in pop culture, but here it is directed at serving up art to the largest audience.</p>
        <p>Unlike the United States, France has appropriated break dance as an experimental art form. It would be easy to see this street dance, which boomed in France in the 1980's (especially in the Lyon area) as today's folk dance.</p>
        <p>It did not take long, however, for French social and cultural agencies to pay attention to this raw talent and support it financially, or to co-opt it, depending on the point of view.</p>
        <p>''Def' Hip-Hop,'' which opened the biennial on Sept. 12 at the Gerland Sports Arena, was a far cry from the 1988 opening, which glittered with Paris Opera Ballet stars like Sylvie Guillem and Jean-Christophe Paré, magnificently beplumed as Louis XIV in a Baroque solo.</p>
        <p>Asked in an interview why he had shifted the biennial's image so radically, Mr. Darmet, 55, said: ''Because I am older now, and I'm interested in the world around me. I see these break dancers all year. I wanted to show a positive, not a negative, aspect of these young people. This opening was meant as a statement, that culture cannot be reserved for the few.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Darmet sent Gilberte Hugouvieux, a seasoned outreach expert, to pick the break-dance groups off the streets of Eastern and Central Europe. The result was a good-natured exhibition dance, a contest with no prizes awarded.</p>
        <p>The sight of skipping blond break dancers from Estonia and Slovenia was a change from local multicultural teams. Among the 60 visitors were teams from Austria, Croatia, Hungary, Latvia, the Czech Republic and Finland, whose group (Flow Mo) offered the most surprises. Not content to spin on their heads, they moved in unison with great impact.</p>
        <p>The second part of the program featured two choreographed pieces by French crews. Pockemon offered a bravura pure-dance work while Wanted Posse moved with fierce attack as a predatory group around a huge web.</p>
        <p>At the other end of the scale are soloists performing in small spaces. Sonia Baptista from Portugal is a genuine find. Although waiflike and speaking English with an Audrey Hepburn accent, she came up with a provocative and witty suite that was seen live and on video.</p>
        <p>The title, ''Haikus,'' is apt only in that each idea is expressed by a remote image. The delicate style does not conceal the tough material.</p>
        <p>In a film, Ms. Baptista offers a study of a disintegrating personality. Fearing solitude, her character is later seen with plastic miniature animals stuck in her nostrils, ears and mouth. Now filled with their voices, she laments the silence of the past. In a live solo, she jiggles pasties on her bare chest while discussing men. On film, she wears a kimono and commits hara-kiri with a bar of chocolate.</p>
        <p>Jyrki Karttunen from Finland is a far gentler spirit. He too used video, projected on several screens in ''Fairy.'' Looking like an elfin sage, he danced with deliberate awkwardness and his multiple filmed selves.</p>
        <p>The same afternoon, Michael Schumacher, an American who lives in Holland, delighted all, especially children, with his darting, clever dancing as he popped in and out of bushes in the Museum of Fine Arts garden. Alex Waterman, his American cellist, played excerpts from Bach's cello suites.</p>
        <p>Just in case 40 groups from 21 countries don't keep you busy, there are the biennial's theme balls. On Saturday a tribute to Jean Cocteau's film ''Beauty and the Beast'' came to life with performers sitting in illusionist's boxes (a head in a vase of flowers). Masked revelers danced to a disco beat.</p>
        <p>DANCE FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
