<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jump in Inflation Rattles Markets; Consumer Prices Rose 0.4% in April In Broad Increase</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="608798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PRICE INDEX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCER PRICE INDEX</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LABOR DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASAR, SYLVIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Producer Price Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7143DF937A25756C0A965958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jump in Inflation Rattles Markets; Consumer Prices Rose 0.4% in April In Broad Increase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIA NASAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASAR, SYLVIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A spurt in consumer prices last month, coming right after a surge in producer prices, increased concerns that inflation may indeed be creeping back, even though economic growth remains modest.</p>
        <p>The Consumer Prices Index jumped four-tenths of a percent in April, the Labor Department reported yesterday. That was twice as much as many forecasters had predicted. The rise was pervasive, reflecting price increases in most of the goods and services Americans use every day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A spurt in consumer prices last month, coming right after a surge in producer prices, increased concerns that inflation may indeed be creeping back, even though economic growth remains modest.</p>
        <p>The Consumer Prices Index jumped four-tenths of a percent in April, the Labor Department reported yesterday. That was twice as much as many forecasters had predicted. The rise was pervasive, reflecting price increases in most of the goods and services Americans use every day.</p>
        <p>The increase lifted gold prices and led many forecasters to raise their inflation predictions. It also unsettled the bond and stock markets. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 34.32 points.  [ Page D6. ]</p>
        <p>The figures were widely viewed as dashing expectations that inflation this year would be lower than last year, as well as any lingering hopes that the Federal Reserve would push interest rates further down. Above Expectations, Again</p>
        <p>What bothered many analysts was not just the April jump, but the fact that three of the last four reports on consumer prices were higher than expected. The index has been climbing at a 4.3 percent annual rate so far this year, well above last year's 2.9 percent increase; the measure that excludes volatile food and energy prices has been rising at an even faster 4.5 percent annual rate.</p>
        <p>"The inflation rate has bottomed out." said Joel Popkin, president of Joel Popkin &amp; Company in Washington. Mr. Popkin has said for several months that the Fed's expectation of further gains on the inflation front this year was overly optimistic and that inflation would be a bit higher this year than last.</p>
        <p>That could complicate matters for the Clinton Administration, which has been counting on lower long-term interest rates to offset the drag higher taxes would have on the economy.</p>
        <p>But Laura D'Andrea Tyson, chairwoman of the Council of Economic Advisers, held out hope for relief in coming months. "I'm not dismayed," she said. "It's hard to accept two or three months as evidence of a fundamental change in the trend."</p>
        <p>President Clinton hit much the same note. "There is no -- at the present time -- no cause for long-term concern," he said. "It could be just a blip."</p>
        <p>The unsettling inflation report stole the limelight from several reassuring economic reports yesterday. Jobless claims ticked down a bit in the latest week, while consumers spent more freely in April, especially on cars, after staying away from stores in March. Auto producers also reported that sales were strong in the first 10 days of May.</p>
        <p>The inflation report pushed up interest rates generally and seemed to leave the Fed with less maneuvering room to respond to the slow-growing economy.</p>
        <p>"The C.P.I. report would certainly foreclose any Fed easing in the near future," said William Poole, a monetary economist at Brown University.</p>
        <p>"It's a classic dilemma," he added. "If we pay attention to the soft economy, we'd say monetary policy should ease. If we look at the inflation numbers, we might say the Fed should tighten a little."  No Quick Shift Expected</p>
        <p>Still, several analysts said the next crop of inflation reports is likely to be a little less grim than those from this winter and spring, and they suggested that the Federal Reserve, whose monetary policy committee meets next Tuesday, would probably wait before shifting toward tighter money.</p>
        <p>The Fed said as recently as February that it expected inflation for this year to come in well below 3 percent. Now some economists are raising their forecasts to about 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>"Inflation is a little above where the Fed would like, and growth is a little weaker than the Fed would like," said Mickey Levy, chief economist at CRT Securities. "All in all, the Fed is on hold."</p>
        <p>One negative for economists was that April's price increases were so ubiquitous.</p>
        <p>"One doesn't want to make too much out of one month's data," said Patrick C. Jackman of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, "but the rise in the C.P.I. is not due to special factors, and it's pretty pervasive."</p>
        <p>In six of the seven categories of goods and services that make up the Consumer Price Index, prices rose more in April than they increased in March. The only exception was a catch-all category that includes tobacco and education. A 3.5 percent rise in meat and vegetable prices was probably weather-related. A jump in hospital rates pushed up the price of medical care at an annual rate of more than a 7 percent. Car prices, which typically come down in the spring as dealers start discounting models, rose instead.</p>
        <p>But most of the pick up in the inflation rate from March to April reflected higher housing costs -- both for renters and homeowners -- and firmer clothing prices, which had been falling. Higher Prices, Modest Growth</p>
        <p>What could make inflation creep up in an economic expansion that has been sufficiently modest to keep the unemployment rate at 7 percent? Three things, economists say.</p>
        <p>First, the economy's supply capacity may be smaller than thought. "There are signs that the long period of slow growth had an impact on supply," Mr. Popkin said, pointing to companies downsizing and shutting plants in four or five years of slow growth. "The effect is to reduce supply."</p>
        <p>Second, productivity growth, which was stronger last year than in any year since 1972, will inevitably slow this year. That means that unit labor costs, a good indicator of basic inflation trends, are likely to rise a bit faster.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Fed, while not overly easy, has supplied plenty of liquidity in recent quarters, judging by the rapid growth of bank reserves and currency in circulation, the relatively weak dollar and the large spread between short- and long-term interest rates.</p>
        <p>The 1.2 percent rebound in retail sales in April suggested that consumers have not totally lost faith in the economic expansion and that a large part of the eight-tenths of a percent drop in sales in March did reflect the weather. Nonetheless, spending is still barely higher than December's level, and the outlook is for merely modest gains.</p>
        <p>On the employment front, applications for unemployment insurance edged down by 3,000, to 339,000. But the four-week average still ticked up to 345,075.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
