<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; Rummaging An Era For Names And Words</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19921014T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAGNUSON, ANN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">YOU COULD BE HOME NOW (ONE-WOMAN SHOW)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1F3DF931A25753C1A964958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; Rummaging An Era For Names And Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In her one-woman show "You Could Be Home Now," Ann Magnuson reveals herself as an omnivorous collector of names and buzz words that have gained at least temporary currency. Listening to her monologue at the Joseph Papp Public Theater is a bit like browsing through a stack of trendy magazines and reading everything in bold print.</p>
        <p>For a performer who seems to pride herself on her timeliness, the references can seem slightly out of sync: for example, she imagines throwing Beluga caviar at Jay McInerney rather than at Donna Tartt. During the 90-minute performance, she impersonates a variety of characters but without the chameleonesque agility of Lily Tomlin and others who have explored related territory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In her one-woman show "You Could Be Home Now," Ann Magnuson reveals herself as an omnivorous collector of names and buzz words that have gained at least temporary currency. Listening to her monologue at the Joseph Papp Public Theater is a bit like browsing through a stack of trendy magazines and reading everything in bold print.</p>
        <p>For a performer who seems to pride herself on her timeliness, the references can seem slightly out of sync: for example, she imagines throwing Beluga caviar at Jay McInerney rather than at Donna Tartt. During the 90-minute performance, she impersonates a variety of characters but without the chameleonesque agility of Lily Tomlin and others who have explored related territory.</p>
        <p>An earlier version of "You Could Be Home Now," in the Serious Fun festival, directly referred to Thornton Wilder's "Our Town," with Ms. Magnuson playing a contemporary variation of Emily Gibbs. A hint of that character remains as the actress returns to her hometown looking for her roots and for signs of permanency amid drastic change. While this approach gives the monologue a framework of sorts, the show is also marked by its randomness, as she rummages in her basement, literal as well as metaphorical, searching for memories and mementos.</p>
        <p>Although she can be an appealing actress (as in the movie "Making Mr. Right"), the material in her monologue is a potpourri of whatever passes through her mind, including an obsession with repeating a tasteless joke about a dead dog. Distillation is not Ms. Magnuson's strong point as a writer and in his direction David Schweizer has been unable to offer her the necessary editing guidance, at least to encourage her to eliminate gratuitous remarks about famous personalities (and dead dogs).</p>
        <p>In one extended scene, she plays a real estate broker whose vow is "to learn Japanese and start making money off the decline of civilization." While on the subject of decline, she uses "The Cherry Orchard" as a motif. In this town, open land is being subdivided to put up time-share condominiums. Every time she mentions the orchard, on cue a large branch is moved to center stage over her head. That amusing sight gag is one of the few aspects of Bill Stabile's cluttered scenic design that is used to make a legitimate point. The setting in her so-called surround looks like the aftermath of a tag sale.</p>
        <p>Through all this, Ms. Magnuson sings, lip-syncs and dances the "Oliver Stone Ballet of the Fourth Estate." She tosses off one-liners along with her character sketches while also announcing her concern over AIDS and the plight of the homeless. There are moments when she is on target as in her comments about pollution and in her suggestion that a satellite dish should be named as the new state flower. But there are too many casual elements and more than a few examples of silliness.</p>
        <p>Near the end of the monologue, Ms. Magnuson puts aside her alias and as herself sings a raplike song by Tom Judson, interspersing it with piquant observations, as in the line, "It's easier to accept Jesus as your personal savior when he looks like Willem Dafoe." Then she segues into a sarcastic analysis of Richard Gere's social consciousness as represented by the movie "Pretty Woman." But before she gets to this cultural criticism, she has wandered through an erratic performance piece in which she is too often content with identifying the label instead of satirizing the contents. You Could Be Home Now Written and performed by Ann Magnuson; directed by David Schweizer; original music and songs composed by Tom Judson; choreographer, Jerry Mitchell; set by Bill Clarke; lighting by Heather Carson; costumes by Pilar Limosner; sound by Eric Liljestrand; production supervisor, Bill Barnes. Presented by the New York Shakespeare Festival and Women's Project and Productions. At the Joseph Papp Public Theater/Martinson Hall, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 14, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A theater review on Monday about "You Could Be Home Now," Ann Magnuson's one-woman show at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, misidentified the set designer. He is Bill Clarke, not Bill Stabile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 14, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A theater review on Monday about "You Could Be Home Now," Ann Magnuson's one-woman show at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, misidentified the set designer. He is Bill Clarke, not Bill Stabile.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
