<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Trenton, Budget Battle Keeps Legislators Working Into Morning</title>
    <meta content="01TREN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/01/nyregion/01TREN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1405113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgreevey, James E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EED71F3EF932A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Trenton, Budget Battle Keeps Legislators Working Into Morning</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Trenton, Budget Battle Keeps Legislators Working Into Morning</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MANSNERUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Legislature works into early morning hours in effort to adopt largest budget in state's history and close its largest projected deficit ever; session dissolves into bitter fighting among Democrats over proposed Newark sports arena; Senate's vote on corporate business tax is suspended to give leaders and Gov McGreevey time to placate Democrats who defected in effort to force hearing on arena bill (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Legislature worked into the morning today in an effort to adopt the largest budget in the state's history and close its largest projected deficit ever.</p>
        <p>Early today, the extraordinary session that began Sunday afternoon dissolved in bitter fighting among the Democrats over the proposed sports arena in Newark. The State Senate's vote on the corporate business tax, the centerpiece of Gov. James E. McGreevey's budget proposal, was suspended to give Senate leaders and the governor time to placate Democrats who had defected in an effort to force a hearing on the arena bill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Legislature worked into the morning on Sunday in an effort to adopt the largest budget in the state's history and to close its largest projected deficit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Jersey Legislature worked into the morning today in an effort to adopt the largest budget in the state's history and close its largest projected deficit ever.</p>
        <p>Early today, the extraordinary session that began Sunday afternoon dissolved in bitter fighting among the Democrats over the proposed sports arena in Newark. The State Senate's vote on the corporate business tax, the centerpiece of Gov. James E. McGreevey's budget proposal, was suspended to give Senate leaders and the governor time to placate Democrats who had defected in an effort to force a hearing on the arena bill.</p>
        <p>The fighting behind closed doors led to threats and even shoving, according to one Republican senator. And after submitting enough votes to assure that the corporate business tax bill would pass, most Republicans went home.</p>
        <p>The $23.4 billion budget, which follows Governor McGreevey's blueprint, would restructure the corporate income tax, borrow against revenue expected from the state's share of the national tobacco settlement, nearly double the cigarette tax to $1.50 a pack and raise an array of fees.</p>
        <p>By midnight Sunday, Republican legislators had supplied the deciding votes for most of the budget measures in the evenly divided State Senate, but not until they had harshly criticized the Democrats for increasing spending and relying on bond sales to finance operating expenses. And they made their final protests against the business-tax overhaul.</p>
        <p>The Senate's Republican co-president, John O. Bennett, addressed the Democrats, naming all 20 senators, and said, ''Each one of you will be charged with the responsibility to explain this Democrat budget that increases state spending while raising countless taxes on all New Jerseyans.''</p>
        <p>The state's fiscal problems have consumed Mr. McGreevey's first five and a half months in office. As if extending his campaign, the new governor blamed his Republican predecessors for the state's fiscal straits, then sought to raise new revenue while insisting that he was keeping his promise not to raise taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey turned almost immediately to business as a source of new money, claiming that big corporations had escaped their ''fair share'' of the tax burden. The administration maintained that three-quarters of the corporations in the state, and 30 of the 50 largest employers, were paying only the $200 minimum required under the old law.</p>
        <p>The new plan would impose an ''alternative minimum'' tax, on a graduated basis, that is calculated according to gross receipts or gross profits. The plan would also end an exemption for dividends that New Jersey corporations receive from out-of-state subsidiaries, and would tax out-of-state sales that are not already taxed by the other states.</p>
        <p>The budget was also a test of whether the Republicans, who share control of the State Senate with Democrats, could check the new governor's moves. With business groups, they orchestrated an advertising campaign against the business-tax plan.</p>
        <p>In the end, they could wrest only a few concessions. Last-minute bargaining for Republican votes shifted some of the burden from small businesses, and provided for a commission to review the tax and report in two years on whether it should continue. But the revised tax is still projected to raise $1.8 billion, more than twice the amount collected this year.</p>
        <p>There are few new spending programs in the budget. It provides for increased property-tax rebates, staff increases at centers for the disabled that are needed to keep their accreditation and $40 million for counterterrorism efforts. It freezes aid to school districts and municipalities at this year's levels.</p>
        <p>The budget calls for spending about $500 million more than the budget adopted one year ago. But the increase in actual spending is expected to be considerably higher, since the state made unusually large spending cuts this year after the softening economy and the terrorist attacks of Sept. 11 began to depress tax collections.</p>
        <p>Late Sunday, the Democrats were still dwelling on one of Mr. McGreevey's main themes: that the Republican-controlled budget for the fiscal year that ended Sunday night contained wildly optimistic projections. Some Democrats called them fraudulent.</p>
        <p>''I am glad to say that in this year's budget, that number is real, and not an accounting gimmick designed to pull the wool over the people's eyes until the next election,'' said Senator Wayne R. Bryant, the Democratic chairman of the Senate budget committee.</p>
        <p>Republicans complained bitterly from the outset that they were shut out of budget decisions as Mr. McGreevey and Democratic lawmakers put off sharing details of their proposals. They did not release the appropriations bill until Thursday, which was to have been the last voting day of the session.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
