<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A new device that gives customer service a heads-up on which callers are spoiling for a fight.</title>
    <meta content="01PATE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/01/technology/01PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020704T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1405009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Patents"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voice Recognition Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mitel Knowledge Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Discovery Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohacek, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schulz, Dieter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wire and Cable</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wire and Cable</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customer Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Levy, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDF1F3EF932A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A new device that gives customer service a heads-up on which callers are spoiling for a fight.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Way to Deal With Angry Callers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Bohacek and Dieter Schulz patent for Mitel Knowledge Corp voice-prompt system for customer service phone systems that detects outrage or anger and directs caller to specially trained operators; inventors at Discovery Communications patent system that calculates person's mood, interests and television-watching history to suggest shows they might like to see; invention uses television set-top box and is linked to incoming program guide; is part of Discovery's digital strategy; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMONG the tens of thousands of people who call customer service numbers every day are countless individuals spitting fury and demanding redress for all sorts of problems: software that freezes a computer hard drive, seat assignments on a flight that mysteriously disappear, catalog purchases that arrive with defects.</p>
        <p>If an unprepared or inept customer representative takes one of those calls, it can make a bad situation worse. So two inventors for a California company have patented a voice-prompt system that detects outrage or anger, and directs the caller to operators trained to handle customers who are spoiling for a fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two inventors have patented a voice-prompt system that detects outrage or anger in a caller's voice, and directs the caller to customer-service operators trained to handle customers who are spoiling for a fight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMONG the tens of thousands of people who call customer service numbers every day are countless individuals spitting fury and demanding redress for all sorts of problems: software that freezes a computer hard drive, seat assignments on a flight that mysteriously disappear, catalog purchases that arrive with defects.</p>
        <p>If an unprepared or inept customer representative takes one of those calls, it can make a bad situation worse. So two inventors for a California company have patented a voice-prompt system that detects outrage or anger, and directs the caller to operators trained to handle customers who are spoiling for a fight.</p>
        <p>Peter Bohacek and Dieter Schulz won the patent on behalf of the Mitel Knowledge Corporation in Kanata, Calif. They say the system can pick out customers who are mad, impatient or speaking with fury without the customers realizing that they are being singled out for special attention.</p>
        <p>The system relies on the P.B.X. -- or private branch exchange -- telecommunications routing technology that is already common in call centers. It offers an automated menu of options from which callers can choose using voice commands or touch-tone buttons, and then routes calls to the appropriate department or customer service agent.</p>
        <p>The invention inserts what the inventors call a mood analyzer into the system. It gathers information from the way callers answer voice prompts or use the touch-tone buttons when asked for information like an account number, reservation code or customer number. For systems using voice, a speech-recognition program would scan for voices full of stress or annoyance. It would listen for rapid speech, stuttering or other patterns that might indicate anger. It would also compare a caller's vocabulary against a list of keywords, looking for mood giveaways.</p>
        <p>''Some words clearly indicate a greater degree of annoyance than others,'' the inventors point out, like ''added words in speech that indicate moods (e.g. swearwords).''</p>
        <p>There is also a timer that calculates mood from the way people enter touch-tone digits. Anyone who very quickly punches the buttons, jabs at them repeatedly, or deliberately holds a button down for a long time is likely to be ''a customer who is angry or in a hurry,'' the inventors write in their patent.</p>
        <p>Once the system has decided that a caller is angry, it tries to figure out how much. If the ''annoyance level'' exceeds a threshold set by the system, the call is routed to an operator trained to handle annoyed customers. The system can also detect gender -- so that an angry male caller could be directed to a patient female operator in the hopes of soothing the customer.</p>
        <p>A message signaling that an irate person was on the line would flash on the operator's computer screen. The system would even try to describe the degree of annoyance or impatience, so that the operator could choose an appropriate opening greeting, the inventors say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bohacek, who lives in Dallas, and Mr. Dieter, in Kanata, received patent 6,411,687.</p>
        <p>With hundreds of television channels available to most viewers, it is increasingly difficult for many people to ferret out programs they want to watch. So a team of inventors at Discovery Communications, owner of the Discovery Channel, has patented a system that calculates a person's mood, interests and television-watching history to suggest shows they might like to see in the future.</p>
        <p>The invention uses a television set-top box and is linked to an incoming program guide, the kind of database available with most cable or satellite systems. It includes a receiver, a processor and memory storage unit, and a menu that appears on the TV screen.</p>
        <p>The patent is part of a digital strategy by Discovery, which announced in April that it would start a video-on-demand network to be offered over digital cable and satellite systems. A Discovery spokesman, David Levy, said the company held ''over 100 patents related to menu navigation.'' Discovery is trying to figure out ''the best way to exploit our patent portfolio to help with the digital rollout and video on demand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the newly patented approach, the viewer would have to set up the system by answering questions or choosing adjectives to describe his entertainment preferences. He would do so by punching numbers on a remote control. He could choose a type of program, an actor, a time of day or show length, or a review or rating preference. He would be able to highlight comedies, dramas, documentaries or movies, for example. He could also order the system to avoid programs of no interest to him, like cartoons. If the system finds the word ''cartoon'' in a description of a show, it can automatically exclude that show from the list.</p>
        <p>The viewer would create a personal profile the same way, by providing his gender, age, job, education level, the total hours of TV he watches every week along with the number of shows in certain categories, like sports or sit-coms.</p>
        <p>Once the system is set up, the viewer has to help it narrow program choices each time he sits down to watch TV.</p>
        <p>''The set top terminal will present the viewer with a series of brief questions to determine the viewer's mood at that particular time,'' the inventors explain. It might ask if the viewer feels like a short show or a long one, or is feeling thoughtful or serious.</p>
        <p>''A variety of other mood questions are possible such as the fatigue level of the viewer,'' they say, ''or whether the viewer is in the mood for older programming.''</p>
        <p>The system then analyzes the person's mood along with his general profile and information about his most-often watched programs. The results are cross-referenced with the program guide to generate a list of suggested shows.</p>
        <p>Over time, the system would learn a viewer's habits and preferences by analyzing the choices he makes from the suggestion lists. It could also suggest groups of programs to watch, and offer them in order of priority. The viewer could also reprogram the system to reflect changing interests.</p>
        <p>John Hendricks, Alfred Bonner and Richard Wunderlich won patent 6,408,437.</p>
        <p>Patents Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 4, 2002, Thursday  The Patents column in Business Day on Monday about a system for customer service centers that detects anger in callers and directs them to operators trained to handle such calls misstated the location of the headquarters of the Mitel Knowledge Corporation, on whose behalf the inventors won a patent for the system. It is based in Kanata, Ontario, not in California.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 4, 2002, Thursday</p>
        <p>The Patents column in Business Day on Monday about a system for customer service centers that detects anger in callers and directs them to operators trained to handle such calls misstated the location of the headquarters of the Mitel Knowledge Corporation, on whose behalf the inventors won a patent for the system. It is based in Kanata, Ontario, not in California.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
