<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOUSE PANEL BACKS $1 TRILLION BUDGET</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="128431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DB1139F93BA25750C0A96E948260" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOUSE PANEL BACKS $1 TRILLION BUDGET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The House Budget Committee today approved a $1.1 trillion Federal budget for the fiscal year 1989 that generally follows the budget accord reached with President Reagan but raised some of his domestic spending proposals while reducing others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The House Budget Committee today approved a $1.1 trillion Federal budget for the fiscal year 1989 that generally follows the budget accord reached with President Reagan but raised some of his domestic spending proposals while reducing others.</p>
        <p>The House Budget Committee today approved a $1.1 trillion Federal budget for the fiscal year 1989 that generally follows the budget accord reached with President Reagan but raised some of his domestic spending proposals while reducing others.</p>
        <p>The spending plan for the fiscal year that starts Oct. 1 would leave a deficit of $134.1 billion, according to the budget panel, enough to avoid automatic spending cuts under the budget-balancing law.</p>
        <p>The Senate plans to write its budget resolution next month. The resolution, which does not need the President's signature, serves as a blueprint for actual spending legislation that will be enacted later by Congress.</p>
        <p>In a separate action, the White House sent Congress a supplemental spending request for the current fiscal year that would increase spending by $1.1 billion, mostly for veterans. Closed-Meeting Compromises</p>
        <p>The House committee's budget resolution, expected to be sent to the full House next week, was put together over the last several days by Republican and Democratic committee members meeting in closed sessions. The panel approved the document on a voice vote with no objections at a five-minute public session.</p>
        <p>''We've had a bipartisan process, with full participation by Republican members,'' said William H. Gray 3d, Democrat of Pennsylvania, the committee chairman.</p>
        <p>The budget accord reached last November between Mr. Reagan and lawmakers locked in new taxes and spending levels for the fiscal years 1988 and 1989 for the military, foreign affairs and overall domestic spending. The main disagreements have been over how to distribute the $169.2 billion limit for the domestic programs that Congress directly oversees and are not financed under automatic formulas.</p>
        <p>In the 1989 budget he presented Congress Feb. 18, Mr. Reagan proposed a 20 percent increase in spending on space and science programs to $13.1 billion. The budget panel, looking to restore proposed cuts to several other domestic programs, reduced Mr. Reagan's proposal to $12.2 billion.</p>
        <p>''The committee felt that was a realistic figure for NASA to carry out its mission,'' Mr. Gray said. Medicare Cuts Are Rejected</p>
        <p>In programs aimed at low-income people, such as job training and child health care, the budget panel would allow enough of a spending increase to keep up with inflation, expected to reach 4 percent this year.</p>
        <p>The committee's budget also rejected $1.2 billion in savings in Medicare proposed by Mr. Reagan. The panel's budget proposes $1.5 billion for AIDS research, slightly more than the President proposed, and retains previously planned levels of spending for education, fighting drugs and providing aid to the homeless.</p>
        <p>The panel also proposed a 3 percent pay raise for Federal workers and civilian employees of the military.</p>
        <p>The committee's budget leaves intact the agreed upon spending level of $294 billion for military programs for the 1989 fiscal year and does not change the proposal designed to raise $14 billion in new taxes. Most of the levies would be on corporations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
