<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH ASKS LANDS IN MIDEAST TO TRY DEMOCRATIC WAYS</title>
    <meta content="07PREX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/07/international/middleeast/07PREX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1533358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Egypt</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Endowment for Democracy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Human Rights Watch</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malinowski, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Middle East</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDC1539F934A35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH ASKS LANDS IN MIDEAST TO TRY DEMOCRATIC WAYS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Asks Lands in Mideast to Try Democratic Ways</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush challenges Iran, Syria and American allies Egypt and Saudi Arabia to begin embracing democratic traditions, and to view fall of Saddam Hussein as 'watershed event' in global democratic revolution, speech before National Endowment for Democracy; argues that 60 years of Western nations excusing and accommodating lack of freedom in Middle East has not made world safe, because stability cannot be purchased at expense of liberty; speech seems intended to change perception of Iraq occupation, describing it in far broader strategic terms than ouster of dictator; his pressure for reform runs risk of backfiring in Arab world, where some Arabs like to compare his remarks about human rights to America's treatment of suspected terrorists held at Guantanamo Bay, or his reluctance to demand that Israel stop constructing its barrrier along West Bank; even Arab intellectuals urging greater civil liberties say Bush's remarks undermine them, because it paints them as stooges of US; Tom Malinowski of Human Rights Watch praises Bush for doing something Clinton administration had been loath to do: identifying Middle East nations that have refused to liberalize (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush on Thursday challenged Iran, Syria and two crucial Middle East allies of the United States -- Egypt and Saudi Arabia -- to begin embracing democratic traditions, and to view the fall of Saddam Hussein as ''a watershed event in the global democratic revolution.''</p>
        <p>''Sixty years of Western nations excusing and accommodating the lack of freedom in the Middle East did nothing to make us safe,'' Mr. Bush argued, in a critique that embraced both Democrats and Republicans who preceded him, ''because in the long run, stability cannot be purchased at the expense of liberty.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush challenged Iran, Syria and Middle East allies of the U.S. to begin embracing democratic traditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush on Thursday challenged Iran, Syria and two crucial Middle East allies of the United States -- Egypt and Saudi Arabia -- to begin embracing democratic traditions, and to view the fall of Saddam Hussein as ''a watershed event in the global democratic revolution.''</p>
        <p>''Sixty years of Western nations excusing and accommodating the lack of freedom in the Middle East did nothing to make us safe,'' Mr. Bush argued, in a critique that embraced both Democrats and Republicans who preceded him, ''because in the long run, stability cannot be purchased at the expense of liberty.''</p>
        <p>The speech, before the National Endowment for Democracy, appeared to be part of an effort by the White House to change American and world perceptions of the Iraq occupation, describing it in far broader strategic terms than the ouster of a dictator.</p>
        <p>But it came at a moment when Mr. Bush is struggling to create democratic institutions in Iraq itself, and when the daily casualties among the American and allied soldiers have led many in the region to question whether the United States is capable of transforming the nation it invaded.</p>
        <p>In the speech, the president sought to position the American experiment in remaking Iraq alongside the United States' efforts to spread democracy in Asia and Europe after World War II and to bring about the fall of the Soviet Union. He directly compared what he called his administration's new ''forward strategy of freedom in the Middle East'' to President Ronald Reagan's 1982 declaration in England that Soviet Communism had failed.</p>
        <p>He identified four nations where he said dictatorship was doomed to failure: North Korea, Myanmar -- which he referred to by its former name, Burma -- Cuba and Zimbabwe, declaring that ''these regimes cannot hold back freedom forever.'' He predicted that just as Nelson Mandela emerged from captivity in South Africa to lead his nation, ''one day, from prison camps and prison cells and from exile, the leaders of new democracies will arrive'' in the four countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush had sounded similar themes before, notably in a speech at the American Enterprise Institute a month and a half before he ordered the invasion of Iraq. But until Thursday's speech, he had not identified nations that he thought urgently needed to reform. For the first time, he also raised, gingerly, the issue of the absence of liberty in Saudi Arabia, one of America's major oil suppliers and a nation that has long been spared presidential rebuke.</p>
        <p>''The Saudi government is taking first steps toward reform,'' he said, choosing his words carefully about a country that one of his senior aides said recently ''is probably the most resistant to change of any nation in the region.'' He referred to its experiment with local elections, avoided any mention of the struggle within the Saudi royal family over whether and how to surrender some authority, and he offered the most gentle of encouragement.</p>
        <p>''By giving the Saudi people a greater role in their own society,'' Mr. Bush said, ''the Saudi government can demonstrate true leadership in the region.''</p>
        <p>He also pressed Egypt -- which receives upward of $2 billion annually in aid from the United States -- saying it ''has shown the way toward peace in the Middle East, and now should show the way toward democracy in the Middle East.'' But later, his spokesman, Scott McClellan, said the president was not threatening any consequences for his Arab allies if they failed to heed his warning.</p>
        <p>The pressure runs the risk of backfiring. In the Arab world, Mr. Bush's remarks about human rights and democracy are often viewed as hypocritical, and Arabs often compare those statements to the treatment of suspected terrorists held by American forces at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba, or the president's reluctance to demand that Israel stop constructing its barrier along the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Some Arab intellectuals urging greater civil liberties say Mr. Bush's endorsement undermines them, because it paints them as stooges of the United States.</p>
        <p>But a scattering of experts feel that it is welcome pressure on governments that have been stuck in place for decades, and Tom Malinowski, the Washington advocacy director for Human Rights Watch, praised Mr. Bush for doing something the Clinton administration had been loath to do: identifying Middle East nations that have refused to liberalize.</p>
        <p>''They have ended the Mideast exception to American human rights policy,'' he said of the Bush administration. ''It is welcome moral clarity in the service of a policy that still lacks moral authority.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Bush heaped the most scorn on Iran and Syria, which his administration accuses of seeking to undermine the Iraq occupation. ''The regime in Tehran must heed the democratic demands of the Iranian people or lose its last claim to legitimacy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He lumped Syria's leaders with Mr. Hussein, saying they had promised a restoration of ancient glories but instead left ''a legacy of torture, oppression, misery and ruin.''</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Bush spoke, it was already evening in the Middle East, and there were no official reactions from governments. But Imad Fawzi Shueibi, a Syrian political analyst and professor at Damascus University, suggested that Mr. Bush's message would be tainted in the Middle East by the widespread negative perception of the messenger.</p>
        <p>''I don't think someone who violates the human rights against people all over the world and especially the Arab world can speak about freedom and democracy,'' he said. ''How can we believe that Mr. George Bush wants us to enter the era of democracy and the era of freedom when he remains biased toward Israel despite its violations of human rights, despite its long occupation of Arab land and its apartheid system toward the Arabs in the occupied territories?''</p>
        <p>Others found plenty to praise.</p>
        <p>''It was exciting,'' said Omar Baghour, a Saudi economist and columnist at the newspaper Al Madina.</p>
        <p>The United States, he said, ''is hated in the Arab and Islamic world because it has always been viewed as supporting repressive regimes.'' Mr. Bush has now turned, he said, to ''a more moderate approach, a more rational approach to democratization in the Arab world rather than the threat of force.''</p>
        <p>Most notable about Mr. Bush's speech was his tone in discussing Iraq. In February at the American Enterprise Institute, he said with certainty that Mr. Hussein's ouster would make Iraq the democratic kernel at the heart of the Middle East. But on Thursday, he raised the specter of what a nondemocratic Iraq might look like in a post-Hussein era, though he assured listeners that success was inevitable.</p>
        <p>''The failure of Iraqi democracy would embolden terrorists around the world, increase dangers to the American people, and extinguish the hopes of millions in the region,'' he said. ''Iraqi democracy will succeed, and that success will send forth the news, from Damascus to Tehran, that freedom can be the future of every nation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush did not mention the issue of weapons of mass destruction. The possible threat from such weapons was the administration's chief argument for war against Iraq, but no evidence of them has been found.</p>
        <p>Two hours after the speech, the president gathered leaders of the House and Senate and his security team in the East Room and signed the legislation that provides $87 billion for military action and reconstruction in Iraq and Afghanistan. Flanked by Secretary of State Colin L. Powell and Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld, he called the money ''the greatest commitment of its kind since the Marshall Plan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
