<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dance in Review</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BALLET THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNNING, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BALANCHINE, GEORGE (1904-83)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DB1E30F937A15756C0A965958260" item-length="416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dance in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Dunning</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNNING, JENNIFER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Symphonie Concertante' American Ballet Theater Metropolitan Opera House</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Symphonie Concertante' American Ballet Theater Metropolitan Opera House</p>
        <p>American Ballet Theater's matinee on Wednesday brought new dancers to new roles with enjoyable results. The afternoon began with a glowing performance of George Balanchine's "Symphonie Concertante." The two lead ballerinas were Amanda McKerrow, who danced with a kind of creamy delicacy, and Julie Kent, standing out in this role debut for a crystalline clarity and regal bearing that made it even plainer that this is a ballet about classical ballet manners. In another role debut, Wes Chapman was their cavalier, noble yet relaxed and a gravely attentive partner.</p>
        <p>The fine demi-soloists were Claudia Alfieri, Marie France, Gabrielle Brown, Shannon Chain, Paloma Herrera and Ashley Tuttle. Ron Oakland was the violin soloist, Janet Hill the violist.</p>
        <p>The balance of the afternoon was devoted to Irish jigs and modern ballet plunges. The French dancer Guillaume Graffin looked astonishingly Irish as the Young Fighter, a new role for him, in "The Informer," an atmospheric but oddly static ballet by Agnes de Mille danced to Celtic songs arranged by Marc Blitzstein, Martha Johnson, John Morris and Trude Rittmann. There was a charming hint of giddy nonchalance to his boyish freedom fighter, and his encounters with a rosy Elizabeth Ferrell were touching. Ms. Ferrell, also new in her role, was convincingly sweet then confused as the Girl, who falls in love with both the Young Fighter and the Wounded Veteran who betrays him, portrayed with sympathy by Ethan Brown.</p>
        <p>Keith Roberts took the lead role for the first time in "The Rite of Spring," Glen Tetley's sleek and gleaming foray into the Stravinsky score. Mr. Roberts was the plunging, spinning sacrificial victim, and such was the teeming muscular energy, controlled abandon and attention to detail that it did not take the character's trapeze swing upward at the close to suggest that this was an indomitable life force.</p>
        <p>As the ballet's youthful elders, Kathleen Moore and Robert Conn had just the right balance of stoical strength and resiliency. Mr. Conn, a marvel of strength and imperturbability, must be every ballerina's dream of a partner. The fluent demi-soloists were Clinton Luckett and Gabrielle Brown, and Carld Jonassaint and Veronica Lynn. Mr. Jonassaint's performance suggested once more the value of a gifted dancer's strong classical approach to a variety of styles.</p>
        <p>Jack Everly and Charles Barker were the afternoon's conductors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
