<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Bruising Run, How Sweet the Taste</title>
    <meta content="Y02BEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1006777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE PRESIDENT'S LAWYER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abramson, Jill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Susan Webber (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Paula Corbin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Robert S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED6163AF931A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Bruising Run, How Sweet the Taste</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL ABRAMSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abramson, Jill</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Susan Webber Wright's decision throwing out Paula Corbin Jones case is sweet and unexpected vindication for Pres Clinton's lead lawyer, Robert S Bennett, whose combative strategy drew much criticism in long proceedings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though his public response was uncharacteristically muted, today's decision throwing out the Paula Corbin Jones case was sweet and unexpected vindication for Robert S. Bennett, whose combative strategy as President Clinton's lead lawyer drew much criticism in the long proceedings.</p>
        <p>In a brief statement outside his law office at the powerhouse firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom, Mr. Bennett told reporters, ''It was a very strong and a very powerful opinion, and I'm very pleased.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Though his public response was uncharacteristically muted, today's decision throwing out the Paula Corbin Jones case was sweet and unexpected vindication for Robert S. Bennett, whose combative strategy as President Clinton's lead lawyer drew much criticism in the long proceedings.</p>
        <p>In a brief statement outside his law office at the powerhouse firm of Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom, Mr. Bennett told reporters, ''It was a very strong and a very powerful opinion, and I'm very pleased.''</p>
        <p>Under his stewardship, Mr. Bennett's critics said, the Paula Jones case escalated from a minor distraction into a full-fledged Presidential crisis, as the independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr opened a criminal investigation into allegations that Mr. Clinton had perjured himself during his January deposition in the Jones case and had encouraged others to lie.</p>
        <p>In a particularly biting commentary at one stage, for example, Alan Dershowitz, the Harvard Law School professor, accused Mr. Bennett of turning ''a political problem into a legal nightmare.''</p>
        <p>While Judge Susan Webber Wright's decision was a giant victory for Mr. Bennett and his client, it came at a high price. As each pleading contained more embarrassing and salacious allegations against the President, the case drew greater press attention. And the potential for political damage to the White House grew as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett's first big setback in the case was a stinging rebuke last May from the United States Supreme Court, which unanimously rejected his argument that the President should not be embroiled in civil litigation while in office. But what seemed like a major legal defeat was an important political victory. Mr. Bennett's appeal succeeded in pushing the Jones trial beyond the 1996 election.</p>
        <p>Later, settlement discussions with Ms. Jones's first legal team broke down after she demanded an outright apology from Mr. Clinton. While Mr. Bennett was criticized for not settling the case, he was constrained by his client's refusal to give in.</p>
        <p>The 58-year-old litigator also managed to incur the wrath of feminists. After the Supreme Court ruled against him, Mr. Bennett issued an implied threat to unveil Ms. Jones's own sexual history during a controversial appearance on NBC's ''Meet the Press.''</p>
        <p>The controversy was rekindled last month, when the pugnacious Mr. Bennett again seemed on the verge of introducing derogatory personal information about Ms. Jones. Her lawyers had just submitted a 700-page court filing full of damaging allegations concerning the President's past behavior with women and claiming that Mr. Clinton's actions toward her had caused her to suffer from sexual aversion. But Mr. Bennett again demurred.</p>
        <p>Finally, some legal analysts thought Mr. Bennett's move for summary judgment was unlikely to succeed in getting the Jones case thrown out. They argued that when Mr. Bennett used selected portions of Ms. Jones's deposition in his brief, he incited Ms. Jones's lawyers to fight fire with fire. Their 700-page response, which included President Clinton's full deposition, drew huge news media coverage and introduced a battery of new, potentially damaging testimony. Especially embarrassing was a deposition from the former White House aide Kathleen Willey, who said the President made an unwelcome sexual advance in the White House.</p>
        <p>Privately, Mr. Bennett said that he did not expect Judge Wright to throw out the case entirely, but that he hoped she would streamline it and dismiss some of Ms. Jones's claims.</p>
        <p>Instead, he won a total victory so surprising that President Clinton wanted assurance that the news was not an April Fool's joke.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bennett was clearly savoring his triumph today, not all of his critics were silenced. Lynne S. Bernabei, a Washington lawyer who specializes in sexual harassment cases, said that despite Judge Wright's ruling, she thought the case could have been handled better by Mr. Clinton and his lawyer.</p>
        <p>''Consider what it took to get here,'' she said of the President. ''He paid a huge liability in having all this damaging material out there.''  TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE PRESIDENT'S LAWYER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
