<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Step Right Up: Monsters Mate, Monsters Fight</title>
    <meta content="02GAME$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980404T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1006664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cd-Rom (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tecmo (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herz, J C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7DB1F3BF931A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Step Right Up: Monsters Mate, Monsters Fight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. C. HERZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herz, J C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Monster Rancher, computer game by Tecmo, spawns virtual creatures using data generated by music CD's or CD-ROM's; object of game is to breed, raise and train monsters and then pit them against rivals; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MONSTER RANCHER is the video game industry's answer to genetic engineering. The object of this game is to breed, raise and train virtual monsters and then pit them against rival monsters in the ring. It's a cross between a Tamagotchi, an Ultimate Fighting contest and the Westminster dog show.</p>
        <p>And it has been successfully cloned: 500,000 copies have found their way into the Sony Playstations of North America. But what makes this game a real mutant is the way the monsters are conceived: you spawn them from audio CD's. Slip your favorite album into the console, and Monster Rancher (Tecmo; $34.99) will generate a creature based on the way that data is arranged on the disk. Depending on track lengths and the number of songs, the monster will emerge with a different configuration of attributes like speed, strength, intelligence and body parts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MONSTER RANCHER is the video game industry's answer to genetic engineering. The object of this game is to breed, raise and train virtual monsters and then pit them against rival monsters in the ring. It's a cross between a Tamagotchi, an Ultimate Fighting contest and the Westminster dog show.</p>
        <p>And it has been successfully cloned: 500,000 copies have found their way into the Sony Playstations of North America. But what makes this game a real mutant is the way the monsters are conceived: you spawn them from audio CD's. Slip your favorite album into the console, and Monster Rancher (Tecmo; $34.99) will generate a creature based on the way that data is arranged on the disk. Depending on track lengths and the number of songs, the monster will emerge with a different configuration of attributes like speed, strength, intelligence and body parts.</p>
        <p>The natural impulse, of course, is to feed your entire music collection through this thing to see what kind of goblins spring to life. Watching them congeal slowly from a nebula of colored light, at long last you see . . . a Mayan mythological beast, born of ''Jerry Lee Lewis's Greatest Hits!'' A slithering rodent with mouse ears and a forked tongue, the digital offspring of the Orb's ''Orblivion!'' The Squirrel Nut Zippers' ''Hot'' morphs into a green tyrannosaur with pink flower-shape splotches. The ''Pulp Fiction'' soundtrack produces a yellow eyeball wiggling its fins, licking its lips and spoiling for a fight.</p>
        <p>And once you have spawned these creatures, you can combine them. What do you get when you cross the Chemical Brothers with Beck? The Beastie Boys with Evgeny Kissin's ''Chopin, Volume One''? Mating CD's becomes a game in itself.</p>
        <p>My favorite monster was a translucent blue tiger-triceratops, the product of P. J. Harvey's ''Rid of Me.'' It emerged from its pixellated goo wagging its tail. And I can tell you authoritatively, with no bias at all, that this creature is totally adorable and superior to every other monster on the ranch. I understand that all the other monster ranchers feel that way about their monsters, but this tiger-triceratops thing is phenomenal.</p>
        <p>He is so smart. He learns really fast. Which is important because raising monsters is expensive. To make your monster a contender, you have to make sure that it gets the proper training, which drains the virtual bank account. So you have to put it to work. But you can't drive it too hard because monsters can burn out. They are subject to injuries, exhaustion and disgruntlement. According to the rancher handbook, ''If your monster is tired from work or is treated badly, he becomes grumpy and won't listen to you.''</p>
        <p>On the other hand, you cannot give your monster the run of the ranch because it will become lazy and petulant if overindulged. There are seven points along the continuum of discipline: Spoil, Gentle, Easy, Even, Firm, Strict and Cruel. If you are going to bring up a champion, instilling character is important.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, when the monsters are little, they are not very strong and don't do a very good job at tasks like guarding. If you decide to punish them, they whimper a bit and feel very sorry, and you feel horrible and throw them a piece of candy to make them feel better. Then their loyalty scores go up and you breathe a tremendous sigh of relief because you did the Right Thing. So you can get on with the business of raising a lean, mean, merciless gladiator.</p>
        <p>When faced with monster-rearing dilemmas, it is important to keep in mind that thousands of ranchers have faced the same difficult decisions. And you can find them on the Web. These people manage to combine a Doom clan's fervor with the fastidiousness of an orchid-breeding club. At the Monster Rancher HQ site, you can find killer combat moves, detailed cross-pollination and lineage charts, and a cross-referenced database of CD's and monster species (home.earthlink.net/ rbrdrgn/monster).</p>
        <p>The CD-monster correlation is rife with inside jokes. ''Jesus Christ Superstar'' generates the same monster as Marilyn Manson's ''Antichrist Superstar.'' And the rabid, terrifying Evil Hare springs from Bill Gates's ''Road Ahead'' CD-ROM as well as from ''The Beavis and Butt-head Experience.''</p>
        <p>And there is one extremely rare monster, the fabled Doodle, which you can get only with the Damned's seminal 1977 punk rock album, called ''Damned Damned Damned.'' The album is available for ordering at Flea's Ranch (pages.prodigy.net/ channonw/rancher.htm), a Monster Rancher site whose chief cowboy has struck a deal with CD Now, the on-line music retailer. In a strange and unexpected way, the Web is fulfilling its promise here: it has become a kind of glue between media. Audio recordings generate video-game monsters. The monsters lead you on line. And the Web takes you back to recorded audio and another generation of monsters. If you could breed these beasties on line and pit them against one another on the Web, we wouldn't have to fret about convergence anymore. It would be a fait accompli, with green spines down its back and long pointed teeth.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail address: Herz@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 4, 1998, Saturday  An article in the Circuits section on Thursday about a computer game called Monster Rancher included an erroneous price provided by its maker, Tecmo Inc. The game costs $49.99, not $34.99.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 4, 1998, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in the Circuits section on Thursday about a computer game called Monster Rancher included an erroneous price provided by its maker, Tecmo Inc. The game costs $49.99, not $34.99.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Herz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
