<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Stolid and Big-Shouldered, Now a Cinderella on the Lake</title>
    <meta content="15CHIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Chicago Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="943915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Chicago Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E0DA1538F936A25754C0A961958260" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Stolid and Big-Shouldered, Now a Cinderella on the Lake</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, July 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago, with image of being stolid and big-shouldered, may be trading its working-class reputation in booming real estate market that has seen realtors salivating at virtually every scrap of land in city; abandoned railroad property is being transformed into upscale housing; even near public housing projects, new town houses are commanding prices of $350,000 and parts of city do not seem different from suburbs anymore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Property values are zooming. Crime is plunging. Unemployment is falling. The Bulls are reigning.</p>
        <p>Test scores in the public schools are rising. And the 110-story Sears Tower has regained its status as the tallest building in the world, at least by some measures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Property values are zooming. Crime is plunging. Unemployment is falling. The Bulls are reigning.</p>
        <p>Test scores in the public schools are rising. And the 110-story Sears Tower has regained its status as the tallest building in the world, at least by some measures.</p>
        <p>In this city that always has one eye on the mirror, the self-image of Chicago, as in ''Sweet Home, Chicago,'' has lately been something to dance about.</p>
        <p>Describing the mood of Chicagoans, Greg Longhini, the city's spokesman for the Department of Planning and Development, sounded a bit like James Brown:</p>
        <p>''We feel good.''</p>
        <p>If not for the hapless Cubs (still in last place) and the shady politicians (five current or former Aldermen are among 13 people charged in a recent Federal investigation of corruption), it would seem that this capital of Middle America had lost its salt-of-the-earth demeanor.</p>
        <p>It helps, of course, that it is summertime. With the music in Grant Park, the revelers at outdoor cafes on Rush Street and the sailboats on Lake Michigan, this city looks distinctly more charming than it does, say, in January, when hypothermal pedestrians cling desperately to light poles to avoid being swept away by the freezing wind.</p>
        <p>But not even the infamous winter wind, known here as The Hawk, appears likely to chill the property market here.</p>
        <p>It does not take a rocket scientist to figure out why Chicago is booming. In a national economy that seems almost too good to be true, the industrial Midwest is a regional leader. And this city is the financial and cultural center of the vast sweep across the heart of the nation.</p>
        <p>Developers seem to be salivating at virtually every scrap of land in Chicago. Abandoned railroad property is being transformed into upscale housing. Even near public housing projects, new town houses are commanding prices of $350,000.</p>
        <p>While many malls outside Chicago are struggling, suburbanites now flock to Michigan Avenue to shop on weekends. And many of them, weary of long commuting times to work, have been returning to live in the city.</p>
        <p>Parts of the city do not seem so different from the suburbs anymore. Neighborhoods like Bucktown and Wicker Park, downright dangerous a decade ago, have become yuppie havens. Lincoln Park, once a hot spot for the young and hip, is now rich and staid. The 43d Ward, a nerve center for the antiwar movement in the 60's, now has Republican leanings.</p>
        <p>This city still gets plenty of mileage out of the Big Shoulder image, the dominant Chicago cliche since Carl Sandburg coined the phrase in 1914.</p>
        <p>In truth, it can be tough to find the old Chicago, the lunch-bucket, working-class town that jumped to the sound of factory whistles.</p>
        <p>One of the greatest symbols of that plain-spoken ethos was Montgomery Ward, which started its mail order catalogue in 1872, a year after the Great Fire. Now in desperate straits, the company recently filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection, and dismissed 400 people, or 20 percent of its staff at the corporate headquarters here.</p>
        <p>Chicago these days, especially on the North Side and along the lakefront, is no longer a town filled with typical Montgomery Ward customers: sensible, no-frills shoppers who think twice before spending a hard-earned dollar.</p>
        <p>Rather, it is the razzle-dazzle of North Michigan Avenue, the high-end stores along the Magnificent Mile, that has been setting the Chicago retail market on fire.</p>
        <p>Unemployment has dropped below 6 percent, the lowest in more than 20 years. The fastest job growth is in the financial sector, including people who have grown suddenly rich in the high-flying stock market.</p>
        <p>Chicago is gaining on the dirty rats, and not just the kind targeted by the prosecutor's office.</p>
        <p>Rodents are dying off in this city. Not so long ago, rats outnumbered Chicagoans more than 2 to 1.</p>
        <p>People strolling along Rush Street in the Gold Coast, a neighborhood of expensive brownstones and boutiques along the lakefront just north of downtown, sometimes crossed paths with the furry creatures -- which did not create the best kind of advertisement for tourists.</p>
        <p>But an aggressive campaign to clean up neighborhoods and require tighter lids of garbage containers has cut the rat population to about 500,000, down from about 6 million in 1979, according to the city.</p>
        <p>Chicago politics have become so peaceful they are almost boring, except, of course, for the corruption. During the 1980's, Chicago was called Beirut on the Lake for its political warring, often along racial lines.</p>
        <p>For the last few years, this city has largely been getting the kind of ink that is better than advertisements, like the glowing reviews that surrounded last year's Democratic National Convention here.</p>
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley, the son of the legendary boss of the Chicago machine, much prefers the role of efficient manager to ward politician. In his easy re-election in 1991, Mr. Daley won 25 percent of the black vote, up from the single-digit percentage in his first successful campaign for the office.</p>
        <p>But one politician who thinks Mr. Daley is vulnerable is Representative Bobby Rush, a former Black Panther and later an influential alderman. A Democrat, he is considering a run against Mr. Daley next time around.</p>
        <p>In the view of Mr. Rush, Chicago, under Mayor Daley, has evolved into two unequal societies. He sees the division not so much along racial lines as class ones. He says the Daley administration has used tax incentives to rebuild neighborhoods for the rich, while lining the pockets of developers, a pin-stripe patronage.</p>
        <p>''He's trying to suburbanize Chicago,'' Mr. Rush said.</p>
        <p>The City Council, however has presented Mayor Daley the younger, as he is sometimes called, with virtually no opposition. And he is reaping the rewards of the improvements in the city's fortunes.</p>
        <p>''He will be Mayor as long as he wants,'' said Paul Green, an author on Chicago politics and professor at Governors State University. ''He has far more control over this city than his father ever had.''</p>
        <p>Chicago Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
