<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUT COUNTESS, WE'VE ONLY JUST MET</title>
    <meta content="1ISLANDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FALL AND WINTER CRUISES" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="881398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FALL AND WINTER CRUISES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cunard Line Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Awani Cruise Lines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Furlaud, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EED9113CF935A35753C1A960958260" item-length="1973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUT COUNTESS, WE'VE ONLY JUST MET</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE FURLAUD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Furlaud, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Furlaud article on Caribbean cruise aboard Cunard Countess, just after its announced sale to Awani Cruise Lines; photos; map; says she had just made acquaintance with British crew and passengers when all learned that vessel would sail immediately for new Indonesian home port with new Indonesian crew (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Aug. 17, three and a half weeks  before the Cunard Countess was sold to an Indonesian company called Awani Cruise Lines, I boarded the cruise ship in San Juan, bound for the Lesser Antilles.  From my taxi on the waterfront under a gray, menacing sky, the Countess looked inviting. She was slim-lined and brightly white, with a raked red and black smokestack: a brand-new-looking toy. And next day we were to set out on a Caribbean Capitals cruise, packing six island visits into  seven days, including what the brochure described as ''a relaxing day at sea.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the only relaxing day I had on the activity-packed Cunard Countess was the 18 hours or so I spent in bed, where I crashed  with a fever that first night. I blamed my fever on my unexpectedly exhausting trip from where I live on Cape Cod to San Juan:  the misplacement of my suitcase by the Plymouth and Brockton Bus Company; Logan Airport at 5:44 A.M., full of tired, shorts-clad people heading west with cartons of moribund lobsters. I had been wondering why people go off on cruises, assuming the main motive was my own -- not having to wash the dishes for a week or two. Now I realize people choose cruises to get away from the kind of travel they have to endure to get to the cruise's port of embarcation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Aug. 17, three and a half weeks  before the Cunard Countess was sold to an Indonesian company called Awani Cruise Lines, I boarded the cruise ship in San Juan, bound for the Lesser Antilles.  From my taxi on the waterfront under a gray, menacing sky, the Countess looked inviting. She was slim-lined and brightly white, with a raked red and black smokestack: a brand-new-looking toy. And next day we were to set out on a Caribbean Capitals cruise, packing six island visits into  seven days, including what the brochure described as ''a relaxing day at sea.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the only relaxing day I had on the activity-packed Cunard Countess was the 18 hours or so I spent in bed, where I crashed  with a fever that first night. I blamed my fever on my unexpectedly exhausting trip from where I live on Cape Cod to San Juan:  the misplacement of my suitcase by the Plymouth and Brockton Bus Company; Logan Airport at 5:44 A.M., full of tired, shorts-clad people heading west with cartons of moribund lobsters. I had been wondering why people go off on cruises, assuming the main motive was my own -- not having to wash the dishes for a week or two. Now I realize people choose cruises to get away from the kind of travel they have to endure to get to the cruise's port of embarcation.</p>
        <p>Before crawling into bed I made it in to dinner at a table with six friendly Britons who had already been aboard for a week  and were clearly loving the experience. At first glance all the passengers seemed to be British -- cheerful, middle-aged couples looking at home on the dull-colored, well-worn upholstery and tucking heartily into English tea-shop-style creamy layer cake. It turned out that along with some 500 Britons, there were about 35 Americans and the same number of Germans and South Americans aboard. There was also a healthy sprinkling of young people and children, but the older British set the tone of the cruise. I got the feeling that, like me, most of them had bought their summer clothes around 1970 and saw no need to buy new ones.</p>
        <p>Several of my tablemates knew that the Cunard Line, Britain's pride and joy for generations, had been sold six months  earlier to a Norwegian conglomerate. But none of us guessed that the Countess's career as a Cunard ship would end very shortly -- on Oct. 26 -- and that she would leave San Juan that day for her new Indonesian home port with a new Indonesian crew. It turned out that not one of her starched-white, gold-braided officers knew this either; nor did the jolly bar staff in gaudily flowered ''Caribbean'' shirts or the waiters-of-all-nations so well versed in the Anglophone song ''Happy Birthday.'' (Cunard is going for the richer trade with its six remaining ships, four of which will ply the Caribbean this winter.)</p>
        <p>The British Virgin Island of Tortola was the first stop on our cruise down the curving chain of islands between Puerto Rico and  South America, but all I saw of it was a view from my bedside porthole of the green, embracing hills of Road Town Harbor. I wasn't in a state to mind missing the Tortola glass-bottom boat tour, or any of the day's on-board activities -- Arts and Crafts with Olga, for instance, or the Singles Party (''Travelling Solo? Come along and meet some new acquaintances'').</p>
        <p>But without what turned out later to be Lyme disease, I might never have met the ship's doctor, Dr. Henry Bodsworth, an exact copy of Dr. Graham, ''a kindly elderly man of about 65'' in Agatha Christie's ''Caribbean Mystery,'' which I had started to read on the plane. Dr. Bodsworth's Christie connection, his spiffy navyish whites, his cozy charm and his antibiotics had me on my feet next morning, more or less ready for Antigua, where we had sailed overnight.</p>
        <p>But I hated to leave my cabin, which, in spite of its department store decor and the leak from the bathroom ceiling, became my favorite spot on the boat. It measured 13 feet 6 inches by 8 feet 4 inches. For two people it would be sheer hell, unless they were wildly,  passionately in love. The narrow beds form an L so that my bed, under the generous pair of rectangular portholes -- each about 25 by 14 -- was the only one with a view. The other bed's occupant would have had to crane his (or her) neck across me to see, as I could on waking, a long, gray-green lumpy island topped by a sun-illumined cloud, or a tubby  tugboat chugging importantly toward us.  Now that I know I will never see it again, I miss Cabin No. 4096. And I miss breakfast in bed brought by a superb cabin steward -- Mayet Lorena of the Philippines, who has worked for Cunard for 21 years, 11 of them on the Countess.</p>
        <p>''Hard work, all this enjoying oneself,'' said an old Englishman, toiling with me up the Countess's main staircase after a morning on Antigua. Yes, indeed. Just coming off the air-conditioned ship into the hot West Indian wind and the wild welcome of the Hot Hot Steel Band was so exciting that I got in the wrong bus and missed Lord Nelson's Dockyard and ''an invigorating rum punch at the Admiral's Inn.''</p>
        <p>I kept missing things all week. ''See that mongoose crossing the road?'' ''No. Where? Where?'' I missed having my hair done in cornrows and beads by a beach hairdresser.  I missed a barracuda in St. Thomas's Red Hook harbor; several flying fish off Barbados, including the unfortunate ones on the menu ''prepared in the traditional Bajan way''; a game of Caribbean stud poker (whatever that is), and a volcano that erupted on the island of Montserrat, off our port side, just as I was looking the other way.</p>
        <p>I missed Barbados. But if I had gone ashore, I would have missed the concert by 17 members of the Royal Barbados Police  Band playing during tea in the Showtime Lounge. These musicians, sternly dazzling in dark blue uniforms with red belts and gold epaulets, were the last people you'd  expect to raise the roof as they did with the refrain from the Mouseketeers song, M-I-C-K-E-Y M-O-U-S-E. They were an even greater sensation than the limbo dancer that night, squeezing her body under a flaming bar about three inches from the deck.</p>
        <p>It wouldn't have done to miss Capt. Ron Bolton's Cocktail Party as we rumbled out of the harbor of St. John's, Antigua, on the way to Martinique. A splendid massage by an American masseuse, Myra Engelen, had revived me for this exceedingly British occasion. The couples in the Noah's-Arkish line waiting to be photographed with the genial, sunburned Captain Bolton wore  stately evening dresses, black ties, even an occasional kilt, which they had brought across the Atlantic in order to sail around  their ex-empire in style. And the officers, resplendent in white mess jackets and brass buttons -- the younger ones monopolizing the few young women -- Staff Capt. Richard Burge making sure that everybody had enough champagne.  had something of the seafaring courtesy of Lord Nelson's day. Their correctness was in contrast with the slipshod interior of the ship: the Showtime Lounge's pink-and-gold-curtained stage where the light shone mostly into the onlookers' eyes; the sauna's heat-regulating dial whose numbers had worn off  (''Kaput!'' warned a Viennese passenger -- an engineer).</p>
        <p>''It's pretty tatty at the corners,'' said David, a British executive at my table who with his glamorous German companion, Karin, is a veteran of ''some dozen'' cruises. He added affectionately, ''It's a very British cruise.'' David and Karin had not attended the Passenger Talent Show, thus missing a moving interpretation of ''Old Man River'' by a British passenger so old himself that when he got to ''sweat and strain'' we all feared for his life. And when the baked Alaska procession appeared -- 30 or 40 waiters dancing through the dining room in a kind of conga line, each holding aloft a flaming dessert, David merely commented, ''You notice there's only a little brandy in an eggshell at the top.''</p>
        <p>The cruise was too buttoned-down for my new friend Lorraine, a youngish Englishwoman with a shock of  Troll-doll-like magenta hair. ''The Big Red Boat cruise is much more fun than this,'' she said. ''Pirates kidnap you and take you onto their ship.'' We were walking back to the ship in Fort-de-France, Martinique, after a spectacular bus drive up in the mountains, through Jurassic Park-like rain forests, a butterfly  farm (why have a butterfly farm? I didn't have time to ask) and the ruins of St.-Pierre, a town buried in a volcanic eruption that killed 30,000 people in 1902.</p>
        <p>I spent the last morning of the cruise on a crowded beach -- white, with translucent cerulean waters.  The ship had circled back from the Leeward islands to the Virgin Islands, and this was St. John, V.I. I lay in the shade of a sea grape tree, feeding a flock of odd-looking gulls with scraps of bread I'd saved for this occasion. My honeymoon took place here 44 years ago, before tourists, electricity or automobiles, and we were ridiculously young and happy.</p>
        <p>I was about to become mawkish  when I met up with Nicola and Keith, a couple in their 30's from Bakewell, Derbyshire, who had been on the Countess for two weeks in a state of bliss.  Nothing daunted them, even their  tiny inside cabin, and they were all agog for another cruise on the Countess when they could afford it. They had taken an organized excursion every day, gotten up early for copious English breakfasts and stayed up late to admire the watermelon carvings at the midnight buffet. Now, after a strenuous morning in the water (''He doesn't snorkel but I do,'' said Nicola), they couldn't wait to get back to the ship for Open House on the Bridge.</p>
        <p>The officer who showed us around was Larry, a tall, young Irishman full of shy good will and with one stripe on his shoulder. He told us the Countess still used hoses to put out fires on board, a method no longer legal at sea. ''Next year we're installing a sprinkler system,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Oh dear. Next year, it seems, the Countess will be cruising without Larry, and among other islands -- Java? Sumatra? Bali? -- under another name. Farewell, good ship Cunard Countess and all your gallant crew!</p>
        <p>More than one ship in the sea</p>
        <p>For those who have reserved cabins on the Countess for cruises that are not to be, there are various forms and degrees of compensation. If passengers simply want their money back, they will get a full refund of whatever they paid, including air fare, plus a credit (roughly $385 to $785, depending on the cabin booked for the Countess) valid on any Cunard cruise through June 1997. Call (800) 728-6273.</p>
        <p>Those who still want to cruise the Caribbean are offered a number of alternative choices on Cunard ships. The Cunard Dynasty, Queen Elizabeth 2, the Sea Goddess II and the Vistafjord will be in the Caribbean this winter. (See page 16 for complete schedule.)</p>
        <p>FALL AND WINTER CRUISES  ALICE FURLAUD, a writer and radio broadcaster, divides her time between Paris and Cape Cod.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ALICE FURLAUD, a writer and radio broadcaster, divides her time between Paris and Cape Cod.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
