<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Car Leases Clarified: At Least a Stab at It</title>
    <meta content="06LEAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="SPENDING IT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="881686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="SPENDING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siwolop, Sana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D7133FF935A35753C1A960958260" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Car Leases Clarified: At Least a Stab at It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANA SIWOLOP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siwolop, Sana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve Board, which regulates most consumer car leases, issues new rules aimed at simplifying transactions and clarifying actual charges to consumers (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the prospect of leasing rather than buying a new car has you cowering in confusion, you are not alone.</p>
        <p>While car leasing has become popular, it is often impossible to determine the true costs because the contracts have never had to follow strict disclosure rules. Many consumers simply assume they are paying a relatively paltry sum -- say $199 a month over three years -- to lease a car. But what are the actual lease charges, as well as the car's basic price? And how much do consumers have to pay if they end leases early?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the prospect of leasing rather than buying a new car has you cowering in confusion, you are not alone.</p>
        <p>While car leasing has become popular, it is often impossible to determine the true costs because the contracts have never had to follow strict disclosure rules. Many consumers simply assume they are paying a relatively paltry sum -- say $199 a month over three years -- to lease a car. But what are the actual lease charges, as well as the car's basic price? And how much do consumers have to pay if they end leases early?</p>
        <p>On Sept. 27, the Federal Reserve Board, which regulates most consumer leases, issued new rules aimed at simplifying leasing transactions and clarifying the actual charges to consumers. The Fed also issued a standardized form for consumers to take to their dealers. It requires the dealers to break out 20 possible leasing costs. Among other things, the form specifically asks dealers to list a car's gross capitalized cost (essentially the car's agreed-upon value), security deposits, insurance premiums, disposition fees, taxes and its residual value, which is the estimated value of the car at the end of the lease.</p>
        <p>Although the forms can be obtained from the Fed now (by writing to the Federal Reserve Board, Publication Services, 20th and C Streets N.W., Washington, D.C. 20551, and asking for the Federal Consumer Leasing Act Disclosures form), the new rules will not go into effect until October of next year. Still, the American Financial Services Association, which represents most big car-leasing companies, plans to encourage members to comply with the new form.</p>
        <p>''This is all information that we would give a customer anyway,'' said Tony Chianese, the general manager at Martin's Manhattan, an auto dealership in New York. ''Most factory-authorized dealers have nothing to hide with leasing.''</p>
        <p>The leasing arms that serve many large car makers say they have already begun to disclose much of the Fed information. Last year, Ford Motor Credit became one of the first large car-leasing companies to simplify its consumer leasing contracts.</p>
        <p>Before Ford Credit took action, the company's leasing contract was a wordy muddle of information.</p>
        <p>Now, however, the contract is not only easier to understand, but it uses four-color icons to steer consumers to important information, like a lease's total monthly costs, fees and taxes. For example, the contract uses a picture of an alarm clock to alert consumers that they will have to pay either a late charge of 7.5 percent or $50 (whichever is less) for payments that aren't received within 10 days after they are due. Several other leasing arms of car makers, including Toyota and General Motors, have also simplified their contracts.</p>
        <p>Despite the growing disclosure, many consumer advocates are not happy with all of the results.</p>
        <p>Mary Ponder, senior projects director at the Consumer Federation of America in Washington, said that although the new form alerted consumers to the possibility of having to pay ''up to several thousand dollars'' if they end their leases early, the warning is so general that ''consumers will tend to read over it.''</p>
        <p>''Before, this information was pretty much buried in fine print, but we'd still like to see an example; in other words, if you terminate, it will cost you 'x' amount,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ponder said she was also unhappy that the new rules do not require a cooling-off period so consumers could cancel if they had second thoughts.</p>
        <p>''This form is a double-edged sword,'' Ms. Ponder added. ''It will help consumers see all the numbers, but they still won't be able to comparison-shop for the best deal.''</p>
        <p>The Fed did consider mandating the disclosure of the annual leasing rate, but decided not to because the rate is subject to variations in a car's residual value. The Fed feared that the residual value would be manipulated to lower the leasing rate.</p>
        <p>''You can get the same monthly payment using a 6 percent interest and a low residual (say, 65 percent), or a 12 percent interest rate and a high residual (say, 73 percent),'' said Bill Odom, the chairman of the Ford Motor Credit Company. ''A customer might look at the two options, select the 6 percent rate and make the wrong decision.''</p>
        <p>SPENDING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
