<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Sex, a Senator and a Press Circus</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PALM BEACH (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, EDWARD M (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, WILLIAM KENNEDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOWMAN, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Palm Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDC163DF935A35757C0A967958260" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Sex, a Senator and a Press Circus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An accusation of rape at the Kennedy family's estate in Palm Beach, Fla., last weekend has generated what may be the most intense news coverage of any story since the war in the Persian Gulf ended last month.</p>
        <p>An estimated 300 journalists have descended on the Florida resort, fighting over news tips, chasing after the woman who said she was raped, running down the vaguest rumors and generating classic tabloid-style headlines like "Bachelors Party," "Teddy Wore Only a T-shirt," and "The Curse of the Kennedys Has Struck Again."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An accusation of rape at the Kennedy family's estate in Palm Beach, Fla., last weekend has generated what may be the most intense news coverage of any story since the war in the Persian Gulf ended last month.</p>
        <p>An estimated 300 journalists have descended on the Florida resort, fighting over news tips, chasing after the woman who said she was raped, running down the vaguest rumors and generating classic tabloid-style headlines like "Bachelors Party," "Teddy Wore Only a T-shirt," and "The Curse of the Kennedys Has Struck Again."</p>
        <p>But beyond the circuslike atmosphere generated by the enormous press presence, editors say, is the serious story of a possible cover-up -- and once again, with the involvement of Kennedys, the idea of a separate standard of justice for the influential and well-born. An Editor is Astonished</p>
        <p>"Isn't it astonishing," asked Jerry Nachman, editor of The New York Post, "that a week after the alleged incident took place, not one of the three potential suspects has been questioned by the police?"</p>
        <p>Many news reports have noted that no information about the incident was made public until Monday and that the Palm Beach police three times changed their account of how the incident was reported to them. By then, Senator Edward M. Kennedy, his son Patrick and his nephew William Kennedy Smith, who encountered the woman at a bar early Saturday, had left Florida.</p>
        <p>But has the coverage been too sensational? "I belong to the res ipsa loquitur school of journalism," Mr. Nachman said. "The thing speaks for itself.</p>
        <p>"It may not be the quintessential tabloid story but it's close. It's got sex, violence, the rich, a sultry setting, a controversial United States Senator who may or may not have been wearing shorts, and the police acting out of character.</p>
        <p>"Or maybe in character," Mr. Nachman went on. "There is that resonance of Chappaquiddick, with its second level of justice."</p>
        <p>Bill Kovach, curator of the Nieman Foundation at Harvard University, said: "It's the job of the press to monitor law enforcement and the behavior of public officials and public institutions. But when you get a thousand papers and TV stations and magazines all on the same story, it creates a lot of questions, such as, 'Is this story that important?'</p>
        <p>"There can be too much of a good thing," he said, "particularly in the early phases of an investigation when public attitudes are so quickly and easily shaped." Battleground Is New York</p>
        <p>While the story unfolds in Florida, the journalistic battleground is New York. There, three tabloids, New York Newsday, The Post and the recently revived Daily News, are battling fiercely over a shrinking newspaper market.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, when the story broke, both The Post and The News devoted the front page to what The News called the "Kennedy Mansion Rape Probe." New York Newsday went with the Mets' signing of Dwight Gooden, "The $16 Million Man."</p>
        <p>The Post carried it on the front page every day: "Bachelors Party" on Wednesday, "I Want Justice," on Thursday, and yesterday, "Teddy's Sexy Romp."</p>
        <p>The News put non-Kennedy articles on the front page on Wednesday and Thursday, but yesterday it was back. The headline: "Palm Beach Cover-Up."</p>
        <p>"I think we're doing well," said Matthew V. Storin, The Daily News's managing editor. "It's a sensitive story, as is any rape story, and it also involves famous people. There is a temptation to go overboard, but we've been accurate; we haven't had to retract anything." Shots in Tabloid War</p>
        <p>Both The Post and The News have found space in their coverage to take shots at each other and at Newsday.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, The Post ran an article in which a woman said that Senator Kennedy was pursuing her through the ocean-front mansion clad only in a T-shirt at the same time the other woman said she was being raped.</p>
        <p>In The News, the woman gave a much less lurid account of the incident and complained that The Post had misquoted her.</p>
        <p>Most papers have refused to publish the name of the woman who filed the rape complaint, even though it is widely known in Palm Beach. And not until a Fort Lauderdale newspaper named Mr. Smith as the prime suspect did others publish his name. The Palm Beach police officially named him as a suspect yesterday.</p>
        <p>Some of the more sensational newspapers were resorting to tactics old-time newsmen refer to as the "Chicago school" of journalistic enterprise. The Washington Post reported that a reporter for The National Enquirer got into the Humana Hospital emergency room, where the woman was being treated. Silently, he handed a nurse his card, on the back of which was written: "$500 for her name."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
