<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Are We There Yet?' Becomes 'Where's the Barney Tape?'</title>
    <meta content="31DRIV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1396573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="DRIVING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kravetz, Stacy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E5DE163AF932A05756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Are We There Yet?' Becomes 'Where's the Barney Tape?'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACY KRAVETZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kravetz, Stacy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>dA</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was a time in the not-too-distant past when playing car games like ''count the cows'' and ''license-plate bingo'' was about as much back-seat entertainment as a child could expect on the road.</p>
        <p>No more. These days, the car, or in many cases, the S.U.V., has become a mobile theater, where back-seat passengers can watch television shows or movies, listen to music or play video games, all without disturbing the driver.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was a time in the not-too-distant past when playing car games like ''count the cows'' and ''license-plate bingo'' was about as much back-seat entertainment as a child could expect on the road.</p>
        <p>No more. These days, the car, or in many cases, the S.U.V., has become a mobile theater, where back-seat passengers can watch television shows or movies, listen to music or play video games, all without disturbing the driver.</p>
        <p>Although the entertainment systems are still in just a small , number of cars, every maker of S.U.V.'s and many carmakers either offer the systems on some models or plan to offer them in the near future.</p>
        <p>Carmakers add about $2,000 to the base price for the entertainment packages, though the systems are available through electronics retailers for less. A system with a six-inch screen has a retail price of about $800, while an upgraded model with a DVD player and a seven-inch screen sells for about $1,000, less than half the price several years ago.</p>
        <p>''The popularity of these products continues to climb, and customers seem to constantly look for new places to install screens,'' said Gary Weinhouse, chief financial officer for Al &amp; Ed's Auto Sound, a chain store based in City of Commerce, Calif. These include on the backs of headrests, behind sun visors and in the trunk (for watching movies at tailgating parties), he said. Rear-seat systems have grown into one of the chain's most popular items.</p>
        <p>Those who have the systems say they don't know how they survived without them. And they certainly don't long for quainter times.</p>
        <p>''It's the best thing I ever did,'' said Brian Prince, a Los Angeles resident, who put an Audiovox flat-screen 6.4-inch monitor with a TV and VCR into his Ford Explorer. Driving with three children in the back, pre-entertainment days, was ''murder,'' he said. ''I didn't want to go too far with them in the car.''</p>
        <p>Now, driving is pleasant again, he said. To be sure, it is not exactly a private pursuit of pleasure, especially in stop-and-go traffic, where it's easy to glance at what's playing in surrounding cars. ''I've had a person pull up next to me and say, 'Great movie,' '' Mr. Prince said. ''And that was the driver.''</p>
        <p>Tricia Turner, a San Francisco driver, was so distracted by a car with two TV screens that she found herself paying attention to the passengers and their shows rather than watching the road. ''It irked me that I couldn't tell what was on,'' she said. ''Needless to say, that is not a good scenario while on the freeway at night.''</p>
        <p>Add to that the distraction of talking on a cellphone and keeping a chai latte from spilling, and driving can become quite a challenge.</p>
        <p>The basic rear-seat entertainment system features a six- or seven-inch flat screen that flips down from the ceiling or is a monitor mounted in the console between the front seats. The systems come with a VCR or a DVD player, and most are capable of receiving TV signals and playing local programs. Passengers can either plug a headset into the unit or use a wireless version. Most of the systems have a remote control.</p>
        <p>Other options include the ability to plug in video-game players like Sony PlayStation or Nintendo 64. Some systems are compatible with personal computers.</p>
        <p>The main appeal of the rear entertainment systems is for parents, who say they can finally get some peace in the car, now that their children are wearing headsets and silently watching television or a movie.</p>
        <p>''These systems are targeted toward children,'' said Jennifer Zajac, a spokeswoman for Delphi Automotive Systems, a Troy, Mich., maker of rear-seat systems offered in General Motors cars and Ford S.U.V.'s. ''We're trying to keep back-seat passengers entertained and occupied.''</p>
        <p>Even parents who like the concept say it is not the be-all to back-seat boredom. ''It has been pretty good for long car rides, although I am not sure its use justifies what was then about a $1,000-plus price tag,'' said Ann Louise Price, who put a VCR and a monitor in her Mercedes-Benz S.U.V. three years ago. Only one of her two children uses the system regularly on their winter drives from Farmington, Conn., to Vermont because the other often gets carsick and ends up not watching anything.</p>
        <p>But for many, the mere concept of keeping children entertained on the road has proven too good to pass up. ''Ten percent of cars we sell end up with a Rosen video screen and DVD player,'' said Phil Vass, manager of a Land Rover dealership in Mission Viejo, Calif.</p>
        <p>The same is true on the East Coast. ''We were selling one a month, and now we're selling three a month,'' said Bill Hogan, manager of a Land Rover dealership in Parsippany, N.J.</p>
        <p>Some drivers apparently don't find enough sport in simply gawking at the liquid-crystal display screens of others.</p>
        <p>While none of the car manufacturers offer video entertainment for front-seat passengers, it is possible to buy them from car-stereo retailers and have them installed after buying a car. Some car owners are buying adapters that allow them to convert dashboard navigation systems into DVD players. Others are buying small dashboard-mounted monitors for video entertainment, despite the ideal of actually watching the road while driving.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, drivers can be distracted by them,'' said Mr. Weinhouse of Al &amp; Ed's. So the store will only install video monitors on the dashboard or on the driver's sun visor if they are linked to the parking brake. That way, drivers can watch them only when their cars are stopped.</p>
        <p>For those who would rather not watch, or for drivers who are worried they're missing out on the entertainment revolution, there are always audio systems, some of which promise surround-sound ability with a dozen speakers. Other audio systems feature satellite radio or the ability to play MP3's.</p>
        <p>But just try to convince a child that radio is as good as a DVD player. Or that counting cows is as much fun as watching ''Spider-Man'' for the 14th time. You're better off keeping your eyes on the road.</p>
        <p>SOURCES  Entertainment, From Television To Chilled Perrier</p>
        <p>Rear-Seat Entertainment Systems  Most car manufacturers are offering these systems on certain models of new S.U.V.'s, minivans and cars, and individual dealers are including them as an aftermarket option. Entertainment systems can also be installed on older cars or S.U.V.'s by purchasing them through electronics retailers. Popular makers of rear-seat systems include Bosch, Visteon and Delphi.</p>
        <p>MP3 Players  For the musically inclined driver who doesn't get enough from the radio or CD's, MP3 players will accommodate music downloaded from the Internet. Offered by most car-stereo makers.</p>
        <p>Satellite Radio  The new wave in radio is the satellite system, which allows drivers to listen to up to 100 digital channels broadcast via satellite to an in-car receiver catering to specialized preferences, including jazz and blues, comedy and sports. They are provided by XM (www.xmradio.com) and Sirius (www.siriusradio.com).</p>
        <p>OnStar  Although OnStar is known mainly for its ''talking'' navigation system, it also offers services like a ''live concierge,'' which will help get tickets to events or make dinner reservations. Available for the following makes: Acura, Buick, Cadillac, Chevrolet, GMC, Oldsmobile, Pontiac, Saab and Saturn (www.onstar.com).</p>
        <p>Chilled Perrier  There's always the option of entertaining in your car. Volvo's 75th anniversary edition of its S80 features an optional refrigerator compartment mounted in the center armrest, which can hold two 750-milliliter bottles. There is a glassware storage cabinet in the rear shelf.</p>
        <p>DRIVING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
