<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="17DIAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DA1F3AF934A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy and Ron Alexander</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>On a flight from Hartford to Chicago recently, a lovely lady who has to be everyone's idea of a grandmother settled into the seat next to me. Obviously not a frequent flier, she looked about with lively interest.</p>
        <p>''Not a spacious seat,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>On a flight from Hartford to Chicago recently, a lovely lady who has to be everyone's idea of a grandmother settled into the seat next to me. Obviously not a frequent flier, she looked about with lively interest.</p>
        <p>''Not a spacious seat,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''No,'' I replied.</p>
        <p>''They certainly don't give you a lot of room for your knees, do they?''</p>
        <p>''No, they don't,'' I said.</p>
        <p>When our meals arrived, she examined the salad closely, and she poked the cellophane-wrapped roll with an inquiring finger.</p>
        <p>''Bread,'' I said, anticipating her question.</p>
        <p>Then the main course arrived, which bore a faint resemblance to chicken. She looked at it and tested it with her fork. Then, very quietly, she mused: ''So this is life in the fast lane.''</p>
        <p>LEE HANNA</p>
        <p>Trying on a bathing suit at Bloomingdale's, Menorah Rotenberg overheard the following conversation between the woman in the next dressing room and the woman's husband, waiting outside.</p>
        <p>He: Honey, are you hungry?</p>
        <p>She: After trying on these suits. I'll never be hungry again.</p>
        <p>Verla C. Gabriel was in an elevator with two other women, obviously friends. One, who had seen a list of to-do chores posted in the other's kitchen, asked what ''metal'' meant.</p>
        <p>''It means cleaning silver,'' the friend replied. ''I didn't want to write silver because if a burglar came, he'd start looking for it.''</p>
        <p>''You could write 'argent' or another foreign word,'' the first woman suggested.</p>
        <p>No way, said the woman. ''New York burglars are multilingual, everyone knows that.''</p>
        <p>Rachel Hirshorn, on the verge of her fifth birthday, is ''a real New Yorker,'' according to her grandmother, Nancy Yanes-Hoffman. Recently, after finishing her dinner, Rachel jumped up from the table, eager to read a new book.</p>
        <p>''What do you say before you leave the table?'' her mother asked.</p>
        <p>''Check,'' Rachel replied.</p>
        <p>''No Rachel,'' her mother groaned. ''That's not what you say.''</p>
        <p>Rachel thought for a minute. ''I know,'' she said. ''Check, please.''</p>
        <p>The softball field is a short walk from Robert T. Quade's house in Bernardsville, N.J., and for more than three decades he has strolled down on summer evenings to watch the men's teams in action.</p>
        <p>Over the years, there have been changes: uniforms and equipment, sponsors, haircut styles, cellular phones.</p>
        <p>Many players, coming directly from work, have wolfed down pizza slices, hamburgers and sub sandwiches, but on a hot dusty day last month there was another innovation. As his team was at bat, an infielder took over third-base coaching, keeping a keen eye on the batter and runners while, with great aplomb and handling his chopsticks faultlessly, he munched sushi.</p>
        <p>Sheila Stuart was looking for a parking space on East 71st Street recently when she spied a car about to pull out. So did the motorist ahead of her. As she attempted to pull forward into it, the driver ahead simultaneously tried to back in. Stalemate. Both sat there, neither one able to claim the spot,  and neither one willing to give it up.</p>
        <p>After a few minutes, the other driver got out of his car and walked back toward Ms. Stuart, who rolled down her window and asked, ''Are you a gambling man?'' He was, he said. How about flipping a coin for the space, she asked. He produced a quarter, flipped it and said, ''Your call.''</p>
        <p>''Heads,'' Ms. Stuart called -- and it was. The man smiled, got into his car and drove off, no doubt to continue his search.</p>
        <p>Commuters to New York are so used to traffic jams that they generally take them in stride. In five years of commuting from New Jersey to Manhattan over the George Washington Bridge, Leslee Fetner has seen drivers reading newspapers, styling their hair, applying makeup and, of course, talking on their cell phones. But she was pleasantly distracted one day recently when traffic was particularly heavy. A sleek blue sports convertible pulled alongside. The driver -- white plastic baton in hand -- was earnestly conducting a symphony that was obviously coming from his radio or compact disk player. Next stop, Carnegie Hall?</p>
        <p>Scene: Express train from Old Greenwich to Grand Central.</p>
        <p>Players: Two businessmen</p>
        <p>Observer: Jennifer Sherwood</p>
        <p>First businessman: ''We finally got our new Suburban. It's perfect. It has two pull-down movie screens in the backseat and two matching headsets. We don't have to worry about the kids bothering us on long car trips. You should look into it.</p>
        <p>Second businessman, not missing a beat: ''Well, I'll have to come over soon with the kids, and we'll put them in the driveway.''</p>
        <p>Scene: Evelyn Murphy in her local supermarket, watching:</p>
        <p>Action: A woman in the soup aisle, looking tired and completely uninterested. She glances at the rows and rows of soup labels and takes out her cell phone. She punches several buttons, still looking bored. ''So, what do you want for supper?'' she asks.</p>
        <p>Francine Silverman enjoyed this sign on the United Methodist Church in Fleischmanns, N.Y.</p>
        <p>IF YOU'RE NOT AS CLOSE TO GOD AS YOU USED TO BE, GUESS WHO MOVED.</p>
        <p>Observations for this column may be sent to Metropolitan Diary, Style Department, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036. Please include your name, address and daytime telephone number; upon request, names may be withheld in print. Letters become the property of The Times and cannot be returned. They may be edited, and may be republished in all media.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
