<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Old Times Square, Home for the Hopeless</title>
    <meta content="04WATC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/04/arts/04WATC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1298899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mai-Yi Theater Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ong, Han</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arcenas, Loy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Watcher (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Times Square (New York)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Ong, Han</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D7143FF937A35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="870" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Old Times Square, Home for the Hopeless</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Mai-Yi Theater Co's premiere production of Han Ong's play Watcher, directed by Loy Arcenas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So thoroughly has Times Square been transformed in the past decade that depictions of its red-lighted, ominously atmospheric recent past are already nostalgic. That's one effect of ''Watcher,'' a piquing but unfulfilling play by the Filipino-American playwright Han Ong receiving its premiere production by the Ma-Yi Theater Company at Cap 21 Theater. But another is to be reminded that while for native New Yorkers the sleaze at the crossroads of the world was a perverse badge of identity (the equivalent of the T-shirt slogan ''Welcome to New York -- Now Go Home''), for the newly arrived and culturally disoriented it represented entry-level opportunity.</p>
        <p>The characters in ''Watcher'' -- Loretta, a Filipino who has moved from California, fleeing an unhappy marriage; her 19-year-old son, Angelo, who seems vaguely intellectually impaired; Loretta's patient suitor, Cinquenta, a Hispanic man with whom she works at a movie theater; and Nestor, a 25-year-old gay hustler who befriends Angelo -- are all adrift in the now-vanished Times Square. The setting is a kind of time capsule that circumscribes the world of the play and holds within it the raw materials from which future lives are forged. That the play makes vivid an unusual perspective on a familiar setting is its biggest strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So thoroughly has Times Square been transformed in the past decade that depictions of its red-lighted, ominously atmospheric recent past are already nostalgic. That's one effect of ''Watcher,'' a piquing but unfulfilling play by the Filipino-American playwright Han Ong receiving its premiere production by the Ma-Yi Theater Company at Cap 21 Theater. But another is to be reminded that while for native New Yorkers the sleaze at the crossroads of the world was a perverse badge of identity (the equivalent of the T-shirt slogan ''Welcome to New York -- Now Go Home''), for the newly arrived and culturally disoriented it represented entry-level opportunity.</p>
        <p>The characters in ''Watcher'' -- Loretta, a Filipino who has moved from California, fleeing an unhappy marriage; her 19-year-old son, Angelo, who seems vaguely intellectually impaired; Loretta's patient suitor, Cinquenta, a Hispanic man with whom she works at a movie theater; and Nestor, a 25-year-old gay hustler who befriends Angelo -- are all adrift in the now-vanished Times Square. The setting is a kind of time capsule that circumscribes the world of the play and holds within it the raw materials from which future lives are forged. That the play makes vivid an unusual perspective on a familiar setting is its biggest strength.</p>
        <p>For these characters Times Square is not only foreign, threatening and squalid, it is a kind of home, and they need to make it what home needs to be: a place of safety and promise. What Mr. Ong and his director, Loy Arcenas, have mainly accomplished here is to suggest a genuine society in which decent people accept their very specific impoverished lot as the playing field of their lives.</p>
        <p>Loretta, stressed out with breadwinning and motherhood and played with stirring grimness by Mia Katigbak, finds refuge behind the glass of her ticket booth, even after the theater switches to adult movies; Nestor (Anthony Ruivivar) has developed an eagle eye for the hungry and naïve young men he can exploit. Cinquenta (Gilbert Cruz, in a touching portrait of gentleness) has learned to be a master of accommodation to circumstance.</p>
        <p>''These men want hope,'' he says, explaining how he can stand to work in the theater among its furtive and leering customers. ''They wanna be seduced. They wanna be touched. If you ask me, that's what they want.''</p>
        <p>And the slow-thinking but impetuously moody Angelo (Orlando Pabotoy), on the brink of independence and perplexed about where to place his affection and trust, is almost puppyishly eager to resolve his confusion. His dreams fed by movies, he rattles about among the three others like a pinball.</p>
        <p>With the help of a handful of minor characters, these four people manage to define a remarkably layered network of emotions and issues, and Mr. Arcenas has directed so that the sense of a teeming city is palpably hovering. Wearing his more familiar hat as the set designer, Mr. Arcenas has used besmeared clear panels, chipped gray walls, the glass coffinlike ticket booth and a handful of subway signs to create an abstract urban decrepitude; it has a war-torn quality without the war.</p>
        <p>He has encouraged his actors to reflect the playwright's subtly singular diction: the characters speak with preoccupied abruptness, sudden shifts of focus, eruptions of emotion, and there's kind of ferocity to their moods. Their moment-to-moment behavior has a piquant, nonnative idiom.</p>
        <p>It is therefore disappointing that the characters respond so conventionally, apparently in the interest of plot, to the tests and temptations of their environment. The older characters use their maturity and patience to carve some peace and goodness for themselves, and the younger ones, rebelling against their elders, are irresistibly drawn by the road to depravity.</p>
        <p>The story, which traces a family crisis, develops along predictable lines. Angelo, resenting Cinquenta's incursions on his mother's affections, leaves home in a misguided fit of abandonment and attaches himself to Nestor, whom he sees as loyal and guiding and even fatherly. The rudimentary psychology of it all may be credible but isn't very provocative or even idiosyncratic.</p>
        <p>It is of course part of the playwright's intention to make these people recognizable to those in the audience who might otherwise be in the habit of dismissing them. But the pleasure of looking through a theatrical peephole on the atmospheric life in a now-vanished neighborhood is more or less used up by intermission. Afterward, the connect-the-dots, tie-up-loose-ends focus makes you impatient; there's a great deal of ponderous talk in the service of the familiar and the inevitable. It does to the play what Disney has done to Times Square: diminished the luridness and the allure.</p>
        <p>WATCHER</p>
        <p>By Han Ong; director and set designer, Loy Arcenas; lighting by James Vermeulen; composer and sound designer, Fabian Obispo; costumes by Clint E. B. Ramos; production stage manager, Cristina Sison. Presented by Ma-Yi Theater Company, Jorge Ortoll, executive director; Ralph Pe~na, artistic director; Andrew Eisenman, company manager. At Cap 21 Theater, 15 West 28th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mia Katigbak (Loretta), Marty Zentz (Man/Boy), Orlando Pabotoy (Angelo), Gilbert Cruz (Cinquenta), Virginia Wing (Bessie), Jojo Gonzalez (Jun), Anthony Ruivivar (Nestor), Ching Valdes Aran (Tia Maria) and Harvey Perr (Johnson).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
