<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thoughts Are Turning (Not Lightly) to Spraying</title>
    <meta content="19MOSQ$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1185134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirby, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4D7143AF93AA25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thoughts Are Turning (Not Lightly) to Spraying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KIRBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirby, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Community leaders, elected officials and environmental groups are raising concerns about pesticide spraying as New York City prepares for new mosquito season and re-emergence of West Nile virus; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the city prepares for a new mosquito season and the re-emergence of the West Nile virus, community leaders, elected officials and environmental groups are raising concerns about pesticide spraying.</p>
        <p>Opponents of spraying have urged the city to explore alternatives to malathion, the pesticide used around the city last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the city prepares for a new mosquito season and the re-emergence of the West Nile virus, community leaders, elected officials and environmental groups are raising concerns about pesticide spraying.</p>
        <p>Opponents of spraying have urged the city to explore alternatives to malathion, the pesticide used around the city last year.</p>
        <p>Led by Borough President Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx Borough Board, including representatives of 12 community boards, passed a resolution calling on Mayor Giuliani to consult with the City Council and the borough presidents before any spraying, and urging the city to use the ''least toxic alternatives to malathion'' should spraying be unavoidable.</p>
        <p>The measure also calls for ''aggressive and accurate'' public notice to prevent pesticide exposure, and for data collection on any ill effects. And it asks the mayor ''not to refer to malathion as 'harmless.' ''</p>
        <p>Last month, the Manhattan Borough Board passed a similar resolution, and efforts are under way to get it approved in the remaining three boroughs, Mr. Ferrer said.</p>
        <p>Councilman Victor Robles, the chairman of the City Council's Health Committee, said that if all the borough boards pass such resolutions, he would introduce a similar one.</p>
        <p>No one from the mayor's office was available for comment.</p>
        <p>City officials say that malathion is safe it is used within federal guidelines. After the recent discovery of genetic signs of the virus in hibernating mosquitos in Fort Totten, Queens, and reports of an infected hawk found in Bronxville in Westchester, the city has stepped up efforts to eliminate mosquito breeding grounds.</p>
        <p>But city officials also say they will consider pesticide spraying if there is a significant public health threat. Last year, seven deaths and 62 serious illnesses in the New York region were attributed to the virus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrer said last year's spraying ''happened at the worst times; when kids were coming home from school and parents from work, in spite of assurances to the contrary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrer said he was concerned about the use of malathion. ''Malathion is found in Raid,'' he said. ''Spray some of that over your head and see how you feel.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Johnson, who overseas the United States Environmental Protection Agency's pesticide program, said malathion was undergoing an independent scientific review, as mandated by a 1996 federal law to re-evaluate pesticides. Malathion, he said, is currently classified as ''slightly toxic.'' But the chemical is typically applied ''at ultralow volumes'' and, as such, has minimal impact. Still, he said, no pesticide is 100 percent safe.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the New York League of Conservation Voters has urged that the city use ''the least toxic means of protecting public health,'' and that it use aerial spraying only as a last resort.</p>
        <p>And the New York Green Party has formed what it calls the No-Spray Coalition to seek a city moratorium on pesticide spraying against mosquitoes. Mitchell Cohen, a party spokesman, said his group received hundreds of calls last year from people saying they suffered ill effects.</p>
        <p>DAVID KIRBY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
