<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Same-State Series Have Been TV Losers</title>
    <meta content="18SAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/18/sports/baseball/18SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1432868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <org class="online_producer">San Francisco Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Hunt, Bonnie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Goren, Ed</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DE133DF93BA25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Same-State Series Have Been TV Losers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Same-State Series Have Not Been Ratings Winners</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California teams Anaheim Angels and San Francisco Giants face off in this year's World Series, prompting many to wonder how large television viewership will be for same-state series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Anaheim-San Francisco World Series, which Fox will televise, is the fifth Series since 1985 to be played in one state.</p>
        <p>There may be joy in California, but similar matchups in the past have shown that they do not usually attract viewers in the numbers of World Series between teams from different states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Anaheim-San Francisco World Series, which Fox will televise, is the fifth Series since 1985 to be played in one state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Anaheim-San Francisco World Series, which Fox will televise, is the fifth Series since 1985 to be played in one state.</p>
        <p>There may be joy in California, but similar matchups in the past have shown that they do not usually attract viewers in the numbers of World Series between teams from different states.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the Yankees' five-game triumph over the Mets was the lowest-rated, least-viewed World Series in Nielsen Market Research's record books.</p>
        <p>In 1989, when an earthquake before Game 3 interrupted the most recent all-California Series for 12 days, the Oakland Athletics' four-game sweep of the Giants produced record lows in viewership and ratings that lasted 11 years.</p>
        <p>The closest comparison to the Anaheim-San Francisco series occurred in 1988, when the Dodgers beat Oakland. The Dodgers, like the Angels, come from the Los Angeles market; the A's share the Bay Area with the Giants. That series attracted 34.5 million viewers, more than any to come in the 1990's, but the 1987 World Series, when Minnesota beat St. Louis in seven games, attracted 35.3 million.</p>
        <p>The seven-game Kansas City-St. Louis World Series in 1985 shared the state of Missouri and also attracted 34.5 million viewers. But the next year, the Mets-Boston series averaged 36.4 million.</p>
        <p>Numerous factors affect why viewers watch the World Series: home team passions, the competitiveness of the games, the length of the Series, the buildup of compelling story lines, unforgettable performances and unexpected heroes.</p>
        <p>''I have to believe that a matchup of two teams that keep coming at you, with fans beating ThunderStix and rally monkeys jumping at you and ships in the bay should be as exciting as Bonnie Hunt doing her morning show,'' Ed Goren, the president of Fox Sports, said Wednesday during a conference call, referring to the ABC sitcom ''Life with Bonnie,'' which will be shown opposite Tuesday's Game 3.</p>
        <p>Still, it helps if the teams come from different states. The Yankees-Mets series, for example, was sandwiched between the scintillating Arizona-Yankees matchup last year and a sweep by the Yankees of Atlanta in 1999.</p>
        <p>The Arizona-Yankees series attracted 24.5 million average viewers, and the Yankees-Braves series drew 23.7 million. In between, only 18.1 million watched the Subway Series.</p>
        <p>''Is this a test for baseball, an all-California World Series?'' Goren said. ''Well, I'll tell you, an all-California World Series will outrate the most recent New York-L.A. N.B.A. finals. So who's being tested?''</p>
        <p>The Nets-Lakers National Basketball Association finals last June averaged 15.6 million viewers. Had the Knicks and not the Nets represented the New York market, the viewership very likely would have been higher given the Knicks' longer history and predominance in the region. The N.B.A. finals drew an average 18.9 million viewers in 2001, 17.4 million in 2000 and 16 million in 1999.</p>
        <p>Goren is hoping that the surprise story of the Angels combined with the possibility of a show of power by the Giants' Barry Bonds will make the World Series attractive outside California.</p>
        <p>But it might be too much to expect a repeat of last year's drama, when the Diamondbacks defeated the Yankees. ''Last year, we had a seven-game Series where the games were won on the last pitch of the game,'' Goren said. ''You don't get that every time around.''</p>
        <p>The only Super Bowls with teams from the same state have not performed as well as others featuring clubs from two markets. When San Francisco beat San Diego, 49-26, in 1995, there were 83.4 million viewers. But the year before, Dallas's 30-13 victory over Buffalo attracted 90 million, and the year after, when Dallas beat Pittsburgh, 27-17, there were 94 million.</p>
        <p>The other one-state matchup, in 1991, was the Giants' 20-19 victory over Buffalo. The game attracted 79.5 million, more than the 73.8 million for San Francisco's 55-10 trouncing of Denver the previous year, but fewer than any Super Bowl since and fewer than any going back to 1984.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
