<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beneath the Speeding Cyclone, a Look Back in Time</title>
    <meta content="29coney" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/29/nyregion/29coney.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1850724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CONEY ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DD1430F93AA15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beneath the Speeding Cyclone, a Look Back in Time</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Beneath the Speeding Cyclone, a Look Back in Time</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Headless bodies paraded down Surf Avenue in Coney Island all afternoon Saturday, past the half-closed gate of the little shack under the Cyclone where Charles Denson was hanging banners and photos on the white walls.</p>
        <p>Every once in a while, a body bent over and a head poked under the gate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new exhibition space for the Coney Island History Project is literally built into the base of Brooklyn’s most famous roller coaster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Headless bodies paraded down Surf Avenue in Coney Island all afternoon Saturday, past the half-closed gate of the little shack under the Cyclone where Charles Denson was hanging banners and photos on the white walls.</p>
        <p>Every once in a while, a body bent over and a head poked under the gate.</p>
        <p>''What is it?'' the head would say, peering sideways around the room and taking in the ancient amusement horse and the memory booth and the glass display case.</p>
        <p>It is a window into Coney Island's incredible history, Mr. Denson would say.</p>
        <p>It is, in fact, a lot of things.</p>
        <p>It is a former souvenir stand and a former hot dog stand and a former ice cream stand, a structure literally built into the base of the Cyclone, with support pillars that shake when the roller coaster passes overhead.</p>
        <p>It is the new exhibition space for the Coney Island History Project, which Mr. Denson, the group's executive director, was readying for the grand opening on Thursday. It is the permanent home, said Mr. Denson, who like many Coney Islanders is fluent in hyperbole, of the two most important Coney Island artifacts known to exist.</p>
        <p>But though the space has been turned into an exhibit hall in part because its current landlord cannot find anyone else to rent it, it is not, Mr. Denson stressed, a cultural mausoleum or any other sort of grim harbinger for the place that has meant cheap seaside thrills for generations of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''It's not about nostalgia and longing for the past,'' Mr. Denson said of the project. ''It's about Coney Island's future, and what endures. It's reminding people of what Coney Island has meant to New York over the years.''</p>
        <p>Yet even Mr. Denson says that Coney Island is at a crossroads.</p>
        <p>The crowds lining up outside the shack to get on the Cyclone all sunny, sweltering Saturday and through Memorial Day weekend augured a strong start to the season. But for some stalwarts of the midway, this year may be the last.</p>
        <p>Astroland, venerable preserve of bawling barkers and raucous rides crowned by the 270-foot Astro Tower, is scheduled to close in September, after the property beneath it was sold last year to a developer who has bought up much of the amusement area and shut several attractions.</p>
        <p>The developer, Joseph Sitt, has a $2 billion plan to remake the neighborhood, and though he says he wants to keep the fun in Coney Island, his plan to finance his vision with luxury condos makes some Coney Islanders very nervous.</p>
        <p>The Cyclone and the shack beneath it, both leased by the city to Astroland, are city landmarks and cannot be torn down, but much is up for grabs.</p>
        <p>''This year is so important to Coney Island because there's this misconception that it's all closing down,'' Mr. Denson said. In fact, he said, ''Coney Island could go either way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Denson, 53, who grew up in Coney Island and turned his obsession with its crazy, grand, seedy history into an acclaimed book, ''Coney Island Lost and Found,'' led a whirlwind tour of the exhibit space.</p>
        <p>Against one wall stood a battered sign made from two planks nailed together. It once hung outside the first structure erected by Europeans on Coney Island -- a tollhouse, fittingly enough, through which carriages passed in 1824 on their way to the island's unspoiled beaches.</p>
        <p>''Rates of toll for coach, coachee, phaeton, chariot, barouche drawn by horses, 9 cents,'' the sign reads.</p>
        <p>''It's a miracle that this thing survived,'' Mr. Denson said.</p>
        <p>In a near corner stood a sleek, fierce-eyed onyx steed with rollers beneath its hooves, an original horse from the Steeplechase coaster ride, built in 1897. Mr. Denson explained how until the 1950s, dismounting riders would be zapped by a midget with an electric paddle, then harassed by clowns.</p>
        <p>''They finally had to stop it after some guy hit a clown,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A human head poked under the gate. It belonged to Gabriella Bekeffi, whose eyes widened when she saw the horse.</p>
        <p>''Can I touch it?'' she asked.</p>
        <p>''You want to sit on it?'' Mr. Denson offered. ''Just be careful getting off.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bekeffi, 34, an event planner, said she had read about the Steeplechase and Luna Park and all the other bygone marvels. She had come to Coney Island to ride the Cyclone but also to document.</p>
        <p>''What I want to do,'' she said, ''is go around and take photos before everything gets lost forever.''</p>
        <p>In the exhibit's memory booth, Mr. Denson said, visitors will be able to record their Coney Island stories for an oral history archive started three years ago by Mr. Denson and Astroland's owner, Carol Hill Albert.</p>
        <p>They have collected more than 100 tales, some of which can be heard at coneyislandhistory.org.</p>
        <p>''We're not just looking for old-timers,'' Mr. Denson said. ''We have 12-year-olds talking about the good old days when they were 8.''</p>
        <p>Another head poked in. It was Amy Datz, 54. She offered an oral history of her own.</p>
        <p>''I was born in July,'' she said, ''and my father never had a birthday party for me. They always took me here.'' Every time, she would ride the Steeplechase. ''It was terrifying,'' she said. ''You looked down and there was nothing but track beneath you.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Datz lives in Florida now, but she came up to Coney Island, she said, because she had heard the place was closing. Not so, Mr. Denson said.</p>
        <p>After she rode the Cyclone she came back in with her 15-year-old son, Sam.</p>
        <p>''Can my son take my picture with the horse?'' she asked Mr. Denson. Sure, he said.</p>
        <p>Mother posed. Son clicked with all the uninterest a 15-year-old can muster. Sam, he was asked, what do you think of the horse?</p>
        <p>''I think it's pretty old,'' he said.</p>
        <p>CONEY ISLAND JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
