<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="109546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSS, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WROBEL, ARTHUR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PSEUDO-SCIENCE AND SOCIETY IN 19TH CENTURY AMERICA (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4D7143FF936A25752C0A96E948260" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Gross</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GROSS, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  PSEUDO-SCIENCE AND SOCIETY IN 19TH-CENTURY AMERICA. Edited by Arthur Wrobel. 245 pages. The University Press of Kentucky. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  PSEUDO-SCIENCE AND SOCIETY IN 19TH-CENTURY AMERICA. Edited by Arthur Wrobel. 245 pages. The University Press of Kentucky. $24.</p>
        <p>PSEUDO-SCIENCE AND SOCIETY IN 19TH-CENTURY AMERICA. Edited by Arthur Wrobel. 245 pages. The University Press of Kentucky. $24.</p>
        <p>THE 19th century was the golden age of many things, and pseudo-science was one of them. Nowhere was this more obviously the case than in America. If he shopped around, a 19th-century American could consult a psychographer or a hydropath or a magnetizer (in 1843, there were supposed to be more than 200 magnetizers - practitioners of mesmerism -in Boston alone). As soon as he had taken off his water girdle, he was free to put on his Heidelberg Electric Belt, and perhaps smoke an electric cigarette. He could read pamphlets explaining why husbands and wives ought to have sex once every two years, on a sunny day in August or September, between 11 A.M. and noon.</p>
        <p>These are only a few of the topics touched on in ''Pseudo-Science and Society in 19th-Century America,'' a new collection of essays edited by Arthur Wrobel, a professor of American literature at the University of Kentucky. Mr. Wrobel and his fellow contributors trace the impact of most of the major pseudo-sciences of the period, and some of the minor ones; they look at them in the light of other 19th-century cultural developments, and try to set them in a specifically American context.</p>
        <p>Only one of the essays deals with an individual pseudo-scientist - Taylor Stoehr's absorbing account of Robert H. Collyer, a lecturer of the 1830's and 40's whose specialties included phrenology, mesmerism and painless dentistry (fairly painless, thanks to a combination of mesmerism, alcohol and opium). In due course, Collyer concocted a hybrid science of his own called phrenomagnetism, which enabled him to detect a whole host of ''organs'' in the brain that orthodox phrenology had somehow missed - organs of Sarcasm, Love of Pets, Desire for Seeing Ancient Places and other specialized propensities. His final inspiration, which plainly owed something to the advent of photography, was psychography, a system of transferring mental images by bouncing them off a bowl of molasses.</p>
        <p>Collyer was the kind of charlatan who fascinated Poe, who had met him, and who succeeded in hoaxing him (to his obvious satisfaction) with ''The Facts in the Case of M. Valdemar,'' a bogus account of suspended animation. He had a picturesque career, and Mr. Stoehr tells his story well.</p>
        <p>One's only doubt about according him so much prominence is that he doesn't seem to have been an altogether representative figure. Or rather, he was representative of the lower levels of pseudo-science - and there were other, more respectable levels.</p>
        <p>Hydropathy, for example, probably did most of those who were subjected to its watery ministrations a certain amount of good; and though it could have its hazards, they were mild in comparison with some of the treatments doled out by orthodox medicine at the time. The water-cure establishments that began springing up in the 1840's were not unlike modern health farms, and the eventual fate of hydropathy, as Marshall Scott Legan observes in his essay on it, was not so much its complete disappearance as ''its sublimation into the general hygienic cult.''</p>
        <p>Bogus sciences could have their worthy social aspects, too. An essay on Andrew Jackson Davis, who tried to provide a philosophical basis for spiritualism, is a reminder of how closely 19th-century spiritualism, in its less sensational aspects, was linked with reform movements and the urge to improve the quality of life here on earth. And in its later manifestations, phrenology, as Mr. Wrobel shows, came to be treated as a form of political science, offering guidance about how to preserve sound democratic values.</p>
        <p>Other essays are devoted to such varied subjects as the vagaries of ''electric medicine,'' the application of phrenology to 19th-century American sculpture, and Washington Irving's reliance on his homeopathic physician (whom he and his family consulted no fewer than 598 times in the last seven years of his life). Pseudo-scientific ideas about sex provide a predictably rich crop of absurdity; in analyzing them, Harold Aspiz concentrates on the widely promoted theory that vigorous acts of conception produced vigorous children, and that eugenic improvements could be brought about by couples bottling up their passions for long periods in order to release them ''in a volcanic baby-begetting session.''</p>
        <p>Pseudo-science was a tribute to the ever-growing prestige of genuine science in the 19th century, to a new sense that anything might be possible. It was a response, in an age of bewildering complexity, to the need for big all-embracing systems. At a time when traditional religious beliefs were being eroded, it was an attempt to stay ''in tune with the infinite'' and heal the split between body and soul.</p>
        <p>The conditions that encouraged its growth were not, of course, uniquely American. All the major pseudo-sciences apart from spiritualism were originally imported from Europe, and most of the figures discussed by Mr. Wrobel and his contributors had their European equivalents. Robert H. Collyer may sound like a characteristic American figure of his time, but he was in fact an Englishman, who returned to England in the mid-1850's.</p>
        <p>Yet there are also distinctively American aspects to the story. On the whole, pseudo-science went further in America, and thought bigger. It chimed in with American utopianism, inherited the traditions of American revivalism, appealed to the American hankering for instant solutions. One member of Mr. Wrobel's team, Robert C. Fuller, in a thoughtful essay on ''Mesmerism and the Birth of Psychology,'' keeps the differences between American and European developments steadily in view; but in general it is a subject that would repay being explored at much greater length.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
