<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="20BENE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/20/nyregion/20BENE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1482475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6DA153AF933A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="2501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Benefits</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henry Street Settlement  WEDNESDAY -- A dinner-dance at the Copacabana, 560 West 34th Street, will raise money for the social service programs of the Henry Street Settlement. Drinks at 7 will be followed by dinner at 8 and dancing to the music of D.J. Tom Finn. Tickets, $650, from (212)868-4043.</p>
        <p>Homeless Women  WEDNESDAY -- Peter Jennings will talk with clients of Women In Need, which provides transitional and permanent housing to homeless women and their children, among other social services, at a dinner at the Plaza. The evening begins at 6:30 with cocktails, with dinner at 7:30 and the dialogue at about 9. Tickets, $500, from (212)838-6033.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Henry Street Settlement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Henry Street Settlement  WEDNESDAY -- A dinner-dance at the Copacabana, 560 West 34th Street, will raise money for the social service programs of the Henry Street Settlement. Drinks at 7 will be followed by dinner at 8 and dancing to the music of D.J. Tom Finn. Tickets, $650, from (212)868-4043.</p>
        <p>Homeless Women  WEDNESDAY -- Peter Jennings will talk with clients of Women In Need, which provides transitional and permanent housing to homeless women and their children, among other social services, at a dinner at the Plaza. The evening begins at 6:30 with cocktails, with dinner at 7:30 and the dialogue at about 9. Tickets, $500, from (212)838-6033.</p>
        <p>'Gypsy' for Hospital  WEDNESDAY -- An evening of dinner and a performance of ''Gypsy'' at the Shubert Theater, 225 West 44th Street, will raise money to expand emergency services at Lenox Hill Hospital. The evening begins at 5:15 with drinks at the Harvard Club, with dinner at 6. The show begins at 8. Tickets, $325, or $125 for dinner only or $200 for the show alone, from (212)434-6858.</p>
        <p>English Ball  WEDNESDAY -- A black-tie dinner dance at the Pierre will raise money for the St. George's Society, which aids needy British and Commonwealth citizens who live in the New York area. Drinks at 6:30 will be followed by dinner at 7:30 and music. Tickets, $250, from (212)924-1434.</p>
        <p>Cerebral Palsy Aid  WEDNESDAY -- William H. Macy will be the host at a dinner at the New York Marriott Marquis to raise money for United Cerebral Palsy and its social service and advocacy programs. Drinks at 6:30 will be followed by dinner at 8, with entertainment by Lillias White. Tickets, $750, from (212)683-6700, ext. 205.</p>
        <p>Groceries for the Poor  THURSDAY -- Michael Romano, the chef and restaurateur, will speak at a party at House of the Redeemer, 7 East 95th Street, to aid the Yorkville Common Pantry, which gives groceries to poor residents of East Harlem. Wines and food tastings will be served at 7, and an auction of trips, restaurant dinners, golf outings, Yankees tickets and other items at 8:45. Tickets, $200, or $125 for those 30 and under, from (212)410-2264, ext. 114.</p>
        <p>Harlem Children's Zone  THURSDAY -- A dinner at the Regent Wall Street will raise money for Harlem Children's Zone, which offers educational and community programs to poor children and families in Central Harlem. Drinks at 6 will be followed by dinner at 7. Tickets, $600, from (212)245-6570, ext. 22.</p>
        <p>Lower East Side Education</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- The GO Project, a program of the Grace Church School that aids academically struggling students on the Lower East Side, will benefit from a reception and concert. The evening begins at at 6:30 with a wine and cheese reception at the school, 86 Fourth Avenue (Tenth Street). A performance by Los Ciegos del Barrio will follow at 8 at Grace Church, at 802 Broadway (Tenth Street). Tickets, $125 for reception and concert, or $50 for concert only, from (212)533-9844.</p>
        <p>Watch Your Step  THURSDAY -- A costume ball in the theme of Dante's ''Divine Comedy'' will raise money to buy international fiction for the New York Public Library. The party, by young supporters of the library, begins at 9 with drinks, hors d'oeuvres and dancing. Tickets, $150, from (212)930-0730, or $200 at the door.</p>
        <p>Party for Research  FRIDAY -- A cocktail party at St. Maggie's Cafe, 120 Wall Street (South Street), will raise money for the clinical research program at the Weill Medical College of Cornell University supported by the Cancer Research and Treatment Fund. The event, by young supporters of the fund, begins at 6:30 with drinks and hors d'oeuvres, and ends at 8:30. Tickets, $50, from (212)288-6604.</p>
        <p>Free Summer Concerts</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- A performance of ''Carmilla'' at La Mama E.T.C., 66 East Fourth Street (Second Avenue), and a dinner at Frutti di Mare, 84 East Fourth Street (Second Avenue), will raise money for the Washington Square Music Festival, which will offer four free classical and classic jazz concerts this summer. The evening begins at the theater at 7:30, with the dinner about 9. Tickets, $100, or $50 for the theater only, from (212)677-0388.</p>
        <p>Dinner at and by Daniel  NEXT SUNDAY -- Meals for the homebound elderly in New York City provided by Citymeals on Wheels will be supported by a five-course dinner at Daniel, 60 East 65th Street, prepared by Daniel Boulud. The evening begins at 6 with drinks, with dinner at 6:45. Tickets, $1,000, from (212)687-1290.</p>
        <p>In the Kitchen  NEXT SUNDAY -- A serve-yourself-in-the-kitchen dinner at the Four Seasons Restaurant will raise money for the Irvington Institute for Immunological Research. The evening begins at 7 with drinks, with the dinner line at 8 and dancing to the music of D.J. Tom Finn. Tickets, $1,000, from (212)576-1005.</p>
        <p>Water Wonders  APRIL 28 -- Rowdy Gaines, the United States synchronized swimming team and students of Asphalt Green's sporting programs will perform at an aquashow at Asphalt Green, 1750 York Avenue (91st Street) to support the organization's free swimming lessons for New York public school students. The evening begins in the aquacenter with drinks at 6 and the show at 7:30. Dinner and dancing at 8 will take place at the center's gymnasium. Tickets, $600, or $175 for drinks and the show only, from (212)369-8890, ext. 232.</p>
        <p>For Cancer Research  APRIL 28 -- Libby Pataki and Marvin Hamlisch will be among those honored at a black-tie dinner at the Pierre to raise money for the American Cancer Society and its education, research and advocacy programs. Drinks at 7 will be followed by dinner, dancing and a performance by J. Mark McVey at 8. Tickets, $500, from (212)237-3892.</p>
        <p>Precious Leftovers  APRIL 29 -- Harrison Ford will be among those honored at a black-tie dinner at the Pierre to raise money for City Harvest, which delivers leftover prepared food from events, hotels and restaurants to food pantries, shelters and other community food programs. Drinks at 6:45 will be followed by dinner at 7:45 and dancing. Tickets, $500, from (212)874-5457.</p>
        <p>Health With Latin Beat  APRIL 29 -- A Latin-themed party at the Angel Orensanz Center for the Arts, 172 Norfolk Street (East Houston), will raise money for the Continuum Center for Health and Healing, a clinic of Beth Israel Medical Center that combines Western and alternative medicines and therapies. The evening begins at 7 with drinks, Latin fare, free salsa, merengue, tango, mambo and samba lessons, and a performance by Ballet Hispanico. Tickets, $300, from (212)243-7300.</p>
        <p>Bellevue and Children  APRIL 29 -- Tom Brokaw will be honored at a tasting dinner at Essex House to aid Children of Bellevue, which supports pediatric programs at Bellevue Hospital. The evening begins at 7:30 with the wine and food samplings, with an auction of trips, dinners and other items at 8:45. Tickets, $150, from (212)562-4130.</p>
        <p>A New 'Cinderella'  APRIL 29 -- A premiere of ''Cinderella'' by choreographer Jean-Christophe Maillot and Les Ballets de Monte-Carlo, at the Brooklyn Academy of Music's Gilman Opera House, will raise money for BAM. The black-tie evening begins at 6 with drinks in a tent adjacent to BAM, with the performance at 7. A dinner will follow the ballet, at about 9, back in the tent, with an auction during the dinner to raise money for Les Ballets de Monte-Carlo. Tickets, $600, or $200 for the cocktail reception and ballet only, from (718)636-4182, ext. 1.</p>
        <p>Ballet Opening Night  MAY 5 -- Opening night of American Ballet Theater, with performances of ''Within You, Without You: A Tribute to George Harrison'' and excerpts from other works, at the Metropolitan Opera House, will raise money for the ballet and its educational programs. The black-tie evening begins at 6:30 with the ballet, with dinner at about 8:30 in the Tent at Lincoln Center, in Damrosch Park. Tickets, $1,000, from (212)873-4652.</p>
        <p>E-mail society@nytimes.com  Information: (212) 556-1141</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
