<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He's Not Just a Bunny. He's My Brother.</title>
    <meta content="20TVKID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="55" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1482223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macneille, Suzanne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Max &amp; Ruby (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DF133BF933A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He's Not Just a Bunny. He's My Brother.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Suzanne MacNeille</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macneille, Suzanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Max and Ruby are television bunnies aimed at pre-school set who are mutually affectionate but forever derailing one another's plans; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the world of preschool entertainment, bunnies don't limit their appearances to the Easter holidays. Take the Nickelodeon series ''Max &amp; Ruby'' (weekdays at 9 a.m. ), which stars two animated rabbit siblings: Max, a headstrong 3-year-old with a prodigious collection of wind-up toys, and Ruby, his bossy yet tolerant 7-year-old sister. Despite their mutual affection, the two are constantly derailing each other's best-laid plans. If Ruby wants to have a quiet telephone conversation with her best friend, Max is determined to interrupt it with his ''ear-splitter space cadet''; if Ruby puts the robot away, out comes Max's equally noisy mechanical parrot.</p>
        <p>So realistic is the sibling relationship between the two characters that a parent might wonder: Why are they bunnies? Why not just make them children?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the world of preschool entertainment, bunnies don't limit their appearances to the Easter holidays. Take the Nickelodeon series ''Max &amp; Ruby'' (weekdays at 9 a.m. ), which stars two animated rabbit siblings: Max, a headstrong 3-year-old with a prodigious collection of wind-up toys, and Ruby, his bossy yet tolerant 7-year-old sister. Despite their mutual affection, the two are constantly derailing each other's best-laid plans. If Ruby wants to have a quiet telephone conversation with her best friend, Max is determined to interrupt it with his ''ear-splitter space cadet''; if Ruby puts the robot away, out comes Max's equally noisy mechanical parrot.</p>
        <p>So realistic is the sibling relationship between the two characters that a parent might wonder: Why are they bunnies? Why not just make them children?</p>
        <p>''Child figures would make the stories dead serious,'' explained Rosemary Wells, the author and illustrator of the Max and Ruby book series on which the half-hour show is based. ''Animals are much funnier.'' Besides, she said in a recent telephone interview, ''I love rabbits, and I don't draw children well.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wells, who worked closely with the producers, scriptwriters and animators on the episodes -- each of which is divided into three seven-and-a-half-minute stories -- noted that ''television is much more complicated than writing a book. You can imply more in a book than on television.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Wells hopes that the show conveys ''the incredible funniness of children'' without being ''syrupy sweet.'' ''I don't like to make the world sweet and cute,'' she said, preferring instead to add a good strong shake of ''salt and pepper, the real flavor of life.''</p>
        <p>Diana Manson, an executive producer of the show, describes Max and Ruby as ''real kids in real situations.''</p>
        <p>Except that they aren't real kids, of course, they are bunnies, bunnies with faces reminiscent of West Highland white terriers (another one of Ms. Wells's favorite animals) and with the lyrical voices of Samantha Morton, who speaks for Ruby, and Billy Rosenberg, who provides the voice of Max.</p>
        <p>Max's sparse vocabulary was one of several challenges, said Ms. Manson, noting that limited dialogue may work in a preschool book but is much harder to carry off on television. In the development phase of ''Max &amp; Ruby,'' Ms. Manson said, she wondered if they should create an internal voice for Max, or perhaps a narrator.</p>
        <p>The problem resulted in ''a design breakthrough,'' said Ms. Manson. The art team, with Ms. Wells's help, developed a visual dictionary of eye expressions for Max. Each expression -- anticipation, devilish intent, joy and dozens of others -- spoke volumes, allowing Max to remain true to his literary persona: nearly speechless.</p>
        <p>The absence of parents was another hurdle, said Ms. Manson. ''There were many questions caught up in that particular problem,'' she said. ''How will Max and Ruby be safe? Should we give them parents?'' In the presence of grown-ups, Ms. Wells said, ''kids have a different type of conversation.'' On the other hand, when they're among themselves, she continued, ''there's no one to impress, no one to please.'' Parents were out of the question.</p>
        <p>Ultimately that challenge led to the creation of East Bunnyhop, an ideal toy village with picket fences, old-fashioned buses and pristine meadows stretching out beyond Max and Ruby's dollhouse-like home -- a place that bestows an overwhelming feeling of safety and familiarity. That environment, along with the stories and the characters themselves, forms what Ms. Wells calls ''a netherworld of childhood before television, a place suspended in time and innocence.''</p>
        <p>''And if there is anything I wish to convey,'' she said, ''it is the innocence of childhood.''</p>
        <p>Suzanne MacNeille</p>
        <p>Connections  www.nickjr.com and www.rosemarywells.com offer several ''Max &amp; Ruby''activities, including interactive games, paper-doll print-outs and printable ''bunny money.''</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
