<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing Vegetables? Think Multidimensional</title>
    <meta content="20WCCUTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1482397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reich, Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7DE143AF933A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="884" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing Vegetables? Think Multidimensional</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE REICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reich, Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lee Reich Cuttings column describes how to create multidimensional vegetable garden; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE traditional vegetable garden is a two-dimensional affair, with rows of single vegetables widely separated by bare ground, the better to enable tilling and tending. That layout works fine when backyard gardens measure in quarter-acres and not in square feet. Today's vegetable gardens tend to be small, challenging gardeners to create higher yields per valuable square foot.</p>
        <p>The trick is to make your garden multidimensional, exploiting every element of space and time.</p>
        <p>The first step is to plant in beds, not rows. The rectangular beds of my vegetable garden are 36 inches wide, allowing easy reach from paths just wide enough (18 inches) to walk in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE traditional vegetable garden is a two-dimensional affair, with rows of single vegetables widely separated by bare ground, the better to enable tilling and tending. That layout works fine when backyard gardens measure in quarter-acres and not in square feet. Today's vegetable gardens tend to be small, challenging gardeners to create higher yields per valuable square foot.</p>
        <p>The trick is to make your garden multidimensional, exploiting every element of space and time.</p>
        <p>The first step is to plant in beds, not rows. The rectangular beds of my vegetable garden are 36 inches wide, allowing easy reach from paths just wide enough (18 inches) to walk in.</p>
        <p>Neighboring plants are spaced closely enough in the beds so that, when mature, their leaves touch. That means four of rows of lettuce, six inches apart in all directions, or three rows of cabbage, or five rows of carrots or onions.</p>
        <p>With some vegetables, the closer you plant, the more you get, but each vegetable is smaller than usual. By playing around with the spacing of the vegetables, you can strike a balance. I plant onions 4 inches apart in a bed that is 36 inches wide and 10 feet long, and you will reap more than 50 pounds of onions with diameters of 3 to 4 inches.</p>
        <p>''Grow up,'' I tell some of my vegetables, knowing I will be pleased by the results. A trellis or stake can increase the yield of peas, cucumbers, melons, tomatoes and other vining plants, because plants that grow up can also grow closer together. Staked vegetables are also out of the dirt and away from nibbling slugs and other ground-dwelling creatures.</p>
        <p>Some trailing plants reach out for support while others are more ambivalent. Twining plants (like pole beans) and plants with tendrils (peas and cucumbers) flounder about until they find support to pull themselves up. Not so with tomato vines. With long stems but no means of clinging, tomato plants are as happy to crawl over the ground as to climb a stake, so they need to be nudged up.</p>
        <p>Next I incorporate into my garden the fourth dimension: time. By thinking ahead to harvest schedules, I can use one bed to grow two or more crops.</p>
        <p>A bed of broccoli and lettuce, for example, can include two lettuce plants spaced eight inches apart, living among broccoli plants spaced two feet apart. The lettuce is harvested and out of the way by the time the broccoli finally fills the bed.</p>
        <p>Interplanting, as it is known, can involve more than two different vegetables. Run a long row of spring radishes up the center of that same bed of broccoli and lettuce (or just squeeze it in, with short rows here and there); the radishes can be harvested and out of the way before the lettuces fill, and the lettuces are out of the way before the broccolis fill in.</p>
        <p>Because so few vegetables are in the ground from the very beginning to the very end of the growing season, different ones can be grown in succession in the same bed. For instance, slip tomato plants into the ground after an early crop of spinach, which thrives, unlike tomatoes, in cool weather. Bush beans that peter out by midsummer can be followed by cabbage. I have successfully followed early beets with late bush beans (and vice versa). I have also followed early lettuce with bush beans -- followed by late radishes. Peas can precede corn if it is a short-season variety.</p>
        <p>Another way to exploit time is to start the succession out of the garden. While seeds are being sprouted in moist paper towels, the beds can belong to another crop. Or cheat time and increase yield by transplanting vegetables sown in containers. From midsummer on, lettuces can be moved to the garden as space is freed up (in a bed where the bush beans or corn plants have been cleared away, for example, or onions harvested). Cabbage, broccoli, endive and Chinese cabbage take longer than lettuce to mature, but transplants can similarly be slipped into the garden whenever space is free.</p>
        <p>Yet another way to cultivate the dimension of time is by extending the limits of the growing season. One way to do this is to hasten the warming of the soil in spring. Dry soil warms up faster than wet soil, making raised beds, with their good drainage and increased exposure, ready for planting early in spring.</p>
        <p>Mulch insulates the soil, so pull it back to let the warm air reach the beds.</p>
        <p>Finally, trap warmth at either end of the season. The traditional glass bell jar has been superseded by a variety of alternatives: plastic versions, water-filled tubes (Walls o' Water), fiberglass A-frames, floating row covers and plastic tunnels held aloft by metal or plastic hoops anchored in the soil.</p>
        <p>Trying to fill every niche of space and time in a vegetable garden is as challenging as doing a multidimensional jigsaw puzzle. Don't get overwrought trying to integrate every puzzle piece. When in doubt, just go ahead and plant.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
