<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EVERYWHERE, 'IN HONOR OF THE 300TH'</title>
    <meta content="20EVENTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/20/travel/20events.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1482285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kishkovsky, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">St Petersburg (Russia)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3DF1F3BF933A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EVERYWHERE, 'IN HONOR OF THE 300TH'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Everywhere, 'In Honor of the 300th'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kishkovsky, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sophia Kishkovsky travel article on events within and outside St Petersburg, Russia, which are being dedicated to city's 300th birthday; list; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE race to prepare St. Petersburg for its 300th-birthday bash can compare only to Peter the Great's rush to build an exquisite imperial capital of palaces and canals atop a forbidding swamp. This year it seems that all efforts are being devoted to celebrating the anniversary of his majestic and maddening creation. Cultural bastions like the Hermitage, with its unparalleled collection of some three million works of art, and the Mariinsky Theater, home to the Mariinsky (Kirov) Opera, Ballet and Orchestra, are going all out to mark the celebration.</p>
        <p>But just about any event in the city this year, from the sublime to the ridiculous, has ''in honor of the 300th'' slapped on it, often to comic, time-warped effect. The European billiards championship honoring the anniversary will be held at a very Soviet place: the House of Culture of the First Five-Year Plan. For those wishing to escape culture, there are beer festivals and bodybuilding and hairdressing competitions. Animal lovers can attend a huge dog show. For those seeking an intellectual lift, there is a symposium of 25 Nobel laureates. Those struggling to keep their sanity amid the rush can turn to the conference of Russian psychologists that will convene in the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No effort is being spared to prepare St. Petersburg for its 300th birthday, with events ranging from the sublime to the ridiculous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE race to prepare St. Petersburg for its 300th-birthday bash can compare only to Peter the Great's rush to build an exquisite imperial capital of palaces and canals atop a forbidding swamp. This year it seems that all efforts are being devoted to celebrating the anniversary of his majestic and maddening creation. Cultural bastions like the Hermitage, with its unparalleled collection of some three million works of art, and the Mariinsky Theater, home to the Mariinsky (Kirov) Opera, Ballet and Orchestra, are going all out to mark the celebration.</p>
        <p>But just about any event in the city this year, from the sublime to the ridiculous, has ''in honor of the 300th'' slapped on it, often to comic, time-warped effect. The European billiards championship honoring the anniversary will be held at a very Soviet place: the House of Culture of the First Five-Year Plan. For those wishing to escape culture, there are beer festivals and bodybuilding and hairdressing competitions. Animal lovers can attend a huge dog show. For those seeking an intellectual lift, there is a symposium of 25 Nobel laureates. Those struggling to keep their sanity amid the rush can turn to the conference of Russian psychologists that will convene in the city.</p>
        <p>The best way to stay sane, though, is to avoid the city entirely during the jubilee week of May 23 through June 1, the highlight of the jubilee year (the city's birthday is May 27), being celebrated all through 2003. As it is, the city's main airport, Pulkovo Airport, will be closed to the public for three days to receive foreign leaders arriving for a summit May 31 with President Vladimir V. Putin, who is from St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>The week will be jam-packed with athletic events, concerts and grand openings of everything from the recently renovated Marble Palace to the painstakingly recreated Amber Room, marching military cadets, wreath-laying ceremonies, religious services and water shows on the Neva River. Since access to the week's events will be near impossible, anyone planning a visit should time it to enjoy the pleasures of St. Petersburg before and after the jubilee week. Although events will be held throughout the year, the light and the weather are best during the celebrated white nights from early June to mid-July.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the high points of the festivities. But since confusion reigns at many of the events, with schedules still in flux, be sure to check dates, times and locations. Information: www.spb300.ru.</p>
        <p>Some things are certain, though. The annual Stars of the White Nights Festival, which has been shining brightly for 10 years, is especially brilliant this year, running May 5 to Aug. 5. The brainchild of Valery Gergiev, director of the Mariinsky Theater and principal guest conductor of the Metropolitan Opera, the festival opens with Andrei Konchalovsky's staging of ''War and Peace.'' Highlights include the Rotterdam Philharmonic, the Vienna Philharmonic, John Neumeier and the Hamburg Ballet, Britain's Royal Ballet and the New York City Ballet. A grand ball, open to those of the public with deep pockets, will be held June 28 at Konstantinovsky Palace in Strelna, built by Peter the Great outside the city and renovated in a frenzy for President Putin for $200 million; tickets are $1,500. Cultural tickets can be bought online or at the Mariinsky Box Office, 1 Teatralnaya Ploschad; (7-812) 326-4141 or 114-1211; www.mariinsky.ru. They can also be booked through the White Nights Foundation, 399 Park Avenue, 23rd floor, New York, N.Y. 10022; (212) 759-4979, fax (212) 371-7003; $30 to $200, at 32 rubles to $1.</p>
        <p>Students of the Vaganova Ballet Academy perform Delibes's ''Sylvia'' at the Hermitage Theater, one of the oldest theaters in Russia, a gem built at Catherine the Great's behest within the Hermitage Museum. May 7 and 9 at 8 p.m.; about $47. Tickets through Souzsporttheatre, (7-812) 279-0226 or telephone and fax (7-812) 272-9682.</p>
        <p>The State Russian Museum, housed in an expanding array of palaces, with the largest collection of Russian art in the world, has a number of exhibitions devoted to the 300th anniversary. The Marble Palace, until 1992 the Lenin Museum, will have its grand reopening on May 23; Ulitsa Millionnaya 5/1; (7-812) 312-9196. Open 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; to 5 p.m. Monday; closed Tuesdays; $7.50. The Stroganov Palace reopens May 18; Nevsky Prospekt 17; (7-812) 311-2360. Same admission and hours. Information: www.rusmuseum.ru.</p>
        <p>The stuff of legend, stolen by the Nazis then lost after World War II, the glowing, toffee-colored Amber Room has been lovingly recreated by master craftsmen for more than 20 years. Housed in the grand Catherine Palace in Tsarskoye Selo, the Romanovs' summer residence, in Pushkin, about 30 minutes from St. Petersburg, the room will open to the public soon after its unveiling on May 31; $10.95. Open daily, except Tuesdays and the last Monday of every month, 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. June to September; to 6 p.m. the rest of the year; (7-812) 465-5308; www.tzar.ru.</p>
        <p>Hermitage Museum exhibitions devoted to the 300th include a huge show on Peter the Great in the museum's main halls, May 27 to Aug. 31; the general public will have access from June 2, and will be able to enter from the Palace Square entrance, now restored. A retrospective of the works of the architect Giacomo Quarenghi will be on display May 27 to June 29. Open daily except Monday 10:30 a.m. to 6 p.m. Tickets cost $10, with extra fees for photos or video recording, at the box office; they may also be bought online at www.hermitagemuseum.org. In the United States, call (866) 701-5653 (tickets $16 for one day; $24 for two; prices include the photo/video fees).</p>
        <p>A ''Parade of Peoples'' exhibition at the Museum of Ethnography, opening May 15 and running through the end of the year, chronicles St. Petersburg's multiethnic history. The museum, by turns charmingly and frustratingly old-fashioned, has a striking marble hall built in Greek-Roman style as a pantheon to Czar Alexander III, with all the peoples of his empire depicted along the perimeter. Ulitsa Inzhenernaya 4/1; (7-812) 313-4228; www.ethnomuseum.ru. Open 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Closed Mondays and the last Friday of the month; $3.75.</p>
        <p>''Joseph Brodsky: Urania. Leningrad-Venice-New York,'' an exhibition of memorabilia and books of the Nobel Prize-winning poet who lived in Leningrad but never returned after his exile in 1972, is held through August at the Anna Akhmatova Museum. The museum is devoted to one of Russia's greatest poets. Naberezhnaya Reki Fontanki 34; (7-812) 272-2211 or 272-5895. Open 10:30 a.m. to 6:30 p.m.; closed Monday and the last Wednesday of the month; $1.90.</p>
        <p>The State Russian Museum is whipping up a veritable feast of free performances, kicked off at noon May 18 with a concert in the Letny Sad (Summer Garden) in the city center featuring the Leningrad Military District Orchestra. ''Concert Promenades'' with wind orchestras are scheduled for Saturdays throughout the summer in the Summer Garden. ''St. Petersburg in Waltzes'' on June 12 at 8 p.m. will focus on Glinka, Tchaikovsky and Strauss and include fireworks on the Summer Garden side of Mikhailovsky (Engineers') Castle. The castle opens May 27 after extensive restoration. Information: (9-812) 314-8617; www.rusmuseum.ru.</p>
        <p>Dmitri Kaminker's conceptual sculpture, ''Stone Oarsman,'' to be unveiled May 17, will be adjacent to a lake and a modern sculpture garden at the Artists' Village of Shuvalovo-Ozerki, near the edge of the city, which opens sometime in July. Mr. Kaminker and other artists live and work in the village and hold exhibitions on rafts in the lake. The sculptor's studio is at Ulitsa Novoorlovskaya 40; (7-812) 514-3770.</p>
        <p>The ''White Nights Swing'' jazz festival, July 3 to 6, with local ensembles at the Jazz Philharmonic Hall, is directed by David Goloschokin, who jammed with Duke Ellington. Tickets: $6.25. Free concert at the Mikhailovsky Garden on July 6. Zagorodny Prospekt 27; (7-812) 164-8565; fax (7-812) 164-9843 or 164-9915.</p>
        <p>The name of the ''Okna Otkroi!'' (''Open the Windows!'') rock festival on June 28 refers to Peter the Great's vision of the city as a window on Europe. Featuring some of Russia's hippest groups, it is to be held at the Kirov Stadium at Morskoi Prospekt 1 from noon until dusk; tickets, about $6.25, can be ordered at (7-812) 315-0516..</p>
        <p>The Music of the Fountains Festival will be held June 29 to July 20 at Peterhof, half an hour from the city by hydrofoil. Concerts at the Lower Park, with a view of the elaborate gilded fountains, are at noon or 2 p.m. and may be included in the $8 entrance fee to the park. Concerts in the Great Palace start at 7 p.m.; $9.40. Call (7-812) 427-9223 for concert dates, or ask a Russian speaker to call, since staff members do not speak English; www.peterhof.org.</p>
        <p>The Hermitage Museum Orchestra and guests such as the Accademia Bizantina from Italy are scheduled to perform at the Music of the Great Hermitage Festival in July. Concerts will be held at 7 p.m. on July 21 in the Italian Skylight Hall, July 24 at the great church and July 26 in the main stateroom of the Winter Palace, St. George's Hall. The program for ''Carnival in Northern Venice,'' with concerts on July 23 and 25, is still tentative, but scheduled for 10 p.m. in the Grand Courtyard by the Palace Square. Contact the Hermitage Music Academy for information and tickets; (7-812) 311-5059 or 110-9543; fax (7-812) 311-7602.</p>
        <p>International Baltic Regatta, July 15 to 23, is held in the Gulf of Finland, starting from the Central Yacht Club, where spectator boats will be available; Petrovskaya Kosa 9; (7-812) 235-5095, 235-7067 or 230-4234; www.rcom.ru/ruspol/regatta.htm.</p>
        <p>Sand Sculpture Festival, June 30 to July 4, a new tradition on the beach of the SS. Peter and Paul Fortress; this year the theme is ''And the Ship Sails On,'' referring to both the Fellini film and the city's seafaring history; (7-812) 232-6368, or telephone and fax (7-812) 232-6919 or 324-7502.</p>
        <p>The sixth international Early Music Festival takes place around the city from Sept. 14 to Oct. 5. Featuring European soloists and ensembles, Russian musicians, the only Baroque orchestra in Russia and an opera premiere by Catherine the Great's court composer, Giovanni Paisiello. Tickets, $35 to $100, can be bought online at www.earlymusic.ru or (7-812) 325-7052.</p>
        <p>Baltic House International Theater Festival will be playing host to the International Festival of the Union of Theaters of Europe, along with a European festival of modern dance, Oct. 4 to 30. Aleksandrovsky Park 4; (7-812) 232-0961; www.baltichouse.spb.ru.</p>
        <p>The Ninth International St. Petersburg Open will take place Oct. 20 to 26; for tickets and packages, call (7-812) 326-5544, fax (7-812) 326-5543.</p>
        <p>Culture overload? Hop on a Harley and let loose at the Sixth Annual International Biker Festival, Aug. 15 to 17, organized by St. Petersburg's Werewolf Biker Club and dedicated, of course, to the 300th; (7-812) 936-3366.</p>
        <p>SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY contributes to The Times from Moscow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SOPHIA KISHKOVSKY contributes to The Times from Moscow.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
