<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honecker's Move to Moscow Causes an Uproar in Germany</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="430369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HONECKER, ERICH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6153DF935A25750C0A967958260" item-length="369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honecker's Move to Moscow Causes an Uproar in Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, March 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Soviet Union said today that it had given advance notice to Germany before flying Erich Honecker, the former East German Communist leader, here for medical care necessary for "humanitarian considerations."</p>
        <p>The transfer of Mr. Honecker has caused an uproar in Germany, where justice officials are demanding his return because of pending charges relating to the deaths of East Germans who were shot by his govenment's police in the days of a divided Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Soviet Union said today that it had given advance notice to Germany before flying Erich Honecker, the former East German Communist leader, here for medical care necessary for "humanitarian considerations."</p>
        <p>The transfer of Mr. Honecker has caused an uproar in Germany, where justice officials are demanding his return because of pending charges relating to the deaths of East Germans who were shot by his govenment's police in the days of a divided Germany.</p>
        <p>Charges of Soviet meddling and German collusion are being made in the German press, because Mr. Honecker's flight occurred not long after German courts had declared that Soviet diplomatic immunity did not extend to the Soviet military hospital in Beelitz where Mr. Honecker was treated.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Foreign Minister, Aleksandr A. Bessmertnykh, denied today that the move was in any way improper, saying "we had talks with the Germans before the fact, as it occurred."  'Not Possible' to Block It</p>
        <p>The Soviet Foreign Ministry later said that Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany had been told several hours in advance of the flight on Wednesday of the 78-year-old Mr. Honecker. A Kohl spokesman said in Bonn that the German Government had been told of the transfer about 90 minutes before it happened, and that by then it was "not possible" to block it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Honecker was said by Soviet officials to be suffering severe cardiac problems that required his shift from the hospital in Germany to a better equipped hospital in the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Since the fall of the Berlin wall and the end of the East German Government, Soviet officials had rejected requests from German officials that Mr. Honecker be turned out of the Soviet hospital in Germany to face charges in the deaths of some of the 200 people who had been shot trying to escape to West Germany from 1983 to 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Honecker, who had manslaughter charges pending through an extensive period of illness in Germany, has no intention of ever leaving here, according to Friederich Wolff, the lawyer for Mr. Honecker who was quoted in the German press.</p>
        <p>According to the Cologne-Bonn Express, Mr. Wolff said: "He will probably spend the autumn of his life in the Soviet Union."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
