<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Northeast Governors to Ask Voluntary Packaging Rules</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="430376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANDFILL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COALITION OF NORTHEASTERN GOVERNORS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D7133DF935A25750C0A967958260" item-length="372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Northeast Governors to Ask Voluntary Packaging Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unable to forge a compromise between industrial and environmental interests on wasteful packaging, the Coalition of Northeast Governors is about to seek voluntary reduction.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists, having split with the coalition, are pursuing the legislative approach. Bills to impose bans on packaging that is not re-usable or made of recycled materials are pending or about to be introduced in 11 states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unable to forge a compromise between industrial and environmental interests on wasteful packaging, the Coalition of Northeast Governors is about to seek voluntary reduction.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists, having split with the coalition, are pursuing the legislative approach. Bills to impose bans on packaging that is not re-usable or made of recycled materials are pending or about to be introduced in 11 states.</p>
        <p>The announcement of the voluntary program was made yesterday by Gov. John R. McKernan Jr. of Maine. Officials of the coalition, which consists of the six New England states plus New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania, said the letter announcing the program had not yet been approved by all the governors.  Breakdown of Consensus</p>
        <p>The call for a purely voluntary program could represent the final breakdown of a two-year effort to mold a consensus of government, industry and environmental groups on reducing packaging, which accounts for about 50 percent of the volume of trash going to landfills.</p>
        <p>When the packaging study group, known as the Source Reduction Council, was established in 1989, it said that a final report would be issued before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>But little progress was made, as environmentalist insisted on developing model legislation with numerical targets, while some industry and state officials backed a less structured approach.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups bowed out last year, citing the lack of progress and procedural issues. Allen Hershkowitz, a former member of the council and a scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, said environmental groups would now focus on legislation. Failure Is Seen</p>
        <p>The voluntary program, he said, "means the governors have been unable to put forward a coherent regulatory program."</p>
        <p>In an effort to curb the growth of solid waste, which Mr. Hershkowitz said had been increasing 1.5 percent annually, environmental and consumer groups are backing legislation that would promote re-use and recycling of packaging. Bills have been introduced in nine states, including New York, and are scheduled to be introduced in three more, said Jeanne Wirka, an official of the Environmental Action Foundation, one backer of the legislation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
