<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Battle Over Rights Bills Emphasizes Sexual Bias</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="427746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEXUAL HARASSMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLYMER, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD163DF937A35750C0A967958260" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Battle Over Rights Bills Emphasizes Sexual Bias</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLYMER, ADAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With its heavy focus on women, this year's fight over civil rights legislation already has a tone different from last year's conflict or most previous confrontations.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration proposal released Friday night and the hearings held by two House committees earlier in the week concentrated on sexual harassment and other forms of discrimination against women in the workplace, not on the racial minority members whose access to voting, housing and public facilities have been the historic focus of civil rights legislation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With its heavy focus on women, this year's fight over civil rights legislation already has a tone different from last year's conflict or most previous confrontations.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration proposal released Friday night and the hearings held by two House committees earlier in the week concentrated on sexual harassment and other forms of discrimination against women in the workplace, not on the racial minority members whose access to voting, housing and public facilities have been the historic focus of civil rights legislation.</p>
        <p>In fact, the legislative issues are unchanged since last fall, when President Bush vetoed a Congressional effort to overturn several recent Supreme Court interpretations of the 1964 Civil Rights Act. The vetoed bill would have made it easier for victims of job discrimination -- women, racial and religious minority members and the handicapped -- to sue employers and collect.</p>
        <p>In his veto message, Mr. Bush said the bill would lead employers to use quotas for hiring and promotion. Proponents insisted that all they were trying to do was return to earlier Supreme Court standards, and they said those standards had not led to quotas.  Same Issues, but Wider Gap</p>
        <p>While the Bush Administration did not dwell on the quota issue on Friday, the issue is likely to be heard strongly again. Supporters of the House bill, mostly Democrats, will not only deny that it is a quota bill, but will argue that what matters about their bill is the fairness to workers it seeks to insure.</p>
        <p>But while the issues are the same, the gap between the two sides is a bit wider than it was last fall. For example, the House bill discards the limit of $150,000 in punitive damages for discrimination against women, religious minority members and the handicapped that was inserted to win Southern votes for the bill Mr. Bush vetoed.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration bill, on the other hand, sets an easier standard than it offered last fall on the kind of "business necessity" employers must demonstrate to justify the discriminatory effects of practices like written tests or height limits.</p>
        <p>The disputed provisions, and there are many, are hardly immutable. House advocates who oppose the $150,000 limit, for example, might change their minds if they saw hard evidence that restoring it would get them enough votes to override a veto. Action in the House First</p>
        <p>It is not at all clear when the legislative process will reach that kind of critical stage. There have been no serious discussions between the Administration and the Congressional majorities who favor broader legislation.</p>
        <p>The bill has not even been introduced yet in the Senate</p>
        <p>Floor action is sure to come first in the House, probably next month. House leaders are pressing the committees to move swiftly. The Judicary Committee and the Education and Labor Committee are scheduled to complete their hearings in the coming week. Each is considering a bill very much like the one vetoed last year.</p>
        <p>Neither committee is expected to change it much, but Representative William D. Ford, the Michigan Democrat who heads the Education and Labor Committee, is inclined to add provisions requring the Labor Department to establish two commissions to examine the "glass ceiling," or limits on how high women can rise in major corporations, and whether women get equal pay for equal work.</p>
        <p>But the overwhelming focus of the argument right now is about women. Mr. Ford's committee heard tales of how women encountered vulgar sexual harassment and how courts could only award them back pay and order them rehired. There were also accounts of women who won court orders to given them jobs and partnerships, but could not collect monetary damages.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's bill would allow up to $150,000 in damages in sexual and religious harassment cases, but none in the promotion cases. Nor would it allow the handicapped to sue for harassment. The House bill would allow compensatory damages and, in extreme cases, punitive damages in harassment and promotion cases. It would also cover the handicapped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brooks complained that present law allows racial minority members to sue for compensatory and punitive damages in all kinds of job discrimination cases, but denies that opportunity to women.</p>
        <p>The issue of quotas and "business necessity" standards has won far more attention. But the other major element of the bill, extending the right to collect damages in job discrimination cases to women, religious minority members and the handicapped, has caused considerable concern in the business community.</p>
        <p>Testifying on behalf of the National Association of Manufacturers on Thursday, Zachary D. Fasman, a Washington lawyer, insisted, "The path to equal employment does not run through the courthouse door."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
