<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unlikely Trio With Music at the Core</title>
    <meta content="10BRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/10/arts/10BRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1269599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFDB1231F933A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unlikely Trio With Music at the Core</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews dance program choreographed to classical composers by New York City Ballet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Fearful Symmetries,'' ''Robert Schumann's 'Davidsbündlertänze' '' and ''Brandenburg.'' No three ballets could be more dissimilar than this trio presented by New York City Ballet on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater. Yet music was the springboard for the choreography in each case.</p>
        <p>The opener was ''Fearful Symmetries,'' in which Peter Martins's textured, plotless design dynamically meets the exciting rhythmic pulse of John Adams's score of the same title. Choreographed in 1990, the ballet has lost none of its energy, and new dancers take to its phenomenal speed and pumped-up Neo-Classical style with explosive thrust.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Fearful Symmetries,'' ''Robert Schumann's 'Davidsbündlertänze' '' and ''Brandenburg.'' No three ballets could be more dissimilar than this trio presented by New York City Ballet on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater. Yet music was the springboard for the choreography in each case.</p>
        <p>The opener was ''Fearful Symmetries,'' in which Peter Martins's textured, plotless design dynamically meets the exciting rhythmic pulse of John Adams's score of the same title. Choreographed in 1990, the ballet has lost none of its energy, and new dancers take to its phenomenal speed and pumped-up Neo-Classical style with explosive thrust.</p>
        <p>The first hint of Wednesday's effervescence came from the bouncing body of Paul Mann, the guest conductor. Thanks to him and the orchestra, the exhilarating pace never flagged.</p>
        <p>Beautifully lighted by Mark Stanley in shades of red, then blue, the ballet avoids the minimalist repetition of steps that the score's minimalist undertones could encourage. Mr. Martins picks up on its rhythms. The pace is relentless, tempered by lyrical passages for two main couples who briefly swap partners and then join in the quiet ritualistic coda that is always a surprise.</p>
        <p>Those dancing up a storm included the first trio, Christopher Boehmer, Kyle Froman and a teenage prodigy, Daniel Ulbricht.</p>
        <p>Alexander Ritter, whose performance this season in the ''Melancholic'' solo of George Balanchine's ''Four Temperaments'' has been sensational in its clarity and coiled-spring expressiveness, sliced through the corps patterns with his leggy partner, Carrie Lee Riggins.</p>
        <p>The fine principals were Monique Meunier, partnered by Charles Askegard until she seemed abducted by Nilas Martins, who had been Miranda Weese's cavalier.</p>
        <p>An entirely different world, evoking the love of Schumann and his wife, Clara, as well as love in all its aspects, pours out of Balanchine's ''Robert Schumann's 'Davidsbündlertänze.' '' For all its Neo-Romantic aura around four couples, it is Balanchine's final statement (1980) about the alienation of the artist. When five shadowy Philistines menace the lovers, the choreography refers to Schumann's coded references to the Philistines of his own day.</p>
        <p>Except for Kyra Nichols, tender and expressive as the Clara figure, and Mr. Askegard, dazed and nicely mad as the Schumann figure, the cast is very different from the original. The dancers relate less to one another but are strongly individualized. Maria Kowroski is robust and sexy as the woman pursued by Philip Neal, and Jennie Somogyi has a vibrant girlishness. The other dancers were Helene Alexopoulos, Nilas Martins and Arch Higgins. Richard Moredock was the pianist.</p>
        <p>Jerome Robbins's breezy approach to Bach in ''Brandenburg'' ended the evening.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
