<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="10TRANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1269705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD91331F933A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>Championship Auto Racing Teams  CART--Announced the resignation of Patrick Leahy, senior vice president of marketing.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with SS Deivi Cruz on a one-year contract.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Agreed to terms with LHP Eric Milton on a four-year contract.  NEW YORK YANKEES--Agreed to terms with SS Derek Jeter on a 10-year contract.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with RHP Kelvim Escobar on a one-year contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>Championship Auto Racing Teams  CART--Announced the resignation of Patrick Leahy, senior vice president of marketing.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with SS Deivi Cruz on a one-year contract.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Agreed to terms with LHP Eric Milton on a four-year contract.  NEW YORK YANKEES--Agreed to terms with SS Derek Jeter on a 10-year contract.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Agreed to terms with RHP Kelvim Escobar on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>National League  CINCINNATI REDS--Agreed to terms with C Matt Walbeck on a minor league contract.  FLORIDA MARLINS--Named Mike Veeck consultant.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Agreed to terms with RHP Robert Person on a one-year contract.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Agreed to terms with INF Craig Paquette on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>California League  RANCHO CUCAMONGA QUAKES--Named Adam Humbert director of marketing and Ryan Rose media relations assistant.</p>
        <p>Atlantic League  CAMDEN RIVERSHARKS--Acquired C Josh Brinkley and INF Yuri Sanchez from Newark in the 2001 expansion draft.</p>
        <p>Frontier League  LONDON WEREWOLVES--Announced the retirements of OF Chris Gavriel and LHP Meleti Melehes. Traded INF Alex Zardis to Kalamazoo for a 2002 fourth-round draft pick and RHP Wade Bruton to Fort Worth of the All-American Association for future considerations. Traded 1B Wayne Chinapen to Richmond for 1B Macky Waguespack.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  CINCINNATI BENGALS--Signed G Anthony Byrd to a two-year contract.  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Named Steve Hagen tight ends coach and Pete Garcia assistant coach.  DETROIT LIONS--Named Glenn Pires linebackers coach.  PHILADELPHIA EAGLES--Signed OT Joe Wong and WR Kenny Mitchell to two-year contracts.</p>
        <p>XFL  CHICAGO ENFORCERS--Activated CB Jayson Bray, WR Fred Coleman, QB Kevin McDougal and LB Brian Rogers.  LOS ANGELES XTREME--Activated DT Chad Pegues, WR Damon Dunn and G Bruce Beaton.  LAS VEGAS OUTLAWS--Waived DT Blaine Burger.  NEW YORK-NEW JERSEY HITMEN--Activated RB Joe Aska and T Jeff Pilon.  ORLANDO RAGE--Activated DE Sedric Clark and DT Mark Campbell.  SAN FRANCISCO DEMONS--Activated OT Harvey Goins and WR Tyus Winans.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  NHL--Suspended San Jose Sharks RW Owen Nolan for 11 games for a blow to the head of Dallas Stars RW Grant Marshall during a game on Feb. 1.  ATLANTA THRASHERS--Acquired F Ladislav Kohn from the Anaheim Mighty Ducks for D Sergei Vyshedkevich and G Scott Langkow. Activated LW Tomi Kallio from injured reserve. Placed D Steve Staios on injured reserve, retroactive to Feb. 2.  DALLAS STARS--Activated D Richard Matvichuk from the injured list. Sent D Richard Jackman to Utah of the IHL.  LOS ANGELES KINGS--Recalled D Philippe Boucher from Manitoba of the IHL.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Assigned D Mark Moore to Charlotte of the ECHL.  ST. LOUIS BLUES--Recalled D Peter Smrek from Worcester of the AHL.  TORONTO MAPLE LEAFS--Recalled RW Alexei Ponikarovsky from St. John's of the AHL.</p>
        <p>American Hockey League  HERSHEY BEARS--Signed LW Terry Ryan.</p>
        <p>Central Hockey League  BORDER CITY BANDITS--Signed F Francis Boulay. Waived F Scott Ross and G Cam MacDonald. Activated G Trevor Matter from injured reserve.  HUNTSVILLE CHANNEL CATS--Signed D Mark Macera.  MEMPHIS RIVERKINGS--Transferred C Jeremy Kyte from 14-day to season-ending injured reserve. Placed RW Curtis Voth on 14-day injured reserve, retroactive to Feb. 9.  OKLAHOMA CITY BLAZERS--Announced D Wade Brookbank has been recalled by Orlando of the IHL.  TULSA OILERS--Activated D Aldo Iaquinta from injured reserve. Signed C-LW Peter Campbell.</p>
        <p>East Coast Hockey League  AUGUSTA LYNX--Suspended F Todd Gillingham.  FLORIDA EVERBLADES--Added F Oleg Timchenko to the roster.  JACKSON BANDITS--Added C Jeff Bes to the roster. Placed G Scott LaGrand on 7-day injured reserve.  JOHNSTOWN CHIEFS--Waived D Karl Infanger.  PENSACOLA ICE PILOTS--Added F Jim Bermingham, D Chris Wismer and F Tyson Holly to the roster.  PEORIA RIVERMEN--Released G Brian Hamilton.  RICHMOND RENEGADES--Activated F Frank Novock from injured reserve. Waived F Doug Altschul.  SOUTH CAROLINA STINGRAYS--Placed RW Craig Brunel on 7-day injured reserve. Activated C Buddy Wallace and D Mike Nicholishen from injured reserve.  TRENTON TITANS--Traded LW Sandy Cohen to Florida, completing a previous trade.</p>
        <p>United Hockey League  MUSKEGON FURY--Acquired LW Michel Massie from Port Huron and D-F David Dartsch from Adirondack. Sent Dartsch to Port Huron and the rights to D Lucas Nehrling to Adirondack.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  NEW ENGLAND REVOLUTION--Named Jorge Espinoza assistant coach.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>ARMY--Named David Fields assistant baseball coach.  CALIFORNIA--Announced the resignation of Pete Doyle, women's assistant gymnastics coach.  CLEVELAND STATE--Extended the contract of Rollie Massimino, mens basketball coach, through the 2004-05 season.  LSU--Announced the resignation of Mel Tucker, defensive backs coach, to take a similar position at Ohio State.  MIAMI--Promoted tight ends coach Rob Chudzinski to offensive coordinator.  NORTH CAROLINA-GREENSBORO--Named Eddie Radwanski women's soccer coach, effective Feb. 15.  NORTH TEXAS--Fired David Mitchell, offensive coordinator and wide receivers coach, and Chuck Mills, linebackers coach and special teams coordinator.  SOUTHEAST MISSOURI--Promoted assistant football coach Kip Shaw to assistant head football coach. Named defensive secondary coach Shannon Morrison as defensive coordinator.  TEXAS A&amp;M--Announced the resignations of Larry Kirksey, assistant head football coach, to become wide receivers coach for the Detroit Lions, and Steve Kragthorpe, offensive coordinator, to become quarterbacks coach for the Buffalo Bills.  UCLA--Announced it will add women's rowing as an intercollegiate sport, beginning with the 2001-2002 school year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
