<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Periscope' Shows an Expert What Defenders' Cards Are</title>
    <meta content="10CARD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1269593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EEDC1231F933A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Periscope' Shows an Expert What Defenders' Cards Are</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column describes play by Bill Pollack, one of America's finest players, in regional Swiss team event; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beginners sometimes say admiringly of an expert friend: ''So-and-so knows every card in everyone's hand before the play starts.'' Unless so-and-so regularly employs a periscope, the statement is in principle false, but there are some rare hands on which it is valid.</p>
        <p>So-and-so on the diagramed deal,  South, was Bill Pollack of Warren, N.J., who has long been one of America's finest players. A month ago he was playing in a regional Swiss team event in Rye, N.Y., and heard his left-hand opponent open one club. With the vulnerability against him, he felt nervous when Rozanne Pollack, his partner at the table and in life, bid two clubs. She too has many playing credentials, including a world title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beginners sometimes say admiringly of an expert friend: ''So-and-so knows every card in everyone's hand before the play starts.'' Unless so-and-so regularly employs a periscope, the statement is in principle false, but there are some rare hands on which it is valid.</p>
        <p>So-and-so on the diagramed deal,  South, was Bill Pollack of Warren, N.J., who has long been one of America's finest players. A month ago he was playing in a regional Swiss team event in Rye, N.Y., and heard his left-hand opponent open one club. With the vulnerability against him, he felt nervous when Rozanne Pollack, his partner at the table and in life, bid two clubs. She too has many playing credentials, including a world title.</p>
        <p>Two clubs was Michaels, a cue bid showing length in the major suits. At a different vulnerability East-West would have headed for three no-trump, but as it was East thought he could collect a substantial penalty. He doubled two clubs, and doubled again when South bid two hearts. West passed the double after some hesitation.</p>
        <p>Cover the East-West hands, and work out how much Pollack knew about his opponents' cards when the diamond three was led.</p>
        <p>He was sure that East held all four missing hearts. He was inclined to think that West had five clubs, since with six he would probably have pulled his partner's double to three clubs. His clubs were presumably headed by the ace-queen, for he would have been able to lead from another combination.</p>
        <p>West would surely not underlead the diamond ace, and he had to have the values to open the bidding. All this strongly suggested the spade king, the diamond king, and 4-0-4-5 distribution. With this knowledge South had to try to make his contract. He knew, however, that a one-trick defeat would be a reasonable result, since the opponents could surely make three no-trump.</p>
        <p>South ruffed the diamond lead in dummy and led a low club. East put up the ten and returned a low diamond, forcing another ruff in the dummy. When another club was led from dummy East rose with the king. He had decided that he ought to cut down the declarer's ruffs, so he cashed the heart ace. South followed suit from his hand and thoughtfully called for the jack from the dummy.</p>
        <p>At this point, East would have done best to lead the heart queen, a surprising play aimed at preventing South from having an immediate entry to his hand. But the declarer could have survived this by winning with dummy's king, ruffing the club jack and taking a spade finesse. Then he could cash the spade ace and crossruff, making his contract.</p>
        <p>In practice, West led a low heart, allowing South to win with the ten, finesse dummy's spade ten with confidence, and ruff a club. Another spade finesse left this ending:</p>
        <p>Diagram</p>
        <p>South needed two more tricks. Knowing from his original assessment that East was about to ruff a spade, Pollack did not make the mistake of trying to cash the ace. Instead he called for a low spade, and East was helpless.</p>
        <p>If he had ruffed and led a trump, South would have scored an overtrick. If he had discarded, South would have ruffed and trumped a diamond in the dummy. East chose to ruff and lead a diamond, but that was no better. The declarer ruffed in dummy and scored his heart five en passant at the finish.</p>
        <p>Thanks to his card-reading skill, Pollack won eight tricks and his team gained 15 imps. His teammates made three no-trump with an overtrick in the replay.</p>
        <p>The one-session Silver Point pair games scheduled for 1 and 7 p.m. today at the New York Helmsley Hotel, 212 East 42nd Street, are restricted to players with fewer than 200 master points.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
