<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MCI Posts Profitable Quarter, First Since End of Bankruptcy</title>
    <meta content="10mci" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/10/business/10mci.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1693722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">MCI Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DF143EF933A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MCI Posts Profitable Quarter, First Since End of Bankruptcy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">MCI Posts Profitable Quarter, First Since End of Bankruptcy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MCI Inc., the long-distance carrier that has agreed to be sold to Verizon Communications, said yesterday that it earned $64 million, or 19 cents a share, in the second quarter, beating Wall Street's expectations. It was MCI's first profitable quarter since emerging from bankruptcy last year.</p>
        <p>The company, based in Ashburn, Va., lost $71 million, or 22 cents a share, in the quarter last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>MCI Inc. said that it earned $64 million, or 19 cents a share, in the second quarter, beating Wall Street's expectations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MCI Inc., the long-distance carrier that has agreed to be sold to Verizon Communications, said yesterday that it earned $64 million, or 19 cents a share, in the second quarter, beating Wall Street's expectations. It was MCI's first profitable quarter since emerging from bankruptcy last year.</p>
        <p>The company, based in Ashburn, Va., lost $71 million, or 22 cents a share, in the quarter last year.</p>
        <p>MCI has been aggressively cutting costs and has eliminated about 15,000 jobs in the last year. The reductions have helped the company offset a continued decline in sales.</p>
        <p>Revenue fell 10 percent in the quarter from a year earlier, to $4.7 billion, compared with $5.2 billion. Operating expenses, however, slid 11 percent, to $4.6 billion.</p>
        <p>MCI also said it had $5.3 billion in cash and marketable securities on its balance sheet at the end of June, and $5.9 billion in debt.</p>
        <p>MCI's shares rose 7 cents yesterday, to close at $25.38.</p>
        <p>MCI, like AT&amp;T and other long-distance carriers that serve corporate customers, has been in a price war resulting from the construction of too many fiber optic networks during the late 1990's, as well as the emergence of cheaper Internet-based phones and other technological innovations.</p>
        <p>The entry of the Bells into the long- distance residential phone market has also led MCI, AT&amp;T and others to retreat from the consumer business.</p>
        <p>With its future in doubt, MCI agreed this year to be acquired by Verizon for $8.5 billion. The company rejected a $9.8 billion bid from Qwest Communications. MCI and Verizon hope to receive approval from regulators for their deal by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Verizon's purchase came a few months after SBC Communications agreed to buy MCI's primary rival, AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>If both deals are approved, as many industry analysts expect, Verizon and SBC will end up controlling 56 percent of the country's $134 billion corporate telecommunications market, according to the Yankee Group.</p>
        <p>BellSouth, Qwest and Sprint control another 19 percent of the market.</p>
        <p>Without AT&amp;T or MCI competing in regions dominated by SBC and Verizon, prices for wholesale high-speed data lines in those areas will rise 11 to 400 percent, depending on the connection, according to Simon J. Wilkie, a former economist at the Federal Communications Commission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilkie, who prepared a study for the Alliance for Competition in Telecommunications, a group of non-Bell telecommunications companies, said that wholesale carriers would ultimately pass these higher costs on to their customers.</p>
        <p>The merging companies, however, insist that there will still be plenty of competitors in the high-speed data line market after the deals are concluded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
