<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay;Memories of Yitzhak Rabin</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="807208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGNSERVICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RABIN, YITZHAK (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIXON, RICHARD MILHOUS(1913-94)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFD81739F935A35752C1A963958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay;Memories of Yitzhak Rabin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a dinner in the Israeli Embassy in Washington early this year, Yitzhak Rabin took issue with a column of mine opposing the use of U.S. troops on the Golan.</p>
        <p>As usual between us, he minced no words, zinging me as being duped and manipulated by press agents for the opposition coalition in Israel. Stung, I responded more vigorously than I would to any other chief of government. The man sitting at the table between us -- Secretary of State Warren Christopher, who never breaches protocol -- blanched at the seeming heatedness of the exchange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a dinner in the Israeli Embassy in Washington early this year, Yitzhak Rabin took issue with a column of mine opposing the use of U.S. troops on the Golan.</p>
        <p>As usual between us, he minced no words, zinging me as being duped and manipulated by press agents for the opposition coalition in Israel. Stung, I responded more vigorously than I would to any other chief of government. The man sitting at the table between us -- Secretary of State Warren Christopher, who never breaches protocol -- blanched at the seeming heatedness of the exchange.</p>
        <p>Then the Prime Minister laid his hand on the Secretary's arm and said through the cigarette smoke: "Relax. We can do this because we go back a long way. Let me tell you a story."</p>
        <p>He recalled the days he had been Israel's Ambassador in Washington and I was  a pro-Israel Nixon speechwriter. Rabin had a special relationship with the President: In the 60's, when Nixon was a nonentity in the political wilderness,  he visited Israel and General Rabin showed him the respect that few others did,  taking time to point out military defenses in detail.</p>
        <p>Nixon did not forget that after his comeback; Rabin was his favorite foreign  ambassador. The Israeli made the most of that high regard, and Nixon knew that Rabin would frequently lobby some liberal Jewish Americans on Nixon's behalf.</p>
        <p>"There was the time I was sitting in the synagogue on Connecticut Avenue during Yom Kippur," Rabin told Christopher that night. Just before the Kol Nidre service was about to start, he saw this Nixon speechwriter race into synagogue and collapse into his seat near the Ambassador. Out of breath, the Nixon writer  told Rabin he had just left the Agnew plane on the 1970 Congressional campaign trail, and made it back just in time.</p>
        <p>Then came the rabbi's sermon. To the dismay of both writer and Ambassador, it included a blast at "those who would use alliteration to polarize our society."  Rabin commiserated with the Nixon aide and later probably had a few words with the rabbi.</p>
        <p>"That's why we can get angry with each other today without getting angry with each other," the Prime Minister told the Secretary 25 years later. I walked out  of the Ambassador's residence that night with a good, hot column for my paper and a good, warm feeling for Yitzhak Rabin.</p>
        <p>Why did this first Sabra to govern Israel engender such trust in those of us  who disagreed with the pace and scope of his West Bank withdrawal?</p>
        <p>Because he had been present at the creation of Israel and was as responsible  as anyone for its survival; nobody else had such hard-earned credentials. Because Rabin had made a political comeback to win his position fair and square, he earned the right to carry out his policy.</p>
        <p>Frankly, it was a grudging faith in Rabin -- in his cool judgment, military experience and absolute integrity -- that kept this pundit from heaping advice on Israelis this year. Not one of his Labor colleagues engenders such trust.</p>
        <p>I remember interviewing Rabin in the 70's, during his first prime ministership. It was about midnight; he had just returned to Israel from a trip  in Europe but had promised to see me before a deadline and was not one to use exhaustion as a reason to break a promise. His message that night was the urgent need to retain the West Bank for Israel's security; a generation later, he changed his mind and changed his world.</p>
        <p>Another memory, shared with millions, is that of his show of exquisite reluctance at the signing ceremony with Yasir Arafat on the White House lawn. The pain of his gamble for peace captured the dissonance torturing Israelis, in  contrast to the enthusiasm shown by his rival-partner Shimon Peres.</p>
        <p>Some of the Hebrew words spoken by Rabin that day -- part of an ancient prayer -- will be repeated today at his funeral. That is because Jews, in the midst of death and grief, are taught to praise God and celebrate life.</p>
        <p>The Jewish people, who go back a long way, have always been inspired by fallen heroes like Yitzhak Rabin to reaffirm their faith.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
