<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>By the BBC, The Glory Of Gospel</title>
    <meta content="05OCON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="TELEVISION REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="906662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Great Performances (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7D71E3DF936A35751C0A961958260" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>By the BBC, The Glory Of Gospel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Connor, John J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John J O'Connor reviews BBC-TV program The Story of Gospel Music, part of PBS series Great Performances; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fact that an exceptionally fine documentary about American gospel music is produced by the BBC no doubt says something about American television. But instead of bickering, let's just rejoice because ''The Story of Gospel Music'' has been acquired by public television and can be seen on ''Great Performances'' tonight.</p>
        <p>A combination of performance snippets from 1994 and 1995 have been combined with archival clips covering several decades, all wrapped in commentaries from experts like the Rev. Dr. Wyatt Tee Walker, author of ''Somebody's Calling My Name.'' The 90-minute program skillfully traces gospel from its religious roots in the 19th century to its crossover excursions, not entirely appreciated or accepted by some black churches, in recent years. Popular performers coming out of a gospel background have included Aretha Franklin, Sam Cook, Della Reese and Whitney Houston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fact that an exceptionally fine documentary about American gospel music is produced by the BBC no doubt says something about American television. But instead of bickering, let's just rejoice because ''The Story of Gospel Music'' has been acquired by public television and can be seen on ''Great Performances'' tonight.</p>
        <p>A combination of performance snippets from 1994 and 1995 have been combined with archival clips covering several decades, all wrapped in commentaries from experts like the Rev. Dr. Wyatt Tee Walker, author of ''Somebody's Calling My Name.'' The 90-minute program skillfully traces gospel from its religious roots in the 19th century to its crossover excursions, not entirely appreciated or accepted by some black churches, in recent years. Popular performers coming out of a gospel background have included Aretha Franklin, Sam Cook, Della Reese and Whitney Houston.</p>
        <p>There is no overestimating the role that gospel music has played in the lives of American blacks. Commenting on the early days, Amiri Baraka, the writer, observes that the songs were ''really meant to communicate a whole social life of the slaves that is more or less obscure to the masters.'' Although the African drum was taken away, he adds, ''all music slaves made is like percussive without the drum.''</p>
        <p>The traditional hymns of white Baptists, Methodists and Presbyterians were, as one commentator puts it, decorated with curlicues. In gospel, the call-and-response pattern of the preacher and his congregation was incorporated into the music. The effect was and is electrifying. Dr. Walker doesn't mince words: ''It has been the primary ingredient which has bonded us together as a surviving people.''</p>
        <p>Most of the major figures are seen and heard. The lineup includes everyone from composers like Thomas Dorsey, called the godfather of gospel, and W. Herbert Brewster to the legendary singers Mahalia Jackson, James Cleveland and Clara Ward. We're reminded that Miss Jackson's religious convictions were so strong that she turned down lucrative offers to appear at popular places like Harlem's Apollo Theater and Las Vegas. We're also reminded that her performance contributed one of the more memorable moments to the 1963 March on Washington with the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</p>
        <p>What is it about gospel that leaves even nonbelievers exulting? There are, of course, the gloriously seductive syncopations and rhythms. Then there's the fervor and unmistakable conviction. (One scene shows jaded whites at the 1957 Newport Jazz Festival being brought to surprised life by the Clara Ward Singers.)</p>
        <p>Whatever, the tradition is still brimming with vitality, although Dr. Walker is wary. He is ''glad gospel singers can make a living'' but warns that ''they have to be disciplined enough not to sell out.'' Then he adds, with a smile, ''Let me rock for Jesus and roll for God.'' That hint of flexibility is both charming and crucial.</p>
        <p>GREAT PERFORMANCES  The Story of Gospel Music</p>
        <p>PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9:30)</p>
        <p>Andrew Dunn and James Marsh, directors; Howard Porter and Anne Elletson, producers; John Walker, senior producer for music; David Horn, series producer for music; Glenn DuBose, managing director; Jac Venza, series executive producer. Produced by BBC Television and presented by an public television alliance: WNET/New York, KERA/Dallas-Fort Worth, KQED/San Francisco, Maryland Public Television, South Carolina ETV and WTTW/Chicago.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mahalia Jackson, Aretha Franklin, James Cleveland, the Edwin Hawkins Singers, Cissy Houston, the Dixie Hummingbirds, Sister Rosetta Tharpe, Shirley Caesar and the Caravans and Clara Ward. Commentary by Amiri Baraka, Horace Boyer and the Rev. Dr. Wyatt Tee Walker.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
