<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Semitism Hasn't Tainted Solidarity Rift</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTI-SEMITISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DERSHOWITZ, ALAN M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1439F930A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Semitism Hasn't Tainted Solidarity Rift</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Alan M. Dershowitz makes mischief when he asserts (letter, July 19) that Polish anti-Semitism plays a major role in the dispute between the trade union faction of Solidarity, led by Lech Walesa, and the Government faction, led by Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki, a prominent Roman Catholic. When the mostly Catholic Government faction is called a ''band of intellectuals,'' that is not a euphemism for Jews, but an apt description: many of them, like Mr. Mazowiecki, were drawn from the Clubs of Catholic Intellectuals.</p>
        <p>While a few Poles not affiliated with Solidarity may use the words ''intellectuals'' and ''pluralists'' as code words for Jews, other Poles use these words with their plain meaning. The use of code words debases the language; Professor Dershowitz's tactic of attributing a coded meaning where the plain word is meant, to impute anti-Semitism to a Nobel Peace Prize winner like Mr. Walesa, is an even worse abuse of language.</p>
        <p>That Jewish figures like Bronislaw Geremek, Adam Michnik and Karol Modzelewski rose to prominence in Solidarity shows that anti-Semitism is not so deeply rooted in Poland as Professor Dershowitz would have us believe. Nor was being Jewish a handicap in the 1989 parliamentary elections. When Mr. Modzelewski ran for the senate, he was the victim of an anti-Semitic leaflet campaign by the secret police. Mr. Modzelewski not only won, but his 75 percent majority also exceeded the 68 percent of the district's other Solidarity candidate, who was not Jewish.</p>
        <p>The 1946 Kielce pogrom was carried out not by Polish nationalists, but by the Soviet-controlled army and militia of the newly installed Communist Government, precisely to discredit the non-Communist opposition. The wave of Jewish emigration from Poland in 1968 resulted from a Communist Party factional fight, in which the population's non-Communist majority was not involved.</p>
        <p>Solidarity's 10-year struggle for freedom, which won worldwide admiration and brought democracy not only to Poland but also to most of East Central Europe, should inspire trust in the democratic instincts of Polish society, except unfortunately among those with an emotional investment in denigrating Poland and the Poles.</p>
        <p>CHARLES CHOTKOWSKI</p>
        <p>Fairfield, Conn., July 21, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
