<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reading The Text</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ABROAD AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1538F930A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reading The Text</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When hearings get under way next month on the nomination of Judge David Souter to the Supreme Court, it would be a relief if senators and others dropped from their vocabularies the weary slogans applied to judges in recent years. We have had enough of ''activist'' and ''originalist'' and the like.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When hearings get under way next month on the nomination of Judge David Souter to the Supreme Court, it would be a relief if senators and others dropped from their vocabularies the weary slogans applied to judges in recent years. We have had enough of ''activist'' and ''originalist'' and the like.</p>
        <p>When hearings get under way next month on the nomination of Judge David Souter to the Supreme Court, it would be a relief if senators and others dropped from their vocabularies the weary slogans applied to judges in recent years. We have had enough of ''activist'' and ''originalist'' and the like.</p>
        <p>President Bush contributed to the sloganeering tendency when he announced the nomination. Asked by a reporter about Judge Souter's constitutional views, the President said: ''What I'm certain of is that he will interpret the Constitution, not legislate from the Federal bench.''</p>
        <p>Ever since 1803, when it decided Marbury v. Madison, the Supreme Court has been displeasing one group or another by its constitutional decisions. Disagreement is inevitable because of the nature of the American Constitution. Its great clauses are so spacious in their phrasing that judges are bound to differ in applying them to concrete cases.</p>
        <p>''Due process of law'' or ''the freedom of speech'' are not self-defining commands. And they were not meant to be. The Framers of the Constitution used such open-ended phrases because they understood that a detailed, specific code would soon be dated and useless. A leading authority on the First Amendment, Prof. Leonard W. Levy of the Claremont Graduate School, put it:</p>
        <p>''The Framers had a genius for studied imprecision. They were conscious of the need to phrase the Constitution in generalized terms and without a lexicographical guide, for they meant to outline an instrument that would serve future generations.''</p>
        <p>Of course judges differ in the weight they give to earlier decisions, to precedent. But there again slogans are unhelpful. Justice Antonin Scalia of the present Court is called a conservative. But no one is more radical in the desire to wipe out precedents that he considers ill founded.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is romantic - I confess to being a romantic about the Supreme Court - but it should be possible to discuss a judge's philosophy without pejorative slogans. Justice William J. Brennan Jr. did that on the Supreme Court, never questioning his colleagues' good faith, no matter how strong their disagreements.</p>
        <p>President Bush noted that in some graceful remarks on Justice Brennan's retirement. ''His powerful intellect,'' the President said, ''his winning personality and, importantly, his commitment to civil discourse on emotional issues that at times tempt uncivil voices, have made him one of the greatest figures of our age.''</p>
        <p>Sloganeering about the Supreme Court has gone on for a long time, and people on all sides of the political spectrum have engaged in it. If it seems nastier now, that may be because of the heat aroused by the fight over Judge Robert Bork's nomination to the Supreme Court and its rejection by the Senate.</p>
        <p>Judge Bork advanced an extreme theory of constitutional interpretation: that the only lawful way for a judge to proceed is to find the ''original intention'' of the Framers. Judge Bork did not himself rigidly follow such a precept when he was on the bench. But in the bitterness of defeat, he and his followers have nailed their colors to it.</p>
        <p>A review of Judge Bork's book by Prof. Bruce Ackerman of Yale exposes the concept for what it is: a historical theory with no basis in history. The review, in the April issue of The Yale Law Journal, appears in somewhat shorter form in the summer issue of the new quarterly The American Prospect.</p>
        <p>American judges cannot escape the duty of finding the meaning of the Constitution again and again. The reason was well stated in an opinion explaining why the First Amendment disallowed a political libel suit:</p>
        <p>''We know very little of the precise intentions of the framers and ratifiers of the speech and press clauses of the First Amendment. But we do know that they gave into our keeping the value of preserving free expression. . . .</p>
        <p>''Perhaps the framers did not envision libel actions as a major threat to that freedom. . . . But if, over time, the libel action becomes a threat to the central meaning of the First Amendment, why should not judges adapt their doctrines? Why is it different to refine and evolve doctrine here, so long as one is faithful to the basic meaning of the amendment, than it is to adapt the Fourth Amendment to take account of electronic surveillance . . .?</p>
        <p>''To say that such matters must be left to the legislature is to say that changes in circumstances must be permitted to render constitutional guarantees meaningless.''</p>
        <p>The opinion was by Judge Robert Bork.</p>
        <p>ABROAD AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
