<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gifts Of Gab</title>
    <meta content="WLN110544" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/16/magazine/16ONLANGUAGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1351690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 12-16-01: ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA173FF935A25751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gifts Of Gab</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gifts of Gab</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column comments on some books about language that would make good holiday gifts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I would hesitate before giving somebody a bar of soap for the holidays, no matter how expensively perfumed and fancily packaged the soap may be, because it would seem insulting to suggest ''you really need this.'' But books about language make great gifts for that very reason: we all really do need them. Here goes this year's gifts of gab:</p>
        <p>The New Oxford American Dictionary ($50). I was all set to recommend this 2,023-page work because Oxford has always been so good at dictionaries, and lexicographic publishing needs a boost after Random House suddenly abandoned the field. But the preface to N.O.A.D. brought me up short: ''Past attempts to cover the meaning of all possible uses of a word,'' Oxford's editors boldly explain, ''have tended to lead to a blurred, unfocused result, in which the core of the meaning is obscured by many minor uses.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>And the new dictionary controversy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I would hesitate before giving somebody a bar of soap for the holidays, no matter how expensively perfumed and fancily packaged the soap may be, because it would seem insulting to suggest ''you really need this.'' But books about language make great gifts for that very reason: we all really do need them. Here goes this year's gifts of gab:</p>
        <p>The New Oxford American Dictionary ($50). I was all set to recommend this 2,023-page work because Oxford has always been so good at dictionaries, and lexicographic publishing needs a boost after Random House suddenly abandoned the field. But the preface to N.O.A.D. brought me up short: ''Past attempts to cover the meaning of all possible uses of a word,'' Oxford's editors boldly explain, ''have tended to lead to a blurred, unfocused result, in which the core of the meaning is obscured by many minor uses.''</p>
        <p>That means room for more words, which is fine, but with fewer meanings for each, which is a bummer to those of us who like to see how wide a swath a word can cut. Sol Steinmetz, retired but tireless rex of lex, tells me that ''attempts to justify quickie definitions often disguise the slightly more practical desire to save space.''</p>
        <p>I prefer a dictionary that gives the most common meaning first, then lists the others, with the least common last. That's because the so-called core meaning often shifts: core is now most often an adjective defined as ''having the essential part,'' pushing ahead of a noun meaning ''the center of a fruit,'' which Oxford seedily lists first. Merriam-Webster's 10th Collegiate puts the newer big use first. Both include narrower meanings like ''the place in a nuclear reactor where fission occurs,'' but Oxford, worried about blurring, has half as many.</p>
        <p>How ''American'' is N.O.A.D.? It has A.Y.T., e-mail for ''are you there?'' and dub-dub-dub, the weird shortening of W.W.W. of the World Wide Web, but not the more generally used 24/7. It has the somewhat dated limousine liberal and blue dog Democrat but not soccer mom, road warrior, slamming and branding, all of which can be found in the fourth edition of Webster's New World. If you're standing on one leg wondering which of these dictionaries has lawn flamingo, only Oxford does (and what's an American lawn without a plastic flamingo?). Though American Heritage is flamingo-free, it shames N.O.A.D. with its flat tax, hate crime, parental leave, butthead, punditocracy and spinmeister.</p>
        <p>Give Oxford and American Heritage credit for being best on the Americanism bummer, as used above; not only does N.O.A.D. list ''a thing that is annoying or disappointing'' first, with ''an unpleasant reaction to a hallucinogenic drug'' second, but both suggest that the origin is the German bummeln, ''to stroll, loaf around,'' which is what bums used to do before they became homeless persons. In sum, I'd give the N.O.A.D. to a person looking for a quick answer, not semantic or etymological depth.</p>
        <p>Dictionary of the Future, by Faith Popcorn and Adam Hanft (Hyperion, $22.95), is the cheery ''speak preview'' product of a couple of marketing futurists. They create words like geriborg, a robot built to make old age easier for ''baby boomers growing old in the digital age'' with never-hungry electronic dogs wagging their feather tails, ever ready to take out the garbage. Sinister hacktivists flood computer servers with denial-of-service attacks, while old-fashioned spamming is blocked by address munging, ''modifying one's e-mail address in such a way that computers can't read it but humans can.'' My favorite description of a growing annoyance is secondhand speech, ''the cellphone equivalent of secondhand smoke.''</p>
        <p>The Word Detective (Plume paperback, $11) is breezy etymology by Evan Morris. Kangaroo court, for example, is not rooted in Australia, home of that marsupial with strong hindquarters, but in Texas in the mid-19th century. He defines it as ''any court whose verdict is arranged in advance or otherwise clearly unfair'' and ''draws a sardonic analogy between the hopping gait of a kangaroo and the irrational and unpredictable conduct of the original frontier tribunals,'' complete with their ''leaps of logic.'' Because the animal was exotic and unseen by Americans, Morris notes, ''labeling something kangaroo back then was roughly equivalent to calling it abnormal or bizarre today.'' The frontier expression was recently picked up by vituperative columnists objecting to military tribunals for noncitizens ordered by President Bush to circumvent the delays of due process.</p>
        <p>Yiddish, a Nation of Words, by Miriam Weinstein (Steer Forth Press, $26), is a popular history of the language that has been spicing the American lingo. Puns are important: why, for example, are carrots a favorite dish served on the High Holy Days? Because the Yiddish word mern, which as a noun means ''carrots,'' as a verb means ''multiply,'' expressing hope for the year to come. So that's why such a tsimmes is made of it.</p>
        <p>The Atoms of Language, by Prof. Mark C. Baker of Rutgers (Basic Books, $28), is for linguistic heavy hitters, but his discussion of the Navajo ''code talkers'' is an ear-opener. When Japanese code breakers were causing U.S. casualties in World War II, our Marines called in a dozen native speakers of the difficult-to-fathom Navajo language. These Americans were able to translate English into Navajo -- a syntactic code that proved unbreakable -- and then back into English immediately. But this led to a paradox; how could English and Navajo be so different and yet so similar?</p>
        <p>The wonder, Baker writes, is that ''children, without graduate training, government funding or even adequate secretarial help, manage in five years what computer scientists and linguists have been wrestling with unsuccessfully for 50.'' How? ''Children must have a huge head start . . . substantial enough to help them master the complexities of language with relative ease yet general enough to be applicable to any human language they come into contact with. This implies that all human languages must be more similar than they appear,'' and the paradox of the Navajo code talkers ''convinces linguists that at some level all languages must be the same.''</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 12-16-01: ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
