<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mix-up of Remains From Crash Causes Family More Pain</title>
    <meta content="16MIXU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="51" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/16/nyregion/16MIXU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1352017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">American Airlines</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Borakove, Ellen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDF163EF935A25751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mix-up of Remains From Crash Causes Family More Pain</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mix-up of Remains From Crash Causes Family More Pain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clerical error at New York City's medical examiner's office allows hand of victim of American Airlines' Flight 587 in Queens to be sent to another victim's family; there are also three cases in which victims of World Trade Center attacks were wrongly identified (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a disaster like the crash of American Airlines Flight 587 in Queens last month, the hard truth is that the bodies of many victims are difficult to recover. That is why when even a small body part is found, relatives often feel a great sense of relief.</p>
        <p>So it was on Dec. 4 when the children of Luz Maria Lendof, 64, of the Bronx, who died with her husband in the crash, were informed by the New York City medical examiner's office that their mother's hand had been recovered. The hand, and the remains of Mrs. Lendof's husband, Teofilo Hernandez, 69, were flown to the Dominican Republic, where the victims were born. The couple's five children held a double funeral for them Monday in Santo Domingo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A clerical error in handling the body parts of a woman killed in American Airlines flight 587 is reopening a wound for her family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a disaster like the crash of American Airlines Flight 587 in Queens last month, the hard truth is that the bodies of many victims are difficult to recover. That is why when even a small body part is found, relatives often feel a great sense of relief.</p>
        <p>So it was on Dec. 4 when the children of Luz Maria Lendof, 64, of the Bronx, who died with her husband in the crash, were informed by the New York City medical examiner's office that their mother's hand had been recovered. The hand, and the remains of Mrs. Lendof's husband, Teofilo Hernandez, 69, were flown to the Dominican Republic, where the victims were born. The couple's five children held a double funeral for them Monday in Santo Domingo.</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, a representative from the medical examiner's office arrived in Santo Domingo unexpectedly with some shocking news. The hand was not Mrs. Lendof's. It belonged to another victim of the plane crash, whose family had not yet been notified of the mistake and whose name had still not been made public yesterday.</p>
        <p>''We thought that the nightmare was over and we were thinking of coming back here to New York and going back to our normal lives,'' said Francis Lorenzo, a friend of the family who attended the funeral in Santo Domingo and was acting as a family spokesman yesterday. ''It was like getting hit the first time and then getting hit back the second time. But this time it is worse. It is like having a wound that is reopened.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the medical examiner's office, Ellen Borakove, said the mix-up was caused by a clerical error. Someone had transposed the last two figures in Mrs. Lendof's case number in a computer file, making it DQ 587 instead of DQ 578, the correct number. The hand, identified through DNA analysis, actually belonged to the person whose case number was DQ 587. The hand will be brought back to New York from the Dominican Republic, Ms. Borakove added.</p>
        <p>One possible explanation for the error, she said, was that almost all employees in the medical examiner's office have the number 587 etched in their minds because it was the plane's flight number. Ms. Borakove said she did not know how the error with Mrs. Lendof's case was detected, but when it was, the office instituted a system that now requires all computer entries of case numbers to be double-checked.</p>
        <p>''It is a coincidence that 587 was the flight number but that could have been part of the reason that the person transposed a number similar to it,'' Ms. Borakove said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, there have been other mistakes in the medical examiner's office that have no link to the flight number or, for that matter, the crash on Nov. 12 in Queens. Though only one incident has received publicity, there have been three cases of remains from the Sept. 11 World Trade Center attack being erroneously identified, according to the medical examiner's office.</p>
        <p>Ms. Borakove would not provide details in two of the cases, saying the families had requested they be kept private. She said one error was the result of a bureaucratic mistake and the other the result of some unspecified scientific difficulties.</p>
        <p>In the third case, the medical examiner's office misidentified Firefighter Christopher Santora as Firefighter Jose Guadalupe, both of whom were killed in the collapse of the twin towers. The men belonged to Engine Company 54, part of a firehouse in Midtown Manhattan, and both had the same unusual condition in which adjacent neck vertebrae  had similar congenital flaws. The error was discovered after Firefighter Santora's body had been buried under the name of Firefighter Guadalupe.</p>
        <p>''We apologize to all of the families concerned,'' Ms. Borakove said yesterday. ''We don't want to be adding to the burden they are already under from the World Trade Center and the airplane crash. It is a very tragic time for everybody.''</p>
        <p>It is also a very hectic time for anyone associated with law enforcement in the city, including the staff at the medical examiner's office. In a typical year, the office, which employs about 450 people, handles about 5,000 autopsies. Since Sept. 11, it has handled 11,000 remains from the World Trade Center attacks and 2,000 from the plane crash in Queens, Ms. Borakove said.</p>
        <p>In all those numbers there was some comfort for the children of Mrs. Lendof. Though the hand was misidentified, there was in fact a case DQ 578 documenting a body part that the medical examiner's office had correctly identified as belonging to Mrs. Lendof. There was also another body part, given the case number DQ 245, which the office accurately identified as belonging to Mrs. Lendorf.</p>
        <p>So yesterday afternoon, for the second time in a week, Mrs. Lendof's children gathered for a funeral, this time in Manhattan. A lawyer for the family, Ralph DeSimone, said Mrs. Lendof's remains would be flown today to the Dominican Republic to be buried alongside her husband.</p>
        <p>''The medical examiner's office has been apologetic and they tried to be as accommodating as possible,'' Mr. DeSimone said. ''But this is still a horrific mix-up.''</p>
        <p>The family friend, Mr. Lorenzo, said Mrs. Lendof's children were leaving nothing to chance. He said they had hired their own medical expert to confirm the identity of the new remains.</p>
        <p>''We can't sleep,'' Mr. Lorenzo said. ''It is hard to understand what has really happened.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
