<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Urges That Immigrants Become Further Americanized</title>
    <meta content="T01IMM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="961749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration Reform, Commission on (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rogers, Harold (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DA1E3AF932A35753C1A961958260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Urges That Immigrants Become Further Americanized</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Commission on Immigration Reform, in its final report to Congress after five years of work, calls for major campaign to integrate new immigrants into American society; Rep Harold Rogers supports commission's proposal to dismantle Immigration and Naturalization Service (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal advisory panel called today for a major campaign to integrate new immigrants into American society, and it won support from an influential Republican Congressman for its proposal to dismantle the Immigration and Naturalization Service.</p>
        <p>In its final report to Congress after five years of work, the panel, the United States Commission on Immigration Reform, also said that some decisions on applications for visas should be subject to review by a new Government agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal advisory panel called today for a major campaign to integrate new immigrants into American society, and it won support from an influential Republican Congressman for its proposal to dismantle the Immigration and Naturalization Service.</p>
        <p>In its final report to Congress after five years of work, the panel, the United States Commission on Immigration Reform, also said that some decisions on applications for visas should be subject to review by a new Government agency.</p>
        <p>That would represent a radical change. Now, would-be immigrants and their American sponsors generally cannot appeal decisions of consular officers who deny applications for visas. The panel would allow such appeals in some cases.</p>
        <p>Bruce A. Morrison, a member of the panel, explained the reason for appeal rights by saying, ''Lack of accountability in any decision-making structure is not tolerable.''</p>
        <p>The nine-member commission concluded its work with a ringing endorsement of the value of legal immigration, saying that migrants contributed to the nation's economic growth and productivity.</p>
        <p>But it said that Federal and state officials must step up their efforts to incorporate immigrants into the nation's civic and political culture. For example, it said, newcomers need help in English-language skills and should be trained for high-tech jobs, so that they will move up the economic ladder.</p>
        <p>Susan Martin, executive director of the commission, said that many children of Hispanic immigrants dropped out of school and that many immigrant teen-agers never enrolled in schools in this country.</p>
        <p>Cecilia Munoz, deputy vice president of the National Council of La Raza, a Hispanic civil rights organization, said she saw great merit in the proposal for a new emphasis on the ''Americanization'' of immigrants.</p>
        <p>''The United States has relied on immigrant families and on employers to help immigrants adjust to life in this country -- to find jobs and housing, to enroll in school, to open bank accounts,'' Ms. Munoz said. ''If the Government and the larger society would invest in such services, we could get a huge return, and immigrants would make a quicker adjustment to American life. Immigrants are accused of not wanting to learn English, but they are eager to do so. Many English-language programs have enormous waiting lists.''</p>
        <p>The chairman of the House Appropriations subcommittee responsible for the immigration service, Harold Rogers, a Kentucky Republican, welcomed many of the panel's recommendations. He endorsed the proposal to dismantle the immigration service and distribute its functions among the Departments of Justice, State and Labor.</p>
        <p>He agreed with the commission's conclusion that the immigration service was suffering from ''mission overload,'' but not from a lack of money. Indeed, he said, the budget of the agency, $3.1 billion this year, has increased 50 percent in the last two years and has more than tripled in the last decade.</p>
        <p>''At last,'' he said, ''someone is telling it like it is. The I.N.S. is overloaded, and money is no longer an excuse. The agency has too much on its plate. It cannot control our borders, process immigrants and safeguard U.S. citizenship. We've seen tens of thousands of criminals granted the most precious benefit our country has to offer: U.S. citizenship.  We have over five million illegal aliens residing in the United States, the same all-time high of 10 years ago.''</p>
        <p>The House Appropriations Committee recently instructed Attorney General Janet Reno to devise a plan to ''transfer some of the responsibilities of the I.N.S. to other departments and agencies.''</p>
        <p>Advocates for immigrants and immigration lawyers were cool to the proposal to break up the I.N.S.</p>
        <p>Jeanne A. Butterfield, executive director of the American Immigration Lawyers Association, said she doubted that immigrants would receive better service from the State Department than from the immigration service, which is now part of the Justice Department. From years of dealing with State Department officials, she said, ''we know that they are opposed to review of their decisions, have no mechanisms in place to assure due process of law and are ill equipped to deal with the volume and complexity of cases that I.N.S. must adjudicate on a daily basis.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
