<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smelling Mud? Look for Snowdrops</title>
    <meta content="25CUTT$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/25/living/25CUTT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1280558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Ann Arbor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">england</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Longwood</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pennsylvania</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Gloucester</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Ann Arbor</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Scheepers Inc.</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5DE153CF936A15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smelling Mud? Look for Snowdrops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH GINSBURG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FEW weeks ago I began looking for snowdrops. It was an exercise in futility, as I had anticipated, but I felt strangely compelled to do it anyway. Other harbingers of temperate weather were in place: the temperature was almost springlike, the earth was bare. In England and parts of the South snowdrops bloom in late fall and winter. At Longwood Gardens in Pennsylvania they bloom in the rock garden in late February. It seemed reasonable to check.</p>
        <p>As I went out the back door, I sniffed. There was no fresh earthy smell. In my experience, snowdrops usually appear about the time you can smell the mud (in addition to seeing it and mopping it up off the kitchen floor). A tour of the backyard revealed crocus tips and onion grass, but no sign of the distinctive white, nodding flower heads of the genus Galanthus. It was disappointing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FEW weeks ago I began looking for snowdrops. It was an exercise in futility, as I had anticipated, but I felt strangely compelled to do it anyway. Other harbingers of temperate weather were in place: the temperature was almost springlike, the earth was bare. In England and parts of the South snowdrops bloom in late fall and winter. At Longwood Gardens in Pennsylvania they bloom in the rock garden in late February. It seemed reasonable to check.</p>
        <p>As I went out the back door, I sniffed. There was no fresh earthy smell. In my experience, snowdrops usually appear about the time you can smell the mud (in addition to seeing it and mopping it up off the kitchen floor). A tour of the backyard revealed crocus tips and onion grass, but no sign of the distinctive white, nodding flower heads of the genus Galanthus. It was disappointing.</p>
        <p>Snowdrops are simplicity itself, which is probably why they have been garden favorites for centuries. Some species are native to Europe and others originated in western Asia. Ever since 19th-century plant hunters first descended on Turkey and other countries where Galanthus grows wild, unscrupulous plant foragers have threatened snowdrop populations.</p>
        <p>Lately I have seen snowdrops on printed pages all around me. An armchair foray into my garden clippings notebook produced an old article from The English Garden magazine about an ancient English estate called Hodsock Priory in Notinghamshire. The Priory, in addition to having the requisite moats and towers, is home to a five-acre garden full of snowdrops. The article featured a scrumptious close-up of the S. Arnott cultivar (Galanthus S. Arnott), one of the 80 different types that bloom annually at the Priory. Other photos show huge clumps of snowdrops mingling with a heady assortment of hellebores, crocuses, iris and aconite in a woods full of birch trees. Needless to say, Hodsock Priory, a former religious structure that once played host to Henry VIII, has a full-time gardener.</p>
        <p>Snowdrops are also important enough to merit their own chapter in E. A. Bowles's 1914 book, ''My Garden in Spring.'' Bowles, an independently wealthy English gentleman gardener, was so fascinated by Galanthus that he even devoted considerable space to a detailed description of the dissection of a typical snowdrop bulb.</p>
        <p>Bowles was also a consummate collector. He bought ''a few hundred'' snowdrops every year in the era before World War I, establishing more and more Galanthus colonies on his property. It also appears that  he accepted gifts of bulbs from fellow connoisseurs and was not above pleading with other gardeners who were less forthcoming.</p>
        <p>Many of the cultivars described in the English Garden article and the Bowles book sound virtually indistinguishable from one another unless you get down on your hands and knees and peer at them intently. I am not usually inclined to do that in the muddy season, so I think that there are probably a number of Galanthus cultivars that I can live without.</p>
        <p>Now that my common snowdrops (G. nivalis) are finally up, however, it might be interesting to complement them with a few clumps of G. lutescens, a snowdrop with yellow (instead of green) markings. Bowles also mentions a double yellow form (G. flavescens), that would make my heart sing. Somewhere, probably in England, there are distinctive green-marked double varieties, among them Lady Beatrix Stanley. If I could locate Lady Beatrix, she would also find a home in my beds.</p>
        <p>Last fall I planted quite a few bulbs of G. nivalis Flore Pleno, a lovely double. Unfortunately they were either eaten or tossed into the street by the neighborhood squirrels.  Late next summer when the catalogs come, I can easily order hundreds more to replace them. I may also be tempted to indulge in G. Sam Arnott of Hodsock Priory fame), a scented variety, or perhaps G. caucasicus, a gray-leafed specimen. For something a bit bigger, there is the Giant Snowdrop (G. elwesii). It isn't really giant, but the blooms are a bit bigger than those of G. nivalis, and they tend to appear. Lady Beatrix, unfortunately, doesn't seem to be available in this country.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, I don't have to wait until fall to increase my existing supplies; I can go right out and divide the clumps. Unlike hostas and ornamental grasses, dividing Galanthus is as easy as digging up a clump and separating it into pieces with your fingers.</p>
        <p>The gardening books advise doing this while they are blooming, but I usually wait until after the blooms have started to fade. This strategy works as long as you don't get distracted by cleaning the gutters or filing income-tax returns. If you hold out too long, the clumps disappear completely, and do not return until late winter or early spring next year.</p>
        <p>I started with one small clump of snowdrops nine years ago. I made divisions every year, and brought several with me two years ago when I moved. If I keep dividing my clumps, perhaps someday, when I am elsewhere, this place will be dappled with spring snowdrops like a venerable English garden.</p>
        <p>G. nivalis bulbs are available in the fall from local nurseries and garden centers. A wide variety of Galanthus species and cultivars are available from:</p>
        <p>Brent and Becky's Bulbs, 7463 Heath Trail, Gloucester, Va. 23061, (877) 661-2852; free catalog; www.brentandbeckysbulbs.com</p>
        <p>John Scheepers Inc., 23 Tulip Drive, Bantam, Conn. 06750, (860) 567-0838; free catalog; www. johnscheepers.com</p>
        <p>Old House Gardens, 536 W. Third Street, Ann Arbor, Mich. 48103, (734) 995-1486; catalog $2; www. oldhousegardens.com</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
