<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>De La Hoya Hits Town With a Title in Mind</title>
    <meta content="07BOXI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DB1E3DF934A35753C1A961958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>De La Hoya Hits Town With a Title in Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boxing notebook (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oscar De La Hoya, the World Boxing Council welterweight champion, brought his road show east yesterday to talk about his championship bout against Wilfred Rivera at the Atlantic City Convention Center on Dec. 6.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya has not fought in the East since he defeated James Leija at Madison Square Garden two years ago. Since then, De La Hoya has won a welterweight championship and has increased his appeal as one of the top draws in professional boxing. He will spend three to four weeks training in the Poconos at Caesars Resort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oscar De La Hoya, the World Boxing Council welterweight champion, brought his road show east yesterday to talk about his championship bout against Wilfred Rivera at the Atlantic City Convention Center on Dec. 6.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya has not fought in the East since he defeated James Leija at Madison Square Garden two years ago. Since then, De La Hoya has won a welterweight championship and has increased his appeal as one of the top draws in professional boxing. He will spend three to four weeks training in the Poconos at Caesars Resort.</p>
        <p>Bob Arum, the president of Top Rank and De La Hoya's promoter, said the 24-year-old boxer will produce more than $100 million in revenues on pay-per-view for the four bouts he has had this year. Arum said the 850,000 buys for De La Hoya's bout against Pernell Whitaker last April was a record for a non-heavyweight title bout.</p>
        <p>Before De La Hoya can step into the ring against Rivera, who pushed Whitaker to the limit in two controversial losses, he has a date in court. But De La Hoya will not be a defendant or a plaintiff. Instead, he will be a juror in Superior Court in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''They were insistent that I be a juror,'' De La Hoya said.</p>
        <p>De La Hoya is not underestimating Rivera. Many people said they believed Rivera had defeated Whitaker in the first bout between the two on April 12, 1996, even though Whitaker won a unanimous decision. Whitaker also won a unanimous decision in their second fight, last September.</p>
        <p>Of De La Hoya, Rivera said: ''He has one head, two arms and two legs. I have the same thing. I will prepare for this fight like I did the two Whitaker fights.''</p>
        <p>Emanuel Steward, De La Hoya's trainer, said this could be De La Hoya's toughest fight to date, because unlike many of his opponents, Rivera does not want simply to survive.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time that I've seen a guy who's coming in to beat him,'' Steward said of Rivera. ''I've seen enough of him to know that he's a very strong person. I know he can fight. And this might be one of the few times that Oscar won't have the crowd support. Oscar is used to fighting in the West where there are a lot of Mexican Americans. This is the East Coast and it's different.''</p>
        <p>On the undercard, Raul Marquez, the International Boxing Federation junior middlewieght champion, will meet Keith Mullings of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Stricter Exam for Golota</p>
        <p>Larry Hazzard, the New Jersey boxing commissioner, said he was not going to order an investigation into the circumstances of Andrew Golota's collapse after his first-round loss to Lennox Lewis in their World Boxing Council heavyweight championship bout at the Atlantic City Convention Center on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>But Hazzard said Golota would be required to take a more rigorous medical test before he would be allowed to fight in the state again.</p>
        <p>''He may have some medical problems beyond what will show up on the standard medical test,'' Hazzard said.</p>
        <p>About 20 minutes after the referee stopped the fight, Golota collapsed in his dressing room and appeared to have a seizure. According to the doctor who attended to him, Golota stopped breathing and had no pulse for 35 seconds and had to be revived by c.p.r. before he was taken to Atlantic City Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Golota was kept overnight and underwent a CAT scan, which was negative, according to Main Events, his promoter. He was released from the hospital Sunday and returned home to Chicago.</p>
        <p>Saturday Night at the Apollo</p>
        <p>The Apollo Theater in Harlem will be the site for a heavyweight bout between Lou Savarese (36-1) and David Izonritei (19-2) on Nov. 1 as part of HBO's Boxing After Dark series. The last time Savarese was on HBO, he gave George Foreman a rough time. On the undercard is another heavyweight bout between Hasin Rahman (23-0) and Obed Sullivan (28-1-1). Outside of some exhibitions by Joe Louis and Jack Johnson, it is believed to be the first time that a professional boxing match has been held at the Apollo.</p>
        <p>BOXING: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
