<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mahler Songs, Miniaturized but Unmistakably His</title>
    <meta content="07LUKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orchestra of St Luke's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herreweghe, Philippe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D8113DF934A35753C1A961958260" item-length="553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mahler Songs, Miniaturized but Unmistakably His</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philippe Herreweghe conducts Orchestra of St Luke's at Metropolitan Museum of Art; photo; Paul Griffiths review (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The main work on the program for Friday's concert at the Metropolitan Museum was a version of a version of Mahler's ''Song of the Earth.'' Mahler intended that piece for two singers declaiming heroically over a large orchestra; Schoenberg had the notion of reducing the orchestra to a chamber group of around 15 players, in the way he liked to do in order to make big scores performable by the private concert organization he ran for a few years after World War II;  Rainer Riehn, in the 1980's, eventually carried through Schoenberg's project.</p>
        <p>What was being heard on Friday, then, was a long way from the original. But distance can in some cases bring you back around the circle to closeness. So it was when Mahler wrote ''The Song of the Earth.'' He found his words in Chinese poetry, but though this encouraged him to give a certain Chinese tang to the music, the singing persona is still very much as it was in ''Songs of a Wayfarer,'' which he composed at the beginning of his career to his own words. Schoenberg's miniaturization of that work, completed at the time, was appropriately included in the concert as a prelude to ''The Song of the Earth.'' Whether the hand writing the verse was Austrian or Chinese, the voice is the same, alternately affirmative and alienated, gregarious and solitary, but always, always highly subjective.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The main work on the program for Friday's concert at the Metropolitan Museum was a version of a version of Mahler's ''Song of the Earth.'' Mahler intended that piece for two singers declaiming heroically over a large orchestra; Schoenberg had the notion of reducing the orchestra to a chamber group of around 15 players, in the way he liked to do in order to make big scores performable by the private concert organization he ran for a few years after World War II;  Rainer Riehn, in the 1980's, eventually carried through Schoenberg's project.</p>
        <p>What was being heard on Friday, then, was a long way from the original. But distance can in some cases bring you back around the circle to closeness. So it was when Mahler wrote ''The Song of the Earth.'' He found his words in Chinese poetry, but though this encouraged him to give a certain Chinese tang to the music, the singing persona is still very much as it was in ''Songs of a Wayfarer,'' which he composed at the beginning of his career to his own words. Schoenberg's miniaturization of that work, completed at the time, was appropriately included in the concert as a prelude to ''The Song of the Earth.'' Whether the hand writing the verse was Austrian or Chinese, the voice is the same, alternately affirmative and alienated, gregarious and solitary, but always, always highly subjective.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Schoenberg's rescorings do not change -- except perhaps to intensify -- what is most Mahlerian in Mahler: the search for home (represented in the Schoenberg versions by the idealized domesticity of chamber music), the converse willingness to range through styles, textures or colors, and certainly the omnipresent subjectivity. This aspect is brought forward in ''The Song of the Earth'' because there is now no need for the singers to fight the accompaniment, so that the music is open to more lyrical and intimate kinds of projection.</p>
        <p>The advantages were proved here in the performances of the two soloists, Annette Markert and Thomas Young. Ms. Markert has a full contralto richness, and once she had sung herself in, she was fluid as well as precise, and could reach with undiminished power into the bottom register. She sang with authority, and with dignity, and so did Mr. Young. He was no more inclined to relish the fun of his drinking songs than she was to reach for weepiness in her long adieu. His excellence was in pure singing -- in a voice so hot and bright it seemed to scorch you.</p>
        <p>William Sharp, who sang the earlier cycle, hit bad luck, and there were some misfortunes, too, in the accompaniments to both works, played by members of the Orchestra of St. Luke's. Philippe Herreweghe, conducting, encouraged the musicians to enjoy their opportunities as soloists to put a personal light on the musical images, and thereby to make these scores exceedingly Schoenbergian as well as deeply Mahlerian. But this cascading, variegated music (Schoenbergian and Mahlerian at once, in that respect) could have done with an extra rehearsal.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
