<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Eyes Are on Fort Lee</title>
    <meta content="23CNBC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cnbc (Cable Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kernen, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haines, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DE1E31F930A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Eyes Are on Fort Lee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>FORT LEE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey-based CNBC cable television network is becoming epicenter of world of financial news, turning anchor Mark Haines and reporter Joe Kernen household names; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ralph Larsen could have been almost anywhere on Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>Cloud Nine would have been one good place. Or maybe teeing off at Baltusrol Golf Club in Springfield, where he is a member.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ralph Larsen could have been almost anywhere on Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>Cloud Nine would have been one good place. Or maybe teeing off at Baltusrol Golf Club in Springfield, where he is a member.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larsen is the chief executive of Johnson &amp; Johnson in New Brunswick, and his company, the subject of a glowing cover story in the latest issue of Barron's, reported outstanding quarterly earnings that morning. Its stock was headed up four points in the first hour of trading.</p>
        <p>But where Mr. Larsen chose to be was in a rather undistinguished office building on Fletcher Avenue here, since that is where what happens in business is really happening these days. On the sixth floor -- just north of the KFC and across the street from the Red Oak Diner -- is CNBC, the most popular financial news network in the world.</p>
        <p>After getting made up, Mr. Larsen would have a few minutes on the air with Ted David, the CNBC anchor of ''Market Watch,'' telling his compadres and competitors alike how wonderful things are at Johnson &amp; Johnson.</p>
        <p>''I'm getting more comfortable at this,'' Mr. Larsen said about his time on CNBC. ''You have to. This is important for us.''</p>
        <p>More and more, New Jersey-based CNBC is becoming the epicenter of the world of financial news. On Friday, April 14, when the Dow Jones industrial average nosedived 618 points, the Nielsen company counted more than a million viewers tuned to the network from 4:15 to 4:30 p.m., just after trading closed on the stock market.</p>
        <p>''Nielsen doesn't count bars and trading floors and offices, so you've got to figure that could be up by a factor of three,'' said Joe Kernen, a CNBC stock market reporter, known for his ''Winners and Losers'' segments. ''We are essential news for anyone who wants to know what happens on Wall Street.''</p>
        <p>And CNBC is not NBC's only hand in New Jersey. Its sister cable news network, MSNBC, is situated farther south, in Secaucus. The network's presence, if only out of convenience, opens for the nation a window on New Jersey.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, for example, Ben &amp; Jerry's was celebrating its anniversary by giving out ice cream cones. The company was also announcing its quarterly earnings -- not as robust as expected -- so CNBC's afternoon producer, Andy Hoffman, sent a crew to Ben &amp; Jerry's on Palisades Avenue in downtown  Englewood to illustrate the story.</p>
        <p>''We could have done it anywhere, but why not here in New Jersey,'' said Mr. Hoffman. ''When Kohl's was expanding, we went to a Kohl's on Route 4. It was a legitimate business story, and we could illustrate it close by. And we're always mentioning Fort Lee on the network.''</p>
        <p>Since merging with the Financial News Network in 1991, CNBC -- a sister cable network of NBC, which is owned by General Electric -- its viewership has increased tenfold -- to an average 323,000 households ecah business day, in some measure due to Wall Street's continuing bull market.</p>
        <p>''The long good times for stocks means more people own them, which means more people care about watching us,'' said Mr. Kernen. ''I've been on the tarmac at the airport and some baggage guys said, 'Hey, say something good about Continental so the stock goes up.' ''</p>
        <p>Little wonder that some of those formerly faceless financial reporters who regularly roam the highways and mini-malls of North Jersey have had cases of mini-stardom. Take Mr. Kernen, who has been profiled by several national magazines. And Ron Insana, the anchor on the program ''Street Signs,'' appears regularly on many NBC news programs as well as the nationally syndicated ''Imus in the Morning'' radio show -- which is also broadcast on MSNBC.</p>
        <p>Another of CNBC's market reporters, Maria Bartiromo, has even been Regis Philbin's guest co-host on ABC's ''Live with Regis and Kathie Lee.''</p>
        <p>But the soul of CBNC may be the three wise guys who appear on ''Squawk Box'' from 7 to 10 a.m. -- which Mr. Kernen affectionately calls ''our pre-game show.'' Mr. Kernen and his stock-reporting sidekick, David Faber, banter while reporting  the mornings business news with the program's anchor, Mark Haines.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't be here and be boring about business news,'' said Mr. Haines, who was a local news anchor in New York and Philadelphia before attending law school at the University of Pennsylvania and then coming to CNBC. ''We have to inject a little fun into it. About five years ago, things weren't going all that well in the morning, so management said, 'O.K., try it your way.' It gives us a healthy perspective.''</p>
        <p>The group has popularized the Alan Greenspan Briefcase Index, which has been uncanny in predicting the moves by the Federal Reserve Open Market Committee to raise and lower interest rates. Alerted by a viewer, Mr. Haines -- a Plainfield native who now lives in Monmouth County -- researched tapes and noted that when Mr. Greenspan, the head of the Federal Reserve, carried a fat briefcase to the meetings, interest rates rose; a thin briefcase indicated lower rates.</p>
        <p>For a time, when Mr. Faber, called ''The Brain'' by his co-anchors, reported on Priceline.com, the hotel and airline Internet company whose advertisements feature William Shatner, the ''Star Trek'' theme would play.</p>
        <p>More often than not, however, Mr. Kernen and the rest are deadly serious about getting their information right.</p>
        <p>And ''Squawk Box'' viewers, particularly day traders, can hang on Mr. Kernen's every word.</p>
        <p>''I may do a tease going into a commercial like, say, 'There's a biotech stock with some interesting results,' '' he said. 'By the time we come back, they've figured out what I was previewing and the stock could be up or down three points. It's daunting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kernen, an eight-handicap golfer at Baltusrol and a former stockbroker,said: ''I'm an unabashed capitalist. I like bull markets and I'm not fond of bear markets. A strong economy is good for everyone. A day like last Friday, well, I don't like those days, but I guess they keep people watching.'</p>
        <p>A resident of Englewood, Mr. Kernen added, ''One day we may even be able to get Faber over here from that Sodom, New York.''</p>
        <p>And like a real Jersey guy, he then drove across Fletcher Avenue for lunch at the Linwood Plaza strip mall.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
