<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Club Sues Hawaii On Tourism Promotion</title>
    <meta content="23REP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hawaii Tourism Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D61431F930A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Club Sues Hawaii On Tourism Promotion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Club has sued Hawaii Tourism Authority in Hawaii Supreme Court; suit, filed Jan 11, seeks to force state agency to perform statewide environmental assessment, which it claims is required by law, before allocating $114 million to Hawaii Visitors and Convention Bureau for marketing and promotion; if suit is upheld, it could have major implications for Hawaii, where tourism is major industry (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a move that shocked the Hawaii tourist industry and caused jitters among tourist officials on the mainland, the Sierra Club has sued the Hawaii Tourism Authority in the Hawaii Supreme Court. The suit, filed Jan. 11, seeks to force the state agency to perform a statewide environmental assessment, which it claims is required by law, before allocating $114 million to the Hawaii Visitors and Convention Bureau for marketing and promotion.</p>
        <p>If the suit is upheld, it could have major implications for Hawaii, where tourism is the major industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a move that shocked the Hawaii tourist industry and caused jitters among tourist officials on the mainland, the Sierra Club has sued the Hawaii Tourism Authority in the Hawaii Supreme Court. The suit, filed Jan. 11, seeks to force the state agency to perform a statewide environmental assessment, which it claims is required by law, before allocating $114 million to the Hawaii Visitors and Convention Bureau for marketing and promotion.</p>
        <p>If the suit is upheld, it could have major implications for Hawaii, where tourism is the major industry.</p>
        <p>''Seven million tourists descend on Hawaii each year, drinking our water, using our electricity, generating sewage and garbage and filling our beaches,'' said Jeff Mikulina, the director of the Sierra Club's Hawaii chapter. ''An environmental assessment would tell us whether Hawaii's physical and natural infrastructure can handle more tourists.''</p>
        <p>Though Sierra Club officials said they were not contemplating other such suits, tourism officials elsewhere are worried. ''If the State of Hawaii loses this lawsuit,'' said Lt. Gov. Lorraine Hunt of Nevada, the chairwoman of that state's tourism commission, ''it could set a precedent for blocking other states, such as Nevada, as well as county and local entities from promoting tourism.''</p>
        <p>John Hunt, professor emeritus of resource recreation and tourism at the University of Idaho, said he would have preferred another way of calling attention to the need for an environmental assessment. But, he added, the suit ''may make all of us pay more attention to certain aspects of tourism that can have a negative impact on the environment.''</p>
        <p>In its petition to the court, the Sierra Club said that before government agencies in Hawaii spend state funds, they are required to undertake an environmental assessment.</p>
        <p>But Robert Fishman, the tourism authority's chief executive, called the suit ''a patently ridiculous and inappropriate interpretation'' of the law. The environmental assessment process, he said, applies to land use, construction and excavation.</p>
        <p>A bill in the State Legislature would exempt tourism from having to comply with the law requiring environmental assessment, a procedure that could lead to a full-fledged environmental impact study.</p>
        <p>Differences about the law and the lawsuit extend even to the two largest newspapers in the state. An editorial in The Honolulu Star-Bulletin was headlined ''Sierra Club's Bid to Wreck Tourism'' while The Honolulu Advertiser said that ''the Sierra Club petition raises important and crucial points.''</p>
        <p>In addition, a coalition comprising the 13-member Western States Tourism Policy Council, along with such organizations as the Travel Industry Association of America, the American Hotel and Motel Association, the National Tour Association, the American Bus Association and the National Council of State Tourism Directors, sought to file a brief on behalf of the tourism authority, but it was rejected without explanation. A similar petition by the Hawaii Visitors and Convention Bureau was also rejected.</p>
        <p>John Myrdal, the Honolulu lawyer who represented the coalition, said its members joined the suit because ''they were concerned that if it was upheld, states' tourism efforts could get bogged down.''</p>
        <p>The national Sierra Club itself sponsors tours to Hawaii, as part of its 99-year-old Outings Program. Of its 350 worldwide tours last year, Molly Neal, a Sierra Club spokeswoman, said 7 were to Hawaii, with a total of 92 people. This year it will sponsor nine tours to Hawaii.</p>
        <p>Asked if there isn't a certain irony in the Sierra Club's promoting such tours while its Hawaii chapter's lawsuit could result in curbing tourism, Mr. Mikulina replied, ''There's no comparison between 92 campers a year and 7 million tourists.''</p>
        <p>The tourism authority plan, unveiled last summer, proposes to entice visitors to stay longer by encouraging more events and activities, Mr. Fishman said. It puts greater emphasis on eco-tourism and hiking and other outdoor experiences.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club suit contends that the tourism authority's plan would increase visitors by about 15 percent by 2005. It also pointed to an independent study that found that a $10 million emergency advertising campaign in 1997 attracted more than 800,000 additional visitors over a two-year period -- almost 500,000 from the mainland, the remainder from Japan.</p>
        <p>Because the $114 million earmarked by the tourism authority represents an elevenfold expenditure over the next three years, the Sierra Club argued, its implementation ''will result in like increases'' in visitors.</p>
        <p>Hawaii tourism has been in a prolonged slump, as a report issued last summer by the state's Department of Business, Economic Development and Tourism made painfully clear. The reason for the stagnation, the report said, was primarily the weak mainland economy in the first half of the 90's and the Asian economic slump later.</p>
        <p>But the report also pointed to the long-term maturing of Hawaii's tourism industry, including high prices in Hawaii, and aging hotels and overbuilding in Honolulu, especially in Waikiki.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikulina said that by trying to protect Hawaii's environment, the Sierra Club is acting in the best interest of the state.</p>
        <p>''If the Hawaii Tourism Authority agrees that the natural environment is what makes Hawaii so attractive, then they should have no problem with preparing an environmental assessment so that any adverse impact could be prevented or minimized,'' he said. ''And if the assessment finds there would be no harm to the environment under their plan, we would have no problem with it.''</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
