<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="23GUID$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1D71131F930A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1178" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Benefit Boxes</p>
        <p>Tickets to a cocktail party, buffet and an auction of specially prepared boxes, to be held at the Neuberger Museum of Art at Purchase College next Saturday, will cost $125. Buying one of the boxes could cost considerably more, because the highest bidders will have acquired boxes designed, built, reconfigured, painted, filled, or whatever, by one of 27 noted artists. It could be Sol LeWitt, Robert Goodnough, Will Barnet, William Wegman, Cleve Gray . . . or any of the remaining 22 fabricators.</p>
        <p>The evening will begin at 6:30 with drinks, the buffet and a silent auction of trips, restaurant dinners, tickets to cultural events and tours with art experts. Bidding will close at 9:15.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Benefit Boxes</p>
        <p>Tickets to a cocktail party, buffet and an auction of specially prepared boxes, to be held at the Neuberger Museum of Art at Purchase College next Saturday, will cost $125. Buying one of the boxes could cost considerably more, because the highest bidders will have acquired boxes designed, built, reconfigured, painted, filled, or whatever, by one of 27 noted artists. It could be Sol LeWitt, Robert Goodnough, Will Barnet, William Wegman, Cleve Gray . . . or any of the remaining 22 fabricators.</p>
        <p>The evening will begin at 6:30 with drinks, the buffet and a silent auction of trips, restaurant dinners, tickets to cultural events and tours with art experts. Bidding will close at 9:15.</p>
        <p>Auctioning of the boxes will be held from 8:30 to 10:30, presided over by Richard Francis of Christie's.</p>
        <p>Each of the artists received a box to work on from the museum. Most were used, many were altered, some were discarded in favor of the artist's own concept, but every box reflects its maker's style or medium. Red Grooms's whimsical cows, Carol Anthony's cigar boxes, Angiola Churchill's Italian garden of paper and plexiglas and Kenneth Snelson's loafers, preserved in silver like baby shoes are a few examples.</p>
        <p>Proceeds from the auctions will help pay for the museum's exhibitions and educational programs. The number to call for tickets is 251-6115.</p>
        <p>Casino Night for Hospital</p>
        <p>This is the season of fund-raisers, and one that started in 1970 is Mayfair, which contributes its proceeds to New York United Hospital Medical Center in Port Chester.</p>
        <p>Mayfair Casino 2000, scheduled  Friday at the Westchester Country Club in Rye, will begin with cocktails and hors d'oeuvres at 6:30 p.m., a buffet dinner and an open bar, which will operate throughout an evening of blackjack, craps, roulette, a money wheel and slot machines.</p>
        <p>Admission of $150 includes a stack of chips and play money. Winners will receive prizes of vacations and hotel packages, golf outings and restaurant dinners. Dancing to music provided by a disk jockey and a silent auction are also features of the event. For tickets, call 934-3415.</p>
        <p>Outdoor Spring Cleanup</p>
        <p>L.I.F.E., a 27-year-old, Lachmont-based nonprofit organization, whose initials stand for Local Fund for Environment, holds its Annual Beautification Day, or spring cleanup, next Saturday from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>Larchmont and the village and town of Mamaroneck will have some of their parks, conservation areas, school grounds, neighborhoods and beaches picked clean of debris by volunteers. Last year more than 1,000 people donated a minimum of 2 hours to the task.</p>
        <p>Some of the targets will be the Larchmont Reservoir, Sheldrake River Trails, Leatherstocking Trail, Hommocks and Premium River Conservations areas, Harbor Island and Flint Park.</p>
        <p>The numbers to call to volunteer are 833-3615 for the Larchmont cleanup, 833-2842 for the village of Mamaroneck and 698-6783 for the town of Mamaroneck.</p>
        <p>L.I.F.E, with offices at 685 Weaver Street, will also conduct a nature walk next Saturday at 10 a.m., and every other Saturday thereafter through June. Led by a naturalist, the leisurely hourlong strolls through a variety of conservation areas offer a better understanding of the region and its natural resources. There is no charge, and all ages are welcome. For a list of areas to be covered and the dates, call 834-1443.</p>
        <p>Two-Day Film Seminar</p>
        <p>Loved the book, hated the movie? Vice versa? Sarah Lawrence College in Yonkers will sponsor a seminar on the conversion of printed page to film next weekend. Three novelists and a filmmaker will discuss the shedding of blood, sweat and tears and the rays of sunshine that can brighten such collaborations.</p>
        <p>The two-day event includes screenings of the films under discussion in film viewing room PAC I. ''Mary Reilly'' by Valerie Martin will be shown on Friday at 8 p.m., with Julia Roberts and John Malkovich in leading roles, directed by Stephen Frears.</p>
        <p>''The Ice Storm'' by Rick Moody, with Kevin Klein and Sigourney Weaver, directed by Ang Lee, will be seen next Saturday at 10 a.m., and ''The Sweet Hereafter'' by Russell Banks, with Ian Holm and Bruce Greenwood, directed by Atom Egoyan, will run at 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>''Fiction Into Film,'' a discussion by the three authors and E. Paige Simpson, producer of ''Leaving Las Vegas,'' taken from the novel by John O'Brien, is scheduled at 4 p.m. in Reisinger Hall. Mary Morris, a member of the college's writing fac  ulty, will serve as moderator.</p>
        <p>Admission to the films and panel is free, but reservations must be made by calling 395-2371.</p>
        <p>Holocaust Memorial Day</p>
        <p>The Holocaust Memorial Day observance at Sarah Lawrence College will begin on Tuesday at 5:30 p.m. with segments of the 1997 Academy Award-winning film ''The Long Way Home'' in Titsworth Lecture Hall.</p>
        <p>The film clips will be followed by a panel discussion among three men, including Jay Sommer, survivor of a labor camp in his native Czechoslovakia, who emigrated to the United States and became a teacher at New Rochelle High School.</p>
        <p>In 1982 he was named National Teacher of the Year, and today he is a professor of Russian and Hebrew at Fairfield University.</p>
        <p>His fellow panelists are Jeremy Varon, associate fellow at the Center for Historical Analysis at Rutgers University; and Melvin Bukiet, a faculty member in literature at Sarah Lawrence. The moderator will be Deborah Hertz, a member of the college's history faculty and author of ''Jewish High Society in Old Regime Berlin,'' published in 1988 by Yale University Press.</p>
        <p>Admission is free. Call 395-2411 for more information.</p>
        <p>Parkway Foot Races</p>
        <p>One of the first 10K foot races of the season gets under way next Sunday at 10 a.m. on the Bronx River Parkway, beginning and ending at the the County Center in White Plains.</p>
        <p>The event is sponsored by the Bronx River Parkway Conservancy and the Westchester County Department of Parks, Recreation and Conservation. As is customary when races are held on the parkway, the event will close the road to all traffic, including cars, bicycles, skateboards and inline and roller skates.</p>
        <p>Competitors, who pay an entry fee of $15, will be divided into eight age categories, from under 14 to over 70, and medals will be presented to three men and three women who are the first finishers.</p>
        <p>Fun runs of a mile and one-half mile will step off at the same time. The fee is $5, and winners will receive special medals.</p>
        <p>The County Center is situated at the junction of the Bronx River Parkway, Central Park Avenue and Route 119.</p>
        <p>Those who wish to register should telephone either 242-6361 or 242-6352.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 21, 2000, Sunday  A brief article on April 23 about a spring cleanup in Larchmont and Mamaroneck misstated the full name and the age of the sponsoring organization, LIFE. The initials stand for Local Involvement for Environment, not Local Fund for Environment; the group is 29 years old, not 27.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A brief article on April 23 about a spring cleanup in Larchmont and Mamaroneck misstated the full name and the age of the sponsoring organization, LIFE. The initials stand for Local Involvement for Environment, not Local Fund for Environment; the group is 29 years old, not 27.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
