<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Istanbul Express</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SARAY (CLIFFSIDE, NJ, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHUMER, FRAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFD61F39F932A15754C0A960958260" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Istanbul Express</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRAN SCHUMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHUMER, FRAN</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFFSIDE PARK</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS part of Anderson Avenue is like the neighborhood where I grew up: no privacy and ample ethnic food. And these restaurants, unlike those in the "international food court" of your nearest mall, are run by the people who own them.</p>
        <p>"Turkish?" friends ask hesitantly when I tell them about this latest find. They're favorably disposed toward French, Italian and anything Asian, but uninterested in the cuisine of Turkey. They'll change their minds after an evening at Saray. This simple storefront, which presents the same jarring mix of rustic and elegant that perplexes Western visitors to the Near East, serves just what you crave in summer: sizzling barbecued chicken and lamb and abundantly cold, herb-speckled salads. The food is not only more flavorful than what the average French or Northern Italian restaurant in New Jersey serves, but it's also half the price.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS part of Anderson Avenue is like the neighborhood where I grew up: no privacy and ample ethnic food. And these restaurants, unlike those in the "international food court" of your nearest mall, are run by the people who own them.</p>
        <p>"Turkish?" friends ask hesitantly when I tell them about this latest find. They're favorably disposed toward French, Italian and anything Asian, but uninterested in the cuisine of Turkey. They'll change their minds after an evening at Saray. This simple storefront, which presents the same jarring mix of rustic and elegant that perplexes Western visitors to the Near East, serves just what you crave in summer: sizzling barbecued chicken and lamb and abundantly cold, herb-speckled salads. The food is not only more flavorful than what the average French or Northern Italian restaurant in New Jersey serves, but it's also half the price.</p>
        <p>One of my dining companions is a talented cook who has eaten widely and enthusiastically in Turkey. He says that the patlican tavasi, the traditional combination of eggplant, garlic and yogurt, is more deftly rendered in Istanbul  (the smaller Asian eggplants are hard to get in New Jersey) but that every other dish is comparable.</p>
        <p>I'd be surprised if the bread weren't chewier at Saray. Nurettin Kukul, an assistant in the kitchen, produces what looks like a cross between focaccia and  pita. The top of each pie-shaped wedge is charred and redolent of charcoal. Don't be surprised if all the bread vanishes before you order.</p>
        <p>Coban salatasi, or shepherd salad, is like Greek salad minus the feta cheese, but these confetti-sized pieces of cucumber, green pepper, onion, tomato and fragrant parsley are lighter and more refreshing. Saray doesn't serve wine, but  you may bring your own, preferably a good riesling or a light red wine. The 1994 Barco Reale di Carmignano Ambra has just the right acidity for these mildly spicy dishes.</p>
        <p>Not all of them sound as interesting as they are. Curd of yogurt with walnuts and garlic? You shouldn't avoid this oddity, which has the richness and heft of  sour cream, the buttery flavor of walnuts and the garlic needed to bind these disparate elements. Boursin has a similar flavor, but this variation is frothy and full of nuts.</p>
        <p>Tarama will make the bread disappear even faster. A smear of this dip, made with yogurt and salmon roe, has the salty, earthy flavor of cream cheese and smoked salmon, but its texture is more like mousse. What a decadent way to eat caviar.</p>
        <p>Some appetizers will remind you of those served in Greek restaurants -- hummus and baba gannouj, for example -- but others, like grape leaves, will seem like an entirely different species. Huseyin Yuksel, the chef and a co-owner, adds raisins and pine nuts to the rice he tucks into his grape leaves, which makes them sweet, crunchy and more interesting than the soggy diner kind.</p>
        <p>His falafel is equally novel. The interior is green, not the golden color of  chickpeas, because of the generous amounts of celery he adds to these small, crunchy patties. The results are so light you don't mind eating them without salad.</p>
        <p>"I've never had it when it hasn't been oily," my Turkish expert says about imam bayildi, the popular stuffed-eggplant appetizer. It's oily here as well, but you'll like its rich, fruity flavor of this version and the heat of the charred, blistering green peppers that surround it. And unlike the eggplant, the calamari are fried in a minimum of oil. You'd prefer to dip them in tomato sauce and save the tahini served with them for your falafel instead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yuksel's chicken kebabs are beautifully seasoned, the skinless, boneless  chicken of your dreams. And they're not even his best entree. His baby lamb chops, with their strong, smoky, almost primitive flavor, win that distinction.  However thin, they're succulent, and a bargain: more meat than you can finish, grilled tomatoes, green peppers and onions, and irresistibly buttery rice is only $14.50.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yuksel was chef when the restaurant, under different ownership, was Topkapi, and then as now, he demonstrates his ability even when he isn't grilling. His breast of chicken with mushrooms, tomatoes and cream has so many slivers of garlic that it looks like something amandine. Now try his delicate rolls of stuffed cabbage. What makes them so light and flavorful? More rice, peppers and onions than beef, and herbs that the chef won't identify (can you blame him?).</p>
        <p>He's also reluctant to reveal the ingredients he uses to season his doner casserole, a lusty mix of ground beef and lamb wedged, lasagne-style, between layers of yogurt and fried bread. It and the other meat dishes are livelier than his red snapper, which doesn't taste as fresh as the calamari, although you'll love the tangle of paper-thin onions and parsley marinating in their own garden-sweet juices beside it.</p>
        <p>For dessert, you can order the honey-sweetened dishes of Turkey or wander to  any of the local Italian cafes for espresso, cappuccino or chocolate mousse pie. Most people wave off the desserts at Saray, but the waiter brings them anyway -- and surprise! They're appealing even by Western standards. Taste the shimmering  pudding of sugar and heavy cream. Now what do you think of the cuisine of Turkey? Saray 520 Anderson Avenue, Cliffside Park (201) 313-9118</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD ATMOSPHERE Primitive but warm. SERVICE See "atmosphere." RECOMMENDED DISHES Shepherd salad; falafel; fried calamari; tarama; yogurt curd  with walnuts and garlic; stuffed cabbage; baby lamb chops; chicken in white wine with garlic; grilled and marinated chicken kebabs; doner with fried bread and yogurt; apricots filled with almonds and cream; milk pudding. PRICE RANGE Lunch and dinner: appetizers, $2.75 to $5.50; entrees, $8.25 to $14.50; desserts, $3. HOURS 11:30 A.M. to midnight daily. CREDIT CARDS All major. RESERVATIONS Recommended. WHEELCHAIR ACCESS Everything on one level. RATINGS Poor to Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
