<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old Fears and New Hope: Tale of Burned Black Church Goes Far BeyondArson</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARSON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DIXIANA (SC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST JOHN BAPTIST CHURCH (DIXIANA, SC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EMERSON, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EMERSON, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRENNER, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DD1639F932A15754C0A960958260" item-length="2041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old Fears and New Hope: Tale of Burned Black Church Goes Far BeyondArson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</byline>
      <dateline>DIXIANA, S.C.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When three white teen-agers were arrested in May and accused of burning down  an old slave church here, the authorities said the fire was the result of drinking and fireworks that went awry, not an act of racism.</p>
        <p>But the burning of the church, St. John Baptist, reveals a more complex tale  of racial intimidation reaching far back into the past. Its fate reflects the clash between the Old South and the New, between segregation and greater racial  harmony.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When three white teen-agers were arrested in May and accused of burning down  an old slave church here, the authorities said the fire was the result of drinking and fireworks that went awry, not an act of racism.</p>
        <p>But the burning of the church, St. John Baptist, reveals a more complex tale  of racial intimidation reaching far back into the past. Its fate reflects the clash between the Old South and the New, between segregation and greater racial  harmony.</p>
        <p>An estimated 67 black churches have been burned across the South since January 1995, and Federal investigators say there is no evidence of a single pattern in the arsons, much less a conspiracy. But like the fire at St. John, they speak of racial divisions out of the Old South.</p>
        <p>Attacks on St. John, which was established in 1765, have been going on for as long as anyone in this hamlet eight miles southeast of Columbia can remember. In recent years, as well as in an earlier generation, young troublemakers vandalized the church, enticed by a local myth that it was haunted.</p>
        <p>There were also older whites who telephoned death threats to people associated with the church, the authorities said, and who tried to run one church supporter off a road after smashing the skulls of her two dogs.</p>
        <p>Only a few miles away, Klansmen often staged rallies at the home of the Grand Dragon of the South Carolina chapter of the Christian Knights of the Ku Klux Klan.</p>
        <p>Yet there was another group of whites, including the president of the school  board, the prosecutor and a number of sheriff's deputies, who worked on their own time over the last decade to protect and restore the small church from previous vandalism before the final conflagration last August.</p>
        <p>Out of Old South, Reign of Vandalism</p>
        <p>Twelve years ago, the authorities said, a group of whites shot out the church's windows during Sunday services, then returned later and scrawled "KKK"  on the door, littered the pews with beer cans, chopped up the piano, smashed the crucifix, tore up all the Bibles and took the sacrament cloth out of the sanctuary and defecated on it.</p>
        <p>In the church's small graveyard, they unearthed the coffin of a deacon who had recently died and ran over it with a truck.</p>
        <p>In the dozen years between that orgy of mayhem and the fire on Aug. 15, more  than 200 people were arrested for vandalism at St. John, by the count of Sheriff James R. Metts of Lexington County.</p>
        <p>"All the attacks on the church are straight out of the Old South," said Ammie Murray, the president of the county school board who, in 1985, formed a biracial Save St. John Committee after the attacks. She was one of the people who received threatening phone calls and it was she who was endangered on the highway.</p>
        <p>"I could see the hatred in their red faces when they tried to ram me off the  road," said Mrs. Murray, who is white. She said she could hear the racism in their voices when they telephoned her, using a racial epithet to describe her for helping the church.</p>
        <p>Eventually, after more phone calls threatening her two young grandchildren unless she stayed away from the church, Mrs. Murray moved from her rural home into a suburb closer to Columbia. There, someone fired shots through the door of her new house.</p>
        <p>Hope in Mixed Faces Of the New South</p>
        <p>But at the same time, Mrs. Murray said, about 60 people she described as representative of the New South drove out on Saturdays to clean and restore the  church.</p>
        <p>"They were people you'd never expect to see working together," Mrs. Murray said, "half white and half black, Democrats and Republicans."</p>
        <p>One man had Confederate stickers on his hat, Mrs. Murray said.</p>
        <p>"Nobody said anything to him about them," she said, "but then one day I noticed they were gone."</p>
        <p>Jerry Bellune, the editor of the local newspaper, The Lexington Chronicle, said he thought the work on the church "was a story of hope for race relations in the South."</p>
        <p>As people labored at St. John together, Mr. Bellune said, they discovered that "it doesn't matter who your daddy was, or where he came from."</p>
        <p>"That is an enormous change for the South," Mr. Bellune said.</p>
        <p>Some nights, especially on Halloween, sheriff's deputies volunteered to stake out the church to protect it.</p>
        <p>One night about five years ago, as Mrs. Murray and some officers waited inside the church, a group of 30 whites smashed open the front door. As the leader of the group walked in, a deputy pulled out his pistol and put it against the man's head.</p>
        <p>"Ladies and gentlemen, come on in," Mrs. Murray recalled the officer intoning. "Join us in a prayer."</p>
        <p>The leader proved to be the manager of a nearby steak house.</p>
        <p>What Mrs. Murray and others find incomprehensible is how, after so much effort to protect St. John, it was still burned to the ground, leaving only the  white cinder-block entrance way.</p>
        <p>Part of the explanation is that the church is in a remote site, hidden by corn fields and pine forests. Blacks, from the time of slavery, deliberately built their churches in isolated places, away from the prying eyes of whites, and to be near the fields where they labored.</p>
        <p>But today the church's remote site and the fields are part of the past. Lexington County is now the most affluent county in South Carolina, dotted with  suburbs formed by whites fleeing school integration in Columbia.</p>
        <p>It is also the most Republican county in South Carolina, the most Republican  state in the South, said Mr. Bellune, the editor.</p>
        <p>Tom Turnipseed, a civil rights lawyer in Columbia who has filed suit against  two Klansmen in the burning of two other black churches in South Carolina last year, said the flames of racism were fanned by politicians' attacks on affirmative action and welfare and calls for getting tough on crime. They are a  disguised attack on blacks, he said.</p>
        <p>"When you've got people who don't have much and aren't very well educated, you can scapegoat blacks," said Mr. Turnipseed, who admits to being "a reformed  racist" after having once been national campaign manager for former Gov. George  Wallace of Alabama.</p>
        <p>He said he had been brought up to revere his grandfather, a member of the Klan who had killed a young black boy. Mr. Turnipseed even named his son Jefferson Davis Turnipseed. Mother of Accused Disavows Racism</p>
        <p>But it is a sign of the changes in South Carolina's racial atmosphere that even the mother of two of the young men charged in the St. John arson, Mary Emerson, insists that her boys are not racists.</p>
        <p>Her sons, Roger, 19, and Robert, 17, along with James Brenner, 17, were arrested on May 11 and charged with arson and burglary.</p>
        <p>"The thing that really upsets Roger and Bobbie is being called racists," said Mrs. Emerson, who lives with them in a small, ramshackle house at the end of a sandy track in the woods. Most of their neighbors are black, Mrs. Emerson pointed out, as are many of her sons' friends, and they often spend nights at one another's homes. "In our family," Mrs. Emerson said, "skin color doesn't make no difference."</p>
        <p>The Emersons are free on bonds of $10,000 each while Mr. Brenner remains in jail, unable to raise his $20,000 bond. The charges they face carry a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison. No trial date has been set.</p>
        <p>In interviews, both Mrs. Emerson and Michael Ellisor, the lawyer for Mr. Brenner, recalled that they had been fascinated by the tales of the haunted St.  John church and had gone there themselves with friends as teen-agers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellisor said that Mr. Brenner "comes from a troubled home" and that he had been expelled from ninth grade three years in a row for discipline problems, resulting in permanent expulsion.</p>
        <p>Robert Emerson and Mr. Brenner were close friends, Mrs. Emerson acknowledged, adding, "Brenner was a bad influence on Bobbie."</p>
        <p>Mr. Brenner made a statement admitting he was at the church when it caught fire, claiming that it had been the result of his accidentally dropping a lighted cigarette.</p>
        <p>But the prosecutor, Donnie Myers, said there was evidence that the teen-agers had been drinking and using fireworks at the church. He said that had led to the fire.</p>
        <p>Shelling Peas, Talking Racism</p>
        <p>Sheriff Metts said there was no evidence linking the teen-agers to the Klan,  and Horace King, the Grand Dragon of the South Carolina chapter of the Klan, agreed.</p>
        <p>A rail thin, 63-year-old man with a pinched face and white hair, Mr. King lives on a sandy hillside with Confederate flags and a large cross in his front  yard, along with a garden ornament in the shape of a hooded, green-robed Klansman. The green robe is the mark of his high office, and Mr. King's own satin robe was hanging on a laundry line. His home had recently been the site of a rally of Klan members from North Carolina and South Carolina.</p>
        <p>The rally was to raise money for the two Klan members charged in the burning  of the two other South Carolina churches. About 50 members and sympathizers attended the rally. The largest announced was donation $50.</p>
        <p>Sheriff Metts, who infiltrated Klan rallies in the 1960's as an undercover officer, said the small turnout showed that the Klan had lost its popular appeal and that Mr. King had become a relic. "They used to have 600 or 700 Klansmen in  their robes and they would march right through town," Sheriff Metts said, "but now if they try to parade, they get booed."</p>
        <p>Mr. King is unfazed. "I'm proud of standing up for the white race," he said,  sitting in a chair shelling peas from his garden, "and I don't mind people knowing what I am. I never told anybody to burn a church. One day I will meet God, and I don't want that on my head."</p>
        <p>The problem at St. John, Mr. King said, is that teen-agers are out of control because the country has degenerated with race mixing.</p>
        <p>"Back when I was coming up, teachers kept a switch for correcting kids," Mr.  King said, "but now with integration, teachers can't whip kids no more. If a white teacher whipped a black student, there would be all kinds of trouble."</p>
        <p>Declining Members, Growing Support</p>
        <p>Over the years, as some members of St. John Church have moved north and others have been scared away, the membership has shrunk to about 20 from 100, said Willie Simmons, the senior deacon.</p>
        <p>Since the fire, Mr. Simmons said, with the help of the biracial committee, a  third of the $150,000 needed to rebuild the church has been raised.  Mr. Simmons said that he was confident that the rest of the money would be raised.</p>
        <p>"The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away," Mr. Simmons remembered saying when he saw his church in ashes. "Blessed be the name of the Lord."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
