<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Culture Shock</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866334"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DC1639F932A15754C0A960958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Culture Shock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Venuti</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEREIRA DECLARES A Testimony. By Antonio Tabucchi. Translated by Patrick Creagh. 136 pp. New York: New Directions. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEREIRA DECLARES A Testimony. By Antonio Tabucchi. Translated by Patrick Creagh. 136 pp. New York: New Directions. $19.95.</p>
        <p>The received wisdom is that literature and special interests don't mix. The subtlety of literary form, the psychological complexity of character vanish at the touch of political ideology or the profit motive, replaced by blowhard polemic or romantic puff. Good writing triumphs over political correctness and commercial escapism, refining our taste, enabling us to discriminate among the exquisite shades of meaning in every classic work.</p>
        <p>Antonio Tabucchi's latest novel explodes this sort of thinking. Set in 1938 under the Portuguese dictator Antonio de Oliveira Salazar, it's a tale of political intrigue whose slant is strongly antifascist. In Italy it became an immediate best seller. And since that was in 1994, when fascism re-emerged in Italian politics and the right swept into office with Silvio Berlusconi's Forza  Italia movement, the book's left-wing ideology can't be divorced from its success. As Mr. Tabucchi later explained, "Those who didn't love the Italian political situation took it as a symbol of resistance from within."</p>
        <p>All the same, "Pereira Declares" is certainly a work in the high esthetic mode, a historical novel cast in delicately evocative prose and filled with witty references to the great figures of modern European literature. In it Italians could examine their political consciences through an artful image of another country's past. The novel is worth reading not simply because it is ingenious and moving, but because it links politics, commerce and good writing in a way that's rare in this country.</p>
        <p>As the curious title hints, the novel is presented as the testimony of one Pereira, the aging cultural editor of a Lisbon newspaper who at the climax prints an attack on the Salazar regime. Pereira's story relates the growth of his radicalism over a few increasingly frenetic weeks. Although he is employed by a conservative newspaper, his editing is more private than political, keyed to his fondness for French Catholic writers (Georges Bernanos, Francois Mauriac) and colored by his elegiac life as a childless widower with a bad heart. One day, while paging through a magazine, he is drawn to a philosophical rumination  on death written by Francesco Monteiro Rossi, a recent university graduate, whom he invites to contribute obituaries of famous writers.</p>
        <p>Pereira has been acceding to Government censorship. When Monteiro Rossi submits an impassioned eulogy of Federico Garcia Lorca in which the Spanish poet is "assassinated" by "his political opponents," the editor brands it unpublishable, reminding his young assistant that "there's a civil war raging in Spain, and the Portuguese authorities think along the same lines as General Francisco Franco."</p>
        <p>Yet events conspire to jolt Pereira out of his acquiescence. The police murder a socialist carter in the market. Monteiro Rossi -- whom Pereira affectionately imagines as the son he never had -- writes more unpublishable articles, scathing critiques of the protofascists F. T. Marinetti and Gabriele D'Annunzio and a paean to the Russian Communist poet Vladimir Mayakovsky. Then Monteiro Rossi goes underground with his fiancee, Marta, working to recruit Portuguese volunteers for the republican brigades in Spain. Pereira's poor health requires a brief stay in a clinic, where the attending physician explains to his patient the subversiveness of printing a patriotic story by Alphonse Daudet. Suddenly a favorite writer, Bernanos, publicly denounces Franco. By the  end Pereira can't avoid judging literature in ideological terms, so we aren't surprised when he dismisses the poet Rainer Maria Rilke as "that snobbish society-haunting dandy."</p>
        <p>What Pereira learns is the impossibility of separating culture from its social significance. Initially his approach to literature is purely a matter of  discerning taste acquired through experience. When Pereira's youthful friends challenge his convictions, he becomes aware that his approach doesn't just lack  critical detachment but actually transforms literary works into personal allegories. He chooses to translate a story by Balzac because, he says, "I read  it as autobiography." His interest in the Daudet piece starts off as sheer nostalgia, a tender memory of his wife. But when his editor in chief describes it as an anti-German "panegyric on France" that "caused a lot of offense in high places," Pereira realizes that the decisive political act can also take a literary form.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tabucchi attributed this novel's Italian success to his invention of "an  antihero, a common man in whom people can recognize themselves." And Pereira's testimony does say enough about Italian writing and politics to support analogies between Portugal in the 1930's and Italy past and present. Yet the popularity of the story was no doubt secured by the thriller genre. An author noted for his sophisticated narrative experiments, Mr. Tabucchi favors the interior monologue that is at once dense with suggestion and taut with suspense. "Pereira Declares" is his first foray into political history. The effect is dazzling. The reader is positioned in Pereira's consciousness, where events rapidly unfold in a haze of memory, dream and reflection that heightens the growing sense of danger. We don't completely identify with Pereira; a telling detail occasionally surfaces to question his motives or impulses. But he is so companionable, so simpatico, that we wish him well -- and want to see him resist the Salazarist repression.</p>
        <p>Patrick Creagh's translation is wonderfully suited to the conversational quality of the Italian. His English consists mostly of the standard dialect, but he strews it with slangy colloquialisms that make the writing eminently readable. He renders "quattro uomini dall'aria sinistra" (literally, "four men with a sinister air") as "four shady-looking characters," "un personaggio del regime" ("a figure in the regime") as "bigwig" and "senza pigiama" ("without pajamas") as "in his birthday suit." Yet, since he also mixes in some colorful British expressions ("Bolshie," "I'm in a pickle," "natter"), the translation overlays the Italian text with a distinctively English resonance, conjuring up writers who have dealt with similar issues, like Graham Greene, while at the same time highlighting the different politics that animates Mr. Tabucchi's novel.</p>
        <p>The pleasures to be had from "Pereira Declares" are rich and varied, but best of all it's very enjoyable -- even when you don't recognize all the public figures.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Venuti's latest book is "The Translator's Invisibility: A History of Translation."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lawrence Venuti's latest book is "The Translator's Invisibility: A History of Translation."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
