<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giant Flying Saucers! Better Run and Hide.</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FILM VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN JEFF GOLDBLUM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">INDEPENDENCE DAY (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0D61F39F932A15754C0A960958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giant Flying Saucers! Better Run and Hide.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Caryn James</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN JEFF GOLDBLUM;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE NIGHT AFTER "Independence Day" opened, an intensely serious talk-show host asked her guest, a NASA expert, whether we should worry about the movie coming true. What's that? Should we worry that creatures from outer space will arrive in 15-mile-wide Scooter Pies that emit deadly green rays, killing millions and generally ruining the weekend?</p>
        <p>A more astute question about fighting off aliens comes from the movie itself. Will Smith, as a hotshot Marine pilot, and Jeff Goldblum, as a computer whiz, have just concocted an elaborate scheme. Mr. Smith will fly a creaky alien spacecraft into the mother ship while Mr. Goldblum slips a computer virus into its system. After Mr. Goldblum maps out his scheme in exhaustive detail, the two partners have a friendly, confidential chat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE NIGHT AFTER "Independence Day" opened, an intensely serious talk-show host asked her guest, a NASA expert, whether we should worry about the movie coming true. What's that? Should we worry that creatures from outer space will arrive in 15-mile-wide Scooter Pies that emit deadly green rays, killing millions and generally ruining the weekend?</p>
        <p>A more astute question about fighting off aliens comes from the movie itself. Will Smith, as a hotshot Marine pilot, and Jeff Goldblum, as a computer whiz, have just concocted an elaborate scheme. Mr. Smith will fly a creaky alien spacecraft into the mother ship while Mr. Goldblum slips a computer virus into its system. After Mr. Goldblum maps out his scheme in exhaustive detail, the two partners have a friendly, confidential chat.</p>
        <p>Can you really fly that thing?" Mr. Goldblum wonders casually.</p>
        <p>Just as easygoing, Mr. Smith answers: Do you believe all that stuff you just  said?</p>
        <p>They know -- better than most talk-show hosts and news magazines, as it turns out -- that what they're doing is impossible and that they'll do it anyway. "Independence Day" doesn't offer post-modern winks at the audience. Instead, the film has a genial it's-only-a-movie attitude that sets it apart, quite emphatically, from other blockbuster action movies.</p>
        <p>Today's typical blockbuster is either an earnest Michael Crichton film or an  earnest Michael Crichton clone. "Jurassic Park" and "Twister," both based on Crichton stories, work overtime to offer realistic-sounding scientific premises for their fantasies. "Mission: Impossible" and the latest Arnold Schwarzenegger film, "Eraser," are based on new computer technology. No one in the audience is supposed to understand that technology; it's there to make the complicated action seem credible, too advanced for ordinary viewers.</p>
        <p>"Independence Day" is the anti-Crichton. An essential aspect of its appeal -- and its phenomenal success -- is that the film is a joyful relief from the bullying intensity of pseudo-scientific action. Its apocalyptic story of aliens  out to destroy the Earth may have a veneer of science, but the jargon about sound waves and computer viruses is merely a veneer, not a serious premise. The  film's fun comes from an outrageous scenario that as every review has noted, owes its life to B movies. The social relevance of "Independence Day" is that it scarcely has any.</p>
        <p>Something as vague as a film's sensibility is hard to pin down, of course, which is why "Independence Day" has gathered more than its share of knee-jerk, Crichtonesque responses. Time and Newsweek, in Siamese-twin cover stories, set the film in the context of the immense popularity of science fiction in movies,  television and books. Time talks about aliens as metaphors for America's enemies, and Newsweek even did a poll about how many Americans believe that U.F.O.'s are real.</p>
        <p>This trend toward science-fiction exists. "The X-Files," for example, taps into national paranoia, effectively hinting that clever aliens have sneaked into America and are hiding in plain sight. Whether you believe in aliens or simply in allegory, the show's realistic underpinning is crucial.</p>
        <p>But "Independence Day" bucks the trend. With its gargantuan invasion and wacky solution, it appeals more strongly to people who don't think alien ships are circling the White House looking for a parking place. That's why the film's  destroyed cities, millions of deaths, even a nuclear weapon fired for nothing (whoops!) don't sting emotionally, much less suggest a real threat. Although many people believe that life exists on other planets, this over-the-top movie is worlds away from that serious question.</p>
        <p>There's no better evidence of the way "Independence Day" flaunts its own escapism than a scene in which Mr. Smith and Mr. Goldblum are at the mercy of the aliens. What can they do? "Hide!" Mr. Goldblum yells, and they do. It's an old-fashioned movie line, and it works because "Independence Day" has lured viewers into its spirit of playful adventure. If a movie doesn't succeed on the  level of "Hide!," it doesn't matter how many special effects it has.</p>
        <p>Look at how a similar line fails in "Twister." When Bill Paxton and Helen Hunt, as the intrepid tornado chasers, are about to be sucked into yet another twister, Mr. Paxton yells, "Run!" Oh, sure, they'll outrun the tornado. It is the most ludicrous line in the film, because the script has relied on supposedly realistic jargon all along. In that context, "Run!" seems stupid rather than comically desperate.</p>
        <p>In the wake of "Twister," a spate of real tornado chasers turned up on television. They were nudged to agree that the film was realistic and at a certain point started squirming conspicuously. One reason "Twister" seems so empty and by-the-numbers is that it strains, and fails, to convince viewers of its realism. Jan De Bont's relentless action and special effects may have made "Twister" a box-office hit, but they couldn't overcome that fundamental problem.</p>
        <p>"Jurassic Park" worked better because Steven Spielberg directed it, and his sense of adventure took all the strain out of the premise. Lengthy and learned essays did appear, considering whether dinosaur DNA really could be preserved in amber for millions of years, then rejuvenated. The short answer was, "Of course  not, silly."</p>
        <p>Audiences for "Independence Day" instinctively know that "Of course not, silly" is the right answer to "Should we worry about this happening?" The NASA expert on television ducked the question. Maybe he thought it was too inane to answer. Of course, there's always the slim chance he knows something we don't.</p>
        <p>FILM VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
