<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Is Holding Talks on Lifting Its 3-Year Ban on Iraqi Oil Sales</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="632936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABINETS AND SUB-CABINETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBARGOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SURAT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZUBAIDI, MOHAMMED HAMZA AL-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN KHUDAYYIR, AHMED (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D9103CF935A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Is Holding Talks on Lifting Its 3-Year Ban on Iraqi Oil Sales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years after it imposed a stiff trade embargo against Iraq because of its invasion of Kuwait, the United Nations is seriously considering lifting its ban on Iraqi oil sales and allowing Baghdad to earn billions of dollars by selling unlimited quantities on world markets.</p>
        <p>An easing of the embargo, which diplomats say is still many months away, would come about if Iraq provided information about its efforts to build arms and agreed to let the United Nations monitor its military industries to insure it does not reacquire weapons. Baghdad must also demonstrate that it is willing to cooperate with monitoring, diplomats said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years after it imposed a stiff trade embargo against Iraq because of its invasion of Kuwait, the United Nations is seriously considering lifting its ban on Iraqi oil sales and allowing Baghdad to earn billions of dollars by selling unlimited quantities on world markets.</p>
        <p>An easing of the embargo, which diplomats say is still many months away, would come about if Iraq provided information about its efforts to build arms and agreed to let the United Nations monitor its military industries to insure it does not reacquire weapons. Baghdad must also demonstrate that it is willing to cooperate with monitoring, diplomats said.</p>
        <p>In a first step toward an agreement on lifting the oil embargo, a high-ranking team of Iraqi officials led by Gen. Amer Mohammed Rashid, the Director of Iraq's military industrialization corporation, is visiting New York for talks with Rolf Ekeus, the Swede who leads the special commission set up by the Security Council in 1991 to oversee the elimination of Iraq's weapons of mass destruction after the Persian Gulf war. Intense and Serious</p>
        <p>Officials described the talks, which began last week and are expected to end on Thursday, as intense and serious. The Iraqi Deputy Prime Minister, Tariq Aziz, has invited Mr. Ekeus to come to Baghdad at the end of September for a further round of discussions aimed at completing the agreement.</p>
        <p>While lifting the oil embargo would allow Iraq to sell oil freely again, the Security Council would still require Iraq's customers to turn over a third of their payments to the United Nations to compensate victims of the invasion of Kuwait and cover its own expenses in Iraq. The trade embargo would otherwise remain in force, meaning that foreign companies wishing to supply any goods other than food and medicine would still be required to seek permission from the Security Council committee overseeing enforcement.</p>
        <p>A resumption of Iraqi oil sales would be a boon to neighbors like Turkey and Jordan. Before the sanctions were imposed, both countries had a booming food trade with Iraq.  Pressure From Turkey</p>
        <p>The new Turkish Government of Prime Minister Tansu Ciller has recently initiated a campaign to persuade the Security Council to let Iraq resume oil exports through the pipeline that runs across Turkish territory to the port of Yumurtalik. At a meeting with Secretary of State Warren Christopher on Aug. 16, the Turkish Foreign Minister, Hikmet Cetin, urged that the sanctions be lifted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ekeus opened the way for the current talks by brokering an agreement in Baghdad with the Iraqi Government, ending the standoff over the special commission's move to install monitoring cameras to insure that Iraq does not build the long-range rockets it is banned from acquiring under Resolution 687, which set the terms for the cease-fire that ended the gulf war.</p>
        <p>Iraq agreed in July to accept the Security Council's plan for long-term monitoring of its military industries as set out in another Council measure, Resolution 715. Baghdad had previously refused to discuss long-term monitoring until the Council started to ease the trade embargo.</p>
        <p>"In these present talks we are trying to agree on the outline of a package setting out both sides' responsibilities," said Iraq's United Nations representative, Nizar Hamdoun.</p>
        <p>In persuading Iraq to reach the agreement in July, Mr. Ekeus pointed out that once the Security Council decided that Baghdad was in full compliance with the disarmament provisions and had accepted monitoring, Paragraph 22 would stipulate that the worldwide ban on buying Iraqi oil would "have no further force or effect."</p>
        <p>In subsequent talks with the Clinton Administration and the British, French and Russian Governments, diplomats say, Mr. Ekeus has secured their support for linking a lifting of the embargo on oil sales to Iraqi compliance with the disarmament and industrial monitoring requirements.</p>
        <p>"We will want to see a demonstrable track record of compliance first" with inspections of arms sites, a senior Clinton Administration official said.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>CABINET CHANGES IN IRAQ</p>
        <p>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Sept. 5 (Reuters) -- President Saddam Hussein removed Prime Minister Mohammed Hamza al-Zubaidi and eight other ministers from their posts today in a surprise shuffle of the Cabinet.</p>
        <p>The new Prime Minister, Ahmed Hussein Khudayyir, is a longtime confidant of Mr. Hussein who had served as Finance Minister since July 1991. In that post he nearly succeeded in cleansing the Iraqi money supply of bogus notes, but the strain of sweeping United Nations sanctions has prevented him from achieving his goal of strengthening the dinar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
