<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Search for Cause of Fatal Fire Goes Slowly</title>
    <meta content="08FIRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DF143AF93BA35755C0A96E958260" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Search for Cause of Fatal Fire Goes Slowly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fire marshals search remains of row of Brooklyn buildings for definitive clues to what caused five-alarm blaze that killed fire lieutenant and left fire captain severely burned and clinging to life; fire officials say privately that they suspect fire started in mattress; say extent of damage is complicating investigation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fire marshals spent yesterday slowly searching what was left of a row of Brooklyn buildings in search of definitive clues to what caused a five-alarm blaze that killed a fire lieutenant and left a fire captain severely burned and clinging to life, fire officials said.</p>
        <p>The injured captain, Scott LaPiedra, 40, of Staten Island, was in critical condition last night at Jacobi Medical Center in the Bronx with second- and third-degree burns over more than 70 percent of his body.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fire marshals spent yesterday slowly searching what was left of a row of Brooklyn buildings in search of definitive clues to what caused a five-alarm blaze that killed a fire lieutenant and left a fire captain severely burned and clinging to life, fire officials said.</p>
        <p>The injured captain, Scott LaPiedra, 40, of Staten Island, was in critical condition last night at Jacobi Medical Center in the Bronx with second- and third-degree burns over more than 70 percent of his body.</p>
        <p>''His wife, Addie, was just asking people to pray for him today,'' said Deputy Fire Commissioner Michael Regan. ''He's as strong as an ox.''</p>
        <p>Fire officials said scores of firefighters streamed through Jacobi Medical Center yesterday as Captain LaPiedra's family held vigil.</p>
        <p>''All of us in the department are praying for him,'' said Firefighter Elbert Washington, a Fire Department spokesman. ''There's an extreme danger of infection. It's a matter of time. We're hoping for improvement.''</p>
        <p>Investigators picked through the charred remains of the three-story, wood and brick city-owned apartment building at 2530 Atlantic Avenue in East New York, which burst into flames Friday night. No occupants of the building were hurt, but the blaze spread to three adjacent buildings and took more than 220 firefighters more than four hours to bring under control.</p>
        <p>Fire officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity said they suspect the fire started in a mattress in the apartment building about 8:20 P.M. But Firefighter Washington said yesterday that fire marshals had not announced a definitive cause of the blaze. The extent of the damage was complicating the investigation, he said.</p>
        <p>''You had three buildings that were destroyed,'' he said. ''Given the number of buildings that were involved, combined with the gathering of physical evidence, it's not unusual for it to take this long.''</p>
        <p>Fire officials said funeral services would be held Wednesday for Lieut. James W. Blackmore, 48, who died of a heart attack in the fire. In addition to Captain LaPiedra, five other firefighters injured in the blaze remained hospitalized with second- and third-degree burns and other injuries yesterday, fire officials said. None of their injuries was considered life threatening.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Blackmore, Captain LaPiedra and the other firefighters were injured when they rushed onto the second floor of the burning apartment building after a woman told them her elderly mother was trapped there. As the firefighters searched for the missing woman, the second floor collapsed, dropping them into a raging fire.</p>
        <p>Other firefighters dragged the injured men from the building. The missing woman, it was later discovered, had already escaped.</p>
        <p>The wake for Lieutenant Blackmore will be held today and tomorrow at the McCourt &amp; Trudden Funeral Home at 385 Main Street in Farmingdale, N.Y. His funeral will be held on Wednesday at 11 A.M. at St. Kilian Roman Catholic Church at 485 Conklin Street in Farmingdale.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
