<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awfully Serious Genre Gets a Little Playtime</title>
    <meta content="18MASL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/18/books/18MASL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1520403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schine, Cathleen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">She Is Me (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Schine, Cathleen</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">She Is Me (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4D6143AF93BA2575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awfully Serious Genre Gets a Little Playtime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Awfully Serious Genre Gets a Little Playtime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews book She Is Me by Cathleen Schine; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHE IS ME  By Cathleen Schine  262 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>The cover of Cathleen Schine's new novel shows the pastel-pretty likeness of an attractive woman. Her expression is alert and her age indeterminate. There is the interesting detail of an open book at her feet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this clever, idiosyncratic novel by Cathleen Schine, three generations of women feel twinges of Flaubertian discontent and alter their lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHE IS ME  By Cathleen Schine  262 pages. Little, Brown &amp; Company. $23.95.</p>
        <p>The cover of Cathleen Schine's new novel shows the pastel-pretty likeness of an attractive woman. Her expression is alert and her age indeterminate. There is the interesting detail of an open book at her feet.</p>
        <p>But this image makes ''She Is Me'' resemble the dozens of whiny, narcissistic chick-lit novels that come with similarly bright packaging. And here is its first delicious flash of wit: Ms. Schine's satirical starting-off point is the literary turf where chick-lit truly started. This author, who specializes in teasing tenderness and domestic wisdom out of her vastly enjoyable erudition, has gotten her gifted hooks into ''Madame Bovary.''</p>
        <p>The title is Flaubert's of course. But if ''Emma Bovary, c'est moi'' originated as his sentiment, it has long since achieved bumper-sticker universality. Even when characters in this book talk about going to see the film ''Thelma and Louise,'' they are aware of Flaubert's gift to all stories about restless married women. So perhaps it is not surprising when the book's main character, an academic named Elizabeth (also addressed here as ''Professor Smarty-Pants'') finds herself dragged into the Bovary orbit. A movie producer has talked her into dreaming up a latter-day Bovary adaptation.</p>
        <p>Dream she does: if you would like to know how it's possible to work Jet Ski injuries and Beverly Hills real estate into a story that began in rural France, watch how outrageously Elizabeth tarts it up. This adaptation process is even scarier to read about in the wake of a recent MTV television version of ''Wuthering Heights'' that more or less dropped the ''Wuthering.''</p>
        <p>So ''She Is Me'' would have the makings of a pop-cultural satire no matter what. ('' 'Madame Bovary,' '' the producer complains. ''A franchise it's not.'') But as its title underscores, a deeper transformation is also at work. At heart this is a novel in which three generations of women feel twinges of that Flaubertian discontent and wind up altering their own lives. That they are grandmother, mother and daughter (Elizabeth is the youngest), and that the shadow of death influences all of their decisions make this idiosyncratic book as haunting as it is clever.</p>
        <p>The family matriarch is Lotte, imperious and vain. (Ms. Schine somehow manages to make such attributes perversely adorable.) ''Hitler should have my pain,'' Lotte says about the illness that has begun to consume her. Though she is dauntless enough to be ordering a jacket from the Victoria's Secret catalog, Lotte is a cancer patient with a malignancy that will first affect her face. Ms. Schine writes with deep, gentle empathy for what this must be like to a woman with Lotte's overbearing pride.</p>
        <p>While Lotte goes from doctor to doctor ''like a tractor trailer laboring up a steep hill,'' her 53-year-old daughter is often unavailable to help. The reason for this, ostensibly, is that Greta has the flu. But she, too, is undergoing cancer treatment. This leaves Elizabeth with both a mother and grandmother to care for, and a sense that the sun is vanishing from her world, even as her Bovary project proceeds.</p>
        <p>Grim as this may sound, Ms. Schine sees beyond the mortality and fear. She has written a sweetly disarming testament to the unpredictability of romantic impulse. The novel's three heroines experience a kind of wake-up call in the face of impending loss, and each one is surprised to find herself trying something new. ''What am I trying to prove?'' Greta asks herself. ''That I'm alive? Couldn't I take up oil painting instead?''</p>
        <p>Apparently not: Greta has taken up with Daisy, a movie director who is a friend of her daughter's. ''Would she have felt better if she were more of a cliché, if she'd been waiting to have an affair with a man instead of a woman?'' Greta wonders. but sexual orientation does not much change the basic Bovary-based sentiments here. If anything, Ms. Schine throws Daisy into the mix and makes her book's possible permutations that much more dizzying.</p>
        <p>''Elizabeth, why don't you marry that nice husband of yours?'' Lotte asks her granddaughter. In fact Elizabeth does not want to marry Brett, a former student of hers, with whom she lives and has a son. Something about the way he ponders the difference between a romantic notion and an antiromantic notion seems to have sent romance right out the door. In any case Bovary strikes again: Elizabeth is convinced that Emma Bovary -- or ''Barbie Bovaine,'' as she has become known in the screenplay -- could have avoided an awful lot of grief if she had stayed single.</p>
        <p>''She Is Me,'' Ms. Schine's sixth book, is an improvement on her preceding one, ''The Evolution of Jane,'' which bogged down in thoughts about Darwin. Here, as in ''Rameau's Niece'' and ''The Love Letter,'' she interweaves bright literary gamesmanship with potent, difficult mother-daughter emotions. ''Your mother is very old,'' Greta tells herself. ''Very very old. Pretend she is a child. Just like your child, your highly competent, adult, big horse of a child sitting at the kitchen table biting her fingernails and spitting them on the floor.''</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
