<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ARTS BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="18ARTS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1520420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Contemporary Art Museum St Louis</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cash, Johnny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zevon, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oprah Winfrey Show (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DD153AF93BA2575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ARTS BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Van Gelder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts Briefing column: Swedish Broadcasting Commission reportedly censures an Oprah Winfrey talk show, saying it showed bias in favor of US attack on Iraq; Nielsen SoundScan ratings of final albums by Warren Zevon and Johnny Cash reportedly have been rising on pop charts since their deaths; ribbon-cutting and inaugural gala benefit will signal opening of new home for Contemporary Art Museum St Louis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>STOCKHOLM: CENSURING OPRAH -- An Oprah Winfrey talk show has drawn censure from Sweden's broadcasting watchdog, the Swedish Broadcasting Commission. The agency said the show betrayed bias toward a United States attack on Iraq, Reuters reported yesterday. ''Different views were expressed, but all longer remarks gave voice to the opinion that Saddam Hussein was a threat to the United States and should be the target of attack,'' the commission said. Annelie Ulfhielm, a commission official, said the censure meant that TV4, a Swedish television network, must publish the decision but that it is not subject to legal or financial penalties. The show was broadcast in February. Sweden's government opposed the invasion of Iraq, which began in March. A TV4 spokesman told Reuters that Ms. Winfrey's show usually drew an audience of 100,000 to 140,000, making it one of Sweden's most popular daytime offerings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>STOCKHOLM: CENSURING OPRAH -- An Oprah Winfrey talk show has drawn censure from Sweden's broadcasting watchdog, the Swedish Broadcasting Commission. The agency said the show betrayed bias toward a United States attack on Iraq, Reuters reported yesterday. ''Different views were expressed, but all longer remarks gave voice to the opinion that Saddam Hussein was a threat to the United States and should be the target of attack,'' the commission said. Annelie Ulfhielm, a commission official, said the censure meant that TV4, a Swedish television network, must publish the decision but that it is not subject to legal or financial penalties. The show was broadcast in February. Sweden's government opposed the invasion of Iraq, which began in March. A TV4 spokesman told Reuters that Ms. Winfrey's show usually drew an audience of 100,000 to 140,000, making it one of Sweden's most popular daytime offerings.</p>
        <p>MUSIC: POP POST-MORTEM -- The final albums by Warren Zevon and Johnny Cash have been rising on the pop charts since their deaths. For the week that ended Sept. 14, according to data issued by Nielsen SoundScan and reported by Reuters, ''The Wind'' by Mr. Zevon leaped 28 places to No. 12, and Mr. Cash's Grammy Award-winning ''American IV: The Man Comes Around'' ascended 72 places to No. 22. Mr. Zevon died on Sept. 7, Mr. Cash on Sept. 12.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS: MUSEUM'S NEW HOME -- A new home for the Contemporary Art Museum St. Louis opens tomorrow with a ribbon-cutting and inaugural gala benefit that usher in a weekendlong celebration. Adjacent to Tadao Ando's building, above, for the Pulitzer Foundation for the Arts, the 27,000-square-foot Contemporary Art Museum, designed by Brad Cloepfil of Allied Works Architecture, nearly quadruples the museum's existing space. It includes three galleries; a multimedia, performance and lecture space; a lab and education center; a lobby; a courtyard; a cafe; and a bookshop. The opening exhibition in the museum, continuing through Jan. 3, is ''A Fiction of Authenticity: Contemporary Africa Abroad.''</p>
        <p>JAZZ: AT LINCOLN CENTER -- From Russia with jazz comes the Igor Butman Big Band, which will open the 13th season of Jazz at Lincoln Center with ''Moscow Nights,'' in concert with the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra, led by Wynton Marsalis. The concerts, at 8 tonight and Saturday night in Alice Tully Hall, are the first collaborations of the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra with a foreign big band.</p>
        <p>FILM: SILENT NIGHTS -- Taking its cue and its content from the Pordenone Silent Film Festival in Italy, BAMcinématek at the Brooklyn Academy of Music will present a weekend of silent films, beginning at 7:30 tonight. The opening attraction of the Pordenone Silent Film Weekend is the United States premiere of a restored print of ''Once Upon a Time'' (1922), Carl Theodore Dreyer's tale of a Danish prince who tries to woo a princess by appearing to her in disguise. At 7:30 tomorrow night ''Treasures From a Chest'' will present films from a trove, some unscreened for more than 90 years.</p>
        <p>ART: THE KENNEDY EFFECT -- What was the impact of the presidency of John F. Kennedy on American and European artists and their work? An answer will be delivered, beginning on Saturday, when more than 40 paintings (including a James Wyeth portrait, detail at right), sculptures, drawings and photographs assembled from public and private collections worldwide go on view at the Bruce Museum of Arts and Science in Greenwich, Conn. Coinciding with the 40th anniversary of the assassination of Kennedy on Nov. 22, 1963, ''JFK and Art'' includes works by Pablo Picasso, Norman Rockwell, Robert Rauschenberg, Jasper Johns and Andy Warhol. The exhibition, billed as the first to examine artists' responses to Kennedy will close on Jan. 11. It will be seen from Feb. 2 through May 2 at the Norton Museum of Art in West Palm Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>ART: INDIAN BASKETS -- More than 200 of the finest baskets from the collection of the National Museum of the American Indian will go on view there on Saturday. The exhibition, ''The Language of Native American Baskets,'' focuses on the weavers' points of view and emphasizes the process of making the baskets. The exhibition in the museum, at 1 Bowling Green in Lower Manhattan, continues through Jan. 9.</p>
        <p>FOOTNOTES</p>
        <p>Everything from a walk-on role in a Broadway show to props from Off Broadway hits to autographs and photo opportunities with stars of daytime drama will be up for sale at the 17th annual Broadway Flea Market &amp; Grand Auction, from 10 a.m. to 7 p.m. on Sunday. This event, in Shubert Alley, between 44th and 45th Streets, west of Broadway, is a benefit for Broadway Cares/Equity Fights AIDS. . . . Gunther Schuller will lead the Manhattan School of Music Chamber Sinfonia in works by Rameau, Mozart, Ibert and Delius at 8 tomorrow night in a free concert in John C. Borden Auditorium, Broadway and 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. The concert will open the 2003-4 season of the school, now in its 85th year. The season will present more than 400 public performances of orchestral, jazz, opera and chamber music, most of them free. . . . The National Theater of Greece, with a cast of 30, will stage the American premiere of Euripides' ''Medea'' in modern Greek at 8 on Saturday night and 7 on Sunday night in the open-air Hearst Greek Theater at the University of California at Berkeley. The 100th anniversary of the 8,000-seat theater, inspired by ancient Greek amphitheaters, is being observed this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
