<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witchcraft for Lovers and Other Explorers</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="588741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="FORAGING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WITCHCRAFT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAGICKAL CHILDE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENBERG, CARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC1031F934A35751C0A965958260" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witchcraft for Lovers and Other Explorers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cara Greenberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENBERG, CARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN all else fails (prayer, psychotherapy, exercise), some people turn to witchcraft. Others try it just for fun. Whatever the case, witchcraft may not be all that you think it is. Steve Teicher, the manager at Magickal Childe, the appropriately dusty West 19th Street haunt of those interested in the occult, was reassuring on a recent afternoon. "It's not like it was in ancient times, when they slaughtered things in blood," he said. "A lot of people are afraid of the word 'witchcraft.' They think it's evil, but generally it's not."</p>
        <p>At Magickal Childe, founded in the mid-1970's as the Warlock Shop by Herman Slater, who died last July, the walls are lined with curiosities like voodoo dolls from New Orleans stuffed with Spanish moss ($45) and plaster figurines representing the Cretan snake goddess ($66) and other goddesses of antiquity. You can also find herbs that sound perfect for a witch's brew (devil's shoestring, dragon's blood), skull-shaped candles ($4.25), talismans and amulets ($5 and up), and wood, stone and terra-cotta gargoyles ($12 and up).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN all else fails (prayer, psychotherapy, exercise), some people turn to witchcraft. Others try it just for fun. Whatever the case, witchcraft may not be all that you think it is. Steve Teicher, the manager at Magickal Childe, the appropriately dusty West 19th Street haunt of those interested in the occult, was reassuring on a recent afternoon. "It's not like it was in ancient times, when they slaughtered things in blood," he said. "A lot of people are afraid of the word 'witchcraft.' They think it's evil, but generally it's not."</p>
        <p>At Magickal Childe, founded in the mid-1970's as the Warlock Shop by Herman Slater, who died last July, the walls are lined with curiosities like voodoo dolls from New Orleans stuffed with Spanish moss ($45) and plaster figurines representing the Cretan snake goddess ($66) and other goddesses of antiquity. You can also find herbs that sound perfect for a witch's brew (devil's shoestring, dragon's blood), skull-shaped candles ($4.25), talismans and amulets ($5 and up), and wood, stone and terra-cotta gargoyles ($12 and up).</p>
        <p>But the heart of the store is its collection of books on witchcraft, palmistry, divination, secret societies, kahuna Hawaiian magic, voodoo, Santeria (an Afro-Caribbean religion) and other arcane specialties.</p>
        <p>Peter Conte, who reads tarot cards at a small table at the back of the store four days a week ($25 a reading), said, "I'm an initiated third-degree Gardnerian." That means he follows the teachings of Gerald Gardner (1884-1964), identified on book covers as "the father of modern wicca."</p>
        <p>Wicca is a form of witchcraft based on the worship of pagan gods and goddesses. "In thinking about God, you should be aware that half the godhead is female, that there's an equally powerful heavenly mother," he said. He referred interested parties to a book called "The Spiral Dance" by Starhawk (HarperCollins, $14). It contains exercises, rituals and invocations to develop psychic powers, he said.</p>
        <p>How does one qualify as a witch? "If the goddess is in your heart, that's 75 percent," Mr. Conte said. "The rest is just paperwork."</p>
        <p>Witches won't tell outsiders much about their rituals, Mr. Teicher warned. "If you go blabbing about magic, that weakens it," he said. But Mr. Conte shared information on candle burning, one of the more accessible practices. The store stocks colored candles in the shapes of humans, crosses, skulls, cats and mummies ($2.25 and up). "Yellow candles enhance optimism," he said. "White is for protection. Blue is good for healing and getting rid of sorrow. Purple and black are power candles. Not everybody can handle their intensity."</p>
        <p>Mr. Conte believes that candle burning is "like turning on your computer. You may not know how it works, but it does." None of the customers in the store on a recent afternoon identified themselves as practitioners of witchcraft.</p>
        <p>Harry Mena, a photographer from Brooklyn, was just passing by and "thought the store looked fascinating." He asked, "What do you know about the number 3?"</p>
        <p>"It comes after the number 2," Mr. Conte shot back.</p>
        <p>"Three pops up everywhere," Mr. Mena went on. "The Holy Trinity, the pyramids, in baseball -- three strikes, you're out. Three is</p>
        <p>essential</p>
        <p>."</p>
        <p>Lee Mazzini, a playwright who lives in Long Island City, browsed through a selection of self-hypnosis cassettes ($10), including tapes about fear of heights, nail biting, freedom from guilt and painless dentistry. "Wouldn't Novocain help more?" he wondered.</p>
        <p>Anthony Bonilla, 15, of Middle Village, Queens, was at the store to buy tarot cards ($10 to $35). "I want to learn to read them," he said. "You can make money and get a lot of girls like that."</p>
        <p>With Valentine's Day coming up, one of the store's most popular items is the love-spell kit ($35), containing oils, candles and books of invocations that are supposed to scare up a mate. "You have to be careful," Mr. Teicher said. "They're not reversible. If you put a spell on someone, they're yours forever. You have to make sure they wear clean socks."</p>
        <p>Magickal Childe's address is 35 West 19th Street; telephone: (212) 242-7182. It is open Monday through Saturday from 11 A.M. to 8 P.M. and Sunday from noon to 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>FORAGING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
