<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demonic Choreographers, Angelic Ballerinas</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="607539"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD1639F93AA35756C0A965958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demonic Choreographers, Angelic Ballerinas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Anderson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Choreographers can seem like meanies. They give ballerinas such daunting things to do. But great choreographers are really softies. Even as they tax ballerinas, they bestow riches on them. Take, for instance, the challenges of such classics as "The Sleeping Beauty," "Swan Lake" and "Giselle."</p>
        <p>All three ballets are grueling to perform. Nonetheless, ballerinas and audiences adore them. "The Sleeping Beauty" is in the spring repertory of both American Ballet Theater and the New York City Ballet. Ballet Theater is also doing "Swan Lake," which the San Francisco Ballet offered earlier this year at the New York State Theater. And the Dance Theater of Harlem's "Giselle" delighted audiences at the State Theater this winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Choreographers can seem like meanies. They give ballerinas such daunting things to do. But great choreographers are really softies. Even as they tax ballerinas, they bestow riches on them. Take, for instance, the challenges of such classics as "The Sleeping Beauty," "Swan Lake" and "Giselle."</p>
        <p>All three ballets are grueling to perform. Nonetheless, ballerinas and audiences adore them. "The Sleeping Beauty" is in the spring repertory of both American Ballet Theater and the New York City Ballet. Ballet Theater is also doing "Swan Lake," which the San Francisco Ballet offered earlier this year at the New York State Theater. And the Dance Theater of Harlem's "Giselle" delighted audiences at the State Theater this winter.</p>
        <p>The title character of "Giselle" is surely the most eloquent starring part in these ballets. But its demands are enormous. Any dancer who attempts it must know how to invest technical expertise with a multitude of dramatic nuances. Giselle is first seen as an innocent peasant hopelessly in love with a mysterious stranger; then she suffers from physical as well as emotional heart pangs; shortly thereafter, she goes mad and dies -- all this in the first act alone. In the second act, Giselle returns as a ghost and saves her lover from evil spirits.</p>
        <p>The many facets of characterization and the varied steps required to express them could bewilder dancers. But few ballerinas are failures in "Giselle." Clearly, Jean Coralli and Jules Perrot knew what they were doing when they choreographed it in 1841.</p>
        <p>The sheer variety of steps for Giselle enables performers who are not at home in one aspect of the role to emphasize others. The interpretive possibilities are almost unlimited. Thus, Alicia Alonso was a passionate Giselle, Carla Fracci was frail, and Margot Fonteyn sweet. And just as mature, gifted actresses can be convincing as Shakespeare's Juliet, so can sensitive, older dancers look miraculously youthful as Giselle. Both Alonso and Galina Ulanova, when no longer youngsters, were memorable Giselles.</p>
        <p>"Swan Lake" is varied in its own way. Strictly speaking, it has two female starring parts: Odette, the enchanted Swan Queen, and Odile, the sorcerer's daughter who disguises herself as Odette. Because the choreography for Odette flows and Odile's steps flash, companies occasionally assign these characters to two temperamentally distinct ballerinas. Yet ever since the premiere of this work, choreographed by Lev Ivanov and Marius Petipa in 1895, it has been customary for the same star to portray both women. The dual role allows her to be doubly effective.</p>
        <p>Of course, lyrical dancers are not necessarily coruscating technicians, and some technicians fail to be lyrical. Such limitations may not be insuperable if a ballerina can shine in one of the two roles. Provided she is not hopelessly at sea in the other, her weaknesses will probably be excused. Whereas some dancegoers thought Maya Plisetskaya an icy Odette, she struck sparks as Odile. And although Fonteyn could wobble in Odile's virtuoso passages, she was a sublimely tender Odette. As a result, both Plisetskaya and Fonteyn are fondly remembered in "Swan Lake."</p>
        <p>In terms of sheer difficulty, the choreography for Princess Aurora in "The Sleeping Beauty" presents ballerinas with the most formidable challenges of any of the classics. That's one reason why the dance fans who excitedly compared the Auroras of Darci Kistler, Judith Fugate, Kyra Nichols and Margaret Tracey at City Ballet earlier this season will be eager to watch Cynthia Harvey, Susan Jaffe and Amanda McKerrow, who are currently dancing Aurora for Ballet Theater.</p>
        <p>Petipa, who created the ballet in 1890, does not bring Aurora onstage often. Nevertheless, whenever she is present, he keeps her busy. Almost as soon as Aurora enters, she has a brief allegro solo, followed by an absolutely fiendish sequence: the Rose Adagio, in which the princess is required to sustain balances while suitors present her with flowers. Each pose must be perfect, and even the slightest unsteadiness will be noticeable. What's more, the ballerina must appear radiant throughout. Fonteyn's glowing stage presence in the adagio remains legendary. But the aristocratic dignity of Irina Kolpakova was also impressive.</p>
        <p>Should a ballerina emerge from her Rose Adagio ordeal unscathed and still smiling, she will find that the audience is now on her side. She will doubtless be cheered on in other episodes, including the passage in which Aurora pricks her finger on the evil fairy's spindle and the vision scene in which she appears before the prince as an ideal woman.</p>
        <p>Problems multiply once more in the final pas de deux. If the ballerina has grown tired from her exertions, she may dance the pas de deux with technical caution. No matter. Dancegoers appreciative of her efforts throughout the ballet will forgive a moment of weariness. Or the ballerina may be so relieved that the work is almost over and so elated by her triumph thus far that, in a burst of creative energy, she and her partner bring the duet to an exalted conclusion.</p>
        <p>"The Sleeping Beauty," like "Giselle" and "Swan Lake," is filled with snares. And, like those ballets, it abounds with riches. The choreographers who can seem malevolent wizards because they devise such demanding steps ultimately prove benign magicians.</p>
        <p>DANCE VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
