<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="04MOVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC133BF937A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="4255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on page 10.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''AMERICAN HISTORY X,'' starring Edward Norton, Edward Furlong and Beverly D'Angelo. Directed by Tony Kaye (R, 118 minutes). Flawed but gut-slugging, renounced by its director yet still a showcase for his effective style, this story of a neo-Nazi skinhead who develops a heart of gold presses every possible hot button. And its toughest images stick even when its lurid self-aggrandizing, presented in the ersatz poetic idiom of videos and commercials, spins out of control. In a show of De Niro-like fury and versatility, Mr. Norton plays a savage, racist killer who learns the error of his ways through simple-minded but brutally effective plot devices and trying to protect his younger brother (Mr. Furlong). Hotheaded and sensationalistic, but startlingly tough (Janet Maslin).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on page 10.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''AMERICAN HISTORY X,'' starring Edward Norton, Edward Furlong and Beverly D'Angelo. Directed by Tony Kaye (R, 118 minutes). Flawed but gut-slugging, renounced by its director yet still a showcase for his effective style, this story of a neo-Nazi skinhead who develops a heart of gold presses every possible hot button. And its toughest images stick even when its lurid self-aggrandizing, presented in the ersatz poetic idiom of videos and commercials, spins out of control. In a show of De Niro-like fury and versatility, Mr. Norton plays a savage, racist killer who learns the error of his ways through simple-minded but brutally effective plot devices and trying to protect his younger brother (Mr. Furlong). Hotheaded and sensationalistic, but startlingly tough (Janet Maslin).</p>
        <p>''BABE: PIG IN THE CITY,'' starring Magda Szubanski and four-legged friends. Directed by George Miller. (G, 95 minutes). Babe the pig, he of the sweet voice and twitchy pink snout, remains a cute little porker in this elaborately ambitious sequel. But once he and his mistress head for the city, they must contend with many discouraging urban sights, including Mickey Rooney in a purple clown suit. And once he winds up at the eccentric, creature-filled hotel that is the film's main setting, the film turns rougher than its G rating suggests.  Had this ''Babe'' been made first, it wouldn't have prompted a sequel of its own (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''A BUG'S LIFE,'' featuring the voices of Dave Foley, Julia Louis-Dreyfus and Kevin Spacey. Directed by John Lasseter and Andrew Stanton (G, 94 minutes). The best animated ant colony movie of the year. And this is a more clearly defined family film than the verbally adult ''Antz,'' too. With the same anthropomorphism that gave Mr. Lasseter's ''Toy Story'' so much spark, this pastel-hued, visually ingenious feat of animation tells a tale of ant courage while also incorporating lively wit and an enchanting sense of nature.  And it's a showcase for the incredible range of facial expressions that make this type of animation more and more invitingly lifelike all the time (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''CELEBRITY,'' starring Kenneth Branagh, Judy Davis, Joe Mantegna, Winona Ryder and Melanie Griffith. Directed by Woody Allen (R, 113 minutes). Following in the footsteps of ''La Dolce Vita,'' Mr. Allen presents a New York in which the only thing worse than being famous for nothing is not being famous at all.  At the center of it all he places Mr. Branagh as a journalist with all the Allen tics but none of the filmmaker's comic flair. The bitter breakup at the center of the film (with Ms. Davis as the journalist's beached wife) is regularly upstaged by guest-star segments, a few of which stand out in witty relief against an otherwise weary backdrop. Charlize Theron dazzles as a capricious, headstrong model, and Ms. Griffith plays a pampered movie diva with aplomb. Best of all is Leonardo DiCaprio's brief, wicked appearance as a bad-boy wonder (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''CENTRAL STATION,'' starring Fernanda Montenegro, Vinicius de Oliviera and Marilia Pera. Directed by Walter Salles (R, 115 minutes). In this quiet, luminous Brazilian gem, a joyless older woman crosses paths with an orphaned young boy. There's plenty of room for sentimentality here, but the wonder of Mr. Salles's film is all in the telling. As these characters develop a fractious bond, then embark on a road trip that takes them vividly to Brazil's hinterlands in search of the boy's father, Mr. Salles brings great tenderness and surprise to the events that punctuate their journey. Ms. Montenegro's tough, bravura performance is one of the year's very best (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''DANCING AT LUGHNASA,'' starring Meryl Streep, Brid Brennan, Michael Gambon, Kathy Burke and Catherine McCormack. Directed by Pat O'Connor (PG, 94 minutes). Ms. Streep is grand, as are the other principals here, in an actors' heyday of a film adapted from Brian Friel's delicate play. And if Mr. O'Connor has lost some of the play's intensity by opening it up so overwhelmingly, he's also gained a good deal in the way of lovely Irish scenery and quaint rural charm. Set in 1936, the story presents a family of five unmarried sisters on the brink of change and revolves around the return of their gently eccentric brother from many years' missionary work in Africa. Rather than major dramatic events, this beguilingly atmospheric film observes the sea changes that alter these characters' lives (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''ELIZABETH,'' starring Cate Blanchett, Joseph Fiennes, Geoffrey Rush and Christopher Eccleston. Directed by Shekhar Kapur (R, 124 minutes). In this lurid costume drama depicting Queen Elizabeth I as a royal rookie, the impressive Ms. Blanchett plays the monarch as if her principal responsibilities were being bejeweled, selecting consorts and saying ''Leave us!'' with a wave of the hand. For all its putative concern with Roman Catholic-Protestant strife at the start of Elizabeth's reign, it's historical drama for those whose idea of history is back issues of Vogue. Intent on spectacle, complete with burning at the stake and one dance scene reminiscent of ''Saturday Night Fever,'' it winds up imagining the Queen as a glamorously stressed-out modern woman, afflicted by a super-intense case of having it all (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''ENEMY OF THE STATE,'' starring Will Smith, Gene Hackman, Jon Voight and Regina King. Directed by Tony Scott (R, 128 minutes). Mr. Smith goes on the run in a paranoid thriller whose high-tech gizmos are a main attraction. He also carries the story ably in his first real leading role, that of a successful lawyer who suddenly finds himself under surveillance by a sizable nerd squad at the National Security Agency and a satellite in space. Fortunately, it all hurtles by too fast for audiences to stop for plot questions. Sterling cast members like Mr. Hackman as an eccentric technology wiz and Mr. Voight as a chilly advocate of surveillance tactics add an additional touch of class (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''GODS AND MONSTERS,'' starring Ian McKellen and Brendan Fraser. Directed by Bill Condon (not rated, 105 minutes). In a performance that well deserves to be remembered at the end of the year, Mr. McKellen becomes the deliciously urbane James Whale, playing the gay ''Frankenstein'' director late in life. Shaken by the aftereffects of a mild stroke, this Whale finds his past coming back to greet him just as the present offers new fascination in the Adonis-like form of the gardener (Mr. Fraser, also fine), whom Whale finds mowing his lawn. This beautifully acted, witty and heart-tugging film, from a Christopher Bram book, imagines what Whale's final days might have been like while shaping a splendid character study and a droll portrait of closeted gay Hollywood. Lynn Redgrave provides ballast and comic relief as Whale's perpetually scandalized housekeeper (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''HAPPINESS,'' starring Jane Adams, Dylan Baker, Philip Seymour Hoffman and Lara Flynn Boyle. Directed by Todd Solondz (not rated; 135 minutes). In a much bigger film than his ''Welcome to the Doll House,'' this audacious, deadpan filmmaker explores loneliness in his murderously funny fashion. Outrageous touches -- none more so than its title -- come easily to ''Happiness,'' and so do the dark secrets that would surely have brought it an NC-17 rating. No point in cataloguing this film's perverse details: what emerges most clearly is a ruthless yet tender portrait of suburban characters seeking romance, captured with enough acid precision to make this a ''Bob and Carol and Ted and Alice'' for totally dysfunctional times. Ms. Adams plays the dartboard in a three-sister family with hilarious tremulousness. Mr. Baker's gutsy portrayal of a bland-seeming pederast who is also a respected doctor and a loving father is impossible to forget (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''HOME FRIES,'' starring Drew Barrymore. Directed by Dean Parisot (PG-13, 105 minutes). An absurdist satire of sex, sibling rivalry, Oedipal ties, homicidal jealousy, fast  food and helicopters in the American heartland, ''Home Fries'' isn't funny enough in its  particulars to make you break up laughing, but at least it tries for a sophistication beyond  the typical gross-out Hollywood comedy. Most of the humor comes from the collision of caricatures that suggest refugees from ''Tobacco Road,'' reinvented for a 90's version of the classic 70's sitcom ''Mary Hartman, Mary Hartman.'' Ms. Barrymore, who is winsome throughout, plays a very pregnant server at a burger outlet who falls in love with the stepson of her recently deceased married lover (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''LIFE IS BEAUTIFUL,'' directed by and starring Roberto Benigni (PG-13, 122 minutes). Italy's most antic funnyman dares to find humor and tenderness in the midst of the Holocaust, and his risk pays off. This Cannes prize winner is as stubbornly entertaining as its central character, a Jewish waiter named Guido who jokes his way through the nightmare for the sake of his loved ones. Daring also to combine an opening hour of romance and pranks with a more somber second act, Mr. Benigni avoids all traces of the maudlin and effectively creates a situation in which comedy is courage. In this unpretentious, enormously likable film, he shines as a father whose fibs and hilarious buffoonery know no bounds, and no fear (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''MEET JOE BLACK,'' starring Brad Pitt, Anthony Hopkins and Claire Forlani. Directed by Martin Brest (PG-13, 170 minutes). Mr. Hopkins zestily plays a noble tycoon in this otherwise somnolent, emotion-free, nearly three-hour (!) weepie. And Mr. Pitt appears blankly as Death with blond highlights, serving as a kind of personal afterlife trainer to the tycoon, whose number is up. Ms. Forlani plays the big man's beautiful daughter in a story based on ''Death Takes a Holiday.'' In a suffocatingly lavish film that cries out for a trip to the cutting room, virtually every character is allowed to overstay his or her welcome, with Mr. Pitt especially diminished by the watching-paint-dry pace. The story drags on so slowly that there's room for a subplot about party planning, and several scenes establish how much Death loves peanut butter (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''PLEASANTVILLE,'' starring Tobey Maguire, Reese Witherspoon, Joan Allen, William H. Macy, Don Knotts, J. T. Walsh and Jeff Daniels. Written and directed by Gary Ross (PG-13, 116 minutes). This cleverly executed fantasy, with a back-to-the-future trip into the small-town, squeaky-clean paradise of a 1950's television show, tends toward the black and white, visually and otherwise. The missionary zeal with which teen-agers from the 1990's try to awaken benighted 50's types from their slumber is an attitude that wears thin. But in the meantime there are witty tricks integrating color into black-and-white images, and nice little touches abound. The cast is poignant and amusing, with Ms. Allen especially touching as a prefeminist housewife who's the prime recipient of 90's hindsight (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''VERY BAD THINGS,'' starring Jon Favreau, Christian Slater, Cameron Diaz and Daniel Stern. Directed by Peter Berg (R, 100 minutes). A film that means to make the most of black-humored misanthropy had better be funnier than this mirthless exercise in witlessness and sadistic humor. Five dull middle-class buddies accidentally kill a prostitute while at a bachelor party in Las Vegas, and that's only the beginning of the fun. While it's possible to share the screenplay's eagerness to see these unappetizing guys wind up dead, the direction reveals so little point of view that it doesn't much matter who lives or dies. Ms. Diaz, so cleverly funny in ''There's Something About Mary,'' plays a wedding-obsessed ninny this time (Maslin).</p>
        <p>* ''WAKING NED DEVINE,'' starring Ian Bannen, David Kelly and Fionnula Flanagan. Directed by Kirk Jones (PG, 91 minutes). Delightful shenanigans greet the news of a winning lottery ticket in a tiny Irish village. Especially after the winner turns out to be dead. Mr. Bannen and Mr. Kelly are wonderfully funny as two old coots who concoct a plot to claim the winnings, and who unite the town's cast of hearty characters in the process. Mr. Jones's prize-winning career directing television commercials means that everyone here is an amusing eccentric with colorful quirks, and that the septuagenarian stars' naked motorcycle-riding scenes are played for all they're worth. This comedy doesn't have the tart edge of ''The Full Monty,'' but it knows how to coax laughs from making a spectacle of elderly gentlemen in the buff (Maslin).</p>
        <p>''THE WATERBOY,'' starring Adam Sandler, Kathy Bates and Fairuza Balk. Directed by Frank Coraci (PG-13, 91 minutes). The team behind ''The Wedding Singer'' looks like honorary Farrelly brothers with a comedy that, like ''There's Something About Mary,'' is both cheerfully outlandish and genuinely endearing. Mr. Sandler plays an amazing 31-year-old freshman who morphs from water-distribution engineer to sports hero, and he succeeds in doing to football whatever he did to golf in ''Happy Gilmore.'' There's a lot more innocence to his happy-idiot antics here than there is in many a film made specifically for children. Ms. Bates is a great hoot as the waterboy's overprotective mama, perfectly in tune with the film's sneaky sense of fun (Maslin).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
