<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Criticizes A.M.A. Backing of Abortion Procedure Ban</title>
    <meta content="Y04DOC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Medical Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDE103BF937A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Criticizes A.M.A. Backing of Abortion Procedure Ban</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investigators hired by AMA say orgn ignored its own decision-making procedures, got swept up in politics and failed to protect welfare of patients when it endorsed Republican bill banning specific abortion procedure last year; scathing report, part of larger investigation of board of trustees, concludes that 'the AMA blundered' in its handling of bill to outlaw procedure that opponents call partial birth abortion; trustees had been seeking concessions from Congress to make bill more acceptable to doctors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investigators hired by the American Medical Association say the organization ignored its own decision-making procedures, got swept up in politics and failed to protect the welfare of patients when it endorsed a Republican bill banning a specific abortion procedure last year.</p>
        <p>In a scathing report, the investigators said trustees of the group had abandoned its longstanding positions on abortion and rushed to embrace the bill even though it did not meet the criteria previously set by the association for such an endorsement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investigators hired by the American Medical Association say the organization ignored its own decision-making procedures, got swept up in politics and failed to protect the welfare of patients when it endorsed a Republican bill banning a specific abortion procedure last year.</p>
        <p>In a scathing report, the investigators said trustees of the group had abandoned its longstanding positions on abortion and rushed to embrace the bill even though it did not meet the criteria previously set by the association for such an endorsement.</p>
        <p>The report, part of a larger investigation of the board of trustees, concludes that ''the A.M.A. blundered'' in its handling of the bill to outlaw the procedure that opponents call partial birth abortion. The trustees had been seeking concessions from Congress to make the bill more acceptable to doctors.</p>
        <p>But the report said the association  ''set itself up for accusations of playing politics'' because it announced its support for the abortion bill on the same day it asked Congress to shield doctors from deep cuts in Medicare spending.</p>
        <p>''Rather than focusing on its role as steward for the profession and the public health,'' the report said, ''the board got enmeshed in operational issues of lobbying and lost sight of its responsibility for making decisions which, first and foremost, benefit the patient and protect the physician-patient relationship.''</p>
        <p>The report, a ''management audit'' by Booz Allen &amp; Hamilton, the consulting company, is based on  scores of confidential documents and interviews with people at all levels of the association. The report will be discussed next week in Honolulu at a meeting of the A.M.A. house of delegates, the 486-member policy-making body for the association. At that time, some doctors will press the association to rescind its endorsement of the abortion bill, which passed Congress but was vetoed by President Clinton.</p>
        <p>The investigators expressed no views for or against abortion. But they cited the association's handling of the abortion bill as an example of serious flaws in its decision-making process. The report suggests that leaders of the association were manipulated by Republican members of Congress and that the trustees were inexperienced and unable to deal with the intense political pressures surrounding their negotiations with Congress over the abortion bill in the spring of 1997.</p>
        <p>''As the A.M.A. became determined to cut a deal with the Congressmen,'' the report said, ''the decision-making process began to reel out of the control of the A.M.A. and into the control of the Congressmen on the other side of the negotiating table.''</p>
        <p>Although the trustees negotiated directly with Congressional sponsors of the legislation, they failed to consult adequately with the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and other groups of medical specialists, the report said.</p>
        <p>Some members of the association said they agreed with the auditors' findings. In the association, ''political considerations often take precedence over the profession's needs,'' said a panel of doctors who studied the structure and governance of the organization, at the behest of the house of delegates. The investigators from Booz Allen &amp; Hamilton worked under the supervision of the doctors' panel.</p>
        <p>The extraordinary self-examination was prompted by a fiasco in which the association last year agreed to endorse health care products of the Sunbeam Corporation in return for millions in royalty payments. Stung by charges of commercialism and conflict of interest, the doctors' group canceled the deal, and its chief executive resigned.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the abortion bill repeatedly cite the medical group's endorsement as a reason for Congress and state legislatures to impose such restrictions, and many states have done so. The Federal version was twice vetoed by President Clinton, in April 1996 and October 1997, but it is sure to come up again next year in Congress.</p>
        <p>The bill would make it a crime for a doctor to perform a partial birth abortion, defined as a procedure in which a doctor ''partially vaginally delivers a living fetus before killing the fetus and completing the delivery.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the legislation say it is aimed at a specific late-term abortion procedure. But judges have struck down similar language in state laws, saying it is so broad that it has the effect of banning abortion techniques widely used in earlier stages of pregnancy.</p>
        <p>In July, for example, Judge Richard G. Kopf of the Federal District Court for Nebraska ruled that the state's ban on the abortion procedure  was unconstitutionally vague because it did not give ''fair warning'' to doctors and patients about what conduct was prohibited.</p>
        <p>''One simply cannot ascertain from the legislative history precisely what the Legislature wanted to ban,'' Judge Kopf said. ''We know the legislators wanted to ban 'partial birth' abortions, but that term is unknown in medical circles.''</p>
        <p>Janet Benshoof, president of the Center for Reproductive Law and Policy, an abortion rights group, said courts had blocked or limited laws covering the abortion procedure in 18 states. At least six of the laws were modeled on the Federal bill endorsed by the medical association.</p>
        <p>The audit report also makes these points:</p>
        <p>*Through the timing of its action on the abortion bill, ''the A.M.A. painted a picture of itself as primarily concerned about protecting the financial interests of physicians.''</p>
        <p>*The trustees had ''a general sense, based on national polls, that the American public was opposed to the partial birth abortion procedure,'' but the association did not survey its members to ascertain what would be in the best interest of patients and doctors.</p>
        <p>*The decision to support a ban on the abortion procedure ''contradicted longstanding A.M.A. policy'' and deviated from positions reaffirmed by the house of delegates just five months earlier, in December 1996.</p>
        <p>*The association ''appeared to get swept up by the high-profile nature of the issue'' last year.</p>
        <p>*The association had well-established procedures to set policy in a ''thoughtful, deliberative and democratic way,'' but disregarded them. Instead, it used a ''crisis mode of policy-setting.''</p>
        <p>The trustees decided that they had to take a position on the abortion bill in May 1997, rather than wait for the house of delegates to consider the issue at its regularly scheduled meeting one month later.</p>
        <p>As a result, the report says, ''many doctors were outraged.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
