<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Calls Garbage Plan Regional Plus</title>
    <meta content="04GARB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5D9103BF937A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Calls Garbage Plan Regional Plus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph Giuliani vows to forge ahead with his plan to ship most of New York City's residential trash to transfer stations in New Jersey, saying political storm will die down when economic benefits are understood; opponents in both states vow to thwart scheme (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani vowed yesterday to forge ahead with his plan to ship most of New York City's residential trash to transfer stations in New Jersey, saying that politicians furious about the proposal would calm down once they realized the economic benefits that their constituents stood to reap.</p>
        <p>The unveiling of the plan on Wednesday piqued the interest of a number of New Jersey towns eager to do business with the city, Mr. Giuliani said, adding that he had received calls from ''at least three public officials'' who were ''very, very anxious to make deals with us.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani vowed yesterday to forge ahead with his plan to ship most of New York City's residential trash to transfer stations in New Jersey, saying that politicians furious about the proposal would calm down once they realized the economic benefits that their constituents stood to reap.</p>
        <p>The unveiling of the plan on Wednesday piqued the interest of a number of New Jersey towns eager to do business with the city, Mr. Giuliani said, adding that he had received calls from ''at least three public officials'' who were ''very, very anxious to make deals with us.''</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Giuliani unflinchingly predicted that the plan would be in place by the end of 2001, when the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island is scheduled to close, opponents in both states were threatening to do everything in their power to thwart it. In New Jersey, elected officials said they would block construction of huge transfer stations in Newark and Carteret, where garbage from Manhattan and Queens would be shipped under the plan.</p>
        <p>And in Brooklyn, where a third transfer station would be built, community groups were considering a lawsuit on grounds that the plan violated environmental laws.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, a Republican whose second term will end just as Fresh Kills is supposed to close, has a lot resting on the proposal. Overwhelming support from Staten Island helped him win the mayoral elections of 1993 and 1997, and that backing would also be important if he decides to run for the United States Senate in 2000. If the garbage proposal failed, it could also hurt any plans Mr. Giuliani might have to seek a national office by raising questions about his ability to carry out plans he proposes.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, the Mayor insisted that the plan would be relatively easy to carry out -- even as he admitted that his administration made what he called ''a good faith mistake'' by waiting until the last minute to tell the New Jersey Governor, Christine Todd Whitman, about the plan. Mr. Giuliani said his administration kept the plan from public officials in New Jersey until it was complete because of New York City's strict rules for reviewing bids.</p>
        <p>''On reflection, it certainly should have meant that Governor Whitman was briefed,'' Mr. Giuliani said in a rare show of contrition. ''That was a mistake, but it wasn't a bad faith mistake. It was a good faith mistake.''</p>
        <p>Joseph J. Lhota, the Deputy Mayor for Operations, said that he had discussed the plan with Mrs. Whitman's chief of staff in several phone conversations yesterday, and that officials from both administrations would continue the talks in person. But while Mrs. Whitman's aides said they were not necessarily against having some of the city's garbage brought to the state, they promised to fight Mr. Giuliani's plan to ship it to Newark and Carteret on barges and to build new transfer stations to store it.</p>
        <p>''This isn't about New York City's trash,'' said Pete McDonough, chief spokesman for Mrs. Whitman. ''It is about the method for receiving it.''</p>
        <p>United States Senator Robert G. Torricelli also denounced the plan, using even sharper language than the Governor's aides. ''This is not going to happen,'' said Mr. Torricelli, a Democrat. ''Garbage cannot be transferred on barges off of beaches without impacting the quality of life in New Jersey. We must present a united front in opposition to this plan.''</p>
        <p>Back in New York City, at in a news conference for which he chose the Hudson River and the not-so-distant shores of New Jersey as a backdrop, Mr. Giuliani insisted that the plan would succeed once politicians there realized how much it would spur economic development. ''This is going to happen,'' he said. ''You've got to understand, the politics of garbage is different from the business of garbage.''</p>
        <p>But in New York, opponents of the proposal said they feared that the two transfer stations planned for New Jersey would never be built. In that case, they said, the one that is to be built in Brooklyn would get much more than its share of garbage.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration is already locked in a legal battle with Brooklyn, which is fighting a short-term plan for dealing with the city's garbage while the long-term plan is phased in over several years. The borough has already stalled one proposed short-term site for a transfer station in court.</p>
        <p>Jim Tripp, general counsel for the Environmental Defense Fund, said the controversy surrounding the city's long-term plan could leave the short-term plan in effect for years after the landfill closes. ''The interim plan may not be so interim,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
