<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africa Must Mine Its Human Resources</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (NON-US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D6143AF937A35751C0A964958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africa Must Mine Its Human Resources</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your Jan. 7 report that only 39.2 percent of black South African high school students passed their senior year matriculation exam did not surprise me. I work with South Africans and have seen how 45 years of apartheid education policies have deprived this "Lost Generation" of adequate education and, for many, of hope.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there is reason for hope. President F. W. de Klerk and like-minded South African leaders are struggling to put aside apartheid and bring blacks into the political and economic mainstream. However, if a democratic South Africa is to work, it needs to view the empowerment of blacks not as charity or even the righting of past wrongs, but as taking advantage of the enormous resources, resourcefulness and talent to be found among black youths who are being lost to society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your Jan. 7 report that only 39.2 percent of black South African high school students passed their senior year matriculation exam did not surprise me. I work with South Africans and have seen how 45 years of apartheid education policies have deprived this "Lost Generation" of adequate education and, for many, of hope.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there is reason for hope. President F. W. de Klerk and like-minded South African leaders are struggling to put aside apartheid and bring blacks into the political and economic mainstream. However, if a democratic South Africa is to work, it needs to view the empowerment of blacks not as charity or even the righting of past wrongs, but as taking advantage of the enormous resources, resourcefulness and talent to be found among black youths who are being lost to society.</p>
        <p>This was brought most forcefully to my attention by 22-year-old Jabulani Mabaso, whose self-help Masmove learning movement in strife-torn Natal province targeted students who had failed the "matric." Study groups of 6 to 15 students were formed, who enlisted tutors, set their own work schedules and helped one another. The result is a phenomenal 87 percent pass rate. Masmove is expanding and will soon be tried in schools throughout South Africa.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Mabaso is tackling his country's severe educational problems suggests there is no alternative to empowering black South Africans in the search for solutions. Your statistics demonstrate the problem's magnitude, but what underlies them is even more desperate. The teacher-to-student ratio for blacks is 45 to 1, against 16 to 1 for the wealthy white school system. It is estimated 37,500 more black classrooms are needed, half again as many as there are now.</p>
        <p>Almost half the black schoolteachers have not themselves passed the "matric," while 42 percent have only the "matric" plus the minimum one-year primary teaching certificate. This leaves only 7 percent with the "matric" plus a three-year certificate. Education spending per black pupil is about $160 a year, against more than $1,000 for white pupils.</p>
        <p>This "Lost Generation" was in the forefront of the struggle against apartheid. Some 30 percent of black secondary schools were boycotted during the upheavals of the mid-1980's, and 90 percent of these were closed by the Government. That is one reason kids from the most active townships did worst on the exam.</p>
        <p>The most depressing statistic is that only 1 in 20 black children entering the school system reaches the final year; three-fifths do not complete primary school.</p>
        <p>The problems are overwhelming, but black South Africans must have an opportunity to find solutions to their socioeconomic problems in this crippled environment. If South Africa is ever to be whole, it must mine its rich human resources with the same deliberation and dedication with which it mines gold, diamonds and platinum. Except the payoff is likely to be far greater. MIRIAM PAREL  Arlington, Va., Jan. 16, 1992</p>
        <p>The writer directs South Africa programs for Ashoka Innovators for the Public, a private, nonprofit organization that supports public-service innovation internationally.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
