<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sumitomo Executive Is Recruited by Kidder</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="328440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS PEOPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KIDDER PEABODY &amp; CO INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUMITOMO BANK LTD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAITO, KEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BUSINESS PEOPLE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB123EF932A15751C0A966958260" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sumitomo Executive Is Recruited by Kidder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Sterngold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company, the Wall Street securities firm, took a big step toward increasing its investment banking presence in Tokyo yesterday, announcing that it had recruited Ken Saito, a top deal maker at Sumitomo Bank, to head its mergers and acquisitions department in Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company, the Wall Street securities firm, took a big step toward increasing its investment banking presence in Tokyo yesterday, announcing that it had recruited Ken Saito, a top deal maker at Sumitomo Bank, to head its mergers and acquisitions department in Japan.</p>
        <p>Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company, the Wall Street securities firm, took a big step toward increasing its investment banking presence in Tokyo yesterday, announcing that it had recruited Ken Saito, a top deal maker at Sumitomo Bank, to head its mergers and acquisitions department in Japan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saito, 42 years old, had served more than 20 years at Sumitomo and was co-head of the bank's mergers and acquisitions department, one of the better known and more aggressive in Japan. As well known for his skiing ability as for his strong contacts in corporate Japan, Mr. Saito had also worked in Sumitomo's New York and Los Angeles offices.</p>
        <p>Kidder, which is rebuilding after being jolted by waves of defections over the last few years, has been following a strategy in Japan of trying to place Japanese executives in senior positions. Mr. Saito's decision to join Kidder is one of the rare occasions in Tokyo when an American company has been able to recruit a well-regarded and senior executive from a top Japanese institution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saito is not the first executive to leave Sumitomo. Last fall, Toshihiko Yamamoto, co-head of mergers with Mr. Saito, left the bank to join Drexel Burnham Lambert, which filed for bankruptcy last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saito said he had left Sumitomo for what he sees as a good opportunity to build a department at Kidder, where he will be a senior vice president.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a good move for him, and we've been friendly with Kidder, Peabody for a long time,'' said Akio Asuke, the head of investment banking at Sumitomo and Mr. Saito's former boss. ''I know he had been thinking of joining an American investment bank, and if he had waited a couple of more years, it might have been too late for him to do this kind of thing.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Saito's departure was friendly, officials of both companies said, changing jobs and joining a competitor in Japan can be ticklish. In this case, Sumitomo was reportedly satisfied that Mr. Saito joined an American firm that is still trying build its presence in Tokyo, rather than a head-on competitor.</p>
        <p>''I spoke to Mr. Asuke today and we were very pleased that Mr. Saito was able to make it a friendly move,'' said Ryoei Matsunami, the head of investment banking for Kidder in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS PEOPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
