<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Armory's Opera Debut Is Delayed</title>
    <meta content="15armo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/15/arts/music/15armo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1769158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seventh Regiment Armory (NYC)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wakin, Daniel J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sellars, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Viola, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wagner, Richard (1813-83)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tristan and Isolde (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seventh Regiment Armory (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDE1031F936A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Armory's Opera Debut Is Delayed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Armory's Opera Debut Delayed by Lincoln Center</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL J. WAKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wakin, Daniel J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seventh Regiment Armory's future as cultural center suffers setback as Lincoln Center pulls semi-staged production of Wagner's Tristan and Isolde after determining that costs of improving audience amenities in time for performance scheduled for next spring are too high; production, collaboration betwwen video artist Bill Viola and director Peter Sellars, will play at Avery Fisher Hall (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Seventh Regiment Armory's future in the arts has suffered a small setback. Lincoln Center said Wednesday it was pulling a semi-staged production of Wagner's ''Tristan und Isolde'' scheduled for next spring from the armory. The costs of improving audience amenities in time for the performances next spring were too high, Lincoln Center said.</p>
        <p>Instead ''The Tristan Project,'' as the production is called, will play at Avery Fisher Hall. The performances will be on May 2 and May 5 instead of April 27 and May 5. Three separate performances of each individual act will be canceled because dates were unavailable at Fisher Hall, a Lincoln Center spokeswoman, Eileen McMahon, said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lincoln Center said Wednesday it was pulling a semistaged production of Wagner's "Tristan und Isolde" scheduled for next spring from the armory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Seventh Regiment Armory's future in the arts has suffered a small setback. Lincoln Center said Wednesday it was pulling a semi-staged production of Wagner's ''Tristan und Isolde'' scheduled for next spring from the armory. The costs of improving audience amenities in time for the performances next spring were too high, Lincoln Center said.</p>
        <p>Instead ''The Tristan Project,'' as the production is called, will play at Avery Fisher Hall. The performances will be on May 2 and May 5 instead of April 27 and May 5. Three separate performances of each individual act will be canceled because dates were unavailable at Fisher Hall, a Lincoln Center spokeswoman, Eileen McMahon, said.</p>
        <p>Plans have been set in motion to turn the armory into an arts organization, an important addition to New York City's cultural scene. The New York Philharmonic is considering using it as a temporary home during a future restoration of Fisher Hall, and Lincoln Center too is still hoping to stage events there.</p>
        <p>The armory and Drill Hall, its 55,000-square-foot, column-free space, has long been eyed hungrily by performing arts presenters.</p>
        <p>''It's a raw space,'' said Rebecca Robertson, the president and chief executive of the Seventh Regiment Armory Conservancy. ''I know how tough it is.'' The conservancy was established to oversee the building's renovation as a center for visual and performing arts, along with antique fairs.</p>
        <p>''It was really superbrave and wonderful of them to think about it,'' Ms. Robertson said. The cancellation, she added, had no bearing on the arts center's future.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, all the amenities will be available when we do the renovation,'' she said. ''This is a short-term problem.''</p>
        <p>Major work is likely to begin in two or three years, Ms. Robertson said. The landmark building, on Park Avenue between 66th and 67th Streets, is the city's main showplace for art, antiques and crafts shows.</p>
        <p>The ''Tristan'' production, first performed at Disney Hall in Los Angeles in 2004, is a collaboration between the video artist Bill Viola and the director Peter Sellars. The music will be performed by the Los Angeles Philharmonic, with Esa-Pekka Salonen conducting. The performance in New York will be under the aegis of the Great Performers series at Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>But questions remained about the costs and timing of the decision. Lincoln Center declined to say what the cost estimates were, or what caused them to be considered too high. In announcing the performances in January, Lincoln Center officials said it would create a ''unique performance space'' inside the armory to ''realize the full impact of this remarkable presentation.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McMahon said the armory was chosen precisely because of its height, ideal for the 32-by-18-foot screen used in the production. But Lincoln Center said in a statement on Wednesday, ''It became apparent that existing air-conditioning, restroom and other patron amenities would be inadequate for the expected number of ticket holders, and anticipated alterations would be prohibitively expensive to install in time for the performances.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McMahon said those amenities included a box office and emergency exits to serve an expected seating capacity of 1,800 people. But it was unclear who was paying for what.</p>
        <p>''The whole project was a joint production with the armory,'' Ms. McMahon said, declining to give a breakdown.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Robertson said the armory was paying only to install air conditioning, which it had planned to do anyway. ''We just fast-tracked it so it could get done in time for 'Tristan,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. McMahon said ''transition'' in leadership at the armory delayed budgeting and production.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robertson declined to comment on that point. ''Our part of the deal was to provide raw space in its current form and an air-conditioned Drill Hall,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. McMahon said the production would go forward unchanged at Fisher Hall. An extension to the stage will allow the installation of the large screen, she added.</p>
        <p>In the Los Angeles production Mr. Viola's images displayed on the screen included surf breaking to the rhythms of the music, lovers swimming under water, bleak forests and freighters sailing at night. The New York Philharmonic's spokesman, Eric Latzky, interviewed by telephone from Parma, Italy, where the orchestra is on tour, said the glitch would not affect the orchestra's plans to move some concerts to the armory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
