<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. RECORD SET IN POLLUTION CASES</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="205113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDA163AF93AA35751C1A96E948260" item-length="307" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. RECORD SET IN POLLUTION CASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHABECOFF, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHABECOFF, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it took a record number of enforcement actions last year against violators of pollution laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it took a record number of enforcement actions last year against violators of pollution laws.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency announced today that it took a record number of enforcement actions last year against violators of pollution laws.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and some members of Congress have sharply criticized the agency in recent years for what they called its failure to enforce aggressively the clean air and water acts, the toxic waste laws and other pollution statutes.</p>
        <p>Since the first two years of the Reagan Administration, when the number of enforcement actions take by the E.P.A. against polluters plunged, critics have charged the agency with showing more interest in easing the regulatory burden on polluters than in carrying out the law.</p>
        <p>Since then, however, the number of legal actions taken by the agency has risen steadily. Today it announced that the number of civil and criminal cases it sent to the Justice Department in the fiscal year ended Sept. 30 was the highest in the E.P.A.'s 18-year history.</p>
        <p>Lee M. Thomas, the Administrator of the agency, said the cases referred to the Justice Department last year ''reflect a continuing strong environmental enforcement effort.''</p>
        <p>''The figures we are releasing today,'' he said, ''should put the regulated community on notice that E.P.A. is serious about enforcement.''</p>
        <p>The agency reported that it referred 372 civil cases to the Justice Department last year, of which 86 were for violations of the clean air law, 123 of the water law, 143 of the hazardous waste laws and 20 of the toxics and pesticides laws. Until now the largest number of civil cases sent to the department was 342 in 1986.</p>
        <p>The agency also filed 59 criminal cases, more than the previous high of 41 in 1986 and 1987.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said today that they welcomed the greater enforcement effort but added that the numbers concealed major failings in carrying out environmental laws.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
