<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patience Is the Key To Victory For Hart</title>
    <meta content="09GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="GOLF" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Canadian Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dorman, Larry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hart, Dudley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4DE133BF93AA3575AC0A960958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patience Is the Key To Victory For Hart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY DORMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dorman, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>OAKVILLE, Ontario, Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dudley Hart wins Canadian Open golf championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the better part of six years, he has fought. The battles were against himself, his temper, injuries and self-doubt. It was all supposed to be so easy for Dudley Hart when he arrived on the PGA Tour in 1991 as an acclaimed collegian, a four-time all-American from the University of Florida, a smiling blond kid with looks and game and as much talent as any rookie in years.</p>
        <p>But it took until today, on a gray and sullen Canadian afternoon, with the tail end of a dying hurricane sweeping across Glen Abbey Golf Club, for Hart to beat them all. With his final round of 70, a hard-grinding and patient round during which he got up and down for par six times -- once for each season without a victory -- Hart won his first tournament, the rain-shortened Bell Canadian Open, by one stroke over David Duval, who shot 69.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the better part of six years, he has fought. The battles were against himself, his temper, injuries and self-doubt. It was all supposed to be so easy for Dudley Hart when he arrived on the PGA Tour in 1991 as an acclaimed collegian, a four-time all-American from the University of Florida, a smiling blond kid with looks and game and as much talent as any rookie in years.</p>
        <p>But it took until today, on a gray and sullen Canadian afternoon, with the tail end of a dying hurricane sweeping across Glen Abbey Golf Club, for Hart to beat them all. With his final round of 70, a hard-grinding and patient round during which he got up and down for par six times -- once for each season without a victory -- Hart won his first tournament, the rain-shortened Bell Canadian Open, by one stroke over David Duval, who shot 69.</p>
        <p>With his 14-under-par total of 202 for the 54-hole tournament, Hart became the most famous Dudley to hit Canada since Dudley Do-Right of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police, a cartoon character from the old Rocky and Bullwinkle television show. He also, finally, shed his own cartoon image and overcame his worst golfing enemy. Himself.</p>
        <p>''I've been working really hard on not getting down on myself, on not getting in my own way,'' said Hart, 28. ''I've been a perfectionist all my life, and when I didn't hit it eight feet from the hole, I'd get all bent out of shape. Today, I was able to stay patient.</p>
        <p>''I'm really proud of myself.''</p>
        <p>He should be. This was the sort of day -- rainy, gusty and uncomfortable -- that can test the most imperturbable of men. And Hart, who was nicknamed the Mini-Volcano because of his tendency to go seismic over any mis-hit, has always had a fuse shorter than Sam Torrance's new haircut.</p>
        <p>Not today. He got up and down at the 2d hole, the 4th, the 7th, the 10th, the 11th, the 12th and the 14th.</p>
        <p>So, as he went to the tee at the 16th hole, he was two strokes clear of Duval and Taylor Smith and Scott Dunlap, the overnight leader who eventually would balloon to 76 and a tie for third. Hart left his approach shot on the 516-yard, par-5 hole some 60 feet from the pin, a valley between himself and the hole.</p>
        <p>In the past, he might have buried his iron in the turf, maybe shattered the shaft like he did to his driver last week at Milwaukee when he hit a bad drive at the 18th hole on Friday and missed the cut. But he didn't. He smiled, he walked resolutely to the green, and he two-putted for birdie.</p>
        <p>And that was the difference. Duval pulled within a stroke with birdies at the 16th and 18th holes, but he was destined to finish second for the second time this year. Hart played the final two holes like a player who has learned his lessons well.</p>
        <p>During his months off earlier this year while his surgically repaired right wrist healed between December and June, Hart had plenty of time to think about his past mistakes and about his future goals, about his blown opportunities and his situation as a non-exempt player.</p>
        <p>He was told by the PGA Tour that his application for an injury exemption was denied on a technicality, something about needing to average at least top 100 on the money list for five years. He averaged 102d. Before this week, he was 157th on the money list with $80,629.</p>
        <p>Now, his ball sitting in the short cut of rough at the 508-yard 18th hole, he decided against going for the green. Par would be good enough to win. He hit sand wedge, 60-degree wedge and two-putted for victory and $270,000 and a two-year exemption.</p>
        <p>''I can't put it into words,'' he said. ''Maybe it'll sink in soon. But I know this. I learned about patience. It finally sunk in. I might forget it next week, but I don't think so.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>TIGER WOODS shot 68 for an eight-under-par total of 208 that gave him his best finish in a professional event, a solo 11th. Woods, who earned $37,500 for the week, now has a total of $40,044 in two events with five tournaments remaining in his quest for exempt status on the 1997 PGA Tour. His schedule: Quad City Classic (Sept. 12-15), B.C. Open (Sept. 19-22), Buick Challenge (Sept. 26-29), Las Vegas Invitational (Oct. 2-6), LaCantera Texas Open (Oct. 10-13).</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Gilbert Edges Irwin</p>
        <p>AUGUSTA, Mo., Sept. 8 (AP) -- Gibby Gilbert, who forced a playoff by making birdies on three of the final six holes, parred the first playoff hole today to beat Hale Irwin in the Senior PGA Tour's innaugural $1.2 million Boone Valley Classic. Gilbert finished 54 holes at 10-under 203, tied with Irwin, who closed with a 70.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
