<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; How Jack Nicholson Got That Way</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="674955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGILLIGAN, PATRICK</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">JACK'S LIFE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5D71E3DF934A25750C0A962958260" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; How Jack Nicholson Got That Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jack's Life  A Biography of Jack Nicholson  By Patrick McGilligan  Illustrated. 478 pages. W. W. Norton. $25.</p>
        <p>What comes as a small surprise in Patrick McGilligan's intermittently engrossing "Jack's Life: A Biography of Jack Nicholson" is that the screen actor's career did not begin with his performance as George Hanson, the alcoholic Southern small-town lawyer, in "Easy Rider" (1969). That part, incidentally, was modeled by the screenwriter Terry Southern after William Faulkner's fictional lawyer Gavin Stevens and was originally meant to be played by Rip Torn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jack's Life  A Biography of Jack Nicholson  By Patrick McGilligan  Illustrated. 478 pages. W. W. Norton. $25.</p>
        <p>What comes as a small surprise in Patrick McGilligan's intermittently engrossing "Jack's Life: A Biography of Jack Nicholson" is that the screen actor's career did not begin with his performance as George Hanson, the alcoholic Southern small-town lawyer, in "Easy Rider" (1969). That part, incidentally, was modeled by the screenwriter Terry Southern after William Faulkner's fictional lawyer Gavin Stevens and was originally meant to be played by Rip Torn.</p>
        <p>At the time "Easy Rider" was being planned, Mr. Nicholson had already been trying to make it in Hollywood for a decade. As Mr. McGilligan writes, "Ten years of scrounging for parts had left him bottomed out as an actor, and he had thrown himself into writing and producing." He happened to be working on the first Monkees movie for the people who ended up producing "Easy Rider." When Rip Torn quit over salary problems, Mr. Nicholson was already working on the film as production troubleshooter, so he was available to step into the vacant part. Life as a film star began.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGilligan, whose previous books include biographies of James Cagney, Robert Altman and George Cukor, shrewdly uses the history of Mr. Nicholson's serendipitous involvement with "Easy Rider" as his prologue. Then he tops it with the even more surprising story of Mr. Nicholson's origins.</p>
        <p>It seems that he had an unremarkable lower-middle-class Catholic upbringing in Neptune, N.J. His parents were John J. and Ethel May Nicholson, respectively a window dresser and a beautician. Except that they were not his parents, but his grandparents. As he was not to learn until 1974, when he was 37, his mother was June Frances Nicholson, the woman he had always thought was his sister. His father was reputed to be Don Furcillo-Rose, a professional singer Ethel May banished from her daughter's life before her grandchild was born. Mr. McGilligan also mentions the possible paternity of Eddie King, an actor and dance partner of June's whom neighbors thought Mr. Nicholson grew up to resemble. The actor never met either of his putative fathers.</p>
        <p>By the time you absorb all this, you are sufficiently caught up in Mr. Nicholson's story to put off wondering whether "Jack's Life" was authorized, or why a biography of the film star should be written while he is in midcareer.</p>
        <p>Along with wonder at his origins, you feel anticipation over the roles he will be playing that have made him the most electrifying screen actor of the last two decades: Bobby Dupea in "Five Easy Pieces," Billy Buddusky in "The Last Detail," J. J. Gittes in "Chinatown," Randle P. McMurphy in "One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest," Tom Logan in "The Missouri Breaks," Jack Torrance in "The Shining," the Joker in "Batman" and James R. Hoffa in "Hoffa."</p>
        <p>As Jack Lang, France's Minister of Culture, put it when he awarded Mr. Nicholson the Commander of Arts and Letters ribbon in 1990, "Your angular eyebrows, your ironic smile, your taste for exaggeration have etched out characters who are memorable, sometimes satanic."</p>
        <p>But as it turns out, the earlier years of Mr. Nicholson's career are the most absorbing to read about. Apparently, he was always the Jack Nicholson he so often radiates in his roles: the fractious but likable clown with the manic smile. He seems to have picked up his slow drawl with its peculiar emphasis from a high-school friend who was notorious for talking that way. He always loved to follow professional sports and he always attracted a crowd of buddies to accompany him.</p>
        <p>Yet although he was formed early, he worked extremely hard at his art, observing, practicing, reading about and discussing technique. "For all of his improvisational mystique," Mr. McGilligan writes, "he is one of the more assiduously trained motion-picture stars in the history of Hollywood." Although his early work still attracts a cult following in France, it was not until his 11th movie, "Back Door to Hell," shot in 1964 in the Philippines, that he began to loosen up. "I get it now," he is supposed to have remarked to a friend on the set. "I think I know what it's about."</p>
        <p>In the second half of "Jack's Life," my interest began to flag. True, occasional tidbits of trivia are fed us. At least three people claim credit for the defining restaurant scene in "Five Easy Pieces," where the actor tells the waitress to make a chicken-salad sandwich on wheat toast and then "hold the chicken" and "bring me the toast." Studying for the part of Charley Partanna in "Prizzi's Honor," Mr. Nicholson noticed that certain Italians spoke without moving their upper lips; so he stuffed tissue paper under his upper lip, which gave him the spine of the character.</p>
        <p>But less engaging sides of the star emerge: his taste for drugs and one-night stands; his indulgence of crackpot thinkers like the orgone-box psychoanalyst, Wilhelm Reich; his habit of mooning in public places like Boston Garden.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. McGilligan's prose begins to wear, with its affinity for expressions like "life style" and "at this point in time." He doesn't seem to be building toward any crowning point, even though in an explanation of why he wrote the book he says "that a serious and thorough book about Jack's life, at this point in time, would be a valuable endeavor." But he never makes it clear just why.</p>
        <p>In this same concluding section the author says that while Mr. Nicholson didn't deter him from writing the book, neither did he talk to the author, and Mr. Nicholson somehow discouraged many of his intimates from cooperating. Mr. McGilligan adds: "I was fortunate, however, in that over the course of the last 25 years I have interviewed many persons closely connected with Nicholson's career. . . . These interviews, expressly or otherwise, helped inform my portrait of Jack."</p>
        <p>In short, for all its considerable fascination, "Jack's Life" is finally not very much more than upper-drawer fan-magazine gossip.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
