<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Program of Workshops To Help the Unemployed</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="841971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN ASSN OF RETIRED PERSONS (AARP)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COMMUNITYCOLLEGE AMERICAN ASSOCIATION OF RETIRED PERSONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINGER, PENNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D91339F934A35757C0A960958260" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Program of Workshops To Help the Unemployed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SINGER, PENNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUCH has changed and none of it is good, since the spring of 1988 when A.A.R.P. Works, a career-planning program for out-of-work executives, was first  held. The program, a series of seven job workshops sponsored by the American Association of Retired Persons for unemployed people older than 50, has become a barometer reflecting the downsizing taking place in the county, said Claire Watsky, who runs the program.</p>
        <p>"We can tell precisely what the job climate is like," Ms. Watsky said. "For instance, when real estate went into a decline, real estate people flocked to the program. And when I.B.M started letting people go, the majority of those in  the program were former I.B.M.-ers." The next A.A.R.P. Works workshop will start on April 15 and run through May 16. The fee is $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUCH has changed and none of it is good, since the spring of 1988 when A.A.R.P. Works, a career-planning program for out-of-work executives, was first  held. The program, a series of seven job workshops sponsored by the American Association of Retired Persons for unemployed people older than 50, has become a barometer reflecting the downsizing taking place in the county, said Claire Watsky, who runs the program.</p>
        <p>"We can tell precisely what the job climate is like," Ms. Watsky said. "For instance, when real estate went into a decline, real estate people flocked to the program. And when I.B.M started letting people go, the majority of those in  the program were former I.B.M.-ers." The next A.A.R.P. Works workshop will start on April 15 and run through May 16. The fee is $20.</p>
        <p>We hope people looking for jobs will come to our free information session to learn about a practical approach that makes finding a job successful," Ms. Watsky said. "The information session, open to all, will be held on Wednesday from 10 A.M. to noon at Diversified Investment Advisors at 4 Manhattanville Road in Purchase."</p>
        <p>The program, conducted by professional career counselors, team trainers and a social worker, will focus on helping participants assess and redefine their job  skills and work experience, teaching them how to write an effective resume and cover letter, showing them how to tap hidden potential and find employment opportunities and strategies for overcoming employment barriers.</p>
        <p>"The last survey done by A.A.R.P. showed that people over 55 have seven times the unemployment rate of those in the 16-to-54 age range," Ms. Watsky said. "Our program tries to prepare people to re-evaluate themselves and their goals. Several years ago what people worried about was the kind of job they would be offered. Would it be nearly as good as the one they had left? Now the biggest fear people have is that they may never find a job again, any job."</p>
        <p>Participants who come to the program have college degrees and professional training, Ms. Watsky said.</p>
        <p>"In our last program, which was held in November, we had an international banker, a French teacher, a public relations executive, a journalist, an electrical engineer, a lawyer, a paralegal, an architectural engineer and even a minister," she said. "They all wanted to work, but, through no fault of their own, they found themselves unemployed; for many it was the first time in their lives. No wonder they came into the program very depressed. As part of the program, we had them meet with the social worker on a one-to-one basis to discuss their feelings."</p>
        <p>Registration for the workshop, which is co-sponsored by Mainstream, the retirement institute of Westchester Community College, is limited to 24. Ms. Watsky can be reached for more information at 381-2048.</p>
        <p>PENNY SINGER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
