<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Calls Victims 'the Best of America'</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="842283"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E7DF1039F934A35757C0A960958260" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Calls Victims 'the Best of America'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <dateline>DOVER, DEL., APRIL 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a chill military tarmac, on a day as gray as mourning, President Clinton today honored Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown and the 32 Americans who perished with him when their plane slammed into a croatian hillside on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>They were, he said, "the best of America."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a chill military tarmac, on a day as gray as mourning, President Clinton today honored Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown and the 32 Americans who perished with him when their plane slammed into a croatian hillside on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>They were, he said, "the best of America."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, his hand over his heart, stood with the grieving families early this evening and watched as the 33 coffins, each wrapped in an American flag, were carried from a C-17 military transport plane onto the tarmac of Dover Air Force Base and placed in two lines of hearses.</p>
        <p>"The 33 fine Americans we meet today on their last journey home ended their  lives on a hard mountain a long way from home, but in a way they never left American," Mr. Clinton said. "On their mission of peace and hope they carried with them America's spirit, what our greatest martyr, Abraham Lincoln, called the last best hope of earth."</p>
        <p>The President invoked the patriotism of the dead. "They believed," he said,  "that America, through their efforts, could help to restore a broken land, help  to heal a people of their hatreds, help to bring a better tommorrow through honest work and shared enterprise."</p>
        <p>For half an hour before Mr. Clinton spoke, the military pallbearers worked,  bringing out from the C-17 the bodies of Mr. Brown; Government employees some of them young veterans of the Clinton campaign; corporate executives; the aircraft crew, and a New York Times reporter, Nathaniel C. Nash. As a military band played "The Stars and Stripes Forever" and the national anthem, the dead were honored with a 19-gun salute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton hailed each group -- the "brave" members of the military, the "outstanding business leaders," the "Brilliant correspondent" and the "public servants, some of them still in the fresh springtime of their years, who gave nothing less than everything they had because they believed in the nobility of public service."</p>
        <p>For one moment his voice broke when he spoke particularly of Mr. Brown, 54,  who as chairman of the Democratic National Committee had played a critical role  in Mr. Clinton's election in 1992. "There was a noble Secretary of Commerce." Mr. Clinton said, "who never saw a mountain he couldn't climb or a river he couldn't build a bridge across."</p>
        <p>The muted families, wearing red, white and blue ribbons, and the extended family of Cabinet officers and White House officials who had counted so many of  the victims as colleagues and friends sheltered in a hangar opened onto the tarmac. Some mourners cradled babies. One man raised a child on his shoulders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton arrived at midday. He emerged from Air Force One clasping the hand of Alma Brown, the widow of the Commerce Secretary. Behind them came Vice President Al Gore side by side with Doris Meissner, the commissioner of the Immigration and Naturalization Service, whose husband, Charles F. Meissner, was  killed in the crash.</p>
        <p>They proceeded to Bulding 704, normally used for Air Force logistics, where  for nearly two hours the President, the Vice President and Hillary Rodham Clinton met privately with the families of the victims; each family was in a separate room along a long hallway so they could grieve in private. "It's a solemn atmosphere," said Ginny Terzano, a White House spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Later at the memorial ceremony, Mr. Clinton spoke of his moments with the families as he reflected that the victims of the crash "show us the best of America."</p>
        <p>"They are a stern rebuke to the cynicism that is all too familiar today," he said. "For as family after family told the Vice President and Hillary and me today, their loved ones were proud of what they were doing. They believed in what they were doing. They believed in this country. They believed you could make a difference. How silly they make cynicism seem."</p>
        <p>The Administration has been mourning since Wednesday, when word first came that Mr. Brown's plane, carrying Government and business officials exploring postwar reconstruction in the devastated Balkans, was missing.</p>
        <p>The wreckage was found along a rocky hill less than two miles from Dubrovnik airport. Officials said the T43 aircraft had made its approach to the airport off course, buffeted by a furious storm and guided by antiquated radio beacons.</p>
        <p>The audience today was made up of family members, but it was also a who's who of Washington's power elite, of Mr. Brown's fellow Cabinet members and senior White House officials.</p>
        <p>Besides the families of Mr. Brown and Mr. Meissner, the President brought with him on Air Force One Vernon Jordan, the powerful Washington lobbyist close  to both Mr. Clinton and Mr. Brown; Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, where Mr. Brown had grown up, and Henry Oliver, who had been Mr. Brown's driver  both at the Commerce Department and at the Democratic National Committee, which  Mr. Brown had led for four years.</p>
        <p>[After the ceremonies, President Clinton boarded his plane for the return trip to Washington and spoke to reporters about Mr. Nash's son, also named Nathaniel.</p>
        <p>["His two little sisters were too young to understand what was going on, so  he wanted to be strong," Mr. Clinton said. "He put on his Cub Scout uniform and  sat right up front. He wanted to see everything, but it was too much for him. He was just crying."]</p>
        <p>The bodies were to be kept at Dover for what is expected to be several days  as final identification is made by forensic specialists.</p>
        <p>Ms. Terzano, the White House spokeswoman, said that sometime next week, after the bodies are released, Mr. Brown will lie in repose at the Commerce Department and be memorialized at the Metropolitan Baptist Church in Washington. The funeral is to be held at the National Cathedral, where the President will deliver the eulogy for the man he called his "dear friend."</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, who had once served as a captain in the Army, is to be buried at  Arlington Ceremony with full military honors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
