<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Grooming Meets Good Groovin' At J. Luv's Hip-Hop Barbershop</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="842112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BARBERS AND BARBERING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARRIOTT, MICHEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JENKINS, JIMMY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D71339F934A35757C0A960958260" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Grooming Meets Good Groovin' At J. Luv's Hip-Hop Barbershop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHEL MARRIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARRIOTT, MICHEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S a steady buzz around J. Luv's Spot, and it's not just from the electric hair clippers that seem to mow heads nonstop at this cozy, new midtown  Manhattan barbershop.</p>
        <p>On a weeknight last week, several dozen people squeezed into J. Luv's narrow  expanse of exposed brick, parquet floor, black lacquer sinks and cherry-stained  wood cabinets to be part of a hip-hop happening that merges good grooming with good groovin'.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S a steady buzz around J. Luv's Spot, and it's not just from the electric hair clippers that seem to mow heads nonstop at this cozy, new midtown  Manhattan barbershop.</p>
        <p>On a weeknight last week, several dozen people squeezed into J. Luv's narrow  expanse of exposed brick, parquet floor, black lacquer sinks and cherry-stained  wood cabinets to be part of a hip-hop happening that merges good grooming with good groovin'.</p>
        <p>It is, said Jimmy Jenkins, better known as Luv, the barbershop's fashionably understated owner and creator, where the urban and the urbane can meet over their shared appreciation for creative haircuts and creative music.</p>
        <p>Far-fetched?</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenkins, a thirtyish, hip-hop record executive, does not think so. He said he is convinced in this era of proliferating theme restaurants -- Planet Hollywood, the Motown Cafe, the Fashion Cafe, to name a few -- that his shop's formula not only makes sense, but promises to make dollars and cents as well.</p>
        <p>In his show-biz world, "haircuts and music are synonymous," Mr. Jenkins said  between flashes of his incandescent smile.</p>
        <p>He even has a situation comedy in development, in which the star would be the barbershop as a kind of hip-hop crossroads of black culture.</p>
        <p>"One day you could have Shaquille O'Neal sitting in the chair," Mr. Jenkins said, noting that at other times the actor-director Bill Duke or the entertainment executives Russell Simmons and Andre Harrell could pay either a comical or uplifting visit.</p>
        <p>The shop's speakers were pounding out the latest street beats. Television monitors stood ready to churn out "flavor of the month" music videos. And young  men took turns getting $15 haircuts in a shop that, Mr. Jenkins contends, specializes "in everything."</p>
        <p>On another day in a back corner, Anthony Hamilton, a singer-songwriter, posed in an old-fashioned barber chair for publicity photos for his coming debut album. Outside, Heavy D, the rapper, actor and new president of Uptown Records,  eased up to the front door in a sugar-white $125,000 Mercedes-Benz SL600. Heavy  D, a bulging figure with a friendly face, shook hands and hugged his way to a chair for a quick trim of his cropped dark curls.</p>
        <p>The shop, at 322 West 49th Street, just south of Worldwide Plaza (the soon-to-be New York headquarters for Motown Records), is expected to profit from the area's concentration of entertainment officials and artists, said Mr. Jenkins, a Bronx native. He is the chief executive of J. Luv Entertainment, which operates his barbershop and record label, Polo Ground.</p>
        <p>As an Uptown Records promotions executive for more than eight years, Mr. Jenkins worked closely with his childhood buddy Mr. Harrell, then president of the company, which glittered with hip-hop stars like Mary J. Blige, Jodeci and Heavy D.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenkins said that Mr. Harrell, who recently became president of Motown Records, remains one of his most enthusiastic supporters. And to judge by the gallery of gold and platinum records on his shop's walls, Mr. Jenkins has a bevy of buddies in high places in the record industry. Many of them have been asked to attend a celebration Thursday of the shop's opening last month.</p>
        <p>Heavy D. says he plans to be a regular at his friend's barbershop.</p>
        <p>"I'll be here," he said, noting that his office is only four blocks away. "You know, a barbershop is more than a place to get a haircut. It's a hangout."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
