<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="842264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0D61339F934A35757C0A960958260" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-10</p>
        <p>YELTSIN SUDDENLY REVIVES News Analysis: President Boris N. Yeltsin has emerged from months of seclusion to suddenly become a highly energetic leader in the run-up to Russian elections  in June.1</p>
        <p>SPREAD OF AIDS SLOWS IN UGANDA Signs have emerged that the spread of AIDS has slowed markedly in Uganda after young adults adopted safer sexual practices. 1</p>
        <p>BEING DISABLED IN JAPAN The disabled in Japan say they feel excluded in a socitey where conformity is prized and physical and mental disabilities often arouse feelings of shame. 3</p>
        <p>TENSIONS RISE IN KOREA South Korea accused North Korea of sending 260 heavily armed soldiers into the demilitarized zone that divides them, creating a state of emergency on the border.4</p>
        <p>'BEST OF AMERICA' The bodies of 33 Americans killed in the crash in Croatia were returned to the U.S., honored by the President as "the best of America."8</p>
        <p>AN INTERNATIONAL CRIMINAL COURT Scholars and diplomats at the United Nations are close to agreement on a permanent international criminal court to deal with crimes against humanity.5</p>
        <p>THREAT TO JOURNALISTS IN CUBA Journalism has become even more risky in Cuba since the Government began a new crackdown on dissidents in February. 6</p>
        <p>National 12-19</p>
        <p>POLL SHOWS DOLE RESURGENT Senator Bob Dole, once ridiculed as unelectable, is now gaining ground against President Clinton on many traits, a new poll shows. 1</p>
        <p>WHO SHOULD POLICE POLLUTERS? Many states are adopting legislation protecting companies from punishment when they discover environmental offenses at their own plants, a move that proponents say encourages self-policing but that environmentalists say can be exploited by  polluters. 1</p>
        <p>SEARCHING FOR CONNECTIONS Several striking intersections exist between the life of Theodore J. Kaczynski and the trail of attacks in the Unabom case. 1</p>
        <p>MASSACHUSETTS MAELSTROM A tax-evasion case and a fight for the Speaker's job show just how trying times are for Democrats in the Massachusetts Legislature. 12</p>
        <p>ROCKING THE LEGAL BOAT An inmate in California has used his jailhouse-lawyer skills to shake the legal  establishment. 12</p>
        <p>7 MIGRANT WORKERS DIE IN CRASH Seven people suspected of being illegal Mexican immigrants were killed and 18 others were injured when their stolen truck crashed near a United States Border  Patrol checkpoint. 17</p>
        <p>Metropolitan 21-26</p>
        <p>HOSPITAL CLOSINGS ARE FORECAST With managed health care steamrolling through New York City, two leading research groups predict that in the next three years it will force at least 15 of the city's 78 hospitals to shut down and more than 12,000 hospital beds and up to 80,000 jobs to be eliminated. 1</p>
        <p>CRIME DECLINE SEEMS TO SLOW The double-digit decline in crime that New York has enjoyed in the last two years is slowing, statistics show, with an increase in rapes citywide and a growing number of murders, burglaries and robberies in several neighborhoods. 21</p>
        <p>Parents are sweating the private-school admissions process.21</p>
        <p>Obituaries 27-28 Greer Garson, actress. 27 Raymond Rubinow, led efforts to save New York City landmarks.28</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
