<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Acquittal, Woman Vows to Press On in Rape Trials</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="839617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GOUVERNEUR (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARTLE, MARK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABSALON, KRISTA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PISTOLESI, MARIO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUMMINGS, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURCIO, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STREETER, GREGORY L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DD1539F934A15750C0A960958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Acquittal, Woman Vows to Press On in Rape Trials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It poured the whole ride home from Canton to Syracuse Monday night, more than two hours of angry, windswept rain that rattled cars and turned the sky an eerie silver. Krista Absalon said she imagined that "God had opened up the heavens, and the angels were just circling around, crying."</p>
        <p>At least the rain made sense. For Ms. Absalon, nothing else does. She was expecting "guilty." She had waited five years, and yielded her privacy. Not even the notorious false start in her case -- the initial misdemeanor fines given to the five men who admitted having sex with her after she passed out from drinking -- prepared her for seeing the first man tried on rape charges go free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It poured the whole ride home from Canton to Syracuse Monday night, more than two hours of angry, windswept rain that rattled cars and turned the sky an eerie silver. Krista Absalon said she imagined that "God had opened up the heavens, and the angels were just circling around, crying."</p>
        <p>At least the rain made sense. For Ms. Absalon, nothing else does. She was expecting "guilty." She had waited five years, and yielded her privacy. Not even the notorious false start in her case -- the initial misdemeanor fines given to the five men who admitted having sex with her after she passed out from drinking -- prepared her for seeing the first man tried on rape charges go free.</p>
        <p>I'm so sad," she said yesterday in a telephone interview from her home. The words came out in a tumble. "I don't know how I can keep going. I couldn't even  go to work today. I can't do anything but think about what has happened, what this means."</p>
        <p>For now, her story is the story of all women who have sworn they were raped,  only to find a jury of their peers believed otherwise. All she can conclude after a jury on Monday found Mark Hartle, 29, not guilty is that her fight was not worth the trouble. "A rapist walked out of that courtroom," she said. "We tried everything we could. It's like the courts in St. Lawrence County don't want to believe what happened."</p>
        <p>Ms. Absalon, 28, has traveled an arduous road through the criminal-justice system. She was 23 when her story became "The Casablanca Rape," for the restaurant in Gouverneur where she had passed out on the ladies-room floor after downing too many beers and shots. Until a couple of weeks after the assault, she said, she was just another Jane Q. Citizen, working at a local hospital as a phlebotomist, raising two young children alone after a divorce. Then she heard about the party five acquaintances had had at the Casablanca, and were bragging  about.</p>
        <p>She pressed charges, and after a judge allowed the men to plead guilty and pay $840 each in fines and court costs, public outrage forced a re-examination of the case. Ms. Absalon said she felt vindicated when one of the defendants, Gregory Streeter, pleaded guilty to sexual assault in September and agreed to testify against the other four men.</p>
        <p>"Mark Hartle signed a statement," she said. "The way I look at it, he said he made penetration without my consent."</p>
        <p>At Mr. Hartle's trial, one of Ms. Absalon's former co-workers contradicted Ms. Absalon's testimony and said she had told of being awake through the ordeal. "There were people who told the truth and people who lied," Ms. Absalon said. "The jury chose to believe the people who lied."</p>
        <p>She knows some people in Gouverneur blamed her. After she spoke out on television about the case, some people grumbled that she was basking in the publicity. They said she was giving the town a bad name.</p>
        <p>Ms. Absalon said she had never wanted her ordeal to become a cause, never intended to go public. But she filed a $4 million civil suit against the men, and a radio station and a newspaper used her name in reports about the suit. "They just violated my privacy," she said. "Then everyone knew. I felt like I better stand up for a cause." Her voice trailed off. "If you can call it a cause . . . now."</p>
        <p>Ms. Absalon's sister, Robin, has said there were so many people in town giving her sister a tough time that she was forced to leave. But Krista Absalon  said she left her home in the small talc-mining town in northern New York for another reason. "I know there are people who are supportive of me," she said. "I just had to move because I couldn't stand looking at these five guys every day."</p>
        <p>She also did not want her children subjected to rumors after their names were printed in a local newspaper against her wishes. "That really hurt," she said. "They're just little people, and they don't need to hear about what happened."</p>
        <p>In Syracuse, where she lives with her boyfriend and has found a job in her field, life has assumed a rhythm. "I like it here," she said. "It's nice. My new boss has been very understanding. My co-workers have been really supportive. But it's not like I can run to my mother's house for a cup of coffee."</p>
        <p>Her family, she said, has remained close throughout the five years her case has dragged on, but it is taking its toll. She expects the three coming trials will be harder than the first. "I don't know how much I and my family can do this," she said. "But I can't back down now. I still have to stand up and do what's right, no matter what."</p>
        <p>She said she heard there was a big celebration for Mark Hartle Monday night at a restaurant in Gouverneur. "And I feel," she added, "I'm the one who should  have been celebrating."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
