<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turmoil Hangs Over Investigation of 9 Killings at Phoenix Temple</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="490422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDDHISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHOENIX (ARIZ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">THAILAND</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Phoenix</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DB163BF933A05752C1A967958260" item-length="845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turmoil Hangs Over Investigation of 9 Killings at Phoenix Temple</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, Nov. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The release of four Tucson men charged in the killing of nine people in a Buddhist temple last August has perplexed the Thai population and underscored already persistent questions about the conduct of the investigation.</p>
        <p>And the apparent turmoil in the case has resulted in a political battle between the county attorney and sheriff that some say could damage both men's careers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The release of four Tucson men charged in the killing of nine people in a Buddhist temple last August has perplexed the Thai population and underscored already persistent questions about the conduct of the investigation.</p>
        <p>And the apparent turmoil in the case has resulted in a political battle between the county attorney and sheriff that some say could damage both men's careers.</p>
        <p>"At this point, I don't know what's right and what's wrong," said Lek Laha, a member of the temple, Wat Promkunaram, about 20 miles west of Phoenix, where the killings occurred.  "I hope they know what they're doing."</p>
        <p>Noi Brantley, also a Thai, said temple members were confused about the legal details in the case and worried that the killers may have been let go. "They do not know who to trust anymore," she said.  Pressure From Relatives</p>
        <p>The killings drew international attention and have resulted in demonstrations in Thailand in sympathy for the slain Buddhists. And the arrests and handling of the case have brought protests here and caused frustration among supporters of the suspects.</p>
        <p>Relatives of the four suspects appeared almost daily in newspapers and on television stations here demanding that the men be set free. The families also held demonstrations in Phoenix and Tucson, creating public pressure on the county attorney's office to find evidence or let the men go.</p>
        <p>There is no question among investigators and others close to the case that the mounting pressure played a role in the decision by County Attorney Richard Romley to ask judges to release them for lack of physical evidence linking them to the crime.</p>
        <p>Less than a week after his release, Leo Valdez Bruce, 28, one of the Tucson suspects, filed a $10 million suit against the sheriff's office in Maricopa County asserting that he was the victim of civil rights violations and malicious arrest.  He said in the complaint that he had been subjected to 12 hours of intense questioning, was threatened with the death penalty and was given information by investigators that he included in his confession.</p>
        <p>The suit may be the first of several to be filed, seeking damages and adding further turmoil to the case.</p>
        <p>That same interrogation technique may be challenged by the lawyers of Johnathan Doody, 17, and Alex Garcia, 16. The two youths are being held in the murder case, linked to the crimes by a rifle used in the slayings and by their confessions that they killed the Thais to insure there were "no witnesses" to a planned robbery. They said in confessions that they were drawn to the temple by stories of riches inside.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia's father, John Garcia, a retired Air Force sergeant, has asserted that he was duped by sheriff's deputies into convincing his son that he should confess. The elder Garcia also said that Capt. Jerry White of the Sheriff's Department had offered his son a deal if he would testify that he knew the Tucson men, even though the youth had already denied having met them.</p>
        <p>The release of the four men cleared the way for the 66 investigators assigned to the case to focus on the two Phoenix-area juveniles, who confessed to the slayings and from whom two firearms were confiscated that tests linked to the slayings.</p>
        <p>The pair, who are friends and members of the Reserve Officers Training Corps at their high school in Avondale, Ariz., about 20 miles west of Phoenix, admitted to planning the temple robbery and to killing monks and other people they found inside to eliminate witnesses, court records show.</p>
        <p>Investigators also are leaning heavily on a link between Mr. Doody, who is half Thai, and his younger brother, David, who briefly studied at the temple to become a monk and who told him of money and other valuables inside, according to Mr. Doody's confession, which he later recanted.</p>
        <p>Despite thousands of hours of work, investigators have not produced any evidence against the Tucson men or established a link between them and the two teen-agers.</p>
        <p>Some prosecutors say they believe further investigation would turn up the evidence they need to prosecute the Tucson men. It was Mr. Romley's decision to ask county judges to release the four men because of a lack of evidence, which has angered those who think evidence could have been found.</p>
        <p>Sheriff Tom Agnos remains one of the few who says he believes that the Phoenix youths and the Tucson men carried out the killings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romley's motions to dismiss murder charges against Mr. Bruce, Michael Lawrence McGraw, 24, Mark Felix Nunez, 19, and Dante Parker, 20, are considered by investigators and others to be an attempt to shift criticism from his office to the sheriff.</p>
        <p>Some already are saying that the case poses a political threat for the sheriff. Mr. Romley also cannot escape blame, critics say, because his office rushed to seek grand jury indictments against three of the men and took the unusual step of taking the fourth man to a preliminary hearing to show the court, and the public, what he believed to be a solid case. But he changed his position after the youths' arrest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
