<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1997 ELECTIONS: RIGHT TO DIE ; In Oregon, Opening a New Front in the World of Medicine</title>
    <meta content="Y06SUI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971204T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1997 ELECTIONS: RIGHT TO DIE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DC1F30F935A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1997 ELECTIONS: RIGHT TO DIE ; In Oregon, Opening a New Front in the World of Medicine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore., Nov. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oregon voters, in heavy turnout, decisively rebuff proposal to repeal law permitting doctor-assisted suicide; law, approved narrowly by voters in 1994, has been held up by court challenges; vote reflects how fast public opinion has shifted on once-taboo issue; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As recently as 15 years ago, doctors were prosecuted for withdrawing life-support systems from dying patients, even at the behest of a family. Today in Oregon, after a surprisingly strong vote that takes one state to the frontier of medical ethics, doctors can begin helping terminally ill patients kill themselves.</p>
        <p>The vote reflects how far and how fast public opinion, at least in this state, has moved on an issue once considered taboo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As recently as 15 years ago, doctors were prosecuted for withdrawing life-support systems from dying patients, even at the behest of a family. Today in Oregon, after a surprisingly strong vote that takes one state to the frontier of medical ethics, doctors can begin helping terminally ill patients kill themselves.</p>
        <p>The vote reflects how far and how fast public opinion, at least in this state, has moved on an issue once considered taboo.</p>
        <p>There was little ambiguity to the Oregon vote. In a huge turnout, perhaps the biggest in 34 years, about 60 percent of this state's voters rebuffed an effort to repeal the nation's first assisted suicide law. The law, which was passed in 1994 by 51 percent to 49 percent, had been held up by court challenges.</p>
        <p>The law allows doctors to prescribe a lethal dose of drugs to a terminally ill patient who has made a written request to die. Opponents promise fresh legal fights, though the Supreme Court has held that the states have a legitimate right to pursue such laws.</p>
        <p>''This is a turning point for the death with dignity movement,'' said Barbara Combs Lee, one of the leaders in Oregon's assisted suicide campaign. ''Not because we won. But because we proved the citizens of the state can band together and overcome the political machinery of those who oppose choice.''</p>
        <p>At least one other state, Michigan, is in the early stages of a campaign to pass a measure similar to Oregon's. But given that assisted suicide has been turned down by voters in two states and legislatures in more than 20 states, supporters do not expect the Oregon vote to start a trend.</p>
        <p>Rather, the significance is that something considered sinful by many religions, and ethically abhorrent to medical professional groups, is now legal in one state.</p>
        <p>''There's been some suggestion that people didn't really know what they were voting for, that if only they knew about hospice care and pain medication they wouldn't go for something like this,'' said Dr. Timothy Quill, a professor of medicine and psychiatry at the University of Rochester, and a leading supporter of assisted suicide. ''But this vote says that people know better, that they don't want to be told what they can and can't do with their own death.''</p>
        <p>The Roman Catholic Church, which spent nearly $2 million trying to repeal the Oregon law, has tried particularly hard to make the point that any taking of a life is morally wrong. Today, church officials condemned Oregon's decision.</p>
        <p>''The vote is a tragedy for all Americans,'' said Cardinal Bernard Law, of the United States Catholic Conference. ''Most of all it is a tragedy for seriously ill patients, who deserve better care for their needs, not an invitation to suicide.''</p>
        <p>Oregon, more than most states, has upgraded its care for dying patients, becoming the No. 1 user of prescription morphine, supporters of assisted suicide say. But even with all the medical help available, patients want the power to control their deaths, they say.</p>
        <p>''I've been a surgeon in practice for 50 years, so I speak from experience when I say many patients would have liked to had this option available to them,'' said Dr. Glen Gordon, a former president of the Oregon Medical Association. ''Fifteen years ago, we heard arguments over refusing life support. Now it's accepted. The move toward helping patients at the end of their lives is expanding.''</p>
        <p>Doctors would not give lethal injections under Oregon's law. Rather, after two doctors have concluded that a patient of sound mind who has made a written request to die has less than six months to live, a prescription for a lethal dose of drugs could be written. Most likely, the dosage would be self-administered.</p>
        <p>Oregon has drawn up some early standards on monitoring the law, the dosages, and the type of drugs that can be used. Gov. John Kitzhaber, a Democrat who is also a doctor, was against repealing the law. But he says it may need to be refined, with tougher language on judging the mental competence of patients.</p>
        <p>Many doctors say Oregon will now get its share of botched suicides, prompting outrage. The image of Dr. Jack Kevorkian, the Michigan doctor  who advocates suicide as a choice for the terminally ill, was used by opponents of the Oregon law to urge voters to repeal it. ''He'll bring his machine and set up shop in our backyard,'' went one advertisement.</p>
        <p>Doctors in the state are split on how to proceed. Although the official professional organizations, like the American Medical Association and its Oregon chapter, have voted not to back the Oregon law, many individual doctors have come out in support of it. Under the law, doctors will not be required to prescribe lethal dosages if their patients wants it; they can opt out, if they chose.</p>
        <p>But any law that allows doctors to help patients kill themselves is a profound turnabout from the longstanding medical role of doctors as healers, the professional groups say.</p>
        <p>Opponents of assisted suicide promise another legal fight. ''This tragic vote means death rather than positive treatment for countless numbers of the most vulnerable in our society,'' said Laura Echevarria, of the National Right to Life Committee in Washington.</p>
        <p>James Bopp, a lawyer for opponents of assisted suicide, had successfully held up the law when he won an injunction from a Federal  District Court three years ago, arguing that it was unconstitutional. That decision had been overturned by the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit. Three weeks ago,  the Supreme Court refused to hear an appeal of the Ninth Circuit's decision, effectively lifting the injunction.</p>
        <p>Supporters of Oregon's law said they did not know of anyone who had requested help with suicide. Under the act, there is a 15-day waiting period after the initial request.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bopp said today that he will try later this month to get another injunction against the law. ''I would hope the merits of this case will be litigated before people start killing themselves,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>But lawyers for supporters of assisted suicide say the voters, and the courts, have now spoken. ''Jim Bopp's litigation is politically motivated,'' said Eli Stutsman, a lawyer  who is chairman of the group opposed to the repeal. ''He is essentially asking the courts to interfere with public policy issues that are up to the voters and legislatures.''</p>
        <p>Nearly $5 million was spent in the campaign, with opponents of assisted suicide outspending the proponents by $4 to $1. The campaign was emotional and personal. Neil Adkins, the son of a woman who was one of the first people to die with help from Dr.  Kevorkian, had said: ''I will probably die with this inside me, with this question: Could I have prevented my mother from dying?''</p>
        <p>The measure was defeated, in part, because Oregon voters were angry that they had to pass judgment again on something they had decided, political experts said.</p>
        <p>''The other thing was that public opinion has really moved on this issue from three years ago,'' said Jim Moore, a professor of political science at Portland State University. ''There was an appeal to libertarian, Republican types and an appeal to Democrats who have favor choice.''</p>
        <p>THE 1997 ELECTIONS: RIGHT TO DIE</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 4, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Nov. 6 about the Oregon vote on assisted suicide misstated the affiliation of Jim Moore, a political science professor who commented on the result. He teaches at the University of Portland, not Portland State University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 4, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Nov. 6 about the Oregon vote on assisted suicide misstated the affiliation of Jim Moore, a political science professor who commented on the result. He teaches at the University of Portland, not Portland State University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
