<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Organic Clothing: On Backs, Not Minds</title>
    <meta content="06ORGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cotton</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Levi Strauss &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nike Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gap Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adelson, Andrea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFDC1E30F935A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Organic Clothing: On Backs, Not Minds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Adelson, Andrea</byline>
      <dateline>TAFT, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fledgling organic-cotton industry almost went bust when consumers balked at paying higher prices for all-organic clothing; now industry is enjoying quiet resurgence, with help of several of nation's biggest apparel makers; farmers have talked Levi Strauss, Nike Inc and Gap Inc into buying big chunk of their minuscule output of all-natural fiber and simply mixing it with millions of ordinary bales they buy; in this way, clothing companies get chance to boast about their commitment to green cause without being saddled with unsold goods; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans cannot seem to get enough organic food. Consumption of fruits and vegetables grown without pesticides or chemical fertilizers has soared 20 percent a year since 1990, creating a $2.5 billion industry.</p>
        <p>But organic cotton? Forget it. When apparel makers introduced high-priced ecologically correct fashion lines in the early 1990's, like Levi Strauss &amp; Company's ''Naturals'' pants costing $50 to $60, shoppers put their environmental convictions aside at the cash register, and the fledgling organic-cotton industry faced ruin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans cannot seem to get enough organic food. Consumption of fruits and vegetables grown without pesticides or chemical fertilizers has soared 20 percent a year since 1990, creating a $2.5 billion industry.</p>
        <p>But organic cotton? Forget it. When apparel makers introduced high-priced ecologically correct fashion lines in the early 1990's, like Levi Strauss &amp; Company's ''Naturals'' pants costing $50 to $60, shoppers put their environmental convictions aside at the cash register, and the fledgling organic-cotton industry faced ruin.</p>
        <p>Now, though, with the help of several of the nation's biggest apparel makers, the industry is enjoying a quiet resurgence. The farmers, spurred on by Patagonia Inc., a outdoor-wear maker and longtime environmental crusader, have talked Levi Strauss, Nike Inc. and the Gap Inc. into trying an unusual experiment: Buy a big chunk of their minuscule output of all-natural fiber and simply mix it with the millions of ordinary bales they buy.</p>
        <p>Consumers will not get to wear all-organic shirts and sweaters, though they apparently never wanted to pay for the privilege. But the clothing companies will get the opportunity to boast about their commitment to the green cause without being saddled with unsold goods. And they will be able to sidestep a marketing quandary that may have undercut their earlier organic efforts.</p>
        <p>''They get scared to have a pure product; what does that make all the rest of their products?'' asked Sally Fox, founder of Natural Cotton Colours Inc. in Wickenburg, Ariz., which used to sell naturally colored cotton to Levi Strauss.</p>
        <p>The biggest winners should be the farmers, 30 at last count, who grow organic cotton on 100,000 acres, mostly here in the San Joaquin Valley of California and in the high plains of Texas. Instead of using insecticides, they plant alfalfa beds next to their fields to lure bug-eaters like lacewings. Compost replaces fertilizer. Seeds are planted deep to allow mechanized weeding.</p>
        <p>But with their output plummeting 55 percent in two years, to a projected 14,000 bales this year from a peak of 31,000 in 1995, they account for less than 1 percent of the nation's $6 billion cotton crop. So the new buying arrangements, hashed out over the past couple of years, came just in time.</p>
        <p>Referring to the companies that blend organic with ordinary cotton, Jill M. Vlahos, director of fabric development for Patagonia, said, ''If these companies that are blending remain consistent, it'll be fantastic for the industry.''</p>
        <p>For an endangered species, of course, fantastic is anything that offers hope. And organic farmers still face an uphill battle to overcome the skepticism of much of the rest of industry and the Federal Government, to say nothing of the indifference of consumers.</p>
        <p>''Cotton isn't even on consumers' environmental radar,'' said Nathan Boone, coordinator of the Organic Fiber Council, a unit of the Organic Trade Association.</p>
        <p>It ought to be, organic-farming advocates say. Most cotton is sprayed with herbicides, fungicides and growth regulators as many as 10 times during the growing season and then with a defoliant at harvest time, and the runoff of all these chemicals has become the greatest source of water pollution in many states.</p>
        <p>And the problem is worsening. California cotton growers have increased their pesticide use by 45 percent since 1991, state officials say, and today, half of all high-risk pesticides sold in the state are sprayed on the crop. Nationwide, the industry is coming under pressure as state and Federal regulators reconsider acceptable exposure levels.</p>
        <p>The arrangement with the three big apparel makers was the brainchild of William L. Allen, 61, leader of the Sustainable Cotton Project in Oroville, Calif., a nonprofit group of eight mentor farmers who are demonstrating how to grow organic cotton commercially. On average, their yields match the state average of 2.3 bales per acre.</p>
        <p>Getting their message out has been a struggle, and Mr. Allen reveals something of a siege mentality as he talks about his dream of ridding the United States' cotton fields of toxic chemicals.</p>
        <p>''Even though I have a Ph.D.,'' he said, ''the public thinks we're a bunch of idiots. We're bumpkins.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen speaks with missionary zeal about his group's purpose, saying: ''We're in a totally toxic community. We're addicted to chemicals. But it's all fixable.''</p>
        <p>By using their buying power to support organic fiber, Levi Strauss, Nike and the Gap want to encourage farmers who would be reluctant to risk the investment required for organic planting without purchase contracts, even though organic cotton sells for up to $1.30 a pound, compared with about 74 cents for the traditional crop.</p>
        <p>''We want to reduce the impact of pesticide-intensive agriculture,'' said Clarence Grebey, a spokesman for Levi Strauss in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Last year, the company began mixing organic fiber into its existing lines of jeans and khakis, and this year it will triple its organic purchasing to 2,300 bales, or 16 percent of the nation's output.</p>
        <p>The Gap is asking some suppliers to buy about 500 bales of organic cotton over the next year.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to put it in our garments; just prove you've bought it,'' said Maria Moyer Angus, director of environmental affairs for the Gap in San Francisco. It is not as sexy as a clothing label displaying a company's environmental credentials, she said, ''but it's effective.''</p>
        <p>Nike, which generates half its revenue from apparel, made its first purchase of 1,000 organic cotton bales this year, scooping up leftovers from last year's harvest. About 21 million Nike T-shirts shipped to retailers next fall will have 3 percent organic cotton content.</p>
        <p>''We haven't stitched a shirt yet with this blend,'' said Katherine A. MacCarthy, a Nike spokeswoman.  ''If it works, then most likely we would go into contracts.''</p>
        <p>The most enthusiastic supporter of organic cotton is Patagonia, of Ventura, Calif. Last year, it shifted its entire cotton line to organic fibers, and now buys 3,000 bales a year. It expects sales of its all-natural clothing to reach $20 million this year.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the hurdles facing the the organic-cotton movement are formidable. Pesticides are a big business, and manufacturers are unlikely to just go away. Organic cotton farmers also claim to be shut out of the cotton industry's national marketing arm, Cotton Inc., which is financed by a Federal $1.50 tax on each bale.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boone of the Organic Fiber Council said his group wanted the Department of Agriculture ''to spend money collected from our farmers for their benefit.''</p>
        <p>''It's taxation without representation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Cotton Inc. denies that it neglects organic-cotton farmers. And John W. Radin, the Agriculture Department's head cotton researcher, said cotton had become a cleaner crop than it once was, but called ''complete abstinence from pesticides'' unrealistic.</p>
        <p>Some people even question how devoted to the cause the three big apparel makers are. Sandra D. Sanders, a farmer in the Sustainable Cotton Project, doubts that they are inspired solely by a concern for the environment.</p>
        <p>''It's money,'' Ms. Sanders said. ''It's so they can say 'Look how good we are.' ''</p>
        <p>David Harrison, president of Trad Hound, a distributor of organic-cotton casual clothes in Asheville, N.C., does not care what their motives are as long as they encourage organic plantings.</p>
        <p>''It's not about putting on cotton underwear,'' Mr. Harrison said. ''It's about saving the farmer's life. It's about saving the ground water.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
