<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Paula Jones: Lessons</title>
    <meta content="06LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Susan Webber (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Paula Corbin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DB103AF935A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Paula Jones: Lessons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column on lessons of Paula Corbin Jones's sexual harassment lawsuit against Pres Clinton; says suit, dismissed by Judge Susan Webber Wright, showed importance of having judges who are prepared to rule without regard to political pressures, and pointed up failure of judicial system; says way in which case was handled did terrible and unnecessary damage to nation's politics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The surprising thing is that so many people were surprised when Judge Susan Webber Wright threw out Paula Jones's lawsuit.</p>
        <p>It was a worthless suit, reeking of politics. Most Americans thought just that. Then why the surprise? Because, as was often said before the decision, the political stakes were so high that the judge would duck it to a jury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The surprising thing is that so many people were surprised when Judge Susan Webber Wright threw out Paula Jones's lawsuit.</p>
        <p>It was a worthless suit, reeking of politics. Most Americans thought just that. Then why the surprise? Because, as was often said before the decision, the political stakes were so high that the judge would duck it to a jury.</p>
        <p>Judge Wright did not duck. And there is the first lesson of her decision: how important it is that we have independent judges in this country, judges prepared to decide without regard to political pressures.</p>
        <p>Most legal experts thought Judge Wright was correct in her judgment. Some disagreed with it, but no one questioned its legitimacy. That is the respect we pay to decisions by judges whose independence is protected by the Constitution.</p>
        <p>The judiciary is the one branch of the Federal Government that has that public respect today: the one seen to be functioning as it should. Congress is distorted by partisan warfare and the lust for money. The Presidency has been weakened by scandal and the obsessive search for more; the obsession has gone so far that some now talk as if lying about sex were an impeachable High Crime.</p>
        <p>Not that the judicial system worked perfectly in the Paula Jones case. Far from it. That is a second lesson. The way the case was handled did terrible and unnecessary damage to our politics.</p>
        <p>The worst mistake was the Supreme Court's decision last year rejecting President Clinton's request to postpone the Jones case until after his term ended. The Court's opinion, by Justice John Paul Stevens, said the case should not take much of the President's attention. ''Most frivolous and vexatious litigation,'' it said, is soon dismissed, ''with little if any personal involvement by the defendant.''</p>
        <p>Even as a general proposition, that notion was divorced from reality. Civil litigation these days, with its extensive pretrial discovery, can put appalling burdens on defendants. And in this particular case, Ms. Jones's lawyers turned the discovery process into a political onslaught on the President, with salacious press releases far afield from the legal issues.</p>
        <p>It is overwhelmingly clear now that no President of the United States should have to defend himself against civil lawsuits while in office. Congress should act to require postponement of such cases. Otherwise, after the example of Paula Jones, people with real or fancied grievances will be tempted to sue future Presidents.</p>
        <p>But once postponement was ruled out, did the Jones case have to be such a donnybrook before trial? To put it another way, why was the lawsuit thrown out only after Ms. Jones's lawyers had turned the pretrial discovery process into an anti-Clinton political campaign and the two sides had run up more than $5 million in legal fees? The answer -- the fault -- lies in the failure of courts to control discovery.</p>
        <p>Judge Wright wanted to keep Jones v. Clinton from becoming a media circus -- wanted to deal with it as an ordinary tort action. But the higher courts have allowed wide scope for discovery, not least in sexual harassment cases. So she must have felt unable to restrain the Jones lawyers from their pursuit of other alleged victims, even though in the end they were irrelevant when Ms. Jones could show no damage to herself.</p>
        <p>There is a lesson for the press, too, in the Jones case and all that sprang from it. The press has been too credulous, too ready to believe the worst about Bill Clinton, too slow to examine the bona fides and the financing of his attackers, too eager to report the unconfirmed.</p>
        <p>For the country, the most important lesson is the first: the value of an independent judiciary. And that should lead to reflection by Congress and the President.</p>
        <p>Congress has done severe damage to the principle of judicial independence in recent years. Members have threatened to impeach judges for decisions they disliked. Congress has stripped the courts of power to review asylum and other immigration cases. It has gutted habeas corpus, the historic remedy for unjust imprisonment.</p>
        <p>President Clinton was complicit in the immigration and habeas corpus legislation's blows to the constitutional role of judges. Perhaps now he can better understand why the protective hand of independent judges is needed by immigrants, citizens and Presidents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
