<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good Word From Mets? It's Young</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE113CF933A05750C0A964958260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good Word From Mets? It's Young</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>VERO BEACH, Fla., March 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anthony Young's fastball has always had explosive movement. It sinks, it sails. It darts and detours.</p>
        <p>"Tremendous movement," said Mel Stottlemyre, the pitching coach for the Mets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anthony Young's fastball has always had explosive movement. It sinks, it sails. It darts and detours.</p>
        <p>"Tremendous movement," said Mel Stottlemyre, the pitching coach for the Mets.</p>
        <p>And so now Young's fastball is being asked to perform its greatest movement. It is being asked to make the jump to the major leagues. Young, a 26-year-old right-hander with 10 games of experience in the majors, has been named to the starting rotation for the Mets in 1992.</p>
        <p>"What can you expect of him?" asked Gerry Hunsicker, the vice president for baseball operations for the Mets. "I think you can expect a solid effort every five days. But I don't think we should get carried away. Can you expect 15 wins? No." Sharp From Day One</p>
        <p>Based on Young's spring, though, that's not a preposterous question. From his first informal warmup, the right-hander has been sensationally sharp, and as often as not he's been entirely dominant.</p>
        <p>"His fastball does all kinds of things," said Stottlemyre. "Most of the time, it sinks -- late and hard. "</p>
        <p>Young, quickly and convincingly distinguishing himself from his rivals for the rotation, didn't allow a hit in his first six innings of the spring. Manager Jeff Torborg, who had heard more of Pete Schourek's curveball than Young's fastball in his informal briefings from organization personnel, instantly conceded his eyes had been opened by Young's start.</p>
        <p>More than anything, though, Torborg kept repeating that what he liked most was the way Young carried himself on the mound, his cold, concentrated stare unbroken by fortunes good or bad. That opinion was then cemented when Young endured an outing sabotaged by poor defense without complaint or even a grimace.</p>
        <p>"His worst day might have made his greatest mark," Torborg said. Shrugs Off Homer</p>
        <p>Of course, the grade he earned with his five innings of hitless baseball against the Dodgers last week didn't hurt. And today, Young added further evidence that if his spring has been a fluke, it's been a mighty consistent one. Absorbing a giant two-run homer by Eric Davis, Young survived seven innings in what became an 8-6, 10-inning triumph over the Dodgers here at Holman Stadium.</p>
        <p>"He doesn't appear to be intimidated by anyone," said Stottlemyre.</p>
        <p>And he no longer seems so taken with himself. Last season, Young, wounded at his failure to stick with the Mets after a quality spring, sulked through most of his season in the minors, distracted and ineffective. He was added to the Mets rotation when the team was out of the race, and finished with a 2-5 record.</p>
        <p>"I think he learned something about himself last season," said Stottlemyre.</p>
        <p>And in 1992, he has discovered another pitch, a change-up that is the critical component to his evolution as a prime-time pitcher. Stottlemyre, who believed Young threw the change-up too hard last season, modified the weapon and got Young to alter his grip.</p>
        <p>"We have some great strengths that we didn't have as a staff a year ago," said Stottlemyre. "And Anthony Young is definitely one of them." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DARRYL STRAWBERRY and BOB OJEDA, former Mets familiar with the strains of performing amid intense media scrutiny, both said they sympathized with the decision by the current players on the Mets to end contact with reporters and broadcasters in the aftermath of weeks of unpleasant reports on everything from criminal investigations to civil suits.</p>
        <p>"They are trying to at least stop the flow of blood," Ojeda said. "You don't know what somebody is going to say or whether someone is going to snap. It could make an ugly situation uglier." Said Strawberry: "It's a sad, sad thing. It's wrong, uncalled for, what people are trying to do to them. They're trying to begin a season and they are being targeted. It's going to carry over into the season, and that's a hard burden for a club to carry. They need to have peace as a team. That's what people have to realize. I never saw anything like what's going on there this spring."  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
