<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Says Chretien Will Not Undo Nafta</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="645038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRETIEN, JEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KANTOR, MICKEY (TRADE REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D9133BF934A15753C1A965958260" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Says Chretien Will Not Undo Nafta</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton and his aides said today that they did not expect that the Liberal Party's victory in Canadian elections would hurt the prospects for approval of the North American Free Trade Agreement or lead to renegotiation of the pact.</p>
        <p>"From my point of view, it will have no impact at all," President Clinton said this morning, discounting the Liberal Party's platform plank that called for renegotiation of the accord. "I see no reason to renegotiate the agreement or any grounds or basis for it, and I think we should just go ahead."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton and his aides said today that they did not expect that the Liberal Party's victory in Canadian elections would hurt the prospects for approval of the North American Free Trade Agreement or lead to renegotiation of the pact.</p>
        <p>"From my point of view, it will have no impact at all," President Clinton said this morning, discounting the Liberal Party's platform plank that called for renegotiation of the accord. "I see no reason to renegotiate the agreement or any grounds or basis for it, and I think we should just go ahead."</p>
        <p>Several Administration officials said they believe that Jean Chretien, the Liberal Party leader, is more enthusiastic about free trade than others in his party and less interested in renegotiating the pact. Chretien Has the Muscle</p>
        <p>President Clinton, who spoke by telephone with Mr. Chretien this morning, said the Canadian gave him no specific assurances on the trade accord. But, the President added, "nothing occurred in the conversation which made me have any doubt that our course of proceeding is the right course."</p>
        <p>A White House official who spoke on condition that he not be identified said, "My sense is that given the scale of Chretien's win, he is going to be under less pressure" to seek renegotiations. A smaller victory margin could have forced the Liberal Party to seek the support of the left-leaning New Democratic Party, which is implacably opposed to the pact.</p>
        <p>"What he has been saying is quite moderate," the official said. "What he has been saying is an open-access -- I don't want to say free trade -- but it's a very open-access, moderate agenda."</p>
        <p>Mickey Kantor, the United States trade representative, said Washington opposed any renegotiation.</p>
        <p>But at two news conferences and in an interview today, he refused to say whether the United States might be willing to discuss with the Canadians how to interpret the pact. The Administration is currently pursuing similar talks with Mexico on trade in sugar, fruit and vegetables. Well, There Are Other Accords</p>
        <p>Mr. Kantor said he had seen nothing in Mr. Chretien's statements suggesting that he would seek to reopen the pact. "The Canadians have raised no concerns directly with us and so, therefore, there's nothing to renegotiate," he said.</p>
        <p>A Canadian withdrawal from the North American Free Trade Agreement would have little economic effect on the United States because the 1988 United States-Canada Free Trade Agreement already covers trade between the two countries.</p>
        <p>If Canada withdraws, the United States would still conclude a pact with Mexico, Robert Rubin, the head of the National Economic Council, said last month. Without Canada in Nafta, free trade would be in effect between Canada and the United States and between Mexico and the United States, but not between Canada and Mexico.</p>
        <p>The House of Representatives is tentatively scheduled to vote on Nov. 17 on legislation to put the agreement into law; the Senate is likely to vote the following day. President Clinton has been aggressively wooing members of Congress, and met with several Representatives today.</p>
        <p>But Representative Sander Levin, a Michigan Democrat and a vocal opponent of the agreement, contended that the wide support in Canada for a party that favored renegotiation reinforced his view that Nafta should be redrawn. Fence-Sitter Leans to the North</p>
        <p>Representative Toby Roth, a Wisconsin Republican who is one of the few undecided members of Congress, expressed concern at the Canadian vote, saying it would influence him and others who have not decided how to vote.</p>
        <p>"I think that Nafta was a big issue in the Canadian elections," he said, "and I think that the American politicians have to take that, factor that into their equation as they're making up their mind as to whether to vote for it."</p>
        <p>Most Canadian political experts today blamed the crushing defeat of the ruling Progressive Conservative Party mainly on the weak economy and a badly run campaign. They assigned a secondary role to trade concerns and the loss of jobs to the United States.</p>
        <p>To bolster the trade pact, the Administration struck a tentative four-part deal with most House and Senate leaders today on how to raise $2.8 billion to cover the lost trade tariffs, worker-retraining programs and a cleanup program along the Mexican border, all facets of Nafta. Covering Nafta's Costs</p>
        <p>Bowing to pressure from conservative Republicans, the Administration agreed to increase the customs inspection fee for arriving passengers by only $1.50, to $6.50, instead of doubling it, to $10, as proposed last week. But $6.50 will cover only the cost of the inspections and no more.</p>
        <p>To make up the $2.8 billion, the Administration and Congressional leaders tentatively settled on three accounting maneuvers: requiring companies to send in income-tax deductions from workers' checks more quickly, requiring the Customs Service to use Internal Revenue Service data to discover undervaluation of imported goods subject to tariffs and projecting that the Agriculture Department would spend less to hold up crop prices as sales to Mexico rise.</p>
        <p>But the tentative deal was not put in writing because of objections from conservative Republicans. Representative Thomas W. Ewing, an Illinois Republican who organized a revolt by 26 colleagues last week against doubling the $5 customs inspection fee, said he and a dozen allies probably would not vote for the accord if it included even just a $1.50 increase.</p>
        <p>The Administration is also preparing to announce as soon as Wednesday that some money for the border cleanup would be used to set up a North American Development Bank to make loans to communities anywhere Nafta might cause job losses, officials said. The announcement is intended to woo legislators from districts far from the border.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
