<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; The Minstrel Tradition: Not Just a Racist Relic</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="645158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEFFERSON, MARGO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOTT, ERIC</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LOVE AND THEFT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD113FF934A15753C1A965958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; The Minstrel Tradition: Not Just a Racist Relic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO JEFFERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEFFERSON, MARGO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Love and Theft  Blackface Minstrelsy and The American Working Class  By Eric Lott  314 pages. Oxford University Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Of course the recent blackface colboration between Ted Danson and Whoopi Goldberg at the Friars Club knocked Somalia off the front page: culture wars on the home front leave no civilians untouched. Entertainment and politics are both about power, and entertainment is a lot more fun.</p>
        <p>All of which is at the heart of Eric Lott's terrifically smart and unexpectedly timely study of blackface minstrelsy. Rightly, he sees it as a crucial source for, and form of, popular culture. It was big business. It was a riot of ethnic and regional styles. And it was a psychic map that traced and exposed its fans' curiosity about the boundaries between races, classes and sexes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Love and Theft  Blackface Minstrelsy and The American Working Class  By Eric Lott  314 pages. Oxford University Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Of course the recent blackface colboration between Ted Danson and Whoopi Goldberg at the Friars Club knocked Somalia off the front page: culture wars on the home front leave no civilians untouched. Entertainment and politics are both about power, and entertainment is a lot more fun.</p>
        <p>All of which is at the heart of Eric Lott's terrifically smart and unexpectedly timely study of blackface minstrelsy. Rightly, he sees it as a crucial source for, and form of, popular culture. It was big business. It was a riot of ethnic and regional styles. And it was a psychic map that traced and exposed its fans' curiosity about the boundaries between races, classes and sexes.</p>
        <p>Blackface minstrelsy was an American descendant of commedia dell'arte and an American cousin of English music hall. At its baldest, Mr. Lott writes, it was "an established 19th-century theatrical practice, principally of the urban North, in which white men caricatured blacks for sport and profit," assuring themselves of their racial superiority in the process. More complexly, these caricatures were stoked by fascination as well as derision. The gestures, voices, songs and dances borrowed from blacks or imagined to be black, he goes on, were "less a sign of absolute white power and control than of panic, anxiety, terror and pleasure." Imitation always implies admiration of some kind.</p>
        <p>Put this all together and you have the form that gave rise to vaudeville and rock, Billy Crystal and Howard Stern, Al Jolson and Michael Bolton, "Saturday Night Live" and "In Living Color." And, given that its stars were all men, many of whom specialized in playing women (mainly viragos and wenches) onstage, it can be said that it paved the way for the mainstream cross-dressing of Milton Berle, Jonathan Winters, Flip Wilson and RuPaul (who, I'm told, attended the Goldberg roast dressed in a nun's habit).</p>
        <p>Minstrelsy ruled the American stage during the 1830's, 40's and 50's, playing to an economically and socially distraught country. The industrial North and its wage labor was pitted against the agrarian South and its slave labor. Immigrants were at odds with those longtime citizens who considered themselves the "real" Americans. Economic changes sent women into the workplace and jobless men back to the home. The anti-slavery movement was gearing up, as was the struggle for women's suffrage. Minstrelsy's first audiences largely comprised working-class men who were at the center of these crises and felt at the mercy of them.</p>
        <p>The first successful minstrel was a song-and-dance man named T. D. Rice, who, according to The Atlantic Monthly, was sauntering down a Cincinnati street one day in 1830 when he heard a voice singing: "Turn about an' wheel about an' do jis so/An' ebery time I turn about I jump Jim Crow." The voice belonged to "a Negro stage-driver lolling lazily on the box of his vehicle," and Rice was enchanted. "As a national or 'race' illustration, behind the footlights, might not 'Jim Crow' and a black face tickle the fancy of pit and circle . . .? Out of the suggestion leaped the determination."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lott is at his best tracking the ways in which a "national illustration" -- a figure, like Uncle Sam, meant to embody a nation's identity -- became a "race illustration." Black Jim Crow, thanks to slavery, embodied a nation's identity crisis. The key to this transformation lies in the unruly power of comedy, as this telling quote from Freud makes clear: "The discovery that one has it in one's power to make someone else comic opens the way to an undreamt-of yield of comic pleasure and is the origin of a highly developed technique." And the power to make other people comic is linked to the power to make one's own fears and uncertainties comic.</p>
        <p>Minstrelsy did just that. It began with black makeup and pseudo-plantation songs, dances and stories. It extended itself to mocking and ambivalent commentary on abolition, suffrage, political corruption, city life, country life and westward expansion. It made burlesque out of Shakespeare, ballet and the manners of the nouveau riche. It assimilated the passionate melodrama of "Uncle Tom's Cabin." It produced ballads, polkas, jigs and the syncopated predecessors of ragtime. And it accommodated, without removing the blackface, Irish, German, Italian and Yiddish accents.</p>
        <p>The beat goes on, and minstrelsy puts on new masks with every generation. Mr. Lott cites Elvis Presley's now-legendary blackface turns without makeup: what would he make of Chuck Berry's forays into whiteface? (Mr. Berry sounds like a rockabilly redneck in "Johnny B. Goode" and a bemused sitcom father in "School Days.") Irish, Italian or Yiddish accents have been replaced by Puerto Rican, Polish and Russian ones.</p>
        <p>And if rock videos are any indication, Asians are the new exotics of choice. They exude "Last Emperor" lust and mystery in Janet Jackson's "If I Was Your Girl." They exude technocratic lust and mystery in Madonna's "Rain." And, as the jazz musicians behind the black rappers in Digable Planets' "Cool Like Dat," they signify the ultra-hip, just as black jazz musicians used to signify it when they played behind white poets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lott is a professor of American studies at the University of Virginia, and he is so alert to minstrelsy's multiple impulses and strategies that I would like him to pursue them into the 20th century. But I want him to do so in a language that refuses to hide behind the mask of academic theory. Phrases like "the signifying chain linking working men to Bowery amusements" or the "inescapable synecdoches of plantation, factory and home" are deadly at this point. And the endless chain of quotes from like-minded scholars, reads, as Mr. Lott notes trenchantly in another context, "like a self-serving roll call of brand names." Every field, from American studies to journalism, has a standardized language. But it is up to scholars and writers to take the best of this and discard the rest. Mr. Lott has a mind of his own. Why not find a voice, too?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
