<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientist at Work: Dr. Patricia Wright; Saving Madagascar's Bounty for Its Lemurs and Its People</title>
    <meta content="11LEMU0AG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madagascar</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ranomafana National Park (Madagascar)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Patricia Wright</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Patricia (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Scientist at Work</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Madagascar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DB163AF932A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientist at Work: Dr. Patricia Wright; Saving Madagascar's Bounty for Its Lemurs and Its People</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Brody profile of Dr Patricia Wright, animal biologist whose research on rare Madagascar lemurs led to establishment of Ranomafana National Park that helped save island's endangered rain forest; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patricia Wright's trail to Madagascar and environmental heroism began in the 1960's with an act that is now considered the antithesis of conservation: the purchase in a Brooklyn pet store of an owl monkey, and then a second one to keep it company.</p>
        <p>Within a week of the birth of her own daughter, Amanda, the monkeys too produced a Brooklyn baby, and Dr. Wright, then a mother and housewife, became increasingly intrigued by the behavior of these nocturnal monkeys. The female monkey's only responsibility appeared to be breast-feeding. The male did all the parenting, carrying and caring for the baby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patricia Wright's trail to Madagascar and environmental heroism began in the 1960's with an act that is now considered the antithesis of conservation: the purchase in a Brooklyn pet store of an owl monkey, and then a second one to keep it company.</p>
        <p>Within a week of the birth of her own daughter, Amanda, the monkeys too produced a Brooklyn baby, and Dr. Wright, then a mother and housewife, became increasingly intrigued by the behavior of these nocturnal monkeys. The female monkey's only responsibility appeared to be breast-feeding. The male did all the parenting, carrying and caring for the baby.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wright, who had loved the woods growing up in upstate New York and had an undergraduate degree in biology, decided she wanted to study these monkeys in the wild. Books in the New York Public Library told her that the ''wild'' meant the jungles of Peru, home to wild boar, jaguars and deadly fer-de-lance snakes. She consulted Dr. Warren Kinzey, then an anthropologist at City University of New York, pumping him for guidance.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kinzey told her that without a graduate degree and university affiliation, no one would finance her effort. But she was undeterred. Through a friend, she arranged an affiliation with the New School for Social Research and persuaded Nancy Mulligan, a wildlife fancier from Rochester, N.Y., to finance the expedition for herself, her husband, their daughter, 3, and a native guide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wright's library research had led her to a site that turned out to have long since been converted from jungle to coffee plantations. No monkey had been seen there for 25 years. The next stop was a six-day canoe ride into the jungle, family in tow. Her guide soon got bored looking for monkeys in the dark, so one night Dr. Wright ventured alone into the jungle. Frightened by what sounded like wild boar and with her flashlight growing dim, she spent the night in a spiny tree, only to be scolded by none other than two owl monkeys whose territory she had invaded.</p>
        <p>They were the first of many for Dr.  Wright. Six months later, she returned to Brooklyn with notebooks filled with observations, the first data ever gathered on nocturnal monkeys in the wild.</p>
        <p>At Dr. Kinzey's urging, she enrolled in graduate school at the City University in 1977. After nine years, which included a 14-month trip to the Amazon, she received her doctorate.</p>
        <p>Then it was off to Madagascar, known for its rare species, especially lemurs. Armed with a grant from the World Wildlife Fund, Dr. Wright hoped to find the ''probably extinct'' greater bamboo lemur. Madagascar, in the Indian Ocean, had physically split from the African mainland about 150 million years ago, becoming a laboratory of isolated evolution. The shrinking jungles harbor thousands of species of plants and animals known nowhere else on earth. Eighty percent of Madagascar's wildlife is unique to the island, including nearly all of its mammals, 90 percent of its reptiles and amphibians, 80 percent of its plants and half its birds. The rosy periwinkle that is the source of the life-saving leukemia drug vincristine is one of 8,000 native plants. But all of this bounty was imperiled.</p>
        <p>''Flying over the island,'' she recalled, ''all I saw was devastation,'' the result of decades of slash-and-burn farming.</p>
        <p>En route to establishing that the greater bamboo lemur, a little primate with big, watchful eyes and charcoal-gray fur, was indeed alive and doing better than expected in the  rain forest, Dr. Wright discovered a new species of lemur with golden red fur, the golden bamboo lemur, which thrives on the cyanide-laced shoots of young bamboo, though how this three-and-a-half-pound primate tolerates an amount of poison that could kill a man is still anyone's guess.</p>
        <p>''But no sooner had I found this new species than I heard farmers sawing down 200-year-old rosewood trees, each of which takes about nine smaller trees with it,'' Dr. Wright said. An appeal to an official to protect the forest ended with a challenge to Dr. Wright to help establish a national park.</p>
        <p>She explained that the inroads into the rain forests were nothing more than stopgaps for the farmers living in one of the 10 poorest countries in the world. After only two years of farming on newly cleared land, the soil would be depleted, forcing them to cut down yet more forest. Meanwhile, the runoff of ochre-tinted soil ruined waterways and the loss of trees threatened the watershed. And since few Malagasy were aware of the economic potential of ecotourism, the farmers gave little thought to the fast-disappearing habitats of Madagascar's unique flora and fauna, which include 32 species of lemurs (16 of the largest ones have already become extinct).</p>
        <p>By the time Dr. Wright arrived there in 1985, more than 80 percent of the forests had disappeared from the island and there were only two national parks in Madagascar, the last one established in 1930.</p>
        <p>It took her five years to create the park, five years of days-long treks to visit farmers and explain the purpose of the park and its potential value to their families, five years of negotiations with village elders and government officials, five years of international phone calls and grant proposals to raise the money needed, not just to create the park but to give the villagers something for the land they would sacrifice.</p>
        <p>In the end, with the help of $6.27 million from the United States Agency for International Development and the support of various conservation groups, there was not only a 108,000-acre park but eight new schools, 10 renovated schools, four health-care centers, a team of visiting doctors and nurses, rural libraries with books on conservation and 133 villagers working in the park. In addition, the villagers receive half the entrance fees to the park, now visited by 10,000 tourists a year.</p>
        <p>''Pat's extraordinary contribution has been her ability to see the intimate link between the beauty and fascination of the animals and the lives of the people,'' said Dr. Alison Jolly, a primatologist at Princeton University who studies ring-tailed lemurs in Madagascar. ''It's so easy to say that what matters is the animals or what matters is the people. Pat has been able to say that what matters is both.''</p>
        <p>Among her many prized honors is the Knight of the National Order of Madagascar, bestowed in 1995 by the President of a country that now knows the rewards of saving its rain forests.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wright is executive director of the Institute for the Conservation of Tropical Environments at the State University of New York at Stony Brook and international coordinator of Ranomafana National Park, the rain forest in Antananarivo, Madagascar, rescued by her determination to save the only known home of the newly found lemur.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wright is now in her 13th year of studying lemurs, most recently the diademed sifaka, a large, black diurnal primate. ''I've finally come out of the dark,'' she noted, which makes her work attractive to Earthwatch volunteers, amateur researchers who pay to help support environmental research all over the world.</p>
        <p>Nowadays, Dr. Wright and an expanded research team work intensively during the six months a year that are not cyclone season. Though Dr. Wright and co-workers still sleep in tents without electricity, the campsite now has two buildings: a research station and a dining hall. The onetime rice-and-beans diet has been enhanced as well by a local cook who persuaded Dr. Wright to send him to cooking school.</p>
        <p>During the off-season, Dr. Wright teaches courses on primate conservation and behavior and ecology at Stony Brook. There she is joined by her second husband, Jukka Jernvall, a Finnish paleontologist and developmental biologist who works at the University of Helsinki when she is in Madagascar. He visits her there and they spend a month together each summer in Finland.</p>
        <p>''We have a tricontinental marriage,'' she said, obviously pleased with the unusual arrangement.</p>
        <p>She is also pleased with her study subjects. The sifaka, a spectacular leaping lemur that at 15 pounds is the biggest of the living lemurs, is a lot easier to track than owl monkeys. One by one, each animal is tranquilized and fitted with a color-coded nylon necklace. Once a year, the animals are weighed and measured, tooth impressions are taken and their reproductive condition noted.</p>
        <p>''As with most other species of lemurs, the female sifaka rules the roost,'' Dr. Wright explained. ''The female is first into the fruit tree where she gets the best and most fruit. Her mate dares not enter the tree until she's finished. If the male forgets and starts up the tree, she'll slap him in the face. If he persists, she'll lunge at him and may even nip him. He then backs away saying 'I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I didn't mean it.' ''</p>
        <p>And, of course, when it comes to courting, the females choose. The males fight each other, she said, but often, females do not choose the winners. According to the ''wimpy male hypothesis'' formulated by Dr. Alison Richard, an anthropologist at Yale University, the female, by selecting a loser, may insure her dominant status.</p>
        <p>With the sifaka's habitat protected, Dr. Wright said the main loss of these animals nowadays is the work of another endemic species, the fossa, ''a fierce mongooselike animal with big teeth and a big appetite and retractable claws that enable it to climb trees fast. The fossa is long, lean and mean and it eats lemurs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
