<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cleared of Rape by DNA, Man Is Accused in 2d Case</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="842542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEOXYRIBONUCLEIC ACID (DNA)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SUFFOLK COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOUT, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOTLER, KERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DD1039F93AA35757C0A960958260" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cleared of Rape by DNA, Man Is Accused in 2d Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STOUT, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A little over three years ago, a Suffolk County, L.I., man was freed after 11 years in prison when DNA testing seemed to show he had been wrongly convicted of rape. Now he is back behind bars, accused of another rape, and this time DNA testing is the prosecution's weapon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A little over three years ago, a Suffolk County, L.I., man was freed after 11 years in prison when DNA testing seemed to show he had been wrongly convicted of rape. Now he is back behind bars, accused of another rape, and this time DNA testing is the prosecution's weapon.</p>
        <p>Kerry Kotler, now 37, is charged with first-degree rape and second-degree kidnapping in an attack last Aug. 12 on a 20-year-old college student, who told investigators that Mr. Kotler posed as a police officer, abducted and raped her, then used a water bottle to try to wash traces of his semen from her body.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kotler pleaded not guilty yesterday at his arraignment before Judge Morton Weissman in Suffolk County Court. Bail was set at $25,000 cash or a $100,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors agreed with the defense lawyer, Jack T. Litman, that the use of DNA testing to clear a defendant of one offense and incriminate him in another is highly unusual, even in an era when forensic analysis of the genetic building blocks of life is becoming more common. Scientists say that no two people have the same DNA material, unless they are identical twins.</p>
        <p>But the story unfolding around Mr. Kotler, who Mr. Litman said has made a living as a commercial diver, seemed both tantalizing detective yarn and battle  over science.</p>
        <p>When he was released in December 1992, after DNA tests indicated he had not raped an East Farmingdale woman in 1978 and 1981, he cried tears of joy and said he bore no grudge against the woman, who insisted throughout that Mr. Kotler was her attacker no matter what the laboratory said.</p>
        <p>The Suffolk County District Attorney, James M. Catterson Jr., said that he had reservations about agreeing to Mr. Kotler's release in 1992, but that he had no choice, given the DNA evidence that might have caused the jury to decide differently a decade before.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman, who did not represent Mr. Kotler in the first case, said last night that he was convinced that his client was innocent of the 1978 and 1981 attacks. He declined to comment extensively on the latest case, saying he was just getting acquainted with the evidence and with his client.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Catterson and Randall Hinrichs, an assistant district attorney, said  the current case did not begin with the DNA material that was recovered from the victim's dress but rather from the fact that the woman was able to read part of  her abductor's car license number and note its make and color: a late-model white Pontiac.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kotler was arrested in Montauk Point a few days after the attack, driving a 1988 White Pontiac Grand Am that belonged to his girlfriend, the authorities said. Dog hairs found in the car and on the victim's dress were traced to Mr. Kotler's German shepherd, investigators said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman said a Court of Claims judge in Suffolk County ruled in January that there was "overwhelming evidence" that Mr. Kotler was innocent of the earlier charges, and that a civil suit to determine damages is expected to go to trial this summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman said Mr. Catterson's personal presence at yesterday's arraignment  suggested that the prosecutor has a grudge against his client, since the district attorney was criticized for his handling of the earlier rape case. Mr.  Catterson and Mr. Hinrichs dismissed any such suggestion and asserted that they  have strong evidence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Litman pointed to a recent State Police scandal in which several troopers were found to have planted evidence against suspects. Even if a laboratory can determine whose bodies fingerprints and blood come from, Mr. Litman said, it cannot determine that the evidence was gathered and handled with integrity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
