<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Andersen Sends New Proposal For Settlement To Government</title>
    <meta content="Y25AUD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/25/business/25AUDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andersen, Arthur, &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Half, Robert, International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichenwald, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glater, Jonathan D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Leslie R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, C E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Arthur Andersen &amp; Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DF153EF936A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Andersen Sends New Proposal For Settlement To Government</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Andersen Sends New Offer of Settlement to Government</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD and JONATHAN D. GLATER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glater, Jonathan D; Eichenwald, Kurt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyers for Arthur Andersen &amp; Co, in effort to head off impending trial, submit proposed settlement of its criminal case to government, offering fewer concessions than prosecutors were seeking last week when talks collapsed; seeking last week when talks collapsed; settlement proposal is made in letter to Leslie Caldwell, head of Justice Department's Enron task force; Andersen reiterates its commitment to acknowledge wrongdoing as part of deferred-prosecution agreement but declines certain other provisions that government has sought; civil settlement talks between Andersen and creditors and shareholders of Enron are on brink of collapse; Andersen reaches tentative agreement to sell its risk management business to Robert Half International, human resources firm that specializes in providing professional staff like lawyers and accountants; deal is another sign of Andersen's efforts to sell business lines and move closer to audit-only model of accounting firm; managing partner C E Andrews comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to head off an impending trial, lawyers for Arthur Andersen submitted a proposed settlement of its criminal case to the government yesterday, offering fewer concessions than prosecutors were seeking last week when talks collapsed, people involved in the case said.</p>
        <p>The settlement proposal was said to be made in a letter to Leslie Caldwell, the head of the Justice Department's Enron task force. In it, these people said, Andersen reiterated its commitment to acknowledge wrongdoing as part of a deferred- prosecution agreement but declined certain other provisions that the government had sought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to head off an impending trial, lawyers for Arthur Andersen submitted a proposed settlement of its criminal case to the government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trying to head off an impending trial, lawyers for Arthur Andersen submitted a proposed settlement of its criminal case to the government yesterday, offering fewer concessions than prosecutors were seeking last week when talks collapsed, people involved in the case said.</p>
        <p>The settlement proposal was said to be made in a letter to Leslie Caldwell, the head of the Justice Department's Enron task force. In it, these people said, Andersen reiterated its commitment to acknowledge wrongdoing as part of a deferred- prosecution agreement but declined certain other provisions that the government had sought.</p>
        <p>By late yesterday, the government had not formally responded to the proposal. However, when talks broke down last week, prosecutors formally withdrew their settlement offer and declared their position final.</p>
        <p>The letter to prosecutors was part of a swirl of legal developments in the Andersen case. At the same time, civil settlement talks between Andersen and creditors and shareholders of Enron were on the brink of collapse yesterday, people close to the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>With the letter to the government providing the bare bones of a full settlement proposal, the effort appears to be Andersen's last shot at a negotiated resolution of the criminal case stemming from the destruction last fall of thousands of documents related to Enron. Indeed, in an interview, Rusty Hardin, an Andersen lawyer, said that the letter was not an attempt to restart the aborted negotiations.</p>
        <p>''It really is our answer to their proposal of last week,'' Mr. Hardin said in a telephone interview. Last week, he said, government lawyers had given Andersen too little time to decide on and describe the changes the firm would have to make to avoid a criminal trial. ''They wanted a response sooner than we thought we could intelligently provide it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The government gave Andersen a deadline for last Wednesday, after which talks would be over. The firm's lawyers responded after the deadline passed by saying that they were not in a position to state whether the deal would be acceptable. At that point, prosecutors ended negotiation.</p>
        <p>The new proposal was said to contain as much as 90 percent of what had been on the table last week. The sticking points were said to involve procedural issues. While declining to describe those issues, Mr. Hardin has said in the past that they would have impeded the firm's ability to do business in the future.</p>
        <p>Since talks broke down, Andersen's lawyers and officials have said that the firm has not called off the discussions, nor is it abandoning the negotiating table. Mr. Hardin repeatedly expressed the hope that the two sides might be able to restart discussions and reach a resolution.</p>
        <p>But discussions of a settlement at this point are something of a high-wire act, because Andersen's trial is scheduled to begin in less than two weeks. Even if the government accepted the proposal on its face, such deals usually require additional work, which would have to be done even as both sides are preparing for a trial in the event the final terms are not reached.</p>
        <p>The letter was sent out after the firm's senior management team advised partners of its contents in a videoconference call yesterday afternoon. Patrick Dorton, a spokesman for Andersen, declined to comment on the letter.</p>
        <p>Andersen's efforts to settle the civil claims against it, which would resolve securities lawsuits filed against Andersen for approving misleading or erroneous financial disclosures from Enron, have continued despite the setback in talks with the government. An agreement has been hindered by disagreements over how to allocate the payout and how it might affect how much other parties -- like banks that helped to finance Enron -- would have to pay in any future settlement or judgment.</p>
        <p>If no deal can be reached, plaintiffs could end up with nothing because the amount Andersen can pay has fallen precipitously as clients have abandoned it. Andersen initially offered to settle claims for $750 million, with $250 million from insurance coverage and the remainder paid out of future revenue. That amount then fell to $500 million, and the most recent offer was for a total of just $300 million, people close to the talks said.</p>
        <p>Failure to negotiate a settlement would hamper Andersen's efforts to sell some business lines because buyers would be leery of picking up the firm's potential liability, said Roman L. Weil, a professor of accounting at the University of Chicago Graduate School of Business.</p>
        <p>''A settlement of the thing today could make it easier to sell off pieces of the business and disband,'' Professor Weil said.</p>
        <p>A dispute among plaintiffs has been a significant hurdle to settlement talks, people close to the discussions said. Large institutional plaintiffs like some of Enron's lenders, which are also potential defendants in suits by Enron shareholders, want to be able to reduce their liability based on Andersen's share of responsibility for Enron's collapse.</p>
        <p>Enron shareholders and their lawyers, of course, do not want to give up their potential claims against banks and other potential defendants.</p>
        <p>Andersen did announce yesterday that it had reached a tentative agreement to sell its risk management business to Robert Half International, a human resources firm that specializes in providing professional staff like lawyers and accountants. The deal is yet another sign of Andersen's efforts to sell business lines and move closer to an audit-only model of an accounting firm.</p>
        <p>''This transaction is consistent with our plan to move forward with the Andersen firm,'' C. E. Andrews, the managing partner of Andersen's audit practice, said in a statement yesterday. ''It will provide our people with career opportunities and our clients with continued quality service from respected professionals.''</p>
        <p>The deal, whose terms were not disclosed, would affect about 70 partners and up to 1,000 other employees, according to a person close to the negotiation of the transaction. Andersen has already announced layoffs of 7,000 employees and is negotiating several other possible deals for sale of business units with an assortment of buyers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
