<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Lost Almost $1 Billion, But There Were Bright Spots</title>
    <meta content="Y25PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/25/business/25PHON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, C Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AT&amp;T Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EEDD143EF936A15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Lost Almost $1 Billion, But There Were Bright Spots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">AT&amp;T Lost Almost $1 Billion, but There Were Bright Spots</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T Corp reports first-quarter loss of $975 million compared with loss of $373 million year earlier; revenue fell 11.3 percent, to $12.02 billion from $13.55 billion; chairman C Michael Armstrong comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T, the nation's No. 1 long-distance communications and cable television company, said yesterday that it lost almost $1 billion in the first quarter while its revenue shrank more than 11 percent, the fifth consecutive quarterly decline.</p>
        <p>Although those were hardly rosy results, in light of the carnage in the telecommunications industry recently, it was not such a poor performance. The company's shares fell 10 cents, to $13.75.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT&amp;T said that it lost almost $1 billion in the first quarter while its revenue shrank more than 11 percent, the fifth consecutive quarterly decline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT&amp;T, the nation's No. 1 long-distance communications and cable television company, said yesterday that it lost almost $1 billion in the first quarter while its revenue shrank more than 11 percent, the fifth consecutive quarterly decline.</p>
        <p>Although those were hardly rosy results, in light of the carnage in the telecommunications industry recently, it was not such a poor performance. The company's shares fell 10 cents, to $13.75.</p>
        <p>For AT&amp;T, perhaps the most positive aspect of yesterday's announcement was that its financial results for the quarter were generally in line with the forecast the company offered in January.</p>
        <p>Investors fear surprises above all else, and while many telecommunications concerns have revised their financial estimates recently or have missed their goals altogether, AT&amp;T's core telecommunications operations appear to be more or less on track to reach the modest 2002 goals that the company outlined three months ago.</p>
        <p>Moreover, there were bright spots for AT&amp;T in some of the areas it has identified as growth opportunities, like providing local phone service to business customers and handling Internet traffic.</p>
        <p>''I can't help but draw on what I've been trying to do for so long, which is to build a new AT&amp;T,'' C. Michael Armstrong, the company's chairman, said in an interview yesterday. ''And when you look at it, we really didn't have to change any guidance.''</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's cable television unit, though, lost many more customers in the first quarter than many analysts had expected, and the company appeared to reduce its financial forecast for the unit modestly. Comcast has agreed to acquire AT&amp;T's cable business in a deal that is expected to close near the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The AT&amp;T cable division said it lost 179,000 subscribers in the first quarter, with about 13.4 million customers. It said most of that loss was a result of the company's finally disconnecting customers who should have been cut off months ago because they had fallen behind on their bills. To some analysts, the bright side appeared to be that AT&amp;T was cleaning up its customer rolls. A darker interpretation was that only shoddy management could have allowed such a situation to develop.</p>
        <p>In January, AT&amp;T said the cable unit could be expected to generate earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization of about $2.52 billion this year. Yesterday, it modified that estimate to a range of $2.4 billion to $2.5 billion. AT&amp;T added that even that figure would be too high if a pending dispute could not be resolved with one of the companies that provides billing services for the cable operation.</p>
        <p>Besides the telecommunications industry's various bankruptcy filings and accounting scandals, its big story continues to be the erosion of the long-distance market. The proliferation of new long-distance providers in the 90's coincided with the mass adoption of cellphones and e-mail, prompting a collapse in long-distance calling rates even as calling volume declined at many companies.</p>
        <p>The overall weakness in the long-distance telephone market continues to take its toll on AT&amp;T.</p>
        <p>In the first quarter, revenue at the consumer services unit, which is dominated by long-distance calling, fell 22 percent, to $3.1 billion, from $4 billion a year earlier. In January, AT&amp;T predicted that revenue at the consumer unit would decline ''in the mid-20 percent range.''</p>
        <p>The AT&amp;T unit that serves business customers also suffered. Its revenue declined 8 percent, to $6.53 billion from $7.10 billion in the first quarter of 2001. The company said, however, that the unit's Internet-related revenue increased 37 percent. In January, AT&amp;T predicted that overall revenue would decline about 6 percent this year at the main business-services division. Yesterday, it revised that to a 7 percent decline.</p>
        <p>Not counting special charges, AT&amp;T said it would have earned 6 cents a share. Financial analysts surveyed by Thomson Financial/First Call had predicted a profit of 4 cents on that basis. Including all charges, AT&amp;T reported a net loss of $975 million, or 28 cents a share. A year earlier, the company posted a loss of $373 million, or 10 cents a share. Revenue fell 11.3 percent, to $12.02 billion from $13.55 billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
