<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro-North Braces for a Strike, Again</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">METRO-NORTH COMMUTER RAILROAD CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ-PENA, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D81039F934A15752C1A963958260" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro-North Braces for a Strike, Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEREZ-PENA, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 15 of its unions still without a contract and a strike possible as early as tomorrow, the Metro-North Commuter Railroad plans to distribute its strike contingency plan today at Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>Negotiators for the teamsters and the Metropolitan Transportation Authority,  Metro-North's parent agency, met over the weekend, and talks are scheduled to resume with a coalition of other unions this morning to try to reach contracts retroactive to Jan. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 15 of its unions still without a contract and a strike possible as early as tomorrow, the Metro-North Commuter Railroad plans to distribute its strike contingency plan today at Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>Negotiators for the teamsters and the Metropolitan Transportation Authority,  Metro-North's parent agency, met over the weekend, and talks are scheduled to resume with a coalition of other unions this morning to try to reach contracts retroactive to Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>It's all up in the air," William Mitchell, general chairman of the International Association of Machinists, said yesterday. "We're contemplating a  strike, but we're also hopeful that there will be an agreement. We'll know tomorrow some time, but right now, we can't give the passengers any assurances."</p>
        <p>Metro-North has developed a contingency plan that includes bus service from 21 of its stations outside the city, and from several major parking lots like those at Rye Playland and Yonkers Raceway, that would transport riders to subway stations in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Details of the contingency service are contained in a brochure that will be handed out to riders today on the main concourse at Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>"It outlines their options, which, unfortunately, are not comparable to Metro-North service," said Marjorie Anders, a spokeswoman for the railroad. "In  the event of a strike, we expect to be able to handle about 60 percent of our normal morning rush hour, which is about 70,000 people."</p>
        <p>Metro-North commuters can also park at Yankee Stadium and Shea Stadium and take subways into the city, Ms. Anders said.</p>
        <p>A coalition of 17 Metro-North unions threatened a strike in June and July, before the M.T.A. invoked a provision of Federal law that postponed any job action for four months. That waiting period will expire at 12:01 A.M. tomorrow,  after which the M.T.A. cannot prevent a strike.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers and the United Transportation Union, representing conductors, signed tentative contracts, subject to ratification votes by their members. Along with the teamsters, the two unions were the most defiant in the earlier round of talks, and railroad officials hoped that with their contract settled, the other unions would fall into line and settle.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, John Cunningham, an M.T.A. spokesman, said, "We believe our differences with the teamsters are modest, and we're hopeful."</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, two mediation boards appointed by President Clinton recommended a 10.3 percent wage increase over three years for the unions, along  with modest changes in work rules that would save the railroad money and cost workers some extra income beyond their base salaries. The two unions that settled reportedly agreed to 10.3 percent over four years and limited work rule  changes, while winning other concessions, like additional sick leave.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
