<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Eccentric's Legacy Gets a Pro's Touch</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ESHERICK MUSEUM (PAOLI, PA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESHERICK, WHARTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DC153AF937A25755C0A966958260" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Eccentric's Legacy Gets a Pro's Touch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL deCOURCY HINDS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HINDS, MICHAEL DECOURCY</byline>
      <dateline>PAOLI, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THIS part of the world is thick with historic sites and small museums like the home of Wharton Esherick, a sculptor and furniture maker who reputedly refused to do anything he didn't enjoy. ''If it isn't fun, don't bother doing it,'' he used to say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THIS part of the world is thick with historic sites and small museums like the home of Wharton Esherick, a sculptor and furniture maker who reputedly refused to do anything he didn't enjoy. ''If it isn't fun, don't bother doing it,'' he used to say.</p>
        <p>THIS part of the world is thick with historic sites and small museums like the home of Wharton Esherick, a sculptor and furniture maker who reputedly refused to do anything he didn't enjoy. ''If it isn't fun, don't bother doing it,'' he used to say.</p>
        <p>For 18 years the Esherick Museum, down the road from a covered bridge and octagonal school house in this westernmost Main Line suburb near Valley Forge, has been a family affair, open primarily on weekends by appointment. Now the family has hired a full-time director to operate the museum and to raise a $1 million endowment to insure its survival.</p>
        <p>But trying to raise money for a tiny museum in the suburbs of Philadelphia, particularly when major arts organizations are scrambling for contributions, will be difficult. Joel N. Bloom, president of the Franklin Institute, said, ''The only way for a small museum like this to succeed is to find something it can sell to visitors, like reproductions.''</p>
        <p>The Esherick Museum has no plans to go that route, even though an original Esherick table sells for more than $20,000, suggesting there might be a demand for reproductions.</p>
        <p>Esherick, considered by many the dean of American craftsmen, died in 1970 at the age of 83. He left no money to help preserve his house or artwork.</p>
        <p>About 3,000 people a year visit the museum, adults paying $5 and children $3. The building, of stone, concrete and wood, is filled with sensual shapes, hidden spaces and childish fancies. There are secret drawers, trapdoors and light switches made from oxtail bones left over from soup made by Esherick.</p>
        <p>There are no straight lines; even the carved bookshelves sag. The place is a merry-go-round of curving sofas, tables, chairs, spiral stairs and abstract sculptures that radiate off curving walls. It is dizzying at times, but eventually it all meshes like a dovetail joint, since Esherick made or designed every piece.</p>
        <p>''As soon as I walked into this place, I said, 'Yeah, I want to do this,' '' said the new director, Robert Leonard, 50. He started out as a banker, then raised money for social service organizations before taking the museum job in January.</p>
        <p>''I was overwhelmed by the amount of creation and the inherent joy in it,'' he continued.''This house says, 'Look what is possible to do with your life.' It definitely needs to be preserved so people can see it and feel inspired.''</p>
        <p>Some people advised the Esherick family to donate their collection to museums so more people could appreciate it, said Ruth Esherick Bascom, a daughter of the sculptor.</p>
        <p>''You can't pick up a dining room floor and donate it to a museum,'' said Mrs. Bascom, who lives with her husband, Mansfield, a retired architect, in a series of hexagonal structures next door that once were her father's workshop. ''We felt it should all stay together. Anyway, this is our only inheritance. We're not rich.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
