<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I. D. White, World War II Commander, Dies at 89</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="361070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITE, I D (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOWLER, GLENN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DE1F38F937A25755C0A966958260" item-length="315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I. D. White, World War II Commander, Dies at 89</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN FOWLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FOWLER, GLENN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gen. I. D. White, who commanded the Second Armored Division in the European Theater in World War II and later was overall commander of United States Army forces in the Pacific, died Monday at Mary Hitchcock Memorial Hospital in Hanover, N.H. He was 89 years old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gen. I. D. White, who commanded the Second Armored Division in the European Theater in World War II and later was overall commander of United States Army forces in the Pacific, died Monday at Mary Hitchcock Memorial Hospital in Hanover, N.H. He was 89 years old.</p>
        <p>Gen. I. D. White, who commanded the Second Armored Division in the European Theater in World War II and later was overall commander of United States Army forces in the Pacific, died Monday at Mary Hitchcock Memorial Hospital in Hanover, N.H. He was 89 years old.</p>
        <p>Associates said General White, who retired in 1961 and lived in Dublin, N.H., died of natural causes.</p>
        <p>He joined the Second Armored Division in 1940 as a major and led units of the division in North Africa, Sicily, France and Belgium.</p>
        <p>In 1944, at the age of 43, he was promoted to major general and given command of the division. In April 1945, the division played a central role in sealing off German forces in the Ruhr Valley, capturing more than 45,000 prisoners. His troops were the first Allied soldiers to reach and cross the Elbe River in Germany, where British and American armies linked up with Soviet armies.</p>
        <p>Corps Commander in Korea</p>
        <p>In 1952 General White commanded the X Corps in the Korean War, and later supervised the training of four South Korean divisions. At his retirement he was commander of all Army forces in the Pacific.</p>
        <p>Isaac Davis White was born in Peterborough, N.H., and graduated from Norwich University in Northfield, Vt., in 1922, where he later became a trustee.</p>
        <p>An expert horseman who joined the Seventh Cavalry Brigade in the 1930's, he managed the Army equestrian team at the 1948 Olympic Games in London.</p>
        <p>Much of his Army career paralleled the development of armored tactics and weapons. As an adviser to the Army Chief of Staff, he helped speed the design and manufacture of armored weapons in the Korean War.</p>
        <p>General White held more than 13 American and 16 foreign decorations, including the Distinguished Service Medal with Oak Leaf Cluster and the French Croix de Guerre.</p>
        <p>His wife of 61 years, the former Julia Cotton, died last July 31. There are no immediate survivors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
