<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The King of Conflict of Interest</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="327759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KING, DON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DD1038F93BA25751C0A966958260" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The King of Conflict of Interest</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For nearly two years now, Don King and Mike Tyson have emerged as the Siamese twins of boxing. Siamese twins joined at the money clip. One is seldom seen in public without the other. And last Tuesday, as King apologized meekly and weakly for having protested that James (Buster) Douglas didn't deserve to be the new heavyweight champion because of a long count, the promoter kept using the word ''we,'' meaning himself and the dethroned champion who was sitting nearby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For nearly two years now, Don King and Mike Tyson have emerged as the Siamese twins of boxing. Siamese twins joined at the money clip. One is seldom seen in public without the other. And last Tuesday, as King apologized meekly and weakly for having protested that James (Buster) Douglas didn't deserve to be the new heavyweight champion because of a long count, the promoter kept using the word ''we,'' meaning himself and the dethroned champion who was sitting nearby.</p>
        <p>For nearly two years now, Don King and Mike Tyson have emerged as the Siamese twins of boxing. Siamese twins joined at the money clip. One is seldom seen in public without the other. And last Tuesday, as King apologized meekly and weakly for having protested that James (Buster) Douglas didn't deserve to be the new heavyweight champion because of a long count, the promoter kept using the word ''we,'' meaning himself and the dethroned champion who was sitting nearby.</p>
        <p>''But if you have options on Douglas's next few fights,'' King was asked, ''why don't you use 'we' when talking about him?''</p>
        <p>With a cackle, the promoter spouted that ''we'' was a familiar word among boxing people, that the late Yank Durham, once Joe Frazier's manager, often used ''we'' to couple himself with his heavyeight champion.</p>
        <p>Thank you, Don King. Thank you for sharpening the point of the question.</p>
        <p>Yank Durham was entitled to use ''we,'' as so many other managers do, because Yank Durham was a manager, not a promoter. In boxing, a promoter isn't allowed to be a manager. In boxing, this is the ultimate conflict of interest. But during Tyson's estrangement from Bill Cayton, the dethroned champion's manager of record, Don King walks and talks in public defiance of boxing law as if he were Tyson's manager.</p>
        <p>''No person,'' reads the World Boxing Council bylaws, ''is permitted to act concurrently both as manager of a boxer and as promoter of a W.B.C. championship contest involving the same boxer, and so as to avoid any potential for a conflict of interest, no contest will be certified by the W.B.C. if any person acts in such dual capacity.''</p>
        <p>King argues that he's merely an ''adviser, a friend'' to Tyson, and Jose Sulaiman, the W.B.C. president, accepts that explanation as if it were written on a stone tablet. Sulaiman, of course, also accepted King's protest that Douglas had been granted a long count near the end of the eighth round. But a promoter shouldn't be allowed to be even an adviser.</p>
        <p>If King wants to be Tyson's adviser, fine. If he wants to be a promoter, fine. One or the other, but not both.</p>
        <p>In the records of the New York State Athletic Commission and other boxing organizations, Bill Cayton remains Tyson's de jure manager. But it's obvious that King is now Tyson's de facto manager. For proof, simply consult the videotape of King's brazen protest of Douglas's long count.</p>
        <p>As a promoter, that was none of King's business. But as Tyson's ''adviser,'' it was King's business.</p>
        <p>King also acted as Larry Holmes's adviser throughout that heavyweight champion's reign.</p>
        <p>Not that King invented conflict of interest in boxing. On July 28, 1952, Rocky Marciano, who would dethrone Jersey Joe Walcott as the heavyweight champion two months later, arrived early at the Madison Square Garden lobby to weigh in for his fight that night with Harry (Kid) Matthews, who was late. Al Weill, then the Garden matchmaker for the International Boxing Club, was whispered to be Marciano's undercover manager although no proof existed. But as Robert K. Christenberry, then the chairman of the New York State Athletic Commission, waited impatiently for Matthews, he turned to Weill.</p>
        <p>''Where's Matthews?'' the chairman asked.</p>
        <p>''How should I know?'' Weill replied. ''All I know is, my fighter's here.'' Weill had called Marciano ''my fighter.'' That afternoon, Christenberry granted the Garden 24 hours to get a new matchmaker. Otherwise, the chairman threatened to lift the Garden's license. That night, Weill resigned as matchmaker; he openly managed Marciano for the remainder of the undefeated champion's career.</p>
        <p>But with his brazen protest, King is now vulnerable to inspection, if not investigation, at a time when boxing is under siege.</p>
        <p>Instant critics of the not-so-sweet science usually jump on a soap box only when a boxer is killed in the ring. But this time King's shabby treatment of Douglas has aroused and annoyed even those who ordinarily don't care that much about boxing.</p>
        <p>As a promoter, King should have hailed Douglas's triumph as a boon for boxing. But as an ''adviser,'' he whined over Tyson's loss.</p>
        <p>The moral is, don't try to rewrite the storyline of an unbettable underdog who not only defeated the undisputed, undefeated and supposedly unconquerable champion, but also beat him clearly and soundly. And the result is, politicians and other caring persons are wondering: who is Don King and why was he taking Mike Tyson's side when he's supposed to be a neutral promoter?</p>
        <p>In Washington, Rep. Bill Richardson, Democrat of New Mexico, talked of introducing Federal legislation to police promoters and such organizations as the World Boxing Council, the World Boxing Association and the International Boxing Federation. Other politicians, such as Jim Florio, the Governor of New Jersey, a casino-boxing state, also threaten to question boxing's law and order.</p>
        <p>Not that a Federal boxing commission is necessary. If properly operated, a nongovernmental national boxing commission would provide enough clout to regulate promoters.</p>
        <p>The public perception is that boxers and their managers are free agents just waiting to listen to the best deal. The reality is that although three primary promoters exist (Bob Arum and Dan Duva in addition to King), the best boxers are tied to long-term contracts or options. King, for example, has acknowledged holding ''quite a few'' options on Douglas, reportedly for five or six fights.</p>
        <p>Eliminate the long-term contracts. Eliminate the options. And eliminate Don King's dual role as Mike Tyson's promoter and manager.</p>
        <p>Don King hasn't dared to call Mike Tyson ''my fighter,'' at least not when anybody in authority was listening. But when asked about using the word ''we'' to link himself with the dethroned champion, he instantly identified with a manager, Yank Durham, not a promoter. Surely a Freudian slip that deserves to be ruled a knockdown, if not a knockout.</p>
        <p>SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
