<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living in: Fort Lee</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="327892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FORT LEE (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHESLOW, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living In</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA163EF93BA25751C0A966958260" item-length="1675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living in: Fort Lee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY CHESLOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHESLOW, JERRY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THE name George Washington brings grimaces to the faces of many Fort Lee residents. But it's not the Father of the Country - who laid out a fort on the site in 1776 - they have a grudge against; it's the bridge named for him, the one that was opened in 1931 to connect New Jersey with Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THE name George Washington brings grimaces to the faces of many Fort Lee residents. But it's not the Father of the Country - who laid out a fort on the site in 1776 - they have a grudge against; it's the bridge named for him, the one that was opened in 1931 to connect New Jersey with Manhattan.</p>
        <p>THE name George Washington brings grimaces to the faces of many Fort Lee residents. But it's not the Father of the Country - who laid out a fort on the site in 1776 - they have a grudge against; it's the bridge named for him, the one that was opened in 1931 to connect New Jersey with Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Although seven major highways funnel into the double-decker bridge, Fort Lee's narrow Main Street is always jammed during the morning rush hour as Manhattan-bound drivers try to save a few minutes on their way to the toll booths.</p>
        <p>''Every year, one hundred million cars cross that bridge, half of which is in Fort Lee,'' complained Mayor Nicholas Corviscello. ''The gridlock is horrible. And we don't get a penny in revenue from it. The bridge has a $250 million assessed valuation, but for us, it's a thorn in the side.''</p>
        <p>''We're taking on more people than this town is cut out for,'' said Theodore Grieco, the borough's former Police Chief and a longtime resident. ''The traffic volume just doesn't go with the town. From 7 to 9 A.M. it's useless to try and get through the center.''</p>
        <p>Easy access to Manhattan not only creates congestion, but has also pushed real estate prices sky high. The total assessed valuation of the 2.5-square-mile borough is $3.4 billion, making it Bergen County's most valuable municipality and the state's sixth most valuable. Nearly all the taxable property is residential, although there are several new high-rise office buildings near the bridge.</p>
        <p>The tax base is expected to increase significantly soon with the development of a 15-acre tract owned by Harry B. Helmsley near the bridge approach. According to the Mayor, the tract, which is worth about $100 million, is the most valuable piece of undeveloped land in the Northeast. Mr. Helmsley has already received local approval to put up two large office buildings and two high-rise apartment buildings on the site. The project still requires county approval.</p>
        <p>Fort Lee's granite Palisades cliffs, which tower 300 feet above the river, helped Washington harass the British during the blockade of New York in 1776. According to local histories, Continental troops sank ships in a line across the Hudson River from Fort Washington, in what is now Washington Heights, to Fort Constitution, on the Palisades. The two forts trained their cannon toward the Hudson, to further obstruct the passage of British ships. Eventually, Fort Constitution was outflanked and Washington's army retreated over what is now Main Street, en route to Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Remnants of Fort Constitution, which was renamed Fort Lee, after General Washington's assistant, Gen. Charles Lee, are preserved in Historic Park, a 200-acre site that includes part of the Palisades and much of the riverfront property below. Historic Park, part of the Palisades Interstate Park system, includes a museum containing Revolutionary War relics and dioramas depicting Revolutionary War battles. It is open, free, from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Wednesday through Sunday, from April 1 through Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>In addition to Historic Park, about 50 acres of Fort Lee is parkland, owned by the borough. As a result, Fort Lee has an abundance of tennis courts, wading pools, baseball fields, picnic areas and playgrounds. It also has a recreation center with a 500-seat auditorium in William T. Birch Park, named for a Fort Lee policeman killed in the line of duty in 1966.</p>
        <p>Fort Lee was also an early center of the American movie industry. According to Rita Altomara, author of ''Hollywood on the Palisades,'' more than 900 films were shot in Fort Lee between 1903 and 1927. At one time, 10 large movie studios, including Metro and Universal, operated in the borough. Among the stars who acted in Fort Lee were Douglas Fairbanks Sr., Mary Pickford, Charlie Chaplin, Lillian Gish and Fatty Arbuckle.</p>
        <p>The presence of the industry gave the town a cachet and attracted many visitors. Among the institutions that served them was the Fort Lee Park Hotel, set on 40 acres overlooking the Palisades. It had bowling alleys, a billiard room and restaurants that could seat 1,000 people. Another was the Cella's Park Hotel, where the Screen Actors Guild was founded.</p>
        <p>Among the film players who lived in Fort Lee were Joan Bennett and Lionel, Ethel and John Barrymore.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Altomara, who is also the director of the 90,000-volume Fort Lee Public Library, said that the movie industry left Fort Lee for sunny California because of the ''iffy'' New Jersey weather and the World War I coal shortage, which made it difficult to heat the massive studio buildings. Today, all that remains of the movie industry is a film storage company.</p>
        <p>Because of the borough's movie connection the library has a large collection of books on the history of film making. It also has copies of 35 motion pictures that were shot in Fort Lee.</p>
        <p>HIGH-RISE apartment buildings now dominate the Palisades, with prices of up to $1.5 million for a 3,000-square-foot penthouse condominium and $375,000 for a two-bedroom apartment, according to George Tsoullis, owner or the GT Realty Company. Many residents of the borough work in Manhattan, an easy commute over the George Washington Bridge.</p>
        <p>''The new people really don't take part in Fort Lee life,'' said Mr. Grieco, the former Police Chief. ''They just change their clothes here and go back and forth to the city.''</p>
        <p>Of the 15,000 dwelling units in the borough, 11,000 are apartments. Although most of the apartment buildings were constructed as rentals, two-thirds were converted into co-ops and condominiums in the last 10 years. One of the largest condominium apartment buildings is the 231-unit River Ridge on Old Palisade Road, where one-bedroom units go for about $275,000 and two-bedrooms for about $375,000.</p>
        <p>AMONG the larger co-op projects is Century Towers, which has 500 units, with one-bedroom apartments selling for about $190,000 and two-bedroom units about $285,000. The 4,000 remaining rental units are divided equally between rent-controlled apartments, which go for $700 to $800, and uncontrolled apartments, at $1,100 to $4,000 a month for two bedrooms.</p>
        <p>Single-family homes range in price from $200,000 for a 70-year-old, two-bedroom house on an older street, such as Cedar Street, Myrtle Avenue or English Street, to $1.6 million for a mansion in the Palisades East and Palisades Gardens sections. There are several town-house developments, the largest of which is Westgate on Route 46. Mr. Tsoullis said units go for $350,000 to $1.3 million. ''For us it was the perfect solution,'' said Alisa Ellworth, who moved to a two-bedroom condominium with her husband, John, in May 1988. ''We wanted to live near Manhattan, but not in it. And Fort Lee is pretty, peaceful, convenient and an easy commute to the city.''</p>
        <p>One of Fort Lee's main attractions is its school system. According to Dr. Alan W. Sugarman, the superintendent, 90 percent of the high school graduates go on to college. Twenty-nine of Fort Lee's high school courses can be taken for college credit through a program under which the students register as adjunct students at universities in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Fort Lee High School, which has 700 students, was the only high school in the state to be awarded a Presidential Certificate of Excellence as a Drug Free School in 1988.</p>
        <p>''We have a comprehensive drug and alcoholism education program that stresses decision making and community service from grades K though 12,'' explained Dr. Sugarman. ''We make the students feel that they are a part of the overall community by encouraging volunteerism. At the same time, we assign adult mentors to many students, to insure that they have positive role models.''</p>
        <p>The school system, which has a total of 2,500 students and an annual budget of $23 million, includes, in addition to the high school, four elementary schools and the Louis F. Cole Middle School.</p>
        <p>Fort Lee has three supermarkets, which serve both borough residents and New Yorkers, who are attracted by the lower food prices in New Jersey - a result of lower taxes. Main Street has many banks, boutiques, specialty shops and restaurants, which range from Archer's, which local residents say might be the most expensive in Bergen County, down to hot-dog stands.</p>
        <p>Archer's features a southern Italian menu, with entrees averaging $20. Some of the other fine restaurants are Harbor House, with a continental menu, Armondo's with Italian cuisine, and JD's Steak Pit. There also are Chinese, Japanese, Armenian and Indian restaurants and kosher delicatessens.</p>
        <p>Among the borough's 15 houses of worship is the Church of the Madonna on Church Lane. Built in 1859 as the first Roman Catholic church in Bergen County, it is listed on the National Register of Historic Places.</p>
        <p>GAZETTEER</p>
        <p>Population: 36,000 (1990 estimate).</p>
        <p>Median household income: $70,000 (1990 estimate).</p>
        <p>Median price of one-family house: $275,000.</p>
        <p>Property taxes on median house: $3,800.</p>
        <p>Median price of two-bedroom condominium: $165,000.</p>
        <p>Median rent on two-bedroom rent-controlled apartment: $750.</p>
        <p>Median rent on market-rate two-bedroom apartment: $1,300.</p>
        <p>Distance from midtown Manhattan: 5 miles.</p>
        <p>Rush-hour commutation to midtown: 30 minutes by New Jersey Transit bus to Port Authority midtown terminal, $2.30 one way, or 7 minutes to George Washington Bridge terminal - $1 one way, $53 unlimited monthly - then 20 minutes on A subway line.</p>
        <p>Government: Mayor (Nicholas Corbiscello, Republican) elected to four-year term and six-member Council to three-year term..</p>
        <p>Celluloid Suspense: The word cliffhanger - meaning a film in which the heroine (or hero) is left at the end of each chapter of a series tied to a railroad track or otherwise in deep trouble - is said to have been coined in Fort Lee when early moviemakers there ended episodes with heroines about to plunge over the Palisades. One of the most famous was the 1914 ''Perils of Pauline'' with Pearl White, followed two years later by Miss White's ''The Exploits of Elaine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
