<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In East, Ivy's a Puzzle Amid 2 Likely Cases</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="381859"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">OGRODNICK, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D91130F936A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In East, Ivy's a Puzzle Amid 2 Likely Cases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: As usual, the Ivy League is beyond the scope of prophets. The Patriot League, formerly the Colonial, may have a new name but the same team, Holy Cross, is the one to beat. In the Yankee Conference, Connecticut is likely to fly away from eight others on the passing of Matt DeGennaro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: As usual, the Ivy League is beyond the scope of prophets. The Patriot League, formerly the Colonial, may have a new name but the same team, Holy Cross, is the one to beat. In the Yankee Conference, Connecticut is likely to fly away from eight others on the passing of Matt DeGennaro.</p>
        <p>Ivy League</p>
        <p>Among the Ivies, whose season begins Sept. 15, Yale is the consensus favorite, something more often a curse than a prognostication.</p>
        <p>Carm Cozza, beginning his 26th season as Yale's coach, has offensive weapons: eight returning starters from an 8-2 team, including Darin Kehler, the daring wishbone quarterback; Kevin Callahan and Chris Kouri at running back, and the Michalik twins, Chris and Rob, at guard.</p>
        <p>Princeton, last year's co-champion with Yale, has a terrific quarterback in Joel Sharp, who is only 5 feet 9 inches and 175 pounds. Chris Lutz, the league's best kicker, is another of Coach Steve Tosches's assets.</p>
        <p>Dartmouth, which won its last four games in 1989, has 14 starters returning, 8 on defense. On offense, the quarterback, the fullback, the tight end and the kicker will all be new. The probable quarterback is a senior, Kevin Peck.</p>
        <p>Mickey Kwiatkowski, whose disciplined teams at Hofstra always impressed, is Brown's new coach, bringing welcome enthusiasm to Providence. The coach is still sorting out three quarterbacks to run his wing-T flex but has proven talent in Nick Badalato, a tiny tailback; Mike Geroux, an all-Ivy receiver, and Reid Smith, a defensive tackle.</p>
        <p>Cornell's Jim Hofher, a 33-year-old alumnus, is another new coach, the Big Red's third in three seasons. He has a cadre of 13 starters, 8 on offense, including Chris Cochrane, the big quarterback, and John McNiff at running back. Rob Ryder at defensive end and Paul Tully at cornerback are the key defensive players.</p>
        <p>After defensive collapse from midseason on and a 4-6 record, Penn will come back strong, says Coach Gary Steele. He has had to reconstruct the offense after graduation losses, and beef up the defense. Key players are Joe Valerio at guard, Brian Matthews at running back and Joe Kopcha and Jay Lee at linebacker.</p>
        <p>The key player in a rebuilding year at Harvard will be Adam Lazarre-White, who can pass, run and catch. He could be the new quarterback, a wingback or a wideout. Coach Joe Restic, in his 19th season, has only six returning starters and his complex multiflex offense will be limited in early games.</p>
        <p>The freshmen from Columbia's acclaimed and unbeaten 1987 team are seniors now with only three varsity victories to show for their efforts. The touted running backs Greg Abbruzzese and Solomon Johnson, who missed last season because of injuries, are back with Johnson now a receiver. Bruce Mayhew, the quarterback, is tested and there are seven returning starters on defense.</p>
        <p>Patriot League</p>
        <p>Last season, under its old name, this league had five extraordinary quarterbacks, who passed for 14,190 yards and 101 touchdowns. Two remain. Tom Ciaccio has the stronger supporting cast at Holy Cross but don't count out Dave Goodwin and his Colgate team.</p>
        <p>The Crusaders, who have lost one league game in four seasons, are loaded at every position but most notably on defense. Aces include Joe Segreti, the fullback; Mark Gallagher, receiver and punter; Joe Foy Jr. at guard and Matt Fras, Andy Hertz and Marc Kosciuk on the defensive line.</p>
        <p>Colgate's defense, its major concern, was strong in the team's opening victory, 21-10, over Boston University, its first victory on the road after 12 losses. Goodwin, a 6-foot-2-inch, 203-pound political-science major, passed for 252 yards and two touchdowns. In the 100th anniversary season, the team will play five home games at Andy Kerr Stadium, soon to be rebuilt. Lafayette's graduation losses were severe but Tom Costello, a terrific running back, returns.</p>
        <p>Lehigh's Hank Small admits to a ''terrible'' defense in 1988 and 1989, and his best player this time is a running back, Erik Torain. Glenn Kempa, a junior engineering major, will be the quarterback.</p>
        <p>Bucknell has 13 returning starters but will have a new quarterback, Todd Hatajik or Jeff Kelly, to replace the remarkable Scott Auchenbach, the league's most valuable player last season.</p>
        <p>Fordham, now an official member, needs two or three good recruiting years before it can compete in I-AA. The Rams lost their opener to Hofstra, 36-16.</p>
        <p>Yankee Conference</p>
        <p>Connecticut's goal is the championship and with it the automatic bid to the I-AA playoffs, which would be the Huskies' first. The 13 returning starters include DeGennaro, who holds 14 school passing records, and Kevin Wesley, a 1,000-yard rusher.</p>
        <p>Maine has a new coach again, Kirk Ferentz, the third in four years, and a continuing winning tradition. Jeff DelRosso replaces the great Mike Buck at quarterback and the tailback, Carl Smith, is aiming at 2,000 rushing yards.</p>
        <p>Boston University's run-and-shoot offense will feature Stan Greene passing to Daren Altieri.</p>
        <p>Coach Tubby Raymond's 25th Delaware team, solid on defense, will be another contender, along with New Hampshire and Villanova. Massachusetts, Rhode Island and Richmond fall into the rebuilding category.</p>
        <p>This conference, which permits athletic scholarships and postseason play, unlike the Ivy and the Patriot Leagues, expects to be keenly competitive again. There have been two-way or three-way ties for the championship since the conference expansion of 1986, and six of the nine members have shared the titles.</p>
        <p>Faded Ivy</p>
        <p>How Ivy League teams have performed in football games against teams from the Patriot League (formerly the Colonial League) and the Yankee Conference since 1986.</p>
        <p>vs.</p>
        <p>vs.</p>
        <p>Year</p>
        <p>Patriot</p>
        <p>Yankee</p>
        <p>1986</p>
        <p>5-8-0</p>
        <p>1-4-0</p>
        <p>1987</p>
        <p>5-10-0</p>
        <p>2-1-0</p>
        <p>1988</p>
        <p>6-9-1</p>
        <p>0-5-0</p>
        <p>1989</p>
        <p>7-10-0</p>
        <p>1-3-0</p>
        <p>Total</p>
        <p>23-37-1</p>
        <p>4-13-0</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
