<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through the Looking Glass</title>
    <meta content="17ctart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1687952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DE1330F934A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through the Looking Glass</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is little to be said about the artwork of James Britton (1878-1936), the subject of a well meaning if bland art-history recovery effort at the Lyman Allyn Art Museum in New London. His paintings are ordinary, and his subject matter desultory. He liked to do self-portraits, painting himself brush in hand in front of his art with the aid of mirrors. The background images are flipped.</p>
        <p>But talent and quality is not everything when it comes to art history. Mr. Britton, an artist, writer and art critic of modest reputation, was a Connecticut native, and his life story provides a window into the art world of another era, with an accent on artists and events in Hartford and some of the state's other big cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is little to be said about the artwork of James Britton (1878-1936), the subject of a well meaning if bland art-history recovery effort at the Lyman Allyn Art Museum in New London. His paintings are ordinary, and his subject matter desultory. He liked to do self-portraits, painting himself brush in hand in front of his art with the aid of mirrors. The background images are flipped.</p>
        <p>But talent and quality is not everything when it comes to art history. Mr. Britton, an artist, writer and art critic of modest reputation, was a Connecticut native, and his life story provides a window into the art world of another era, with an accent on artists and events in Hartford and some of the state's other big cities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Britton was born and reared in Hartford, where he also trained to be a realist painter with the artist Charles Noel Flagg. Mr. Britton worked for a short period as a staff artist for The Hartford Times, and then as an art critic for The Hartford Courant. In 1910, along with Mr. Flagg, and other like-minded artists, he founded the Connecticut Academy of Fine Arts. Earlier this year Mystic Arts Center was the host for its 94th annual exhibition.</p>
        <p>By 1915, Mr. Britton was living in New York City, where he remained on and off until 1922; he kept a city studio until 1925. Throughout this period he wrote art reviews for publication, published and edited the art magazine Art Review International, and continued to paint and exhibit his work with some success. But he never really made it, and in 1925 returned to live permanently in his home state. He never traveled abroad or left the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Britton painted portraits and landscapes. The portraits were usually done on commission, while the landscapes, his real passion, were made for pleasure. He also dabbled with making bold, striking woodcuts, some of which were printed in magazines; one was used for an advertising poster. But he disdained the art form and quickly gave it up, scribbling in his diary that he had no desire to spend his time ''chipping wood.''</p>
        <p>Most of the paintings shown here are from the last 20-odd years of his life. Much of his early work has been lost or destroyed, according to the exhibition catalog. Portraits tend to dominate, in particular the mirror self-portraits of the artist painting in front of his own artworks. He is pretending to be the great painter in his studio, I think, which is a little sad.</p>
        <p>The one really good portrait here is that of the marine painter Theodore Valenkampf, done in 1907. It depicts the portly artist leaning forward in a chair, one hand holding a cigarette, the other on his thigh. He wears a white shirt, tie and pair of beige pants, the fabric crimping around his thighs as his stomach pushes against his black leather belt. The fabric folds are nicely painted, as is the aged, flushed face. You get the sense here of a real person.</p>
        <p>Mr. Britton painted Mr. Valenkampf in the latter's studio in Gloucester, Mass. Perhaps that is why he seems relaxed and generally lifelike. Or perhaps it is because Mr. Britton, painting an artist and friend, felt no compulsion to flatter his subject. He would save that for the Boston and Hartford dowagers like Anna Roosevelt Cowles, sister of President Theodore Roosevelt, who commissioned him to paint a portrait of her around 1907. Mr. Britton was able to make a modest living from this patronage for a number of years.</p>
        <p>Other rooms in the museum contain miscellaneous woodcuts and paintings, including a group of delicate intimate landscapes, many of which depict Sag Harbor on Long Island or its environs. The landscape paintings are the pick of this uneven group, with one or two nicely capturing changing light and weather conditions.</p>
        <p>''James Britton (1878-1936): Connecticut Artist'' is at the Lyman Allyn Art Museum, 625 Williams Street, New London, through Sept. 18. Information: www.lymanallyn.org or (860)443-2545.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
