<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Staten Island, You Call Those Fires?</title>
    <meta content="17fire" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/17/nyregion/thecity/17fire.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1688017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Leary, Denis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDC1030F934A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Staten Island, You Call Those Fires?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Staten Island, You Call Those Fires?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAKE MOONEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tommy Gavin, the mercurial New York City firefighter played by the comedian Denis Leary on the FX network firehouse drama ''Rescue Me,'' didn't stay long on Staten Island. Still, the place made an impression on him.</p>
        <p>Firefighter Gavin, a troubled sort who transferred to Staten Island from Manhattan at the start of the show's second season, which began last month, promptly poked fun at his new home base. ''The other night,'' he said in the second episode, ''one of the guys on the crew lit two matches by mistake. It's the biggest fire these guys have ever seen. Swear to God.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some on Staten Island are offended by the comments of Tommy Gavin, the New York City firefighter played by the comedian Denis Leary on the FX network firehouse drama "Rescue Me."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tommy Gavin, the mercurial New York City firefighter played by the comedian Denis Leary on the FX network firehouse drama ''Rescue Me,'' didn't stay long on Staten Island. Still, the place made an impression on him.</p>
        <p>Firefighter Gavin, a troubled sort who transferred to Staten Island from Manhattan at the start of the show's second season, which began last month, promptly poked fun at his new home base. ''The other night,'' he said in the second episode, ''one of the guys on the crew lit two matches by mistake. It's the biggest fire these guys have ever seen. Swear to God.''</p>
        <p>He also had mixed feelings about his Staten Island colleagues: one was mentally handicapped, three others wanted him to join a barbershop quartet, and the chief said grace before dinner and penalized foul language by demanding contributions into a prominently displayed ''swear jar.'' The big boisterous city it wasn't.</p>
        <p>All of which, on the real Staten Island, rubbed some the wrong way. Councilman Andrew J. Lanza, who represents a district on the South Shore, said he had never watched the show, but did receive several angry phone calls about this season's episodes. More firefighters and police officers live on the island than in any other borough, he pointed out, noting that the jabs at Staten Island were an insult to them.</p>
        <p>''This is nothing new, with respect to the certain elitism that exists out there,'' Mr. Lanza said. ''I would venture to say that the people who write for these shows have never been to Staten Island.'' (For the record, Mr. Leary started a foundation in 2000 that raises money for fire departments; New York was among the beneficiaries.)</p>
        <p>In something of an unfortunate coincidence, the arrival of the new series coincided roughly with the arrival of a new engine company in Rossville, in Mr. Lanza's district. The engine company was supposed to open in February 2004, but the opening was delayed because of city budget problems. Months of lobbying by elected officials and protests from residents, along with data that showed response times in the area were slower than the city average, led Mayor Bloomberg to reverse the decision. Engine Company 168, staffed by 20 firefighters and four officers, opened last month.</p>
        <p>According to a spokesman for FX network, no one associated with the show would comment on the flap over Tommy Gavin's remarks. And in fact, the tension may be easing. In the season's third episode, Firefighter Gavin got a transfer back to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>As for Engine Company 168, ''Fourdays after they arrived there,'' Mr. Lanza said, ''they were battling a structure fire at a house and saving lives.'' JAKE MOONEY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK ON FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
