<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It's Time to Turn the Page</title>
    <meta content="17hunt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/17/realestate/17hunt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1688007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE HUNT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cole, Thomas (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cole, Katherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/The Hunt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DA1330F934A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It's Time to Turn the Page</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When It's Time to Turn the Page</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Hunt column describes search by Thomas and Katherine Cole for co-op apartment in Manhattan that could accommodate collection of 10,000 books; found co-op with one bedroom large enough for suitable renovations, for $365,000 at 109th St and Central Park West; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHERE do you house 10,000 books? In an apartment with plenty of shelf space, of course.</p>
        <p>So that's what Thomas and Katherine Cole needed when they moved to New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A couple from Connecticut needed a Manhattan apartment for themselves and their 10,000 books. They found one on the Upper West Side for $365,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHERE do you house 10,000 books? In an apartment with plenty of shelf space, of course.</p>
        <p>So that's what Thomas and Katherine Cole needed when they moved to New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cole, 71, who retired five years ago as a classics professor at Yale University, likes working from home, which means having on hand the thousands of reference works he might need. (He is writing a literary study of Ovid.)</p>
        <p>''The books were essential,'' he said. In fact, having sufficient space for them -- probably an extra bedroom or study -- was the defining criterion of the Coles's apartment hunt. Beyond that, they were flexible. Way too flexible.</p>
        <p>''We started off like a tabula rasa,'' said Mrs. Cole, 62, who had directed New Haven's film festival. ''We didn't know where we would go or what we would spend. We were scampering all over town. We were so unfocused we drove our real estate agent nuts.''</p>
        <p>In New Haven, the Coles, who met when she was a graduate student and he was her professor, lived in a five-bedroom Victorian house with their daughters, Helena and Celia. Books were everywhere. ''If you thought you were escaping them by going up to the third-floor bathroom, you weren't,'' Mrs. Cole said. ''The bathroom was lined with bookshelves.'' She had vague worries about floors collapsing under the weight.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, after Mr. Cole spent a semester as a visiting professor at Harvard, they realized they didn't have to remain in New Haven. They had long dreamed about Manhattan. Coincidentally, a friend was vacating her East 23rd Street studio for a few months, so they stayed there. It showed them how much they liked the city, and it gave them a base from which to hunt.</p>
        <p>They attended open houses, focusing on high ceilings and lots of wall space. They liked the Gramercy area. They figured a location near Columbia or N.Y.U. would afford Mr. Cole convenient access to those libraries. They checked out Midtown high-rises, until they realized the ceilings were so low that Mr. Cole, 6 feet 4 inches tall, could touch them if he reached up. The budget they settled upon, $400,000, was also proving low.</p>
        <p>So they drifted to the Upper West Side, noticing a tendency toward higher ceilings and more space. Stopping at an open house on West 111th Street, ''to see what a really expensive apartment was like,'' Mrs. Cole said, they encountered Irene Kruglova, a broker at Bellmarc.</p>
        <p>''Freed of the obligation to be seriously interested in the apartment, we got to talking with her and she seemed to be a really interesting person,'' Mrs. Cole said. ''Irene decided we needed a firm hand and a firmer grasp on the realities of the market.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kruglova steered them away from places that were appealing in the wrong ways, including an airy one-bedroom overlooking Morningside Park. ''The apartment said, 'I'm yours'; at least, it said it to me,'' Mrs. Cole said. The Coles wanted to bid, but Ms. Kruglova pointed out that the layout wouldn't allow for a study.</p>
        <p>''In my enthusiasm, I wanted something so badly that the goal was making a bid,'' Mrs. Cole said. ''It became so important to have an end in sight. I was more cautious from that point on.''</p>
        <p>A fourth-floor walk-up on West 109th Street, with a splendid kitchen, was another place that said, ''I'm yours.'' Ms. Kruglova was appalled. ''I was feeling like I had to protect them sometimes against themselves,'' she said. ''I said, 'You will end up with many people not willing to visit you.' It is a young people's situation -- not for you once you are retired.''</p>
        <p>It was an eye-opener for Mrs. Cole. ''That's when I realized I wasn't young anymore,'' she said. ''Although I had no problem walking up four floors, everybody said that you might come to a point where you can't or don't want to.'' They had stairs in New Haven, but ''you don't think of a three-story house as a walk-up.''</p>
        <p>She also realized, with surprise, that their prospective apartment would likely be their home for the rest of their lives, ''the place you might be living when you're 90,'' she said. They crossed walk-ups off the list.</p>
        <p>Then came a turning point: 345 West 70th Street. The Coles disliked its location next to the new Trump development, but loved its interior. The living and dining rooms had been combined, creating a long room with an uninterrupted wall.</p>
        <p>''I saw this gleam in Tom's eye,'' Mrs. Cole said. With such a wall, he realized he could create a separate little room with floor-to-ceiling bookshelves. Suddenly, they were able to define what they needed. Their books -- the problem -- would become the solution.</p>
        <p>By now, they were preparing to relinquish the 23rd Street studio. ''I felt like I totally ran out of options,'' Ms. Kruglova said. ''There was nothing on the market with the qualities I was considering for them.'' She sent them to one last open house -- a ground-floor one-bedroom co-op on Central Park West at 109th Street.</p>
        <p>The bedroom was huge, with a long wall. The ceilings were nine-and-a-half-feet high. The gleam returned to Mr. Cole's eye. He scribbled floor plans. He measured. It seemed entirely possible to divide the room with a wall of books. They offered the asking price of $365,000, but another offer had just been accepted.</p>
        <p>Needing a break, the Coles arranged for a long-delayed vacation. The morning before their departure, Ms. Kruglova called. The other offer had fallen through. If they waited until they returned, the apartment might be gone. They rushed to Ms. Kruglova's office, granted power of attorney to their lawyer, flew out as scheduled, and spent much of their vacation in Lihue, Kauai, tethered to a fax machine. The apartment was theirs.</p>
        <p>While in Hawaii, they heard from their New Haven agent, too. They received a full-price offer of $469,000 on their house, which they had bought for $40,000 in 1975.</p>
        <p>Carpenter friends built the bookshelves in their new place. Now, Mr. Cole has a secluded study with its own window, though a brick-wall view. He sold or gave away 5,000 books. While setting up the remaining 10,000, he forgot how heavy books are. He stacked them on the mattress, which hasn't been the same since.</p>
        <p>The Coles have a large kitchen, too, where subway commuters pass by their window, entertaining them with snippets of cellphone conversations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cole is often asked whether he has read all those books. His answer: Of course not. But, ''I think I have at one time or another consulted them,'' he said. ''A number of them, I am still waiting to consult.''</p>
        <p>THE HUNT E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: thehunt@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
