<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Virtual Migrants; Need Programmers? Surf Abroad.</title>
    <meta content="18MYER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="988611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD61738F93BA25752C0A96E958260" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Virtual Migrants; Need Programmers? Surf Abroad.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN R. MYERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shortage of computer programmers, and import of many from India and other countries, discussed; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE nation has a shortage of techies, as last week's Government plan to help train more programmers made clear. But corporate America has already hit on a response. It's global telecommuting, through which this nation's technology companies have created a whole new realm of international trade by exporting their work and hiring programmers overseas to do it.</p>
        <p>Having already scooped up any American programmers they could by offering them the chance to ride the Internet to work from their homes in Jackson Hole, Wyo., or Boulder, Colo., the corporations are now reaching out to places like South Africa and the Philippines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE nation has a shortage of techies, as last week's Government plan to help train more programmers made clear. But corporate America has already hit on a response. It's global telecommuting, through which this nation's technology companies have created a whole new realm of international trade by exporting their work and hiring programmers overseas to do it.</p>
        <p>Having already scooped up any American programmers they could by offering them the chance to ride the Internet to work from their homes in Jackson Hole, Wyo., or Boulder, Colo., the corporations are now reaching out to places like South Africa and the Philippines.</p>
        <p>So increasingly, the world's commerce involves not just tankers filled with Brent crude or container ships laden with VCR's, but cables buzzing with computer programming code, product designs and engineering diagrams and formulas. Not to mention overhauls of American software gone too soft. If computer systems squeak into the year 2000 without acting like they're back in 1900, foreign programmers will deserve much of the thanks.</p>
        <p>Some companies bring the workers to the work, searching the world for computer specialists willing to come to the United States. But virtual immigration, where the workers stay put, has become far more common, and remains much cheaper. The software unit of a single company, Tata Sons Ltd. of India, has 5,000 developers, a maquiladora of the mind that can immediately deploy 100 techies on an American corporation's mission. India's software exports have grown from $225 million in 1992 to $1.15 billion in 1996, with a year 2000 goal of $3.6 billion.</p>
        <p>On the Cheap</p>
        <p>Technical advances have made this kind of rapid growth possible. Although banks, among other global institutions, have been electronically advantaged for years, the expense has fallen dramatically. Instead of high-capacity leased lines that can cost hundreds or thousands of dollars a month, a plain old phone connection and an Internet service provider will often do.</p>
        <p>''It's no longer an international phone call. Now, it's an Internet file exchange,'' said Esther Dyson, author of ''Release 2.0: A Design for Living in the Digital Age.'' A cyberdiplomat known for striving to make Eastern Europe at least as wired as its Western neighbors, Ms. Dyson also serves on the board of the PRT Group in Barbados, a software and computer systems design firm, and Softstep, a company doing Year 2000 fixes from Kyrgyzstan in Central Asia.</p>
        <p>While some global telecommuters, like many Americans, work at home, most are clustered in the foreign quarters of American companies or in the offices of foreign contractors like Tata. Projects can receive round-the-clock attention as they are handed from continent to continent. I.B.M. teams in Europe, India and the West Coast have kept the development of Java software for the Internet going at all hours, with handoffs over the Internet itself.</p>
        <p>Even as the giants like Tata prosper, the Internet is also allowing pipsqueaks to be heard and seen, offering electronic sales pitches and work samples. Corporations like I.B.M. find themselves hiring tiny foreign firms that could never have found their way through these companies' front doors.</p>
        <p>Those specialists who do migrate to the United States have an advantage in spotting talent back home. Under Sanjiv Sidhu, a native of Hyderabad, India, and Sandy Tungare, an executive from Bombay, I2 Technologies of Dallas runs software development centers in Bombay and Bangalore, where the neighbors include Motorola, Intel and Hewlett-Packard. Software developers who would earn at least $50,000 in the United States can be had for about a third as much in India, Mr. Tungare says.</p>
        <p>The rise of global telecommuting has already begun shaping trade policies and international relations. India, once utterly protectionist, has allowed American computer companies to import equipment by the tax-free boatload, and extends all manner of other tax breaks and real estate subsidies. Although some villages there are still waiting to join the telephone era, India has given industrial parks digital communications links. Many countries have lowered barriers to foreign (especially American) investment. The payoffs include hard currency from exports and a diminished brain drain.</p>
        <p>Bane Becomes Boon</p>
        <p>Should America's nerds be worried enough to cool their celebrations of their current lordly status?</p>
        <p>Edward Yourdon, a software consultant in New York, wrote a book, ''The Decline and Fall of the American Programmer,'' in 1992 to warn that foreign technicians were threatening American jobs. Some professional groups even sought to limit the export of technological tasks. But Mr. Yourdon and others hardly expected there to be so much more work, and in 1996, he wrote ''The Rise and Resurrection of the American Programmer.'' As he says these days, ''While this offshore situation still exists, now we are looking at it as a boon rather than a bane.''</p>
        <p>Already, a new international division of labor is emerging. Americans create programs to make the Internet sing and dance, or computer games to blow out teen-age minds and eardrums, and parental patience. Foreigners are often more like software second-stringers, stamping out bugs, updating the products and programming clunky mainframes.</p>
        <p>''That's work that people in the United States don't really want to do,'' said Paul J. Kostek, president-elect of the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers-U.S.A. and a systems engineer himself. ''They want to move on to the next challenge.''  Foreign software firms also usually buy American computers and American software for assembling and testing their own  products.</p>
        <p>America's challenge is to keep booming even as Asian markets for American goods shrivel. In an expansion based on technology, though, Asian and other foreign labor sources are providing much of the stamina.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
