<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With the All-Star Game and the Olympics, the N.H.L. Tries to Extend Its Global Reach</title>
    <meta content="18NHLL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="988706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All-Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nagano (Japan)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sweden</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Finland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Czech Republic</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Slovakia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latvia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Hockey League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Latvia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Slovakia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Slovakia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Latvia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Nagano</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D71538F93BA25752C0A96E958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With the All-Star Game and the Olympics, the N.H.L. Tries to Extend Its Global Reach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia, Jan. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Hockey League is trying to extend its global reach with All-Star Game and the Olympics; as best best professionals prepare to represent their nations in Olympics in Nagano, Japan, eight Russians will suit up for NHL All-Star team that represents Europe; they will sake alongside four players from Sweden, four from Finland, three from Czech Republic, two from Slovakia, one from Germany and one from Latvia; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the 19-year-old Wayne Gretzky played in his first National Hockey League All-Star game 18 years ago as a member of the Clarence Campbell Conference team, the opposing Prince of Wales Conference had a 51-year-old right wing named Gordie Howe. Gretzky was a young star in his rookie N.H.L. season. Howe was an old star in his final season. But they had one thing in common: Both were Canadian, as were the overwhelming majority of All-Star participants and N.H.L. players in general.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, eight days away from his 37th birthday, Gretzky will again grace the midseason showcase when his team representing North America plays a team representing the rest of the world. Among Gretzky's Canadian- and American-born teammates and his European opponents will be more than a few whose early childhood memories include watching Gretzky dominate the sport in the first decade of his brilliant career. They, like many fans, must appreciate that Gretzky is still among the elite of his profession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the 19-year-old Wayne Gretzky played in his first National Hockey League All-Star game 18 years ago as a member of the Clarence Campbell Conference team, the opposing Prince of Wales Conference had a 51-year-old right wing named Gordie Howe. Gretzky was a young star in his rookie N.H.L. season. Howe was an old star in his final season. But they had one thing in common: Both were Canadian, as were the overwhelming majority of All-Star participants and N.H.L. players in general.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, eight days away from his 37th birthday, Gretzky will again grace the midseason showcase when his team representing North America plays a team representing the rest of the world. Among Gretzky's Canadian- and American-born teammates and his European opponents will be more than a few whose early childhood memories include watching Gretzky dominate the sport in the first decade of his brilliant career. They, like many fans, must appreciate that Gretzky is still among the elite of his profession.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I'm getting younger as I'm getting older,'' a smiling Gretzky said after a recent multipoint performance.</p>
        <p>Still effective in many games, Gretzky has 12 goals and 33 assists for 45 points in 47 games with the Rangers, his fourth N.H.L. team. Every point sets a new record, as his statistics have eclipsed those of Howe and everyone else. To put the Gretzky era into perspective, consider the hockey world of his first All-Star appearance. It was early February of 1980, just weeks before the United States upset the Soviet Union and went on to win the gold medal at the Winter Olympic Games in Lake Placid. Back then, it would have seemed preposterous to predict that N.H.L. professionals would some day play in the Olympics. And it would have seemed ludicrous to suggest that Russian stars would someday be on display in the N.H.L. All-Star Game.</p>
        <p>But as the best professionals prepare to represent their nations in the Olympics next month in Japan, eight Russians will suit up on Sunday for the N.H.L. All-Star team that represents Europe. They will skate alongside four players from Sweden, four from Finland, three from the Czech Republic, two from Slovakia, one from Germany and one from Latvia.</p>
        <p>The new format was created this season to stoke the flames of rivalry that have cooled since the end of the Cold War and the breakup of the Soviet Union. Gretzky and just about every other player involved said the change is welcome because the high-scoring, low-intensity All-Star games of the recent past have been less than mid-season classics.</p>
        <p>''I think this is a good change,'' Gretzky said. ''We needed something to spice up the All-Star game. Those 10-8 scores are not what our game is all about.''</p>
        <p>It is also part of a larger format, a three-day extravaganza that promotes a growing sport in many ways. On Friday night, the women's teams representing the United States and Canada played before more than 14,000 fans in General Motors Place. Canada won by 2-1 amid waving flags and shaking signs. One of them said: ''Trounce the States at Nagano.'' At the conclusion of the game, many of the Canadian players stood at attention and sang along as the national anthem, 'O, Canada,' was played.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, the N.H.L. players will conduct the skills competition and the old-timers will play an exhibition. In the hallways of the hotels and public buildings, there are booths and exhibits for corporate sponsors. A special honored guest is Willie O'Ree, who became the league's first black player on Jan. 18, 1958. This season, nine black athletes  have appeared in N.H.L. games, the most ever.</p>
        <p>The host city, with its beautiful mountainous vistas and mild winter climate, has a large Asian population and sits on the Pacific rim. It is an appropriate location as many of these All-Stars look westward toward the east and the competition in Nagano next month. One player likely to gain a following in Japan is Canada's Paul Kariya, a Vancouver native who plays for the Mighty Ducks of Anaheim. One of the most talented and charismatic players in the N.H.L., Kariya is of Japanese descent on his father's side.</p>
        <p>The N.H.L. of Gretzky's rookie season had only a handful of players born in the United States or Europe. But the league this season is 61.4 per cent Canadian, 16.1 per cent American and 6 per cent Russian. Players from Sweden make up 5 per cent of the rosters and so do those from the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>In that league rosters are 77.5 per cent North American, it is significant that Europeans make up a disproportionate percentage of the top scorers. Of the top 20 players in total points, 9 are from Europe. Sweden's Peter Forsberg, of the Colorado Avalanche, is first in total points with 59. Steve Yzerman, captain of the Stanley Cup champion Detroit Red Wings and a member of Team Canada for the Olympics, said Friday that he noticed this trend recently.</p>
        <p>''Does it concern me? No,'' Yzerman said, repeating a question. ''I actually counted that the other day. Europeans dominate it, I think, but there are four or five Canadians and four or five Americans. As the Wayne Gretzky and Mark Messier era is . . . ''</p>
        <p>He paused, and then rephrased his thought.</p>
        <p>''It seems to go in cycles,'' Yzerman said. ''There will be Canadian players coming along. You're always going to have the European players up there now. And the Americans are there to stay as well. And that's something that everybody has to get used to.''</p>
        <p>The changes of the last two decades have concerned some Canadians. The influx of European talent and the movement of franchises from Canada to the American Sun Belt causes some here to fear that Canadians are losing control of ''our game.'' But from a marketing standpoint, the mix of nations and cultures is ideal for a sport trying to increase its exposure to a world market. Russia's Igor Larionov, who plays for Detroit, recently noted: ''The N.H.L. is no longer just a domestic league.'' Gretzky, asked about the economic upside to the involvement with the Olympics, said:</p>
        <p>''For the National Hockey League, as far as merchandising and marketing the sport worldwide, it's a win-win situation.''  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
