<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crybaby Boomers</title>
    <meta content="02KIRN$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="941059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Agenda (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirn, Walter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E4D91430F931A35754C0A961958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crybaby Boomers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Kirn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirn, Walter</byline>
      <dateline>LIVINGSTON, Mont.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Kirn Op-Ed article notes that recent Public Agenda survey found that only 37 percent of American adults believe that today's youths will grow up to make world better place; contends that when he was child back around 1970, many of today's adults were burning bras, barricading themselves in college presidents' offices and calling for downfall of Government; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What spoiled children today's grown-ups are. When I was a child, back around 1970, they were on the evening news burning bras and flipping out on acid, barricading themselves in college presidents' offices and calling for the downfall of the Government. I used to lie in bed and pray for everything to be O.K., for the Maoists and the Manson girls to go away.</p>
        <p>Now those same rebels are middle-aged and running the world, having traded manifestoes for mutual funds and tie-dyed jeans for Italian silk ties. They have gone from not trusting anyone over 30 to not trusting anyone under 30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What spoiled children today's grown-ups are. When I was a child, back around 1970, they were on the evening news burning bras and flipping out on acid, barricading themselves in college presidents' offices and calling for the downfall of the Government. I used to lie in bed and pray for everything to be O.K., for the Maoists and the Manson girls to go away.</p>
        <p>Now those same rebels are middle-aged and running the world, having traded manifestoes for mutual funds and tie-dyed jeans for Italian silk ties. They have gone from not trusting anyone over 30 to not trusting anyone under 30.</p>
        <p>That, at least, appears to be the finding of a survey released last week by Public Agenda, a research group, on American attitudes toward the younger generation. ''Americans are convinced that today's adolescents face a crisis -- not in their economic or physical well-being but in their values and morals,'' the study reported. Six in 10 of the adults polled said young people were failing to learn moral values. Just 37 percent said they believed today's youths will grow up to make the world a better place.</p>
        <p>Excuse me, but I see a pattern here. First the members of the 60's generation hated their parents. Now they hate their kids. The generation that gave us instant divorce, pot, speed and insider trading is worried about the moral failings of the young?  Please. If I were 15 now and thus charged with moral corruption, I'd take a long, hard look at my prosecutors, beginning with, but not limited to, their Role-Model-in-Chief. Bill Clinton's America may be prosperous, but morally exemplary it's not.</p>
        <p>Twentysomethings, meanwhile, have gotten a bad rap from their elders, who like to call them ''slackers.'' But despite being burdened by  student loan debt and lavished with unsolicited credit cards virtually since birth, plenty of them are saving for retirement at an age when their parents were still splurging on grams of coke and denouncing materialism. Some of these young people are marrying early, right out of college, apparently eager to avoid the biological waste dump left behind by the previous generation's sexual experiments. As for social activism, there's reportedly growing interest among college students in joining the Peace Corps.</p>
        <p>So who should be lecturing whom? I came of age in the late 70's, when it wasn't uncommon to visit a friend's house and find his twice-divorced father in the living room passed out next to the stereo with a hash pipe. In the 80's, when I went to college, one of the most popular clubs on campus was Alanon, where earnest young people struggled with their parents' addictions. Now I hear 50-year-olds excuse a daily barrage of government dirt as business as usual, nothing to be concerned about. This from the same people who scourged my tender youth with threats of violent revolution if the scoundrel Richard M. Nixon didn't step down.</p>
        <p>At the risk of sounding a bit self-righteous myself, I call these grown-ups the Blame Generation. In the survey, two-thirds of them branded today's youth ''wild,'' ''rude'' and ''irresponsible'' -- the same words  applied to them back when they were young. If I were a teen-ager, I wouldn't worry about it. These folks who are doing the name-calling now were a pretty frightening bunch themselves. Not a few of them still are.</p>
        <p>Walter Kirn is the author of ''She Needed Me,'' a novel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Kirn is the author of ''She Needed Me,'' a novel.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
