<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Steinbrenner Praises Rogers (Gasp!) And Pans Parking</title>
    <meta content="02BOSS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="941142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2D71230F931A35754C0A961958260" item-length="459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Steinbrenner Praises Rogers (Gasp!) And Pans Parking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees owner George Steinbrenner scores parking conditions around Yankee Stadium; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was George Steinbrenner, Yankee owner and part-time de facto general manager, clipboard in hand, playing parking lot attendant outside Yankee Stadium, one night after a massive traffic jam had snagged his car and those of many others.</p>
        <p>It was the Boss acting as traffic cop, matching names and reserved parking spaces for nearly two hours last evening and holding court outside the Stadium he would love to leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was George Steinbrenner, Yankee owner and part-time de facto general manager, clipboard in hand, playing parking lot attendant outside Yankee Stadium, one night after a massive traffic jam had snagged his car and those of many others.</p>
        <p>It was the Boss acting as traffic cop, matching names and reserved parking spaces for nearly two hours last evening and holding court outside the Stadium he would love to leave.</p>
        <p>It was a rare thing to see in so public a setting, but it was not as rare as the words of praise Steinbrenner bestowed on Kenny Rogers.</p>
        <p>The comments came after the much-maligned Rogers had thrown four scoreless innings in relief of the injured Andy Pettitte on Monday night to keep the Yankees alive in what turned out to be a 1-0, 10-inning victory over the Atlanta Braves. Steinbrenner was pleased with what he saw from the left-hander, who has been banished to the bullpen.</p>
        <p>''He has to show me that three times,'' Steinbrenner said, while overseeing operations from a chair in the Yankees' private parking lot. ''That sure counts as one, though. That counts maybe as one and a half, except you can't break them up.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner appeared to be turning things around in the parking lot, which is reserved for players, members of the news media, Yankee officials and luxury suite holders.</p>
        <p>''This place was packed and you couldn't get your car out,'' he said, blaming the previous night's jam on autograph seekers, among others. ''The players have to have some sense of being left to themselves. If they want to stop when they go in, that's their business, and I'm happy to see it. But this is one of the reasons people won't come out here.''</p>
        <p>Almost 40,000 people came out on Monday night to attend a game at the Stadium that Steinbrenner wants out of.</p>
        <p>''I want to be sure that every single opportunity to get people in and out is proposed at night,'' he said. ''You get them up on the Deegan and you get them moving.''</p>
        <p>Minutes after last night's game, Steinbrenner was on the move, ready to resume command at the parking lot. All he was missing was a whistle.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
