<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recent Events Add New Resonance to Bernstein's 'Mass'</title>
    <meta content="25CHOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/25/arts/music/25CHOR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1443620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Collegiate Chorale</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bass, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Collegiate Chorale</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bernstein, Leonard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DA1139F936A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recent Events Add New Resonance to Bernstein's 'Mass'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Recent Events Add New Resonance to Bernstein's 'Mass'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews Carnegie Hall performance of Leonard Bernstein's Mass by Collegiate Chorale, conducted by Robert Bass; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Leonard Bernstein's ''Mass'' was given its premiere in 1971 to inaugurate the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, many critics and concertgoers detested it. Some were put off by the work's pontifications. Coming at the height of the Vietnam War, the peacenik message of ''Mass,'' as much as it could be discerned through the muddled additional text by Bernstein and Stephen Schwartz, was that only by making ourselves emotionally vulnerable would we weather the bitter dissension of the times.</p>
        <p>Many people found Bernstein's mixing of musical styles -- from rock ballads to Broadway sizzle to Mahlerian chaos -- self-consciously trendy. ''Mass'' found its audience, though. In any event, the controversy was short lived because the work faded from view.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Collegiate Chorale brought Leonard Bernstein's "Mass" back to attention with an exuberant concert performance at Carnegie Hall on Tuesday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Leonard Bernstein's ''Mass'' was given its premiere in 1971 to inaugurate the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts in Washington, many critics and concertgoers detested it. Some were put off by the work's pontifications. Coming at the height of the Vietnam War, the peacenik message of ''Mass,'' as much as it could be discerned through the muddled additional text by Bernstein and Stephen Schwartz, was that only by making ourselves emotionally vulnerable would we weather the bitter dissension of the times.</p>
        <p>Many people found Bernstein's mixing of musical styles -- from rock ballads to Broadway sizzle to Mahlerian chaos -- self-consciously trendy. ''Mass'' found its audience, though. In any event, the controversy was short lived because the work faded from view.</p>
        <p>So Robert Bass, the music director of the Collegiate Chorale, deserves thanks for bringing ''Mass'' back to attention with an exuberant concert performance at Carnegie Hall on Tuesday night. His estimable chorus was joined by the Orchestra of St. Luke's; the Brooklyn Youth Chorus; a 16-member ''street chorus'' (as called for in the score); James Danner, a sweet-voiced boy soprano; and, to portray the Celebrant who confronts the Lord and doubts himself, Douglas Webster, a lyric baritone and a veteran of the role. The stage was crammed; the hall was packed. If only Bernstein, who would now be 84, could have been around to bask in the ovation.</p>
        <p>In retrospect it's hard to understand the hostility the work provoked. Admittedly the text is glibly anti-establishment and often mawkish. But after 9/11, a line like ''Everyone who hates his brother is a murderer'' no longer seems such pap. At the time Bernstein sensed a cultural swing, and he jumped aboard it: 1971 was also the year of Mr. Schwartz's rock musical ''Godspell'' and Andrew Lloyd Webber's ''Jesus Christ Superstar.''</p>
        <p>You sense the strain in Bernstein's attempt to make ''Mass'' both a hip theater piece and a grand concert work. But at least he was immersed in the pop sources he drew from, especially jazz. The ''Du bing, du bang, du bong'' Alleluia for six voices on quadraphonic tape is a nimble, be-bopping delight.</p>
        <p>There are some truly gorgeous passages, like the chorale ''Almighty Father,'' with its spacious, aching harmonies, and the subtly powerful meditation sections for orchestra. Yet Bernstein procrastinated terribly while writing the work, and in places it seems a rush job, for example the First Introit, a brassy, marching rondo for full forces that tries for a Shostakovich-like ironic edge but lacks harmonic bite.</p>
        <p>Adding a battery of amplified theater singers into the mix creates balance problems. It must have been discouraging for the Collegiate Chorale to sense that even in full-voiced outbursts it lacked the carrying power of a solo blues singer with a microphone.</p>
        <p>Still, it was wonderful to see the singers from the multiracial Brooklyn Youth Chorus snapping their fingers to Bernstein's jazzy riffs one moment, enraptured by his serene choral writing the next. Mr. Webster vividly enacted the Celebrant's spiritual crisis in ''How Easily Things Get Broken,'' a modern-day mad scene. In many ways ''Mass'' is an earnest mess, but it got to this baby boomer. Here is Uncle Lenny trying to make sense of it all. You have to love the guy.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
