<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'First Go for Life,' Workers Are Told</title>
    <meta content="31rescue" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1698596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="HURRICANE KATRINA: THE RESCUERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6D61631F932A0575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'First Go for Life,' Workers Are Told</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rescue teams in New Orleans mobilize to save hundreds of people stranded on upper floors and roofs by rising floodwaters from Hurricane Katrina, plucking people to safety with arsenal of lifesaving equipment; teams are told to leave bodies and save the living; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''If we come across a body floating?'' Sgt. Chris Fisher of the Jefferson Parish Sheriff's Office asked.</p>
        <p>''Let it go,'' Maj. Bobby Woods replied, as Sergeant Fisher and other rescue workers prepared for the day's mission. ''Let's first go for life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''If we come across a body floating?'' Sgt. Chris Fisher of the Jefferson Parish Sheriff's Office asked.</p>
        <p>''Let it go,'' Maj. Bobby Woods replied, as Sergeant Fisher and other rescue workers prepared for the day's mission. ''Let's first go for life.''</p>
        <p>With hundreds of New Orleans residents stranded on upper floors and roofs by rising floodwater from Hurricane Katrina, rescue teams from across the country mobilized in the gulf area on Tuesday in the largest relief effort since the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks.</p>
        <p>They sailed the seas over Interstate 10 and other submerged arteries, plucking people to safety with an arsenal of lifesaving equipment.</p>
        <p>The people who were saved emerged with anguished testimony of the human toll.</p>
        <p>A 95-year-old invalid drowned in her house after her daughter said she could not carry her to safety.</p>
        <p>''I had to give her mouth to mouth,'' the daughter, Judy Martin, said after swimming to a neighbor's house and being rescued there on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''She just said, 'I give up,''' Ms. Martin said of her mother, Cecile Dupont Martin, a former teacher.</p>
        <p>After being deposited on dry land where the highway emerged from the water and rescuers launched their airboats and other shallow-draft vessels, Judy Martin dropped to her knees, put her forehead on the pavement and wept.</p>
        <p>A truckload of National Guard troops said they had helped rush to the hospital a woman who delivered a baby in the back of a state wildlife and fisheries truck.</p>
        <p>A man stepped out of a rescue boat cradling a piglet.</p>
        <p>Pauline Stauss, 80, was rescued with a dog and three cats that she was keeping for her daughter.</p>
        <p>Kate Guelfo, 83, was the first of five in her flooded house to be rescued. With just one spot available in the rescue boat, her housemates pushed her out the window to safety, agreeing themselves to await later rescue. Ms. Guelfo's arm was black and blue, but she was grateful.</p>
        <p>Such poignant scenes abounded as New Orleans tried to fathom the scope of a disaster that left vast sections of its residential eastern part under water, in places roof deep.</p>
        <p>Natural gas bubbled up from severed lines. Petroleum fires flickered on the water.</p>
        <p>Power lines dangled onto roads, and telephone poles teetered, snapped like matchsticks.</p>
        <p>Levees breached in several places poured water from Lake Pontchartrain into the city.</p>
        <p>''It's worse than I thought it was,'' said Jim Strickland, the team leader for the Federal Emergency Management Agency, who presides over federal emergencies for four months a year, splitting the annual responsibility with two other managers.</p>
        <p>Battling the waters are hundreds of emergency workers mobilized by FEMA, including the Coast Guard and incident teams from Texas, Missouri and Tennessee.</p>
        <p>The teams, 70-member groups of firefighters and medical specialists, arrive with 18-wheelers and other trucks loaded with generators, chainsaws, tents and dogs that can sniff out the living and the dead.</p>
        <p>As of Tuesday night, they reported saving 315 people, including a 400-pound woman who was reached by cutting through a roof and a belligerent woman who had run out of methadone.</p>
        <p>A 50-vehicle convoy made its way into the city from Baton Rouge on Monday night. But the original base of operations, the downtown convention center, proved impossible to reach.</p>
        <p>The vehicles, after making wrong turns in the dark, assembled in an outlying Sam's Club parking lot. The store itself was too damaged to use for sleeping. The workers slept in their buses and trucks, without bathrooms.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday morning, the teams met for briefings.</p>
        <p>''The good news is the rain has gone,'' a supervisor for the federal emergency agency began. ''The bad news is it's going to be hot.''</p>
        <p>A series of briefers warned of the dangers from contaminated water, insects, underwater obstacles, snakes and alligators.</p>
        <p>For all the frantic mobilization, the pace of the operation was often agonizingly slow.</p>
        <p>A boat arrived without a key for the engine. No one knew the best way to the launching site.</p>
        <p>''The fog of war,'' an operations chief for the federal emergency agency, Mike Brown, said.</p>
        <p>The workers seemed impatient to get going, and they clearly relished the task.</p>
        <p>''All the folks that are easy to rescue get rescued right away,'' said Dr. Joe Holley, a physician from Memphis who directs medical operations. ''The problem is the guy in the attic. That's the one we're looking for with infrared and listening devices.''</p>
        <p>Not all the rescues were carried out by the authorities.</p>
        <p>Among a group of several hundred poor people and hospital patients removed from flooded areas and deposited by rescuers alongside Interstate 10 in an outlying area of the city was a retired mail carrier, Leonard J. Morris, 74, credited for his heroics.</p>
        <p>''He saved our lives,'' said Toniliese McNeil, 24, who added that Mr. Morris had come by with his boat and that when it ran out of fuel dragged the boat to their submerged house and rescued her and seven other people.</p>
        <p>''We were trapped in the house,'' Ms. McNeil said. ''And he had no way to get over to us. He had no gas. But he paddled his way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris explained that he knew the women and children across the way were in danger but that the raging wind on Monday morning made it almost impossible to respond.</p>
        <p>''They yelled across the water, 'It's up to our necks!''' he said, explaining that he jumped into the water and pulled the boat by its anchor, tossing the anchor forward each time.</p>
        <p>''I can't watch this,'' he remembered thinking. ''I can't see them die. So I kept throwing the anchor.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday afternoon, Mr. Morris and the survivors gathered alongside the road waiting for Army helicopters to carry them and the others to Houma.</p>
        <p>HURRICANE KATRINA: THE RESCUERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
