<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 'The Producers,' Another Box Office Bonanza</title>
    <meta content="17PROD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/17/nyregion/17PROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1536180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broderick, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lane, Nathan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Producers, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Nathan Lane</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Broderick, Matthew</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lane, Nathan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6D81138F934A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 'The Producers,' Another Box Office Bonanza</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For The Producers, Another Box Office Bonanza</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSE McKINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Producers earns $3.5 million in one day when thousands buy tickets for 14-week return engagement of Matthew Broderick and Nathan Lane; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Who says theater is dead?</p>
        <p>Thousands of musical lovers, theater fans and ticket scalpers descended on the St. James Theater yesterday to buy -- or try to buy -- tickets for the return engagement of Matthew Broderick and Nathan Lane in ''The Producers,'' making for a crowd that snarled pedestrian traffic throughout Times Square and last night toppled Broadway's single-day record for ticket sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands descended on the St. James Theater to buy  or try to buy  tickets for the return engagement of Matthew Broderick and Nathan Lane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Who says theater is dead?</p>
        <p>Thousands of musical lovers, theater fans and ticket scalpers descended on the St. James Theater yesterday to buy -- or try to buy -- tickets for the return engagement of Matthew Broderick and Nathan Lane in ''The Producers,'' making for a crowd that snarled pedestrian traffic throughout Times Square and last night toppled Broadway's single-day record for ticket sales.</p>
        <p>The show sold some 6,000 tickets in less than 90 minutes, both in person and through Telecharge, after the box office opened at noon. By 10 p.m., when the St. James's box office closed, more than 39,000 tickets had been sold, the producers said, and the day's take stood at nearly $3.5 million. Orders were still being taken through Telecharge.</p>
        <p>The previous record for one-day sales was also held by ''The Producers,'' which sold $3.3 million in tickets on the day after the show's opening in April 2001.</p>
        <p>The return of the show's two original stars -- who left the production last year after completing their contracts -- for a 14-week run beginning on Dec. 30, was officially announced last week, and ticket buyers started lining up as early as 5 a.m. on Friday, only to be dispersed by the police.</p>
        <p>Officers finally allowed crowds to start lining up in front of the theater at 12:01 a.m. yesterday, and the resulting crowd snaked around the block most of yesterday afternoon. Officials of the Jujamcyn, which owns the St. James, estimated the line had thousands of people at its peak.</p>
        <p>Those crowds continued to wait well into the evening; the box office, which was to have closed at 6 p.m., was asked by the show's producers to extend its hours, even as hopeful ticket buyers remained standing patiently -- or not so patiently -- along West 44th Street from Seventh to Eighth Avenues.</p>
        <p>''It's been very, very frustrating,'' said Brandon Nazario, 28, who drove in from Bethpage, N.Y. ''The shame of it was that the people before us were not exactly the greatest theater enthusiasts.''</p>
        <p>In addition to die-hard theatergoers, the producers of ''The Producers'' said they were also confronting another, less seemly, crowd: dozens of ''line-sitters,'' equipped with fistfuls of cash, who are paid by scalpers to buy chunks of tickets that are then resold at significant markups.</p>
        <p>A producer of the show, Richard Frankel, said that scalpers began depositing line-sitters by the vanful very early yesterday, and that by sunset many people who had joined that line as early 6 a.m. were still waiting behind scalpers to get tickets.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Frankel said that scalpers were using computer programs to buy blocks of tickets online, causing electronic traffic jams.</p>
        <p>''The good stuff is that there is a tremendous demand, affection, and regard for these performers and this play,'' Mr. Frankel said. ''But it is heartbreaking to see real theater lovers line up behind 250 yards of scalpers.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, while seats run from $30 (in the upper reaches of the balcony) to $1,500 for an orchestra seat for a special New Year's Eve ticket package, including dinner and Champagne, online scalpers were already advertising tickets for several times their face value late yesterday. One pair of the New Year's Eve tickets, for example, was advertised on eBay for $4,999.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frankel said that the police had asked the show's producers, for safety reasons, to limit sales to two tickets per person -- rather than the standard eight -- in an effort to speed up sales and thin the crowd along West 44th Street, which was mingling with large Sunday matinee audiences coming and going at other theaters.</p>
        <p>That reduction was forcing some tough decisions. ''I was going to bring my mother and my fiancé,'' said Tara Tisdale, 30, of Harlem, who had been in line since dawn. ''But I think it's going to be a girls' night out.''</p>
        <p>The sudden demand was a sharp reversal of fortune for a show that was once Broadway's hottest ticket but that had seen its sales fall off since Mr. Lane and Mr. Broderick, the original stars, left in March 2002. With lesser stars in the roles, ''The Producers'' has averaged only about 75 percent of capacity at the 1,706-seat St. James in recent months.</p>
        <p>The production, based on Mel Brooks' 1968 movie about a pair of scheming money men who aim to open a ''sure-fire flop'' and steal their investors' money, won a record 12 Tony Awards, including best musical. It was also one of the shows to recoup its investment most quickly in Broadway history, making back some $10.5 million in a little more than seven months.</p>
        <p>That is not to say that its producers, being producers, were not already wondering what could keep things rolling after its two prodigal stars leave again. Mr. Lane and Mr. Broderick's encore is scheduled to end on April 4.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be a hell of a party,'' said Rocco Landesman, another of the musical's producers. ''But it might also be a hell of a hangover.''</p>
        <p>Such worries, however, were far from the minds of those like Larry Landesman, 46, who had driven into the city from New Jersey at 6 a.m. to get tickets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Landesman -- who is no relation to the producer (he wouldn't be in line if he were) -- said he and his family had seen ''The Producers'' once before, but not with the original stars.</p>
        <p>''My family was so disappointed the first time we missed seeing Broderick and Lane, we decided we'd do anything to get tickets the next time around,'' Mr. Landesman said, still waiting in line at 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>''The parking fee will be outrageous, but it will be worth it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
