<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tyson's Driver Says Woman Was Dazed</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIANAPOLIS (IND)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGER, PHIL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON, DESIREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana/Indianapolis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Indiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE1131F931A35751C0A964958260" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tyson's Driver Says Woman Was Dazed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHIL BERGER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERGER, PHIL</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chauffeur for Mike Tyson during his 36 hours here last summer said today that the woman who has accused Tyson of rape appeared frantic and disoriented when she returned to the limousine from the boxer's hotel room early last July 19.</p>
        <p>During three hours of testimony, the chauffeur, Virginia Foster, described what she recalled about the 18-year-old woman when she joined Tyson in the limousine early that day and when she came out of the fighter's hotel just over an hour later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chauffeur for Mike Tyson during his 36 hours here last summer said today that the woman who has accused Tyson of rape appeared frantic and disoriented when she returned to the limousine from the boxer's hotel room early last July 19.</p>
        <p>During three hours of testimony, the chauffeur, Virginia Foster, described what she recalled about the 18-year-old woman when she joined Tyson in the limousine early that day and when she came out of the fighter's hotel just over an hour later.</p>
        <p>Her hair was fixed in a pretty-type hairdo," Foster said, recalling the woman's entry into the limousine. "There was something about it that caught my eye."</p>
        <p>But when she returned to the limousine, Foster said, "she looked like she may have been in a state of shock."</p>
        <p>One of the prosecutors, Barbara Trathen, asked Foster what she based her conclusion on.</p>
        <p>"Because of the way she was acting," Foster said. "Her appearance was like she was in a state of shock. Dazed. Disoriented. She seemed scared."</p>
        <p>Foster said that the woman, once inside the car, said: "I don't believe him.  I don't believe him. Who does he think he is?"</p>
        <p>Foster's testimony appeared to provide support for the prosecution's contention that the woman had been shaken by what occurred inside the Canterbury Hotel, where Tyson was staying.</p>
        <p>The former heavyweight champion is charged with raping the 18-year-old woman, who at the time was a contestant in a beauty pageant here. Tyson says they engaged in consensual sex, and the defense has tried to portray the woman as fully aware of what was happening when she accompanied Tyson to his room.</p>
        <p>On cross-examination today, Tyson's chief defense attorney, Vincent Fuller, tried to diminish Foster's account by suggesting that her observations were filtered through tired eyes.</p>
        <p>Fuller asked Foster how much sleep she had had when she woke up on July 18.</p>
        <p>"Four hours maybe," said Foster. "Four and a half."</p>
        <p>"You complained from time to time you were overworked," coaxed Fuller.</p>
        <p>"I was tired," said Foster.</p>
        <p>Fuller also sought to raise questions about Foster's character by suggesting she had overcharged Tyson for the use of the telephone in the limousine, that her $300 bill to Tyson was excessive. But Foster denied she had overcharged. 'I Heard Him Pleading'</p>
        <p>Earlier in her testimony today, Foster described how Tyson had convinced the woman to join him in the limousine. "I heard him pleading," Foster said of Tyson's phone call to the woman from the limousine. She was in her room at the Omni Hotel when the fighter phoned her from Foster's gold limousine.</p>
        <p>Foster testified that her phone records showed that Tyson's call to the woman was made at approximately 1:36 A.M. on July 19.</p>
        <p>Foster, a 44-year-old junior high school guidance counselor, quoted Tyson as saying to the woman, "Please. Please come down. I just want to talk to you."</p>
        <p>"It was like he was begging for someone to come down and talk to him," said Foster. "He said it several times, like men do when they're trying to get a woman to do something for them. So they beg and beg for it. 'Please, I just want to talk to you.' "</p>
        <p>Foster said a second call from the limousine was made to the woman's hotel room at 1:48 and that soon after, the woman arrived for her date with Tyson.</p>
        <p>Foster was asked whether there was any physical contact on the ride to the Canterbury Hotel, and she replied that she did not see any. Evidence Disallowed</p>
        <p>Before Foster testified this morning, the defense won an important motion that disallowed testimony from Foster about Tyson's sexual aggressiveness toward her during his stay in Indianapolis.</p>
        <p>Prosecutor J. Gregory Garrison told Judge Patricia Gifford that Tyson's actions were "almost a fingerprint" of the crime for which he is on trial.</p>
        <p>Garrison said that Tyson used virtually the same approach when Foster carried luggage into Room 604 at the Canterbury, the room belonging to Tyson's bodyguard, Dale Edwards, and at that time occupied by Tyson.</p>
        <p>"He says, 'Come on in, I just want to talk to you,' " Garrison said of Tyson. "He grabs her, and to use her phraseology, starts kissing her."</p>
        <p>Garrison said Foster rebuffed Tyson.</p>
        <p>But a Tyson defense lawyer, F. Lane Heard, argued that case law argued against the admission of such evidence. Gifford agreed and ordered the exclusion of the evidence, on which no charge was ever brought. 2 Doctors Testify</p>
        <p>After a recess, Dr. Thomas Richardson, who examined the woman on July 20, more than 24 hours after Tyson had sex with her, said that he observed two small vaginal abrasions. Richardson said the abrasions were of the sort that were common in 20 to 30 percent of the rape cases in which he has been medically involved.</p>
        <p>Richardson, who is an emergency room physician at Methodist Hospital here, said that in more than 2,000 routine pelvic examinations, he had seen that kind of abrasion only twice. On cross-examination, he said, "Her findings on the exam are consistent with forced or very hard intercourse."</p>
        <p>Richardson said that because of the woman's pain and because she backed away from a speculum probe, he did not complete the standard rape examination on the woman. "But 26 hours after, most of the samples would not be very much help," Richardson said.</p>
        <p>Richardson said the accuser was concerned about having either become pregant or having incurred a sexually transmitted disease from her contact with Tyson.</p>
        <p>The last witness on the third day of testimony was Dr. James Akin, an assistant professor at the Indiana University School of Medicine. Akin, who said that he had conducted more than 20,000 routine pelvic examinations, said the two abrasions Richardson found on the woman were "incredibly unlikely to happen in consensual sex."</p>
        <p>The trial continues Monday.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
