<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mutants, Guns And Football, All Right!</title>
    <meta content="19game" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/19/arts/19game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1762722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="VIDEO GAMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">E3 (Video Game Show)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Xbox 360 (Video Game System)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playstation 3 (Video Game System)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nintendo Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sony Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nintendo Company Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD9123EF93AA25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mutants, Guns And Football, All Right!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Best of the Best in Video Games From the E3 Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seth Schiesel article reports on E3 video game show in Los Angeles; reviews 10 notable games for Microsoft Xbox 360, Sony PlayStation 3, Nintendo Wii and PC; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU don't get a lot of sympathy when you tell people how tiring it was to cover the world's top video game convention, the mammoth E3 show in Los Angeles last week. Nongamers tend to offer a wary chuckle and mutter, ''I bet.'' Gamers, on the other hand, want to know whom you killed to get the job.</p>
        <p>Then they want to know what the top games were.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here are the 10 games that most stood out, grouped by platform, at the mammoth E3 show in Los Angeles last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU don't get a lot of sympathy when you tell people how tiring it was to cover the world's top video game convention, the mammoth E3 show in Los Angeles last week. Nongamers tend to offer a wary chuckle and mutter, ''I bet.'' Gamers, on the other hand, want to know whom you killed to get the job.</p>
        <p>Then they want to know what the top games were.</p>
        <p>In the last few days I've gotten that question on the phone, in e-mail, on chat boards, from my online guildmates, at local bars and from friends playing on my couch.</p>
        <p>I reply: ''Do you mean the games that will sell the most copies this year? Because that will be a lot of sequels, mostly for older systems like the PlayStation 2 and GameCube, games like Madden, Zelda, Final Fantasy and the inevitable Pokémon.''</p>
        <p>But top sellers are never what they mean by top games.</p>
        <p>Like most gamers, I went to the show caring about the best games headed to the newest systems. That means Microsoft's Xbox 360, which came out last year, and two consoles due later this year: Sony's PlayStation 3 and the Wii (pronounced whee, not why) from Nintendo. And of course I cared about the best games for the PC, which remains forever young as a gaming system because of constant upgrades.</p>
        <p>So in talking, eating, playing, drinking and (not so much) sleeping video games for a week straight, I tried to avoid sequels and concentrate on games for next-generation consoles and PC's.</p>
        <p>Given those conditions, here are the 10 that most stood out, grouped by platform (most of the games are months away from release, so their prices have not yet been determined):</p>
        <p>Microsoft Xbox 360</p>
        <p>Mass Effect -- Games for the Xbox 360 are first simply because the Xbox 360 will be in the hands of millions more people than the Wii and PS3 for quite some time yet. For most E3 attendees, the standout 360 game was probably the intense shooter Gears of War, due later this year. I admit that I have as much fun with a chainsaw as the next guy. But I often prefer a more atmospheric, story-driven kind of game, so Mass Effect, the new role-playing game due early next year from the famed developer BioWare, stood out as the 360 game I am most looking forward to playing. It looks absolutely sumptuous and should be a lot more expansive than BioWare's last sci-fi pageant, Knights of the Old Republic.</p>
        <p>Too Human -- Where Mass Effect may turn out to be a classic, sweeping role-playing game, à la Baldur's Gate, Too Human goes for a cinematic, fluid, high-action feel; it's a bit like a science-fiction Diablo. This game is all about mowing down waves of cybernetic opponents in truly beautiful settings. (In a nice twist, while the game is mostly set in a high-tech world, ''cyberspace'' is represented by lush, green forestscapes.) Due this holiday season.</p>
        <p>Rockstar Games Presents Table Tennis -- So after you've revolutionized video games and scandalized Capitol Hill with your Grand Theft Auto series, what do you release as your first next-generation project? If you're Rockstar Games, a table tennis game. That's it. No machine guns. No baseball bats. No beatdowns.</p>
        <p>Actually, that's not true. A score of 11-0 does count as a beatdown, as I discovered the hard way. I have to admit that with all of the expansive, high-profile games at E3, I actually spent more time playing Table Tennis than anything else. It just feels right (though the $40 price seems a bit steep). Due next week.</p>
        <p>Nintendo Wii</p>
        <p>Madden NFL '07 -- O.K., so I said I was going to stay away from sequels, but the way that Electronic Arts has reinvented Madden for Nintendo's new Wii console practically makes it feel like a brand-new game. Wondrously, Madden for Wii may actually let people who aren't video game maniacs just have fun playing video game football.</p>
        <p>The Wii's big breakthrough is that you can tilt and wave the TV-remote-style controller to produce action on the screen, rather than having to master complicated sequences of button-pushing and trigger-pulling. On the Xbox and PlayStation consoles, Madden has long since become the province of hard-core experts. If you can't master a serious portfolio of button and joystick combinations, you have no chance.</p>
        <p>But on the Wii, you simply throw your arm to throw a pass. When running, you stick your arm out to block. For those coming into E3, the functionality and fun of the Wii controller were huge question marks for Nintendo. Games like Madden helped turn Wii into one of the stars of the show.</p>
        <p>PC</p>
        <p>Spore -- Will Wright has been a star for years, ever since he designed SimCity. Now his ambitions are a lot broader than cities, or the mere families that populate The Sims, his second huge franchise. With Spore, you start by designing a microscopic bit of amoebalike genetic material, and then you guide your species all the way out of the primordial soup, onto land and into the stars.</p>
        <p>In trademark Wright style, Spore is totally free-form and dictated by the user's own sense of accomplishment rather than by explicit goals. The problem is that you may have heard all this before, because Spore was also one of the standouts at last year's E3. It still has no release date. Because he's Will Wright, he can release the game when he thinks it's ready, and no one at Electronic Arts will be able to tell him otherwise.</p>
        <p>Hellgate: London -- Like Too Human for the 360, Hellgate takes many of its cues from Diablo, the archetypal action role-playing game. Unlike Too Human, Hellgate is being made by many of the top people who invented Diablo. Now reconstituted as Flagship Studios, they are making a game that is meant to be a science-fiction, 3D update on the Diablo concept: random dungeons, slot machine-style loot and a fanatical online community.</p>
        <p>Hellgate isn't a huge multiplayer game like World of Warcraft, but it could appeal to a lot of the same sort of players (like me) as a change of pace and scenery. There are enough fantasy role-playing games at the moment. Like Mr. Wright, the Flagship team will release the game when it's ready, but look for a beta test, at least, this year.</p>
        <p>Sony PlayStation 3</p>
        <p>Assassin's Creed -- After looking at a few dozen games, I realized that one of the hardest things was staying open-minded in comparing Xbox 360 games with games on the way for the PlayStation 3. After all, the 360 has been out for six months, and some developers are working on their second generation of games for it, so naturally the 360 games as a group looked better than their PS3 counterparts.</p>
        <p>Visually, games like Warhawk did give me a sense of the PS3's graphics power. But in terms of game play, Assassin's Creed was really the first PS3 demo I saw that revealed the kind of scope we're starting to see coming to the 360. Assassin's Creed is set during the Crusades, and my demo had the main character sneaking through the bazaars and over the rooftops of Acre in 1191 in search of one William de Montferrat. Assassin's Creed was one of those games I really wanted to play when the demo ended. Due early 2007, from Ubisoft.</p>
        <p>Sonic the Hedgehog -- Sequel alert! But that's why Sonic was clearly the most compelling PS3 action game I saw. High-speed jumping and spinning are what Sonic does, and Sega clearly has the formula down for the PlayStation 3. Did the PS3 version look better than the 360 version around the corner? No. But that's to be expected, given that the PlayStation games are running on test systems. Due this year.</p>
        <p>Resistance: Fall of Man -- It would be easy to gloss over this game simply because the role Sony wants it to fill when the PlayStation 3 comes out this November is so obvious: Gears of War killer. That may be too much to ask, but Resistance will certainly be able to at least stand up to Gears, the coming 360 shooter. Put another way, Resistance is the sharp first-person shooter that Sony has to have to appeal to a broad swath of the hard-core gaming population. Set in an alternate 1951 Britain (World War II never happened; think mutants instead of Nazis), Resistance has good looks and the polish you would expect from a game being published by Sony itself. Due this November.</p>
        <p>Marvel Ultimate Alliance -- The last word goes to my personal surprise of the show. As I wrote online (nytimes.com/e3) last week: ''I'm not a comic-hater, but I don't think I've ever bought a comic book in my life (besides the Fabulous Furry Freak Brothers, but that's a whole different category). Nonetheless, I have to say that Marvel Ultimate Alliance looks like a blast. It's an action game with light role-playing elements that teams up rotating bands of famous Marvel characters in their inevitable battle to save the world. (Or is it the universe? I can't remember.)'' Due this fall, from Activision.</p>
        <p>VIDEO GAMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
