<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Are Tripping Over Themselves, Not the Tigers</title>
    <meta content="21YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/21/sports/21YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DA1630F932A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Are Tripping Over Themselves, Not the Tigers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Detroit Tigers defeat New York Yankees, 5-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Adrian Hernández made his first start in the major leagues tonight and you couldn't have blamed him had he looked giddily around the field, wide-eyed, and wondered if he was surrounded by impostors.</p>
        <p>In fact, there were seven former or current All-Stars in the Yankees' lineup, not that you could tell by their production against a Detroit pitcher with a bloated earned run average, or by their shaky defense, their shabby relief pitching or the crippling base-running mistake by Jorge Posada in the eighth inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Adrian Hernández made his first start in the major leagues tonight and you couldn't have blamed him had he looked giddily around the field, wide-eyed, and wondered if he was surrounded by impostors.</p>
        <p>In fact, there were seven former or current All-Stars in the Yankees' lineup, not that you could tell by their production against a Detroit pitcher with a bloated earned run average, or by their shaky defense, their shabby relief pitching or the crippling base-running mistake by Jorge Posada in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>Hernández, one of three rookies in Manager Joe Torre's rotation, gave his team a chance to win against the Tigers, one of the league's weakest teams, and the Yankees lost, 5-2, at Comerica Park. They fell three and a half games behind the Boston Red Sox in the American League East.</p>
        <p>Boston has won 14 of its last 19 games, without shortstop Nomar Garciaparra and despite the fact that pitcher Pedro Martínez had to miss a start. The Red Sox are playing well, and the Yankees -- who seemed to be on the verge of a lengthy winning streak last week -- are stumbling in what is supposed to be one of the easier segments of their schedule.</p>
        <p>Boston's recent success ''doesn't bother me as much as our losing,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>He added: ''If we can't win our games, we don't deserve to be closer. If we're a good team, we can overcome that.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees played terribly tonight in an absolutely winnable game. Their biggest concern tonight was whether Hernández would be anxious and wild and unsure. But he was composed and aggressive, like his namesake; Hernández is known as El Duquecito because he copied the delivery of El Duque, Orlando Hernández, who is no relation.</p>
        <p>''He had a lot of poise and a lot of energy,'' Posada said of the rookie Hernández, a right-hander.</p>
        <p>Hernández allowed a home run in the second, pitched around a couple of walks in the fourth and would have gotten through the fifth if not for a couple of errors.</p>
        <p>Detroit's Shane Halter hit a grounder at second baseman Alfonso Soriano, a potential double play. But the ball bounced off Soriano's chest, rolled toward Derek Jeter as Jeter prepared for a force at second base, then it skipped off the bag, a freak play. Both runners were safe and Soriano was charged with an error.</p>
        <p>Jarrod Patterson then rolled one to first baseman Tino Martinez, who flubbed the ball, making his first error after 77 consecutive errorless games.</p>
        <p>With the bases filled, a run scored on a wild pitch. With two out, Torre relieved Hernández, Detroit leading by 2-1.</p>
        <p>An inning later, Randy Choate issued a one-out walk before Ramiro Mendoza relieved him, walked a batter and surrendered a two-run double. It was Detroit 4, Yankees 1.</p>
        <p>Mike Stanton relieved in the seventh and allowed a solo home run to Detroit's Bobby Higginson, the 10th homer allowed by the Yankees' bullpen in the past 16 games. The bullpen had allowed one home run from April 29 to June 4, a span of 27 games.</p>
        <p>So the Yankees trailed by 5-1 as the eighth inning began, but the game was still seemingly within their grasp.</p>
        <p>Chris Holt started for the Tigers, having allowed 136 base runners in 79 2/3 innings in his first 14 games and having compiled a 5.76 E.R.A. The Yankees kept initiating rallies against him.</p>
        <p>They had runners at first and second with one out in the second, one run in, and could not score more. They had runners at first and third with nobody out in the third, and could not score. With runners at first and second and one out in the fourth -- and again in the fifth -- they still  could not score.</p>
        <p>Holt was still in the game to start the eighth, and Martinez singled. Posada pulled a hit over first base, thinking immediately that the ball was headed for the corner and that he would get a double.</p>
        <p>Martinez raced for third and Posada turned at first, though the Yankees were down by four runs. As Posada neared second base, he realized he was in serious jeopardy of being cut down. Juan Encarnacion's throw beat him to the bag; Posada was tagged out.</p>
        <p>''It's just not a good play,'' Torre said. ''The fact that we were down by four runs at the time, that's just not a good play.''</p>
        <p>Posada said, ''It's tough to make up for that mistake when you're down by four runs.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees never recovered, finishing the game with two hits in 17 at-bats with runners in scoring position, 11 runners left on base, and a little further behind the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>Rookies have started three times in a four-game stretch for the Yankees for the first time since Andy Pettitte, Mariano Rivera and Brian Boehringer started in a four-game stretch in 1995.</p>
        <p>Ted Lilly left Sunday's game against the Mets with a 5-1 lead. Randy Keisler allowed three runs in six respectable innings Tuesday, the Yankees trailing by 3-1. Hernández surrendered two runs, one earned, in four and two-thirds innings tonight.</p>
        <p>The Yankees lost all three games, but not because of the rookie pitchers.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>ROGER CLEMENS is 9-1 and a strong candidate for the American League All-Star team. He could be in a position to pitch against the Mets' MIKE PIAZZA in the July 10 All-Star Game in Seattle. Clemens said he wasn't thinking about making the All-Star team, but he suggested that perhaps the All-Star Game would provide a more comfortable setting for him and Piazza to talk about the pitch that hit Piazza in the head and the bat toss in the World Series.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
