<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>His Head Held High, Very High, Cuomo Is Done In His Way</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="724460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1994 ELECTIONS: NEW YORK STATE LAST HURRAH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FIRESTONE, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E6DD1E3EF933A25752C1A962958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>His Head Held High, Very High, Cuomo Is Done In His Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FIRESTONE, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Searching through the millions of glistening words that constituted Mario M. Cuomo's final campaign for governor, it is difficult to find more than a handful in which he explained how his fourth term would have been different from the previous three.</p>
        <p>It did not matter that the popular demand for change became so incessant that he could not have mistaken its threatening implications for his career. He declined, for reasons of principle, pride and a trademarked stiffness of neck, to pay tribute to that national mood, instead attacking it in speech after speech as a Republican construct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Searching through the millions of glistening words that constituted Mario M. Cuomo's final campaign for governor, it is difficult to find more than a handful in which he explained how his fourth term would have been different from the previous three.</p>
        <p>It did not matter that the popular demand for change became so incessant that he could not have mistaken its threatening implications for his career. He declined, for reasons of principle, pride and a trademarked stiffness of neck, to pay tribute to that national mood, instead attacking it in speech after speech as a Republican construct.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, while Mr. Cuomo spent the day closeted in his office in Albany, several of the Governor's friends and advisers contemplated the impending demise of his stewardship, insisting that, even as his campaign broadcast negative ads, he himself had run a campaign obstinately high-minded and incapable of resisting the sour tide of the voters. By not giving in to the anger, by not even hinting that life would be somehow different through his 16th year in office, he preserved his singular sense of honor while annoying the electorate and losing his job.</p>
        <p>"The voters' frustration was so great that all they cared about was change," said Meyer S. Frucher, one of the Governor's closest friends and advisers. "But the thing that makes me the proudest was that he never pandered to that. He is a guy who had deep and strong convictions, and what you saw is what you got."</p>
        <p>During the campaign season, Mr. Cuomo was compulsively driven to defend his 12-year record in the face of constant criticisms that he had no memorable accomplishments. The record eventually became everything. If someone asked him the rationale for a fourth term, as editors and reporters of The New York Times did in a five-hour interview on Sept. 26, he would begin to recite the high points of his past three. Pressed explicitly on what would happen in the future, he would refer to projects that would continue from his earlier terms, rather than open a sketchbook of new ideas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frucher said some in the campaign pressed Mr. Cuomo to concentrate more on "the future thing," as staffers put it, and throttle back on the sweeping dioramas of New York's past and present. Advocates for that position, he said, did not prevail.</p>
        <p>"There was always a desire on the part of a lot people in the campaign to talk about 'the future thing' as opposed to 'the vision thing,' " he said. "The problem with the future thing is that no one was listening, and unless you made the case for your incumbency, you could not make the case for the future. If you did, you'd do it in a disconnected way, where you end up looking at the polls and pandering."</p>
        <p>And pandering was the one thing his enormous pride refused to let him do, associates say. He would prefer to answer a simple question with a flip answer rather than give in to what might be seen as sentiment or cliche. When asked during the Times interview which accomplishment he wanted to be remembered for, his arch response was "being a four-term governor." And by the same token, describing the differences of a fourth term would have been admitting that there was something wrong with the first three.</p>
        <p>"Why say you would do it differently over the next four years just to satisfy that sense for change?" asked Geraldine A. Ferraro, the former vice-presidential candidate who campaigned extensively for her Democratic colleague from Queens. "He's not the kind of guy who would change course in order to please the press and the public."</p>
        <p>But why couldn't Mr. Cuomo, with his abundant rhetorical gifts, have tried to grapple with the angry national mood, rather than fire scattershot in its direction, as he did in his concession speech on Tuesday night when he said cynicism simply was not appropriate for the nation or the state? One of his allies, State Senator Manfred Ohrenstein, the retiring minority leader, said the Governor realized that an appeal to logic -- his Jesuitical strong suit -- would have failed in such an attempt, and that he did not want to stoop to emotionalism.</p>
        <p>"Mario Cuomo ran a campaign which expressed his particular style and approach to government," Mr. Ohrenstein said. "Knowing him, I don't see how he could have done it any differently."</p>
        <p>THE 1994 ELECTIONS: NEW YORK STATE LAST HURRAH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
