<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; No Faults Allowed In This Business</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505619"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STRATUS COMPUTER INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIFKIN, GLENN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD1038F936A35751C0A964958260" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; No Faults Allowed In This Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Glenn Rifkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIFKIN, GLENN</byline>
      <dateline>MARLBORO, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN an industry where profit-killing competition and slumping business are the norm, Stratus Computer Inc. continues to defy the odds by stringing up quarter after quarter of solid profits.</p>
        <p>Stratus has quietly and steadily built itself into the second-largest maker of "fault tolerant" computers. Such machines are designed with enough backup components that they are never supposed to fail, as most conventional computers occasionally do, and they have become a mainstay in businesses where uninterrupted computer service is essential. Automatic teller machines, electronic-funds transfers and Wall Street trading operations all rely on fault-tolerant machines.</p>
        <p>For the fourth quarter ending Dec. 29, Stratus's earnings rose 30 percent, compared with the corresponding quarter in 1990. For the full year in 1991,profits jumped 34 percent, to $49.7 million, on revenues of $448.6 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN an industry where profit-killing competition and slumping business are the norm, Stratus Computer Inc. continues to defy the odds by stringing up quarter after quarter of solid profits.</p>
        <p>Stratus has quietly and steadily built itself into the second-largest maker of "fault tolerant" computers. Such machines are designed with enough backup components that they are never supposed to fail, as most conventional computers occasionally do, and they have become a mainstay in businesses where uninterrupted computer service is essential. Automatic teller machines, electronic-funds transfers and Wall Street trading operations all rely on fault-tolerant machines.</p>
        <p>For the fourth quarter ending Dec. 29, Stratus's earnings rose 30 percent, compared with the corresponding quarter in 1990. For the full year in 1991,profits jumped 34 percent, to $49.7 million, on revenues of $448.6 million.</p>
        <p>Since going public in 1983, Stratus, which is traded on the New York Stock Exchange under the symbol SRA, has not had a single losing quarter. Analysts see no end soon to that run. "Stratus can grow 20 percent per year for the next four years," said David Wu, an analyst with S. G. Warburg &amp; Company. "They survive recessions very well."</p>
        <p>The company that created the first fault-tolerant computers, Tandem Computer in Cupertino, Calif., holds more than 70 percent of the $2.3 billion market, according to John B. Jones of Montgomery Securities in San Francisco. But Stratus, founded in 1980, has steadily whittled away at Tandem's lead, growing from a 10 percent share in 1985 to 24 percent in 1991.</p>
        <p>"Tandem was in the business for a good six years before Stratus ever shipped its first system," Mr. Jones said. "I expect them to continue to gain market share against Tandem."</p>
        <p>Stratus's own sales force sells more than half the company's machines, but the company also has agreements with I.B.M., Olivetti, NEC and Ericsson, among others, to resell Stratus computers under their own labels.</p>
        <p>Even as demand grows for fault-tolerant systems, companies are willing to pay a premium price for them, compared with conventional computers. "Any system where the computer has direct contact with the customer is a candidate for fault-tolerant computers," Mr. Jones said. "People are willing to pay 15 percent to 25 percent more for continuous availability."</p>
        <p>Despite the premium, Mr. Wu said, the cost of fault-tolerant computers is falling, enticing more companies to take a look at the technology they once considered too expensive. The starting price for Stratus machines is $50,000, though high-end machines can cost $9 million or more.</p>
        <p>The telecommunications market has become a major target for Stratus and Tandem in the last two years, as telephone companies are increasingly using the machines to provide call waiting, voice mail and other new network services. Stratus has made strong inroads into that market, which company executives see as a potential $4 billion to $8 billion market in the next four years.</p>
        <p>But Stratus also faces increased competition from giants like Digital Equipment, Hewlett-Packard, Fujitsu and Hitachi, which have all entered the fault-tolerant market in recent years. To maintain its pace, Stratus has pushed its technology in the direction of "open systems," the computer industry trend to make different brands of computers work together.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Stratus last year began shipping computers with more advanced components, based on the technology known as RISC, for reduced instruction set computing. As part of this move, Stratus is shifting its entire product line away from Motorola microprocessors to RISC chips made by Intel. Customers of Status's RISC-based systems will be able to use the same hardware to run either the company's VOS software operating system or the more widely used Unix operating system to control the computer's internal operations.</p>
        <p>John Adams, an analyst with Adams, Harkness &amp; Hill in Boston, said Stratus's biggest challenge was a management concern: "how to fight 'creeping large company-itis.' "</p>
        <p>To ward off corporate sprawl, William Foster, Stratus's founder, president and chief executive, has built a fiscally conservative corporate culture. The company has incurred little long-term debt, accrued $100 million in cash and has fought the uncontrolled growth that is now haunting larger competitors like the Digital Equipment Corporation and the International Business Machines Corporation.</p>
        <p>Gary E. Haroian, senior vice president and general manager of Stratus, said: "We want to avoid reducing employment like so many others have had to do. With our profits up 30 percent last year, we only added 100 people to the payroll."</p>
        <p>Mr. Jones of Montgomery Securities rates Stratus a 'buy,' predicting that the stock will outperform the market, with the price rising 10 percent within six months. He estimates earnings per share at $2.70 for 1992, up 22 percent. Mr. Wu rates the stock a "hold," waiting for a small price correction. "It's trading at $47 now and should be at $60 in 12 months," he said. "But the rewards are not high enough to put out a 'buy' just yet."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
