<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EASTERN GERMAN IS INVESTIGATED</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRANDENBURG (GERMANY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STASI (EAST GERMAN INTELLIGENCE SERVICE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOLPE, MANFRED</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DA1038F936A35751C0A964958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EASTERN GERMAN IS INVESTIGATED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Feb. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the most popular leaders of eastern Germany is caught in the crossfire of controversy about collaboration with the old Communist secret police, the Stasi, as east and west come to grips with Germany's near and distant past.</p>
        <p>The parliament of Brandenburg, the largest of the states carved out of old East Germany, has ordered a commission to investigate the activities of Manfred Stolpe, the state's prime minister, when he worked as an lawyer representing East Germany's evangelical protestant church in its dealings with the communist regime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the most popular leaders of eastern Germany is caught in the crossfire of controversy about collaboration with the old Communist secret police, the Stasi, as east and west come to grips with Germany's near and distant past.</p>
        <p>The parliament of Brandenburg, the largest of the states carved out of old East Germany, has ordered a commission to investigate the activities of Manfred Stolpe, the state's prime minister, when he worked as an lawyer representing East Germany's evangelical protestant church in its dealings with the communist regime.</p>
        <p>The decision comes only days after the prime minister of neighboring Thuringia, Josef Duchac, stepped down amid charges of collaboration with the regime.</p>
        <p>In a surprise move, Mr. Stolpe made a public disclosure two weeks ago, revealing in an interview with the weekly Der Spiegel that he had clandestine contacts with senior Stasi officials on church business. But he denied he benefited the secret police, arguing the contacts were required as part of his role in representing the church and East Germans under its wing. Taking the Offensive</p>
        <p>The two cases are the latest in a series of startling assaults on members of the fledgling democratic leadership that emerged in eastern Germany after the collapse of communism for their alleged links with the old secret police.</p>
        <p>In many cases, resignations have come after the disclosure of confidential material by western news organizations, fueling resentment among eastern Germans that the home-grown political leadership is being intentionally compromised by materials obtained from dispersed Stasi files and purposely leaked in the west.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stolpe decided to take the offensive after it became clear that west German television stations were about to disclose information intended to damage him. Bavarian state television, which is closely allied with the governing Bavarian Christian Social Union, made public documents purportedly pointing to a collaboration between the 55-year old lawyer, who is a Social Democrat, and the Stasi.</p>
        <p>Many of the Stasi documents relating to prominent post-communist leaders like Mr. Stolpe disappeared from Stasi files in the waning last days of communism. In some cases, like Mr. Stolpe's, files were thinned in such a way as to render a defense more difficult. Colonization Asserted</p>
        <p>East German dissidents who were expelled from their country in 1988 after a wave of anti-Government protests found that all references in their files to Mr. Stolpe's role as church-authorized negotiator with the communists are gone.</p>
        <p>The gradual decimation of the post-communist leadership is reinforcing accusations among east Germans of a kind of colonialization by western Germany. The assertions gained force last week after the western German leadership overrode strenuous local objections and appointed Bernhard Vogel, a political crony of Chancellor Helmut Kohl and a westerner, to succeed Mr. Duchac in Thuringia.</p>
        <p>Unlike the case of Mr. Duchac, the accusations against Mr. Stolpe have brought forth firm defenders of his innocence, some appealing to historical precedents for justifying dealings with criminal regimes.</p>
        <p>Klaus von Dohnanyi, the former Social Democratic Mayor of Hamburg and the son of Hans von Dohnanyi, a former Nazi intelligence agent who was executed in 1945 for resistance to Hitler, compared Mr. Stolpe's behavior with that of Dietrich Bonhoffer, the younger Mr. Dohnanyi's uncle and a prominent theologian who used contacts with Nazi intelligence during the Third Reich to further efforts to eliminate Hitler. A Double Standard</p>
        <p>Such references to recent history help fuel the argument of those in east and west who increasingly accuse western Germans of applying a double standard in dealing with the east's communist past. They argue that the same West Germany that was soft on former Nazis after the war is now unswervingly pursuing communist collaborators for far less grievous offenses.</p>
        <p>That argument was raised last month, when a Berlin court convicted two former East German border guards of killing their own countrymen at the Berlin wall. The court argued that the guards had the duty to disobey the communist Government's orders when they shot and killed a man who was the last of about 200 East Germans killed trying to flee the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
