<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Space, and in East-West Politics, It's a Very Long Voyage to Mars</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RUSSIA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MARS (PLANET)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA (RUSSIAN REPUBLIC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D61238F936A35751C0A964958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Space, and in East-West Politics, It's a Very Long Voyage to Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the nation's civilian space program drifts aimlessly, undone by the cold war's demise, calls are rising for the United States to join its former Russian foes in history's most ambitious voyage -- sending humans across many millions of miles of space to explore Mars.</p>
        <p>The undertaking would tap skills of East and West and give both sides needed new direction, experts say. They note that NASA's $14 billion-a-year budget is under fire and that Moscow's space program is cracking under political and economic problems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the nation's civilian space program drifts aimlessly, undone by the cold war's demise, calls are rising for the United States to join its former Russian foes in history's most ambitious voyage -- sending humans across many millions of miles of space to explore Mars.</p>
        <p>The undertaking would tap skills of East and West and give both sides needed new direction, experts say. They note that NASA's $14 billion-a-year budget is under fire and that Moscow's space program is cracking under political and economic problems.</p>
        <p>"There's a reservoir of skills, facilities and capabilities in the former Soviet Union that ought to be used for common objectives," says John M. Logsdon, a space-policy expert at George Washington University. "It makes no sense to throw it away."</p>
        <p>Last month, Russian scientists called for a Mars mission, echoing earlier proposals by private American groups like the Planetary Society, the National Space Society and the Federation of American Scientists. Just Talk, for Now</p>
        <p>The White House is said to be actively interested, if uncommitted. In 1990 President Bush announced an "exploratory dialogue" with the Soviet Union about joint ventures in space, including a manned trip to Mars. So far, however, East-West action on this issue has gone no farther than polite discussions.</p>
        <p>Originally, the space programs of both East and West were anything but aimless. Both were cold-war creations, weapons in a costly race for technical superiority and global intimidation: The Soviet Union launched the first satellite in 1957 and the first man into space in 1961, then America forged ahead by landing men on the moon in 1969. The United States pressed onward in 1981 to launch the world's first reusable spaceship, the winged shuttle.</p>
        <p>But this extraordinary feat of engineering initially had no mission aside from getting to the Moon before the Russians did. "The cold war turned our space program into a propaganda program, always in search of spectacular, high-profile stunts," said Walter A. McDougall, a historian at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The Russians concentrated on heft -- bigger rockets, longer missions, more frequent launchings. Beginning in 1971, the Soviet Union put into orbit a series of manned space stations that have kept Moscow's astronauts circling Earth for increasingly long periods. What Each Could Contribute</p>
        <p>Space experts say this experience in long-duration space flights would be of great value on Mars voyages. The Russians could also help in rocketry. Recently, scientists from Moscow described their efforts to perfect nuclear engines and proposed collaboration on an atom-powered trip to the red planet.</p>
        <p>For its part, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration has much technology critical for a Mars venture and has sent astronauts to a planetary body and returned them safely. But NASA is leery of a joint expedition. Among other things, it worries that political discord in the former Soviet Union would rule out the kind of long-term cooperation needed for the endeavor.</p>
        <p>Advocates of a joint Mars voyage say that it would foster the kind of political stability Moscow now wants, bolstering the Russian Government's legitimacy and helping to stem the growing exodus of Russian scientists and engineers to arms factories in foreign lands, a gnawing Western worry in the post-cold-war world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
