<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Saatchi Sets Network for Health Care</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTHCOM INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAATCHI &amp; SAATCHI CO PLC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDB123DF936A35751C0A964958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Saatchi Sets Network for Health Care</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE pediatricians who move their offices closer to nursery schools, Saatchi &amp; Saatchi P.L.C. is changing the way it does business to exploit the rapid growth in health care.</p>
        <p>Effective today, the London-based global advertising giant has formed Healthcom, a worldwide network of health-care agencies that previously operated as part of its two general international agency networks, Backer Spielvogel Bates Worldwide and Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Advertising Worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE pediatricians who move their offices closer to nursery schools, Saatchi &amp; Saatchi P.L.C. is changing the way it does business to exploit the rapid growth in health care.</p>
        <p>Effective today, the London-based global advertising giant has formed Healthcom, a worldwide network of health-care agencies that previously operated as part of its two general international agency networks, Backer Spielvogel Bates Worldwide and Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Advertising Worldwide.</p>
        <p>The consolidation, which establishes a single global brand name for the Saatchi agencies that focus on health care, creates the third-largest such international network, with billings of $214 million and income of $27 million. First is Medicus Intercon International Inc., owned by D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles in New York, followed by Sudler &amp; Hennessey, owned by Young &amp; Rubicam Inc. in New York.</p>
        <p>"We looked at our various holdings," Richard F. O'Brien, vice chairman of Saatchi Worldwide, said in an interview at the agency's office in downtown Manhattan, "and decided that we had in place good health care agencies in most of the economies of the world."</p>
        <p>"But they never had been knitted together into a cohesive, global force," he added. "Perhaps that time has come."</p>
        <p>The consolidation, in development for six months, responds to a boom in health care advertising, which has surged as health care has expanded around the world. For instance, global sales of over-the-counter drugs, now about $23 billion, are expected to exceed $50 billion by 2000.</p>
        <p>Billings in health care advertising are growing at an annual rate of about 9 percent, said Gary D. Landis, who has been named managing director of Healthcom, while there has been little or no growth in general advertising billings.</p>
        <p>The consolidation also responds to the needs of clients, which are merging, amalgamating and forming strategic alliances at a feverish pace as they seek to become worldwide forces in marketing prescription and over-the-counter drugs, herbal and homeopathic remedies and even healthier, better-for-you foods that are advertised as if they were drugs.</p>
        <p>Among such companies are Pfizer, which Healthcom has as a client in France, Germany and Britain; Upjohn, a Healthcom client in Canada, Spain and the United States, and Glaxo, a Healthcom client in France, Italy and Britain.</p>
        <p>"The concept is simple," said Mr. Landis, who is 51 years old, a longtime Saatchi executive who joined Mr. O'Brien for the interview, "to create a global health care communications capability to service a global health care industry."</p>
        <p>The consolidation, which Saatchi calls a joint venture of the two networks, involves eight agencies in eight countries: Britain, Canada, France, Germany, Italy, Spain, Sweden and the United States. Five had been under Backer's aegis and three under Saatchi Worldwide. Two other agencies in Australia and Japan, one from each network, are scheduled to come aboard around April.</p>
        <p>In each case, the agency adds the prosaic Healthcom name, a telescoping of the words Healthcare Communications, to its existing name. For instance, Klemtner Advertising Inc. in New York, a health care agency from the Saatchi Worldwide network, with billings of about $125 million, is being rechristened Klemtner/Healthcom.</p>
        <p>This is Saatchi's second amalgamation of services under a single banner in two months, following consolidation of its direct-marketing operations under the network of Kobs &amp; Draft, formerly a Backer unit.</p>
        <p>"In some of these specialized services, it doesn't make sense to maintain two competitive resources around the world," Mr. O'Brien said.</p>
        <p>"Why have two," he added, "when one will do?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
