<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRADA, MIUCCIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DA1039F935A15752C1A963958260" item-length="504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surge in Sales of Italian Bags Inspires Plan for Large Store</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surge in Sales of Italian Bags Inspires Plan for Large Store</p>
        <p>In the late 1980's, the Italian designer Miuccia Prada's signature knapsacks and evening bags in black leather or nylon "sat on the shelves," a spokeswoman for Ms. Prada's company willingly concedes. "Then all of a sudden we couldn't make enough of them."</p>
        <p>Last year's sales of Prada's bags, clothing and shoes totaled $210 million,  up 31 percent from 1993, said the spokeswoman, Leslie Johnsen. The numbers persuaded Ms. Prada and her husband, Patrizio diMarco, Prada's president, to buy the landmark building on the southeast corner of Madison Avenue and 70th Street  and open a 21,000-square-foot store on three levels. Prada's only other store in the city is a tiny 800 square feet on 57th Street between Madison and Park Avenues.</p>
        <p>The opening was planned for early 1996, but problems in renovating the landmarked building have delayed the opening, now projected for spring.</p>
        <p>Prada bags range from $75 for a cosmetic case to $1,000 for a polished leather handbag; clothing is priced from $600 for a dress to $1,800 for a cashmere coat.</p>
        <p>Family Does It Again: Opening A West Side Restaurant-Pizzeria</p>
        <p>Five years ago, the Cohen family -- Marilyn, a former criminal lawyer; Dan,  a film producer, and their daughter, Kimi, an artist -- opened Don Giovanni, an  Italian restaurant and brick-oven pizzeria on 10th Avenue between 22d and 23d Streets. Last week, they opened another at 358 West 44th Street, between Eighth and Ninth Avenues.</p>
        <p>The new restaurant seats 100 and offers a choice of pastas and sauces that include pesto, Gorgonzola, mozzarella and eggplant, and chopped tomatoes and basil. Entrees range from $6.95 to $13. Pizzas ($6.95 to $11.95) come in many varieties, among them tomato, fresh mozzarella and basil; vegetarian genovese, with spinach, basil, onions, garlic and green pepper, and white clam with garlic, Parmesan and olive oil.</p>
        <p>The restaurant also offers takeout and delivery: (212) 581-4939.</p>
        <p>A Maker of Paper Plates and Cups Buys a Maker of Fancier Ware</p>
        <p>The Fonda Group, a Westchester company that makes paper plates and cups sold under the house labels of several major supermarket chains, recently bought Alfred Bleyer &amp; Company, a 127-year-old manufacturer of decorative paper products in Maspeth, Queens.</p>
        <p>Dennis Mehiel, who heads Fonda, said the acquisition was made with an eye toward taking Fonda public. Last March, the company, with $180 million in annual sales, bought the food service division of Scott Paper, which makes napkins, place mats and table covers.</p>
        <p>Bleyer, with $30 million in annual sales, has 200 employees, a number that Mr. Mehiel expects to grow slightly next year. Bleyer makes more expensive paper and party products that sell under several labels, mainly in convenience and drug stores.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
