<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rare Indeed: A Restaurant Aging Well</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">STAMFORD (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">IL FALCO RISTORANTE (STAMFORD)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DC1039F935A15752C1A963958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rare Indeed: A Restaurant Aging Well</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MANY restaurants open with a surge and end limply. It is more unusual for a restaurant to improve as it ages. Il Falco Ristorante in downtown Stamford, now  in its ninth year, has clearly entered its surge, considerably fine tuned from its early years. It had a Good rating to begin with, but now it merits a Very Good indeed. The recitation of specials has been replaced at dinner by a printed list. Service, always polished, seems even more attentive to diners' needs, without hovering or being obtrusive -- a fine line.</p>
        <p>The decor is much the same, with lace cafe curtains at the front windows and  mirrored walls, though the posters in the nonsmoking section have been replaced  by floral prints. And weren't the orchid walls once a pale pink? Mostly, though, it is the menu and food that have developed into something very special.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MANY restaurants open with a surge and end limply. It is more unusual for a restaurant to improve as it ages. Il Falco Ristorante in downtown Stamford, now  in its ninth year, has clearly entered its surge, considerably fine tuned from its early years. It had a Good rating to begin with, but now it merits a Very Good indeed. The recitation of specials has been replaced at dinner by a printed list. Service, always polished, seems even more attentive to diners' needs, without hovering or being obtrusive -- a fine line.</p>
        <p>The decor is much the same, with lace cafe curtains at the front windows and  mirrored walls, though the posters in the nonsmoking section have been replaced  by floral prints. And weren't the orchid walls once a pale pink? Mostly, though, it is the menu and food that have developed into something very special.</p>
        <p>We began with excellent warmed Italian bread, a small dish of ricotta to spread on it and a bottle of extra-virgin olive oil with a garlic-rosemary accent for dipping. Then came a duet of appetizer specials that proved to be sure-fire. Polenta with shiitake mushrooms was a delicate delight -- a cake of soft, baked polenta surrounded by an abundance of sauteed mushroom slices. Eggplant rollatini, two slices of eggplant wrapped around a ricotta stuffing and baked, came on a plate with two large stuffed mushroom caps, packed with a delicious mixture of ground veal, chicken, mushrooms and tomatoes.</p>
        <p>Other starters that hit the spot were stuffed mushroom caps (five of them with the same filling as above); fried calamari (light and crisply deep fried, with a mildly seasoned red dip), and thinly sliced carpaccio, herb-accented and  crowned with the intense flavor of sliced parmigiano-reggiano cheese.</p>
        <p>Entrees we feasted on included a huge plateful of cloudlike gnocchi enveloped in a vigorously garlicked pesto; pollo plutone, a piping hot chicken breast stuffed with jumbo shrimp and asparagus, and sauteed in a wine-mushroom sauce; scaloppine alla valdostana, a large, meaty, stuffed veal chop, and gamberi Portofino, jumbo shrimp with mushrooms in a zesty wine-mustard sauce that held its own with, and enhanced, the shrimp.</p>
        <p>Desserts at an Italian restaurant are often an afterthought, but not so at Il Falco. A special pleasure was the Sicilian cassata, layers of sponge cake alternating with a rich, sweetened ricotta mixture. Tiramisu (lavish with Kahlua and cognac) was a worthy choice, as was the moist, light-textured chocolate cake with raspberry filling. Only the heavy ricotta cheesecake disappointed. Dinner for two came to $52, before drinks, tip and tax. The wine list has many Italian, French and American vintages beginning at $14.</p>
        <p>Il Falco perseveres, getting better as it goes along.</p>
        <p>A LA CARTE</p>
        <p>Last word on Il Forno, another attractive Italian restaurant in Stamford, which suffered a fire some months ago: there are no plans to rebuild or reopen. The Sforza brothers continue to run their other restaurant, Via Sforza Trattoria, on Westport Avenue, in Norwalk.</p>
        <p>A birthday celebration led us back recently to Bridge Cafe in Westport. The food was good (especially the luscious chicken livers and duck confit) and the cafe bustled with liveliness. and a warm atmosphere. But service was both disorganized and indifferent, confirming what others have reported in recent months. Disappointing at any meal, it was doubly so on a festive occasion. There didn't seem to be anyone in charge.</p>
        <p>Il Falco Ristorante</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>59 Broad Street, Stamford. 327-0002.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Simple, elegant dining areas (nonsmoking section in front, smoking area in back).</p>
        <p>Service: Expert service by a well-trained staff.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Polenta with shiitake mushrooms, eggplant rollatini, fried calamari, carpaccio, gnocchi al pesto, risotto with mushrooms, pollo plutone, gamberi Portofino, costoleta alla valdostana, tiramisu, cassata, chocolate raspberry cake.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch $9-$14, dinner $10.50-$21.50.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours: Noon-3 P.M. Monday-Friday, 5:30-10:30 P.M. Monday-Friday, 5:30-11 P.M. Saturday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Suggested.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Street-level access; restrooms at dining room level.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
