<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scanners</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FELS, ANNA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARK, WILLIAM R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AT WAR WITHIN (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4DD1039F935A15752C1A963958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scanners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anna Fels</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FELS, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT WAR WITHIN The Double-Edged Sword of Immunity. By William R. Clark. Illustrated. 276 pp. New York: Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>WHILE we noisily stumble through our daily lives trying (with greater or less success) to negotiate the world, our immune systems handle our microscopic  adventures with the same outside forces silently and efficiently. Unrecognized until the last century, the immune system is now acknowledged to be the single major determinant of health and disease. Its task is to ask one profound question: what is self and what is nonself? Its fantastically elegant, versatile and vigilant organization scans virtually every molecule we come in contact with. When the system is working, microbial barbarians at the door are handily dispatched. When it is not, the consequences for us are dire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT WAR WITHIN The Double-Edged Sword of Immunity. By William R. Clark. Illustrated. 276 pp. New York: Oxford University Press. $25.</p>
        <p>WHILE we noisily stumble through our daily lives trying (with greater or less success) to negotiate the world, our immune systems handle our microscopic  adventures with the same outside forces silently and efficiently. Unrecognized until the last century, the immune system is now acknowledged to be the single major determinant of health and disease. Its task is to ask one profound question: what is self and what is nonself? Its fantastically elegant, versatile and vigilant organization scans virtually every molecule we come in contact with. When the system is working, microbial barbarians at the door are handily dispatched. When it is not, the consequences for us are dire.</p>
        <p>In "At War Within: The Double-Edged Sword of Immunity," William R. Clark, who teaches immunology at the University of California, Los Angeles, gives us a summary of his rapidly developing field. Starting with a brief scientific history, he goes on to explain the rudiments of the immune system and the terrible consequences that can occur when the immune system is absent, as with AIDS, or when it is misguided, as with autoimmune diseases like lupus. He delves into the ethical questions that have arisen now that we can trick the immune system into accepting alien tissues in organ transplants. And there is a tantalizing section on the new discipline of psychoneuroimmunology -- the relation of the mind to the immune system. That all this is covered in 276 pages is a telling indication of both the book's strength and its weakness. As a panoramic overview, it's highly readable and interesting, but by necessity it lacks depth. It is equally illuminating and frustrating.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most significant omission is a vivid, close-up portrait of the immune system itself. This is a real loss, because one would have to look long and hard throughout the scientific and medical world to find a cast of cellular  characters as strange and brilliant as those of the immune system. As a case in  point, macrophages (the word derives from the Greek for "big eater"), versatile  and ubiquitous cells in the immune system, are described in these pages as gourmand housekeepers from hell: "They are basically the vacuum cleaners and filter feeders of the immune system. They ingest and digest (and often regurgitate) everything in sight that is not part of a normal healthy tissue." In reality, the macrophage is a highly mobile cell that can move nimbly through  virtually any tissue on its delicate, footlike pseudopods. It takes up residence in lymph nodes, combing through the microscopic flotsam and jetsam and sending out the alarm if any worrisome invader is detected. The macrophage has an enormous molecular vocabulary of signals to other cells -- nearly a hundred discreet messages directing immunological responses. It can even structurally transform itself, when dealing with especially resistant microbes, into a giant  megacell. Somehow, in Mr. Clark's down-to-earth prose, the sheer inventiveness and beauty of the system rarely come through.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clark's strong suit is explaining theoretical issues -- in particular the relation of the immune system to the brain. He makes a convincing parallel between these two systems, noting that they are the only parts of the organism with the capacity for identification and memory of encounters with the outside world. They both can learn, and they both have difficulty unlearning. (Any psychiatrist will vouch for this phenomenon of mental intransigence.) Each of them has a language for cell-to-cell communication. As Mr. Clark puts it, "It is almost as if the immune system were a chemical extension of the brain floating around in the bloodstream."</p>
        <p>Amazingly, recent research has begun to demonstrate that the two systems talk to each other. "It turns out," Mr. Clark says, "that the mind and the immune system are completely fluent both in their own language and in the language of the other." Science is closing in on the molecular basis for a fact that has been intuited from time immemorial: emotional conflict undermines physical health, and absence of stress promotes it. This nearly invisible cellular system, laced intricately throughout the organism, is a crucial link between body and mind.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Clark sees the mind and the immune system as a nearly unbeatable duo. "If the built-in defensive genes we have cannot save us," he writes, "we may find that what saves us is the application of our own intelligence and accumulated cultural wisdom. There is precious little a virus -- even one as deadly as H.I.V. -- can do about that." It is a surprisingly sunny view for the 1990's. But is it true? Mr. Clark is slighting one key fact:  nature, ever ingenious at insuring its own survival, is on the side of microbes  too.</p>
        <p>Anna Fels, an internist and psychiatrist, teaches at NewYork Hospital-Cornell Medical Center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anna Fels, an internist and psychiatrist, teaches at NewYork Hospital-Cornell Medical Center.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
