<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On My Mind; The P.L.O. Papers</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="772087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PALESTINE LIBERATION ORGANIZATION (PLO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARAFAT, YASIR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, A M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D7173DF933A05755C0A963958260" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On My Mind; The P.L.O. Papers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. M. ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, A M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Should the United States continue giving hundreds of millions of dollars to the Palestine Liberation Organization, and under what conditions?</p>
        <p>Has Yasir Arafat lived up to the existing conditions of American aid? For instance, is all international money distributed through the P.L.O. being used for the economic benefit of Palestinians in territory turned over by Israel? Or has he used foreign help for his own personal and political purposes?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Should the United States continue giving hundreds of millions of dollars to the Palestine Liberation Organization, and under what conditions?</p>
        <p>Has Yasir Arafat lived up to the existing conditions of American aid? For instance, is all international money distributed through the P.L.O. being used for the economic benefit of Palestinians in territory turned over by Israel? Or has he used foreign help for his own personal and political purposes?</p>
        <p>That is what is going on, according to copies of 28 letters in my possession. They deal with orders from Mr. Arafat's top finance aide in the Palestinian National Authority to Pecdar, the Palestinian economic development organization, which handles international aid and is supposed to be independent of political direction from Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>With admonishments of secrecy, the letters contain instructions, and Pecdar notices of compliance, to allocate money to such projects as buying a large chicken farm, other land, apartments and companies for P.L.O. notables, enlarging holdings in Jerusalem -- and $2.5 million for an expanded propaganda apparatus, the money to be channeled through Mr. Arafat's mother-in-law.</p>
        <p>Pieces of the correspondence have been printed in Israel, but have not surfaced publicly in the U.S, until this column.</p>
        <p>The P.L.O. says they are forgeries. The Israeli Government does not want anything to interfere with U.S. aid to the P.L.O., as these letters could, but has been interestingly noncommittal about the letters.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration also does not want any glitches about U.S. aid to the P.L.O. But American intelligence has been asked to examine the letters by Representative Ben Gilman, New York Republican, chairman of the House International Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>I got them from Israeli and American sources who feel the Labor Government's negotiating techniques with the P.L.O. and Syria amount to a giveaway of Israeli security that will not bring a lasting peace but make it impossible.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials finger Yigal Carmon, former adviser on terrorism to the previous and current Israeli Prime Ministers, as the source. He certainly was not mine. After I showed him the letters a month ago he returned with a reply he said he wished he did not have to make: certain informalities in Arabic usage gave him pause. Now he says that after consultations with other Palestinian and Israeli specialists, his linguistic questions are answered and the letters are authentic. Other anti-terrorist experts, who spent four months checking the letters, say they are not forgeries.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the U.S., Israel and the World Bank tell me that the political projects outlined in the letters do not come from their contributions. They volunteered that the money could have come from other contributing nations or that international funding could have freed up more P.L.O. funds for secret political actions.</p>
        <p>The letters are not the only question that the House and Senate will have to consider about continuing the $500 million U.S. aid to the P.L.O.</p>
        <p>Why has Mr. Arafat not lived up to the condition that the P.L.O. eliminate the death-to-Israel clauses from its covenant? Will he ever stop encouraging Palestinians to believe that the peace negotiations are the first phase toward the covenant goal of control over all of what is now Israel? Why have more Israelis died in terrorist attacks since the Oslo agreement than before?</p>
        <p>But the basic question before Congress is this:</p>
        <p>Will peace be killed by insisting on P.L.O. compliance with conditions already outlined by the U.S. but unfulfilled by the P.L.O.? That is what Israeli and U.S. officials say they believe. Or could that make a lasting peace somewhat more possible? (My belief.)</p>
        <p>In the Senate, Alfonse M. D'Amato, a Republican, demands proof of P.L.O. compliance on anti-terrorist action and changing the covenant as a price of aid. In the House, Democrats and Republicans have introduced wording that would also reduce aid if any is misspent. Among them are Democrats Eliot Engel and Charles Schumer of New York and Republicans Jim Saxton of New Jersey and Tom DeLay of Texas.</p>
        <p>That's one great thing about Congress -- there are always members of both parties around who insist on bringing up issues about which the Administration of the day wants only considerable shut-up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
