<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mother and Companion Charged in Beating of Boys</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD ABUSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKENNA, DAWN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALDERON, MIGUEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DD133BF933A25754C0A967958260" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mother and Companion Charged in Beating of Boys</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCKINLEY, JAMES C JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two small boys who had apparently been severely beaten lay in a Brooklyn hospital yesterday with head injuries, bruises and burns, while their 23-year-old mother and her boyfriend were arraigned on charges of child abuse, the police said.</p>
        <p>One child, a 1-year-old, was in critical condition in the intensive-care unit of Woodhull Hospital with a wound to the back of his skull, the police and hospital officials said. His 2-year-old brother was in serious condition. The police did not identify either child by name.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two small boys who had apparently been severely beaten lay in a Brooklyn hospital yesterday with head injuries, bruises and burns, while their 23-year-old mother and her boyfriend were arraigned on charges of child abuse, the police said.</p>
        <p>One child, a 1-year-old, was in critical condition in the intensive-care unit of Woodhull Hospital with a wound to the back of his skull, the police and hospital officials said. His 2-year-old brother was in serious condition. The police did not identify either child by name.</p>
        <p>The mother, Dawn McKenna, who is pregnant, and her boyfriend, Miguel Calderon, also 23, were arraigned in Brooklyn Criminal Court before Judge Stephen J. Rooney on charges of assault and endangering the welfare of a child. Both were sent to Rikers Island last night in lieu of $50,000 bail for Mr. Calderon and $25,000 for Miss McKenna.</p>
        <p>Miss McKenna took the two children from her apartment at 204 Ellery Street in the Bedford-Stuyvesant section to Woodhull Hospital's emergency room about 10:30 P.M. Sunday, the police said. The younger child, with patches of his hair missing, purple bruises and scrapes over his face and back, and burn marks on his ankles and buttocks, was comatose, detectives said. The other boy had two black eyes, bruises, a split lip and burns on his legs and buttocks, the police said.</p>
        <p>Suspecting child abuse, an emergency room doctor, Carl Barberis, called the 79th Precinct. Detectives immediately took Miss McKenna and Mr. Calderon into custody, questioning the couple throughout the night and well into the next day at the station house. The detectives said that the couple gave conflicting stories, but that both admitted hitting the children with a belt and with their hands. They were charged late Monday.</p>
        <p>"Both individuals were questioned and made culpatory statements regarding beating the children to keep them quiet," Capt. William F. Plackenmeyer of the Brooklyn Detective Bureau said.</p>
        <p>Criminal complaints filed in court yesterday said Mr. Calderon told detectives he "repeatedly hit" the older boy and had "squeezed the 1-year-old's head" hard enough to cause bruises around the eyes. Judging from the marks on the boys' bodies, the police said they believed the children had been beaten over several weeks.</p>
        <p>Investigators said Miss McKenna appeared agitated and incoherent during the questioning, frequently rambling onto disconnected subjects and leaping up out of her chair.</p>
        <p>A native of the Williamsburg section of Brooklyn, Miss McKenna moved to Easton, Pa., where she became involved with the children's father and where her first son was born. She separated from the father in December 1989 and moved back to New York City, living in a shelter for the homeless until November 1990, when she received a government-subsidized apartment at 204 Ellery Street.</p>
        <p>Miss McKenna told investigators she met Mr. Calderon, who lives nearby at 104 Marcy Avenue, on the street last fall and struck up an acquaintance with him. After serving a six-month sentence in city jails on a drug charge, Mr. Calderon began spending much of his time with Miss McKenna at her apartment in May, the police said. Neither was employed.</p>
        <p>Captain Plackenmeyer said Mr. Calderon had been arrested four times since 1987 on charges ranging from selling drugs to possession of burglary tools.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
