<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic's Enemies Find Serbian City Hall Is Hardly a Stronghold</title>
    <meta content="07SERB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="907247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yugoslavia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kragujevac (Serbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DF153CF934A35751C0A961958260" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic's Enemies Find Serbian City Hall Is Hardly a Stronghold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hedges, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>KRAGUJEVAC, Serbia, Feb. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New local administration in Kragujevac, Serbia, has little power; struggle to rule Kragujevac will soon be repeated in 14 of Serbia's largest cities if Parliament adopts Pres Slobodan Milosevic's recommendation to reinstate opposition victories in municipal elections; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Veroljub Stevanovic pushed back the gauzy white curtain in his office and peered through the window at a group of chanting and whistling students in the street below.</p>
        <p>''The schools are shut down and the teachers are on strike for better pay,'' he said. ''The students are out in support. But what can I do? The city is bankrupt, our factories are idle, over half of the people here are living below the poverty line, we have no cooperation with the police, our municipal vehicles are old and usually don't run and the sewage and electrical systems are overloaded.  All this, and Belgrade decides how to spend all but $20 million of our annual expenditures.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Veroljub Stevanovic pushed back the gauzy white curtain in his office and peered through the window at a group of chanting and whistling students in the street below.</p>
        <p>''The schools are shut down and the teachers are on strike for better pay,'' he said. ''The students are out in support. But what can I do? The city is bankrupt, our factories are idle, over half of the people here are living below the poverty line, we have no cooperation with the police, our municipal vehicles are old and usually don't run and the sewage and electrical systems are overloaded.  All this, and Belgrade decides how to spend all but $20 million of our annual expenditures.''</p>
        <p>The struggle to rule Kragujevac will soon be repeated in 14 of the country's largest cities if Serbia's Parliament, as promised, adopts President Slobodan Milosevic's recommendation to reinstate opposition victories in municipal elections.</p>
        <p>Many of the endemic problems facing the opposition are on view in this city of 200,000, where the opposition took control in December after Mr. Milosevic allowed the results of local elections to stand.</p>
        <p>While their victory has raised wildly unrealistic expectations, the new local officials must battle economic crisis and political corruption with little money to spend and limited municipal powers. They say that Mr. Milosevic and his proxies have already begun a campaign to sabotage the city government by mounting a propaganda campaign and restricting the money available to the new administration.</p>
        <p>When the Mayor took office, he said, he found evidence of widespread corruption. ''When the Socialists moved out of city hall at the end of December they handed over empty bank accounts,'' the Mayor said, referring to Mr. Milosevic's party.  ''The books were all cooked. It all looked legitimate, but the more we investigated, the more we uncovered massive theft. The local sports club, for example, got $800,000 last year, according to the accounts, but only $500,000 was ever delivered. Just about every expenditure is like this.''</p>
        <p>The national Government collects most taxes, giving a fraction, usually around 30 percent, to city administrations. The Government in Belgrade also controls most important municipal services, including the police and medical care. While the city government must finance the schools, it has no say over the administration and the teaching staff.</p>
        <p>Today in Kragujevac, Socialist officials loyal to Mr. Milosevic were busy organizing resistance to the new administration.</p>
        <p>Miroslav Klacar, the secretary of the party, spent the morning meeting with 19 reporters and editors who used to work for the weekly magazine Svetlost, a local pro-Milosevic propaganda organ that, in its last issue, accused political opponents of being funded by Albanian terrorist groups to destabilize Serbia.</p>
        <p>The magazine, which cost the strapped city assembly $150,000 a year to publish, was closed two weeks ago by the new administration. Already the Socialists have used the incident to raise accusations in the Government-run national news media that the opposition is mounting purges against city employees and silencing a free press.</p>
        <p>''The media has become a weapon in the hands of the opposition,'' said Mr. Klacar, ''and we intend to fight back. Directors, administrators, clerks, workers, drivers and cleaning ladies are all being removed from their jobs. It's a scandal.''</p>
        <p>When he was asked for the names of workers who lost work, he ducked the issue, saying he had heard ''they would be fired soon.''</p>
        <p>The attacks by the Socialists are disturbing to the new authorities, who see it as part of a concerted campaign by President Milosevic to undermine the city administration.  The new officials, wary of being accused of using the same tactics as the Socialists, say they have removed only a handful of directors from city posts and allowed everyone else to remain, including relatives of the former director of the local television who there.</p>
        <p>The euphoria that has swept Kragujevac was palpable among the staff at the local television station. The new administration had to go to court to win control of the station,  and it was handed over on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Vinka Knezevic and Srdjan Stosic, the two news readers on television, sat in a small studio broadcasting a daily report, including the latest statements by the opposition, which would have been censored at the beginning of the week.</p>
        <p>''I have covered the university for the last year,'' said Snezana Milisavljevic, a local television reporter, ''but even when the students were on strike all I got to report were the statements released by the officials and awards handed out to professors.  Today I am interviewing students about why they are not in the classroom, about what they want. It's great.''</p>
        <p>But, given the social crisis, euphoria may turn to disappointment if the city administration is unable to lift Kragujevac out of its social and economic morass.</p>
        <p>Kragujevac is home to the Zastava car factory, a huge plant that once turned out 200,000 boxy Yugo cars a year. Now production has fallen to under 10,000 and most of the workers have been laid off.</p>
        <p>''People do not have a realistic understanding of what is possible or the severity our problems,'' said Prvoslav Radosavljevic, the local head of the Independent United Branch Trade Unions. ''The city government has its hands tied. There is little it can accomplish. I worry that people will, when things do not improve, see this as a failure of the democratic opposition and begin to turn towards extremists.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
