<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airlines Begin to Look Up, Cautiously</title>
    <meta content="27air" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/business/27air.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDC113FF934A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airlines Begin to Look Up, Cautiously</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Airlines Begin to Look Up, Cautiously</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF BAILEY</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Jan. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The domestic airline industry enters 2006 with a relatively brief window of opportunity to fix its finances.</p>
        <p>By 2008, another bout of bruising competition could begin as significant numbers of new aircraft start arriving, potentially swelling the domestic fleet. That could end the current scarcity of domestic airline seats, which has allowed airlines to raise ticket prices and has kept planes flying about 80 percent full, a record high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The domestic airline industry enters 2006 with a relatively brief window of opportunity to fix its finances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The domestic airline industry enters 2006 with a relatively brief window of opportunity to fix its finances.</p>
        <p>By 2008, another bout of bruising competition could begin as significant numbers of new aircraft start arriving, potentially swelling the domestic fleet. That could end the current scarcity of domestic airline seats, which has allowed airlines to raise ticket prices and has kept planes flying about 80 percent full, a record high.</p>
        <p>''All the windows and aisles and over half the middle seats in a six-across configuration are full,'' said Roger E. King, an analyst at Credit-Sights, an independent research firm. ''The airline industry has the potential to recoup billions of losses.'' Since 2000, the domestic industry has lost an estimated $42 billion.</p>
        <p>Over the next two years -- barring an economic downturn, further significant escalation of fuel prices, serious labor unrest or some travel panic tied to terrorism or disease -- most of the industry is expected to return to profitability. And should fuel prices decline significantly, the industry could report its largest profits ever.</p>
        <p>Oil prices, however, have risen in recent weeks, to about $65 a barrel, giving airline executives pause. ''Fuel prices at 65 bucks aren't going to do it,'' said W. Douglas Parker, chief executive of the US Airways Group. ''In the mid-50's, the industry could actually be profitable.''</p>
        <p>The recent increase, Mr. Parker added, ''had a seriously dampening impact on expectations for 2006.''</p>
        <p>Executives are hoping for relief. ''There's no reason it should be at this price,'' said David G. Neeleman, chief executive of JetBlue Airways. Based on global supply and demand, Mr. Neeleman is convinced oil should be selling at about $40 a barrel. ''I think in the next year or two it's going to be back down there.'' Sooner would be much better for the industry, which is finally operating more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Higher ticket prices and fuller planes are a consequence of the strong economy and of a nearly 20 percent reduction in the fleet since June 30, 2001, among traditional hub-and-spoke carriers like American Airlines, a unit of the AMR Corporation, and United Airlines, a unit of the UAL Corporation. Six big carriers have reduced their combined fleets by more than 700 planes, said John Heimlich, chief economist at the Air Transport Association, an airline trade group.</p>
        <p>So, even though travelers packed into planes will have much to grumble about during 2006 and 2007, that period is the airline industry's best chance to get its house in order.</p>
        <p>In anticipation of profits to come, Wall Street has already bid up the stocks of major airlines. Shares of US Airways, Continental Airlines and American have all roughly doubled in price since Sept. 29, 2005.</p>
        <p>That day brought the initial trading of shares after the merger of US Airways with America West Airlines, a transaction that attracted badly needed capital to the industry and suggested that mergers among other major airlines -- essential to further reducing costs -- might be possible.</p>
        <p>In another sign of optimism, unsecured debt in the UAL Corporation that converts into stock upon United's expected exit from bankruptcy around Feb. 1, has been trading at three times the company's initial high-end estimate of the debt's value. That indicates that United shares, too, could trade higher upon issuance.</p>
        <p>Some analysts are expecting ticket prices to rise through the first half of 2006. The number of seats available on scheduled domestic flights through this July is 4 percent below the figure a year earlier, said Mr. Heimlich, the trade group economist, giving airlines more reason to raise prices.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen how adroitly airlines will take advantage of this potential period of profits. Of course, they have already done much to streamline operations since 2000. Hub-and-spoke carriers have cut payrolls by 37 percent, or 160,000 people, Mr. Heimlich said. By changing work rules, the carriers have increased labor productivity by 30 percent. And by idling their least- efficient planes, airlines have lifted fuel efficiency by 18 percent.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Heimlich estimated, when all the 2005 results are in, cumulative airline losses since 2000 will total about $42 billion. And industry debt, including leases not carried on airline balance sheets, is a staggering $100 billion. ''The airlines remain slivers of equity on top of pillars of debt,'' said Mr. King, the analyst with CreditSights.</p>
        <p>Though ticket prices, by Mr. Heimlich's estimate, are only back up to 1988 levels, it seems certain that both business and leisure travelers will balk at some point if fares keep rising. Airlines need to find the price just beneath that level. ''All bets on an industry recovery are off if the discretionary consumer will not accept higher fares,'' Mr. King said.</p>
        <p>Maintaining higher fares could prove difficult as rising deliveries of new planes swell airline fleets later this decade. Deliveries from Boeing and Airbus fell by about one-third from 1999 to 2003, Mr. King estimated, as airlines deferred planes they had earlier ordered and manufacturers cut back production. Now, deliveries are rising again. And even with international routes absorbing most of the new planes, a surge of orders in 2005 could cause domestic capacity to rise more swiftly than demand for seats as early as 2008, undermining pricing.</p>
        <p>A huge potential source of savings for the industry would be a merger or two among major carriers. That would reduce corporate overhead and potentially allow for fewer domestic hubs, which are expensive to maintain. It is redundant, Mr. King said, to have major hubs in both Atlanta and Charlotte, N.C.; Philadelphia and Newark; Denver and Salt Lake City; Dallas and Houston.</p>
        <p>The value of hubs -- where travelers from smaller airports make connections -- is being steadily undermined by low-cost airlines like Southwest Airlines and JetBlue, which fly point-to-point, often bypassing hubs.</p>
        <p>''The odds are very high, probably 100 percent'' of at least one major merger proposal this year, Mr. King said. Mr. Heimlich agreed.</p>
        <p>Mr. King expects Asian routes held by United and Northwest Airlines, attractive because of that region's rapid growth, to drive merger activity. Northwest and Delta Air Lines each sought bankruptcy protection late last year and, in those proceedings, could adjust their costs and assets to make themselves more attractive to a partner, as US Airways did for America West.</p>
        <p>''I think probably the most likely way those two companies emerge from bankruptcy is through consolidation,'' said Mr. Parker, the US Airways chief executive. ''Our merger has shown you can create a lot of value.'' He does not expect either Delta or Northwest to exit bankruptcy in 2006, however.</p>
        <p>But officials at both Delta and Northwest said the carriers planned on completing their restructuring and emerging from bankruptcies as stand-alone airlines.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
