<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Key Figure in Murder Appeal Is Missing, Acquaintances Say</title>
    <meta content="27tankleff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/nyregion/27tankleff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DB113FF934A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Key Figure in Murder Appeal Is Missing, Acquaintances Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Key Figure in Murder Appeal Is Missing, Acquaintances Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Glenn Harris, who said he was the getaway driver in a 1988 double murder in Suffolk County, has been missing for two months, relatives and friends say. They expressed concern for his safety, saying he had been threatened to keep silent.</p>
        <p>''Right now he's a missing person,'' said Jay Salpeter, a private investigator and former New York City homicide detective who uncovered what Mr. Harris says was his link to the killings of Seymour Tankleff and his wife, Arlene, in Belle Terre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The missing man, Glenn Harris, has been linked to the 1988 murder in Long Island of the parents of Martin Tankleff, who was imprisoned for the crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Glenn Harris, who said he was the getaway driver in a 1988 double murder in Suffolk County, has been missing for two months, relatives and friends say. They expressed concern for his safety, saying he had been threatened to keep silent.</p>
        <p>''Right now he's a missing person,'' said Jay Salpeter, a private investigator and former New York City homicide detective who uncovered what Mr. Harris says was his link to the killings of Seymour Tankleff and his wife, Arlene, in Belle Terre.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salpeter has been reinvestigating the murders for the couple's son, Martin, who was imprisoned for the crimes but insists he is innocent and is appealing his convictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris has acknowledged being in and out of jail and drug addiction treatment most of his life, but acquaintances say he normally keeps in touch.</p>
        <p>''I don't know where he is,'' said his mother-in-law, Susan Lampert, who takes care of his two children. ''He doesn't pick up the cellphone. It was very shocking he didn't call at Christmas.'' She added, ''There was absolutely nothing.''</p>
        <p>Since Thanksgiving, Mr. Salpeter said, he has not been able to reach Mr. Harris at his apartment in the Selden area. Before this, the longest gap in contact was a week or two.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lampert called the police on Wednesday, she said, and officers came to talk to her. The Suffolk County police said last night that they were unaware of a missing-person report or an investigation, but that the district attorney's investigators might be involved. The assistant district attorney for the Tankleff case, who is opposing Martin Tankleff's appeal, did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
        <p>In a breakthrough, Mr. Harris said he had been recruited by Joseph Creedon and drove him and an accomplice, Peter Kent, to the Tankleff home. In court hearings, Mr. Creedon and Mr. Kent denied being involved. But another witness said the three men first visited him that night and invited him to join them, and five witnesses said Mr. Creedon had told them privately that he was involved; one witness was his own son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tankleff's lawyer, Bruce A. Barket, said Mr. Harris had received threats of harm if he persisted in talking. When prosecutors refused to grant Mr. Harris immunity to testify, he invoked his Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination. But the Tankleff lawyers introduced an admission Mr. Harris signed, dozens of letters from him and testimony from Mr. Salpeter and a priest about Mr. Harris's admissions to them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
