<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even as Homes Soar in Value, Some Will See Tax Bill Slashed</title>
    <meta content="27tax" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/27/nyregion/27tax.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1735103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDC113FF934A15752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even as Homes Soar in Value, Some Will See Tax Bill Slashed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even as Homes Soar in Value, Some Will See Tax Bill Slashed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the mailing of property tax notices each January, most New York City homeowners have been reminded of the downside of a booming real estate market: higher assessments and taxes.</p>
        <p>But for thousands of owners of apartments in small co-op and condominium buildings, this year's notices contain a surprise: Their taxes are going down -- a lot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The change, made quietly by the Bloomberg administration, came from attempts to reconcile two provisions of state property tax law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the mailing of property tax notices each January, most New York City homeowners have been reminded of the downside of a booming real estate market: higher assessments and taxes.</p>
        <p>But for thousands of owners of apartments in small co-op and condominium buildings, this year's notices contain a surprise: Their taxes are going down -- a lot.</p>
        <p>For these property owners, the Bloomberg administration has changed the rules without warning and lowered taxes by an average of $1,800 per apartment, or about half of what they had been paying.</p>
        <p>''Having dealt with the city bureaucracy in an intimate way, this is something of a shock,'' said Larry Fuchsman, an artist who lives in a full-floor co-op loft on East 22nd Street, and who has followed the rising property taxes in his building over many years.</p>
        <p>Last year Mr. Fuchsman's building, with just seven apartments, was billed for $102,000 in property taxes. The latest notice showed that -- though the market value on his apartment has continued to go up -- taxes on the building are dropping to less than $60,000 when tax bills go out in June. That's an average cut of $6,000 per apartment.</p>
        <p>The new rules were intended to ensure that the tax on more than 16,000 smaller co-op and condo apartment buildings, those with from 4 to 10 apartments, were no higher than those for similar rental buildings.</p>
        <p>Most of these homes are in more expensive neighborhoods, mainly in Manhattan south of 110th Street, especially on the West Side, in Greenwich Village and SoHo, and in Brooklyn Heights and Park Slope.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, the average tax cut for the affected buildings is $2,800, and in Brooklyn, it is $800.</p>
        <p>Sam Miller, an assistant commissioner at the city's Department of Finance, said the new rules were part of a campaign by Martha E. Stark, the finance commissioner, to make the property tax system fairer and more transparent. Mr. Miller said the change was not made in response to specific complaints from taxpayer groups.</p>
        <p>The change emerged from an effort to reconcile two provisions of state property tax law. One requires that all apartment buildings, both large and small, be assessed the same way, and another allows smaller apartment buildings, both rental and cooperative, to phase in assessment increases over many years.</p>
        <p>For many years, the city set the maximum assessments at 45 percent of market value for all apartment buildings with four or more apartments. But in practice, Mr. Miller said, small rental buildings were assessed at about 15 percent of market value. Small co-ops were assessed at an average of 30 percent of market value, while condominiums were assessed at 40 percent.</p>
        <p>To make the system fairer, he said, the commissioner set the maximum ratio for both small rental, co-op and condo buildings at 15 percent of market value, and reduced all higher assessments to that figure for the fiscal year that begins on July 1.</p>
        <p>City officials put the cost of the program at $90 million, a fraction of the $13 billion in property taxes the city is scheduled to collect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said he called the representatives of co-op and condo owners' groups to explain the changes after they were mentioned in a brief report in The New York Post.</p>
        <p>''I think the Department of Finance honestly decided to be open and fair thinking,'' said Mary Ann Rothman, executive director of the Council of New York Cooperatives and Condominiums.</p>
        <p>Among the buildings affected are many downtown co-op loft buildings that have been selling for prices far higher than what the city previously listed as their market values -- and still far more than what was listed in the latest tax notices compiled by the Department of Finance.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Fuchsman's building, a full-floor home sold for more than $1.7 million nearly two years ago, and since then prices have risen. But in the latest tax notices, the city's value of the building was at an average of about $500,000 per floor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fuchsman said that co-ops like his should ''pay their fair share,'' but that they had been paying more than they should have. ''This levels the playing field,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The change will also reduce taxes for some owners of small rental buildings, but details are not yet clear. City officials said the notices sent out in January had inaccurate market values because of an error in the computer program.</p>
        <p>As a result, the market values for all small apartment buildings were understated by a total of $7.2 billion, or more than 20 percent of market value. So owners of smaller rental buildings, who received notices suggesting that their taxes were going down, too, may want to hold their cheers: The Department of Finance will soon be sending out corrected notices, Mr. Miller said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
