<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>San Andres Journal; On English-Speaking Isle, Tidal Wave of Spanish</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456750"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (NON-US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLOMBIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN ANDRES (COLOMBIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF173AF932A35754C0A967958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>San Andres Journal; On English-Speaking Isle, Tidal Wave of Spanish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANDRES, Colombia</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Coursing over this island's coral cays and through its coconut groves runs an invisible cultural fault line that separates Caribbean reggae from Latin American salsa.</p>
        <p>On one side are the natives -- English-speaking, Protestant and black.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Coursing over this island's coral cays and through its coconut groves runs an invisible cultural fault line that separates Caribbean reggae from Latin American salsa.</p>
        <p>On one side are the natives -- English-speaking, Protestant and black.</p>
        <p>On the other side are "the mainlanders" -- Spanish-speaking, Roman Catholic and Latin.</p>
        <p>In a reversal of roles for a cultural clash common to the Americas, it is the English speakers on San Andres who charge that the Spanish speakers are trying to wipe out their culture and their language.</p>
        <p>"The Spaniards get very cross -- they say they don't want to hear any English around here," said Fernando Broughton, a young taxi driver, telling of friends who were arrested this year for speaking in English to policemen who understood only the Spanish of mainland Colombia.</p>
        <p>English has been the language of inhabitants of this island and nearby Providence since English Puritans arrived in the early 1600's to establish cotton and coconut plantations. After a brief era as a lair for pirates like Henry Morgan, the archipelago in 1822 became part of Colombia, a newly independent nation 500 miles to the southeast.  Declared a Free Port</p>
        <p>But for decades the island was stamped by the Afro-English culture that still survives in pockets on Central America's Caribbean coast -- the nation of Belize and the port towns of Bluefields, Nicaragua; Limon, Costa Rica; and Bocas de Toro, Panama.</p>
        <p>Nervous that an island separatist movement might deprive Colombia of extensive fishing and mineral rights in the western Caribbean, a military dictator declared San Andres a free port in 1953, built a huge airfield here and started a heavy-handed colonization campaign.</p>
        <p>English-language Bibles were collected and burned. Baptist and Adventist schools were temporarily closed and then allowed to reopen only on the condition that teaching be in Spanish. Government jobs and scholarships were restricted to converts to Catholicism. Immigrants were lured here from the mainland with incentives like free passage and subsidized housing and electricity.</p>
        <p>"When Colombia decided to Colombianize us, they cut all our connections with our English-speaking neighbors," charged Bill Francis, a charter member of a native rights group that has emerged here, S.O.S., or Sons of the Soil.  A Dispiriting Island Tour</p>
        <p>Today, Colombians admit they are embarrassed by the effect of the colonization campaign. In 1954, the island had only 7,000 people, largely fishermen and farmers. Today, this 10-square-mile island is crowded with 70,000 people, giving it one of the highest island population densities in the world.</p>
        <p>On a recent afternoon, members of the now English-speaking minority served as guides for what became a dispiriting island tour.</p>
        <p>"This used to be one of our cemeteries," said Enrique Pusey, a Sons of the Soil leader, pointing to a lot now occupied by a tourist hotel and McPollo, a fried chicken joint.</p>
        <p>The coastal road passed other marks of Colombia's domination: a coconut processing cooperative that had been expropriated for a naval base; a mangrove swamp that was bulldozed to build vacation retreats for members of the Cali cocaine cartel, and the rocky skeleton of a two-mile beach in the native section of the island that had been dug up and trucked away for building materials.</p>
        <p>From the steeple of the First Baptist Church, a white clapboard structure built in the 19th century from imported Alabama pine, a visitor could see shantytowns filled with poor immigrants lured from Colombia's coastal cities.</p>
        <p>Although police harassment has subsided, the Sons of the Soil group still spreads its files among members' houses.</p>
        <p>At a recent closed-door meeting, a surprising amount of resentment toward "the Spaniards" flowed out on a river of Caribbean-accented English.</p>
        <p>One complained that English-language books, Bibles and magazines are routinely held up in customs, even though San Andres is a free port. American pastors never seem to get visas to preach for more than a few days. "The Spaniards" are changing place names -- Orange Hill is now Loma Naranja, Bean Hill is now Loma Frijol and Jones Point is Punta San Juan.</p>
        <p>"The Colombian Government wants to destroy our language, our culture and our race," Mr. Pusey said.</p>
        <p>But in Bogota, Colombia's confidence in cultural colonialism seems to be faltering. In the constitutional assembly, a proposal to respect the islanders' linguistic and cultural rights has won support from delegates who represent constituencies that are being heard for the first time in Colombia -- Indians, Protestants and former guerrillas.</p>
        <p>In mid-June, President Gaviria signed a measure declaring 15 mainland towns to be free ports with relaxed import duties -- a first step to move free-port tourism off this crowded island.</p>
        <p>During a break between lobbying the constitutional convention, Kent Francis James, the island's Governor, listed his demands: complete bilingual education, English-language television, restriction on land sales to mainlanders and free passage for immigrants back to "continental Colombia."</p>
        <p>Using a coinage increasingly popular among islanders, the Governor said, "We don't want to end up as the Palestinians of the Caribbean -- a people without a home."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
