<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FINAL CUT IS MADE ON MILITARY BASES THAT SHOULD CLOSE</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19910702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="456818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY BASES AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAVIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPBUILDING, CONVERSION AND REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA (PA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG BEACH (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FORT ORD (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FORT DIX (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA NAVAL SHIPYARD (PA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE BASE CLOSURE AND REALIGNMENT COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">IFILL, GWEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHENEY, DICK (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Long Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DE1531F932A35754C0A967958260" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FINAL CUT IS MADE ON MILITARY BASES THAT SHOULD CLOSE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GWEN IFILL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IFILL, GWEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal commission charged with closing military bases, working until the last hours before its deadline, voted today to recommend closing the huge naval shipyard at Philadelphia and the naval station in Long Beach, Calif., the Army base at Fort Ord in California and a number of smaller installations around the country.</p>
        <p>But the seven-member panel rejected several recommendations by Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who had proposed closing dozens of bases to accommodate a 25 percent reduction in personnel expected by 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal commission charged with closing military bases, working until the last hours before its deadline, voted today to recommend closing the huge naval shipyard at Philadelphia and the naval station in Long Beach, Calif., the Army base at Fort Ord in California and a number of smaller installations around the country.</p>
        <p>But the seven-member panel rejected several recommendations by Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who had proposed closing dozens of bases to accommodate a 25 percent reduction in personnel expected by 1997.</p>
        <p>Among the bases reprieved in the public voting today, as a crowd of lawmakers and local politicians looked on, were the 2-year-old Staten Island naval home port and Fort Dix in central New Jersey. Fort Dix would be kept at reduced levels for training reserves and active units.  [ Page A10. ] Bush's Approval Is Uncertain</p>
        <p>By midnight, the Defense Base Closure and Realignment Commission, working from a list of 45 candidates for shutdown, had voted to recommend closing 24 of them, keeping 15 open, and consolidating the remainder. Seven of the closings were announced on Friday.</p>
        <p>The recommendations go to President Bush and then, if he approves them, to Congress. If adopted, the shutdowns and consolidations would constitute the most extensive reduction of military installations in 20 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's approval is by no means certain. In the past, he has said he supports the Pentagon's recommendations. And fierce opposition to base closings can be expected from members of Congress whose districts are affected. By law, Congress must accept or reject the entire list; if it rejects the list, no bases will be closed.</p>
        <p>Other major bases that would be closed under today's recommendations are Fort Devens in Ayer, Mass., and Fort Benjamin Harrison in Indiana. Others the panel voted to keep, despite Mr. Cheney's suggestions, were Fort McClellan in Anniston, Ala., the Naval Training Center in Orlando, Fla., and Whidbey Island Naval Air Station in Oak Harbor, Wash. McClellan is home to the Army's only chemical training facility.</p>
        <p>Commission members described Fort Dix as a "valuable piece of real estate" that supplies a unique support mission. Similarly, the Staten Island site, a port for the Navy, was preserved after commissioners discounted arguments from those who wanted it closed, including Mayor David N. Dinkins and a number of New York State lawmakers.</p>
        <p>Duane H. Cassidy, a retired Air Force general who is a member of the panel, said he was especially swayed by evidence that financial insitutions had already made a commitment to pay for new housing at the site. Supporters of the base, he said, "are vocal by their action, while the others are only vocal by their words, which I don't put much credit in, frankly."</p>
        <p>Representative Susan Molinari, Republican of Staten Island, called the panel's decision a "magnificent victory."</p>
        <p>But reacting to the vote to close the Philadelphia Naval Shipyard, members of Congress from Pennsylvania and southern New Jersey were just as disappointed as Ms. Molinari was elated. Representative Robert E. Andrews, Democrat of New Jersey, called the recommendation an "injustice" and threatened legal and Congressional action to have it reversd.</p>
        <p>The two Congressional delegations had mounted one of the most vigorous defenses before the commission and had inserted language in the appropriations bill just signed by President Bush that would have guaranteed more work for the shipyard.  'I'm Really Hurt'</p>
        <p>The commission estimated that closing both the Philadelphia shipyard and the naval station would save the military $76 million a year once it is fully shut. It is by far the largest installation that would be closed as a result of the commission's actions today. But its closing would also eliminate thousands of military and civilian jobs.</p>
        <p>"We needed a minor miracle at the beginning of this process," said Representative Robert A. Borski, Democrat of Pennsylvania. "We need a major miracle now."</p>
        <p>Other members of Congress had similar reactions. Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts, said the decision to close Fort Devens "casts a shadow over the validity of the entire base closure process." And Senator John Seymour, Republican of California, said closing Fort Ord would be a "disaster."</p>
        <p>Charles McKinney, a Selectman from Ayer, Mass., who is retired from the Army, wore a "Save Fort Devens" button to today's hearing. "I'm really hurt by what happened," he said.</p>
        <p>As the seven panelists deliberated today, several commented on the difficulty inherent in deciding to close bases that do efficient work but constitute excess capacity.</p>
        <p>Closing the Philadelphia installations, said Jim Courter, the commission chairman, was "an excrutiatingly close call."</p>
        <p>Howard H. Callaway, a commissioner who is a former Secretary of the Army, defended Fort Ord as the "premier training facility for light infantry in the world" and predicted that the Army would be sorry it closed the base to save $70 million. He was the only commissioner who voted to keep Fort Ord open.</p>
        <p>The commission's actions were often preceded by detailed discussion in which members confessed to some vulnerability to the pressure they had received from members of Congress in the 11 weeks since Secretary Cheney announced his list of recommendations.</p>
        <p>One particularly tough vote involved the Army Corps of Engineers. The commission voted to restructure the corps, overruling complaints from members of Congress who had said it was within their jurisdiction to reduce the headquarters and division staff that control projects by the corps. In a concession to Congress, the commission also voted to give lawmakers a year to come up with their own cost reduction alternative before the commission's recommendation takes effect. The changes approved by the commission would trim 2,500 jobs and save $112 million each year.</p>
        <p>The commission also approved the consolidation of a number of military activities that will result in significant mission reductions at Fort Polk in Louisiana and the partial closure of MacDill Air Force Base in Tampa, Fla.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callaway said the process had been difficult for all those involved. "It's been tough for us to go on and make tough decisions," he said. "Let me tell you, it's been even tougher for members of Congress. We don't have to stand for re-election. They do."</p>
        <p>These are the members of the Defense Base Closure and Realignment Commission:</p>
        <p>COURTER, Jim, chairman, former Republican member of the House of Representatives from New Jersey and candidate for governor in 1989. Now in private law practice.</p>
        <p>BALL, William L. 2d, former Secretary of the Navy, now president of the National Soft Drink Association.</p>
        <p>CALLAWAY, Howard H., chairman of Gopac, a conservative political action committee, former Secretary of the Army and chairman of the Colorado Republican Party.</p>
        <p>CASSIDY, Gen. Duane H., former commander in chief of the United States Transportation Command and Military Airlift Command, now vice president of Logistics Technology for the CSX Corporation.</p>
        <p>LEVITT, Arthur C. Jr., former chairman and chief executive of the American Stock Exchange, now chairman of the Levitt Media Company.</p>
        <p>SMITH, James C. 2d, former top aide to John G. Tower when he was chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, now vice president of Brown &amp; Root U.S.A. Inc., an engineering and construction concern in Houston.</p>
        <p>STUART, Robert D. Jr., former Ambassador to Norway and retired chairman of the Quaker Oats Company.</p>
        <p>TROWBRIDGE, Alexander B., Secretary of Commerce in the Johnson Administration and former president of the National Association of Manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 2, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front- page article yesterday about a proposal to close military bases incorrectly listed Alexander B. Trowbridge as a member of the commission that voted on the plan. Mr. Trowbridge resigned from the commission on May 17.</p>
        <p>Because of another editing error, an article on Saturday about actions by the commission mislocated Fort Totten, a base the panel voted not to recommend for shutdown. It is in Queens, not Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front- page article yesterday about a proposal to close military bases incorrectly listed Alexander B. Trowbridge as a member of the commission that voted on the plan. Mr. Trowbridge resigned from the commission on May 17.</p>
        <p>Because of another editing error, an article on Saturday about actions by the commission mislocated Fort Totten, a base the panel voted not to recommend for shutdown. It is in Queens, not Staten Island.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
