<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In City of Millions, an Endless Supply of Memories</title>
    <meta content="08shel" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/08/nyregion/thecity/08shel.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1730427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK BOOKSHELF/NONFICTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Lesesne, Cap</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brokaw, Tom</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pogrebin, Abigail</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rivers, Joan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D91E30F93BA35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In City of Millions, an Endless Supply of Memories</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In This City of Millions, the Memories Are Endless</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONFESSIONS OF A PARK AVENUE PLASTIC SURGEON  By Cap Lesesne, M.D.  Gotham Books  ($26, hardcover)</p>
        <p>After three thrilling, exhausting, mind-bending years at Stanford, I came east for another residency, this one specializing in plastic surgery, at the Cornell and New York Hospital, another world-renowned institution. In North Carolina I'd learned to be a doctor, in California a surgeon. In New York, I would learn to be a plastic surgeon.</p>
        <p>At New York Hospital, I learned an enormous amount -- about different types of face-lifts, about rhinoplasties, about dealing with burns. At Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, one of my last rotations, I did reconstructive surgery on cancer patients. As a surgeon doing that kind of work your mind-set is very different from what it is when you do cosmetic work. You're not worried at all about scars. Instead, you're doing things like repairing large defects and covering chest holes. You're happy if the patient is just able to leave the hospital alive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONFESSIONS OF A.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONFESSIONS OF A PARK AVENUE PLASTIC SURGEON  By Cap Lesesne, M.D.  Gotham Books  ($26, hardcover)</p>
        <p>After three thrilling, exhausting, mind-bending years at Stanford, I came east for another residency, this one specializing in plastic surgery, at the Cornell and New York Hospital, another world-renowned institution. In North Carolina I'd learned to be a doctor, in California a surgeon. In New York, I would learn to be a plastic surgeon.</p>
        <p>At New York Hospital, I learned an enormous amount -- about different types of face-lifts, about rhinoplasties, about dealing with burns. At Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, one of my last rotations, I did reconstructive surgery on cancer patients. As a surgeon doing that kind of work your mind-set is very different from what it is when you do cosmetic work. You're not worried at all about scars. Instead, you're doing things like repairing large defects and covering chest holes. You're happy if the patient is just able to leave the hospital alive.</p>
        <p>I also learned who some of the good guys in New York medicine were, and who were the bad guys.</p>
        <p>THE ELLIS ISLAND SNOW GLOBE  By Erica Rand  Duke University Press  ($22.95, paperback)</p>
        <p>While Ellis Island accounts are generally discreet about physical presence, save for the occasional invitation to imagine the smell of thousands of immigrants newly arrived from steerage, several tidbits about immigrants encountering unfamiliar people at Ellis Island call up the fullness of close looking and proximity.</p>
        <p>One often retold story, also included in the Ellis Island Immigration Museum audio tour narrated by Tom Brokaw, relates that many European immigrants saw a black person for the first time at Ellis Island. Narratives of such encounters from the other side are harder to find -- perhaps because European immigrants formed the vast majority, but just as much, I suspect, because racial difference is more readily popularized as the spectacle of dark people rather than the distasteful odor of white people.</p>
        <p>One example, however, appears in the oral testimony of Ayleen Watts James, which visitors may hear on an audio loop if they pick up a phone in a display called ''The Last Hurdle.'' James, who arrived from Panama with her mother in 1923, recounts that after having spent a year making them new clothes for the journey, with ''handmade lace and all,'' her mother was horrified to find herself surrounded by Europeans filthy from their long voyage, and tried, sobbing, to pull herself and her daughter away from them.</p>
        <p>FUZZ ONE: A Bronx Childhood  By Vincent Fedorchak  Testify Books  ($32, hardcover)</p>
        <p>You should have seen those trains go by! Historic graffiti legends. The writers back then lit up the trains in colorful flames. Ebony Dukes, T.E.D. Incorporated, Graffiti Go-Club, W.A.R. -- Writers Are Respected. Amazing burners soaring through the train stations. Single-hits, top-to-bottoms, window-downs, wholecars, floaters, throw-ups and blockbusters covered the trains that floated by.</p>
        <p>They had flames bursting, crowns on top of letters, stars, stitches, dots and bubbles. Masterpieces flying by. There was the champagne glass with bubbles, and the Playboy bunny with the rabbit ears, one ear up and one down.</p>
        <p>STARS OF DAVID: Prominent Jews Talk About Being Jewish  By Abigail Pogrebin  Broadway Books  ($24.95, hardcover)</p>
        <p>Joan Rivers:</p>
        <p>Did she ever feel she looked too Jewish? ''Oh, I know I do!'' She laughs heartily. ''I look at pictures of myself and I look like what I am: a middle-aged or old Jewish matron. There it is. You are what you are. But I'm also so proud when it's a Jew that wins the Pulitzer Prize or the Nobel Prize. And conversely, I'm always so glad when the serial killer isn't Jewish.''</p>
        <p>She concedes there are times she wishes she had a different religion: ''Every time I see a good-looking German guy in leather.'' She laughs again. ''Show me a blond blue-eyed guy in leather and I'll say, 'Oh, what a pity I'm Jewish!' ''</p>
        <p>But her parents instilled an unshakable self-respect and urged her to marry within the faith. ''It was important to me, too,'' she adds. ''First of all we're the chosen people, and I like that we're continuing; I don't want it to stop. If these people have struggled thousands and thousands of years, it should not stop with me.</p>
        <p>''Who am I to say, 'You buried your candles during the Inquisition and now I've decided not to continue'?''</p>
        <p>CRASH OUT: THE TRUE TALE OF A HELL'S KITCHEN KID AND THE BLOODIEST ESCAPE IN SING SING HISTORY  By David Goewey  Crown Publishers  ($24.95, hardcover)</p>
        <p>In New York City, a gambling racket that brought in $35,000 a day paid for Dutch Schultz's $300 suits -- complete with powder-blue vest and spats. ''Lucky'' Luciano, by then the head of the Unione Siciliane -- America's early Mafia -- and running his bootlegging and prostitution empires from a well-protected, high-rise suite at the East Side Barbizon Plaza, bragged about paying $10,000 to $20,000 a week to New York police headquarters.</p>
        <p>By comparison, federal agents assigned to enforce the 18th Amendment did so on little more than $2,000 a year. Given the raucous disregard in which the law was held, and the obscene sums changing hands, the temptation of graft was overwhelming for many policemen, especially as the economic good times of the 1920's soured.</p>
        <p>By the early 30's, the hard times seemed never-ending. Four area hospitals reported 95 deaths by starvation in 1931, as the Great Depression deepened and bread lines shuffled along the sidewalks. In 1932, New York's worst year of the catastrophe, nearly 1,600 people killed themselves -- the most suicides in more than three decades.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOOKSHELF/NONFICTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
