<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Bargains, Try Spinning the Globe</title>
    <meta content="08global" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/08/business/mutfund/08global.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1730456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand Six (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand Five (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morningstar Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Aenlle, Conrad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6D81E30F93BA35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1316" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Bargains, Try Spinning the Globe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Bargains, Try Spinning the Globe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Aenlle, Conrad</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on gains by international equity mutual funds in 2005, which Morningstar reports rose by 17.8 percent compared with 6.8 percent gain for general domestic equity funds; fund managers predict continued rise in 2006 but caution that foreign outperformance is unlikely to be as great and differ about where best opportunities will be found; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States stock market finished 2005 close to where it began the year, making it the most conspicuous absentee in a powerful worldwide rally. Double-digit percentage gains were routine in major and minor markets when returns were expressed in dollars, and in several countries, including Japan, Brazil and South Korea, they exceeded 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Investors in international equity mutual funds enjoyed an average gain of 17.8 percent in 2005, according to Morningstar, far superior to the 6.8 percent gain of general domestic equity funds. That will be a tough act to follow, although managers of international funds, which invest solely outside the United States, and global funds, which seek opportunities in domestic and foreign markets alike, predicted that investors would continue to find richer pickings abroad this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a strong year, fund managers disagree on which foreign markets will continue to do well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States stock market finished 2005 close to where it began the year, making it the most conspicuous absentee in a powerful worldwide rally. Double-digit percentage gains were routine in major and minor markets when returns were expressed in dollars, and in several countries, including Japan, Brazil and South Korea, they exceeded 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Investors in international equity mutual funds enjoyed an average gain of 17.8 percent in 2005, according to Morningstar, far superior to the 6.8 percent gain of general domestic equity funds. That will be a tough act to follow, although managers of international funds, which invest solely outside the United States, and global funds, which seek opportunities in domestic and foreign markets alike, predicted that investors would continue to find richer pickings abroad this year.</p>
        <p>But after such a strong year, fund managers advise that, foreign outperformance is unlikely to be as great, and they have differing ideas about where the best opportunities will be found.</p>
        <p>''I think it gets much more stock-specific and much more valuation-based,'' Gilman Gunn, manager of the Evergreen International Equity fund, said of the choices that he and his peers would have to make this year. He stressed, though, that ''yields and multiples are more attractive abroad.''</p>
        <p>Global fund managers polled last month by Merrill Lynch appeared to agree. They rated the United States as far more overvalued than Europe, Japan or emerging markets. They said they expected to keep a smaller proportion of their portfolios in domestic stocks during the next year than would be warranted by the size of the market, and they were inclined to be overweight in Japanese or emerging-markets stocks.</p>
        <p>Still, the number of respondents to Merrill's survey who say they expect to be underweight in United States stocks has fallen sharply in the last two months. The foreign stock rally of the last year has reduced the valuation premium that American stocks had over those in many other markets, making foreign stocks somewhat less appealing.</p>
        <p>John Chisholm, co-chief investment officer of Acadian Asset Management, holds that view. ''We're a little bit underweight in the U.S., but we had a more significant underweighting in the past,'' said Mr. Chisholm, who manages a portion of the Vanguard Global Equity fund. The increased allocation to American stocks is ''partly due to valuation,'' he said, ''and partly due to U.S. companies showing more growth than companies elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>Although American stocks have risen in his esteem, they have not surpassed those of emerging markets. He finds them attractively priced, despite heavy investment that has pushed up prices.</p>
        <p>''A lot of money is moving into emerging markets,'' he said. ''I think there will be continued inflows unless there is some shock.''</p>
        <p>As anyone familiar with these markets knows, a shock is not out of the question, and he is watching for signs of trouble.</p>
        <p>''I think at some point over the next year or two, we'll see something happen that gives investors pause,'' Mr. Chisholm said. ''The riskier ones may see some challenges.''</p>
        <p>He is wary of investing in Argentina, which he finds expensive. As for Russia, one of last year's strongest performers, he said that it ''still looks interesting longer term, but near term it looks challenging.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chisholm prefers the main northern Asia markets -- China, Taiwan and South Korea -- all of which he finds reasonably priced, and Turkey, which is benefiting from the prospect of European Union membership.</p>
        <p>His favorite Asian stocks include China Mobile, a provider of cellphone service, and Matsushita, the Japanese conglomerate that is enjoying a growth spurt by exporting industrial equipment to the emerging Asian markets.</p>
        <p>While he says he is ''higher on emerging markets as a group than developed markets,'' he does like established markets, like Canada and Australia, that are benefiting from the boom in commodity prices. In particular, he likes three Australian financial service providers: Westpac, Commonwealth Bank and Macquarie Bank.</p>
        <p>Mark Headley, manager of Matthews Asian Tigers and other Asia portfolios, has little choice than to invest in the region, but that geographic straitjacket couldn't have been too binding last year; the region as a whole rose by 35 percent, as measured by the Morgan Stanley Capital International index. He has hopes for further gains this year but is concerned about valuations after such a big climb.</p>
        <p>''The domestic economic environment in Asia is reasonably favorable, economic growth in most countries is fairly strong, and corporate earnings in most sectors are decent,'' he said. ''Valuations vary from market to market. They are not outrageous, but they are certainly not too cheap.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Headley shares Mr. Chisholm's preference for northern Asia. ''We still have a pretty good growth-value mix in Korea and China,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One of his favorite stocks is Lenovo, the Chinese computer manufacturer that bought I.B.M.'s ThinkPad business. ''It dominates much of the Chinese PC market and has extended its Chinese footprint into a global footprint,'' he said. ''It's a new breed of Chinese company that has tremendous long-term potential.''</p>
        <p>As for Japan, he advised investors to limit their exposure. ''Japan has gotten expensive,'' he said. ''The rally has pushed valuations up sharply.''</p>
        <p>After the big move in emerging markets, Mr. Gunn, who manages the Evergreen fund, says he thinks that this may be a good time to take the money and run. In other words, when things are as good as they can get, they can only get worse.</p>
        <p>''I think the very strong three-year performance we've seen in emerging markets may be coming off the boil,'' he cautioned.</p>
        <p>Many of the stocks Mr. Gunn prefers are in Europe, including the Royal Bank of Scotland Group.  Among its virtues, he said, is a price-to-earnings ratio of less than 9, based on analysts' estimates of 2006 earnings, and a dividend yield approaching 5 percent.</p>
        <p>Other favorites include Smith &amp; Nephew, a British maker of artificial joints and other equipment used in orthopedic surgery and Assa Abloy, a Swedish maker of door locks that Mr. Gunn expects to cut costs after a recent management change.</p>
        <p>He also likes European phone companies including Deutsche Telekom, Eircom in Ireland and Telenor in Norway.</p>
        <p>''The whole sector is very much out of favor,'' he noted. The flip side, he said, is that ''valuation levels and yields are good.''</p>
        <p>Neil Rogan, manager of Gartmore Worldwide Leaders, a fund that looks for three dozen worldwide best bets, has no favorite place to invest because he has found solid returns in every corner of the globe.</p>
        <p>''Performance has come from a variety of stocks, not just one sector or region,'' he said. Particular favorites include Apple Computer and ConocoPhillips in the United States; the Italian bank UniCredito; and O2, a British provider of mobile phone service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rogan owns two South Korean semiconductor makers: Hynix Semiconductor, which he said has undergone ''a big restructuring,'' and Samsung Electronics. He is betting on an upturn in the Japanese real estate market with positions in the property developer Mitsui Fudosan and Mitsubishi UFJ Financial, a large bank holding company.</p>
        <p>International outperformance ''could easily happen again'' this year, Mr. Rogan said. ''If the ideas dry up, it's a sign that things aren't doing well,'' he said, ''but there are still a lot around.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
