<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW JERSEY GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E3DE133BF93BA2575AC0A962958260" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW JERSEY GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary L. Emblen; Elizabeth Ginsburg</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DECOY AND GUNNING SHOW</p>
        <p>The Old Time Barnegat Bay Decoy and Gunning Show will be held Saturday and next Sunday in Tuckerton, with a variety of contests that will produce extensive displays of indigenous boats, decoys and art as well as entertainment recalling the heyday of South Jersey waterfowling.</p>
        <p>The entertainment will begin at 7 A.M. each day, as competitors set out to shoot skeet from sneak boxes -- the broad-beamed, shallow draft boats about 10 to 20 feet long that were developed by baymen to sneak up on unsuspecting waterfowl while withstanding the bay's rough winters. There will be separate competitions for men, women and children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DECOY AND GUNNING SHOW</p>
        <p>The Old Time Barnegat Bay Decoy and Gunning Show will be held Saturday and next Sunday in Tuckerton, with a variety of contests that will produce extensive displays of indigenous boats, decoys and art as well as entertainment recalling the heyday of South Jersey waterfowling.</p>
        <p>The entertainment will begin at 7 A.M. each day, as competitors set out to shoot skeet from sneak boxes -- the broad-beamed, shallow draft boats about 10 to 20 feet long that were developed by baymen to sneak up on unsuspecting waterfowl while withstanding the bay's rough winters. There will be separate competitions for men, women and children.</p>
        <p>The Barnegat Bay sneak box is the design for which the area is most famous. Historians have described it as possibly the only boat designed in America without any Old World ancestors, so it deservedly has its own craftsmanship contests, while the rest of the boats developed in the bay area will be grouped together in other contests. There will also be gaming boat half-model design competitions.</p>
        <p>The South Jersey Goose and Duck Calling Association will conduct competitions to determine the New Jersey state champion in both goose and duck calling and there will be separate contests for hunters' duck and goose calling championships.</p>
        <p>Two-member team contests will involve rowing a sneak box, goose calling and skeet shooting from a sneak box.</p>
        <p>Retriever events for all breeds of hunting dogs will include novice, puppy and open competitions.</p>
        <p>Decoy competitions will feature four classes: marsh ducks, diving ducks, geese and the confidence class embracing gulls, terns, herons, egrets, loons, swans and other varieties. There will also be antique and decorative competitions and a shorebird rig contest, with a dozen carved birds attached to a single stick and displayed along the shoreline of the lake in Tip Seaman County Park.</p>
        <p>Art contests will include oil, acrylic and other media as well as color and black and white photography. More than 400 vendors will participate in the show, which is in its 12th year and attracts about 20,000 visitors each day.</p>
        <p>Admission is free for the show, which will be held rain or shine with displays and activities at three sites: the park and the Pinelands High School and Middle School. In addition, the Barnegat Bay Decoy and Baymen's Museum at the park will be open.</p>
        <p>Free shuttle buses will be provided from parking at either school. The schools are on Nugentown Road, about three miles from Exit 58 on the Garden State Parkway via Route 539. Activities will end at about 4 P.M. each day.</p>
        <p>Information: (609) 971-3085 or (609) 296-5606. ARTS AND CRAFTS SHOW</p>
        <p>An art and crafts show, beginning Saturday and running through Oct. 8, will be sponsored by the Englewood Cliffs Centennial Committee at the local campus of St. Peter's College, off Hudson Terrace.</p>
        <p>The show will open with a reception from 1 to 4 P.M. Saturday.</p>
        <p>Twenty-nine artists who have lived or presently live or work in Englewood Cliffs will display more than 100 art works. Leon Madison, Renee Lerner, Margo Moss and Ina Chapler will be among the artists showing works and attending the reception.</p>
        <p>The collection of both realistic and nonrepresentational art will include oil, pastel and acrylic paintings, sculpture, tapestry, paintings on silk, porcelain and ceramics, jewelry and hair accessories.</p>
        <p>John O. A. Pagano's "Closter Horseman," a depiction of the unknown man who warned Gen. George Washington in 1776 that the British were coming to the New Jersey area, will be displayed on loan from the Fort Lee Historic Park Museum.</p>
        <p>Viewing hours will be noon to 8 P.M. Monday through Thursday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Friday and 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. on Saturday. Admission is free and many of the works are for sale.</p>
        <p>Information: (201) 567-8798. POETRY FESTIVAL</p>
        <p>The Geraldine R. Dodge Poetry Festival, which lays claim to being the largest poetry festival in North America, will open on Thursday and continue through next Sunday at Waterloo Village in Stanhope.</p>
        <p>This year's festival celebrates America and American poetry in the broad, correct sense, which includes all the peoples and cultures on the continents and islands of North and South America.</p>
        <p>Robert Bly, Victor Hernandez Cruz, Michael S. Harper, Robert Hass, Linda McCarriston, Sandra McPherson, David Mura, Naomi Shihab Nye, Mary Oliver, Adrienne Rich and Gary Snyder will be among the about 100 poets participating in the event.</p>
        <p>Festival activities will include readings with questions and comments, workshops conducted by featured and regional poets, panel discussions, conversations and storytelling. They will be continuing throughout the village from 9 A.M. to 10 P.M. each day.</p>
        <p>All events will be open to the public, except for programs from 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Thursday and Friday for preregistered students and teachers.</p>
        <p>This will be the fifth edition of the festival, which is held every two years. Previous festivals have been featured in three PBS television specials by Bill Moyers.</p>
        <p>Admission is $8 for one evening, or $4 for students and the elderly, and ranges to $30 for all three days.</p>
        <p>Information: (201) 540-8443, extension 129. HISPANIC HERITAGE</p>
        <p>"The Classical Music of Spain and South America," played by the pianist Hugo Goldenzweig at 2 o'clock this afternoon will be the first event in the Hispanic Heritage Festival 1994 at the Monmouth County Library in Manalapan.</p>
        <p>Dr. Goldenzweig, a native of Argentina, has performed more than 500 concerts in the Americas and Europe since his debut in 1981. He is a professor of music at Mannes College of Music in New York.</p>
        <p>"The Life and Poetry of Julia de Burgos," a drama and documentary film with English subtitles, will be shown at 7:30 P.M. Tuesday with a discussion led by Dr. Alvin Figueroa, assistant professor of Spanish at Trenton State College.</p>
        <p>"Let's Dance!" a demonstration and lesson featuring the dances of South America will be presented at 7:30 P.M. Wednesday by the Fred Astaire Dance Studio of Red Bank.</p>
        <p>"Los Tarantos," filmed in the gypsy district of Barcelona, will be shown with English subtitles at 2 and 7:30 P.M. Thursday. Flamenco dancing by Carmen Amaya and Antonio Gades is included in the story of young love thwarted by family jealousies.</p>
        <p>Mario La Vera, a Colombian vocalist and guitarist, will perform songs from almost every country in Latin America at the festival's concluding event at 2 P.M. Saturday.</p>
        <p>Other festival programs include a book discussion at 2 P.M. Wednesday and an illustrated lecture at 2 P.M. Friday. Admission is free to all of the events at the library, 125 Symmes Drive.</p>
        <p>Information: (908) 308-3761. DESIGNER HOUSE TOURS</p>
        <p>Far View Manor in Holmdel, the former residence of the Gimbel family, has been dressed up as a designer house for tours benefiting the American Cancer Society of Monmouth County and the Bayshore Community Hospital Foundation.</p>
        <p>Tours of the stone, English-style country manor will be conducted daily through Oct. 2 with Early American craft and living demonstrations each afternoon.</p>
        <p>The Historical Society of Early American Decoration will present a special series of workshops and lectures from noon to 5 P.M. today.</p>
        <p>In former years, the manor's foyer was the setting for photographing winners of the Miss Rheingold beauty contest. A curved stairway leads from the foyer to the upstairs where there are six bedrooms and baths.</p>
        <p>The manor, at 3 Grand View Drive, will be open 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Thursday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 9 P.M. Friday and noon to 5 P.M. Sunday. The last tour will begin one hour before closing.</p>
        <p>The $15 fee includes a catalogue, the afternoon demonstrations and visits to a boutique in the carriage house.</p>
        <p>Luncheon, served from 11 A.M. to 2 P.M. daily but from noon to 4 P.M. on Sunday, is optional. The only rules are no spike heels or cameras.</p>
        <p>Information: (908) 946-2552. MARY L. EMBLEN MUSIC FOR ALL SEASONS</p>
        <p>Music for All Seasons, the Plainfield-based organization that provides musical performances to residents of nursing homes, hospitals, special schools and other institutions, will present a gala benefit concert at Carnegie Hall Saturday at 8 P.M.</p>
        <p>Dudley Moore, the actor and musician who is president of the Music for All Seasons advisory board, will be host of the evening and serve as piano soloist. Roberta Peters, the Metropolitan Opera star, will perform arias by Verdi, Puccini and Donizetti.</p>
        <p>The program will also include orchestral works performed by the Orchestra of St. Luke's conducted by Yoav Talmi. Steven Isserlis, cellist, and Joshua Bell, violinist, will be featured along with Mr. Moore in Beethoven's "Triple" Concerto in C major. Ms. Peters and Gov. Christine Todd Whitman are honorary co-chairwomen for the benefit.</p>
        <p>Concert tickets are priced from $25 to $125. Gala tickets to the concert and receptions preceding and following the concert are $150 to $500.</p>
        <p>Concert tickets are available through Carnegie Charge by calling (212) 247-7800. Gala tickets are available by calling (908) 755-5753. ELIZABETH GINSBURG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
