<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Q&amp;A: John Eells; When Volunteers Compose an Orchestra</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FARMINGTON VALLEY SYMPHONY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EELLS, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOMMER, MIMI G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1DF133BF93BA2575AC0A962958260" item-length="1418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Q&amp;A: John Eells; When Volunteers Compose an Orchestra</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIMI G. SOMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SOMMER, MIMI G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the age of 36, John Eells directs the Farmington Valley Symphony Orchestra, a community organization he founded in 1981, the year he became director of music and chairman of the arts at Miss Porter's School in Farmington. His objective was to create a student-and-community orchestra, an idea that evolved into two separate entities, a school ensemble, and a 60-member all-volunteer Farmington Valley symphony orchestra.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eells was born in Oakland, Calif., and moved at the age of 5 to England, where his father taught math at Warwick University. He has a degree from York University and diplomas in conducting and the French horn from the Royal Academy of Music in London; he has also studied with Seiji Ozawa and Andre Previn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the age of 36, John Eells directs the Farmington Valley Symphony Orchestra, a community organization he founded in 1981, the year he became director of music and chairman of the arts at Miss Porter's School in Farmington. His objective was to create a student-and-community orchestra, an idea that evolved into two separate entities, a school ensemble, and a 60-member all-volunteer Farmington Valley symphony orchestra.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eells was born in Oakland, Calif., and moved at the age of 5 to England, where his father taught math at Warwick University. He has a degree from York University and diplomas in conducting and the French horn from the Royal Academy of Music in London; he has also studied with Seiji Ozawa and Andre Previn.</p>
        <p>Recently, he acquired performing rights to a long-lost Berlioz piece, the Messe Solennelle. Excerpts from a conversation with Mr. Eells in his rooftop office at Miss Porter's follow:</p>
        <p>Q. How was the Farmington Valley Symphony Orchestra founded?</p>
        <p>A. I had just started work at Miss Porter's School. The school had no orchestra, and I thought taking student musicians and putting them with a few adults from the area would be a good idea. I quickly changed my mind. I felt the parents would want to hear the students without any adult help. I already had two names of Farmington residents who were interested in performing. I boldly said I was starting an orchestra. Do you know players? It was a network from then on.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you audition your players? If not, how do you recruit your orchestral membership?</p>
        <p>A. I don't have to audition. I just invite. In addition to the two musicians' names I had from the start, there was an oboist whose name was given to me. He was highly regarded and gave me a list of other wind players -- great names. Each time I have an opening, knowing who the people are, I call up.</p>
        <p>In a symphony you can have a large body of strings, but usually only two flutes, two oboes, two clarinets and two bassoons. Sometimes a piccolo, English horn, a bass clarinet and a contra bassoon are added for a particular piece. My string section is small, and at times there aren't enough string players around. I have 10 first violinists. I'd love to have 14. I have four violas. I'd prefer eight to 10.</p>
        <p>We're also limited in technique, yet there's flexibility in the program. We can take more risks than a professional orchestra.</p>
        <p>Q. What geographic area do you serve, and what is the composition of the orchestra?</p>
        <p>A. Six out of the 55, sometimes 60, orchestra members live in Farmington. It's a very colorful orchestra, people with mixed experience. Next year our youngest member will be 12, the oldest 91. We have high school juniors and seniors, and some medical and college student players.</p>
        <p>They come from a radius of about 30 miles -- from Farmington, West Hartford, Avon, Simsbury, Bristol, New Britain, Burlington, Manchester, Rocky Hill, Canton, a few from Wolcott. We serve an area that extends into Hartford.</p>
        <p>At this point there is no volunteer community Hartford orchestra. The nearest and best one is in Manchester, the other side of the river. We perform half our programs in Farmington, and half in West Hartford.</p>
        <p>Q. Connecticut's musical landscape is punctuated with both regional professional orchestras like the New Haven Symphony and Hartford Symphony, and volunteer community orchestras like your own. What are the essential differences?</p>
        <p>A. A professional level orchestra is made up of very highly trained musicians. A community level orchestra may or may not have highly trained musicians. Probably 10 of the members of my orchestra were music majors who've since gone into other fields. Because of other jobs, practice time is less. They practice once a week for 7 to 8 weeks for each of five programs.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you select your orchestra's programs?</p>
        <p>A. Programing is absolutely key to the success of an orchestra such as this. Keep the players interested. Make sure the audience enjoys the programs. Get the right balance of soloists in terms of the instruments they play.</p>
        <p>I must pick programs that appeal to the players, before the audience. That's the difference between a professional symphony and a volunteer symphony. Professional programs have to sell, and must cater to the audience. We are all about the players first and foremost, yet we create a balanced program, new and contemporary music combined with the classical greats.</p>
        <p>I try to incorporate a new piece each season, a Connecticut artist for a Connecticut audience. Gwenyth Walker, a Connecticut-based composer, attended our performance this season of her composition for brass.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have soloists?</p>
        <p>A. We have guest soloists, one for each program, none of whom are paid. They are in almost every case professional. We've recently had Jay Lichtmann, principal trumpet; Anhared Stowe, principal second violinist, and four horn players, all of the Hartford Symphony.</p>
        <p>Each year the winner of the Connecticut Music Educators Association Piano Competition solos with my orchestra. I keep my ear open for Connecticut composers and Connecticut soloists. It builds our base. We'll need three vocal soloists for the new season's first program, when we perform a recently discovered Berloiz Mass.</p>
        <p>Q. Finding a Berlioz Mass is a bit like uncovering a true copy of the Declaration of Independence in a flea market frame. What is the story of its discovery and rebirth?</p>
        <p>A. The first performance of the Messe Solennelle, written when Berlioz was 20, was in Paris in 1825. An unheralded Berlioz conducted its second performance there with all volunteers in 1827. Many have said he wanted to destroy the piece. It's thought the score, discovered in 1991 in Belgium, was given by Berlioz to a violinist from Antwerp who undoubtedly played in his performance, to say thank you.</p>
        <p>From all accounts the Mass had not been performed in 166 years. The Orchestre Revolutionnaire et Romantique under John Eliot Gardiner performed the piece in Paris in 1993, the National Cathedral Choir in Washington in May this year, and the Boston Symphony will do it in October. Our performances with the Hartt Masterworks Chorale, with 180 to 210 performers, will be on Nov. 4 and 5 in Hartford's Trinity Episcopal Church and in New Britain's Welte Auditorium.</p>
        <p>My discovery of the piece came from a conversation I had with my brother-in-law, who is a lawyer and professional horn player. He had read about the Gardiner recording. I saw on the recording that the Messe Solennelle was published in 1993 by Barenreiter.</p>
        <p>I'm quite sure that ours will be the first all-volunteer group to perform the Mass since Berlioz himself did it in 1827. The piece lasts an hour and will be balanced by a shorter delicate Haydn Symphony, No. 88, a festive opening. Haydn and Berlioz were inventive geniuses.</p>
        <p>Q. Is the Berlioz more a historic find than a great piece of music?</p>
        <p>A. I think it's better than a historic find. Melodies and harmonies that are in this Mass are found in later works, so it's historically very significant. This is a good piece of music. It's not a great Mass; it is a very worthwhile performance piece that should be heard. While over our budget, we figured that we'd sell more tickets, and we'd get more corporate support.</p>
        <p>Q. How are you supported?</p>
        <p>A. Ticket sales, donations by members of the orchestra, by the community, and for each program we have an educational sponsor, who gives us money, usually $500, and in return we list them as the educational sponsor, and give free tickets to students in the town we're playing in. We have an audience of about 300. The admission is regularly $8, and seniors pay $5. Our fifth and benefit concert of the year has a higher ticket price as will the Berlioz. Our concerts are on Friday and Saturday nights.</p>
        <p>Q. In early music history and in early American life, is there an historical precedent for the community orchestra?</p>
        <p>A. I don't know specifically the histories of American orchestras, but almost all of them were started from a collection of musicians getting together. Volunteer community efforts turned into professional groups.</p>
        <p>Q. What is your vision for your orchestra?</p>
        <p>A. I see us going forward and growing in size and talent. I've no grand design to turn this into a professional orchestra. There are so many great pieces out there waiting to be played. Duke Ellington -- he wrote an enormous amount of music for the symphony orchestra.</p>
        <p>Our future is secure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
