<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fashion Gallery</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="74" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD6173BF93BA2575AC0A962958260" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fashion Gallery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lisa Liebmann</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fashion is a most amiable muse, yet many artists tend to be rather wary of it. If one allows that immortality is the artist's ultimate goal, then it stands to reason that fashion, perishable by definition, must be its dread opposite. Certainly, the artists invited here to address some aspect of the New York fall collections strike a multitude of attitudes -- from urban appreciation to a healthy disregard. Working in a variety of media, including life drawing, photography, taxidermy and collage, they are as eclectic a lot stylistically as they are intellectually.</p>
        <p>Beverley Semmes and Pat Oleszko habitually work with clothes, and might both be described as exaggerators. Semmes elongates, in the manner of a latter-day Beardsley. The Calvin Klein T-shirt dress that figures in her piece is cocooned within a characteristically distended, Semmesian garment resembling a Victorian nightgown. Knotted as it is, the gauzy pinafore also suggests some jerry-built means of escape -- in a symbolist fairy tale involving, say, a princess in a tower -- and the little dress inside evokes the dream of liberation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fashion is a most amiable muse, yet many artists tend to be rather wary of it. If one allows that immortality is the artist's ultimate goal, then it stands to reason that fashion, perishable by definition, must be its dread opposite. Certainly, the artists invited here to address some aspect of the New York fall collections strike a multitude of attitudes -- from urban appreciation to a healthy disregard. Working in a variety of media, including life drawing, photography, taxidermy and collage, they are as eclectic a lot stylistically as they are intellectually.</p>
        <p>Beverley Semmes and Pat Oleszko habitually work with clothes, and might both be described as exaggerators. Semmes elongates, in the manner of a latter-day Beardsley. The Calvin Klein T-shirt dress that figures in her piece is cocooned within a characteristically distended, Semmesian garment resembling a Victorian nightgown. Knotted as it is, the gauzy pinafore also suggests some jerry-built means of escape -- in a symbolist fairy tale involving, say, a princess in a tower -- and the little dress inside evokes the dream of liberation.</p>
        <p>Oleszko, a founding force majeure in performance art and video, is best known for sensational, ferociously childlike costumes -- bawdy architectonic numbers with multiple teats, for instance, or bustles built for dragons -- that invoke the Dionysian principles of the 1960's, while also recalling Oskar Schlemmer's Bauhaus designs, Lewis Carroll and Dr. Seuss. Hers is a raw comic vision, close in spirit to vaudeville. In her current "Knee-o" series, with its punning effronteries, Oleszko brings the variety-show antics of a Senor Wences into the age of MTV.</p>
        <p>Meyer Vaisman, too, has something of the old-time showman about him. A few seasons back, the ever-quizzical Vaisman did a group of paintings featuring Sardi's-style caricatures of himself looking like the cigar-smoking comics of yore. Lately, he has been cross-dressing stuffed turkeys, turning them into an outrageous cast of alter egos. Here, poised lividly on its bale of hay, the artist's fowl surrogate wears a formidable evening skirt by Isaac Mizrahi conjuring up mangled Dada-esque visions of Marie Antoinette and Tennessee Ernie Ford.</p>
        <p>Some of the other artists were more intent on social critique. Rob Wynne, for one, embriodered word fragments from Jean Genet's perverse play "The Maids" on the long -- and unattended -- train of a Donna Karan dress. Renee Green designed her own fabric for a nonchalant tableau vivant of a SoHo salon (Her dealer, Pat Hearn is lounging on the sofa looking not unlike a modern Madame Recamier). But Green's traditional-looking toile de Jouy is actually a prime instance of pictorial revisionism with a Afrocentric theme.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Elaine Reichek takes ethnography as her premise, and make class and culture the object of her inquires. The vanished -- and evidently status-free -- Tierra del Fuego tribesmen whose images appear in Reichek's computerized collage have shown up many times before in her wide-ranging work. Here, in the context of a genteel damask and Darwin's words, they form a haunting rejoinder to a group of models applauding Ralph Lauren at the end of a show.</p>
        <p>But if some artists mistrust fashion, others embrace it. Actually people and their possessions are of essential concern to both Jane Kaplowitz and Billy Sullivan, the painters of modern life in this group. Evoking the sketch-pad spontaneity of a contemporary Cocteau,. Kaplowitz has over the years evinced a fey tenderness for everything -- and everyone -- considered fashionable. With a typically sharp yet wistful eye she celebrates 60's fashion -- and flat midriffs -- in this outfit by Ghost.</p>
        <p>Billy Sullivan, finally, takes the ornithologist's approach to people and their plumages. Just as he sketches the endless succession of birds who feed in his country graden, so too does he capture Geoffrey Beene's birds of paradise -- in motion, if not quite in flight. How fitting and sweet of him to remind us that while fashion isn't art, and art isn't necessarily fashion, each is a sure sign of being alive. Lisa Liebmann</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
