<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q. &amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="712773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2D6123BF93BA2575AC0A962958260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q. &amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Landlord's Access To a Co-op Q I sublet an apartment in a co-op building and have lived there for a year now. While going through our renewal lease, I found a term I completely disagreed with. Although I have tried to discuss this with the landlord, she keeps stressing that it is perfectly legal for her to do what she is doing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Landlord's Access To a Co-op Q I sublet an apartment in a co-op building and have lived there for a year now. While going through our renewal lease, I found a term I completely disagreed with. Although I have tried to discuss this with the landlord, she keeps stressing that it is perfectly legal for her to do what she is doing.</p>
        <p>The term I am referring to reads: "The apartment shall be available for showing from March 1, 1995. When this showing is necessary, a 24-hour notice shall be given in advance."</p>
        <p>This technically means that the landlord could be showing the apartment every day from March 1 onward, for six months until our lease runs out. This does not protect my privacy. What are my legal rights in this matter?</p>
        <p>Also, is it legal for the landlord to enter the apartment when the tenant is not home without getting permission in advance? . . . Kamla Vacher-Ta, Manhattan.  A There are no legal rights in this situation, said Michael Finder, a Manhattan lawyer. "There is no statute or regulation which governs the terms of a sublet of a co-op apartment," Mr. Finder said. "These provisions are governed solely by the terms of the agreement between the parties."</p>
        <p>"Thus, assuming that the original sublease agreement, which is now being renewed, did not contain any automatic renewal rights, it is up to the parties involved to negotiate the terms of the renewal," he said. "And if the shareholder -- that is, the landlord -- is insisting on these access provisions, and the subtenant is unwilling to accept them and the parties can't come to an agreement, there won't be an extension of the sublease."</p>
        <p>It is normal for a landlord or a prime tenant subletting an apartment to insert in a lease that he or she be given the right to show the apartment during the last three to six months of the lease's term, Mr. Finder said. "They don't want to first show the apartment after it is vacated and lose a couple of month's rent," he said.</p>
        <p>"But it would also be typical for a tenant to try to limit the frequency with which the apartment is shown," he said, "and to require 72 hours' notice rather than 24. Finally, it would also be typical to provide in the lease that the landlord may not unilaterally access the apartment except in the event of an emergency."</p>
        <p>"But the bottom line is that all of this is subject to whatever contract they can or cannot agree on," Mr. Finder said. "There are no protections beyond the agreement, no governmental authority to superimpose itself. If the landlord insists on the provisions, the tenant has to accept them or not extend the sublease."  Checking Salaries Of a Building's Staff Q We own a co-op apartment unit and are interested in finding out the wage scale of the superintendent, the doormen and the building staff. How do we go about getting this information? . . . F. Bransford Prieto, Manhattan.  A "Most buildings in Manhattan, Brooklyn, Queens and Staten Island have employees who are members of Local 32B-32J of the Service Employees International Union," said Mary Ann Rothman, executive director of the Council of New York Cooperatives. "There is a standard contract that generally lasts for three years and was last negotiated this past spring."</p>
        <p>Under that contract, Ms. Rothman said, all cooperatives are considered Class A buildings. "In those buildings, porters and doormen earn $528.73 a week," she said. "A handyperson receives $579.73 a week. Salary scales for superintendents vary somewhat, but a superintendent usually gets a little bit more than a handyperson and also gets use of an apartment and a telephone for local calls in exchange for providing round-the-clock emergency service for the building."</p>
        <p>If the building is not a union building, Ms. Rothman said, the wages are "whatever has been negotiated with the individual employee."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
