<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Playoffs in View, 76ers Blindside the Nets</title>
    <meta content="13nets" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/13/sports/basketball/13nets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1754202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Philadelphia 76ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia 76ers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D71F30F930A25757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Playoffs in View, 76ers Blindside the Nets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Satisfied Nets Let 76ers Get Their Fill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., April 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia 76ers defeat New Jersey Nets, 116-96; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nets have little to play for until the playoffs, and that was painfully obvious Wednesday.</p>
        <p>For the second straight night, the Nets (47-31) turned in a lackluster effort while losing to an inferior opponent. On Tuesday, they lost in Chicago to the Bulls, 104-101. On Wednesday, they fell to the Philadelphia 76ers, 116-96.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With little motivation, the Nets drop second straight to the Philadelphia 76ers, a team hungry for the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff spot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nets have little to play for until the playoffs, and that was painfully obvious Wednesday.</p>
        <p>For the second straight night, the Nets (47-31) turned in a lackluster effort while losing to an inferior opponent. On Tuesday, they lost in Chicago to the Bulls, 104-101. On Wednesday, they fell to the Philadelphia 76ers, 116-96.</p>
        <p>The Bulls and the 76ers are hungry teams. They are tied for the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff spot with 37-41 records after Wednesday's games. Philadelphia has won three straight, and the Bulls kept pace with a 96-90 victory over Atlanta.</p>
        <p>As for the Nets, they have clinched the Atlantic Division championship, and they have little hope of passing Miami (51-27) for the No. 2 seeding in the Eastern Conference playoffs. For now, there is little to motivate them.</p>
        <p>''This game was definitely something we'll try to forget about,'' Jason Kidd said. ''It was no surprise what team needed the game tonight.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the Nets' problems, starting forward Jason Collins sat out the game with a bruised right knee he sustained Tuesday. He expects to play Friday when the Nets travel to Boston. Cliff Robinson started in his place.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Nets Coach Lawrence Frank insisted his team would not be going through the motions and was ''playing to win.'' Once the game began, it did not seem that way.</p>
        <p>The Nets took a 13-8 lead on a layup by Nenad Krstic with 8 minutes 21 seconds left in the first quarter. It did not last long. Andre Iguodala hit a 3-pointer with 5:59 to go to put the 76ers ahead, 15-14. Krstic followed with a basket for the Nets, but the 76ers responded with an 8-0 run to take a commanding lead.</p>
        <p>The game got no better for the Nets during the rest of the half. The 76ers took a 44-25 lead on a 15-foot jumper by Iverson with 7:58 left in the second quarter. After Iverson made an 18-foot jumper with 1.6 seconds to go before halftime, Philadelphia had a 67-46 lead.</p>
        <p>''For us to come in and relax, that's not how we want to finish the season,'' Robinson said. ''To me, it's disappointing. It's like we relaxed tonight.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the 76ers, he said: ''That's a playoff team that is playing for their playoff lives. That should have been a good tune-up for us. We know what position we're in, but we still need to go out and get ourselves ready for the playoffs."</p>
        <p>With Iverson leading the way, the 76ers were relentless. Iverson scored 12 points in the third quarter, which ended with Philadelphia leading by 90-73.</p>
        <p>By then, it was clear that Frank had seen enough, and he did not want to take any unnecessary risks. He pulled his starters for the fourth quarter and inserted a lineup that consisted of Robinson, Zoran Planinic, Jacque Vaughn, Bostjan Nachbar and Lamond Murray. The seldom-used Scott Padgett also got playing time early in the quarter. But few fans were there to see him as the building was already emptying.</p>
        <p>''We knew this was going to be a tough game for us, but we wish we performed better,'' Frank said. ''Once things got out of hand, we figured we might as well get an opportunity to see some of these other guys who don't get an opportunity to play.''</p>
        <p>Iverson finished with 40 points and 10 assists. He made 13 of 26 field-goal attempts and was 14 for 15 from the free-throw line. Webber added 18 points.</p>
        <p>Vince Carter led the Nets with 21 points. Krstic had 18 points and 11 rebounds. Kidd (9 points) and Richard Jefferson (8 points) had quiet nights.</p>
        <p>The 116 points were the most the Nets have given up this season.</p>
        <p>The Nets have only four regular-season games remaining before the playoffs, including another meeting with Philadelphia on Tuesday. Based on the way they have played so far this week, more of the same is possible, not that it necessarily matters.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
