<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Glut, No Glory? 1 Boxer, 4 Books</title>
    <meta content="11BRAD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/11/books/11brad.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1679237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braddock, James J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howard, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delisa, Michael C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hague, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baer, Max</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schaap, Jeremy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cerasini, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cinderella Man (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cinderella Man: The James J Braddock Story (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Braddock: The Rise of the Cinderella Man (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cinderella Man (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cinderella Man: James J Braddock, Max Baer... (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5D91138F932A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Glut, No Glory? 1 Boxer, 4 Books</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Glut, No Glory? 1 Boxer, 4 Books</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on former heavyweight boxing champion James J Braddock, subject of Ron Howard's new movie Cinderella Man and four new biographies: Cinderella Man: The James J Braddock Story by Michael C DeLisa, Braddock: The Rise of the Cinderella Man by Jim Hague, Cinderella Man: James J Braddock, Max Baer and the Greatest Upset in Boxing History by Jeremy Schaap and Cinderella Man by Marc Cerasini; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly 70 years, biographers have ignored the former heavyweight champion James J. Braddock. Suddenly, he is the subject of four books.</p>
        <p>Braddock was not as popular as Jack Dempsey, as historically significant as Joe Louis, as outsize as Muhammad Ali or as ferocious as Mike Tyson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly 70 years, biographers have ignored the former heavyweight champion James J. Braddock, the hero of the film "Cinderella Man." Suddenly, he is the subject of four books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly 70 years, biographers have ignored the former heavyweight champion James J. Braddock. Suddenly, he is the subject of four books.</p>
        <p>Braddock was not as popular as Jack Dempsey, as historically significant as Joe Louis, as outsize as Muhammad Ali or as ferocious as Mike Tyson.</p>
        <p>But he is the hero of Ron Howard's new film, ''Cinderella Man,'' starring Russell Crowe. All four of the Braddock biographies were published within two months of the movie's release last week. None were the basis of the screenplay, but one was written by the film's historical adviser, Michael C. DeLisa, and another is an official tie-in with the film. (So far, the movie has been less than spectacular at the box office.)</p>
        <p>The saga of Braddock, who was given the name ''Cinderella Man'' by Damon Runyon, is a biped version of the 2003 film ''Seabiscuit'' -- the tale of an undersize, unheralded horse who electrified thoroughbred racing fans in the late 1930's -- which was spawned by only one book, by Laura Hillenbrand.</p>
        <p>Braddock came to prominence as a light heavyweight in New York and New Jersey, but he lost his pugilistic touch and, with his wife and three children, tumbled into profound poverty during the Depression. He rediscovered his skills in the ring as a heavyweight and defeated Max Baer in a stunning 15-round decision at the Madison Square Garden Bowl in Long Island City, Queens, in 1935.</p>
        <p>A rousing story? Certainly. But is it worthy of four biographies in just a few weeks? To compare, four major books about Benjamin Franklin have come out recently, but over a three-year span.</p>
        <p>The publishers of the Braddock books said they knew they would be capitalizing on the film but were unaware that they would be part of a Braddock literary glut.</p>
        <p>''We thought we'd be the only one,'' said Peter Walsh, whose Milo Books is the British publisher of Mr. DeLisa's ''Cinderella Man: The James J. Braddock Story.'' He added: ''I'd read about the casting of the movie and I thought it would make an interesting biography. So I cast about for an author.''</p>
        <p>Carlo DeVito, publisher of Chamberlain Brothers, a division of the Penguin Group, said he was certain he made the first move by signing Jim Hague, a sportswriter at The Newark Star-Ledger, at the beginning of 2004 to write ''Braddock: The Rise of the Cinderella Man.'' ''We got into this as a one-horse affair,'' he said. ''I didn't know the barn would grow so big.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DeVito said he then learned from an agent that Houghton Mifflin had enlisted Jeremy Schaap, an ESPN reporter and anchorman, for ''Cinderella Man: James J. Braddock, Max Baer and the Greatest Upset in Boxing History.''</p>
        <p>Then along came another: HarperEntertainment brought out ''Cinderella Man,'' by Marc Cerasini, the official tie-in book based on the film's screenplay.</p>
        <p>Josh Behar, who acquired the book for Harper, said, ''I would rather there had been no books but my own, but Braddock's a fascinating guy and a cool story.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''The market is small for this, and having four books out is difficult and it hurts every single one of them.''</p>
        <p>Actually, five. Next month, Newmarket Press will publish ''Cinderella Man: The Shooting Script,'' with historical notes following the final ''Fade to Black.''</p>
        <p>The unanticipated Braddock abundance raises the inevitable question: how does a reader choose among these books? They have similar titles and basically tell the same story. Three have similar covers, with photographs of Braddock; the tie-in's cover shows Mr. Crowe kissing Renée Zellweger, who plays his wife, Mae.</p>
        <p>''I knew there'd be other books,'' said Mr. Behar of Harper. ''But we had the tie-in art, and we knew if we did the right things, we'd stand out.''</p>
        <p>Cutting through the Braddock clutter is ''our challenge,'' said Susan Canavan, who edited Mr. Schaap's book at Houghton Mifflin. ''Our book is a hardcover, the rest are paperback,'' she said. The Schaap book is at least $10 more expensive. ''This is a real, nuanced book,'' she added. ''We feel like we have the author with the credentials. Will that translate to the average consumer? We think so.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaap is the best known of the four authors, with regular exposure on ESPN and a family legacy in sports writing. His father, Dick, who died in 2001, wrote more than 30 books, most of them about sports figures.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLisa is a lawyer and boxing historian who runs cyberboxingzone.com, an online research site. ''We're committed to ferreting out every fact we can,'' he said. ''For the book, I went back to old newspapers, and a lot of stuff about him was buried.'' When he was in his 20's, he corresponded with Mae Braddock after her husband's death, gathering information that would help his research many years later.</p>
        <p>The back cover of his book cites his connection to the film, which he said should help differentiate it from the other three books.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Schaap's book is winning the battle of the Braddock biographies. According to the most recent figures from Nielsen BookScan, which tracks retail sales in about 70 percent of the United States, his book has sold 6,500 copies, Mr. Cerasini's 4,000, Mr. DeLisa's 2,000 and Mr. Hague's 1,500. But these are just the early rounds: the real question is who will be left standing once the movie disappears from the theaters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
