<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Public School Seeks Equality in Uniformity</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="184558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNIFORMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HELENE GRANT ELEMENTARY SCHOOL (NEW HAVEN, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BASS, SHARON L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D6133FF931A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Public School Seeks Equality in Uniformity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON L. BASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BASS, SHARON L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW uniform requirement to take effect in a New Haven public school tomorrow promises to quell arguments and fistfights among students over who has the designer T-shirts or the most expensive brand-name sneakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A NEW uniform requirement to take effect in a New Haven public school tomorrow promises to quell arguments and fistfights among students over who has the designer T-shirts or the most expensive brand-name sneakers.</p>
        <p>A NEW uniform requirement to take effect in a New Haven public school tomorrow promises to quell arguments and fistfights among students over who has the designer T-shirts or the most expensive brand-name sneakers.</p>
        <p>At the same time school officials hope that as the importance of clothing plummets, the children's self-confidence and test scores will increase.</p>
        <p>''The uniforms say everybody is somebody,'' said Jeffie Frazier, the principal at Helene Grant elementary school, where the uniforms will be worn. ''You can't say, 'I'm a somebody because I'm wearing Nikes.'''</p>
        <p>According to the State Department of Education, Helene Grant is the first public school in Connecticut to adopt such a requirement and one of only a few in the country. A similar idea was initiated in Cromwell last year, but never got off the ground because most parents were against it, said Alexander Paddyfoote, Superintendent of the town's public schools.  Peer Pressure Over Clothing</p>
        <p>Ms. Frazier said the uniform rule was prompted by parents concerned about mounting peer pressure over clothing. So far, she said, there has been no parental opposition.</p>
        <p>But the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union has calling the requirement unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>''We fee that a mandatory dress code violates First Amendment guarantees that takes away the right of the parent to decide how their children should dress,'' said William Olds, the executive director of the Connecticut group.</p>
        <p>He quoted a passage from a 1985 publication put out by the Connecticut Department of Education titled ''Student Rights and Reponsibilities in Connecticut's Public Schools.'' It said, ''The way a student looks and dresses is a fundamental form of personal expression and should be protected by Constitutional guarantees of privacy and freedom of expression.''</p>
        <p>Even if a majority of the parents want the uniforms, Mr. Olds said, ''that doesn't make it constitutional or legal.''</p>
        <p>''It's analogous to having prayer or teaching creation in school,'' he said. ''The Bill of Rights was created to prevent the majority from taking rights away from the minority.'' He said he had sent a letter to John Dow Jr., the Superintendent of New Haven public schools, asking him to withdraw the practice, which was approved by the school board.  'The Parents Want This'</p>
        <p>''I don't even give that credence,'' Mr. Dow said in response to Mr. Olds's request. ''Urban education has failed and failed miserably. The parents want this. Uniforms have been a great model of private schools and private education has been hailed as the great savior of this nation.</p>
        <p>''These kids deserve the same and I'm going to fight for that. Besides, most of these youngsters can't afford $45 for a pair of sneakers or jeans,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of the 300 students at the Helene Grant school, which goes from kindergarten to fourth grade, 98 percent are black and 75 percent live in families that receive state assistance, Ms. Frazier said.</p>
        <p>''I'd see the children fighting first thing in the morning,'' she said. ''The topic was always clothes and sneakers. Who had the Air Jordans and the Converses. Who had the plain T-shirt versus the ones with the emblems or fancy lettering. If a child didn't wear the right thing, it could lead to a fistfight.''</p>
        <p>''The clincher was when a parent of a kindergarten student came in looking for her daughter's $25 hat,'' she added. ''She was very upset. Instead of learning the alphabet, the little girl was worried about where her hat was.''  15 Parents Volunteer</p>
        <p>Since last year, at every P.T.A. meeting, Ms. Frazier said, parents talked about the pressure children were under to dress well. Together they agreed to adopt a uniform code.</p>
        <p>For the last few months, 15 parents have volunteered their time to sew hundreds of pleated green jumpers which were sold to parents at $15 apiece. The rest of the girls' uniform consists of a white blouse, white socks, a green cardigan sweater and black or brown shoes - no sneakers.</p>
        <p>The boys' uniform consists of gray slacks, white shirts, green ties, a green pullover sweater and brown or black shoes. Ms. Frazier said that the cost for one complete uniform is about $60. She said parents were notified about the uniforms in August to give them time to save money. In addition, they could borrow money from the P.T.A. at no interest.</p>
        <p>''My ultimate goal is to provide a learning environment that promotes excellence by getting their minds off clothes,'' Ms. Frazier said. If a parent refuses to abide by the rule, she said, ''he has the choice of sending his child to another school.''</p>
        <p>''If it's going to work, all the students are going to have to wear it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Parents and students at the school say they are in favor of the new uniforms. ''It will help cut down on expenses and time,'' said Marie Young, who helps with the sewing and has a child in third grade at the school. ''I won't have to look for clothes in the morning. Now my son will put more attention into his work and not his clothes.''</p>
        <p>''I love it,'' said Dorothy Jackson, a cafeteria aide at the school who also has three nieces and two nephews attending the school, three of whom live with her. ''I'm standing in the lunchroom one day and I see a little boy point to another and say, 'Look, he's wearing Jeepers,' which is a cheap sneaker. And the whole class focused on the boy's feet.'' She said she would be be happy when the uniform requirement is at the junior high school.</p>
        <p>LaShonda Smith, a fourth grader at Helene Grant, said she was glad that everyone will look the same. ''I feel sad when I hear children cut down on each other about their holey clothes,'' she said. ''I think everyone will look pretty in the uniform.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
