<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; Tony Randall Directs 'The Master Builder'</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="515426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBSEN, HENRIK (1828-1906)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RANDALL, TONY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MASTER BUILDER, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB133DF933A15750C0A964958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; Tony Randall Directs 'The Master Builder'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICH, FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some theater companies take years to develop and refine a distinctive style, but the National Actors Theater has accomplished this feat in a single season. The latest example of its signature approach to the classics can be found in its production of "The Master Builder" at the Belasco Theater.</p>
        <p>The style might be called the esthetic equivalent of the Heimlich maneuver. The director, whoever he may be, assumes that the classic play at his disposal is near death, or at least thought so by the audience, and must be resuscitated by being pounded out by the actors, with waving arms and often at top volume. If the actors stand in place while declaiming ("The Crucible" and "The Master Builder"), you're at a drama. If they are jumping up and down ("A Little Hotel on the Side"), it's comedy tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some theater companies take years to develop and refine a distinctive style, but the National Actors Theater has accomplished this feat in a single season. The latest example of its signature approach to the classics can be found in its production of "The Master Builder" at the Belasco Theater.</p>
        <p>The style might be called the esthetic equivalent of the Heimlich maneuver. The director, whoever he may be, assumes that the classic play at his disposal is near death, or at least thought so by the audience, and must be resuscitated by being pounded out by the actors, with waving arms and often at top volume. If the actors stand in place while declaiming ("The Crucible" and "The Master Builder"), you're at a drama. If they are jumping up and down ("A Little Hotel on the Side"), it's comedy tonight.</p>
        <p>Though "The Master Builder" is the first of the productions directed by Tony Randall, the company's founder and artistic director -- the Playbill lists no previous directing credits for him of any kind in New York -- he is already a master of this method. The only way you can distinguish his "Master Builder" from Yossi Yzraely's "Crucible" is by the smaller size of the cast.</p>
        <p>Ibsen's plays are not that often given major stagings in New York, and though "The Master Builder" received a decent Roundabout Theater Company reading in 1983, the acclaimed and innovative productions of American directors like Robert Wilson and Mark Lamos and of British directors like Peter Hall and Adrian Noble remain only rumors here. The National Actors Theater "Master Builder," a passionless recital performed on dowdy realistic sets, could set the local Ibsen cause back a decade or two. In place of a psychologically tumultuous, at times mythic drama of an artist's self-inflicted decline and fall is one big slab of solid Norwegian wood.</p>
        <p>Earle Hyman can be an interesting character actor, but his performance as Ibsen's autobiographical stand-in, Solness, is, like much of the production, beyond the purview of professional drama criticism. His voice, body and jowls all quivering, he doesn't act the role so much as sing it, often, unaccountably, in falsetto. As Hilde Wangel, the mysterious young woman from the mountains who tempts him to both ecstasy and disaster, the perky Madeleine Potter is miscast, unless one assumes that Solness's erotic tastes run in the direction of the Trapp Family Singers. Among the others, Maryann Plunkett can be applauded for applying her fierce concentration to the small role of the bookkeeper, and Lynn Redgrave can be praised for bringing some genuine feeling (and a hint of a Norwegian tone) to Mrs. Solness, despite being made up to look like Cloris Leachman in Mel Brooks's "Young Frankenstein."</p>
        <p>In this "Master Builder," when Solness falls from a great height, it is such an anticlimax that he might as well be stumbling from a footstool. Ms. Potter marks Solness's demise by waving her white shawl not once but three times in a manic windmill gesture that, depending on your point of view, is either the apotheosis of the National Actors Theater style or a desperate plea of S O S. The Master Builder  By Henrik Ibsen; translated by Johan Fillinger; directed by Tony Randall; settings by David Jenkins; costumes, Patricia Zipprodt; lighting by Richard Nelson; sound by T. Richard Fitzgerald; executive producer, Manny Kladitis. Presented by the National Actors Theater, Mr. Randall, founder and artistic director. At the Belasco Theater, 111 West 44th Street, Manhattan.  Kaja Fosli . . . Maryann Plunkett Knut Brovik . . . John Beal Ragnar Brovik . . . Pete McRobbie Halvard Solness . . . Earle Hyman Alvine Solness . . . Lynn Redgrave Dr. Herdal . . . Patrick Tull Hilde Wangel . . . Madeleine Potter</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
