<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foot Doctors Try to Ease Pain of H.M.O.'s</title>
    <meta content="CHIREL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Q&amp;A: Hiram Chirel" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="949487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island Q&amp;A: Hiram Chirel"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unionization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Feet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Podiatric Medical Assn (Nys)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">First National Guild For Health Care Providers of the Lower Extre</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chirel, Hiram (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Feet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unionization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EEDA1E3DF933A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="1608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foot Doctors Try to Ease Pain of H.M.O.'s</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Hiram Chirel, executive director of New York State Podiatric Medical Assn, who comments on decision to join First National Guild for Health Care Providers of Lower Extremities, US's first labor union for doctors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIRAM CHIREL is executive director of the 1,400-member New York State Podiatric Medical Association, the nation's largest state organization of foot specialists. In February the group voted to join the nation's first labor union for doctors, the First National Guild for Health Care Providers of the Lower Extremities. The move is an attempt to increase their influence against what the doctors see as restrictive rules imposed by managed care associations. Dr. Chirel, 66, was a president and board member of the medical association before becoming its executive director. He received his Doctor of Podiatric Medicine degree in 1956 from the New York College of Podiatric Medicine, and served on the faculty there as well as at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine. Dr. Chirel and his wife, Elba, also a podiatric physician and who is president of the Nassau County Podiatric Medical Association, live in Port Washington. They have two grown children.</p>
        <p>Q. The idea of doctors becoming unionized seems kind of strange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIRAM CHIREL is executive director of the 1,400-member New York State Podiatric Medical Association, the nation's largest state organization of foot specialists. In February the group voted to join the nation's first labor union for doctors, the First National Guild for Health Care Providers of the Lower Extremities. The move is an attempt to increase their influence against what the doctors see as restrictive rules imposed by managed care associations. Dr. Chirel, 66, was a president and board member of the medical association before becoming its executive director. He received his Doctor of Podiatric Medicine degree in 1956 from the New York College of Podiatric Medicine, and served on the faculty there as well as at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine. Dr. Chirel and his wife, Elba, also a podiatric physician and who is president of the Nassau County Podiatric Medical Association, live in Port Washington. They have two grown children.</p>
        <p>Q. The idea of doctors becoming unionized seems kind of strange.</p>
        <p>A. Traditionally, unions have been for employees, not employers. But situations have occurred in the health care delivery system and we are trying to find some other avenue for accomplishing some of the things we are trying to do.</p>
        <p>Q. What are you referring to?</p>
        <p>A. The H.M.O.'s, health maintenance organizations, whose whole objective is to reduce the cost of health care. However, in order to reduce cost, they reduced the number of health care providers and benefits to subscribers because most of them set up what is called a gatekeeper system. In order for the patient to go to a specialist, he has to go to the gatekeeper first. The gatekeeper has a financial incentive not to refer. So what is happening is that there are less referrals than before.</p>
        <p>Q. The gatekeeper is the primary care physician.</p>
        <p>A. That's correct.</p>
        <p>Q. And he has a financial interest not to refer to specialists?</p>
        <p>A. The H.M.O.'s withhold 10 or 15 percent of his fee and it goes into a pot. If he does a lot of referrals -- and they figure it has cost them more money because of all those referrals -- he's not going to get it back. If he's a nice guy and he doesn't do a lot of referrals, he is going to get that money back. So that's the incentive not to refer.</p>
        <p>Q. How much are we talking about?</p>
        <p>A. It could be a couple of hundred thousand dollars a year.</p>
        <p>Q. Is that across the board with all of the H.M.O.'s or just a few?</p>
        <p>A. Most of them have a gatekeeper and most of them have the withhold, which is financial protection for them at the end of the year. The H.M.O.'s are big business in the United States. In order for the H.M.O.'s to make money, there are two people they can squeeze -- the provider, by cutting down the reimbursement to them, and the patient, by not giving them the care they ordinarily would get if they were in an imdemnity plan where they could go to any provider they chose. So the finest health care system we had years ago is slowly deteriorating.</p>
        <p>Q. How competent are the primary care physicians to handle problems that used to be handled by specialists?</p>
        <p>A. In many instances, the primary care physician doesn't know what he's talking about. That's why specialists developed in this country, because they are more qualified to treat specific conditions of podiatry.</p>
        <p>Q. Are all of your members in H.M.O.'s?</p>
        <p>A. No, about 20 to 30 percent were not taken in to any H.M.O. So the patient who was seeing a doctor regularly in the past can't continue to go to him.</p>
        <p>Q. Why were some podiatrists excluded from H.M.O. panels?</p>
        <p>A. One of the ways H.M.O.'s keep costs down is to limit the number of doctors in the panel. So it becomes more difficult to see a doctor.</p>
        <p>Q. How do the H.M.O.'s go about determining which doctors to accept in their panel? Is it based on the quality of the physician?</p>
        <p>A. That's what they would like you to believe. They have certain criteria that really don't hold water. You may be a great doctor but not meet their criteria. There may be somebody who is a poor doctor who meets the criteria..</p>
        <p>Q. If there is a gatekeeper handling referrals, why not add all specialists to the panel?</p>
        <p>A. By limiting the number of specialists, those in the H.M.O. will become very busy and you may have to wait two months to see a doctor. In that way the H.M.O.'s are limiting the number of patients who can come into the office. And they have established a fee that in most cases is less than what the specialist was accepting before. The doctor accepts it because he is afraid he will lose patients.</p>
        <p>Q. What about patients who do not belong to an H.M.O.?</p>
        <p>A. Somebody was telling me yesterday that he called his internist to make an appointment. The nurse said the doctor couldn't see him for a month. When he told her that he was a paying patient who did not belong to an H.M.O., she said, ''When would you like to come in, this morning or this afternoon?''</p>
        <p>Q. What is the difference between what the H.M.O. will pay the doctor and his normal fee?</p>
        <p>A. Fifty percent.</p>
        <p>Q. Of podiatrists in H.M.O.'s, what percentage of their patients come from primary care physicians?</p>
        <p>A. In New York State, there has been quite a proliferation of H.M.O.'s in the last two years. So I would say that probably 50 or 60 percent of their patients come from H.M.Os.</p>
        <p>Q. What has happened to the practice of some podiatrists?</p>
        <p>A. I've had some members call me and say they used to see 120 patients a week; now they see 20. Some podiatrists are actually going out of practice because they cannot economically make it.</p>
        <p>Q. What percentage of your membership has come to that conclusion?</p>
        <p>A. The 20 percent who are not included in the H.M.O.'s are being forced to drastically curtail their practice or close the door.</p>
        <p>Q. And what about those who are included?</p>
        <p>A. It's happening to the M.D.'s too. I'm not crying for them, but they are having to work harder to maintain the volume that they had before in terms of dollars. Their income has been reduced and they see more patients because of it.</p>
        <p>Q. So they have to see twice as many patients because the reimbursement rate is cut in half?</p>
        <p>A. More or less.</p>
        <p>Q. Are the H.M.O.'s saying there are too many podiatrists out there and this is a way to weed them out?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, and many other specialists are in the same position.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there something wrong with that?</p>
        <p>A. In a number of years from now, I don't know how many, there are not going to be that many specialists and we're just going to rotate back to where we were before and there won't be anybody here to properly use the diagnostic machines.</p>
        <p>Q. How did the union idea come about?</p>
        <p>A. In the United States we have the American Podiatric Medical Association, which is the umbrella organization, and each state has its own chapters. Each decided individually whether it would join the union. It's not really a union, it's a guild. So far 17 states have signed up.</p>
        <p>Q. What are you hoping the union will do for you?</p>
        <p>A. We're looking for the union to help us legislatively to correct some of the problems that have occurred.</p>
        <p>Q. The association could have hired lobbyists, why was the guild necessary?</p>
        <p>A. We have our own lobbyists, of course, but our union lobbyist represents us in New York State, the A.F.L.-C.I.O. union lobbyist represents 2.5 million members, plus their families. So politically they represent a large number of voters.</p>
        <p>Q. How has Medicare been affected?</p>
        <p>A. It has contracted with some H.M.O.'s to allow them to sign up Medicare patients. It's become a contest with some of the H.M.O.'s to see how fast they can sign up Medicare patients. So they have breakfasts for Medicare beneficiaries and explain to them that if they sign up with them, there won't be any out-of-pocket expenses for them. Now, if a doctor were to tell a Medicare patient you don't have to pay me the co-insurance and deductible, they could go to jail. But with these H.M.O.'s, they are forgoing the co-insurance and the deductible. So now the same thing happens in which the patient cannot see the doctor that he has seen for years.</p>
        <p>Q. Have there been cases in which a patient has suffered needlessly because he was not referred to a podiatrist?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, we had instances in which the primary care physician has prescribed antibiotics for severe infections in the toe when the patient really needed a surgical correction. Only after playing with it for a couple of visits and getting nowhere is the patient sent out. And you've heard stories like the one in California where a patient who had cancer was not referred out until it was too late. It doesn't happen every day, but patients are not being referred because the primary care physician has an incentive not to refer him.</p>
        <p>Long Island Q&amp;A: Hiram Chirel</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
