<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Measure Of Disparities: Poor Sanitation In Internet Era</title>
    <meta content="Y12SUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sanitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldwatch Institute</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DC1630F931A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Measure Of Disparities: Poor Sanitation In Internet Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Worldwatch Institute says more people worldwide are getting telephones and access to Internet while increasing number remain without basic household sanitation; says 'sanitation gap' has become greatest risk to public health in many countries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Around the world, more people are getting telephones and access to the Internet while at the same time an increasing number are without basic household sanitation -- toilets, or even simple latrines -- according to a new report.</p>
        <p>The report, ''Vital Signs 1998,'' was published on Saturday by the independent Worldwatch Institute, a Washington environmental group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Around the world, more people are getting telephones and access to the Internet while at the same time an increasing number are without basic household sanitation -- toilets, or even simple latrines -- according to a new report.</p>
        <p>The report, ''Vital Signs 1998,'' was published on Saturday by the independent Worldwatch Institute, a Washington environmental group.</p>
        <p>It is the latest in a series of annual surveys pulling together a wide range of disparate indicators -- crop yields, climate changes, medical advances and retreats, military expenditures or the production figures for bicycles compared with cars -- to spot new trends.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of important trends that never get reported,'' said Lester Brown, who originated the survey in 1992. It is now published in 21 languages.</p>
        <p>Looking at sanitation, an important factor in health crises in poor nations, the 1998 ''Vital Signs'' concluded that the ''sanitation gap'' has become the greatest risk to public health in some countries. Using the latest available World Health Organization figures, the report says the number without facilities in the developing world increased by 274 million in the first half of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>''In some countries,'' the report reads, ''less than half the population is adequately covered.'' These include Afghanistan, Brazil, Cambodia, China, Congo, Egypt, Haiti, India and Senegal. The report notes, however, that some countries, like Brazil, have more exacting definitions of basic sanitation than others, so the statistics are not completely comparable.</p>
        <p>On telecommunications the numbers are firmer and more recent. They indicate ''tumultuous changes,'' the report said. International Telecommunications Union statistics show that more than 200 million telephone lines were installed worldwide from 1990 to 1996, bringing total telephone lines to 741 million. In 1960 there were 89 million.</p>
        <p>Some countries have leapfrogged over the use of traditional telephones into the wireless era, the report found. In Cambodia, one of the world's poorest nations, where a national network of telephone cables is considered a long way away, 60 percent of telephone subscribers use cellular phones.</p>
        <p>Worldwide, cellular phone users have increased an average of 52 percent a year since 1991, with 135 million users by 1996. This trend accentuates the differences between the rich and the poor in many under developed nations with poor communications networks.</p>
        <p>As for the Internet, its use has grown ''exponentially,'' the report shows. Most of the users are still in industrial countries. Of the estimated 107 million people on line, about 62 million are in the United States and 20 million in Europe.</p>
        <p>But the Internet has been harnessed to public services in a number of small, poor countries, the report found. It mentions human rights work by the Kuna indigenous people in Panama, agricultural marketing by cooperatives in Peru and shared medical expertise for countries like Uganda and Bhutan.</p>
        <p>''With 500 million people -- 8 percent of humanity -- projected to be on line by 2001,'' the report reads, ''we can barely guess how the Internet phenomenon will shape the 21st century.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
