<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="12PATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016423"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tocca (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oudejans, Marie-Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Constance C R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4D61F31F931A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance C. R. White</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">White, Constance C R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patterns column on Tocca, little company that revolutionized dress market with its 1950's vintage-style sun dresses, will continue despite departure of its designer and founder, Marie-Anne Oudejans (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Oudejans Surprise</p>
        <p>Tocca, the little company that revolutionized the dress market with its 1950's vintage-style sun dresses, will continue despite the departure of its designer and founder, Marie-Anne Oudejans.</p>
        <p>Eduardo Mantelli, the president of the company, said yesterday that he was searching for a creative team to replace Ms. Oudejans, who left abruptly two weeks ago. She could not be reached for comment, and Mr. Mantelli said he could give no reason for her departure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Oudejans Surprise</p>
        <p>Tocca, the little company that revolutionized the dress market with its 1950's vintage-style sun dresses, will continue despite the departure of its designer and founder, Marie-Anne Oudejans.</p>
        <p>Eduardo Mantelli, the president of the company, said yesterday that he was searching for a creative team to replace Ms. Oudejans, who left abruptly two weeks ago. She could not be reached for comment, and Mr. Mantelli said he could give no reason for her departure.</p>
        <p>He and Gordon Finkelstein will continue to run the company, which they own with Ms. Oudejans. Mr. Mantelli would not say if they planned to buy her out. ''We are in the process of restructuring,'' Mr. Mantelli said. ''Even though Marie-Anne was the creative force behind the label, the label was a team.''</p>
        <p>Tocca has a store in SoHo and stores in Japan. It had recently started home and cosmetics collections. Ms. Oudejans, formerly a stylist, had attracted a glamorous following for her Tocca collection, which included the models Naomi Campbell and Helena Christensen and young socialites. Her dresses and sportswear are sold in Bergdorf Goodman and Saks Fifth Avenue.</p>
        <p>Another Fashion Sendup</p>
        <p>In the last two years, the VH1 Fashion Awards has moved from expendable curiosity to heavyweight pop-cultural event. The latest evidence of the success of the network's growing emphasis on fashion is the news that the parody of a model named Derek Zoolander, which was created by the actor Ben Stiller for the 1996 VH1 Awards, is to be made into a feature-length film.</p>
        <p>The parody, which deals with male supermodels and their work habits, filled the audience of celebrities and fashion insiders with laughter. Then came the success of the film ''Austin Powers,'' another sendup of a fashion power broker, and Hollywood saw the potential in Derek Zoolander.</p>
        <p>Gabe Doppelt, the creative director of fashion programming for VH1 and the VH1 Fashion Awards, said she could not comment on the Stiller deal, to be produced with a major studio. ''We're in heated discussions about this film,'' she said. ''It's the sincerest form of flattery and it will obviously leave plenty of room for fashion cameos.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiller will reprise his Mr. Zoolander character at this year's VH1 awards, on Oct. 23 in New York. ''We'll continue to have moments when we do parody, like when Jim Carey comes out wearing a fig leaf -- of his very own design,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Doppelt was more forthcoming about VH1's own production features on Naomi Campbell, shot by Douglas Keeve in South Africa, where Ms. Campbell staged a fashion show with Donatalla Versace earlier this year, and on Calvin Klein. Both one-hour features are to be shown the week of July 14 as part of VH1's ''Fashion Kingdom'' series.</p>
        <p>A Sisley in SoHo</p>
        <p>The malling of SoHo grows ever more complete with Benetton scheduled to open a Sisley store there during the week of June 23. The addition of the store at 469 West Broadway (Prince Street) will be only the third Sisley store in the United States. But there are 1,100 worldwide, though that number still seems small next to Benetton's 4,000 boutiques globally.</p>
        <p>The Sisley store in SoHo, which replaces a boutique that closed earlier this year at 53d Street and Fifth Avenue, will carry men's and women's clothing and accessories. Sisley's prices are on a par with those of Benetton -- about $20 for a T-shirt to $300 for a chiffon dress -- but more fashion is delivered with each dollar.</p>
        <p>Benetton executives believe a SoHo location is more in keeping with the Sisley image. ''There's been such a resurgence in SoHo,'' Nathalie Moore, a spokeswoman for Benetton's Sisley collection, said. ''The design, the direction of Sisley is more cutting edge. It's definitely for a SoHo market.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
