<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Approves City's Foster Care Efforts</title>
    <meta content="12CHIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Robert J (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4D91630F931A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Approves City's Foster Care Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal District Court Judge Robert J Ward rules that New York City's child welfare agency had made diligent efforts to resolve severe bed shortage that had left more than 2,000 foster children sleeping in city offices over last year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal District Court judge ruled yesterday that New York City's child welfare agency had made diligent efforts to resolve a severe bed shortage that had left more than 2,000 foster children sleeping in city offices over the last year.</p>
        <p>The ruling by the judge, Robert J. Ward of United States District Court in Manhattan, was a victory for the city, which has struggled for more than a year to find beds for the flood of teen-agers and large groups of brothers and sisters pouring into the child welfare system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal District Court judge ruled yesterday that New York City's child welfare agency had made diligent efforts to resolve a severe bed shortage that had left more than 2,000 foster children sleeping in city offices over the last year.</p>
        <p>The ruling by the judge, Robert J. Ward of United States District Court in Manhattan, was a victory for the city, which has struggled for more than a year to find beds for the flood of teen-agers and large groups of brothers and sisters pouring into the child welfare system.</p>
        <p>Advocates for foster children, contending that the city had failed to do enough to properly house the abused and neglected children, had urged Judge Ward to hold the city in contempt. But he refused.</p>
        <p>City officials convinced the judge that they had worked to resolve the problem, allocating about $15 million to expand the foster care system by adding hundreds of beds at group homes and foster homes, and by commissioning a study to determine what places or other agencies the children were coming from.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Scoppetta, who heads the Administration for Children's Services, applauded the judge's decision.</p>
        <p>''It's an affirmation that the court appreciated the extraordinary efforts that A.C.S. has made to solve our problems,'' Mr. Scoppetta said yesterday.</p>
        <p>But despite the city's efforts, dozens of children still sleep on cots in city offices every week because the city has no place for them to go.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow, in another stopgap measure, the city is to begin sending some abused and neglected teen-agers to Covenant House, a shelter for runaways in Manhattan, where 40 beds have been reserved for adolescent foster children, city officials said. The city already houses teen-agers in a shelter in Brooklyn run by a group called Urban Strategies.</p>
        <p>City officials said the use of the shelters was temporary, but the growing reliance on them is another indication that the city has yet to find a permanent solution to the severe shortage of foster care beds.</p>
        <p>In July, child welfare officials promised Judge Ward that they would make their best effort to end overnight stays by foster children in city offices by Nov. 1. But they failed to meet that deadline, and the number of overnight stays have soared since then.</p>
        <p>Judge Ward said he would continue to monitor the city's efforts. And city officials are required to continue to report on their progress to Children's Rights, an advocacy group that sought to hold the city in contempt of the court's order.</p>
        <p>Marcia Robinson Lowry, executive director of Children's Rights, said she was disappointed by the judge's decision. ''They convinced the judge that their efforts were adequate,'' said Ms. Lowry of the city's child welfare officials. ''We don't think it was.''</p>
        <p>In hearings before Judge Ward last week, city officials acknowledged that finding permanent beds had proved to be more difficult than they had expected. But William Bell, a deputy commissioner who testified last week, said his agency would continue to devote its resources to keep children from sleeping in city offices.</p>
        <p>''Ending multiple overnight stays is one of the highest priorities of this agency,'' Mr. Bell said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
