<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Child Disappears: What's the Real Story?</title>
    <meta content="12KAKU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1016422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Price, Richard</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Freedomland (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D61F31F931A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Child Disappears: What's the Real Story?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Richard Price novel Freedomland; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FREEDOMLAND  By Richard Price  546 pages. Broadway Books. $25.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, Tom Wolfe created a small literary storm when he declared that recent novelists had failed to grapple with the convulsive reality of contemporary America and that they needed to ''head out into this wild, bizarre, unpredictable, Hog-stomping Baroque country of ours and reclaim it as literary property.'' He was wrong then, ignoring a myriad of novels by the likes of Robert Stone, John Updike, Don DeLillo, Russell Banks and a host of others. And he is even more wrong today, as Richard Price's gripping new novel ''Freedomland'' so eloquently attests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FREEDOMLAND  By Richard Price  546 pages. Broadway Books. $25.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, Tom Wolfe created a small literary storm when he declared that recent novelists had failed to grapple with the convulsive reality of contemporary America and that they needed to ''head out into this wild, bizarre, unpredictable, Hog-stomping Baroque country of ours and reclaim it as literary property.'' He was wrong then, ignoring a myriad of novels by the likes of Robert Stone, John Updike, Don DeLillo, Russell Banks and a host of others. And he is even more wrong today, as Richard Price's gripping new novel ''Freedomland'' so eloquently attests.</p>
        <p>Since his first novel, ''The Wanderers,'' appeared back in 1974, Mr. Price has been practicing his own tough, gritty brand of social realism, specializing in urban portraits that are as unsentimental as they are capacious. With ''Freedomland'' -- which is set in the same fictional New Jersey milieu as his last novel, ''Clockers'' -- he has given us a big, cinemascope thriller, a novel that captures the racial politics and media madness of the Age of O. J., a novel that transforms today's headlines into a forceful, harrowing drama.</p>
        <p>''Freedomland'' has the social detail (though none of the lugubriousness) of a Zola novel, the jazzy, synesthetic rhythms of a Scorsese film, the slangy street moxie of a Mamet play and the dark, sardonic humor of Wilder's classic ''Ace in the Hole.'' Besides that, it's a terrific read.</p>
        <p>The basic premise of ''Freedomland'' will immediately remind the reader of two high-profile news stories: Susan V. Smith's phony 1994 assertion that her two sons had been abducted by a black carjacker, and Charles Stuart's phony 1989 assertion that his pregnant wife had been killed by a black assailant.</p>
        <p>In the case of ''Freedomland,'' a young white woman named Brenda Martin tells the police that she has been carjacked by a black man who drove off with her 4-year-old son, Cody, in the back seat. Her allegation immediately sets off a heated manhunt in a black housing project, which in turn sets off charges of racism and police brutality.</p>
        <p>While this may sound like so much fodder for a television movie of the week, Mr. Price has not cobbled together a topical potboiler; he has used his keen novelistic eye to conjure up a richly textured world while using his tactical skills as a screenwriter (''The Color of Money,'' ''Ransom,'' ''Mad Dog and Glory'') to create a fast-paced, tension-filled story that reads like a movie in prose. One keeps on reading less to find out whether Brenda is lying or not, than to find out what consequences her allegations will have for everyone around her. As he did in ''Clockers,'' Mr. Price cuts back and forth between the points of view of two central characters: in this novel, Detective Lorenzo Council, a big-hearted, effusive man, known as Big Daddy around the projects for his tireless, avuncular presence (and suffering, as Strike did in ''Clockers,'' from a physical ailment that points up his vulnerability and limitations), and Jesse Haus, a scrappy young reporter who lives off the police scanner, eager ''to witness, to absorb, to taste human behavior in extremis.''</p>
        <p>Both Jesse and Lorenzo, of course, are determined to chase down Brenda's story and find her son, dead or alive. But while their mutual quest for the truth makes them allies of sorts, they are motivated by very different ends: Jesse wants to beat out the competition, to get the scoop of her life; Lorenzo wants to keep a lid on the racial tinderbox that is threatening to explode around him. Both of them will also discover that the Brenda Martin case has an acutely personal meaning for them, that it will stir up emotions they thought they had long suppressed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Price uses the stories of Lorenzo and Jesse to give the reader a wonderfully vivid insider's view of the methods used by police and reporters, and to explore both their own psychology and the psychology they practice on others. His narrative is also peppered with the sort of small, telling details that make palpable the nervous arc of a crime investigation and the media storm that so often follows, delineating the frightening, snowballing rush of incident and outrage that unfurls, willy nilly, after Brenda's charges, enough fodder ''for a dozen more marches, charges, countercharges, commissions, investigations, indictments, headlines, midnight negotiations and political swap meets.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Price shows us the roiling anger in the black housing project of Armstrong, as white police officers sweep through its streets in search of Brenda's carjacker. He shows us Lorenzo's increasingly fevered efforts to contain the emotions of cops and agitators alike. He shows us the incendiary posturing of local politicians and militants as they try to exploit their constituents' anger for their own ends. And he shows us the increasingly frenzied efforts of Jesse and other members of the press to cover the accelerating story, and their own contributions to the ensuing mayhem.</p>
        <p>Along the way, Mr. Price tosses off lots of sharp, hard-edged cameos that leave us with the sense that we know this community firsthand, that we know its troublemakers and peaceniks, its local eccentrics and hotheads, from Hootie Charles, a carjacker who has switched over to lawn furniture scams, to Millrose Carter, a Vietnam veteran known as ''the Man Who Never Sleeps,'' from the Rev. Henry Longway, a local demagogue who's constantly organizing protests and marches, to Paul Rosenbaum, a lawyer known for championing ''the desperate, the technically guilty, the occasionally framed, the submoronic, the psychopathic.''</p>
        <p>By the end of this novel, the reader has not only been thoroughly immersed in the story of Brenda Martin's missing child and the fallout of her allegations, but initiated, as well, into the history of this fictional New Jersey community and its legacy of crime and grief and rage. Though there is a slight falling off at the end, a toying with sentimentality in the book's final pages, it's clear that with ''Freedomland,'' Mr. Price has written his most powerful novel yet, a novel that in wrestling with what Tom Wolfe calls the ''rude beast'' of millennial America, holds up a dark mirror to our times.  BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
