<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show of Work Resembling Items at Hand</title>
    <meta content="15ART.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1002396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DF1330F936A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show of Work Resembling Items at Hand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews art exhibit titled Alternative Measures at Castle Gallery of College of New Rochelle; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ART made of nontraditional materials is nothing new; it is a staple of the 20th century. But those materials are always new, always being updated, and that is why the genre does not wear out. At the College of New Rochelle's Castle Gallery, ''Alternative Measures'' presents a lively and varied selection of recent manifestations.</p>
        <p>Some of the work is deliberately minor, the equivalent of a one-liner. Peter Boynton's ''Cheese Doodle Bonsai'' is in this vein. Even though its bright orange is the opposite of green, the elongated snack food bears a resemblance to the foliage of the diminutive plant, which is often thought to be fake even in its real state. Placed near the show's entrance, the work puts viewers on notice that some beloved brand names will be pressed into service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ART made of nontraditional materials is nothing new; it is a staple of the 20th century. But those materials are always new, always being updated, and that is why the genre does not wear out. At the College of New Rochelle's Castle Gallery, ''Alternative Measures'' presents a lively and varied selection of recent manifestations.</p>
        <p>Some of the work is deliberately minor, the equivalent of a one-liner. Peter Boynton's ''Cheese Doodle Bonsai'' is in this vein. Even though its bright orange is the opposite of green, the elongated snack food bears a resemblance to the foliage of the diminutive plant, which is often thought to be fake even in its real state. Placed near the show's entrance, the work puts viewers on notice that some beloved brand names will be pressed into service.</p>
        <p>Another is M&amp;M's. Martha Benzing's list of the media that go into her painting includes Kool-Aid and the candies themselves. The stain made by the candies when they melt is apparently what Ms. Benzing calls M&amp;M pigment. Another of Ms. Benzing's paintings is a dark diptych in which the candy and its traces resemble a forest of eyes. The other work is more festive. In shades of yellow and orange, it recalls an Impressionist's field of spring flowers.</p>
        <p>A related piece is ''Stained Event'' by Curtis Mitchell, who has his own use for Kool-Aid. He has taken a carpet (its fringed ends are still visible) and coated it with a mixture that includes Kool-Aid and floor varnish. The result, hanging on the wall and marked by fissures, recalls ''process'' painting from the 1970's. The unusual steps that went into such a painting's realization are its subject, but in its day process art was never as blithe or droll as Mr. Mitchell's.</p>
        <p>Larry Mantello is another of those latter-day Pop artists. ''Sister Sity'' is a wall piece made of pop-up greeting cards. The energetic Betty Boop and the languid Miss Piggy are two of the cartoon stars who appear frequently. He also translates his busy yet homey esthetic into a floor piece. ''Auto-Retire'' employs Garfield, the cartoon cat, several times along with heart-shaped pillows, which say, ''I Love Mother,'' and an assortment of slogan-bearing rulers and pencils. If  his aim is to make the viewer giddily dizzy, he succeeds.</p>
        <p>Another group of artists is more reflective and abstract. Seong Chun crochets words from Plato and the novelist Iris Murdoch, which have been printed on paper strips. In her catalogue essay, the exhibition's curator, Susan M. Canning, says that since crocheting is a reflective process, Ms. Chun is merging her thoughts with those of the writers whose texts she uses.</p>
        <p>In a similar potentially profound vein, Hiram A. Rodriguez-Mora makes abstract drawings out of paper and thread. Oliver Herring also engages in a rote-reflective process when he knits plastic shopping bags into a striped afghan.</p>
        <p>There is some surprise in seeing men whole-heartedly engage in what is traditionally woman's work, but there is also some reassurance in seeing that women continue to do it. Using gauzy fabrics, Ava Gerber realizes fetchingly ungainly works: ''Dowry II,'' which resembles a large geometric abstract painting, full of pale squares and rectangles, and ''Hoopa,'' which is more of a sculpture. This free-form wedding canopy is decorated with artificial flowers.</p>
        <p>Polly Apfelbaum has long made velvet her own. The site-specific ''Ground Cover'' consists of many velvet rectangles, colored by dyes, arranged in a corner of the gallery in a way that calls attention to the odd dimensions of the corner.</p>
        <p>Sheer fabric is a major material for Nancy B. Davidson. But it is adornment for her primary ingredient, a fat, white latex weather balloon with cords strategically wrapped around it to produce curves and folds reminiscent of body parts, Mae West's body parts. Ms. Davidson takes photographs of portions of her sculptures, cropping them in ways that emphasize their erotic potential, as if that were necessary.</p>
        <p>Another artist who uses the human body as his point of departure is Willie Cole, a wizard with high-heel shoes. Mr. Cole arranges the footwear so that the long heels become the fangs of feral animals, and shoes in profile become elongated eyes.</p>
        <p>Through cutting and twisting discarded bicycle tires, Chakaia Booker creates unnerving, richly allusive sculptures. A wall piece resembles a nest of black snakes or eels, while a work on the floor is like a cross-section of a human heart.</p>
        <p>Jessica Stockholder's intention is to elevate utilitarian items to art. Her garish assemblage, ''Shoulder Length,'' is named for the yarn that hangs off purple plastic milk crates holding plastic lemons. Tony Feher  tries a similar transformation by stacking polystyrene protective panels into a rough pyramid shape. From a clothesline, he hangs plastic bottles partly filled with water dyed blue. These pieces reflect an impulse to make art out of what is at hand, even though the results may necessarily be awkward.</p>
        <p>The last word should be given to Mr. Boynton, who also had the first word. His second sculpture is vastly different from the caprice of his bonsai. It is a wire-grid construction full of curves, which seem perfect -- as if plotted on a computer. From the multitude of wire squares in it hang clusters of beads. The work is titled ''A Million Cups of Coffee'' and is a statement about the labor-intensive nature of a typical work fashioned from alternative material.</p>
        <p>''Alternative Measures'' is at the Castle Gallery of the College of New Rochelle through April 5. The number to call for information is 654-5427.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
