<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Keeps Murdoch And His TV On Hiatus</title>
    <meta content="15MURD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1002190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hong Kong</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Star TV</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phoenix Satellite Television Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">News Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faison, Seth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DF1439F936A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Keeps Murdoch And His TV On Hiatus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH FAISON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Faison, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, March 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>China continues to keep its media market closed to Rupert Murdoch even though he has curried favor when Chinese leadership for 10 years; Murdoch has invested over $1 billion in Star TV, Asian satellite television network that is intended to be New Corp's route to China, but winning approval to broadcast, collecting subscriptions fees and selling advertising are proving difficult; New Corp points to Star TV's partial ownership of Phoenix Satellite Television Co of Hong Kong as an important is modest sign of progress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the paradoxes of Rupert Murdoch's bend-over-backward efforts to keep good relations with China is that he has been so badly frustrated here.</p>
        <p>China's media market is still so tightly closed to foreign companies, and the authorities are so suspicious of international media companies like Mr. Murdoch's News Corporation, that 10 years of wooing and genuflection has yielded almost nothing so far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the paradoxes of Rupert Murdoch's bend-over-backward efforts to keep good relations with China is that he has been so badly frustrated here.</p>
        <p>China's media market is still so tightly closed to foreign companies, and the authorities are so suspicious of international media companies like Mr. Murdoch's News Corporation, that 10 years of wooing and genuflection has yielded almost nothing so far.</p>
        <p>The recent embarrassment to the News Corporation's book unit, HarperCollins -- which apologized to the former Hong Kong Governor, Chris Patten, after dropping his book for its anti-China content -- might have an economic rationale if there was a heavy payoff in China's market to compensate. Yet media executives and consultants say profitability in China is so far in the future that no one can predict when it will come.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch has put well over $1 billion into a satellite television network called Star TV, which broadcasts in several Asian countries and is intended to be the News Corporation's route into China, where more than 300 million homes have television sets, the world's largest potential market.</p>
        <p>But winning approval to broadcast, collecting subscription fees selling advertising are proving so difficult that media executives measure progress in tiny increments. China's entertainment industry is coming alive, yet business opportunities remain maddeningly elusive to foreign operations.</p>
        <p>News Corporation executives argue that they are taking the long view and that with a small toe in the door, they are ahead of their competitors. ''It's all about position, position, position,'' said Bruce Dover, the company's chief representative in Beijing. ''Our strategy is to be ready for the day when the door opens.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dover pointed to Star TV's partial ownership of a Hong Kong company, the Phoenix Satellite Television Company, as an important if modest sign of progress. The Phoenix channel, with Chinese-language programming, broadcasts decidely cheerful dramatic shows that consultants say will have difficulty winning cable viewers with 40 channels to choose from.</p>
        <p>Limited mostly to viewers in international hotels and to a cable network in a single Chinese city, Guangzhou, Phoenix reaches a tiny segment of China's viewers. Star TV claims that 35 million homes have access to Phoenix, though independent consultants say that is probably optimistic.</p>
        <p>Even worse, Phoenix broadcasts are still technically illegal, since the Ministry of Radio, Film and Television has yet to grant formal approval. Officials are clearly aware of Phoenix's broadcasts, and they are essentially reserving the right to block them at any time. The same is true for Star TV's four channels, which carry music videos, sports, movies and English programs.</p>
        <p>The brightest aspect of Phoenix, consultants say, is that Star TV shares ownership with a Singapore company called Today's Asia and a Hong Kong company called China Wise, which have their own connections to China's television industry. Star TV and Today's Asia each own 45 percent; China Wise owns the remaining 10 percent.</p>
        <p>''China is so tightly controlled that a joint venture like that is quite an achievement,'' said John Wong, of the Boston Consulting Group, who advises media companies in China.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dover said Star TV, which Mr. Murdoch bought for $900 million in 1993, had lost perhaps $100 million a year until last year, when its loss was reduced to $40 million. It will break even in 12 to 18 months, he estimated.</p>
        <p>Advertising revenue for Phoenix, Mr. Dover said, grew to $34 million last year. ''We're quite happy with that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Murdoch has visited China many times, assiduously courting Chinese leaders, he attracted the most notice here in 1993 when he said in a speech in London that technological advances like satellite TV were ''an unambiguous threat to totalitarian regimes everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Alarmed, China's leadership promptly banned individuals from buying satellite dishes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch's efforts to repair ties to Beijing -- by yanking the BBC news service from Star TV's broadcasts, by authorizing a $1 million book contract at HarperCollins for the daughter of Deng Xiaoping, and by reaching a minor Internet deal with The People's Daily -- have yet to win back much encouragement.</p>
        <p>The News Corporation's only other China venture, a television studio in Tianjin, has also been a disappointment, a Star TV executive said. ''It's a waiting game,'' the executive conceded, referring to Mr. Murdoch's plans in China. ''He realizes it's going to be be a long, long trip.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dover, the News Corporation executive, said: ''That problem of control still worries them. But there's an insatiable appetite they have to meet. They need to be more forward-looking.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
