<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Snap Loss Streak As Gatling Scores 24</title>
    <meta content="15NETS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1002280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Mavericks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Dallas Mavericks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D61439F936A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Snap Loss Streak As Gatling Scores 24</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, March 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Nets defeat Dallas Mavericks, 108-93 (M)p</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was only fitting that in the moments after Chris Gatling had helped end the Nets' seven-game losing streak,  while his teammates breathed a sigh of relief, he was in another room having his right shin X-rayed.</p>
        <p>Gatling, who got the chance to step forward thanks in part to the injuries that sidelined Jayson Williams and Keith Van Horn, made it out of the exam healthy by Nets standards: the X-ray was negative, and he had just a bruised shin. And thanks to his 24 points on 8-of-9 shooting, the Nets had posted a 108-93 victory over the Mavericks at Reunion Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was only fitting that in the moments after Chris Gatling had helped end the Nets' seven-game losing streak,  while his teammates breathed a sigh of relief, he was in another room having his right shin X-rayed.</p>
        <p>Gatling, who got the chance to step forward thanks in part to the injuries that sidelined Jayson Williams and Keith Van Horn, made it out of the exam healthy by Nets standards: the X-ray was negative, and he had just a bruised shin. And thanks to his 24 points on 8-of-9 shooting, the Nets had posted a 108-93 victory over the Mavericks at Reunion Arena.</p>
        <p>The victory was the Nets' first since Feb. 26 and allowed them to remain in a tie with the Washington Wizards for the eighth and final playoff berth in the Eastern Conference. Both teams are a half-game behind the Cleveland Cavaliers, who beat the Knicks tonight.</p>
        <p>''It's good to get the monkey off our backs,'' said Gatling, who came to the Nets in a nine-player trade with the Mavericks last season. ''Even though we are short-handed, we still stepped up and did what we had to do down the stretch.''</p>
        <p>Rather than rely on Sam Cassell and Kerry Kittles to carry the offense, the Nets got contributions from Gatling and from Brian Evans, who tied his career high with 16 points on 6-of-9 shooting, including 3 of 4 from 3-point range.</p>
        <p>The Nets broke open a close contest with a 10-0 run, turning an 86-85 deficit into a 95-86 lead with 3 minutes 47 seconds left in the game. Kittles, who scored 11 of his 20 points in the fourth quarter, started it with a long jumper to push the Nets in front. He added a pair of free throws after the former Net Shawn Bradley misfired three times on one possession.</p>
        <p>Gatling then slipped in a follow-up of a Kittles miss under Bradley, drawing a foul on the 7-foot-6-inch center and converting the free throw. Kittles added another free throw when a technical foul was called on Mavericks Coach Don Nelson. Michael Cage capped the run by grabbing a rebound inside of Bradley and dropping in a layup.</p>
        <p>The score belied just how close the game was most of the night, and the beating the Nets took on the boards -- they were outrebounded by 49-32. They also survived numerous mistakes, turning the ball over 23 times.</p>
        <p>''It's nice to break the ice, believe me,'' Nets Coach John Calipari said. ''We needed to get a win to get off the schneid. Every one of these games we've had a chance to win and we lose them all, so this game became so vital, it was almost out of proportion with what it should have been.''</p>
        <p>With the Nets headed to Chicago, and Orlando and Indiana up after that, the fear of the losing streak growing even longer was very real.</p>
        <p>''It went down the same way as the other games, except we pulled away at the end,'' Kendall Gill said. ''I still don't see how they beat the Bulls.'' The Mavericks were coming off an overtime victory over Chicago on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The game was a loss for Van Horn before it began. The rookie forward had hoped to return to action after sitting out Thursday night while trying to heal his broken toe. But after working out before the game, he was called into Calipari's office. He came out deflated and said the proper things, that it was a joint decision. But the true story -- that Calipari insisted he rest the injury -- was clearly etched across his face.</p>
        <p>''He is frustrated,'' Calipari said. ''My one suggestion to him as an option was, 'You stay out five weeks, buddy. You've got to think about that.' Then he got upset. I said, 'I'm just telling you because I care about you.' ''</p>
        <p>Van Horn said: ''It's a combination. He has to be happy playing me and I've got to be comfortable playing. I've already dealt with being out of games early in the year. It's just hard. It's probably one of the toughest injuries to deal with because there's not a whole lot you can do for it. You've just got to take it day by day.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>RONY SEIKALY worked out with the team in Friday's practice session and then went through an individual workout with Nets' coaches following Saturday's morning shoot-around. Those are the first organized workouts with the Nets for the 32-year-old center, who has sat out 11 games with what was diagnosed as a bone contusion. Seikaly is eligible to come off the injured list on Monday in Chicago, but he believes that a more realistic return date would be Thursday when the Nets host the Magic. ''Right now, I don't have the confidence to jump up and down on it,'' Seikaly said.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
