<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Says Dow Corning Implant Plan Is Flawed</title>
    <meta content="Y22DOW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Silicone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Class-Action Suits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Implants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spector, Arthur J (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Implants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Polymers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00EFDB133BF931A15752C1A961958260" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Says Dow Corning Implant Plan Is Flawed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Bankruptcy Court Judge Arthur Spector rules there are numerous flaws in Dow Corning Corp's proposals for disposing of breast implant damage claims; says it would be 'monumental waste of time' for claimants and other creditors to vote on bankrupycy reorganization plan containing the proposals; also says proposals leave Dow Corning with too much control over trust fund that company would set up to distribute up to $2.4 billion to breast implant claimants; Dow Corning says it will continue to negotiate on all of issues court has pointed out (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal bankruptcy judge has ruled that there are numerous legal flaws in the Dow Corning Corporation's proposals for disposing of breast implant damage claims. As a result, the judge said, it would be a ''monumental waste of time'' for the claimants and other creditors to vote on a bankruptcy reorganization plan containing the proposals.</p>
        <p>The ruling by Judge Arthur Spector came late Thursday after four days of hearings. The judge told lawyers in his Bay City, Mich., courtroom that it would be a ''fantasy'' to believe that, as the proposals suggested, he might approve the Dow Corning reorganization plan even if it was voted down by the claimants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal bankruptcy judge has ruled that there are numerous legal flaws in the Dow Corning Corporation's proposals for disposing of breast implant damage claims. As a result, the judge said, it would be a ''monumental waste of time'' for the claimants and other creditors to vote on a bankruptcy reorganization plan containing the proposals.</p>
        <p>The ruling by Judge Arthur Spector came late Thursday after four days of hearings. The judge told lawyers in his Bay City, Mich., courtroom that it would be a ''fantasy'' to believe that, as the proposals suggested, he might approve the Dow Corning reorganization plan even if it was voted down by the claimants.</p>
        <p>Judge Spector said the plan did not provide fair treatment to overseas claimants, who would receive less compensation for similar injuries. He also said the plan put unfair pressure on women to vote in favor because it specified that those who opposed it would not have the same access to compensation.</p>
        <p>In addition, Judge Spector said, the proposal left Dow Corning with too much control over a trust fund that the company would set up to distribute up to $2.4 billion to breast implant claimants. And he objected to the wording of a section that would have barred anyone from pursuing related claims that have been filed against the Dow Chemical Company. Dow Chemical owns 50 percent of Dow Corning in a joint venture with Corning Inc.</p>
        <p>''This is really good news,'' said Kenneth Eckstein, a lawyer for the claimants. ''It sends a strong signal that the company has to go back to the bargaining table with us.''</p>
        <p>Dow Corning, which is based in Midland, Mich., and was once the nation's largest manufacturer of the silicone implants, has been operating under bankruptcy protection for two and a half years while it sought a comprehensive formula for disposing of what could be hundreds of thousands of implant lawsuits.</p>
        <p>The company argues, with growing support in research circles, that although silicone implants may cause limited physical injury, there is no reliable evidence that leaking silicone from ruptured implants causes serious immune system diseases that claimants attribute to it.</p>
        <p>Dow Corning said today that it would continue to negotiate on all of the issues Judge Spector pointed out.</p>
        <p>More than 400,000 women have filed claims. Their advocates say the trust fund would be inadequate, with the actual value in current dollars as low as $500 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
