<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seoul Plans to Ask the I.M.F. For a Minimum of $20 Billion</title>
    <meta content="22RESC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lim Chang Yuel (Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D7133BF931A15752C1A961958260" item-length="1433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seoul Plans to Ask the I.M.F. For a Minimum of $20 Billion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South Korea, one of most glittering economic success stories of late 20th century, says it will seek bailout from International Monetary Fund to avert financial crisis; many economists say package of assistance may have to exceed $60 billion; Finance Min Lim Chang Yuel says South Korea will seek $20 billion in IMF loans, plus additional open line of credit in case amount is insufficient; transformation of South Korea from industrial giant to international pauper suggests that Asian financial ills that began in Thailand in summer and spread throughout Southeast Asia have now begun to spread in Northeast Asia; reckless lending by South Korean banks blamed in part for current crisis; country's plummeting currency and mounting bad debts may reverberate on to America and West; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a remarkable humiliation for one of the most glittering economic success stories of the late 20th century, South Korea announced tonight that to avert a financial crisis it would seek a bailout from the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>The amount will be negotiated in coming days, but many economists say the package of assistance will have to be enormous, perhaps exceeding $60 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a remarkable humiliation for one of the most glittering economic success stories of the late 20th century, South Korea announced tonight that to avert a financial crisis it would seek a bailout from the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>The amount will be negotiated in coming days, but many economists say the package of assistance will have to be enormous, perhaps exceeding $60 billion.</p>
        <p>That would easily surpass the previous record of $48 billion in I.M.F. aid committed to Mexico nearly three years ago. Mexico ultimately used about half of that amount.</p>
        <p>The vulnerability of Japan in particular to the South Korean mess has become a major preoccupation for American monetary officials, who are now viewing Asia's growing economic crisis as a more urgent threat to United States interests because previous I.M.F. efforts to contain it have failed. [Analysis, page D1.]</p>
        <p>Finance Minister Lim Chang Yuel told a late-night news conference that South Korea would seek $20 billion in I.M.F. loans, plus an additional open line of credit in case that amount was insufficient. Mr. Lim also said he expected the United States and Japan, which had rebuffed requests in recent days to provide direct aid to South Korea, to participate in an I.M.F.-led rescue.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Lim's bleak announcement, South Korea became the latest in a string of Asian nations to redefine the term ''Asian miracle.'' Once it referred to the stunning march of East Asia from mud huts to skyscrapers in a single generation, but now it seems more a reminder of how far and how quickly these countries' economies and currencies and stock markets have tumbled.</p>
        <p>In particular, the transformation of South Korea from industrial giant to international pauper suggests that the Asian financial flu that began in Thailand in the summer and spread throughout Southeast Asia has now begun to spread in Northeast Asia. South Korea's plummeting currency and mounting bad debts may reverberate on to America and the West.</p>
        <p>It was just a week ago that South Korea called the idea of I.M.F. aid unthinkable. The Government agonized over the choices, changing its mind several times before making the final decision tonight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lim described South Korea's problems as a ''temporary funding shortage'' but said international help was the best solution.</p>
        <p>''To overcome the nation's financial and currency crises, we've decided to request emergency funding from the I.M.F.,'' he declared.</p>
        <p>''Although Korea's fundamental macro-economic conditions are relatively healthy, with rising exports, a string of corporate bankruptcies have decreased Korea's creditworthiness and produced calls for debt repayments,'' Mr. Lim said. He said of the decision to turn to the I.M.F.: ''The Korean Government hopes that this measure will bear fruit.''</p>
        <p>The money is likely to be used primarily to help distressed banks repay debts they owe, giving them a chance to rework an estimated $50 billion in unrepaid loans owed to them. Reversing the process of defaults is critical to restoring confidence, which will help ease the crisis further by encouraging the return of foreign investors who have been abandoning South Korea.</p>
        <p>But the I.M.F. aid will undoubtedly come at a painful price for South Korea by making the rules for borrowing money more stringent. That could have the immediate impact of increasing interest rates and forcing some companies out of business and raising unemployment for South Koreans, who until recently had barely understood what a layoff meant.</p>
        <p>An I.M.F. delegation group will visit Seoul next week to negotiate the exact size and terms of the rescue, Mr. Lim said, and the money will start arriving in three to four weeks.</p>
        <p>[In a nationally broadcast speech Saturday about the decision, President Kim Young Sam told South Koreans: ''As the head of national affairs, I am truly sorry. Our economy has grown relatively quickly and smoothly, but such rapid development itself has given birth to structural problems.'' He said the country must endure ''bone-carving pain.'']</p>
        <p>Rumors about the prospect that Seoul would turn to the I.M.F. gave a strong lift to Korea's financial markets today. Stocks rose 3.6 percent and the currency, which had plunged for the previous four days, rose sharply as well.</p>
        <p>The news also helped strengthen most other financial markets on optimism that South Korean investments need not be written off.</p>
        <p>[In abbreviated trading on Saturday, South Korean stocks retreated again, falling 4 percent.]</p>
        <p>South Korea suffers from what is known as a liquidity crisis, or a lack of money flowing through the economy, which is causing defaults on corporate loans like falling dominos.</p>
        <p>It descended to this point partly because of reckless lending by South Korean banks -- particularly in other developing markets not only elsewhere in Asia but also in Latin America and Eastern Europe. Billions of dollars in unrepaid loans have forced these banks to borrow from foreign banks that have grown increasingly unwilling to lend more.</p>
        <p>In addition, many of the giant South Korean industrial conglomerates like Kia Motors, Hanbo Group and Sammi Group that helped build the country have fallen, the victims of too much debt.</p>
        <p>The decline in lender and investor confidence in South Korea has been reflected in the diminished value of the won, South Korea's currency, which has fallen by 20 percent against the dollar this year. That has made it even more expensive for South Korea to repay loans.</p>
        <p>Even so, South Korea's economy is still growing at an annual rate of more than 6 percent, considerably faster than the American economy. That is partly because the diminished value of the won has helped the country increase its exports, from computer chips to Hyundai Motor sedans. South Korea also has underlying strengths like a passion for education and a reputation for a diligent labor force.</p>
        <p>In the long run, some economists suggest, I.M.F.-imposed changes to resolve the bad debts and modernize the banking system may be a boon for South Korea. In particular, they  may lead to the establishment of an efficient capital market and banking system, essential if the two Koreas reunified and the South had to rebuild the impoverished North.</p>
        <p>The Korean Government had been loath to turn to the I.M.F., partly because of the stringent conditions the I.M.F. will undoubtedly set, breaching what some South Koreans describe as their economic sovereignty. Indeed, the nation seemed to collectively lament as word of the bailout spread today, bracing for a period of austerity.</p>
        <p>In a prime-time evening news commentary, the MBC television network declared, ''Leaving behind our glorious economic development, our country must suffer the humiliation of going bankrupt.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, the I.M.F. rescue is a stinging humiliation for President Kim, who had been reluctant to admit economic failure before his New Korea Party faces presidential elections on Dec. 18.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim is barred by law from running again, but the ruling-party candidate, Lee Hoi Chang, is already lagging far behind in the polls. The beneficiary from the bailout may be the longtime opposition leader, Kim Dae Jung, who is already leading in the polls by a healthy margin. The business establishment has long been contemptuous of Kim Dae Jung's command of economics, but these days it is equally dismissive of the ruling party's economic management.</p>
        <p>President Kim and Mr. Lim met tonight with the presidential candidates to discuss the decision to turn to the I.M.F. Afterward, the Government said that it had the support and understanding of all the candidates.  Invariably South Korea's economic difficulties also have a security dimension, because North Korea has more than a million troops next door and by some accounts is always sniffing for weakness and an opportunity for military adventure.</p>
        <p>In addition, South Korea and North Korea, which technically remain at war, are now preparing for landmark peace talks that are supposed to reach a lasting peace to replace the armistice that suspended fighting in the Korean War. South Korea would prefer to enter the negotiations at a time when it feels more secure, but instead North Korea is relishing the chance to offer its own analyses of South Korea's problems.</p>
        <p>''There is no way of saving the defective economy that has contradictory structure and cancer of the colonial dependent economy,'' the official North Korean press agency declared today.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
