<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. MATCHUPS: WEEK 10</title>
    <meta content="NFLGR10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="N.F.L. MATCHUPS: WEEK 10" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887035"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L. MATCHUPS: WEEK 10"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1D71E39F932A35752C1A960958260" item-length="1959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. MATCHUPS: WEEK 10</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 P.M. GAMES</p>
        <p>New York Giants (3-5) vs. Arizona (3-5)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Giants offense has the worst third down conversion percentage in the N.F.L. (26.4%). Kent Graham is the No. 2 rated passer in the N.F.C. on third down (107.1), having thrown five TDs and no interceptions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 P.M. GAMES</p>
        <p>New York Giants (3-5) vs. Arizona (3-5)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Giants offense has the worst third down conversion percentage in the N.F.L. (26.4%). Kent Graham is the No. 2 rated passer in the N.F.C. on third down (107.1), having thrown five TDs and no interceptions.</p>
        <p>Comments: Graham and Dave Brown were the understudies to Phil Simms and were supposed to be the 1990s version of Simms and Jeff Hostetler. But Dan Reeves cut that short by waiving Graham last year. Now, Graham has found new life, and success with Arizona. He's anxious to show Reeves the error of his way. With more confidence in the passing game, Reeves has given Brown more weapons to work with. That will help against the Cardinals, who were beaten last week by the Jets. The other New York team will dump the Cardinals this week.</p>
        <p>Game score: New York 25-20.</p>
        <p>Carolina (5-3) vs. Atlanta (0-8)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Panthers defense leads the N.F.L. with 28 sacks. The Falcons defense has just one interception, giving them the worst defensive interception percentage in the league.</p>
        <p>Comments: The Falcons got a wildcard playoff spot last year. However, it's the Panthers, an expansion team last season, who are putting themselves into a wildcard playoff picture this year. Carolina completely dominated the Falcons in the game earlier this season with the defense getting seven sacks and limiting Atlanta to just six points. Atlanta has been playing close games, but losing lately. If they can put together a great effort like they did against Dallas two weeks ago and Pittsburgh last week, they'll down the Panthers. The Falcons are due.</p>
        <p>Game score: Atlanta 23-21.</p>
        <p>Cincinnati (2-6) vs. Baltimore (3-5)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Bengals 23 takeaways leads the A.F.C. Vinny Testaverde's 18 touchdown passes leads the A.F.C.</p>
        <p>Comments: Testaverde has three or more touchdown passes in the last four games, so he has the Ravens offense rolling. With Jeff Blake on the other side this could be a game with footballs filling the air. The Bengals responded to new coach Bruce Coslet last week and pulled off a solid victory against Jacksonville. There should be some carry over this week. Despite Testaverde's solid passing numbers, the Ravens haven't been able to produce more victories. That's because the defense has given up the most points in the league (232). They'll give up a loss to the Bengals.</p>
        <p>Game score: Cincinnati 29-25.</p>
        <p>Detroit (4-4) vs. Green Bay (7-1)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Green Bay's 29 takeaways (22 interceptions) leads the N.F.L. Barry Sanders has averaged 104.6 yards rushing in 13 career games vs. the Packers, but he has been held to under 100 yards in his last six games.</p>
        <p>Comments: The Packers are hurting at wide receiver, after losing Antonio Freeman with a broken arm last week. Quarterback Brett Farve didn't have a touchdown pass last week, breaking a string of 18 games with a passing score. The Packers won't be able to win many games that way, even though their defense is playing extremely well. The Lions are completely confused as to what they're trying to do on offense. The benching of quarterback Scott Mitchell proved that last week. They won't figure it out against the Packers.</p>
        <p>Game score: Green Bay 28-10.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia (6-2) vs. Dallas (5-3)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Ricky Watters leads the N.F.L. in total yards from scrimmage with 936 yards. Dallas has allowed the fewest touchdowns to opponents inside its redzone (six on 20 trips).</p>
        <p>Comments: The Cowboys beat the Eagles on a Monday night in a game that knocked Philadelphia quarterback Rodney Peete out of the season with a torn patella tendon. Peete's replacement, Ty Detmer, has actually done very well. He's shown toughness and he'll need it all to survive the Dallas defense. He has been able pick other teams apart, but he hasn't had to face corners like Deion Sanders and Kevin Smith. The Cowboys are back in synch again. If they can contain Watters and force Detmer into some bad throws, they will win this game.</p>
        <p>Game score: Dallas 23-17.</p>
        <p>St. Louis (2-6) vs. Pittsburgh (6-2)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Eddie Kennison's 20.5 yards per punt return leads the N.F.L. The Steelers are holding opponents to 5.2 yards per punt return, which is the third best in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>Comments: This will be Jerome Bettis' first crack at the Rams since he was traded during the offseason. Think Bettis isn't going to be running hard in this game? There will be some loud explosions coming out of Three Rivers Stadium. The Rams came close to winning last week, but lost in overtime to Baltimore. With the way the Steelers have been playing, St. Louis probably won't get as close as they did to the Ravens.</p>
        <p>Game score: Pittsburgh 24-17.</p>
        <p>San Diego (4-4) vs. Indianapolis (5-3)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Chargers are last in the league in rushing (80.5) and the defense is tied for last in the league in average yards given up per rushing attempt.</p>
        <p>Comments: Chargers coach Bobby Ross actually apologized to San Diego fans last week for the performance of the team at Seattle. They couldn't do anything and lost to a woeful Seahawks team. Ross doesn't want to make this a weekly ritual, so he'll have his team ready to play this week. However, quarterback Stan Humphries, who has a dislocated shoulder, and linebacker Junior Seau (knee injury) are questionable. That will make for rough going in Indianapolis. The Colts can beat a team that's more banged up than they are.</p>
        <p>Game score: Indianapolis 19-14.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay (1-7) vs. Chicago (3-5)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Trent Dilfer's 46.2 completion percentage on third down is the worst among starting quarterbacks in the N.F.L. The Bears have held opponents to just six points in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Comments: The Bucs expect to get more production from running back Errict Rhett this week. If he's up to speed he'll be able to provide Tampa Bay with a much needed threat in the backfield. The Bears are coming off a very big victory over the Vikings on Monday night. Linebacker Bryan Cox wants to play with his broken thumb. His effectiveness will be limited. That could help the Bucs offense attack the middle of the Bears defense. The Bears are a classic up and down team. They're ripe for the Bucs to come in and send them on a down swing.</p>
        <p>Game score: Tampa Bay 14-9.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 4 P.M. GAMES</p>
        <p>Kansas City (5-3) vs. Minnesota (5-3)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Chiefs offensive line has given up one sack in the last three games. The Vikings have the worst average offensive starting field position in the N.F.L. - the 22.6 yard line.</p>
        <p>Comments: Minnesota suffered a major blow when running back Robert Smith injured his knee against the Bears on Monday night and is out for the season. Plus, quarterback Warren Moon reinjured his right ankle. If Moon plays he'll be gimpy. All in all it puts a crimp in the Vikings offensive flow. The Chiefs are coming off a stinging loss to Denver, so they'll be pretty heated up for this game. They have the kind of defense that will feast off a weakened Vikings offense.</p>
        <p>Game score: Kansas City 23-16.</p>
        <p>Houston (5-3) vs. Seattle (3-5)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Michael Sinclair leads the A.F.C. in sacks with nine. Eddie George leads all rookie running backs with 717 yards.</p>
        <p>Comments: The Seahawks pounded San Diego last week, coming up with five turnovers and scoring a season-high 32 points. Quarterback John Friesz has been playing relatively mistake-free football since taking over as starter three weeks ago (just two interceptions) and Chris Warren broke out with 146 yards rushing last week. Oilers quarterback Chris Chandler re-injured his groin muscle and might be replaced by Steve McNair. There's no drop off there. The Oilers are playing with great confidence. They won't play patsy to the Seahawks like the Chargers did last week.</p>
        <p>Game score: Houston 29-17.</p>
        <p>Miami (4-4) vs. New England (5-3)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Punter John Kidd has placed 18 of his 41 punts inside the opponents 20 yard line, which leads the N.F.L. New England's defense has just 14 sacks, which ranks them No. 27 in the league.</p>
        <p>Comments: After a shaky start, the Patriots have climbed back into contention in the A.F.C. East division race and are tied with the Colts and the Bills for first place. They're playing fortuitous football, which means they always seem to be in the right place at the right time. Miami is in the opposite situation right now. They're out of kilter. That might be because Dan Marino, who returned last week from a broken ankle, hasn't been around. He's had another week to get his timing back, but it's not going to make a difference against the Patriots.</p>
        <p>Game score: New England 25-23.</p>
        <p>Washington (7-1) vs. Buffalo (5-3)</p>
        <p>Key stats: The Bills are tied with Seattle for the fewest touchdowns scored (seven) inside the opponents redzone. Washington is the only team in the league to have scored on all its trips (21) into the opponents redzone.</p>
        <p>Comments: There are still several doubters out there who aren't convinced that the Redskins seven game winning streak makes them a legitimate team. If there are any questions about how real the Redskins are Terry Allen answers them when he runs. His 13 rushing TDs leads the N.F.L. and he's putting up Emmitt Smith type numbers. Meanwhile, the Bills are getting by on sheer grit. They lost a tough game to New England last week. They'll be in for another grueling afternoon with Washington. It won't be pretty, but the Redskins will take the win.</p>
        <p>Game score: Washington 28-16.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 8 P.M. GAME</p>
        <p>San Francisco (6-2) vs. New Orleans (2-6)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Niners defense has not allowed a rushing touchdown in 41 quarters. The Saints offensive line has given up just 9 sacks (one per 29.2 pass attempts), which ranks No. 2 in the league.</p>
        <p>Comments: A concussion knocked Steve Young out of the game against Houston last week. But he says he'll be fine for the Saints game. It's just another in a litany of injuries that has plagued Young this year. It hasn't really damaged the Niners chances of winning. They do fine with the backups. This will be Rick Venturi's first game as Saints coach. He replaced Jim Mora who resigned in disgust two weeks ago. Venturi was an interim coach with the Colts back in 1991 (1-10). Unfortunately, he has to go against the Niners with the same disgusting team Mora left. The 49ers will eke out a win.</p>
        <p>Game score: San Francisco 31-10.</p>
        <p>MONDAY 9 P.M. GAME</p>
        <p>Denver (7-1) vs. Oakland (4-4)</p>
        <p>Key stats: Denver is converting 51.3% of its third down opportunities, which is the best in the N.F.L. The Raiders defense is allowing opposing teams to convert just 30.4% of their third down chances, which is the best in the league.</p>
        <p>Comments: Denver had its measuring stick game last week and they blasted the Chiefs 34-7. This is a chance for the Raiders to see where they stack up in the A.F.C. West division. Typically, this is a competitive game. But nothing is typical about the Broncos. They're smashing people with their rushing attack and letting John Elway wipe out the leftovers through the air. It's a tough combination for any team. The Raiders will have to find a way to shutdown running back Terrell Davis and contain Elway. The Raiders aren't up to that kind of challenge.</p>
        <p>Game score: Denver 30-14.</p>
        <p>The Jets and Jaguars do not play this week.</p>
        <p>N.F.L. MATCHUPS: WEEK 10</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
