<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 16, an All-Too-Familiar Test for Wie</title>
    <meta content="11golf" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/11/sports/golf/11golf.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060117T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1731153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sony Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hack, Damon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wie, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii/Honolulu and Oahu</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Honolulu (Hawaii)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">PGA Tour Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EEDD163FF932A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 16, an All-Too-Familiar Test for Wie</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wie Tries to Make History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>HONOLULU, Jan. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Wie participates in Sony Open, first men's tournament since turning professional; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michelle Wie has been practicing her drives in all sorts of conditions, sharpening her skills as best she knows how, preparing for a moment that has been building for several years.</p>
        <p>''I'm taking my driver's test,'' Wie said Tuesday at the Sony Open in Hawaii. ''Hopefully I can pass.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 16-year-old Micheele Wie will attempt to secure her license next Tuesday, but she will first try again to make the cut against PGA Tour golfers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michelle Wie has been practicing her drives in all sorts of conditions, sharpening her skills as best she knows how, preparing for a moment that has been building for several years.</p>
        <p>''I'm taking my driver's test,'' Wie said Tuesday at the Sony Open in Hawaii. ''Hopefully I can pass.''</p>
        <p>The 16-year-old Wie will attempt to secure her license next Tuesday, but she will first try to make the cut against PGA Tour golfers at Waialae Country Club, her seventh professional foray against men. Wie has yet to make a cut, but this will be her first effort since she turned professional in October.</p>
        <p>''I told her, 'Don't beat me too bad this week,' '' said Sean O'Hair, who played a practice round with Wie and Justin Rose on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Wie missed the cut at the Sony Open last January by seven shots, but she missed by only one stroke in 2004, when she birdied the 18th hole. Last year, Wie missed the cut at the Casio World Open in Japan by one shot and at the John Deere Classic by two.</p>
        <p>While the Sony Open is the PGA Tour's first full-field tournament of the year, Wie has become the face of the event. Her practice round with O'Hair and Rose played to a gallery of nearly 100, far more than any other group. Wie has also become familiar to PGA Tour players who have watched her grow up.</p>
        <p>''It's a home crowd for her,'' Vijay Singh, the defending champion, said of Wie, who was born in Honolulu. ''I hope she plays well and I hope she makes the cut.''</p>
        <p>Wie will tee off on No. 10 at 8:40 a.m. local time Thursday with Camilo Villegas and Chris Couch. On Friday, they will tee off on No. 1 at 1:10 p.m.</p>
        <p>SINGH'S BODY SHOP -- Vijay Singh said he physically wore down near the end of the 2005 season, when he missed back-to-back cuts in October and failed to win a tournament after July. The fatigue prompted him to ramp up an already intense regimen of exercise and practice during the short off-season.</p>
        <p>''I worked hard on my body,'' Singh said Tuesday before a practice session on the range. ''I want to play well. I don't want to finish the season like I did last year.''</p>
        <p>Singh, who lost in a playoff to Stuart Appleby on Sunday at the winners-only Mercedes Championships, played in 30 events in 2005, the most tournaments he had ever entered. (Tiger Woods and Phil Mickelson, by comparison, played in 21.)</p>
        <p>While Woods and Mickelson opted for a longer off-season in 2006, skipping the Mercedes Championships and the Sony Open, Singh decided to put his new program to work immediately.</p>
        <p>''I've been playing well and I'm feeling good,'' Singh said. ''I didn't come over here to finish second. I'm going to try the hardest I can to win the golf tournament.''</p>
        <p>MASTERS INVITES -- Augusta National Golf Club announced a list of 99 invitees, including 14 first-time participants, for the Masters during the week of April 3-9.</p>
        <p>Among the familiar names, like Tiger Woods and Phil Mickelson, were players like Sean O'Hair and Bart Bryant.</p>
        <p>O'Hair earned 2005 PGA Tour rookie of the year honors on the strength of winning the John Deere Classic. Bryant won the Tour Championship and the Memorial Tournament last year.</p>
        <p>''I've got a lot of things I want to do with my game,'' O'Hair said of gearing up for the Masters. ''Practice habits, how much you are playing, what you're eating, the whole nine yards to peak at the right time. I'd like to be competitive at that event. I think I can if I keep my head.''</p>
        <p>Players can still earn their way into the Masters by winning the Players Championship, by placing among the top 10 on the PGA Tour money list in the week before the Masters or by placing among the top 50 on the official world golf rankings the week before the Masters.</p>
        <p>The Masters committee may invite additional international players not otherwise qualified.</p>
        <p>GOLF: NOTEBOOK</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 17, 2006, Tuesday  Because of an editing error, a sports article on Wednesday about the golfer Michelle Wie misstated the number of times she has competed against professional men since she turned pro in October. The Sony Open last week in Honolulu was her second tournament, not her seventh, and her first against PGA Tour players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 17, 2006, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a sports article on Wednesday about the golfer Michelle Wie misstated the number of times she has competed against professional men since she turned pro in October. The Sony Open last week in Honolulu was her second tournament, not her seventh, and her first against PGA Tour players.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
