<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Go Ahead, Brooklyn: Be Smug</title>
    <meta content="11rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/11/dining/reviews/11rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1731085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DE163FF932A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Go Ahead, Brooklyn: Be Smug</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Go Ahead, Brooklyn: Be Smug</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOOD lovers who live in Brooklyn, especially food lovers who moved there from Manhattan, love to say that they have better restaurants, ones that wed equally fine food to a humility often absent in the taller, shinier, haughtier borough across the water. Sometimes these people are simply falling prey to local pride and grading on a generous curve.</p>
        <p>Other times they're talking about Al di Là.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al di Là is an ideal neighborhood restaurant that's become much more than a neighborhood restaurant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOOD lovers who live in Brooklyn, especially food lovers who moved there from Manhattan, love to say that they have better restaurants, ones that wed equally fine food to a humility often absent in the taller, shinier, haughtier borough across the water. Sometimes these people are simply falling prey to local pride and grading on a generous curve.</p>
        <p>Other times they're talking about Al di Là.</p>
        <p>I resisted Al di Là for a good long while. One reason was practical: it doesn't take reservations, and I wasn't wild about traveling to Park Slope to wait an hour or more for a table, which can happen if you visit at a prime time on a weeknight or just about any time on a weekend.</p>
        <p>Another reason was journalistic: the charms of Al di Là weren't exactly secrets (hence those waits), so what purpose did a fresh look serve?</p>
        <p>But the main reason was pure stubbornness: so many Brooklyn friends were so smug in asserting that this little Italian gem was the ideal neighborhood restaurant. Even if they were right, I didn't want to grant them that.</p>
        <p>I hereby grant it, and I sing the praises of Al di Là, sung so many times before, because it deserves the music. Because there are food lovers from outside Brooklyn who have never been, and Al di Là is worth a trip. Because occasional chatter that it has grown tired and sloppy after more than seven years of extraordinary popularity needs to be corrected. It hasn't.</p>
        <p>True, Anna Klinger and Emiliano Coppa, the wife-and-husband, American-and-Italian couple who own and run Al di Là, haven't changed the menu all that much since they opened it in late 1998, but why should they? What was described as great then was great when I tried it over recent months, and the restaurant's fans would justifiably squawk if something like the casunziei, a dish of house-made ravioli, disappeared.</p>
        <p>It's not a complicated dish, and it's an important reminder, like so much at Al di Là, that Italian food doesn't need to be fancied up or elaborately fussed over to rise to a high level. The ravioli are stuffed with a blend of roasted beets and ricotta, then coated with melted butter and poppy seeds.</p>
        <p>Both times I had them, they were impeccably cooked, firm but not hard, pliant but not mushy, with pillowy insides and a rich, vaguely grainy gloss.</p>
        <p>Al di Là has also been doing its tripe appetizer since the beginning, and I hope it will do its tripe appetizer until the end. Blissfully slimy and appropriately chewy, the tripe is cooked and served in a bath of white wine, soffritto and tomatoes, with grilled peasant bread that you can, and should, use to mop up the liquid remnants.</p>
        <p>Al di Là prods and trusts you to eat adventurously by presenting that tripe; other appetizers of salt cod and bagna cauda; and entrees of calf's liver, basted with butter and sage as it finishes roasting, and rabbit, braised in white wine and chicken stock.</p>
        <p>But you can also play it safe. On a given night, the half-dozen appetizers are likely to include steamed mussels and carpaccio. The half-dozen pasta and risotto dishes will probably include tagliatelle with a chunky, immensely flavorful ragù of ground beef, pork and veal. And among the half-dozen entrees will be pan-roasted hanger steak served with a balsamic-sweetened sauce and grilled young chicken, tart with lemon juice.</p>
        <p>Over the past year, Al di Là has been preparing a terrific dish of pan-roasted cod, wild striped bass or hake, depending on the night, with hen-of-the-woods mushrooms and plenty of butter.</p>
        <p>Al di Là is unabashed about butter, embracing it in a way that many Italian restaurants in New York don't but that's consistent with the cooking in some areas of northern Italy, which is this restaurant's compass. There was a browned butter and sage sauce, for example, over house-made tortelli filled with squash.</p>
        <p>During my visits the kitchen usually exhibited remarkable precision. A risotto special, made with cuttlefish and cuttlefish ink, had a textbook texture -- the elusive sweet spot between gloppy and soupy.</p>
        <p>But there were missteps. That rabbit, bedecked with olives, was tender the second time I had it, but stringy the first. The chicken, which I sampled once, was dry.</p>
        <p>Al di Là has additional shortcomings, including desserts of widely varying success. While the gianduiotto, an amalgam of chocolate ice cream, hazelnuts and whipped cream, was out of this world, a ricotta tart was earthbound.</p>
        <p>Servers can become harried and distracted, and then there's the anxiety-making threat or reality of a long wait. I usually avoided it by going on a weeknight before 7. If you can't do that, know that about two years ago Al di Là annexed a space with an entrance around the corner and turned it into a pleasant wine bar where you can bide your time.</p>
        <p>The restaurant presents its food on plates that are pretty but mismatched and sometimes chipped, and that seems just right. The dining room isn't dramatic, but it's comfy and warm, with big windows, a combination of lovely yellow wallpaper and exposed brick on the walls, one set of red striped drapes inside the entrance and another framing a passageway to the kitchen.</p>
        <p>It can feel romantic, which is why you see so many young couples, heads bowed toward each other. It can feel homey, which is why you see solo diners and families with young children.</p>
        <p>You see a diverse community of people united by a desire to eat extremely well without preciousness or daunting prices, but you don't really see a neighborhood restaurant, at least not anymore.</p>
        <p>Al di Là, whose name is a kind of Italian double entendre, referring literally to ''the other side'' and figuratively to the great beyond, beckons and rightfully attracts food lovers from far and wide, their local prejudices trumped by its universal appeal.</p>
        <p>Al di Là  ** [Rating: Two Stars]  248 Fifth Avenue (Carroll Street), Park Slope, Brooklyn; (718) 783-4565.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Yellow wallpaper, red drapes and a Venetian glass chandelier add subtly elegant grace notes to an otherwise rustic room.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL -- Robust when crowded.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Creamy salt cod; tripe; ravioli with beets and ricotta; tortelli with squash; tagliatelli with meat sauce; braised rabbit; gianduiotto of chocolate ice cream with hazelnuts.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST -- Entirely Italian and well chosen, with many bottles under $40.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $6 to $10. Pasta dishes and entrees, $10 to $21. Desserts, $6.</p>
        <p>HOURS  -- 6 to 10:30 p.m. Monday, Wednesday and Thursday; 6 to 11 Friday; 5:30 to 11 Saturday; 5 to 10 Sunday. Closed Tuesday.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Not accepted, and waits on weekend nights can approach two hours.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Visa and MasterCard only.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Four-inch step up to entrance. (A ramp is available on request.) Accessible restroom.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  ***Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics:</p>
        <p>nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
