<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE TWIN TOWERS: The Investigation; After Frenzy, Agents Turn To Methodical Routine</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD TRADE CENTER (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLOSIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKING GARAGES AND LOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLUMENTHAL, RALPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLUMENTHAL, RALPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF1E3DF930A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE TWIN TOWERS: The Investigation; After Frenzy, Agents Turn To Methodical Routine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLUMENTHAL, RALPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal agents have stepped up surveillance of suspected terrorists in the United States as investigators press their search for a possible terrorist link to Friday's deadly bombing at the World Trade Center, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>While the officials highlighted recent threats from several groups in the Middle East, they said they had increased the monitoring of a wide range of people -- "seeing how they behave," as one official put it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal agents have stepped up surveillance of suspected terrorists in the United States as investigators press their search for a possible terrorist link to Friday's deadly bombing at the World Trade Center, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>While the officials highlighted recent threats from several groups in the Middle East, they said they had increased the monitoring of a wide range of people -- "seeing how they behave," as one official put it.</p>
        <p>But in many respects, officials said, the investigation has shifted from the scattershot urgency of the first frenzied days after the explosion to a more methodical phase. Four days after the huge underground blast, the work has become sifting through the evidence, separating the dead ends from the fragmentary leads.</p>
        <p>As the first 10 wrecked cars were hauled out of the underground parking garage where the blast originated, agents from the Treasury Department's Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms said yesterday that they had found pieces of a brown van that appeared to have been very close to the explosion or even involved with it in some way. Confusion and Tips</p>
        <p>James M. Fox, an assistant director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, said fragments had been recovered, "but it's nothing we're ready to comment on at this time." There was no reason yet to believe that it may have been the vehicle that delivered the bomb, he said.</p>
        <p>As the investigation continued yesterday, some confusion arose over possibly missing pieces of evidence, and tips from the public continued to pour in: by yesterday afternoon, Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said, some 5,000 calls had been received.</p>
        <p>In a puzzling twist, Mr. Fox, speaking at the now-daily 4 P.M. news briefing on case developments at Police Headquarters, said that while the authorities had obtained videotapes showing car license plates from two surveillance cameras in the garage, one possibly crucial tape spanning an important time period was "missing."</p>
        <p>He said this was a tape from a camera that was one level below the blast covering the period from 8 A.M. last Thursday to 8 A.M. Friday. The explosion occurred at 12:18 P.M.</p>
        <p>"It's incredible, isn't it?" Mr. Fox said. He said the tape had apparently been mislaid by an employee of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which owns the trade center, when he changed tapes. He said there was no reason to believe that anyone connected to the bombing had taken the tape. Other Tapes Obtained</p>
        <p>Port Authority officials said later that they were unaware any tapes were missing and said as far as they knew a complete set had been turned over to investigators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox said that other tapes from that camera on the B-3 level were obtained, as well as tapes from the B-6 level three floors down. He described their quality as generally poor with flashes of clarity that illuminated some vehicle plate numbers that investigators were seeking to trace to their owners.</p>
        <p>Although the B-3 camera was below the blast, it had a wide field that took in sections of the ramp, he said. Other video cameras may be buried in the rubble and could give more information on vehicles in the garage at the time of the explosion, Mr. Fox said. Poor quality tapes can often be enhanced by a painstaking process, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox also said that investigators had been unable to locate a tourist's videotape taken before the bombing and turned over to the authorities, but he said that they had previously determined that it had contained nothing relevant.</p>
        <p>And he denied earlier reports that vehicles seen at the garage had been traced to any known terrorists.</p>
        <p>The investigation had also hit common snags over inaccurate license data, he said. Some plate numbers had been recorded or transcribed incorrectly and had to be restudied, he said. But in an indication of the scope of the inquiry, a man who had parked his car in the World Trade Center last week said yesterday that he had been traced and questioned by detectives seeking any information he could contribute. He had none, he said. Huge Bomb Likely</p>
        <p>In the first major recovery of potential evidence, the 10 wrecked cars were towed out of the garage's Liberty Street entrance and vacuumed and scraped for residues that could yield clues to the chemical makeup of the bomb. Officials have described it as most likely a huge dynamite bomb of up to 1,500 pounds but left open the possibility that it could have been made of another explosive like plastic or some mixture.</p>
        <p>Although some bomb experts have probed the seven-level crater for clues to the blast, the pit remained too unstable for lengthy examination, guarding its secrets as intractably as a cosmic black hole.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox said that he did not foresee much chance that the ruins could be shored up safely enough for investigators to enter before Sunday and that it would then take 24 to 48 hours for the debris to be analyzed in the F.B.I. laboratory in Washington.</p>
        <p>That is expected to be the first time experts will be able to identify the nature of the bomb with any certainty. With the experience of Federalagents in identifying bombers' "signatures," pieces of a bomb can often be traced to its maker.</p>
        <p>While the finding of bomb fragments would undoubtedly advance the investigation, the authorities are separately pursuing another track -- trying to identify the motive. In cases of terrorism, knowing the "why" of an action is often a good clue to the "who," officials said.</p>
        <p>In response to questions as to whether the bombing had been signaled in advance, Mr. Fox and Commissioner Kelly said that there had been no specific warning but that Federal sources had tipped off the police in January that the United States Embassy in Algeria had received a warning that unless the Palestinians exiled by Israel were allowed back an unidentified target would be bombed in New York City within 48 hours. After the deadline passed, a caller extended it by 48 hours, but it again passed without action. Mr. Kelly said it could not be tied to the trade center bombing. Many Questions Remain</p>
        <p>Asked about other reported threats from the Middle Eastern terrorist group Hamas, Mr. Fox said it was "one of the groups we're looking at for a possible connection." But he said it was too early to focus on any one group or even on terrorism.</p>
        <p>While he said the delay in getting into the hole would not make much difference to the state of the evidence, "it gives somebody three or four more days that we wish they didn't have."</p>
        <p>"The big hope for all these questions is when we get down into the crater," Mr. Fox said. "That's where all the key evidence is."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
