<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Jeter Lays Off His Pal's Bait, Saying Plenty</title>
    <meta content="06ARAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/06/sports/06ARAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1275781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Tampa</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Seattle</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rodriguez, Alex</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DF103BF935A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Jeter Lays Off His Pal's Bait, Saying Plenty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses verbal spat between Alex Rodriguez and Derek Jeter; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN one of life's delicious little ironies, Alex Rodriguez recently made the claim that Derek Jeter is a player who is ''never your concern,'' presenting Jeter with the opportunity to demonstrate why he most often is.</p>
        <p>The proof was more in what Jeter didn't say than what he did, in response to Rodriguez's petty comments in the April issue of Esquire magazine. Under pressure, Jeter was collected enough to diffuse a potential spitting contest between two of baseball's glamour players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN one of life's delicious little ironies, Alex Rodriguez recently made the claim that Derek Jeter is a player who is ''never your concern,'' presenting Jeter with the opportunity to demonstrate why he most often is.</p>
        <p>The proof was more in what Jeter didn't say than what he did, in response to Rodriguez's petty comments in the April issue of Esquire magazine. Under pressure, Jeter was collected enough to diffuse a potential spitting contest between two of baseball's glamour players.</p>
        <p>''I'll ask him tonight,'' Jeter said when reporters fed him Rodriguez's bait last Friday at the Yankees' training base in Tampa. ''I'll talk to him and let you know.'' In the context of budding controversy, this solid contact with the increasingly elusive concept of restraint was the equivalent of a two-out, ninth-inning hit with the tying run on second.</p>
        <p>The commentary that Jeter is a Yankee who ''never had to lead'' (and, by extrapolation, perhaps not worth the 10-year, $189 million deal ranking him second behind Rodriguez on baseball's salary charts) had to sting, if only because it was made by a peer Jeter perceived as a pal.</p>
        <p>Only they know how close their friendship has been, but it's worth recalling that Jeter, in one of the few attacks against his team-first character, was criticized for fraternizing with Rodriguez while the Yankees and Mariners rolled angrily around the infield two seasons ago in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Jeter has since gone on with the Yankees to win two more World Series, for a total of four in five years. Rodriguez, bounced with the Mariners from the 2000 postseason by his so-called buddy's team, accepted a record 10-year, $252 million deal from Texas this winter, ending speculation that he would land with the Mets.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez was roundly criticized here following the aborted Mets negotiations, but it was understandable why he went elsewhere, beyond that staggering sum of money. Jeter already has both feet in the New York history book and, more significantly, George Steinbrenner would have made sure that Rodriguez never competed on a level playing field.</p>
        <p>''Jeter's been blessed with great talent around him,'' Rodriguez told Esquire. While that's indisputable, the entirety of his remarks make him sound painfully aware that no matter how much he makes, he can't buy karma. Jeter has obviously been fortunate to be part of the Yankees, but he has been essential to their success, a franchise pillar. In organizational terms, Jeter may have been born on third base, but he stole home and has put himself back in scoring position, time and again.</p>
        <p>Rodriguez. Gary Sheffield. John Rocker. You have to wonder about some athletes and periodical publications. Do they think they are being interviewed for historical archives that they won't be confronted with until age 75? No matter how much they cry context, the magazine quote may be a more honest window into their thinking, as the time between pontification and publication generally offers the opportunity to rethink and retract.</p>
        <p>Defensive people tend to lash out, which I was reminded of a few weeks ago at the National Basketball Association All-Star Game. Under siege about his league, David Stern was told at a news conference that Elvin Hayes, who coached in the game between rookies and second-year players, had called the league's young players immature. Had he withheld comment, Stern might have learned that Hayes had actually praised the players, saying that all they lacked was maturity. Stern, the most respected commissioner in team sports, instead chose to diss his league's own legend.</p>
        <p>Under verbal fire, Jeter, at 26, came across, especially in contrast to Rodriguez, as comfortable with his place, his contract and himself. It bodes well for the coming season and how Jeter will respond to his rich new deal.</p>
        <p>Might he falter in the face of expectation? Get a swelled head? The longtime Yankee Gene Michael tells of how he once asked Jeter if his congenial personality would change when the inevitable big money came. ''Aww, Stick,'' Jeter said, ''my dad would kill me.''</p>
        <p>Charles Jeter, a trained psychologist, once watched young Derek refuse to shake hands with the opposition after losing a Little League game. He told his son: ''Time to grab a tennis racket, since you don't know how to play a team sport.''</p>
        <p>Jeter has since learned a few things about sports and sociology. He graciously gave Alex Rodriguez the room to spin himself out of trouble. Their friendship has most likely taken a hit, but Jeter made his point. Count on him in a big spot, and always expect him to lead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
