<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witness Ties Accused Man to New Jersey Girl Who Vanished</title>
    <meta content="20GIRL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/20/nyregion/20girl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1598045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brick Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Janon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuller, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gregory, Brittney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040720T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DD103AF933A15754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witness Ties Accused Man to New Jersey Girl Who Vanished</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Witness Ties Accused Man to New Jersey Girl Who Vanished</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANON FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Janon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom Long, longtime friend of Jack Fuller, says that Fuller gave him ride home on night that Brittney Gregory was last seen and that she was in car; Gregory, 16-year-old girl of Brick Township, NJ, has been missing since July 11; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day that a man was arraigned in the suspected murder of a Brick Township, N.J., 16-year-old whose body has yet to be found, a neighbor of the accused killer said yesterday that they were both in a car with the girl on the night she disappeared.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors would not say yesterday what evidence they have that might implicate the defendant, Jack Fuller, in what they called the murder of Brittney Gregory, who was last seen on July 11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day that a man was arraigned in the suspected murder of a Brick Township, N.J., 16-year-old whose body has yet to be found, a neighbor of the accused killer said yesterday that they were both in a car with the girl on the night she disappeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day that a man was arraigned in the suspected murder of a Brick Township, N.J., 16-year-old whose body has yet to be found, a neighbor of the accused killer said yesterday that they were both in a car with the girl on the night she disappeared.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors would not say yesterday what evidence they have that might implicate the defendant, Jack Fuller, in what they called the murder of Brittney Gregory, who was last seen on July 11.</p>
        <p>But Tom Long, a longtime friend of Mr. Fuller's, said in a brief interview that Mr. Fuller gave him a ride home that night, and that Brittney, a friend of Mr. Fuller's daughter, was in the car. ''I was the last one to see them together,'' said Mr. Long, 39, who lives near Mr. Fuller in Howell Township. ''She didn't seem scared,'' said Mr. Long, speaking briefly through a screen door at his mother's house in Howell.</p>
        <p>''She wouldn't talk to me; it was like she didn't know me and she didn't want to know me,'' Mr. Long said. He said that she was talking to Mr. Fuller. He said Mr. Fuller dropped him off at his house on Sunset Drive and drove off with Ms. Gregory. He said he could not recall what time it was. Mr. Long declined to give further details, saying that he was cooperating with the authorities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Long's comments are significant because they place Mr. Fuller with Brittney on the night she disappeared.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, as the police combed woods in Howell and Brick Townships to search for her body, Mr. Fuller was arraigned before a judge in Superior Court in Ocean County. Some of Brittney's friends and relatives watched the proceedings. Later, a tearful Debra Gregory, Brittney's mother, raged against Mr. Fuller on the courthouse steps.</p>
        <p>''I don't want the death penalty for him,'' she said, battling her way through a crowd of reporters. ''I want to see him in jail for the rest of his life, and I hope he lives to be 100.''</p>
        <p>Friends and neighbors described Brittney as a petite blond-haired blue-eyed high school cheerleader, a good student who was popular and was interested in forensic science.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fuller, who is being held in the Ocean County Jail in $1 million bail, was released from state prison in April 2003 after serving 117 days on a parole violation stemming from a burglary conviction.</p>
        <p>Outside the courthouse, Stan Kilmartin, 30, who said he was a friend of Mr. Fuller's, said he was surprised by the murder charge.</p>
        <p>''What does he do? Truthfully? He robs drug dealers,'' said Mr. Kilmartin. ''He's a thief, but I wouldn't describe him as a pedophile or a rapist.''</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that Ms. Gregory and Mr. Fuller's daughter, Cassey, are friends.</p>
        <p>Dinnette Oryniak, 33, who lives in the Greenwood Park development, a few doors away from the Gregory home, described her as a sweet, polite young girl full of promise.</p>
        <p>Ms. Oryniak, who has five children, recalled Brittney playing with her 4- and 7-year-old daughters, teaching them gymnastics and cheerleading moves.</p>
        <p>Ms. Oryniak said she has also known Mr. Fuller most of her life. She said that at one point he was living in the woods behind her house in Howell.</p>
        <p>But she said she was surprised by news of his arrest. ''I don't know Jack as a murderer,'' she said. ''I know Jack as a thief.''</p>
        <p>Outside the court today, Robert Gasser, executive assistant prosecutor in the Ocean County prosecutor's office, said that police helicopters would be used to search for the body.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
