<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Contingency Plan in Action: Amex Bank Keeps Money Moving</title>
    <meta content="15BANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/15/business/companies/15BANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1325067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="AFTER THE ATTACKS: THE BACKUP SITES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Express Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Anthony, S</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DE1F38F936A2575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1359" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Contingency Plan in Action: Amex Bank Keeps Money Moving</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">One Contingency Plan in Action: Amex Bank Keeps Money Moving</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Express Bank, which normally works out of 7 World Trade Center, began its contingency plan out of backup offices in New Jersey soon after planes crashed into World Trade Center, processing about 19,000 transfers for total of $14.3 billion, about 70 percent of transactions its customers had entered, by late Sept 11; it was testament to sort of contingency planning that regulators urge on companies, but that only some do; American Express had established backup site as part of computer crisis that never came on Jan 1, 2000; company will make its home in New Jersey indefinitely; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first stunned moments when the horror of the planes crashing into the World Trade Center slowly registered on the people in lower Manhattan, Madhavan Ramaswamy found something that would later be in very short supply: a taxicab.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramaswamy, a manager for international money transfer at the American Express Bank who works at 7 World Trade Center, was a little late for a meeting there when he saw flames atop the twin towers. Jumping into a cab with three colleagues, he told the driver to head to the bank's backup center, never before used, just over the Hudson River in New Jersey. (American Express, nervous about security, asked that its exact location not be disclosed.) The Lincoln and Holland Tunnels were already closed, but Mr. Ramaswamy's group was able to catch a ferry, and by 2 p.m. he arrived in the bank's three narrow rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some companies are now realizing the value of their backup sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first stunned moments when the horror of the planes crashing into the World Trade Center slowly registered on the people in lower Manhattan, Madhavan Ramaswamy found something that would later be in very short supply: a taxicab.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramaswamy, a manager for international money transfer at the American Express Bank who works at 7 World Trade Center, was a little late for a meeting there when he saw flames atop the twin towers. Jumping into a cab with three colleagues, he told the driver to head to the bank's backup center, never before used, just over the Hudson River in New Jersey. (American Express, nervous about security, asked that its exact location not be disclosed.) The Lincoln and Holland Tunnels were already closed, but Mr. Ramaswamy's group was able to catch a ferry, and by 2 p.m. he arrived in the bank's three narrow rooms.</p>
        <p>With most of the bank's employees scattered around the city -- all, it would turn out, thankfully alive -- Mr. Ramaswamy's group met three more colleagues from a New Jersey office, pulled the plastic drop cloths from rows of computers and began rerouting communications from the international banking networks.</p>
        <p>By late Tuesday, they were able to process about 19,000 transfers for a total of $14.3 billion, roughly 70 percent of the transactions its customers had entered.</p>
        <p>It was a testament to the sort of contingency planning that finger-wagging regulators urge on companies, but that only some do. American Express had established the backup site as part of its preparations for the computer crisis that never came on Jan. 1, 2000.</p>
        <p>Yet, as the week went on and the number of employees taxing the air-conditioning of the three rooms grew to about 90, it became clear that the disaster plan had not anticipated the scale of this disaster. The contingency plan had predicted a need to use the backup site for two weeks; now the company will make its home in New Jersey indefinitely, not just for computer operators but for sales representatives, lawyers and a host of other staff members.</p>
        <p>Even some of the most basic elements of the bank's plan did not anticipate the scope of this disruption. Employees had been told that if their building was evacuated, they should reunite at a nearby public school. But on Tuesday that site seemed perilously close, and most joined the mass of dazed refugees streaming north away from the trade center.</p>
        <p>William J. Blomquist, the managing director of the bank's Financial Institutions Group, was about to convene a staff meeting in his office in the American Express headquarters tower, in the World Financial Center just across West Street from the trade center, when he heard the explosion of the first plane crash.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to stay calm when you see people starting to jump out of windows,'' Mr. Blomquist said on Thursday.</p>
        <p>After the second crash the American Express tower was evacuated, and Mr. Blomquist bumped into Farhad Subjally, another bank executive, who had recently left the bank's operations center in 7 World Trade.</p>
        <p>''I fully thought we would be able to go back into our building in half an hour,'' Mr. Subjally said. ''So I was heading over to the World Financial Center to make phone calls.''</p>
        <p>Instead, the executives marched north, finding other bank employees as they went along, periodically stopping to look back at the flaming wreckage.</p>
        <p>''Once the first tower fell, I couldn't look any more,'' Mr. Blomquist said.</p>
        <p>What became a band of 30 people eventually set up camp in the apartment of the brother-in-law of one of them on the Lower East Side. Telephone service was sporadic at best. They were able to place calls to Staten Island, to the wife of Anthony S. DeSimone, the bank's head of New York operations, and she relayed messages to the Amex backup center in New Jersey as well as to concerned family members of the bankers holed up in the apartment. At the end of the day, the group disbanded and reported for work on Wednesday at the center in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, workers from Electronic Data Systems, the big computer company that operates the bank's systems, were busy trying to get the computer system at the backup center running. To do so, they needed backup tapes that were held in a vault farther west in New Jersey. This also proved difficult, since many freeways were closed Tuesday. Eventually, at a street corner halfway between their two offices, an E.D.S. courier met up with someone from the company that kept the backup tapes.</p>
        <p>These days, Amex's international payments are so routine that many can be handled without human involvement. These were processed automatically by the main American Express Bank computer at an E.D.S. center in Britain throughout Tuesday. But by 7 p.m., when Mr. Ramaswamy and colleagues finally had the computers in New Jersey linked back to the mainframe in Britain, thousands of transfers that did need human authorization had piled up. Working until 11 p.m., the team processed all those transactions.</p>
        <p>Although the backup center in New Jersey was equipped with the advanced communication and security equipment needed to transfer huge amounts of money, it was cut off from all other information. There was no television, radio or Internet browser. The backup site was set up to receive e-mail, but the e-mail server in 7 World Trade had been destroyed Tuesday afternoon when that building collapsed.</p>
        <p>''I was totally cut off and didn't know anything other than something bad had happened,'' Mr. Ramaswamy said. His only information came from telephone calls, when the land lines or cell phones were working. ''I was on the phone with a guy in Singapore when he said that he was seeing our office falling on CNN. It was terrible.''</p>
        <p>Other bank officials scattered around the region. Anthony Oliveri, an account officer, went home and called his clients, mainly banks in Latin America, to reassure them and give them his personal cell phone number and e-mail address. Clients, he said, have been very understanding that their money may have been slightly delayed. In a few cases involving longstanding clients, he and other bank officers authorized the release of funds without the normally required documentation to get those clients out of jams.</p>
        <p>By Thursday afternoon, the New Jersey center was filled with workers crowded around dozens of computers squeezed next to one another on long, woodgrain-plastic folding work tables, with power strips dangling underneath.</p>
        <p>Eli Andino was working on completing a $4 million transfer from a bank in France to one in Chicago, typing information from a printout from one system into a computer linked to another. Normally, the two systems were linked, saving time.</p>
        <p>With the air-conditioning out in one of the three rooms and the decibel level almost as high as the temperature, the bankers were coping with adversity both physical and technological.</p>
        <p>''These are low-grade PC's to keep us up and running,'' said George Kreiner, a supervisor in money transfer. ''It would be nice to have Word and Excel and e-mail and all the other things we use every day.''</p>
        <p>Now that the basic systems are in place, even harder work is beginning to turn what had been meant as a temporary setup into the bank's home for many months ahead.</p>
        <p>New computers are on order. E.D.S. is converting some unused space it had in the building into additional space for the bank. It bought three large oscillating fans on Thursday and promised to have the air-conditioning fixed over the weekend.</p>
        <p>AFTER THE ATTACKS: THE BACKUP SITES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
