<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="25BIZD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1561699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DF123CF936A15751C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Europe May Ask Microsoft For 2 Versions of Windows  European antitrust regulators are considering a requirement that Microsoft sell two versions of Windows in Europe -- one with the music- and video-playing software stripped out -- should they find the company to be an abusive monopoly, people close to the case said.</p>
        <p>The European Commission, which is nearing a ruling in the five-year-old case, may also ask Microsoft to propose ''within a few months of a ruling'' what computer code for Windows it should disclose to make the operating system fully compatible with programs and servers manufactured by rivals. [Page C5.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Europe May Ask Microsoft For 2 Versions of Windows  European antitrust regulators are considering a requirement that Microsoft sell two versions of Windows in Europe -- one with the music- and video-playing software stripped out -- should they find the company to be an abusive monopoly, people close to the case said.</p>
        <p>The European Commission, which is nearing a ruling in the five-year-old case, may also ask Microsoft to propose ''within a few months of a ruling'' what computer code for Windows it should disclose to make the operating system fully compatible with programs and servers manufactured by rivals. [Page C5.]</p>
        <p>A New Cycle of Merger Mania  With the economy improving and memories fading of the disastrous string of merger deals during the last stock market boom, big-time Wall Street deal making is back. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Traders that make their living by betting on mergers, buyouts and hostile bids, known as arbitragers, are dipping a toe in the market but expect to dive in real soon. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Rail Lines May Merge  Hong Kong officials called for the mass transit system, the MTR Corporation, to conclude merger talks by the end of August with the Kowloon-Canton Railway Corporation. Currently riders of both lines pay two separate fares. Dr. Sarah Liao, Hong Kong's secretary for the environment, transport and works, said the government did not think it was creating a monopoly that would be harmful to consumers. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Parmalat Units File Chapter 11  Parmalat's United States dairy subsidiaries filed for bankruptcy protection, saying they are trying to protect their assets and are readying for a possible sale that could help settle the parent company's debts. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Buzz About Disney Continues  Questions about who knew what, and when, continue to dog Walt Disney, which disclosed on Monday that its board had been advised of an overture to enter merger talks with Comcast ahead of a formal bid. [C3.]</p>
        <p>S.E.C. Chief Offers a Choice  William H. Donaldson proposed a rule change that could shift trades away from the New York Stock Exchange to its electronic rivals by allowing investors to choose speed over best price. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Saudi Oil Production to Stand Pat  Saudi Arabia executives plan to maintain oil production capacity at its current rate of 10 million barrels a day this decade. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Renovations Bolster Home Depot  Shares of Home Depot rose 61 cents, to $35.99, after the company reported a 39 percent increase in fourth-quarter profit and a 14 percent rise in sales. Home Depot has been renovating stores into a softer, cleaner look. It reported strong gains in several crucial markets, including Baltimore, Cleveland and Washington. The chief executive, Robert L. Nardelli, also acknowledged that there are more improvements that can be be made. One area is increasing the average amount of money Home Depot takes in on each sales ticket. [C12.]</p>
        <p>Court Says Airline Liable for Death  The Supreme Court ruled that Olympic Airways was liable for the death of a 52-year-old passenger who had an asthmatic reaction to cigarette smoke. [A21.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Decline for a 5th Day  Stock gauges fell after a report said consumer confidence tumbled. The Dow Jones industrials slipped 43.25 points, to 10,566.37. The S.&amp;P. 500 lost 1.90 points, to 1,139.09, and the Nasdaq composite shed 2.08 points, to 2,005.44. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Book Chain Enters Inner Cities  Borders Books and Music is tapping into one of the retail industry's few remaining new frontiers -- underserved inner-city neighborhoods. Commercial Real Estate. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
