<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once More, The Fed Holds Rates Steady</title>
    <meta content="Y05FED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DE143DF936A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once More, The Fed Holds Rates Steady</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve votes to leave interest rates unchanged, apparently concluding that the economy will slow enough to repress inflation without endangering seven-year-old expansion (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged, apparently concluding that the economy would slow enough to repress inflation without endangering the seven-year-old expansion.</p>
        <p>The central bank's policy-making committee did not provide any explanation of its decision, which was announced at the end of two-day meeting, its first this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged, apparently concluding that the economy would slow enough to repress inflation without endangering the seven-year-old expansion.</p>
        <p>The central bank's policy-making committee did not provide any explanation of its decision, which was announced at the end of two-day meeting, its first this year.</p>
        <p>But the decision came as no surprise to investors and economists, who had long since concluded that the Fed would hold rates steady. The stock market showed little reaction, with the Dow Jones average falling 30.64 points, to 8,129.7, after a 253.85-point gain over the previous two days. Bond prices rose marginally. [Page 10.]</p>
        <p>Although the economy has been running at a sufficiently strong pace to generate early warning signs of inflationary pressures, economists expect Asia's financial crisis to slow the growth rate in coming months.</p>
        <p>Fed officials have generally continued to focus on concerns about inflation. But Alan Greenspan, the central bank's chairman, has made clear in recent weeks that he and his colleagues have also scrutinized the possibility that the Asian situation could result in widespread price declines and create the risk of recession.</p>
        <p>''The Fed demonstrated that they're willing to be very patient and wait for evidence of just what Asia means for the U.S. economy,'' said Dan Laufenberg, an economist with the American Express Financial Corporation. ''Greenspan seems to think the risks go in both directions.''</p>
        <p>As a result, analysts remain divided over whether the next move by the Fed, whenever it comes, will be to increase or reduce interest rates.</p>
        <p>Today's decision left the primary short-term rate controlled by the Fed, the Federal funds target rate, at 5.5 percent, where it has been since the Fed raised it a quarter of a percentage point last March.</p>
        <p>With growth strong and the unemployment rate near a quarter-century low, the Fed for much of the last year has maintained a formal policy bias toward raising rates. It is possible that the Fed changed its policy stance at its last meeting in December, but that was discounted by economists. Instead, some analysts said it was possible that the central bank scrapped that bias today in favor of a more neutral policy stance to reflect the deflationary risks to the economy. The answer will not be made public until April 1, when the Fed releases the minutes of the meeting that ended today.</p>
        <p>Robert V. DiClemente, an economist at Salomon Smith Barney, likened the situation facing the Fed to two boulders balanced on a seesaw, one representing strong growth and inflation, the other a sharp slowdown and deflation.</p>
        <p>''We're all very nervous about whether this balance can persist and whether something will have to break one way or another,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The economy grew 4.3 percent in the final quarter of 1997, nearly twice the rate that most economists think it can sustain over the long run without setting off a spiral of rising wages and prices. With unemployment at 4.7 percent and job creation growing at a healthy pace, employers must pay more to attract and keep workers, and benefits costs have shown signs of edging up.</p>
        <p>Despite a rise in inflation-adjusted short term interest rates, long-term rates have been declining, helping interest-sensitive sectors of the economy like housing. Consumer confidence remains high, suggesting that spending will remain robust, and the stock market has been bullish despite lingering concerns about the effects of the downturn in Asia on corporate earnings and market sentiment.</p>
        <p>Yet for all that the economy is roaring along, there has been almost no inflation. The Consumer Price Index rose just 1.7 percent last year, the lowest rate in 11 years, and the Asian crisis is likely to help restrain price increases on many goods this year in the United States or even push prices down by generating high quantities of cheap imports. Prices for services, which are less restrained by foreign competition, are more likely to show substantial increases, analysts said.</p>
        <p>''Inflation might be a tad higher, but still very good for an economy entering the eighth year of an expansion,'' Mr. Laufenberg said. ''So the Fed waits, and they can afford to wait.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
