<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A CUNY Revolutionary Looks Back</title>
    <meta content="20CUNY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/20/education/20CUNY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1377236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edelstein, Julius C C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Edelstein, Julius C C</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DA1238F933A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A CUNY Revolutionary Looks Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A CUNY Revolutionary Looks Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arenson, Karen W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Julius C C Edelstein, early fighter for open admissions at City University of New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been 18 years since Julius C. C. Edelstein, one of the architects of open admissions at the City University of New York, stepped down as a senior vice chancellor of the university. But Mr. Edelstein, now 90, never really left CUNY.</p>
        <p>When Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and others argued that open admissions let too many students who were not ready for college onto CUNY's campuses, Mr. Edelstein, the son of a Russian revolutionary, fought back, insisting that the university honor its commitment to greater access. More recently, he wrote to CUNY's chancellor, Matthew Goldstein, and to Gov. George E. Pataki to try to get the university to reverse its policy that illegal immigrants pay the higher cost of out-of-state tuition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Julius C. C. Edelstein, now 90, an architect of open admissions at the City University of New York, has never really left the school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been 18 years since Julius C. C. Edelstein, one of the architects of open admissions at the City University of New York, stepped down as a senior vice chancellor of the university. But Mr. Edelstein, now 90, never really left CUNY.</p>
        <p>When Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and others argued that open admissions let too many students who were not ready for college onto CUNY's campuses, Mr. Edelstein, the son of a Russian revolutionary, fought back, insisting that the university honor its commitment to greater access. More recently, he wrote to CUNY's chancellor, Matthew Goldstein, and to Gov. George E. Pataki to try to get the university to reverse its policy that illegal immigrants pay the higher cost of out-of-state tuition.</p>
        <p>''It's the wrong thing to do,'' he said firmly in an interview, ''even if the letter of the law is saying we should do it. It's not what City University should be in the business of doing. We're the educator of the disadvantaged.''</p>
        <p>Governments always have people behind the scenes who come up with ideas and make them happen, and at CUNY Mr. Edelstein was arguably one of the most influential. And after he officially stepped down, he still made things happen, using a lifetime of contacts garnered from working in Congress, in the White House and at City Hall.</p>
        <p>With the celebration of his 90th birthday last month (the day is actually Feb. 29th, though there was none  this year), and a string of parties to honor him, Mr. Edelstein and his friends reminisced recently about some of his efforts and why he has been so committed to enabling more students to attend the university.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to the raison d'être of City University, Julius Edelstein is our muse,'' said James P. Murphy, the former chairman of CUNY, this month at a party at CUNY's graduate center.</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Edelstein, an elf of a man with streaming white hair, works out of a small, cluttered office at Hunter College. Many days, he breakfasts or lunches with people from his vast network of movers and shakers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edelstein never earned a bachelor's degree himself; he left the University of Wisconsin, where he was studying medicine, before graduation. While there, however, he organized a student Socialist club, following the example of his father, who had been general secretary of the Social Revolutionary Party in czarist Russia before becoming ''a tailor and agitator in Wisconsin.''</p>
        <p>After leaving the university for health reasons, he worked as a journalist and then as a communications officer in the Navy during World War II. After the war, he served as an adviser to both the high commissioner and the president of the Philippines. He also worked in the Franklin D. Roosevelt and Harry S. Truman White Houses, and was a top aide to Senator Herbert H. Lehman.</p>
        <p>He grew close to Mayor Robert F. Wagner in 1961 while serving as his deputy campaign manager, helping to run the ''Beat the Bosses'' campaign after city Democratic officials tried to prevent Wagner from running again. Wagner was re-elected, and Mr. Edelstein became his executive assistant.</p>
        <p>While in city government, Mr. Edelstein thought back to how the University of Wisconsin had been ''a laboratory for state government,'' and sold Albert Bowker, CUNY's chancellor, on doing the same with CUNY. When Wagner decided not to run for a third term, Mr. Edelstein recalled, ''Al Bowker said: 'O.K., I'll hire you. Now you do what you told me to do.'</p>
        <p>''Al Bowker was really the one who thought up open admissions, and I was his handyman,'' Mr. Edelstein said. ''He was a mathematician, and he had done the math of projecting what the enrollment at the city colleges would be if they did not lower their bars and let in some of the educationally disadvantaged. At that time, the percentage of minority enrollment in the senior colleges was 1.5 percent.''</p>
        <p>In the mid-1960's Mr. Edelstein huddled with political officials from Albany and New York, including Shirley Chisholm, Percy Sutton, Charles B. Rangel, Basil A. Paterson and Anthony J. Travia, to draft legislation creating the SEEK program, under which CUNY's four-year colleges were to accept low-income students whom they would not otherwise admit and to provide extra support to help them through college.</p>
        <p>SEEK broke the ice, Mr. Edelstein said, providing access for black and Hispanic students who became the vanguard of the campus militants fighting for open admissions. Their demonstrations shut down City College -- at one point, protesters unhappy with the pace of change locked Mr. Edelstein in a bathroom for three hours -- and became a hot issue in the city elections.</p>
        <p>At a retreat at Wave Hill in the late 1960's, Mr. Edelstein presented a paper -- ''The Tiger at the Gates'' -- to CUNY's trustees, noting the rising anger on campuses across the nation and arguing that ''unless we expanded our enrollments, we would be overwhelmed,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>CUNY agreed to speed up a plan to open its doors wider.</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's, with New York in financial difficulties, Mr. Edelstein and Stanley Lowell, a former deputy mayor under Wagner, set up the Committee on Public Higher Education, a group made up of former public officials and others that served as an advocate for CUNY. When Mayor Giuliani and CUNY's trustees started attacking the university's policies in the mid-1990's, Mr. Edelstein renamed the group Friends of CUNY and reinvigorated it to defend open admissions and remedial instruction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edelstein concedes today that open admissions ''was not perfectly administered,'' but he says the university was never the ''institution adrift'' that Mayor Giuliani's task force charged it was.</p>
        <p>''Open admissions may have gone too far,'' he said. ''Critics of open admissions said the program was designed to let anyone in. But that was never the intent of those who conceived the program. Our intention was to let more students in. The program opened the gates to hundreds of thousands of students and produced substantial and significant achievements.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
