<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE</title>
    <meta content="06bold" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/06/nyregion/06bold.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1729856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Sundance Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Redford, Robert</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DC1E30F935A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">So, Sundance, Would You Rather Play Jack or Ennis?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ; With Regan Morris in Los Angeles</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So, Sundance, Would You Rather Play Jack or Ennis?</p>
        <p>ROBERT REDFORD was in town yesterday to announce a new collaboration between the Brooklyn Academy of Music and the Sundance Institute, which he founded in 1981 to promote independent films.</p>
        <p>Maybe it was BAM's swank surroundings or a recording of ASTRUD GILBERTO whispering about ''Quiet Nights of Quiet Stars,'' but even the usual elbows-out paparazzi seemed restrained, with the mousetrap sounds of their shutters muffled by the saxophone overhead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Redford was in town to announce a new collaboration between the Brooklyn Academy of Music and the Sundance Institute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So, Sundance, Would You Rather Play Jack or Ennis?</p>
        <p>ROBERT REDFORD was in town yesterday to announce a new collaboration between the Brooklyn Academy of Music and the Sundance Institute, which he founded in 1981 to promote independent films.</p>
        <p>Maybe it was BAM's swank surroundings or a recording of ASTRUD GILBERTO whispering about ''Quiet Nights of Quiet Stars,'' but even the usual elbows-out paparazzi seemed restrained, with the mousetrap sounds of their shutters muffled by the saxophone overhead.</p>
        <p>There was no frenzied scrum when Mr. Redford entered BAMCafe and shook hands with STEVE BUSCEMI,  BOB VILA and assorted notables. And no photographer or television cameraman, as far as could be heard, shouted out the local equivalent of ''Aye, Queenie, show us some leg!''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Redford seemed casual, even rumpled. His reddish hair was uncombed and he squinted amiably through wire-rim eyeglasses. He wore a black tuxedo jacket, black scarf, blue jeans and no jewelry except a Navajo turquoise ring.</p>
        <p>MARTY MARKOWITZ, the Brooklyn borough president, gushed to the audience, ''All these years I've said I looked like Robert Redford, but now that I've met him.'' He paused. ''I can't lie to myself anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Markowitz welcomed Mr. Redford to Brooklyn, home to fellow actors Mr. Buscemi; PAUL GIAMATTI, of ''Sideways;'' and HEATH LEDGER and MICHELLE WILLIAMS, of the cowboy love story ''Brokeback Mountain.''</p>
        <p>The rumpled Mr. Redford took to the lectern, smiled at Mr. Markowitz, and said, ''Well, believe it or not, I woke up this morning feeling like I looked a little like Marty.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Redford, 68, confessed to being captivated by Brooklyn since he was a boy, not only because of the Brooklyn Dodgers and their ballpark, Ebbets Field, but also because of writers like IRWIN SHAW and THOMAS WOLFE.</p>
        <p>''So obviously I had a fascination with Brooklyn that led me to where we are today,'' Mr. Redford said.</p>
        <p>It also turned out, he said, that many of the most creative filmmakers and other artists at the Sundance Institute came from Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The Sundance-BAM collaboration will be called Creative Latitude, partly because Brooklyn and Park City, Utah, where the Sundance Film Festival is held, share roughly the same 40 degree latitude.</p>
        <p>Starting in May, winners and other films from the festival will be shown at BAM. Other programs will focus on theater and music.</p>
        <p>And then it was over. Boldface asked Mr. Redford about his favorite films of 2005. ''Oh, I'm going to be diplomatic and I'm not going to answer that,'' he said. ''I'm in a position where that could be very risky.''</p>
        <p>Well, what did you think of ''Brokeback Mountain''?</p>
        <p>''I liked it very much,'' said Mr. Redford, who made a name for himself in 1969 playing THE SUNDANCE KID, after whom his institute is named, in the movie ''BUTCH CASSIDY and the Sundance Kid,'' which also starred PAUL NEWMAN.</p>
        <p>At a panel discussion last month, ANG LEE, director of ''Brokeback Mountain,'' said that Mr. Newman ''would be good for the JACK character,'' which is played by JAKE GYLLENHAAL. Mr. Newman was a ''classic romantic type, if it was shot in the 60's,'' Mr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>In that case, would Mr. Redford have been interested in playing ENNIS, the character played by Mr. Ledger?</p>
        <p>Mr. Redford's face tightened, and his publicist looked stricken.</p>
        <p>''Oh, that's a separate conversation,'' Mr. Redford said.</p>
        <p>His publicist said tersely, ''We're done.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in Los Angeles, Tori Spelling Has a Script</p>
        <p>At the Getty Center, part of the sprawling Getty Museum complex in Los Angeles, JEREMY PIVEN, LING BAI, TORI SPELLING and DEAN McDERMOTT attended a Volkswagen car ''celebration'' on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>What are you doing these days, our correspondent asked Ms. Spelling.</p>
        <p>Best known for ''Beverly Hills, 90210,'' Ms. Spelling replied that her new VH1 show, ''noTORIous,'' was having its premiere in April.</p>
        <p>''It's not a reality show,'' she said, ''it's a scripted sitcom, loosely based on my life, kind of like 'Curb Your Enthusiasm.' ''</p>
        <p>Boldface</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
