<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Good Year, for the Record</title>
    <meta content="06wall" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/06/business/06wall.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1729852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Street Scene"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E4DC1E30F935A35752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Good Year, for the Record</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Good Year, for the Record</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wall Street, the word ''record'' has become another ho-hum adjective thrown around by many investment banks to describe nearly every quarter of the year.</p>
        <p>By the end of 2005, Goldman Sachs, Lehman Brothers and Bear Stearns had reported record years in terms of earnings, revenues and diluted earnings a share. Each bank listed a number of other record items, including fixed-income revenue at Goldman Sachs, net revenue in every segment and in every region at Lehman and revenue from equity derivatives at Bear Stearns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is plausible that Wall Street will have yet another record year in 2006.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Wall Street, the word ''record'' has become another ho-hum adjective thrown around by many investment banks to describe nearly every quarter of the year.</p>
        <p>By the end of 2005, Goldman Sachs, Lehman Brothers and Bear Stearns had reported record years in terms of earnings, revenues and diluted earnings a share. Each bank listed a number of other record items, including fixed-income revenue at Goldman Sachs, net revenue in every segment and in every region at Lehman and revenue from equity derivatives at Bear Stearns.</p>
        <p>The 2005 results followed those from the record year 2004. But can the record setting continue?</p>
        <p>Conventional wisdom has it that Wall Street cannot grow at the pace that it has. Interest rates continue to rise, and the inversion of the yield curve -- when long-term interest rates on government bonds drop below short-term rates -- that occurred in December stoked fears that a recession could be on the horizon.</p>
        <p>Higher short-term rates are usually thought to mean lower profits for the Street, as the spread between the rate banks pay to borrow and the one they charge to make loans shrinks. Since some banks on Wall Street now derive as much as 50 percent of their profits from the credit area, higher rates have been cited as the certain downfall of Wall Street profits. But that has not been the case.</p>
        <p>''Who cares about rates?'' said Richard X. Bove, a securities analyst with Punk, Ziegel, an investment bank. ''High interest rates and a flat yield curve do not cause bank earnings to weaken.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is plausible that Wall Street will have yet another record year in 2006. There are a number of deals and offerings in the pipeline, and some banks are so busy that they are set to add as much as 10 percent to their employee head count. So far, they have defied expectations that rising interest rates will precipitate a stumble.</p>
        <p>The smart banks have aggressively diversified products, clients and geography, and a handful of them -- Citigroup, Merrill Lynch and Lehman Brothers -- have indicated their appetite for strategic acquisitions, reflecting their own financial strength as well as the mood among their corporate clients.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bove recently published a report that traces every inversion of the yield curve for which data was available since 1962. In recent years, he finds, inversions have happened for only two periods since April 1982, each lasting less than a year.</p>
        <p>From 1965 to 1982, however, the curve was inverted 47 percent of the time. Mr. Bove measured bank earnings against each inversion and determined that the net interest income of the banks never declined. When banks did report a decline in earnings, it was because of an increase in loan losses or, in the case of 2000, to a recession.</p>
        <p>There are other reasons to be bullish. Most of the major banks -- Lehman Brothers in particular -- have focused on building franchises abroad. Henry M. Paulson, chief executive of Goldman Sachs, traveled to China five times in 2005 and has been there 60 times since 1999. In the fourth quarter, Lehman's European revenue was up 87 percent and Asian revenue rose 46 percent over the previous year. Bear Stearns said that in the fourth quarter its European and Asian divisions were profitable.</p>
        <p>This will bode well for years to come when growth in capital markets abroad could far outpace that in the United States. According to Thomson Financial, European issuance in 2005 climbed 13 percent, to $2.46 trillion, while Japanese underwriting rose more than 10 percent, to $276 billion. United States issuers raised $3.02 trillion, a bigger total, but up only 4 percent from last year's level. No American company was in the top 10 global initial public offerings.</p>
        <p>Wall Street's traditional business of buying and selling stocks on the exchanges was abysmal last year, so firms focused on more electronic trading -- meaning fewer people -- and expansion in equity derivatives. They have used the long rise in interest rates to diversify the fixed-income revenue stream, securitizing products ranging from loans to toll roads. Except for the mortgage market, which has fueled growth at Bear Stearns and Lehman Brothers and is now slowing, the securitization binge appears to be continuing.</p>
        <p>The party, of course, will not last forever. If there is a recession, all bets are off: equity issuance will stall, trading volumes will decrease and corporate chiefs will retrench.</p>
        <p>There are other red flags: with more proprietary trading, or trading done on behalf of the investment house itself, it is virtually impossible to predict trading profits. And for every strategy that has minted money in 2005, like focusing on commodities and mortgages, this year will bring new entrants into that arena and a push to more normalized returns.</p>
        <p>So the party may not be raging, but it may last one more year.</p>
        <p>Street Scene</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
