<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Ways to Deliver a Life-Saving Jolt</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFIBRILLATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMPLANTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Defibrillators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Implants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD123BF937A15751C0A965958260" item-length="1534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Ways to Deliver a Life-Saving Jolt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ken Rusk remembers the first time the titanium box in his abdomen did what it was supposed to do -- deliver an electric shock to his heart. It felt like being kicked in the chest by a horse.</p>
        <p>The incident happened early in 1991, about a year and a half after surgeons implanted the device.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ken Rusk remembers the first time the titanium box in his abdomen did what it was supposed to do -- deliver an electric shock to his heart. It felt like being kicked in the chest by a horse.</p>
        <p>The incident happened early in 1991, about a year and a half after surgeons implanted the device.</p>
        <p>"Bam!" Mr. Rusk said, recalling the episode at his home in Stockton, Calif. "I sat there for about 15 minutes, kind of in shock. But everything felt fine. So I went and had lunch."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rusk, who is 71 and who figures the implant has saved his life six times in the last two years, is a living breathing symbol of a medical technology that developers say has a potential to help hundreds of thousands of people: the heart defibrillator.</p>
        <p>So far, only about 48,000 people have received defibrillators since their Federal approval in 1985. But the survival rate has been promising -- an estimated 35,000 recipients are still alive, some long enough to require replacement of their unit's five-year lithium batteries.</p>
        <p>Implantable defibrillators are costly, at about $20,000 for the device plus a comparable amount in hospital costs. But so far, government agencies and insurers have not balked at reimbursing the cost, and advances in the technology are expected to make hospital stays shorter and less expensive. Industry analysts project a $1 billion market for the devices by 1996, which at current prices would mean about 50,000 recipients a year.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Rusk's case demonstrates, defibrillators can keep people alive. Statistically, someone identified as a likely candidate for sudden cardiac arrest has only a 60 percent chance of living another year. But for a patient who receives a defibrillator, the odds of living a year rise to nearly 99 percent, said Kurt H. Kruger, a medical device analyst with Hambrecht &amp; Quist.</p>
        <p>"Without device intervention, one dies; with the device, one lives," he said. "There have been many successful medical devices in the last decade, but never has the grip of death been so strong and success of device intervention so clear."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rusk, a retired tire shop owner, had a heart attack in 1979 that left him with cardiac arrhythmia, an irregular heartbeat. It progressed to frequent bouts of ventricular tachycardia, a runaway rapid heartbeat that results in the body's getting insufficient blood. His condition deteriorated, and several times he found himself in a hospital emergency room, where medical workers revived him by placing electric paddles on his chest.</p>
        <p>He tried a series of drugs, some federally approved and some experimental, but all had unacceptable side effects. So, in 1989, he agreed to become the first patient to receive a new kind of implantable heart defribrillator made by Ventritex Inc.</p>
        <p>"It's the best thing I ever volunteered for," he said.</p>
        <p>The human heart is a pump, whose action is regulated by tiny electric currents produced by the heart itself. For people with dangerously irregular heartbeats, an implantable defib- rillator can monitor the condition and deliver electrical pulses or shocks as needed to the heart to correct ventricular tachycardia or to stop the even more dangerous condition known as ventricular fibrillation. In fibrillation, the heart beats in random shallow spasmodic pulses. Without rapid intervention, the patient can quickly go into sudden cardiac arrest. Many Deaths Called Preventable</p>
        <p>"This is a problem of enormous public health dimensions," said Dr. Jeremy Ruskin, director of the cardiac arrhythmia service at Massachusetts General Hospital.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ruskin noted that more than 300,000 people in the United States die of sudden cardiac arrest every year. "The bulk of these patients have underlying heart disease," he said, "but the fact remains that the bulk of them could have lived significantly longer -- decades -- if not for a sudden electrical catastrophe."</p>
        <p>The industry competitors range from tiny start-up companies to giants like the drug maker Eli Lilly &amp; Company and Medtronic Inc., the leading producer of heart pacemakers.</p>
        <p>Cardiac Pacemakers Inc., a unit of Lilly known as C.P.I., has been selling a defibrillator since 1985 that has been surgically implanted in more than 40,000 heart patients. Lilly itself has a more advanced device under development.</p>
        <p>Medtronic received approval last month from the Food and Drug Administration for a device based on technology newer than C.P.I.'s. And Ventritex Inc., a start-up in Sunnyvale, Calif., that developed the experimental defibrillator that Mr. Rusk received in 1989, is expected to receive F.D.A. approval soon to market the product. Other companies testing devices include Intermedics Inc., a maker of pacemakers based in Angleton, Tex., and Telectronics Pacing Systems Inc. of Australia.</p>
        <p>Both the Medtronic and Ventritex devices are third-generation defibrillators, more advanced than earlier ones. The Ventritex Cadence has more features than Medtronic's device, called the PCD. But the PCD weighs less, which is no small consideration in an implanted device. Medtronic intends to add features, which will increase the weight, and Ventritex is promising to trim its product's weight without removing features, so the two devices may become more similar.</p>
        <p>The C.P.I. product, known as the Ventak, can deliver only a high-energy shock, whereas both Ventritex's and Medtronic's devices can deliver so-called tiered therapy. For less extreme bouts of tachycardia, they can coax the heart back to a slower, regular rhythm by delivering a mild repeated dose of electric current that is similar to the amount of electricity that pacemakers send out constantly to speed chronically slow heartbeats in a technique known as pacing.</p>
        <p>If the gentle approach to tachycardia fails, the Ventritex and Medtronic devices can deliver ever-stronger jolts and as a last resort the "kick in the chest" shock needed to halt ventricular fibrillation.</p>
        <p>"Our device will intervene with pacing for certain kinds of arrhythmia and only will use high-energy shock if necessary," said B. Kristine Johnson, vice president and general manager of the tachycardia management business at Medtronic. "The opportunity to intervene quickly at the front end, means you can correct the rhythm and, in many cases, without the patient ever knowing it." Extra Features</p>
        <p>Because Ventritex is a much smaller and younger company, it has added a number of features in hopes of distinguishing the Cadence -- the company's first product -- from the device made by the better-known Medtronic. Cadence's features include the use of a "biphasic" electrical wave form, which delivers first a positive jolt of current, followed immediately by a negative one.</p>
        <p>A biphasic wave form "takes less energy to defibrillate the patient, so our device will be able to defibrillate a greater range of patients," said Frank M. Fischer, Ventritex's president and chief executive. Because too much energy can damage heart tissue, there are limits on the amount of current that defibrillators can deliver.</p>
        <p>Biphasic current will be even more important in the next generation of defribrillators, which will use transvenous leads, wires that enter the heart through veins, rather than electrical contacts that are sewn onto the outside of the heart, as with current models.</p>
        <p>Transvenous-lead systems can be implanted with a less invasive surgical procedure, but are less efficient because the points of contact with the heart are smaller; they inherently require more energy and will benefit from the lower energy requirements of the biphasic approach. Medtronic plans to include this feature in coming models that use transvenous leads.</p>
        <p>Ventritex's Cadence can also record "electrograms," which physicians can later look at on computers to analyze the electrical events that occurred before and after the cardiac episode.</p>
        <p>Ventritex executives say their product's most noteworthy feature is "continuous sensing," which lets the device abort the electrical shock at the last instant if the heart spontaneously returns to a proper rhythm. The abort function is possible because the capacitors in a defibrillator that deliver the shock take a few seconds to charge first, much like those in a photographic flash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fischer said the patient benefits from not receiving an unnecessary shock if the heart should regulate itself during this period. "High-voltage therapy is extremely painful," he said, "so delivering it unnecessarily is not acceptable to us."</p>
        <p>Medtronic's defibrillator does not have such a bailout mechanism, and Ms. Johnson of Medtronic said that was by design. "We don't want the device to stop and reconsider" before it administers therapy, she said.</p>
        <p>In any case, each product has the potential to save thousands of lives. The Ventritex and Medtronic defibrillators are "both superb devices," said Dr. Ruskin of Massachusetts General, who has installed 500 defibrillators in the last 10 years -- many of the early ones by C.P.I., but more recently using ones made by Ventritex and Medtronic, as well.</p>
        <p>Ken Rusk, who owes his life to his titanium box, is also among the believers. "I don't have to call 911 anymore," he said. "I carry it with me."  BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
