<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whittle Executive to Head Home Shopping Network</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOME SHOPPING NETWORK INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITTLE COMMUNICATIONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOGAN, GERALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPEER, ROY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DE123DF937A15751C0A965958260" item-length="333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whittle Executive to Head Home Shopping Network</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gerald Hogan, vice chairman of Whittle Communications, was named president and chief executive of Home Shopping Network Inc. yesterday.</p>
        <p>He will take over from Roy M. Speer, who sold his stake in Home Shopping Network to Liberty Media in December. Libery Media is seeking to buy the remaining Home Shopping shares. When he sold his stake, Mr. Speer said he planned to step down as president and chief executive but would remain chairman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gerald Hogan, vice chairman of Whittle Communications, was named president and chief executive of Home Shopping Network Inc. yesterday.</p>
        <p>He will take over from Roy M. Speer, who sold his stake in Home Shopping Network to Liberty Media in December. Libery Media is seeking to buy the remaining Home Shopping shares. When he sold his stake, Mr. Speer said he planned to step down as president and chief executive but would remain chairman.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department had said it would investigate the sale on antitrust grounds because Liberty Media also owned a stake in QVC Network Inc., the Home Shopping Network's main rival. But the department recently allowed the deal to go through.</p>
        <p>More than 65 million viewers receive the Home Shopping Network on broadcast and cable television.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hogan had been at Turner Broadcasting System Inc. for 19 years before joining Whittle. He was president of Turner Entertainment Networks. Mr. Hogan's work at Turner Broadcasting was primarily in sales. He was also involved in programming, including the start-up of Turner Network Television.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hogan said he left Whittle for the opportunity to run his own company and to work with John C. Malone, Liberty's chairman, and Peter R. Barton, Liberty's president.</p>
        <p>"When I came down and saw what was possible, I became very excited," Mr. Hogan said.</p>
        <p>Liberty and QVC have held discussions on a possible merger, but no decision has been reached.</p>
        <p>Fred Morans, who follows the cable-television industry for Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Inc, said a merger is extremely likely. He noted that other rival cable-television services, including CNBC and Financial News Network, had merged, as did comedy channels owned by Time Warner Inc. and Viacom International Inc.</p>
        <p>QVC is run by Barry Diller, the former chairman of the Fox network, who bought a stake in the company and agreed to vote his holdings together with both Liberty and the Comcast Corporation, the company's other largest shareholder.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
