<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli Expulsions Don't Break Geneva Accords</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEPORTATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEBANON</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HAMAS (ISLAMIC FUNDAMENTALIST MOVEMENT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EIDMAN, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC1F3AF937A15751C0A965958260" item-length="445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli Expulsions Don't Break Geneva Accords</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I take issue with "Israel Relents -- Will the Arabs?" (editorial, Feb. 3), in which you state that deportations of some 400 suspected Hamas terrorists "violated Geneva conventions on the treatment of civilians in occupied territories." A textual and contextual reading of the Geneva document illustrates that Israel's actions in the West Bank and Gaza Strip are consistent with both the letter and spirit of the relevant Convention articles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I take issue with "Israel Relents -- Will the Arabs?" (editorial, Feb. 3), in which you state that deportations of some 400 suspected Hamas terrorists "violated Geneva conventions on the treatment of civilians in occupied territories." A textual and contextual reading of the Geneva document illustrates that Israel's actions in the West Bank and Gaza Strip are consistent with both the letter and spirit of the relevant Convention articles.</p>
        <p>The Fourth Geneva Convention of 1949 was drawn up in the aftermath of the Nazi tactics in occupied Europe. Its second article reads: "The present convention shall apply to cases of partial or total occupation of the territory of a high contracting party." The territories conquered by Israel in the 1967 war did not belong to a high contracting party. Jordan's claim to the West Bank, which it seized in 1948, was recognized neither by the Arab states nor by any Western powers, save for Britain, and Egypt made no claim of sovereignty in the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>Article 49, on which the appeal by the deportees rested, was written in response to the widespread Nazi tactic of deporting civilians, sometimes communities, to German-controlled territory as slave labor or for extermination in concentration camps. It states that "individual or mass forcible transfers as well as deportations of protected persons from occupied territory to the territory of the occupying power, or to that of any other country, occupied or not, are prohibited, regardless of motive."</p>
        <p>Article 49 continues: "Nevertheless, the occupying power may undertake total or partial evacuation of a given area if the security of the population or imperative military reasons so demand."</p>
        <p>That the internationally respected justices of the Israeli High Court of Justice had little trouble in finding the Israeli Government's actions against the admitted members of Hamas consistent with the latter part of Article 49 of the convention should raise the eyebrows of no one familiar with the Hamas charter, which calls for destruction of the Jewish state. In attempting to fulfill this goal Hamas terrorists have spared neither Jewish civilians nor Arabs supportive of the peace process, in the occupied territories and Israel.</p>
        <p>While humanitarian concern, however misplaced, about the plight of the Hamas deportees is understandable, distortions and false assumptions about the legality of the actions of a democratic nation with a strong and independent judiciary must never be tolerated, much less repeated and perpetuated, by a publication with the international standing of The Times. STEVEN EIDMAN  Englewood, N.J., Feb. 10, 1993</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
