<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Halifax Journal; On a Paved Parking Lot, They Put Up a Paradise</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HALIFAX (NOVA SCOTIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GROUP OF SEVEN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Nova Scotia/Halifax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D61231F936A25755C0A963958260" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Halifax Journal; On a Paved Parking Lot, They Put Up a Paradise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>HALIFAX, Nova Scotia, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>First they paved the gravel parking lot, down along the Halifax waterfront. But the result was judged insufficiently pleasing for the important visitors scheduled to gather in the squat, green-tinted glass building overlooking it.</p>
        <p>So last weekend workers hastily covered the lot with sod, potted trees, flowering shrubs and pansies, geraniums and chrysanthemums in blue, red and yellow -- the colors of the official logo for the annual summit meeting of the Group of Seven major industrial nations, which begins here on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>First they paved the gravel parking lot, down along the Halifax waterfront. But the result was judged insufficiently pleasing for the important visitors scheduled to gather in the squat, green-tinted glass building overlooking it.</p>
        <p>So last weekend workers hastily covered the lot with sod, potted trees, flowering shrubs and pansies, geraniums and chrysanthemums in blue, red and yellow -- the colors of the official logo for the annual summit meeting of the Group of Seven major industrial nations, which begins here on Thursday.</p>
        <p>"It all comes away when the leaders leave," said Tom Gribbin, the landscape architect with Parks Canada who designed this pleasing if transient little summit park. "Still, I've had my moment of temporary gratification."</p>
        <p>Along the waterfront and elsewhere in downtown Halifax, a frenzy of planting, painting, repaving, pothole filling and prettifying construction work has local commentators making comparisons with the "Potemkin villages" put up by the favorite field marshal of Catherine the Great to impress her.</p>
        <p>"Potemkin couldn't teach Halifax a thing about putting on the dog," noted Jim Meek, columnist for The Halifax Chronicle-Herald.</p>
        <p>It would take a far greater effort to counter the overall down-at-the-heels look of this gritty, red-brick, often fog-bound port city, depressed in recent years by military cutbacks and the depletion of Atlantic fish stocks. The unemployment rate, above 9 percent, is nearly twice that of the United States.</p>
        <p>But not all the improvements are fake or temporary. Helped by provincial and federal treasuries, the city has pumped some $6 million into permanent waterfront recreation areas and seawalls, fresh streets and sidewalks, and new sidings and canopies for some of the more weatherworn buildings.</p>
        <p>Doug Grant, 70, a former coal miner who bought the Midtown Tavern and Grill in 1949, lucked out, he says, with an outer wall, burgundy and green, for his landmark establishment on Grafton Street.</p>
        <p>When construction crews tore up the road, he explained with a satisfied grin, they also had to install a new sidewalk. But in doing that they damaged his old siding, entitling him to a new one.</p>
        <p>If the summit meeting proves to be a news dud, it will at least be what Janice Manders, executive director of the Downtown Halifax Business Commission, describes as "the catalyst for civic revitalization."</p>
        <p>While giving a boost to Halifax, Prime Minister Jean Chretien, this year's host, has tried to tone down the extravagance of past summit meetings to make this one more businesslike and less ceremonial. He calls it a Chevrolet as opposed to a Cadillac summit. Yet some Canadian officials fret that all the penny-pinching will relegate it in history books as the "Chevette summit."</p>
        <p>In keeping with fiscal prudence, the two negotiating tables, both cherry wood, one that seats at least 9 and the other at least 30, have been borrowed from Italy and recycled from last year's meeting in Naples.</p>
        <p>Canada also asked each country to keep its delegations to a minimum. Only 1,500 officials are expected, about half the number at Naples. The press, 2,000 strong, will be only one-third the Naples contingent.</p>
        <p>The talks are being held on vacant floors of that squat green glass building, recently renamed Summit Place but more familiarly known to Haligonians as the Green Toad. Normally it is used by Kodak Canada as an office building.</p>
        <p>Also to check costs, which are running less than the $25 million Canada spent on its last go-around, in 1988 in Toronto, the Government has allowed private companies to "sponsor" the meeting by providing food and services in return for advertising before a global audience. About 100 companies, from Jost Vineyards offering a selection of Nova Scotia wines to McCain Foods distributing snack foods in news center, have signed up.</p>
        <p>Tourism boosters are elated at the chance to promote the rich culture of Canada's sparsely settled Celtic heartland. Only a million people live in Nova Scotia, of whom about a third are in the Halifax area.</p>
        <p>At least 2,000 policemen -- the precise number is a guarded secret -- are also on hand to provide security.</p>
        <p>A 250-acre area near the waterfront, the "red zone," including the six hotels housing the leaders, is cordoned off by six-foot steel-and-concrete barricades and mesh fences. Only those with highest security clearance get inside.</p>
        <p>To add even more security, the Royal Canadian Mounted Police have spent the last two days welding manhole covers, carting away mailboxes and vending machines and assigning snipers to rooftops.</p>
        <p>A no-flight zone is being maintained around the harbor. Ten percent of the harbor is closed to vessels, enforced by a flotilla of police boats and navy minesweepers. Helicopters and planes scan the city virtually round the clock.</p>
        <p>At their Halifax headquarters, the Mounties have a high-tech command center using newly installed security cameras to monitor everything that happens in each of the buildings where summit activities take place -- and to lock a building electronically should a security breach occur.</p>
        <p>In addition, frogmen have had to secure the harbor's spewing sewer pipes against any terrorists. Halifax still dumps unprocessed sludge into its harbor on the theory that tides take it out to sea. One of the outfall pipes is only a few yards away from where Mr. Chretien is to welcome his guests as they are ferried across the harbor after landing at the Shearwater Canadian Forces base about six and half miles away.</p>
        <p>Diving in the harbor, and especially entering those sewer pipes, acknowledged Inspector Terry Elliott, the Mounties' deputy commander of summit security, "is not an enviable job."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
