<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Common Cause Backs Inquiry Into Gingrich's Book Deal</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="741215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMON CAUSE (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (SPEAKER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WRIGHT, JIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DA1F3FF930A35751C0A963958260" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Common Cause Backs Inquiry Into Gingrich's Book Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Common Cause, the public affairs lobbying group, called today for an outside ethics adviser to examine House Speaker Newt Gingrich's book deal and recommend whether the House ethics committee should allow it or not.</p>
        <p>Common Cause's request, made in a letter to the ethics panel, is significant because it was the group's urging in 1988 for similar action in the case of former House Speaker Jim Wright that eventually turned the tide against Mr. Wright.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Common Cause, the public affairs lobbying group, called today for an outside ethics adviser to examine House Speaker Newt Gingrich's book deal and recommend whether the House ethics committee should allow it or not.</p>
        <p>Common Cause's request, made in a letter to the ethics panel, is significant because it was the group's urging in 1988 for similar action in the case of former House Speaker Jim Wright that eventually turned the tide against Mr. Wright.</p>
        <p>Common Cause joins a growing list of those calling for some sort of independent evaluation of the book contract.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich agreed last fall to a $4.5 million advance from HarperCollins, whose owner, Rupert Murdoch's global media empire, has telecommunications matters worth billions of dollars before the Government.</p>
        <p>Under pressure, Mr. Gingrich later spurned the advance but said he would take the standard percentage of whatever royalties the book earned. This could still win him millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Fred Wertheimer, president of Common Cause, said the group was calling for the action now because it was important to examine the public record surrounding the deal before Mr. Gingrich actually signs a contract. Mr. Gingrich has said he would submit the contract to the ethics committee for review once he signs it, but Mr. Wertheimer said it was important that an outside evaluation is essential.</p>
        <p>Tony Blankley, Mr. Gingrich's press secretary, said there was no comparison between Mr. Wright's activities and Mr. Gingrich's. He said the questions raised about Mr. Gingrich's book "are frivolous allegations being driven by his former political opponent," a reference to Ben Jones, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Citing House rules, the Common Cause letter said members must avoid the appearance of impropriety. It quoted the House ethics manual as saying members "should not seek private gain from public office."</p>
        <p>It also quoted Mr. Gingrich himself, whose relentless push for an outside investigation against Mr. Wright led to the former Speaker's resignation. In making his case in 1988, Mr. Gingrich said the Speaker, who is second in line to be President after the Vice President, should be held to a higher standard than other House members.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Gingrich also praised Common Cause for joining the chorus of questioners over Mr. Wright's activities, saying the ethics committee should not have sole control over the scope of the investigation.</p>
        <p>Citing today's Common Cause letter, a group of five Democrats reiterated their calls for an outside investigation. Representative Richard J. Durbin of Illinois noted that the Speaker's pollsters frequently rely on focus groups to determine policy and challenged those pollsters to discuss the book deal with a focus group and let it decide whether an outside counsel should be appointed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
