<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Is Apprehensive After Bullpen Workout</title>
    <meta content="10CONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stottlemyre, Mel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torre, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DE1539F933A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Is Apprehensive After Bullpen Workout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Sept. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher David Cone, with team doctor, team trainer, Manager Joe Torre and pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre scrutinizing every pitch and every movement, works off bullpen mound at Fenway Park to test his sore shoulder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the team doctor, the team trainer, Manager Joe Torre and the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre scrutinizing every pitch and every movement David Cone made, the valuable and vulnerable Yankee worked off a bullpen mound at Fenway Park yesterday and tried to determine whether he can still be a factor this season. All four Yankee employees held their breath.</p>
        <p>After Cone tested every pitch in his repertory in a session that lasted between 12 and 13 minutes and reported no pain from the tendinitis in his right shoulder, the four observers exhaled. For now. Torre and Dr. Stuart Hershon were excited, while Cone was pleased but cautious about totally overcoming the nagging case of tendinitis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the team doctor, the team trainer, Manager Joe Torre and the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre scrutinizing every pitch and every movement David Cone made, the valuable and vulnerable Yankee worked off a bullpen mound at Fenway Park yesterday and tried to determine whether he can still be a factor this season. All four Yankee employees held their breath.</p>
        <p>After Cone tested every pitch in his repertory in a session that lasted between 12 and 13 minutes and reported no pain from the tendinitis in his right shoulder, the four observers exhaled. For now. Torre and Dr. Stuart Hershon were excited, while Cone was pleased but cautious about totally overcoming the nagging case of tendinitis.</p>
        <p>''Right now, it's the best he's felt since he's been on the disabled list, as far as throwing sessions,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Hershon added: ''We're encouraged. All in all, it was a good day for the Yankees.''</p>
        <p>So why is Cone still not smiling? Although Cone conceded that he made progress because he felt ''much freer,'' the pitcher continued to speak more conservatively about his comeback than Yankee officials. Cone said he did not ''air it out'' by throwing at his peak velocity and contradicted Torre by saying he will probably need two more workouts, as opposed to the one that the manager mentioned as a tentative schedule.</p>
        <p>''I'm still a little apprehensive,'' Cone said. ''I've already had one setback in this process. I want to guard against another setback. In that sense, I'm really pleased. I'm ready for the next step on Friday.''</p>
        <p>Cone will simulate a real game by sitting after a certain number of pitches Friday and then resuming his workout, and Torre speculated that he may be able to then start against Detroit on Sept. 17, if he does not incur a setback. But Cone claimed he would probably want a tuneup outing after Friday's session and instead spoke about starting on Sept. 19.</p>
        <p>''I think it's still too early to speculate,'' said Cone, when asked about starting. ''I still have a ways to go.''</p>
        <p>Torre lauded Cone's freedom in his pitching motion, something he had not seen since the pitcher left a game against the Texas Rangers on Aug. 17 with the tendinitis. Cone felt stiffness and lacked freedom when he quit a three-inning simulated game after two in Philadelphia on Sept. 2, which is why he is so cautious about making it back.</p>
        <p>''The best thing I saw was no effort,'' Torre said. ''In Philadelphia, he was carrying it. Today, he was finishing up all his pitches.''</p>
        <p>After first saying today's test would ultimately decide his immediate future, Cone altered his outlook and said that Friday would be the critical test because he would try to throw ''longer and harder.'' Cone, who said he was not considering a second cortisone shot at this point because of his promising workout, admitted that he will really not know how his shoulder responds until Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say that I'm out of the woods yet,'' said Cone. ''Today was definitely progress.''</p>
        <p>But, no matter how cautious Cone acted, it was a promising day for the Yankees. Cone did not walk off the mound holding his arm. He did not abandon his workout early. He is still moving forward.</p>
        <p>''I feel good that he feels good,'' Torre said. ''You never really know. You don't want to get your hopes up too high.''</p>
        <p>Everyone from the owner George Steinbrenner to General Manager Bob Watson to Andy Pettitte to Paul O'Neill have expressed how important it is for Cone to pitch again, because the Yankees are not as formidable without him. Cone surely realizes this, but he did not want to dwell on it.</p>
        <p>''I'd hate to think there's that much pressure on me,'' Cone said, perhaps naively. ''That's why I came here. That's why I wanted to be a Yankee, to pitch in big games. I'm about as desperate to come back as they Yankees are to have me back. This might be the last chance to pitch in the post-season. You don't get that many chances.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
