<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PNC Bank Buying Sears Loan Unit</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="608405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEARS ROEBUCK &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PNC BANK CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANSELL, SAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D7153DF931A25756C0A965958260" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PNC Bank Buying Sears Loan Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANSELL, SAUL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company said yesterday that it would sell its large mortgage banking company for $329 million in cash to the PNC Bank Corporation, which is as eager to diversify as Sears is to return to its core retail business.</p>
        <p>Like Sears before it, PNC sees the mortgage operation as a way to add new sources of revenue. Many commercial banks, including PNC, are looking to expand income from fees, like servicing home loans, to compensate for slow loan growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company said yesterday that it would sell its large mortgage banking company for $329 million in cash to the PNC Bank Corporation, which is as eager to diversify as Sears is to return to its core retail business.</p>
        <p>Like Sears before it, PNC sees the mortgage operation as a way to add new sources of revenue. Many commercial banks, including PNC, are looking to expand income from fees, like servicing home loans, to compensate for slow loan growth.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh-based PNC is the nation's 10th-largest banking company and will vault into the top ranks of mortgage companies with the addition of Sears Mortgage, which is the 15th-largest company in the nation in servicing home loans. Back to Basics</p>
        <p>In the late 1970's and early 1980's, Sears built a one-stop financial supermarket with insurance, brokerage, credit cards and real estate services. Its mortgage unit tapped into the Coldwell Banker residential real estate division, which accounted for one-third of its new mortgages.</p>
        <p>Last year, however, under intense pressure from dissident shareholders, Sears decided to spin off most of its financial services empire. It has already sold part of its Dean Witter, Discover investment and credit card unit in a public stock offering.</p>
        <p>PNC, by contrast, has been rapidly expanding, largely by buying banks, and in doing so it has been pushed further into the mortgage business.</p>
        <p>"Every time we buy a small bank, we end up generating another $600 million worth of mortgage servicing," said James E. Rohr, PNC's president. "We had to think about how strategically to take advantage of that."</p>
        <p>On the New York Stock Exchange yesterday, Sears stock gained 37.5 cents, to $54.50, and PNC gained $1, to $32.125. High-Volume Business</p>
        <p>Buying Sears Mortgage will give PNC high volume in a business where the largest players have substantially lower costs. Sears generated $12 billion in home loans last year, finishing seventh in the country, the company said. It handles the servicing, which is billing and record keeping, for $27 billion in mortgages, the 15th-largest portfolio. Sears Mortgage had net income of $52 million last year.</p>
        <p>Because most home loans are packaged and sold to investors as securities, the profits from mortgage banking stem largely from servicing fees, which amount annually to about one-quarter to one-third of a percent of the mortgage. PNC's mortgage unit originated $1.9 billion in mortgages last year and serviced $9 billion in loans.</p>
        <p>PNC is also buying Sears Savings Bank, a California institution with $6.7 billion in large mortgages.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
