<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FAMILY FARE</title>
    <meta content="11FAMI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/11/arts/11FAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588439"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Family Fare"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oberfelder, Jody, Dance Projects</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orisha Tales Repertory Company</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dancewave (Dance Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chagall, Marc (1889-1995)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Obatala (King of the White Cloth) (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DB1430F932A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FAMILY FARE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Swirls of Chagall</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laurel Graeber Family Fare column on dance performance by Jody Oberfelder Dance Products inspired by Chagall's paintings at Jewish Museum, Orisha Tales Repertory Company performance of Obatala (King of the White Cloth) and Dancewave's Kids Company Spring Celebration in Brooklyn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Swirls Of Chagall</p>
        <p>The figures in Chagall's paintings often look whimsically adrift, floating like balloons that a spring breeze has tugged from a child's hand. Jody Oberfelder has recreated those images, using a medium that is known for its own dips, twirls, leaps and flights of fancy: dance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jody Oberfelder has recreated the painter's whimsically adrift figures in a dance piece called "Landmarks of Dreams," to be shown on Sunday at the Jewish Museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Swirls Of Chagall</p>
        <p>The figures in Chagall's paintings often look whimsically adrift, floating like balloons that a spring breeze has tugged from a child's hand. Jody Oberfelder has recreated those images, using a medium that is known for its own dips, twirls, leaps and flights of fancy: dance.</p>
        <p>Appropriately titled ''Landmarks of Dreams,'' Ms. Oberfelder's piece will be presented on Sunday at the Jewish Museum. Adapted from a work her company, Jody Oberfelder Dance Projects, performed last winter at the Joyce SoHo, this 45-minute production has been edited for children, emphasizing the festive and fantastical elements in Chagall's work rather than the occasionally nightmarish ones.</p>
        <p>''His iconographic sensibility had to do with seeing the magic in the universe,'' Ms. Oberfelder said.</p>
        <p>In addition to using lifts, leaps and a trapeze dance sans trapeze, she has incorporated visual illusions. Pamela Crimmins took slides of the dancers moving underwater, and B. Wurtz, an artist, replaced the liquid backgrounds with tints. In one case he combined two images of Ms. Oberfelder, so she appears to be gazing at herself floating in an atmosphere of color. Used as backdrops for a solo, the slides heighten the feeling of being inside a painting.</p>
        <p>The performance will also feature a new cast member: Lisa Gutkin, a violinist with the Klezmatics, who will move as she plays. The remaining music, all recorded, includes klezmer by Frank London, theremin themes by Rob Schwimmer and circusy pieces by Edward Ratliff.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Oberfelder was inspired by specific Chagall works, like ''The Fiddler,'' ''The Promenade'' and ''A Midsummer Night's Dream,'' she said the dance was more like a collage of his motifs. And youngsters do not need to know Chagall's work to enjoy it. ''Children are naturally kinetic beings,'' she said. Not to mention natural dreamers.</p>
        <p>''Landmarks of Dreams,'' Sunday at 2 p.m. at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3337. Tickets: $10.</p>
        <p>Spirited Fun</p>
        <p>If you think Zeus, Hera and the other residents of Mount Olympus are a capricious and contentious lot, you should meet the Orishas. And you can do so tonight.</p>
        <p>That's when the Orisha Tales Repertory Company will perform ''Obatala (King of the White Cloth),'' a theater and dance piece dramatizing a creation myth from the Oruba people of West Africa. The opening event in the Riverside Church's free monthlong New York Family Arts Festival, the show will introduce several Orishas, beings who represent aspects of God or nature, explained David Wright, who wrote ''Obatala.'' Often manifested as people, they sometimes exhibit human frailties.</p>
        <p>This piece focuses on Obatala (oh-BAHT-a-lah), the chief Orisha. ''This is a senior citizens' love story,'' Mr. Wright said, ''because he comes to the world as an old man. He finds his first love, Yemmu, who is close to middle-aged. She is an Orisha, too.''</p>
        <p>Obatala is told by a diviner that he should go to earth on a golden chain, with a chicken and a snail shell full of dirt. When the chain proves too short for a smooth landing, ''he spills out the dirt, then drops the chicken, who spreads it all around,'' Mr. Wright said. ''That is how the land is formed.'' Later he and Yemmu create humans from clay and water.</p>
        <p>The piece includes battles with Olokun, Obatala's envious brother, and also touches on the incest taboo and the origins of menstruation. But it has no explicit representations of violence or sexuality, said Mr. Wright, who recommends it for children old enough to enjoy a two-hour drama. During part of it youngsters will be asked to supply sound effects, like thunder and scratching.</p>
        <p>''It's actually a morality piece,'' Mr. Wright said. ''All the pieces I've written are about awapele, which means good character.''</p>
        <p>''Obatala,'' tonight at 7:30 at the Theater of the Riverside Church, 91 Claremont Avenue, at 120th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 870-6784.</p>
        <p>A Real Song and Dance</p>
        <p>Dancers normally perform with their feet. But tomorrow the young members of Dancewave's Kids Company will use their throats, too.</p>
        <p>At the company's spring celebration, they will offer ''Calling,'' a song by Meredith Monk. Inspired by animal calls, the piece includes a little movement but is largely vocalization.</p>
        <p>''Meredith's music is unusual,'' said Diane Jacobowitz, the troupe's artistic director. ''But I'm teaching the kids about so many aspects of dance that we sort of crossed over into performance art with this one.''</p>
        <p>It won't be the evening's only surprise. The dancers will perform Trisha Brown's ''Sololos,'' in which they must respond to a caller who randomly asks individual dancers to reverse their steps. A trio of boys will also do a dance improvisation. Although the piece has a framework, ''it's different every time they do it,'' Ms. Jacobowitz said.</p>
        <p>Kids Company specializes in asking youngsters to think on their feet. The members, all 11 to 18, learn pieces by renowned choreographers. Tomorrow's celebration will also include ''Polka'' by Mark Morris, ''See Level'' by David Dorfman and ''Strict Love'' by Doug Varone.</p>
        <p>''It's a really interesting program for both young and older kids,'' Ms. Jacobowitz said. ''It's so inspiring for kids to see other kids dance.''</p>
        <p>Kids Company Spring Celebration, tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. at the BRIC Studio, 57 Rockwell Place, near Fulton Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 522-4696. Tickets: $16; 12 and under, $12. Reservations required.</p>
        <p>Family Fare</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
