<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Council Tightens a Law On Campaign Disclosures</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="704218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOROUGH PRESIDENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAYORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC ADVOCATE (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPTROLLERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HICKS, JONATHAN P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DF1031F936A3575BC0A962958260" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Council Tightens a Law On Campaign Disclosures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HICKS, JONATHAN P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The City Council agreed yesterday to tighten the city's campaign finance law by requiring candidates for citywide offices and the borough presidencies to make more frequent reports about their spending and the money they take in.</p>
        <p>The measure, which was approved 36 to 9, would not apply to City Council members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The City Council agreed yesterday to tighten the city's campaign finance law by requiring candidates for citywide offices and the borough presidencies to make more frequent reports about their spending and the money they take in.</p>
        <p>The measure, which was approved 36 to 9, would not apply to City Council members.</p>
        <p>Peter F. Vallone, the Council Speaker, said the measure was "a good bill because the citywide candidates should have no problem complying with it." It would apply to candidates for mayor, public advocate, city comptroller and borough presidents.</p>
        <p>Those jobs, Mr. Vallone said, "tend to be where all the money goes, anyway." The Council members were not included, he said, because "it would be an unnecessary burden for them and they don't have the resources to hire the accountants and the staff to prepare the material necessary for filing." Source of Dissent</p>
        <p>But it was the exemption of candidates for City Council that was the source of the dissent for most of the nine -- six Democrats and three Republicans -- who voted against the bill. "If this reform is good enough for the mayor, good enough for the comptroller and good enough for the borough presidents, it ought to be good enough for us," said Charles Millard, a Republican from the East Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The bill is the Council's latest response to new rules adopted earlier this year by the Campaign Finance Board. The rules would have required candidates for all city offices to file regular campaign finance reports twice a year, throughout the four-year election cycle, instead of waiting until June 1 of the election year.</p>
        <p>During the budget negotiations, the Council passed a bill to block the rules, prompting Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who favored more frequent disclosure of financial reports, to say he might veto it. Yesterday's bill represents a compromise.</p>
        <p>Leaders of civic groups applauded the measure, even as they faulted the Council for excluding itself. "Overall, it's a net plus," said Chris Meyer, a lawyer with the New York Public Interest Research Group. "But we are extremely disappointed that the Council chose to exclude itself from the requirements."</p>
        <p>Nicole A. Gordon, executive director of the Campaign Finance Board, said the new rules would provide a systematic flow of information, which the board could process throughout the four-year election cycle rather than in a single barrage before an election. Such a filing system, she said, would be easier for candidates, since it would require them to compile information every six months, rather than seeking to assemble more than three years' worth of records at once.</p>
        <p>"The rules would improve the quality of public disclosure, simplify reporting tasks for candidates and protect taxpayer dollars," she said.</p>
        <p>The Council also passed a resolution yesterday condemning remarks by Deputy Mayor John S. Dyson over the hiring of a second financial adviser to the city. Mr. Dyson had suggested that racial preference had been the basis of the desire by Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi to retain the adviser, the black-owned Philadelphia firm P. G. Corbin &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The issue became more highly charged when Mr. Dyson disputed Mr. Hevesi's contention that the cost would be the same whether the city used one financial adviser or two. He said that Mr. Hevesi "ought to know the difference between a bid and a watermelon." Mr. Dyson apologized later for the comment.</p>
        <p>The resolution passed by the Council yesterday called on Mr. Dyson "to issue a clear, strong and explicit apology to P. G. Corbin and the African-American community."</p>
        <p>The resolution called on the Mayor and the Comptroller to retain two companies and for the Council to conduct hearings on the participation of black and Hispanic companies in providing financial advice and services.</p>
        <p>In a rebuke to Mr. Giuliani, the Council's Finance Committee also put off a vote on the Mayor's request that the budget be modified to account for $14 million in unexpected spending by the Police Department, half of it from overtime costs.</p>
        <p>The committee chairman, Herbert E. Berman, criticized the Mayor's office for underestimating the costs of overtime in the budget for the fiscal year that ended in June and for the new fiscal year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berman, whose criticisms were echoed by other Democrats on the committee, said the committee would not approve the modification until the Mayor's Office of Budget Management explained how the Police Department could keep its costs within budget.</p>
        <p>"It's just unacceptable," he said.  "It's not truth in budgeting. We have to deal with truth in budgeting."</p>
        <p>Fiscal monitors -- the City Comptroller, State Comptroller and the State Financial Control Board -- have also been critical of the Mayor for not including enough money for overtime costs in the current budget.</p>
        <p>The postponement yesterday involved last year's budget. The city will have to dip into its general reserves for the unbudgeted $14 million for the Police Department, which included $7 million in overtime, $3 million in holiday pay and shift differential and $3 million in nonpersonnel items.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
