<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Retailers, Few Patterns In July Sales</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="704226"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALOMON BROTHERS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STROM, STEPHANIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DF1031F936A3575BC0A962958260" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Retailers, Few Patterns In July Sales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STROM, STEPHANIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation's large retail chains reported a grab bag of sales results in July, giving little indication of where sales are heading.</p>
        <p>"The trend in July is no trend," said Susan Silverstein, a retail analyst at Gruntal &amp; Company. "Sales are really all over the board."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nation's large retail chains reported a grab bag of sales results in July, giving little indication of where sales are heading.</p>
        <p>"The trend in July is no trend," said Susan Silverstein, a retail analyst at Gruntal &amp; Company. "Sales are really all over the board."</p>
        <p>The Salomon Brothers same-store sales index, a weighted average of the same-store sales of 22 retailers, rose 3.9 percent in July, compared with 5.8 percent in June and 5.7 percent in July 1993. Same-store sales, also known as comparable-store sales, are those at stores open at least a year.</p>
        <p>Analysts do not usually read much into retailers' July sales because the month is traditionally used to clear out spring merchandising mistakes in preparation for the fall season. 'A Transitional Month'</p>
        <p>This year, however, many retailers said strong sales in June, coupled with lean inventories, left them with little clearance merchandise to drive sales last month. That may bode well for their second-quarter profits, although many retail analysts have shaved their earnings estimates in the last couple of weeks.</p>
        <p>"There was no significant news in July, which is a transitional month -- except that most retailers ended up with clean inventories and got a jump on fall a little early," said Jeffrey M. Feiner, a retail analyst at Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Extending a pattern that has persisted for more than a year, shoppers punished most apparel retailers. But companies that balance their apparel offerings by selling housewares, gardening gear, consumer electronics and other hard goods fared better. Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company's merchandise group said it sold more appliances during the last week of July than in any other week in its history.</p>
        <p>In general, discounters and department stores did better than clothing stores. Comparable-store sales climbed 8.9 percent at Wal-Mart's discount stores, although weak performance at the company's warehouse clubs lowered the overall same-store sales increase to 5.8 percent. Same-store sales rose 9 percent at Target, the Dayton Hudson Corporation's discount chain.</p>
        <p>Analysts regard same-store sales as the best measure of a retailer's performance because they eliminate the effect of new stores. A Federated Surprise</p>
        <p>Same-store sales rose 5 percent at May Department Stores' chains, while Federated Department Stores Inc., which operates Bloomingdale's and Abraham &amp; Straus, surprised itself and Wall Street with a 3.2 percent same-store sales jump. Dayton Hudson's department store division, which operates Marshall Field's, Dayton's and Hudson's, saw its comparable-store sales rise 6 percent.</p>
        <p>Those companies that depend on apparel sales had a harder time. The Gap Inc. said its comparable-store sales increased just 1 percent in July, while the Limited Inc. posted an 8 percent drop in its same-store sales. Even Talbots Inc., whose double-digit increases have been the envy of the retail industry for months, saw its same-store sales slip 4.1 percent last month.</p>
        <p>The Ann Taylor Corporation, however, posted a 17 percent increase in same-store sales last month, in part because it shifted some promotions from August into July. But over all, the company had an outstanding performance, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Some expect apparel sales to pick up this fall, as stores introduce new designs, new fabrics and new colors without raising prices. Many retailers have brought fall merchandise in early this year in hopes of jump-starting apparel sales.</p>
        <p>But higher interest rates are likely to slow sales of houses, which in turn will slow purchases of the home-related merchandise and hard goods that have been lifting sales at many retail chains for almost two years.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Retailers' Sales Detailed</p>
        <p>By The Associated Press</p>
        <p>Here are the domestic July sales reported yesterday by some of the nation's largest retailers:</p>
        <p>Dayton Hudson Corp.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 6.8 percent. Overall sales totaled $1.41 billion, up 13.8 percent from $1.24 billion.</p>
        <p>Federated Department Stores</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 3.2 percent. Overall sales totaled $416.4 million, up 8.8 percent from $382.6 million.</p>
        <p>Gap Inc.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 1 percent. Overall sales totaled $223 million, up 12 percent from $199 million.</p>
        <p>Kmart Corp.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended June 27: Same-store sales fell 0.1 percent. Overall sales totaled $2.63 billion, up 4.7 percent from $2.51 billion.</p>
        <p>Limited Inc.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales fell 8 percent. Overall sales totaled $455.2 million, up 1 percent from $450.6 million.</p>
        <p>May Department Stores</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 3 percent. Overall sales totaled $728.4 million, up 6.3 percent from $685.1 million.</p>
        <p>J. C. Penney Co.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 6 percent at Penney stores only.  Overall sales totaled $1.25 billion, up 6.8 percent from $1.17 billion. (Overall sales include J. C. Penney, drugstores and catalogue.)</p>
        <p>Sears, Roebuck &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Four weeks ended July 30: Same-store sales rose 5.2 percent. Overall sales totaled $2.44 billion, up 5.4 percent from $2.32 billion.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Stores Inc.</p>
        <p>Month of July: Same-store sales rose 5.8 percent. Overall sales totaled $6.63 billion, up 22 percent from $5.44 billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
