<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases;As Family Falters, a Father Worries</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="821960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK TIMES NEEDIEST CASES FUND</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CATHOLIC CHARITIES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADDELL, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DE1039F932A25752C0A960958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases;As Family Falters, a Father Worries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WADDELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WADDELL, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five-year-old Luis Arnold Muller was building a castle, stacking blocks one by one. Then, as easily as he built his creation, he toppled it. Then he started the cycle over.</p>
        <p>Watching his son, Jose Muller said he realized that he, too, was rebuilding fallen blocks -- trying to pull together the life of his family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five-year-old Luis Arnold Muller was building a castle, stacking blocks one by one. Then, as easily as he built his creation, he toppled it. Then he started the cycle over.</p>
        <p>Watching his son, Jose Muller said he realized that he, too, was rebuilding fallen blocks -- trying to pull together the life of his family.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muller came to the United States from Bolivia when he was 14 and served  as an Army cook in Saigon during the Vietnam War. "I was wounded twice," he said. Nonetheless, he remembers his Army days as the best time of his life.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, Mr. Muller took a trip to Ecuador and met the woman who is now his wife. They courted for 20 days and were then married. A year later, his son  was born. "She gave me a look," he said. "It felt like a cupid's arrow in my heart. I never thought I would start a family."</p>
        <p>In 1990, Mr. Muller took his bride and child to his mother's home in Switzerland. "We were both from Latin America, so Switzerland was a novelty," he said, "but after a while, the fact that it snows the whole time gets to you."</p>
        <p>After two years abroad, he and his family moved to a small, cramped room in Woodside, Queens. He was working sporadically as a security guard and lacked the money to move into an apartment. So he turned to Catholic Charities of Brooklyn  and Queens for help. The agency provided the $380 he needed as a security deposit.</p>
        <p>Catholic Charities of Brooklyn and Queens receives donations from The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund, now in its 84th year. Since The Times pays the overhead, contributions to the campaign go directly to the charities.</p>
        <p>The move helped the family through a tough time, but did not solve all their  problems. After five years of family life, Mr. Muller said, things went sour. His wife asked him for a divorce last February, and he is now most concerned for his son.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muller and his wife tried to make this Christmas as memorable as possible, for their son's sake. Luis's greatest interest at the moment is Batman. As he played with his toys, he listened occasionally as his father talked grown-up talk with a visitor. Luis perked up when he overheard that his parents had decided to get him mostly clothes and one toy each.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes, she tells me she's going to take our son and disappear," Mr. Muller said of his wife. "I say what's the use, maybe I should grab a gun and take revenge. Then I say, 'What would happen to my son?' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Muller said that in spite of everything, he feels lucky. He looks forward to seeing his mother when she visits from Switzerland this year. And Mr. Muller  is grateful to be working steadily as a home health attendant and going to school to study computers.</p>
        <p>"My life does look like a soap opera, doesn't it?" Mr. Muller said.  "Life looks like a soap opera, but the thing, the damage done to persons are a lot more severe in real life than on television.</p>
        <p>"An actor gets killed on one soap opera, then the following week he's working on another soap opera. In real life, there's no turning around."</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O.  Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE 285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK 1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS 191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201. CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY 105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK 105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES 281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y.  10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK 130 East 59th Street, Room 427, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
