<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington to New York on 4.3 Gallons</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="402660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUZUKI MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D8163BF932A15752C1A966958260" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington to New York on 4.3 Gallons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some drivers are not willing to trade size and smooth ride for fuel economy, but for those who are, no car sold in the United States gets better gasoline mileage than the Geo Metro. On a recent drive from Washington to New York, the car, made in Japan by the Suzuki Motor Company and sold by the General Motors Corporation, consumed 4.3 gallons, which comes to 58 miles a gallon.</p>
        <p>The Metro's fuel economy, as determined by the Environmental Protection Agency, is 54 miles a gallon. The average car on the road in 1990 gets 20 miles a gallon, according to the Department of Energy. If every car did as well as the Metro, gasoline consumption, now about 7.3 million barrels a day, would fall to 2.7 million barrels a day, a drop of 4.6 million barrels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some drivers are not willing to trade size and smooth ride for fuel economy, but for those who are, no car sold in the United States gets better gasoline mileage than the Geo Metro. On a recent drive from Washington to New York, the car, made in Japan by the Suzuki Motor Company and sold by the General Motors Corporation, consumed 4.3 gallons, which comes to 58 miles a gallon.</p>
        <p>The Metro's fuel economy, as determined by the Environmental Protection Agency, is 54 miles a gallon. The average car on the road in 1990 gets 20 miles a gallon, according to the Department of Energy. If every car did as well as the Metro, gasoline consumption, now about 7.3 million barrels a day, would fall to 2.7 million barrels a day, a drop of 4.6 million barrels.</p>
        <p>Last year, imports averaged 8.1 million barrels a day, so such a switch -- if not accompanied by an increase in the number of cars or the average number of miles each was driven -- would cut imports by more than half. High Technology</p>
        <p>The Metro does the job through high technology and plain old shrinkage. The Metro weighs 1,600 pounds, halfway between an intermediate car and a bicycle.</p>
        <p>Part of the weight loss is from the engine, which is a mere 157 pounds. It is made of aluminum and has three cylinders. (Dropping the fourth cylinder adds six miles a gallon, G.M. engineers say.) To compensate for its small size, the engine squeezes the fuel-air mixture to nine times atmospheric pressure before lighting the spark, a higher ratio than in most cars, allowing more horsepower for each pound of engine weight.</p>
        <p>The five-speed manual transmission is wired to a light on the dashboard that reminds the driver when to shift up. The light urges shifting when revolutions per minute are low relative to when most drivers would shift on their own. That raises mileage at the expense of performance.</p>
        <p>With its low weight, the car does not need power steering, which adds weight to other cars. The copy that General Motors keeps for test drives lacks even ordinary refinements like a passenger-side mirror and a rear-window defogger.</p>
        <p>The model driven to Washington had an ashtray but no lighter, and no radio. And while plusher versions are available, the Metro is designed as a price leader as well as a mileage leader. The Metro is the least expensive model in the Geo line, with a list price for the 1990 version at just under $6,000.</p>
        <p>The car handles nimbly and its performance is nothing special, a compliment for a car with mileage 200 percent over average. Pulling from a line of stopped traffic on the Baltimore-Washington Parkway into the adjacent lane, where the traffic was moving at about 50 miles an hour, the Metro performed much as any other small car would. Coming out of the toll booth at the Baltimore Harbor Tunnel, it reached 55 miles an hour in about 15 seconds, as fast as other cars were accelerating.</p>
        <p>It does this on 58 horsepower, about half the average. But it does leave the driver feeling in much more intimate contact with the road and all of its bumps. And designers have shrunk the back seat to a size functional for no one but small children.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
