<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earnings Fall At Times Co. But Increase At Gannett</title>
    <meta content="13TIME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/13/business/13times.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1573809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gannett Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Jacques</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Russell T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccorkindale, Douglas H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Times</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Gannett Company Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DE1F38F930A25757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earnings Fall At Times Co. But Increase At Gannett</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Earnings Fall at Times Co. but Increase at Gannett</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinberg, Jacques</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times Co and Gannett Co report newspaper advertising climate is showing steady signs of growth so far this year; Gannett reports gain in earnings, while New York Times shows decline; Times Co posts first-quarter net income of $58.4 million, down 15.1 percent from year ago, when it reported profit of $68.8 million; revenue rose 2.3 percent, to $801.9 million from $783.7 million year earlier; chief executive Russell T Lewis comments; Gannett reports net income rose 9.8 percent, to $274.4 million from $249.8 million year earlier; revenue rose 11.4 percent, to $1.73 billion; chairman-president-chief executive Douglas H McCorkindale comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Times Company and the Gannett Company reported yesterday that the newspaper advertising climate was showing steady signs of growth so far this year. But while those improvements were enough to help propel a gain in earnings at Gannett in the first quarter, they were not enough to stave off a decline at the Times Company.</p>
        <p>The Times Company posted net income of $58.4 million, or 38 cents a share, down 15.1 percent from the first quarter of 2003, when it reported profit of $68.8 million, or 45 cents a share. Revenue at the Times Company rose 2.3 percent, to $801.9 million, from $783.7 million in the period a year earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Times Company and the Gannett Company reported that the newspaper advertising climate was showing steady signs of growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Times Company and the Gannett Company reported yesterday that the newspaper advertising climate was showing steady signs of growth so far this year. But while those improvements were enough to help propel a gain in earnings at Gannett in the first quarter, they were not enough to stave off a decline at the Times Company.</p>
        <p>The Times Company posted net income of $58.4 million, or 38 cents a share, down 15.1 percent from the first quarter of 2003, when it reported profit of $68.8 million, or 45 cents a share. Revenue at the Times Company rose 2.3 percent, to $801.9 million, from $783.7 million in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The Times Company said that the comparison in earnings was affected by three unusual items that produced a net benefit of $10.7 million after taxes in the first quarter of 2003. Those special items included the closing of a job fair business, the forfeiture of an advertising credit and reimbursement related to a printing plant. The Times also cited increased newsprint expenses and higher salary costs in the quarter this year.</p>
        <p>Still, earnings per share in the latest quarter were 2 cents higher than analysts had been predicting.</p>
        <p>In addition to The Times, the company owns 18 other newspapers -- including The Boston Globe and The International Herald Tribune -- and 8 network-affiliated television stations.</p>
        <p>Gannett -- which publishes USA Today, as well as 100 other daily newspapers in the United States, and operates 22 American television stations -- reported that net income rose 9.8 percent, to $274.4 million, or $1 a share, in the first quarter, from $249.8 million, or 93 cents a share, in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Revenue jumped 11.4 percent, to $1.73 billion.</p>
        <p>Both companies had advertising gains in the first quarter, fueled by results in March in particular. The Times Company reported a 1.5 percent increase in advertising revenue at its newspaper group in the first quarter, to $477.3 million, in part as a result of gains in the transportation, financial services, banking and hotel industries, as well as in help-wanted advertising. In March, the company said, advertising in those categories accelerated, as the increase was about 7 percent over March 2003.</p>
        <p>Gannett, citing gains in similar advertising categories, said advertising revenue for its newspapers increased 14.9 percent in the first quarter -- to $1.16 billion from $1 billion.</p>
        <p>Douglas M. Arthur, an analyst at Morgan Stanley, said that the results from both companies contained harbingers for more improvement throughout the year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arthur noted that the Times Company, for example, said that two advertising categories that were relatively weak in the first quarter -- entertainment and technology -- were likely to improve in the second quarter as the summer movie season arrives and computer companies start campaigns that had been delayed, at least in part, by the struggling economy.</p>
        <p>''You could really sit back and say this thing is ready to explode, on the upside, for the first time in five years,'' Mr. Arthur said.</p>
        <p>And yet, in a conference call with Mr. Arthur and other analysts, Times Company executives said they were not yet ready to predict increases for the year that exceeded what they had already forecast, including growth in advertising revenue companywide of only ''mid-single digits'' by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''We're cautious people these days, and we've had reason to be,'' said Russell T. Lewis, who has announced he will retire as the company's chief executive later this year. ''We're not going to declare victory prematurely.''</p>
        <p>While citing many reasons for optimism, Gannett executives, too, were restrained in looking toward the near future.</p>
        <p>''We do not expect our growth to be delivered in a straight-line manner,'' Douglas H. McCorkindale, the chairman, president and chief executive of Gannett, said in a conference call with analysts. ''We are not yet seeing a full recovery.''</p>
        <p>The share price of each company fell yesterday in trading on the New York Stock Exchange. Shares of the Times Company fell 34 cents, to $46.73, while shares in Gannett dropped $1.20, to $89.22.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
