<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Does a Fire Horn Have to Be So Loud?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="OUR TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLUNTEERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAGING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RYE (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">OUR TOWNS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D71630F93BA15756C0A965958260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Does a Fire Horn Have to Be So Loud?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Melinda Henneberger</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HENNEBERGER, MELINDA</byline>
      <dateline>RYE, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER the City Council presented awards recognizing the sensitive renovation of several landmark buildings, and before it passed a resolution thanking garden club members for hanging flowering baskets downtown, the debate at last week's meeting turned to an issue that Mayor Warren Ross said he hoped could be settled amicably. Everybody laughed.</p>
        <p>"Look around," Paula Tommins said, reading from a prepared statement on behalf of a newly formed community group, the Concerned Citizens of Rye. "Most of us have never before participated in local government. This issue brought people to City Hall."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER the City Council presented awards recognizing the sensitive renovation of several landmark buildings, and before it passed a resolution thanking garden club members for hanging flowering baskets downtown, the debate at last week's meeting turned to an issue that Mayor Warren Ross said he hoped could be settled amicably. Everybody laughed.</p>
        <p>"Look around," Paula Tommins said, reading from a prepared statement on behalf of a newly formed community group, the Concerned Citizens of Rye. "Most of us have never before participated in local government. This issue brought people to City Hall."</p>
        <p>"The Concerned Citizens of Rye are here to tell you that the blasts diminish our quality of life," she said, referring to the sound of the horns that summon volunteer firefighters to fire calls at all hours. "Should blasts be accepted without exploring the options?"</p>
        <p>This waterfront community of 15,000 on Long Island Sound, founded in 1660, has become progressively tonier in recent years. Life is good, and the good life is not cheap. The average home sells for $585,345. The Concerned Citizens figure they are entitled to undisturbed sleep.</p>
        <p>There are real problems here, as everywhere. A local woman was recently charged in the death of an infant she had been hired to care for, and the shoreline that is the city's pride sustained serious damage in the worst of last winter's storms. Still, some said the debate over the fire horns is the biggest local flap since the skateboard controversy of 1976, when Rye outlawed skateboarding on through streets.</p>
        <p>Amy Butkus, a television producer who helped organize the group, suggested that this conflict runs a bit deeper. "It's very socioeconomic, the locals against the educated, the working professionals," she said. "It's a class thing." Later, she said she had misspoken, and she revised her assessment, saying, "It's more Rye versus outsiders," relative newcomers like herself. In any case, she said, she did not want to say anything that "could in fact hurt our cause."</p>
        <p>In the last six months, the Concerned Citizens have consulted noise experts with Ph.D.'s and collected more than 200 signatures on a petition asking the Council to investigate the possibility of replacing the horn with beepers. They asked the Council to appoint a fact-finding committee, and alerted the news media, including CBS's "Street Stories."</p>
        <p>Fire Chief George Ballantoni, whose volunteer corps responded to 623 alarms in the last year, has also done his homework and concluded that the horns are far more efficient than pagers.</p>
        <p>But for the firefighters, tradition is at much at stake as public safety, and questions about the old ways seem to show a certain lack of respect.</p>
        <p>Horns have been summoning Rye firefighters since the early 1900's. "At one time, every male resident on Park Lane was a member of the Milton Point Engine and Hose Company," the chief said in a memo to the Mayor.</p>
        <p>"They, their families and neighbors on Milton Point never once complained about our system," he said in the memo. He doesn't see why they should start now.</p>
        <p>"It's a big issue, I guess, to them," he said in an interview, referring to the Concerned Citizens of Rye. "Lawnmowers are a big issue to some people."</p>
        <p>At the City Council meeting, a longtime resident who grew up next door to one of the two local firehouses spoke in defense of the horn. Pat Larkin, the mother of a former volunteer firefighter, called the idea of abandoning the horn "the most dangerous thing I ever heard."</p>
        <p>Several people clapped after she spoke. But there was much more applause for the Concerned Citizens, who mentioned babies roused from their cribs by the horns.</p>
        <p>In the most heated moments of the discussion, Mayor Ross said he feared that the proposed committee would amount to a "Supreme Court of some kind, to sit in judgment of the fire wardens" and told Ms. Tommins, "You have a bad habit of interrupting people." He asked whether the Fire Department and the Concerned Citizens couldn't just sit down and work out their differences informally.</p>
        <p>Patrick Mooney of the Concerned Citizens said: "I'm going to remain calm. We asked questions and they didn't answer our questions."</p>
        <p>There was a long pause after Councilman Richard Goldstein made a motion for the formation of the committee proposed by the Concerned Citizens. Councilwoman Ellen Milberg said, "I still like going back to a less threatening situation" of a less official committee.</p>
        <p>"This could go on all night," sighed one man in the audience, who had come to discuss parking stickers for local residents.</p>
        <p>But it didn't, and after an hourlong discussion, the Council voted unanimously to appoint a committee to investigate the use of fire horns.</p>
        <p>Outside the Council chambers, the Concerned Citizens exulted. "My faith in small government has been restored," Ms. Tommins said.  OUR TOWNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
