<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>[ APPEARANCES ] ; The Resistance Movement</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="76" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="724971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="[ APPEARANCES ]"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGE, CHRONOLOGICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTIC SURGERY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TANNEN, MARY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Plastic Surgery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3D8163AF930A25752C1A962958260" item-length="1543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>[ APPEARANCES ] ; The Resistance Movement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Tannen;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TANNEN, MARY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE OTHER DAY THE COLLAGEN Corporation invited some writers and editors to a presentation by Debbie Then, a social psychologist from Stanford University who gave a talk on women's new attitudes toward "cosmetic procedures," meaning anything from chemical peels to collagen injections to surgery. We saw a video of attractive (but not flashy) women talking openly and positively about how they'd had work done to please themselves, and how much happier and more confident they felt afterward. These women didn't look old and they didn't look young; they had the smooth look of affluence. According to Then's survey, women who elect to have cosmetic procedures are trend-setters. Heroines of consumerism, they'd been the first to equip themselves with VCR's and cellular phones.</p>
        <p>One member of the audience objected to the cost -- $400 for collagen injections that in some cases might have to be redone every four months. She didn't mention surgery, which could easily run as high as $8,000, none of it covered by health insurance. Nobody from the Collagen Corporation said anything about trying to bring down the price. But then no one would ever consider bringing down the price of a Prada backpack, either. Wasn't that part of the point, that the ageless face signaled membership in the consumer elite?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE OTHER DAY THE COLLAGEN Corporation invited some writers and editors to a presentation by Debbie Then, a social psychologist from Stanford University who gave a talk on women's new attitudes toward "cosmetic procedures," meaning anything from chemical peels to collagen injections to surgery. We saw a video of attractive (but not flashy) women talking openly and positively about how they'd had work done to please themselves, and how much happier and more confident they felt afterward. These women didn't look old and they didn't look young; they had the smooth look of affluence. According to Then's survey, women who elect to have cosmetic procedures are trend-setters. Heroines of consumerism, they'd been the first to equip themselves with VCR's and cellular phones.</p>
        <p>One member of the audience objected to the cost -- $400 for collagen injections that in some cases might have to be redone every four months. She didn't mention surgery, which could easily run as high as $8,000, none of it covered by health insurance. Nobody from the Collagen Corporation said anything about trying to bring down the price. But then no one would ever consider bringing down the price of a Prada backpack, either. Wasn't that part of the point, that the ageless face signaled membership in the consumer elite?</p>
        <p>I left the lecture considerably enlightened. Over the years, confronting my aging face in the mirror, I've been curiously unconcerned, as if I were watching someone else go through changes. I am 51, the same age as Mick Jagger, and like Mick, I hadn't come to terms with just how old that is.</p>
        <p>Diane Young, founder and president of the Diane Young Anti-Aging Salon on East 57th Street, is also 51, but when we looked in the mirror together, my nasolabial folds looked like canyons compared with her faint lines. The salon has been in business for 12 years, but just last year Young added Anti-Aging to the name, to emphasize prevention. She explained that baby boomers, with their immense buying power, are approaching 50, and will be willing to do "whatever's necessary" to prevent the ravages of time. To meet the demand, she said, there have been "mind boggling" advances in products and procedures over the last four years, and she predicted more to come.</p>
        <p>The new products at Diane Young featured oxygen -- oxygen face creams, oxygen eye treatments and oxygen facials. I noticed some collagen creams on the shelf. "Yesterday's news," said Young. Apparently, the anti-aging industry was rapidly evolving, sloughing off old products with the restless imperiousness of the Queen of Hearts -- off with their heads, on to the next!</p>
        <p>There seems to be no end to the formulas that promise not just to control or retard aging, but to reverse it. "Age is a fact of life," posits the ad for Lancome's Renergie eye and face line, "but why look it?" The copy for La Prairie's Age Management Intensified Serum, a gel-cream in a cylindrical bottle with a double helix running up the side, is even more audacious. "Suddenly the face you thought was gone forever can be yours again."</p>
        <p>A press packet for Cellex-C, an offering from the Toronto-based firm Anti-Aging International, contains a four-color photo of the face of a pretty woman who looks to be in her late 20's. The same face is then shown under ultraviolet light. Now a ghastly blue, it has dark speckles and lines. The dark areas, the copy explains, are already damaged underneath, and will be the first to show signs of aging. Skin damage can begin as early as 25, and accelerates as we grow older, "particularly when we are suffering from physical or emotional stress."</p>
        <p>Once considered an unstemmable force of nature, aging is now being looked upon as if it were a disease, and a preventable one at that. Baby boomers, rescued by Dr. Salk from polio in youth, would inevitably expect a magic bullet to come speeding out of the laboratory and save them from wrinkles in middle age.</p>
        <p>So far, the "cures" are not without drawbacks. Dermatologists have reported seeing patients with scaly patches and even scarring, from misuse of products containing alpha-hydroxy acids, which reduce lines by getting rid of the old skin and bringing new skin to the surface. Other cosmetic procedures can entail even more risk, and pain. In rare cases, for instance, a collagen injection might hit a blood vessel, causing bleeding or tissue death that leads to scarring. After a chemical peel, patients have to stay out of direct sunlight, and should the wrong acid touch their skin, they may suffer irreversible redness and scarring. Face lifts, of course, are surgery, and when a general anesthesia is involved, there is the slight but real risk of death. There is usually vomiting (from the anesthesia), pain from the sutures and a general feeling of malaise. Although surgeons report that patients look well in 3 to 10 weeks, a friend who generally enjoys excellent health told me it was six months before she felt like herself again. Was it really necessary to subject oneself to this punishment to get rid of some lines and loose skin? I still didn't get it.</p>
        <p>Over lunch, a friend who got her first lift in her 40's and is something of a cosmetic-procedure junkie told me that since she does business with 30-year-old investors, she can't afford to look 20 years their senior, not when she's touting her ability to appeal to a youth market. A lined face holds history, personal history that has no place at the negotiating table.</p>
        <p>"They don't want to read my troubles on my face," she said.</p>
        <p>I said my case was different: I used phone, fax, modem. Nobody would know I was getting dewlaps. She flashed me an unfurrowed yet pitying look, and mentioned a world-class author who's past 60 but has a face as smooth as an egg. Even a writer must occasionally meet with agents and editors, she reminded me. And because my "face time" was limited, it had all the more impact. How could I convince others that my ideas were young and fresh if my face was old and worn?</p>
        <p>As an exercise fanatic, I'd always thought that it didn't matter if my chin got flabby as long as I maintained physical strength. Now I was beginning to realize the error of my ways. What good did it do me, in my urban environment, to be able to swim a mile? That was not power. The face was power. And I was losing it.</p>
        <p>The first thing I noticed about the cosmetic surgeon Dr. Steven Herman was that he kept a decanter of sherry and glasses in the waiting room of his Fifth Avenue office. The next thing I noticed was that, although he was just my age, he had hardly any lines. His face had that pink glow that I've come to associate with trend-setters. He said patients had been coming to him in their early 40's, at the first sign of aging, when a decade ago they would have waited until their mid-50's to avail themselves of the whole menu of options he has to offer.</p>
        <p>He can inject the frown lines of their foreheads with Botox, a purified toxin extracted from botulism that will temporarily paralyze muscles so they won't be able to scowl. For deep lines, he prescribes collagen injections. For sagging skin with fine lines, a chemical peel. For anyone over 30, he suggests a treatment plan with Nuderm, a Retin-A based cream.</p>
        <p>Dr. Herman has not had surgery himself, but he has been through the Nuderm treatment. He borrowed the language of fitness to describe how Nuderm works: it's good health; it stimulates the production of collagen. He said that people who enjoy his services have a different look, younger, more vibrant.</p>
        <p>I walked away with a bag full of creams. If I'd knocked back a sherry in the waiting room, I might have signed up for an eye lift. It occurred to me that my creeping desire to conquer age was a paradigm for the desire sweeping the baby boom generation. My unfocused and unexpressed aversion to growing old was being met by more and more products and services that gave it voice. Once my eyes had been opened (figuratively speaking) I was able to see that trend-setters were moving aggressively against the future, while I was being left behind, wearing yesterday's face. For once, I could envision myself going for procedures, opting for surgery, taking advantage of medical science's ever-increasing advances. I would not quibble at the expense. Better to invest in a power face than in power jewels that might make me a target of muggers.</p>
        <p>But just today I was flipping through the October Mirabella, where I came across some black and white photos of Benedetta Barzini, who had been a celebrated model in her 20's. Now she was 51, my age exactly, but she had even deeper nasolabial folds -- double ones! She had crow's feet, and her frown lines were definitely not paralyzed. Her eyes were seductively hooded by just the right amount of extra skin. She looked as if she'd been through a lot but still had energy for plenty more. I suddenly saw that, in a world of the pink, the plumped and the processed, the well-mapped face could be a potent statement. Give me lines and furrows! Let me keep my hooded eyes of experience!</p>
        <p>Then again, Benedetta is a very beautiful woman. Will people understand that I am opting for a face with character, or will they think I just don't get it?  [ APPEARANCES ]  Mary Tannen, a novelist, regularly contributes articles on beauty to the Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mary Tannen, a novelist, regularly contributes
articles on beauty to the Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
