<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the Voters In the Suburbs Boosted Pataki</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="725101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBERG, JACQUES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DF1F3EF930A25752C1A962958260" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the Voters In the Suburbs Boosted Pataki</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINBERG, JACQUES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VOTERS in the New York City suburbs played a pivotal role in George E. Pataki's victory last week, sending him to the Executive Mansion with a margin of victory that far exceeded his statewide performance.</p>
        <p>Interviews with 379 voters leaving polling places in the seven counties immediately north of New York City and on Long Island indicated that 60 percent voted for Mr. Pataki compared with 38 percent for Mario M. Cuomo, whose 12 years in Albany came to an abrupt end. The race statewide was much closer. With 99 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Pataki, a State Senator from Putnam County and former Mayor of Peekskill, had 48 percent of the vote. Mr. Cuomo, a longtime Queens resident, had 45 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VOTERS in the New York City suburbs played a pivotal role in George E. Pataki's victory last week, sending him to the Executive Mansion with a margin of victory that far exceeded his statewide performance.</p>
        <p>Interviews with 379 voters leaving polling places in the seven counties immediately north of New York City and on Long Island indicated that 60 percent voted for Mr. Pataki compared with 38 percent for Mario M. Cuomo, whose 12 years in Albany came to an abrupt end. The race statewide was much closer. With 99 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Pataki, a State Senator from Putnam County and former Mayor of Peekskill, had 48 percent of the vote. Mr. Cuomo, a longtime Queens resident, had 45 percent.</p>
        <p>In New York City, exit surveys showed that Mr. Cuomo drew 70 percent of the vote compared with 28 percent for Mr. Pataki. The suburban survey was part of a larger exit poll of the whole state by the Voter News Service, a consortium of ABC News, CBS News, NBC News, CNN and The Associated Press. In addition to Westchester and Putnam Counties, it represented voters in Rockland, Dutchess, Orange, Sullivan, Ulster, Nassau and Suffolk.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki owed his strong showing in those counties to a confluence of factors, not the least of which was the solid Republican base outside New York City. But some Pataki voters in the suburbs also said they supported his advocacy of tax cuts and the death penalty, felt that the economy was slumping and disapproved of President Clinton's performance.</p>
        <p>When asked about the economy, 9 of 10 of Mr. Pataki's suburban voters described it as not good or poor. One of 4 Cuomo voters said they thought the economy was good. Nearly 1 of 2 Pataki voters said they felt that the family financial situation was in worse shape than it was two years ago.</p>
        <p>Asked what form of punishment they favored for people convicted of first-degree murder, 4 of 5 Pataki voters said they supported the death penalty. Fewer than 2 in 10 said they advocated life in prison without parole. Mr. Cuomo vetoed every death-penalty bill that the Legislature sent to him, but Mr. Pataki promised in the campaign to sign such a measure.</p>
        <p>Asked to identify the one or two issues that mattered most to them, the Cuomo and Pataki voters in the suburbs diverged sharply. More often than not Mr. Pataki's supporters cited the death penalty, government spending and taxes. Mr. Cuomo's backers mentioned his personal qualifications and experience. One of 5 Pataki voters said it was simply "time for a change."</p>
        <p>It was clear that the troubles of Mr. Clinton, who campaigned hard for Mr. Cuomo, loomed large in the minds of suburban voters. Three of 4 Pataki voters said they disapproved of the way Mr. Clinton was "handling his job as President."</p>
        <p>Fewer than 1 of 3 Cuomo supporters said they were unhappy with the President. Three of 4 Cuomo voters said they voted for Mr. Clinton in 1992, and half the Pataki supporters said they had voted to re-elect President Bush. Nearly 1 of 5 Pataki voters said they had supported Ross Perot's candidacy.</p>
        <p>Each candidate received about half his support in the suburbs from voters whose total family income ranged from $30,000 to $75,000 a year. While Mr. Pataki attracted more voters whose incomes fell below $30,000 a year, Mr. Cuomo attracted more votes among those whose incomes exceeded $100,000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
