<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Day's Highlights</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="469894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SOVIET TURMOIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DA1639F93AA1575BC0A967958260" item-length="364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Day's Highlights</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What Shape the Union?</p>
        <p>Ukraine on His Mind: Soviet and Russian delegates flew to the Ukraine today to sort out squabbles and border claims, while in Moscow President Mikhail S. Gorbachev issued ever more urgent warnings that the Soviet Union must survive, even if in a new and yet-undecided form. Page A1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What Shape the Union?</p>
        <p>Ukraine on His Mind: Soviet and Russian delegates flew to the Ukraine today to sort out squabbles and border claims, while in Moscow President Mikhail S. Gorbachev issued ever more urgent warnings that the Soviet Union must survive, even if in a new and yet-undecided form. Page A1.</p>
        <p>Minds of Their Own: As street crowds in Kiev fervently demanded independence, the Ukraine joined other republics in speaking for some sort of loose confederation rather than a renewed federal union. Page A18. At Home and Abroad</p>
        <p>An Unruffled Town: In Klin, up the road from Moscow, Lenin stood untoppled and undefiled as this serene, provincial city poked along at its normal pace, with work and weddings planned. Page A1.</p>
        <p>From War Prize to Enclave: The easternmost outpost ofor Germany for 402 years and the westernmost outpost of the Soviet Union since the end of World War II, Kaliningrad, the Soviet authorities hope, will be retained despite its prospective isolation from Soviet territory. Page A19.</p>
        <p>A Diplomat Rewarded: Boris D. Pankin, a 60-year-old career bureaucrat, was named the new Soviet Foreign Minister. He apparently earned his job by publicly protesting the coup from Prague, where he had been Ambassador. Page A21.</p>
        <p>Some Helping Hands: Despite the best efforts of the Bush Administration to change the subject, debates over aid to the Soviet Union are developing rapidly within the Western alliance and among politicians in Washington. Page A1.  Will It Be Butter or Guns?</p>
        <p>Debate in Congress: Congress began grappling with the murky consequences of the Soviet upheaval as Representative Les Aspin, chairman of the House Armed Services Committee, urged taking $1 billion from the United States military budget to send food and medicine to the Soviet Union this winter. Page A22.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Threat: As Western officials expressed some concern over the long-term stability of the Soviet nuclear arsenal, President Boris N. Yeltsin of the Russian republic said he and Mr. Gorbachev would convene a meeting of security officials and leaders of the Soviet republics to discuss future controls over atomic weapons. Page A22.</p>
        <p>SOVIET TURMOIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
