<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Classical Showcase That Speaks of Bartok and Violins</title>
    <meta content="12gala" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/12/arts/dance/12gala.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1760999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="CITY BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martins, Peter</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wheeldon, Christopher</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Forsythe, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDA173EF931A25756C0A9609C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Classical Showcase That Speaks of Bartok and Violins</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Classical Showcase of Bartok and Violins at the City Ballet</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Ballet's Diamond Project of newly commissioned choreography normally introduces its premieres one at a time. But Wednesday night was the company's spring gala, the one with the sparkling tables deployed in the mezzanine-level lobby of the New York State Theater to greet patrons as they emerge after the performance, both the formally clad diners and the rest of us, scuttling forlornly off into the night. For the occasion, there were two full-length premieres, plus a nice, Diamond-related bonus for the gala only.</p>
        <p>The premieres were by the two choreographers most closely related to the company: Peter Martins, the ballet master in chief, and Christopher Wheeldon, the resident chorographer. The bonus was a pas de deux from William Forsythe's ''Herman Schmerman,'' which made its debut during the first Diamond Project season in 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher Wheeldon offered a pure and fresh ballet and William Forsythe's duet was inventive, witty and sweet at the spring gala on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Ballet's Diamond Project of newly commissioned choreography normally introduces its premieres one at a time. But Wednesday night was the company's spring gala, the one with the sparkling tables deployed in the mezzanine-level lobby of the New York State Theater to greet patrons as they emerge after the performance, both the formally clad diners and the rest of us, scuttling forlornly off into the night. For the occasion, there were two full-length premieres, plus a nice, Diamond-related bonus for the gala only.</p>
        <p>The premieres were by the two choreographers most closely related to the company: Peter Martins, the ballet master in chief, and Christopher Wheeldon, the resident chorographer. The bonus was a pas de deux from William Forsythe's ''Herman Schmerman,'' which made its debut during the first Diamond Project season in 1992.</p>
        <p>Of the new ballets, Mr. Wheeldon's ''Evenfall'' was the more interesting. This was Mr. Wheeldon at his most purely, even primly classical. Everything was neatly symmetrical and impeccably balletic, starting with a diamond-shaped wedge of six ballerinas in light-gray attire at the outset. What made the ballet interesting -- not profound, perhaps, or brilliantly innovative, but interesting and satisfying -- were the ways Mr. Wheeldon found to perk up the primness, to make it both pure and fresh.</p>
        <p>The ballet is for a central couple, elegantly represented by Miranda Weese and Damian Woetzel, and two sextets of women and one sextet of men, all in varied shades of gray. The music is Bartok's lyrical Piano Concerto No. 3, well played by Cameron Grant and well conducted by Maurice Kaplow.</p>
        <p>The music's ruminative tone is reflected in the adagio-flavored choreography. Even when Bartok, and hence Mr. Wheeldon, gets lively, the choreography is so relaxed and deft that the adagio mood is sustained.</p>
        <p>This is abstraction of the sort Balanchine favored. It does not demand the vivid projection of drama or personality, which probably did Ms. Weese a favor and undercut some of Mr. Woetzel's potential impact.</p>
        <p>Yet like Balanchine, if not yet quite with the genius or flair, Mr. Wheeldon is able to enliven classical abstraction with clever quirks. Particularly striking was a recurrent image of a row of trios: one woman demurely seated, her legs extended on an angle toward the audience; a second woman bending over her, her tutu radiating upward like corona; and a man standing behind, his arms upraised in a V.</p>
        <p>Throughout, angular arms accented the classical patterning. And the varied deployment of the 18 corps members looked constantly inventive, attaining an image of symmetry through asymmetry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins's ''Red Violin'' is similarly devoted to dreamy adagio movement, though with less personality. His choice of music was John Corigliano's sweetly tonal score for François Girard's 1998 film ''The Red Violin,'' as arranged by the composer into his Concerto for Violin and Orchestra. Mr. Martins apparently paid little attention to the film's scenario. The score was commissioned by three symphony orchestras and the San Francisco Ballet, but Mr. Martins is the first to use the music for dance, with San Francisco's blessing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martins has assembled a strong cast and dressed them in nice outfits (by Carole Divet) consisting, for the women, of spaghetti-strap tops and loose, short, side-split skirts in single, contrasting colors (the men all wear gray tights and darker loose tops). Jennie Somogyi is in red, partnered by Sébastien Marcovici; Sara Mearns is in purple, with Amar Ramasar; along with Sterling Hyltin, Tiler Peck, Andrew Veyette and Sean Suozzi.</p>
        <p>There is a vaguely implied dramatic scenario, with Ms. Mearns first perceived as a vengeful outsider, though the relations among the central quartet remain unclear and toward the end they're all in a loving roundelay. Most of the duets are, again, adagio; the most interesting of the livelier movements are given to the men in the accompanying quartet.</p>
        <p>Some of the positions Mr. Martins asks of the principals (Ms. Somogyi splayed backward on the floor, for instance) are unusual and a little awkward, and there were some nervous-making insecurities. The end effect was unmemorable. The music was played sweetly and delicately by Kurt Nikkanen as the violin soloist and Andrea Quinn, conducting.</p>
        <p>Despite its dopey title and Thom Willems's typically bland recorded music, the ''Herman Schmerman'' duet was very appealing, especially since it was so surely danced, technically and dramatically, by Wendy Whelan and Albert Evans. Compared with his more recent theatrical and filmic experiments, it showed how far Mr. Forsythe has evolved (or, some might say, devolved) from pure dance.</p>
        <p>It was inventive, witty and sweet. It proved that the Diamond Project has produced at least some ballets that will last, and it made one wish it would crop up in future City Ballet repertory programs.</p>
        <p>Christopher Wheeldon's ''Evenfall'' can be seen again tomorrow afternoon, May 20 and May 23. Peter Martins's ''Red Violin'' will be performed Sunday afternoon, May 20 and May 26. The New York City Ballet season continues until June 25. New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570 or nycballet.org.</p>
        <p>CITY BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
