<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Round Five for a Theatrical Heavyweight</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PULITZER PRIZES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, AUGUST</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PIANO LESSON, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/August Wilson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1630F936A25757C0A966958260" item-length="2814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Round Five for a Theatrical Heavyweight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERVYN ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Sitting in a wooden booth at a restaurant across from the Yale University campus, chain-smoking and sipping cup after cup of black coffee, a 44-year-old bearded playwright is talking about success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Sitting in a wooden booth at a restaurant across from the Yale University campus, chain-smoking and sipping cup after cup of black coffee, a 44-year-old bearded playwright is talking about success.</p>
        <p>Sitting in a wooden booth at a restaurant across from the Yale University campus, chain-smoking and sipping cup after cup of black coffee, a 44-year-old bearded playwright is talking about success.</p>
        <p>This unassuming man's complex and vibrant portrayals of black Americans and their troubles throughout the last century, his use of the black experience to depict how human beings deal with the struggle for existence, have transcended color and made him one of the most important voices in the American theater today.</p>
        <p>Barely a decade ago, he was a little-known poet just starting out in the theater. Then, in 1981, the manuscript of a play he had written was plucked from a pile of submissions to the Eugene O'Neill Theater Center in Waterford, Conn. Within a few years, his plays ''Ma Rainey's Black Bottom,'' ''Fences'' and ''Joe Turner's Come and Gone'' had opened on Broadway, received much critical praise and garnered many Tony nominations. In 1987, one of the plays, ''Fences,'' won both the Tony Award as best play and the Pulitzer Prize for drama.</p>
        <p>Now that playwright, August Wilson, is returning to Broadway, with ''The Piano Lesson,'' which opens tomorrow night at the newly restored Walter Kerr Theater. His success has not made things any easier.</p>
        <p>''All those awards, all that stuff, I take them and I hang them on my wall,'' he says, puffing on cigarette No. 1. ''But then I turn around, and my typewriter's sitting there, and it doesn't know from awards. I always tell people I'm a struggling playwright. I'm struggling to get the next play down on paper. You start at the beginning each time you sit down. Nothing you've written before has any bearing on what you're going to write now.</p>
        <p>''It's like a heavyweight fighter,'' he says. ''You've gotta go out and knock the guy out. It doesn't matter if you're undefeated. There's another guy standing there, and you have to go out again, and you have to duck his punches, and do all the rest of whatever it is you do.''</p>
        <p>He takes a last puff on the cigarette, puts it out, lights another. He sips the coffee. The boxing metaphor he has used is appropriate and comes naturally. He loves the sport. Something there is about him that is the essence of a fighter, but a quiet fighter, one who lets his inner confidence rule. By the time he was 5 he had learned to read, and books have always been of crucial importance. He is a fighter for ideas, especially ideas that involve improving the lot of his fellow blacks in the United States - blacks who, he believes, even today have a culture very different from that of whites.</p>
        <p>Since the beginning of the 80's, he has been writing a series of plays, one for each decade, on the life of black Americans in the 20th century, and ''The Piano Lesson'' is round five. It is set in the 1930's, in Mr. Wilson's hometown of Pittsburgh. The first play in the series, ''Jitney,'' which took place in the 70's, never made it to Broadway. Then came ''Ma Rainey'' (set in the 1920's), ''Fences'' (the 1950's) and ''Joe Turner'' (set in 1911). The most recent, No. 6, is called ''Two Trains Running.'' It opened at the end of March and is playing through Saturday at the Yale Repertory Theater here in what is expected to be the first step on its road to Broadway.</p>
        <p>''The Piano Lesson'' is directed by Lloyd Richards, the dean of the Yale School of Drama and the man who discovered Mr. Wilson at the O'Neill Center. They have had an extremely fruitful stage relationship: Mr. Richards directed the other three Broadway plays, all of which started at Yale, and is also the director of ''Two Trains Running.''</p>
        <p>The Haunted Past Of a Black Family</p>
        <p>The plot of the eight-character ''Piano Lesson'' is simple. Boy Willie (played by Charles S. Dutton) has come up from the South to visit his sister and his niece in Pittsburgh and to claim a family heirloom, an elaborately carved piano, that sits in his sister's house and that he wants to sell to buy land - the land on which his ancestors were slaves - and set up his own farm. But his sister, Berneice (played by S. Epatha Merkerson), will have none of it. There is no way she will let the piano out of her house. It is redolent with family history, and with family blood: two slave ancestors were sold to buy it, a third carved the family history on it, a fourth was killed retrieving it from its white owner. And while Boy Willie and Berneice debate the issue, another element intrudes on their discussion: a ghost.</p>
        <p>''I saw a painting by Romare Bearden called 'The Piano Lesson,' '' Mr. Wilson says, putting out cigarette No. 2. ''I was working on 'Joe Turner' at the time and as soon as I saw the painting I said to myself, 'O.K., that's the next one.' It was a painting of a young girl at a piano, with a woman standing behind her who seems to be admonishing her to learn her scales. So I got the idea from the painting that there would be a woman and a little girl in the play. And I thought that the woman would be a character who was trying to acquire a sense of self-worth by denying her past. And I felt that she couldn't do that. She had to confront the past, in the person of her brother, who was going to sweep through the house like a tornado coming from the South, bringing the past with him.'' (Bearden's paintings of black America have more than once inspired Mr. Wilson. ''Joe Turner'' took form after the playwright saw another work, ''Mill Hand's Lunch Bucket.'') When it came to the piano, ''I knew there was a story behind it,'' Mr. Wilson says. ''What I didn't know was what was carved. And as I wrote, everything sort of came together. It was the idea of linkage. It provided a link to the past, to Africa, to who these people are. And then the question became, What do you do with your legacy? How do you best put it to use?''</p>
        <p>Black Americans, Mr. Wilson says, have made some incorrect choices in capturing their legacy. ''One was the migration to the North. We were land-based agrarian people from Africa. We were uprooted from Africa, and we spent over 200 years developing our culture as black Americans. And then we left the South. We uprooted ourselves and attempted to transplant this culture to the pavements of the industrialized North. And it was a transplant that did not take. I think if we had stayed in the South, we would have been a stronger people. And because the connection between the South of the 20's, 30's and 40's has been broken, it's very difficult to understand who we are.</p>
        <p>''In all my plays,'' he says, ''I always point toward making that connection, toward reconnecting with the past. You have to know who you are, and understand your history in America over more than 300 years, in order to know what your relation is to your society.''</p>
        <p>Broadway Wisdom On Stars and Length</p>
        <p>It is a couple of hours later, and Mr. Wilson and Mr. Richards are sitting in the dean's office at the Yale School of Drama talking about the long road that ''The Piano Lesson'' has taken to Broadway and the difficult decisions that had to be made along the way. This play also began at Yale and made the rounds of regional theaters across the country before coming to New York. It opened here in November 1987, and went on to play in Boston, Chicago, San Diego, at the Kennedy Center in Washington and, most recently, in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The regional runs helped provide the funds needed for the $750,000 Broadway production. A good deal of that money, Mr. Richards says, was generated by the month or so in Washington and the 11 weeks in Los Angeles. (The play was generally well received and drew large audiences in both cities.) In an attempt to help build an audience in New York, the play's producers, including the Yale Repertory Theater and the Center Theater Group/Ahmanson Theater of Los Angeles, arranged with the Manhattan Theater Club to make it part of that company's subscription season.</p>
        <p>The long development period has also given Mr. Wilson and Mr. Richards time to refine the play, and to reach resolutions about its length, whether to have a big-name star and what the ending should be.</p>
        <p>''The Piano Lesson'' runs three hours, including the intermission. Conventional wisdom on Broadway is that a serious play should be two and a half hours long because audiences will not sit still for more. But Mr. Richards and Mr. Wilson will have none of that. ''I find that a sad concept,'' Mr. Richards says. ''Does that rule apply to 'The Merchant of Venice'? I hear it runs more than three hours. Has anybody spoken to Mr. Shakespeare lately about doing something about it?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson is equally emphatic. ''It takes three hours to tell this particular story,'' he says. ''I don't think there should be this arbitrary two-hour limit. The more I hear that kind of thing, the more I'm of a mind to write a five-hour play.''</p>
        <p>''The Piano Lesson'' does not have a big-name star, and another bit of perceived wisdom on Broadway is that a serious play needs a celebrity to succeed. ''Fences,'' which had James Earl Jones in the leading role, was a long-running hit. ''Joe Turner,'' which had no big name in the cast, had a considerably shorter run, even though many people thought it was a better play than ''Fences.''</p>
        <p>''We discussed having a star,'' Mr. Richards says. ''When you get to the point eventually of talking about a play going to New York, someone's going to say, 'Can't you put a star in there, because a star will sell tickets.' But neither August nor I are inclined to do this. We're inclined to create the best production we can do with an ensemble.'' (In fact, Mr. Dutton, for whom Mr. Wilson wrote the part of Boy Willie, will be familiar to theatergoers who saw ''Ma Rainey''; he received a Tony nomination for his role in that play.) Mr. Richards does not attribute the shorter run of ''Joe Turner'' to the lack of a star. It had more to do with the depth and difficulty of the play, he says. ''Joe Turner,'' about a homeless black man searching for his long-vanished wife, ''was a much more mystical play than 'Fences,' a much more challenging play,'' Mr. Richards says. ''It took you deeply into a place where you had never been before. It made you work, and there are people who go to the theater who don't like to work.''</p>
        <p>But What Happened To the Piano?</p>
        <p>As for the ending of ''The Piano Lesson,'' the one that Broadway audiences will see is not the same as the one the play had in Boston, Chicago or San Diego - or even in the early part of its run in Washington. A new ending was put in not long before the end of the Washington engagement, but not without much debate.</p>
        <p>''When we did the play here at Yale Rep, I said to August, 'All right, we have a play that doesn't have an end yet,' '' Mr. Richards recalls.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wilson was not of the same mind. He at first thought the ending was just fine. ''Having set up the situation in which the question is who gets the piano,'' Mr. Wilson says, ''in the original ending I never said what happened to the piano. To me, it wasn't important. The important thing to me was Boy Willie's willingness to engage the ghost in battle. Once you have that moment, then for me the play was over. But I found out that it wasn't over for the audience, which kept saying, 'Yeah, but who gets the piano?'</p>
        <p>''For a while I was persistent in my opinion that it didn't matter,'' he says. ''I didn't want to make a choice between Boy Willie and Berneice, because I thought there was validity in both their arguments. And then I came to understand that in the process of writing the play, I had already made a choice. So I decided to keep the lights on for another 60 seconds on stage so the audience can see what happens after Boy Willie comes down from his fight with the ghost.''</p>
        <p>Back in the restaurant, Mr. Wilson is talking about his next play, ''Two Trains Running,'' set in 1968 at a restaurant in Pittsburgh across the street from a funeral home and a meat market.</p>
        <p>Wanting a Ham, Getting a Chicken</p>
        <p>''There's a character who every morning shows up at the meat market and says to the owner, 'I want my ham,' '' Mr. Wilson says, pausing to light cigarette No. 5. ''And the owner says, 'Take a chicken.' This has been going on for nine and a half years. When the character painted the owner's fence, the owner said, 'If you paint the fence, I'll give you a chicken; if you do a good job, I'll give you a ham.' The character thinks he did a good job; the owner doesn't. And for me that whole situation represents black America standing patiently outside the door of American society saying, 'We want our ham.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wilson has been aware of that situation, of being outside looking in, since he was a youngster in Pittsburgh. ''I grew up in a mixed community of blacks and Syrians and Jews and Italians, in a single-parent household,'' he recalls. His father was white and all but abandoned him.</p>
        <p>''When I was about 7, I began noticing that all the people who were in positions of authority were white. The landlord was white, the person who owned the store was white, the teachers were white, the bus drivers were white, the people at the welfare office were white. And then you discover that anytime you are giving your money to someone, you're giving it to someone who is white.</p>
        <p>''You begin to notice these things. It's not that you question them, it's just something you notice about the world. And then when you get a little older, when you're 14 or 15, you understand the why of the situation.''</p>
        <p>Then, in his 20's, he became exposed to the ideas of Malcolm X and Amiri Baraka. ''Cultural nationalism, all those ideas of the 60's, I still embrace them,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Differences Between Black and White He is convinced that there are major cultural differences between blacks and whites. ''I am more and more concerned with pointing out the differences between blacks and whites, as opposed to pointing out the similarities,'' he says. ''We're a different people. We do things differently. We decorate our houses differently. We dress differently. We party differently. We have different ideas of justice and morality. We have different responses to pleasure and pain. Blacks and whites all do the same things, they just do them differently. And blacks have been all too willing and anxious to say that we are the same as whites, meaning that we should be treated the same, that we should enjoy the same opportunities in society as whites.''</p>
        <p>That part is fine, he says, but blacks are different, and they should be aware of their differences.</p>
        <p>''I find in black life a very elegant kind of logical language, based on the logical order of things,'' he says. ''There's the idea of metaphor. For instance, when one character in 'The Piano Lesson' asks, 'What time does Berneice get home?,' instead of getting a response like 'Berneice gets home at 5 o'clock,' you get: 'You up there asleep, Berneice leave out of here early in the morning, she out there in Squirrel Hill cleaning house for some big shot down there at the steel mill. They don't like you to come late. You come late they won't give you your carfare. What kind of business you got with Berneice?' When you ask a question, instead of getting an answer to the question, you get this guy's ideas, his opinions about everything, a little explanation. You get all these kinds of things just from one question.''</p>
        <p>On April 27, Mr. Wilson will be 45 years old, a time when many people look back on what they have done and think about what they want to do in the time they have left. Mr. Wilson has no doubts. He will not abandon the stage for Hollywood, he says; he is committed to the theater. ''Five years from now, I see myself with four or five more plays, at least,'' he says. ''I discovered the world of theater not too long ago, and for me, there's something about the communal experience of a live audience.''</p>
        <p>He has already started work on his next play - at least to the point that he knows it will be called ''Moon Going Down'' and will be set in a turpentine camp in Georgia in the 1940's. ''When I finish one play, I don't get up,'' he says. ''I stay there until I get an idea for the next one. There's something wonderful about that time of day, just before the dawn, when the moon is going down.''</p>
        <p>The thoughts he wants to communicate with that play, the experience he wants to give that live audience, remain the same as they were when he began: ''It's a testament to the resiliency of the human spirit,'' he says, ''that despite the conditions we have known, despite all the horrors of slavery, despite the sometimes brutal mistreatment blacks have received in this country, we're still here, still managing through it all to find a way to live life with dignity and a certain amount of nobility.''</p>
        <p>A sip, a puff. ''The black culture is still alive, still vital,'' he says. ''The human spirit cannot and will not be broken.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
