<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THROUGH GLASS LIGHTLY, COLORFUL BOTANICALLY</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTIQUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIF, RITA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDA1730F936A25757C0A966958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THROUGH GLASS LIGHTLY, COLORFUL BOTANICALLY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REIF, RITA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The glorious glass fantasies of Louis Comfort Tiffany added a colorpulsing glow to mansions, churches and museums throughout the world over the last century. The flower forms fashioned into vases, the impressionistic botanical images captured in lamps and windows, the mosaic-encrusted columns and the bejeweled inkwells and necklaces are esthetically and technologically among the most innovative glassworks ever produced - as can be seen in the exhibition ''Masterworks of Louis Comfort Tiffany,'' at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, through Sept.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The glorious glass fantasies of Louis Comfort Tiffany added a colorpulsing glow to mansions, churches and museums throughout the world over the last century. The flower forms fashioned into vases, the impressionistic botanical images captured in lamps and windows, the mosaic-encrusted columns and the bejeweled inkwells and necklaces are esthetically and technologically among the most innovative glassworks ever produced - as can be seen in the exhibition ''Masterworks of Louis Comfort Tiffany,'' at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, through Sept.</p>
        <p>The glorious glass fantasies of Louis Comfort Tiffany added a colorpulsing glow to mansions, churches and museums throughout the world over the last century. The flower forms fashioned into vases, the impressionistic botanical images captured in lamps and windows, the mosaic-encrusted columns and the bejeweled inkwells and necklaces are esthetically and technologically among the most innovative glassworks ever produced - as can be seen in the exhibition ''Masterworks of Louis Comfort Tiffany,'' at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, through Sept. 19.</p>
        <p>Dominating the show of 74 objects, one of the most comprehensive ever presented of Tiffany's work, are 12 leaded glass windows, only two of which have been shown publicly in this century. The exhibition was organized by the Smithsonian Institution's National Museum of American Art and became the most popular show ever presented at its Renwick Gallery in Washington, where it was seen by more than 225,000 visitors before it closed last month.</p>
        <p>Originally the exhibition was scheduled to open in Manhattan in late March at the National Academy of Design. According to Elizabeth Broun, director of the National Museum, the show was moved to the Metropolitan Museum of Art when it was realized that the dates for New York ''unfortunately coincided with the extensive staff reorganization at the Academy.''</p>
        <p>As presented at the Metropolitan, under the direction of Alice Cooney Frelinghuysen,associate curator of American decorative arts, the show was allocated twice the space it had in Washington. David Harvey, the show's designer in New York, capitalized by providing long vistas for the windows that enable the viewer to see them from a distance as well as close up. At the same time there is a sense of intimacy wherever the smaller pieces and lamps are shown. Eight objects were added in New York, including two of the most beautiful: an architectural column sheathed in a mosaic of iridescent blue glass squares, one of six that dramatized the interior of Tiffany's studio at Laurelton Hall, in Oyster Bay, L. I., and a gold box awash with enamels, opals, tourmalines, sapphires and chrysoprases used to depict the four seasons, a tour de force of jeweler's skills. The box was executed under Tiffany's direction when he headed the design staff of Tiffany &amp; Company, the store his father, Charles Lewis, Tiffany founded in 1837. Tiffany's leaded glass lamps include some breathtaking studies. The lotus lamp, the largest and most expensive lighting fixture Tiffany ever produced - he charged $750 for it at the turn of the century and only three were made of this design - seems alive, its blossomlike light bulbs extending in an irregular pattern above the shade. A much smaller, equally arresting lamp, depicting either maple leaves or the ivy of the Virginia creeper, has an amber-and-green glass shade that is an exquisitely delicate example of lighting design.</p>
        <p>In the lamps and the floral and landscape windows, Tiffany's genius is seen in the fine detailing that either realistically depicts or dramatically heightens nature. Painted bits of glass suggest live petals; layered glass conveys the look of a water-filled goldfish bowl, and carved glass creates myriad color changes on leaves, clouds and skies. The show was conceived by Alastair Duncan, guest consultant to the exhibition, as an assemblage of many of Tiffany's favorite designs that also happen to be among his most technically innovative works. Mr. Duncan has written four books on Tiffany and is a consultant on 19th- and 20th-century decorative arts for Christie's in New York, where he was formerly head of Art Nouveau and Art Deco sales. For the show he selected 21 objects that had been exhibited in world expositions and 52 that were among Tiffany's favorites and which he had used to publicize the work of Tiffany Studios. ''What we discovered was that Tiffany's work, although much of it appeared in the 20th century, was essentially 19th-century in its preoccupation with nature and with handcraftsmanship,'' Mr. Duncan said.</p>
        <p>The exhibition is sponsored by Tiffany &amp; Company and has no formal catalogue. However, most of the windows, lamps, vases, candlesticks, boxes, jewelry and desk accessories are illustrated or described in ''Masterworks of Louis Comfort Tiffany,'' by Martin Eidelberg, a professor of art history at Rutgers University; Neil Harris, a professor of history at the University of Chicago, and Mr. Duncan. It is published by Abrams ($37.50 cloth, $24.50 paper).</p>
        <p>Prices of Tiffany designs at recent auctions have equaled or surpassed the record sums paid for other examples of the designer's work auctioned between 1979 and 1984, the period when the revival of interest in Tiffany peaked. An 18-carat gold box in the exhibition that depicts the four seasons was auctioned in 1987 at Sotheby's in New York for $411,500. Last June, Sotheby's sold a bronze and glass wisteria lamp for $231,000, a record for this type of lamp.</p>
        <p>Even higher prices were paid at Christie's all-Tiffany sale last Dec. 9. A pair of a leaded glass windows, depicting a peacock perched on a balustrade with a river and hills in the background, was sold for $352,000, a record at auction for leaded glass windows. And a flowering lotus bronze and glass lamp was sold for $550,000, the highest price paid at auction for any work by Tiffany.</p>
        <p>''We had so much success with the December sale, at which we set two new records, that we decided to hold another one,'' said Nancy McClelland, the head of Christie's sales of 20th-century decorative arts. The auction, to be held in early June, is to offer about 100 lots of Tiffany items, including at least seven major lamps and two or three important windows, each of which is expected to bring more than $100,000.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
