<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite the Lockout, Pitchers Are Far Ahead of the Hitters</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="343863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAJOR LEAGUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DE1630F936A25757C0A966958260" item-length="1496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite the Lockout, Pitchers Are Far Ahead of the Hitters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Three weeks of spring training might be enough time for hitters to get ready for the season, the prevailing thinking went at the end of the lockout, but pitchers would most likely need more time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Three weeks of spring training might be enough time for hitters to get ready for the season, the prevailing thinking went at the end of the lockout, but pitchers would most likely need more time.</p>
        <p>Three weeks of spring training might be enough time for hitters to get ready for the season, the prevailing thinking went at the end of the lockout, but pitchers would most likely need more time.</p>
        <p>Given the results of the first five days of the season, have no pity for the pitchers. It's the hitters who could apparently use sympathy and extra batting practice.</p>
        <p>The no-hitter perpetrated on the Seattle Mariners by Mark Langston and Mike Witt of California on the third day of the season epitomized the control pitchers have had over the hitters at the start of this season.</p>
        <p>Initial developments show the effect the abbreviated spring training might have had on the hitters.</p>
        <p>The first 52 games produced 10 shutouts. In three other games, the starting pitchers worked five innings or more and didn't allow any runs. In the first five days of last season, pitchers threw 3 shutouts in 47 games (Friday night's results alone included three shutouts), and two other pitchers allowed no runs in five innings or more. Furthermore, no one pitched a no-hitter all of last season.</p>
        <p>Scoring is down, from 8.62 runs a game (both teams) to 8.17. The collective earned run average has dropped from 3.80 to 3.62. The earned run average for starting pitchers shows an even more significant decline, from 4.12 to 3.49, or more than half a run.</p>
        <p>As effective as the starters have been, though, they are leaving games sooner than they did at this time last year. They have averaged five and one-third innings per start compared with six a year ago. That development clearly stems from the shortened spring training, during which the starters didn't have their usual amount of time to build up to pitching seven to nine innings by the start of the season.</p>
        <p>''It's something of a paradox,'' Mike Port, the Angels' general manager, said. ''There's a distinction between pitchers being ready to go in terms of technique and ability and the endurance factor. Langston threw as well as he ever has the other day; he was sharp. But could he sustain that ability over nine innings? Obviously he couldn't.''</p>
        <p>Langston left after seven innings, having allowed the Mariners no hits. The same night, Andy Benes of San Diego held Los Angeles without a hit for the first six innings before Kal Daniels led off the seventh with a single.</p>
        <p>Two days earlier, opening day, in fact, Bruce Hurst, who works in the same pitching rotation as Benes, held the Dodgers hitless for the same stretch, the first six innings. That time, Hubie Brooks opened the seventh with a single. That was the day, too, that Nolan Ryan of Texas pitched five no-hit innings against Toronto, then left the game.</p>
        <p>Langston wound up with a shared shutout; the others didn't. But eight other starters have participated in group shutouts: Frank Viola of the Mets (seven and two-thirds innings), Greg Maddux of the Chicago Cubs (seven and two-thirds), Chuck Finley of California (six and one-third), John Tudor of St. Louis (six), Kevin Tapani of Minnesota (six), Jack Armstrong of Cincinnati (six), Rick Reuschel of San Francisco (five and two-thirds) and Pascual Perez of the Yankees (five).</p>
        <p>Tim Belcher of Los Angeles shunned the group effort; he pitched all nine innings and shut out San Diego on three hits. His effectiveness and endurance were especially interesting because he spent much of the lockout period traveling to and from and participating in negotiations. On the other hand, his performance may have simply been a matter of habit: Belcher led the major leagues last season with eight shutouts.</p>
        <p>Not all teams have started the season swinging lifeless bats. The Oakland Athletics erupted with a 21-hit barrage Friday night and raised their batting average from .283 to .340. The Boston Red Sox, with Dwight Evans ignoring his aching back and driving in seven runs and hitting .455 (10 for 22), compiled a quick .322 batting average. San Francisco also took a .322 average into yesterday's games, fueled by Will Clark's 7 for 16 (.438).</p>
        <p>The Angels have not received that kind of hitting to match their sizzling pitching (2.00 e.r.a.) In the no-hitter, for example, they scored only one run.</p>
        <p>''I spoke with our offensive coordinator, Deron Johnson, about that 1-0 game,'' Port related, ''and he reminded me that in this game, you need only one more run than the other team scores so why waste them?''</p>
        <p>Gold Turns to Lead</p>
        <p>Kirby Puckett, Minnesota's outstanding center fielder, has won four consecutive Gold Gloves as the best defensive center fielder in the American League. Last season he committed only four errors, the year before three. He already has two this year - and could have easily had three - in the Twins' first three games.</p>
        <p>In the opener, Puckett dropped Carney Lansford's fly ball after he and the left fielder, Dan Gladden, became tangled with each other. The official scorer credited Lansford with a double. Puckett's play, however, was a sign of errant plays to come.</p>
        <p>The next night, Ken Phelps grounded a single to center, and Puckett bobbled the ball when he looked up to see if Dave Henderson, who had been at first base, was going to try for third. The miscue enabled Henderson to advance easily.</p>
        <p>In the third game, the next afternoon, Puckett had difficulty seeing Jose Canseco's fly in the sun, then dropped it for his second charged error.</p>
        <p>At the Head of the Line</p>
        <p>When negotiators for the owners and the players finally reached agreement on salary-arbitration eligibility for some players with two to three years of major league service, speculation began about which players were most likely to be among the 17 percent of the group who could go to arbitration. Keith Miller, the Mets' new center fielder, headed the list of probables because, it was generally believed, he had the most major league service time in the group.</p>
        <p>Miller entered the season with one year and 166 days, but he is not No. 1 on the players-in-waiting-for-arbitration list. That distinction belongs to Urbano Lugo, a pitcher who had been forgotten because he had played in the majors only 6 days last year and 27 the year before.</p>
        <p>But he entered the season with one year and 170 days, and, as a member of the Detroit relief crew, was the winning pitcher in the Tigers' first victory of the season. It was Lugo's first victory in the major leagues since 1986, when he worked for the Angels in the second of five partial major league seasons.</p>
        <p>The 27-year-old right-hander appeared in three games for Montreal last year, then signed with the Tigers last December as a minor league free agent. If he continues winning games in relief, he could enjoy his first full season in the majors and insure himself a spot in salary arbitration next February.</p>
        <p>Not in Total Control</p>
        <p>One slight piece of evidence that pitchers aren't totally in command of their pitches: collectively, they have averaged 7.15 walks a game compared with a 6.49 average at this time last year. . . . The bullpens of the Chicago Cubs and the Cincinnati Reds reached yesteday's games having given up no earned runs. The similarity between the relief corps ended there, though. The Reds' relievers struck out 24 batters in 16Z innings, the Cubs' corps 7 in 14. . . . Todd Zeile, the St. Louis Cardinals' rookie catcher, hit a triple his first time up on opening day, then made 11 consecutive outs before slugging a two-run home run his first time at bat in Philadelphia Friday night. He added a two-run double later in the game.</p>
        <p>Snow and Steinbrenner</p>
        <p>The snow that knocked out games in Cleveland, Chicago and Milwaukee last week recalled the first week of the 1982 season, when the start of the Yankees' season was delayed for five days because of a heavy snowfall in New York. The fifth day of that snowout might be one of the most significant in recent Yankee history, at least the George Steinbrenner part of it. The Yankees are, in fact, still trying to recover from that day.</p>
        <p>On April 10, despite the fact that they had a reliable, serviceable shortstop named Bucky Dent, the Yankees acquired a shortstop, Roy Smalley, from the Twins. The trade was made at the insistence of Steinbrenner, who wanted a heavier hitting shortstop.</p>
        <p>The price, however, was Ron Davis, who had become one of the best setup relievers in baseball. The Yankees never replaced Davis, Smalley never became the panacea for the team's hitting shortage, Dent never recovered from the trauma of his demotion and the Yankees never won another division title.</p>
        <p>In directing that the trade be made, Steinbrenner exhibited the kind of questionable judgment that undermined the sound decisions he made in the latter half of the 70's. While the Yankees continue to try to rediscover the right combination, one element of that ill-advised trade continues to present a reminder of how bad it was.</p>
        <p>The Yankees also gave the Twins a young shortstop from their minor league system, and Greg Gagne is one of the steadier shortstops in the league today.</p>
        <p>NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
