<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holiday Windows: Craft and Fantasy</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="199041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDOWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAKS FIFTH AVENUE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, B, &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LORD &amp; TAYLOR INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAHN, EVE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windows</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DC1231F934A25752C1A96E948260" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holiday Windows: Craft and Fantasy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVE M. KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAHN, EVE M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: THREE Fifth Avenue department stores are unveiling their annual gifts to the street: windows in which mechanical figures dance, bow, wave and curtsy. But few of the fascinated passers-by will realize how much planning, improvising and last-minute frenzy went into assembling these enchanting miniature worlds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: THREE Fifth Avenue department stores are unveiling their annual gifts to the street: windows in which mechanical figures dance, bow, wave and curtsy. But few of the fascinated passers-by will realize how much planning, improvising and last-minute frenzy went into assembling these enchanting miniature worlds.</p>
        <p>THREE Fifth Avenue department stores are unveiling their annual gifts to the street: windows in which mechanical figures dance, bow, wave and curtsy. But few of the fascinated passers-by will realize how much planning, improvising and last-minute frenzy went into assembling these enchanting miniature worlds.</p>
        <p>This year Lord &amp; Taylor, Saks Fifth Avenue and B. Altman's all conceived of windows that re-create scenes from the past. One of the greatest challenges the stores faced was developing settings that are both suitably small and historically accurate.</p>
        <p>''The figures are not doll-house size and not child size, so it's hard to find anything ready-made for them,'' said Kenneth Schliemann, director of regional merchandising at Lord &amp; Taylor. ''Most things have to be fabricated.''</p>
        <p>Since 1976, the Christmas windows in the store, at Fifth Avenue and 38th Street, have been inspired by New York City architecture, and the store has commissioned Spaeth Design, a company that specializes in retail-store displays, to create both the sets and the figures.</p>
        <p>Lord &amp; Taylor's windows, which were unveiled last night, feature four interiors as they looked in the 1930's: the lobbies of Radio City Music Hall and the Daily News Building, the observation deck of the Chrysler Building and the Rainbow Room. Working from historical photos, Spaeth copied many features that had long since disappeared, like the murals in the News Building.</p>
        <p>To produce accessories for the rooms, Spaeth's designers resorted to clever substitutions. The crystal pendants on the Rainbow Room's chandelier were carved from Plexiglas. The tiny green shades on the room's candlesticks are actually doll house-size plastic teacups whose handles were removed.</p>
        <p>Spaeth Design employs 50 people, including sculptors, painters, carpenters and metalworkers. ''We can make just about anything,'' said Richard Pollard, the company's head designer.</p>
        <p>One of the few objects that was purchased this year was the spinning globe for the News Building. ''We had to airbrush out all the countries that didn't exist in the 30's,'' Mr. Pollard said.</p>
        <p>Spaeth also recently completed six Christmas windows that open Tuesday at Saks Fifth Avenue, at Fifth Avenue and 50th Street. They tell the story of the Velveteen Rabbit, in which a young boy's toy magically turns into a real rabbit.</p>
        <p>The Saks staff decided that since the story was written in 1922, the windows should represent a house decorated in the Arts and Crafts style. Mr. Pollard was thrilled by the assignment.</p>
        <p>''This is the year I got to put all the things I really love in the windows,'' he said. ''I collect Arts and Crafts furniture. Most of the pieces in the windows are based on pieces I really own.''</p>
        <p>Three of the windows feature interiors: a living room, a music room and a child's bedroom. Mr. Pollard covered the walls with Art Nouveau friezes and wallpapers and fabrics that have small-scale prints. He transformed white cotton throw rugs into elegant carpets by painting Art Nouveau designs on them.</p>
        <p>Two other windows show the exterior of the house, and the last reveals the forest where the rabbit comes to life, nestled in the arms of a winged fairy. The trees and snowdrifts were made of papier-mache, and cast rubber was used to simulate the fieldstone walls of the house.</p>
        <p>B. Altman's windows, at Fifth Avenue and 34th Street, came from a much less sophisticated shop: a room in the store's basement staffed by two carpenters and a painter. The mechanical figures were fabricated outside the store, by a company in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''We've always done our own windows. It's a matter of pride,'' said Virginia Hurley, the store's production manager.</p>
        <p>Last year's sets, which consisted of street scenes from Colonial Williamsburg, were incorporated into this year's windows, which were unveiled Saturday. They depict six Colonial interiors, including a toy shop, bakery, holiday decoration store, music teacher's study, fine sewing and millinery shop and ballroom.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hurley was responsible for finding many of the accessories. ''I'm a gleaner,'' she said. She found small pine cones near her house and used them in the decoration shop. She turned ashtrays from a fast-food restaurant into pie tins for the bakery. ''Every year, we stay up as late as we have to to finish the windows,'' Ms. Hurley said. ''Almost everyone in the display department helps out. It's a collective effort. There's a sweet zest to it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
