<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Soldier Found Guilty In Iraq Prison Abuse Case</title>
    <meta content="15ABUS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/15/national/15abuse.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1642138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE REACH OF WAR: THE VERDICT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reserves (Military)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fort Hood (Tex)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Abu Ghraib (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graner, Charles a Jr (Specialist)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Guards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Military)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Abu Ghraib</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DD1538F936A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Soldier Found Guilty In Iraq Prison Abuse Case</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Soldier Found Guilty in Iraq Prison Abuse Case</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ZERNIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <dateline>FORT HOOD, Tex., Jan. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Specialist Charles A Graner Jr, Army reservist accused of being ringleader in Abu Ghraib prison abuse scandal, is found guilty on all charges by military jury in Fort Hood, Tex; it is year to day after Pentagon began investigation into photographs showing Iraqi detainees bound and brutalized or forced into sexually humiliating positions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Army reservist accused of being the ringleader in the Abu Ghraib prison abuse scandal was found guilty on all charges by a military jury here Friday night, a year to the day after the Pentagon began an investigation into photographs showing Iraqi detainees bound and brutalized or forced into sexually humiliating positions.</p>
        <p>The jury of 10 soldiers deliberated for five hours before convicting the reservist, Specialist Charles A. Graner Jr., of assault, conspiracy, maltreatment of detainees, committing indecent acts, and dereliction of duty, as well as one battery count that the jury reduced from assault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Specialist Charles A. Graner Jr., who was accused of being the ringleader in the prison scandal, was found guilty on all charges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Army reservist accused of being the ringleader in the Abu Ghraib prison abuse scandal was found guilty on all charges by a military jury here Friday night, a year to the day after the Pentagon began an investigation into photographs showing Iraqi detainees bound and brutalized or forced into sexually humiliating positions.</p>
        <p>The jury of 10 soldiers deliberated for five hours before convicting the reservist, Specialist Charles A. Graner Jr., of assault, conspiracy, maltreatment of detainees, committing indecent acts, and dereliction of duty, as well as one battery count that the jury reduced from assault.</p>
        <p>The jury chose to move immediately into the sentencing phase of the trial Friday night, hearing testimony from prosecution and defense witnesses -- one side arguing that Specialist Graner was a patriotic soldier and a devoted son, the other that his violent actions had permanently damaged the military and the nation, as well as the lives of Iraqis who were abused.</p>
        <p>The judge, Col. James Pohl, dismissed the jury Friday night and said he would reconvene it on Saturday morning to finish hearing testimony and begin deliberations on a sentence. Specialist Graner, a 36-year-old former prison guard from Western Pennsylvania, had faced 17 and a half years in prison, and with the reduced count now faces 15. His lawyers told the judge that Specialist Graner would give a statement to the jury on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Specialist Graner is the first soldier to face a contested court-martial in the abuse scandal, which began after another reservist slipped a CD with the photographs under the door of Army investigators at Abu Ghraib in the dark of night, telling them when the investigation began the next day that he feared Specialist Graner would abuse prisoners again. The photographs leaked out in April, setting off a wave of international outrage against the United States as well as nine high-level Pentagon investigations into reports of abuse of detainees in Iraq and Afghanistan and at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor, Capt. Chris Graveline, urged jurors for a guilty verdict in his closing arguments, saying: ''It will speak volumes to the accused. It will speak volumes to our Army. It will speak volumes to our country. It will speak volumes to the world.''</p>
        <p>Specialist Graner, who chatted and smiled through much of the week, stood at attention and showed no emotion as the jury foreman read the verdict. His parents, who sat behind their son throughout testimony and expressed their love for him before television cameras, also showed no reaction.</p>
        <p>The jury heard from 23 witnesses, but not from Specialist Graner, despite early statements from his lawyers that he would testify because he was the best person to explain the acts seen in the photographs.</p>
        <p>Friday night, the prosecution opened the sentencing phase by presenting three witnesses who spoke to Specialist Graner's bad discipline and the damage caused by the abuse.</p>
        <p>Specialist Matthew Wisdom, 21, who served with Specialist Graner in the 372nd Military Police Company, based in Maryland, told how he had entered the Army wanting to pursue a career in the military. ''But after this, I don't,'' he testified.</p>
        <p>Specialist Wisdom, who came upon Specialist Graner and other soldiers jumping on a pile of detainees, said he also stopped pursuing a criminal justice degree in college.</p>
        <p>Hussein Mutar, an Iraqi who arrived at Abu Ghraib after Iraqi policemen accused him of car theft and ended up in the pile that Specialist Wisdom saw, spoke on videotape about his pain and humiliation.</p>
        <p>He testified earlier in the week about how, after jumping on him, Specialist Graner and other guards ordered him to strip, masturbate and simulate oral sex, and then photographed him and led him back to a cell they had soaked with water, where he had to sleep naked.</p>
        <p>''The Americans came to free the Iraqi people from Saddam -- I didn't expect this was going to happen,'' he said. ''When they first came, it appeared that they were good, but this incident changed the entire picture of what Americans look like.''</p>
        <p>''I think I'm going to have an emotional breakdown -- I wanted to try to kill myself,'' he said. ''My friends, my family, people in my neighborhood all know about this matter. How would I go and see these people?''</p>
        <p>The defense, under military law, is allowed more latitude in calling witnesses to offer mitigating evidence and had a longer list of witnesses, who began speaking last night.</p>
        <p>The defense did not say whether Specialist Graner would testify.</p>
        <p>His mother, Irma Graner, testified, recalling her son's youth outside Pittsburgh, his graduation with honor from Marine Corps training at Parris Island, and his love for his children.</p>
        <p>''I have medical problems, and if I needed my son to take me to the doctor or do anything, all I had to do was call him, he was there lickety split,'' she said. ''I never had an ounce of problems with him growing up. He's a wonderful son, he's kind, he's gentle, he'll do anything for anybody, and he's not the monster he's being made out to be. To this day I get many calls from strangers that think he's a hero, and in my eyes, he'll always be a hero.''</p>
        <p>His father, Charles A. Graner Sr., wept as he recalled how he and his son had made plans to go fishing when he returned from Iraq. When the scandal broke, he said, he knew ''it was going to be postponed.''</p>
        <p>''How long it's postponed is up to you,'' he told the jury. ''I'd get down and beg, but I know he wouldn't want me to do it, so I won't.''</p>
        <p>The defense also presented testimony from Sgt. Kenneth Davis, who spoke of Specialist Graner as a ''faithful'' soldier who helped hand out Bibles to Iraqis.</p>
        <p>Michael John Zavada, Specialist Graner's former supervisor at a prison in Pennsylvania, where Specialist Graner went to work shortly after getting out of the Marines after the Persian Gulf war, said, ''He was very disciplined, he was very easy to train.'' Mr. Zavada had chosen him for a special team that dealt with difficult prisoners, saying Specialist Graner was ''way above average.''</p>
        <p>Brian Cassidy, another supervisor, said Specialist Graner sometimes supervised prisoners on death row and performed ''on a professional level at all times.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cassidy also acknowledged that Specialist Graner was fired from the prison for disobeying a direct order not to leave his shift. He said he had to pick up his children, Mr. Cassidy said, and later got his job back.</p>
        <p>Throughout the trial, Specialist Graner's lawyers argued that he had been following orders to treat detainees harshly, and that the photographs resulted from these orders. They argued that he was taking the fall for higher officers -- some of whom have been implicated in Pentagon investigations, though none have been charged.</p>
        <p>But even defense witnesses admitted under questioning from the prosecution that there had been no orders for the acts seen in the photographs.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors portrayed Specialist Graner as a sadistic thug, abusing detainees for the fun of it.</p>
        <p>In closing arguments, they read his words to friends at the prison and from e-mail messages sent home, in which he boasted about beating and bloodying detainees.</p>
        <p>''These are the words that give you insight and context into his actions,'' Captain Graveline said. ''These are the words that give a frame to the photos taken at Abu Ghraib.''</p>
        <p>Specialist Graner is one of seven soldiers to be charged in the Abu Ghraib scandal. Three have pleaded guilty, including Specialist Jeremy C. Sivits, who agreed last May to testify against the others. Three others have yet to face a court-martial, including Lynndie R. England, who was seen in photographs holding a leash attached to the neck of a naked Iraqi detainee.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Soldier Convicted in Teen's Death</p>
        <p>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Jan. 14 (AP) -- A United States military judge convicted an Army sergeant of murder and sentenced him to a year's imprisonment Friday in the death of an injured Iraqi teenager that was described as a mercy killing.</p>
        <p>Staff Sgt. Jonathan J. Alban-Cardenas of Inglewood, Calif., was convicted of shooting the wounded 16-year-old. Witnesses say the teen was found with severe burns and abdominal wounds in a burning truck.</p>
        <p>The Americans decided that the boy was beyond help and that ''the best course of action'' was to put him ''out of his misery,'' a criminal investigator has said.</p>
        <p>Staff Sgt. Johnny M. Horne Jr., also with the Fort Riley, Kan.-based 41st Infantry regiment, was sentenced to three years in prison after pleading guilty in the same killing.</p>
        <p>THE REACH OF WAR: THE VERDICT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
