<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Please Turn Down the Music, We're Trying to Hear the Words</title>
    <meta content="15MERK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/15/arts/15merk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050120T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1642010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sequitur (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sequitur</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3D81438F936A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Please Turn Down the Music, We're Trying to Hear the Words</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Please Turn Down the Music, We're Trying to Hear the Words</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews concert by contemporary music ensemble Sequitur; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Compositions that combine music with spoken text are not easy to pull off. This issue came up in the two longest pieces on ''Creating the World,'' a program presented by Sequitur, the adventurous contemporary music ensemble, on Wednesday night at Merkin Concert Hall.</p>
        <p>When a text is set to music and sung, the words and music can strive for equitable balance. But when a text is spoken over music, the words stand out. If the text is interesting, the music can seem merely background, or even a distraction. On the other hand, if the text is folded into the musical textures as if it were just another instrument, then you wonder, why have a text at all?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The difficulties of pairing music with the spoken word were in evidence at Sequitur's concert on Wednesday at Merkin Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Compositions that combine music with spoken text are not easy to pull off. This issue came up in the two longest pieces on ''Creating the World,'' a program presented by Sequitur, the adventurous contemporary music ensemble, on Wednesday night at Merkin Concert Hall.</p>
        <p>When a text is set to music and sung, the words and music can strive for equitable balance. But when a text is spoken over music, the words stand out. If the text is interesting, the music can seem merely background, or even a distraction. On the other hand, if the text is folded into the musical textures as if it were just another instrument, then you wonder, why have a text at all?</p>
        <p>The inspiration for the composer Eve Beglarian's ''Creating the World'' (1996) was a poem of that title by Czeslaw Milosz, as translated into English by Milosz and Robert Hass. The poem's playful and wildly imagistic language conjures creation as a dizzying romp through stupefying chaos. Ms. Beglarian's score, which subtly combines amplified guitar, electric keyboards, percussion, bassoon and violin with taped elements and sampled sounds, opens with an evocation of a shimmering, murky, primordial cosmos. But once the spoken text (as recorded by the actor Roger Rees) begins, it's hard for the music to compete. One of the Celestials at the Board of Projects, as Milosz calls the creators, bursts into laughter after designing a hedgehog. Another Celestial, not to be left behind, creates a soprano: ''Eyelashes, a bust, and ringlets, plenty of ringlets.'' The text is so captivating that you want the music to pipe down. Still, Ms. Beglarian's musical imagination is always in evidence in this jam-packed and kaleidoscopic score.</p>
        <p>Richard Carrick's ''Cosmicomics,'' which received its world premiere, is scored for a large, varied instrumental ensemble, conducted here by Richard Hostetter. It also employed video elements by Peter Nigrini, which if anything created even more distraction from the business at hand: four extracts from Italo Calvino's novel of the same title, spoken here by Richard Lalli. Whole stretches of this organic, restless and unruly score conveyed the sense of creation as a tumultuous process. Again, the problem was that Mr. Lalli, who spoke the words with such elegant understatement during some passages, had to shout into a microphone to be heard at all during the music's rambunctious episodes.</p>
        <p>Two instrumental pieces had an easier time of it. Bunita Marcus's ''Adam and Eve,'' though lulling and pretty with its rippling repeated riffs, was finally too drawn out and musically thin. But Carlos Carrillo's gentle and harmonically beguiling ''Como si fuera la primavera'' was a joy.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 20, 2005, Thursday  A classical music review on Saturday about a program by the Sequitur ensemble at Merkin Concert Hall misstated the given name of the conductor for ''Cosmicomics'' by Richard Carrick. He is Paul Hostetter, not Richard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 20, 2005, Thursday</p>
        <p>A classical music review on Saturday about a program by the Sequitur ensemble at Merkin Concert Hall misstated the given name of the conductor for ''Cosmicomics'' by Richard Carrick. He is Paul Hostetter, not Richard.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
