<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/New Jersey; Standing Room Only at Schools That Train Agents</title>
    <meta content="25NJZO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/25/realestate/25NJZO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1418441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Century 21</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7D7173CF936A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/New Jersey; Standing Room Only at Schools That Train Agents</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Standing Room Only at Schools That Train Agents</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTOINETTE MARTIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN last we glimpsed Carmela Soprano -- in last season's finale of HBO's ''The Sopranos'' -- she was in the midst of trying to transform a life she realized was ''financed by crime,'' and appeared to be turning to New Jersey real estate. In a telling moment, Mrs. Soprano sat at a simple table in the McMansion that mob money bought and pored over a primer used by students preparing for the state licensing exam.</p>
        <p>When the new season begins in three weeks, ''she might as well join the crowd,'' laughed Edward Davies, director of the American School of Business. Mr. Davies's school offers the classes required for people who want to take the state test to become a real estate agent. ''Enrollment is through the roof right now,'' he said. ''We are taking down walls to expand classrooms, moving furniture -- anything we can do to accommodate people.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Schools in New Jersey that offer classes for people who want to take the state test to become real estate agents say enrollment has soared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN last we glimpsed Carmela Soprano -- in last season's finale of HBO's ''The Sopranos'' -- she was in the midst of trying to transform a life she realized was ''financed by crime,'' and appeared to be turning to New Jersey real estate. In a telling moment, Mrs. Soprano sat at a simple table in the McMansion that mob money bought and pored over a primer used by students preparing for the state licensing exam.</p>
        <p>When the new season begins in three weeks, ''she might as well join the crowd,'' laughed Edward Davies, director of the American School of Business. Mr. Davies's school offers the classes required for people who want to take the state test to become a real estate agent. ''Enrollment is through the roof right now,'' he said. ''We are taking down walls to expand classrooms, moving furniture -- anything we can do to accommodate people.''</p>
        <p>The American School of Business has eight sites in eight cities around the state where it prepares 1,500 students a year to take the licensing exam. It is the largest of several dozen independently operated schools in New Jersey, although it is small compared with the Weichert Real Estate School, affiliated with Weichert Realtors.</p>
        <p>Weichert trains about half of those who take the state exam, and its enrollment is also soaring. Weichert has enrolled 5,702 students so far this year, said the program's director, Pat Renner, which is 53 percent higher that than at the same point last year.</p>
        <p>''And last year,'' Ms. Renner said, ''we had our highest enrollment ever.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Davies, Ms. Renner spoke of pushing classroom space to the legal limit for professional classes, which is 60 students.</p>
        <p>There are now 82,817 licensed real estate agents in New Jersey, according to the National Association of Realtors. That is up 3.7 percent from January.. The association says there is a high rate of attrition in the real estate field generally, however, pointing out that many licensees never get a single listing or sell a property.</p>
        <p>''The real estate market in New Jersey is very strong for residential properties right now,'' said Frank W. Kovats, who directs the Kovats Real Estate and Insurance Schools he founded 30 years ago in Maywood. ''When the market is strong, then the market for real estate students is very strong. Our classes are filled.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kovats said current enrollment was still not as high as during the big housing boom in the 1980's, when there were more course providers. In the last 15 years, most county and community colleges have stopped offering the real estate classes, Mr. Kovats said, because their tuition costs could not compete with those at schools like his.</p>
        <p>The American School of Business offers the required 75 hours of instruction over three weeks on a Monday-to-Thursday schedule or over 12 weeks on two nights a week or on 12 Saturdays. The cost is $350.</p>
        <p>Weichert's school costs $249 for a two-week all-day class, a 10-week night class or a 10-week Saturday class. Mr. Kovats's fee is $395, including materials, for a similar set of scheduled classes.</p>
        <p>SOME students are sponsored by a particular real estate agency that wants to hire them after they graduate. Mr. Davies said he had agreements with Coldwell Banker, Burgdorff ERA, Century 21 and other agencies to pay a discounted price for students they sponsored.</p>
        <p>In a Weichert class in Westfield this month, two students sitting beside each other in a classroom on the second floor of the Westfield Inn were being sponsored by Weichert's office in Union.</p>
        <p>Nick Rawls, 28, of Hillsdale said he had recently been laid off at the General Motors plant in Linden. ''I like the idea of selling homes, and I'd like to be comfortable financially again,'' he said. His seatmate, Jacqueline Floyd, 38, of Irvington, said she had worked at a health insurance company. ''Real estate is something I always wanted to do,'' she said. ''As a single parent, I also like the idea of a job with flexibility.''</p>
        <p>Other students in the class gave different reasons for being there. Marcus Mera of Flushing, Queens, said he was primarily a ''diamond man,'' selling rare and unusual stones. But he also seeks properties to buy for his father's construction business in Somerset and needs to be licensed as a buying agent for that, said Mr. Mera, 26.</p>
        <p>Anita Deochand, 19, a sophomore at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, said she worked part time assisting Richard Abrams, a Century 21 agent in Plainsboro. ''He thinks I would make a good agent,'' Miss Deochand said. ''I think it's a great thing to have on your résumé and use throughout your life. I'm extending my horizons.''</p>
        <p>Most students plan to sell residential real estate, rather than commercial properties, and work for an agency in their home communities, directors at various schools said. Ms. Renner said many students planned to work for the numerous relocation companies in the state.</p>
        <p>Those hired to teach real estate classes are generally active or retired residential sales agents, according to several school directors. Linda Finkelstein, the teacher in Westfield, is a former agent. Mrs. Finkelstein, like other teachers and school officials, said she had noted a rise in the quality of students along with the rise in numbers. A growing number of students have had previous experience in fields like banking or insurance, school officials said, and had lost jobs in the wave of corporate layoffs.</p>
        <p>''But in a two-week class on real estate,'' Mrs. Finkelstein said, ''there is a tremendous amount for anybody to absorb.'' Just before the final exam in a class that ended Aug. 15, Mrs. Finkelstein fired questions about the different types of property ownership: ''With tenancy in common, do you have a right to partition when you inherit? If you want to divorce and still hold the real estate, how do you hold it? How about if you are living together?''</p>
        <p>There was a jackhammer pounding a staccato racket outside as she spoke, but the students stayed focused, calling out responses in unison like a corps of Army recruits. Then, Mrs. Finkelstein popped a question about the four unities of joint tenancy -- apparently just to break the tension because giggles and cries of ''Brad Pitt, smoking a joint!'' broke out around the room.</p>
        <p>''You got it,'' Mrs. Finkelstein said, with a satisfied smile. ''Possession. Interest. Time. Title.'' She had told this class about a story a previous class made up as a memory device, using the initials P.I.T.T.</p>
        <p>The percentage of students in any class who pass final exams and are thus approved to take the state exam at a designated testing center varies widely, school directors said. The State Real Estate Commission does not disclose how many of those who take the licensing exam pass it. But directors said it was usually about 80 percent.</p>
        <p>On the licensing exam, a passing grade is 70 percent. A test taker must answer at least 56 of 80 general questions about real estate correctly as well as 21 of 30 questions about New Jersey laws and regulations on the two-part test.</p>
        <p>Some students exhibit serious ''math anxiety,'' Mr. Kovats said. But a few years ago, the number of math questions was halved, he said. There were 16 questions about capitalization rate, sales commission, acreage and the like. Now there are only eight, he said.</p>
        <p>Would-be real estate agents come from a ''mixed bag of backgrounds,'' Ms. Renner said. ''In summertime, there are a lot of people just out of high school or college in class, but we have a wide variety of ages, including people in their 70's or 80's. Some people may barely speak English and have to work very hard to absorb the material. It's amazing to see.''</p>
        <p>It is not unusual for a student to show up the first day and never return, she said. The most common reason for students who do show up and master the material not to get their licenses is that they have a legal problem, such as unpaid child support, or a criminal record they failed to disclose when asked on the licensing exam, Ms. Renner said. An undisclosed past conviction is one reason a license can be revoked.</p>
        <p>''The state is very concerned about criminal records,'' Ms. Renner said. ''After all, these people will be handling other people's funds -- escrow checks, and so on. We always tell students they're better off telling the state up front that they had a challenge somewhere back.''</p>
        <p>''I hope Carmela has been forewarned,'' added Ms. Renner, a major fan of the show.</p>
        <p>Another matter Mrs. Soprano may need warning about involves a photographic record. Licensing exams are given on computers and results are instantly available. A test taker emerges from a silent room with soft lighting, is given the news about passing by a desk clerk and is instantly photographed by a black-and-white camera on the wall. ''Even with the most attractive people, it's usually a pretty ghastly photo,'' Ms. Renner said. ''She better be warned about that, too.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
