<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Merrill Lynch Explores Sale Of a Big Stake In Its Fund Unit</title>
    <meta content="03PLAC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/03/business/03place.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Merrill Lynch &amp; Co Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Legg Mason Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Landon Jr</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Merrill Lynch &amp; Company Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Legg Mason Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E5DA1531F930A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Merrill Lynch Explores Sale Of a Big Stake In Its Fund Unit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Merrill Lynch Explores Sale of a Big Stake in Its Fund Unit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LANDON THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Landon Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Merrill Lynch is talking with Legg Mason about selling big stake in its investment business; mutual fund trading scandal and increased scrutiny of fund marketing by state and federal regulators have made business riskier for investment banks (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Merrill Lynch has been exploring the possibility of selling a big stake in its investment management business, according to bankers who have been briefed on the discussions.</p>
        <p>The firm has long been a gatherer of assets. But the mutual fund trading scandal and increased scrutiny of fund marketing by state and federal regulators has made the business riskier for investment banks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Merrill's talks are the most concrete sign that investment banks are reassessing their commitment to fund companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Merrill Lynch has been exploring the possibility of selling a big stake in its investment management business, according to bankers who have been briefed on the discussions.</p>
        <p>The firm has long been a gatherer of assets. But the mutual fund trading scandal and increased scrutiny of fund marketing by state and federal regulators has made the business riskier for investment banks.</p>
        <p>In recent months, these executives say, Merrill has had talks with Legg Mason, the Baltimore-based investment management company, about such a sale. For Legg Mason, which manages $286 billion in assets, taking on Merrill's $513 billion would lift it into the big leagues of money management.</p>
        <p>Merrill's talks with Legg Mason have been described as exploratory, and both firms declined to comment, citing policies that prohibit them from addressing market rumors.</p>
        <p>Merrill's talks are the most concrete sign that investment banks, which spent billions of dollars over the past decade buying fund companies in pursuit of smoother revenue streams and a stable of internal funds to sell through their brokers, are reassessing their commitment to these divisions.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley, which recently paid a $50 million fine to regulators for improper mutual fund sales practices, closed 13 proprietary funds in April as part of its effort to increase the sales of its Van Kampen funds through outside financial advisers.</p>
        <p>Merrill has been undergoing a broad reconsideration of its fund business. In a recent research note by Richard Strauss, a brokerage analyst for Deutsche Bank Securities, Robert C. Doll Jr., the president of Merrill's investment management division, acknowledged that a partial sale of the fund unit would ease regulatory conflicts.</p>
        <p>For a senior Merrill executive to contemplate such a move publicly represents a stark reversal from the more expansive view held by past Merrill chairmen that the firm should be ready to provide every possible financial service to its clients no matter the cost.</p>
        <p>''That a broker would even think of owning less than 100 percent of its asset management subsidiary speaks to the pressures affecting the industry right now,'' Mr. Strauss said. ''But it has become clear, that under Stan O'Neal, Merrill is looking to tap into new avenues for growth.''</p>
        <p>E. Stanley O'Neal, the current chairman and a former chief financial officer at the firm, has placed more emphasis on cutting costs and maximizing returns -- a strategy that has reaped dividends as Merrill's profits soared last year on the back of a boom in the firm's bond trading business.</p>
        <p>Like other Wall Street firms and Morgan Stanley in particular, Merrill Lynch originally developed a proprietary fund business to provide its sprawling brokerage network with a ready source of mutual funds to sell.</p>
        <p>But spotty performance by the funds, as well as greater restrictions on the incentives that banks can offer their brokers to market them, has prompted banks like Merrill to consider severing the money management and distribution arms of the businesses.</p>
        <p>In many ways, Legg Mason could be the perfect partner for Merrill. Unlike many of its peers, Legg has steered clear of any major run-ins with regulators over improper trading in its mutual funds or questionable sales practices by its 1,400 brokers.</p>
        <p>Unlike Merrill's funds, which are managed by a fleet of mostly anonymous portfolio managers, Legg Mason boasts perhaps the best-known fund manager in the industry in William H. Miller 3d, the manager of Legg Mason Value Trust, who has a 13-year streak of beating the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller's performance record has driven Legg Mason's success in two ways. At the sales level, it has been a magnet for incoming assets. But his rigid and disciplined investing style has created an unusual and admired stock-picking culture within Legg Mason, and that could be the primary draw for Merrill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doll has provided a shot in the arm for Merrill's once struggling funds -- 70 percent of assets are now outperforming their benchmark. Still, Merrill's inconsistent performance history suggests that dedicated fund management companies tend to produce better performance than investment banks in the long run.</p>
        <p>What remains to be seen is how Merrill's brokers accept such an arrangement, given that Legg Mason brokers compete directly with them in many areas, especially on the Eastern Seaboard.</p>
        <p>But for Merrill executives, the move makes sense on paper.</p>
        <p>If Legg Mason took a controlling stake in Merrill's fund business, Legg would have primary responsibility for managing the hornet's nest of potential conflicts that arise when brokers sell in-house funds.</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
