<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Real Super Sleuths, With Real Superglue</title>
    <meta content="03HEFF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/03/arts/television/03HEFF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1586458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heffernan, Virginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Papa, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">First 48, The (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Come to Papa (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">A&amp;E Television Networks</org>
        <object.title class="online_producer">First 48, The (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DE1531F930A35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Real Super Sleuths, With Real Superglue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Real Super Sleuths, With Real Superglue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia Heffernan reviews A&amp;E's new reality series The First 48 and new NBC sitcom Come to Papa starring Tom Papa; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unlike the directors of photography on feature documentaries, camera operators on reality television don't have months to accustom their subjects to their presence. Consequently the cameras distract everyone, and people invariably play to them. To minimize this temptation -- in hopes of keeping the on-screen drama semi-authentic -- reality television producers try to shoot action that is more emotionally urgent than the cameras themselves, leaving characters no choice but to stay involved in it.</p>
        <p>The producers of ''The First 48,'' which starts tonight on A&amp;E, have done that. They've chosen the premiere theme -- murder -- that can be counted on to intrigue the show's participants more than being on television. Beginning with the premise that to solve a homicide, the police ought to find a lead within the case's first 48 hours (after that, the chances of solving the crime are said to diminish by half), ''The First 48'' sticks by detectives as they swab down crime scenes, hunt for witnesses and interrogate suspects. These cops also make jokes about junk food and the obesity of suspects, but less than the officers on fiction shows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the countdown, the lingo, the crime-scene images, the tough and tender cops and the resolutions, "The First 48" is near-perfect television drama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unlike the directors of photography on feature documentaries, camera operators on reality television don't have months to accustom their subjects to their presence. Consequently the cameras distract everyone, and people invariably play to them. To minimize this temptation -- in hopes of keeping the on-screen drama semi-authentic -- reality television producers try to shoot action that is more emotionally urgent than the cameras themselves, leaving characters no choice but to stay involved in it.</p>
        <p>The producers of ''The First 48,'' which starts tonight on A&amp;E, have done that. They've chosen the premiere theme -- murder -- that can be counted on to intrigue the show's participants more than being on television. Beginning with the premise that to solve a homicide, the police ought to find a lead within the case's first 48 hours (after that, the chances of solving the crime are said to diminish by half), ''The First 48'' sticks by detectives as they swab down crime scenes, hunt for witnesses and interrogate suspects. These cops also make jokes about junk food and the obesity of suspects, but less than the officers on fiction shows.</p>
        <p>The series starts in Miami -- the locale changes from episode to episode -- with the report of ''a bang'' to 911. A clock begins to count down, and the show keeps firing. Detective Mayree Morin, elegantly dressed in diamonds, a cream-colored coat and three-inch heels, appears on the scene. A man has been shot and killed in Little Havana, apparently a gang murder. Potential witnesses decline to comment.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, in Coconut Grove, a woman is found shot in her kitchen. A huge commando type named Pepi Granado takes the call. Emma Lew, a medical examiner, says the murder is ''almost an execution shot.'' (Armchair detectives always sit up straighter at the mention of ''execution style.'' Why do we all think we know what that implies?)</p>
        <p>The victim's son is questioned. Like so many people interrogated by the police, innocent or guilty, the son's speech is guarded, and he talks in monosyllables. ''Whappened?'' is among his greatest expressions of curiosity. Several other people appear to lose their focus and lapse dreamily into silence. Police shows rarely show so much incidental or drug-induced muteness. Do the cameras affect this?</p>
        <p>Heaps of Superglue are made to fume on ''The First 48.'' One of the central principles of the show is that Superglue fumes bond with the amino acids of fingerprints, making them easier to observe. Even with the fuming procedure, however, the police find few clues to the Coconut Grove murder. Back in Little Havana, Detective Morin treats suspects to a display of interrogation room theatrics -- ''She's a great actress, man; she's awesome,'' says her boss, Sgt. Joe Schillaci, a keyboard player -- which finally elicits a confession.</p>
        <p>Next week's episode follows Philadelphia cops as they pursue two equally perplexing murder cases. The first concerns a body found burned beyond recognition. A composite sketch, as well as some clues to her clothing, lead them to identify the victim as a woman named Carmen, whose boyfriend is violent and -- but she's alive. Eventually the police determine that it's another dark-haired girl, with another bad boyfriend, name of Benny Moose.</p>
        <p>Very good fume-induced fingerprints on a rum bottle point the cops to a suspect in another murder, this one of a man in his rented house. The prints belong to Little Herb, the victim's brother. He can't be found. Even Big Herb, his father, doesn't know where he is. Or isn't telling.</p>
        <p>With the countdown, the lingo, the crime-scene images, the tough and tender cops and the resolutions, ''The First 48'' is near-perfect television drama. It might not be better than ''Cops,'' but it's as good. And that's saying a lot.</p>
        <p>COME TO PAPA  NBC, tonight at 8:30, Eastern and Pacific times; 7:30, Central time</p>
        <p>Hey, ''Come to Papa,'' we've seen ''King of Queens.'' We love ''King of Queens.'' You're no ''King of Queens.''</p>
        <p>Yes, this new NBC sitcom, which starts tonight, has a bald sweetheart husband, backtalking wife, charmer friend and crotchety geezer. It's nice. Tom Papa, the good-natured stand-up comic who used to open for Jerry Seinfeld, created the sitcom as a showcase. He stars, writes and produces. He seems like a decent man.</p>
        <p>But this sitcom is opiated, so slow it appears mentally impaired. An early joke about pigeons tonight lasts 400 beats, by my count. A story line about a madcap tire salesman -- Mr. Papa plays a full-time newspaper reporter who is unaccountably also an adman and a comedian -- is obsolete, labored. Maybe this adagio, along with the vintage sitcom setup, is meant to seduce viewers who have expressed disdain for the auctioneer-pace of ''The West Wing,'' ''Gilmore Girls'' and even ''Friends.''</p>
        <p>Or maybe ''Come to Papa'' is some kind of experimental theater. In any case, for the consolations of happy, harmless comedy, stick with ''King of Queens.''</p>
        <p>THE FIRST 48  A&amp;E, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time</p>
        <p>Laura Fleury and Nancy Dubuc, executive producers for A&amp;E Network; Charles Tremayne, executive producer for Granada America New York; John X. Kim, supervising producer. Produced by Granada America New York for A&amp;E Network.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
