<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Berlin Journal;Exoneration Still Eludesc An Anti-Nazi Crusader</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="822288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BERLIN, GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OSSIETZKY, CARL VON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DB1039F930A25752C0A960958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Berlin Journal;Exoneration Still Eludesc An Anti-Nazi Crusader</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, Jan. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During his turbulent life, Carl von Ossietzky, winner of the 1935 Nobel Peace Prize, did not lack for enemies.</p>
        <p>In the years before the Nazis took power in 1933, he edited a crusading Berlin magazine, Weltbuhne, which preached pacifism and strongly opposed German  rearmament. He spent time in jail and in two concentration camps before dying of the effects of his mistreatment in 1938, at age 48.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During his turbulent life, Carl von Ossietzky, winner of the 1935 Nobel Peace Prize, did not lack for enemies.</p>
        <p>In the years before the Nazis took power in 1933, he edited a crusading Berlin magazine, Weltbuhne, which preached pacifism and strongly opposed German  rearmament. He spent time in jail and in two concentration camps before dying of the effects of his mistreatment in 1938, at age 48.</p>
        <p>But today, some powerful Germans refuse to embrace Ossietzky as a hero. In 1992 a federal court rejected an attempt to void his conviction and to grant him posthumous rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Recently, several members of the German Parliament introduced a bill that would set the stage for his rehabilitation. They hope that the bill, which would broaden the grounds on which such rehabilitation may be granted, will be debated within the next few months.</p>
        <p>"It is hard to accept a court decision which asserts the correctness of giving heavy sentences to oppressed citizens for failing to observe a fully false 'loyalty' to an illegal and unconstitutional regime," said Jurgen Meyer, a sponsor of the bill.</p>
        <p>A plaque now marks the Berlin building where Ossietzky published Weltbuhne, and last year a Hamburg publisher brought out an eight-volume collection of his writings. Nearly everyone who grew up in East Germany knows his story, although the East German Government published only carefully selected extracts from his work and falsely portrayed him as a Communist sympathizer. But many West Germans learned little or nothing about him.</p>
        <p>"The Nazi regime demonized Ossietzky, and the effects of that campaign can still be felt in Germany today," said Eckhart Rottka, an organizer of the campaign for Ossietzky's rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>"He was a pacifist, and during the cold war that was viewed very badly in West Germany. Add to that the fact that the Communists in East Germany seized on him as a symbol and tried to make him into a hero of their own, and you have an  idea of why there is so much resistance to the idea of rehabilitating him."</p>
        <p>The difficulty in winning a rehabilitation for Ossietzky reflects one of the  many anomalies in the way Germany deals with victims of Nazism and their survivors. Most widows of executed resistance fighters, for example, are entitled to no compensation, while retired Nazi officers and their widows receive monthly pensions.</p>
        <p>Persuading German judges to reverse decisions by their predecessors has proven all but impossible. Even many patently political verdicts decreed by Nazi military courts, including death sentences, are still officially considered valid.</p>
        <p>"The German judicial system has never faced the facts of its role in the Nazi period," said Elke Suhr, who published a biography of Ossietzky in 1989. "The judiciary considers itself a nonpolitical branch of Government and has never looked self-criticlly at what it did in service to an unjust regime."</p>
        <p>Ossietzky was a principal target of German nationalists in the late 1920's and early 1930's. They considered his antimilitarism a form of treason.</p>
        <p>In 1929, Weltbuhne published an article asserting that tests of new German planes violated provisions of the Versailles Treaty after World War I that were  intended to prevent German rearmament.</p>
        <p>Ossietzky was convicted of revealing military secrets and sentenced to 18 months in prison. He was released under an amnesty after eight months.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 28, 1933, the day after the Reichstag fire, Ossietzky was one of many anti-Nazi figures arrested in police sweeps. He was sent to a concentration camp and was still in custody when he learned that, after a vigorous campaign by German exiles including Albert Einstein, Thomas Mann and Willy Brandt, he had been awarded the Nobel Prize.</p>
        <p>The Nobel Committee described him as "a citizen of the world whose cause is freedom of thought, freedom of speech and free competition in the realm of ideas."</p>
        <p>Air Force Minister Hermann Goring offered to free Ossietzky if he would renounce the prize, but he refused.</p>
        <p>In 1938, Ossietzky died in a Nazi hospital. Relatives believe that he had been injected with tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>Efforts to win a judicial rehabilitation for Ossietzky began as Germany was unified in 1990. They failed when a three-judge panel ruled that rehabilitation  was not possible because the petitioners, who include Ossietzky's daughter, had  failed to present "new facts or evidence."</p>
        <p>"Erroneous applications of law are not sufficient grounds for reopening a criminal case," the court ruled.</p>
        <p>Supporters of Ossietzky in Germany and elsewhere were outraged.</p>
        <p>"I couldn't believe it," the Swedish author Jan Myrdal said in an interview.  "As far as I know, Germany is the only country which has formalized the principle that the state stands above the law. Fidelity to the state is everything."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
