<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Medical Schools Found to Vary In Their Drug-Testing Standards</title>
    <meta content="26TRIA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/26/national/26trial.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1675367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED71339F935A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Medical Schools Found to Vary In Their Drug-Testing Standards</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Medical Schools Found to Vary in Their Drug-Testing Standards</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A survey of more than 100 medical schools has found that they vary widely in their standards for testing new medicines for drug companies, with some saying they would accept far more control from the companies than others would.</p>
        <p>In the survey, being reported today in The New England Journal of Medicine, almost none of the medical schools said they would allow private sponsors to quash publication of research findings. But they differed greatly on other standards, like whether researchers should be allowed to discuss trials publicly while they are under way or share raw research data with other scientists, and whether drug companies sponsoring the tests should be allowed to insert their own analyses into research reports, suggest revisions before they are published or even draft reports in the first place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a survey of more than 100 medical schools, some said they would accept far more control from drug companies than others would.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A survey of more than 100 medical schools has found that they vary widely in their standards for testing new medicines for drug companies, with some saying they would accept far more control from the companies than others would.</p>
        <p>In the survey, being reported today in The New England Journal of Medicine, almost none of the medical schools said they would allow private sponsors to quash publication of research findings. But they differed greatly on other standards, like whether researchers should be allowed to discuss trials publicly while they are under way or share raw research data with other scientists, and whether drug companies sponsoring the tests should be allowed to insert their own analyses into research reports, suggest revisions before they are published or even draft reports in the first place.</p>
        <p>The researchers, from the Harvard School of Public Health and the University of Massachusetts, Boston, said the variation in these standards might lead drug companies to channel their research money ''to relatively permissive institutions.'' And they reported that 69 percent of the administrators surveyed said competition for research money ''created pressure on administrators to compromise'' with drug companies seeking to finance trials.</p>
        <p>Commercial sponsorship of drug trials has come under scrutiny recently amid allegations that industry sponsors did not adequately disclose evidence of safety problems in a class of arthritis drugs called cox-2 inhibitors. The researchers said the industry now provided about 70 percent of the financing for clinical drug trials in the United States, contracting with academic medical centers and commercial research enterprises.</p>
        <p>Government research contracts ''tend to look pretty different,'' Dr. Michelle M. Mello of the Harvard School of Public Health, an author of the new study, said in an interview. For example, ''there is no issue with proprietary information,'' Dr Mello said, adding, ''And a government sponsor would not be involved in shaping manuscripts.''</p>
        <p>The researchers acknowledged that they were not able to examine research contracts themselves. Instead, they relied on administrators' replies to a survey about what kinds of restrictions would or would not be allowed at their institutions. The researchers obtained responses from administrators at 107 of the 122 American medical schools they surveyed.</p>
        <p>Scott Lassman, assistant general counsel for the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, which represents drug makers, questioned the study's relevance to actual research.</p>
        <p>''It's a hypothetical study,'' Mr. Lassman said. ''It doesn't measure what these institutions routinely do or don't do.''</p>
        <p>He said it was hard to believe that drug makers would shop around for an acquiescent medical school before awarding a research contract. ''The main thing they focus on is whether the researchers are high quality,'' Mr. Lassman said.</p>
        <p>The researchers said 82 percent of the institutions surveyed reported they had experienced at least one dispute with an industry sponsor after a trial agreement had been signed. Usually the disputes involved money, the researchers wrote, but sometimes they exhibited ''embedded ethical issues.''</p>
        <p>One respondent told of commercial sponsors who refused to make the last payment for a drug trial ''apparently because they did not like the results of the study.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
