<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pedomania</title>
    <meta content="COHENT23" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Brian</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Madeleine's World (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDE1538F930A15752C1A961958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pedomania</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Cohen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Cohen reviews book Madeleine's World. A Child's Journey From Birth to Age Three by Brian Hall; drawing (L)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MADELEINE'S WORLD</p>
        <p>A Child's Journey</p>
        <p>From Birth to Age Three.</p>
        <p>By Brian Hall.</p>
        <p>262 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MADELEINE'S WORLD</p>
        <p>A Child's Journey</p>
        <p>From Birth to Age Three.</p>
        <p>By Brian Hall.</p>
        <p>262 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $20.</p>
        <p>Some literary scholar of tomorrow, writing in zero gravity with his laser pen, may point back to this book as the apotheosis of the late 20th-century memoir. Brian Hall has written the life of a 3-year-old. His own 3-year-old. This is not a sly literary satire of biographical excess; this is paternal doting:</p>
        <p>''We had sometimes called her the Bun when she was in the womb, as in 'the bun in Pam's oven,' and at birth the moniker had lengthened naturally into Honeybun, or Hon-bun, which later exfoliated into Hon-bun Humbledy Bum, at which point it was futile trying to keep out the Bumble Bee tuna jingle of my childhood, and I went the whole nine yards: 'Hon-bun Humbledy Bum Bum Hon-bun Bum,' and so on.''</p>
        <p>And so on. And on and on. For 262 pages. That we find our own children utterly endearing is nature's way of assuring that we don't kill, cook and eat them. But it would be false to assume that their appeal is universal.</p>
        <p>Being made foolish by love is one of its perverse pleasures; this is as true of parental love as any other. Sadly, this gentle madness does not sharpen one's judgment. Hall subtitles his book ''A Child's Journey From Birth to Age Three.'' One can surmise a great deal about a book if the word ''journey'' appears on the cover but no railroad train has appeared by page 10. What does appear is exclamation points and plenty of them. I open the book at random and find six on page 64, six on 147, five on 212 -- a sort of graphic hyperventilation. We are not merely presented with Madeleine, but grabbed by the lapels and forced to marvel at the miracle of her growth. This is a book that uses the adjective ''Wordsworthian'' three times, that employs the term ''Whitmanesque'' to discuss Dr. Seuss' ''Horton Hears a Who!'' Love struck. Goofy.</p>
        <p>Hall's design is to alternate observation with speculation, recording some new Madeleinian behavior and then theorizing about its meaning or prehuman origins or cultural parallels or Darwinian roots. Here Madeleine, just a few months old, waves to her dad as he feeds her: ''As I guided the spoon toward her mouth, was she waving to me to signal that, yes, we were in agreement, I had understood what she wanted? Or was she waving to the food itself, out of some inarticulate need to pay tribute, the unburied seed of a culture's prayers to the corn god, or the saying of grace?''</p>
        <p>Dr. Johnson is said to have commented on a book: ''It is both good and original. Unfortunately, those parts that are good are not original, and those that are original are not good.'' In his journalism and particularly in his well-received novel ''The Saskiad,'' Hall's interest in myth, philosophy and psychology informs his work. But in contemplating his young daughter, his exegesis of her behavior caroms between the familiar and the farfetched.</p>
        <p>Early in his brilliant and moving ''Edwin Mullhouse,'' a novel in the form of a biography of one 11-year-old boy written by another, Steven Millhauser meticulously records infant Edwin's earliest utterances: ''aaaaa (crying), nnnnn (complaining), kkkkk (giggling).'' In these chapters, he accomplishes many things; among them, he acutely observes infant behavior, explores the biographer-subject relationship, satirizes the portrait of the artist. One wishes Hall had better used his skill and passion as an observer to link his daughter's story to larger ideas beyond herself.</p>
        <p>Instead we get a chapter that begins ''Madeleine's words had lost much of their sympathetic magic'' and goes on to list her adorable linguistic missteps. ''At the end of a meal she would contentedly say, 'I ate a fair amountain of that.' '' Cute indeed, but it is not Piaget; it's Art Linkletter doing ''Kids Say the Darnedest Things.''</p>
        <p>One wonders what the adult Madeleine will think of all this. Will she be pleased when her college roommate stumbles across this passage: ''She had lately been introduced to a potty seat, which she called 'papa,' and would try it, as long as I dropped my pants and sat on the toilet at the same time''? If you marry a writer, you know what you're getting into. But have children no claims to privacy? Are they to be denied even the protection of a pseudonym?</p>
        <p>Our language needs a kid version of the word ''uxorious'' to convey a man's preoccupation not with his wife but with his baby. Pedomania, perhaps. It is a comic condition of course, and also rather moving, filled with tenderness and affection. But until it passes, those so afflicted should be cautious about the urge toward memoir.  Randy Cohen has recently written for the on-line magazine Slate; his ''West Side Diaries'' can be heard on WNYC-FM.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Randy Cohen has recently written for the on-line magazine Slate; his ''West Side Diaries'' can be heard on WNYC-FM.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
