<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Search of Chow Mein</title>
    <meta content="23FEAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD7123BF930A15752C1A961958260" item-length="2293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Search of Chow Mein</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Corey Kilgannon discusses her search of Chinese restaurants for Chicken Chow Mein dish that she recalled as youth; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Marcel Proust's ''Remembrance of Things Past,'' a stream of memories is  triggered by the taste of a madeleine  cookie, the kind the narrator used to eat in his childhood.</p>
        <p>My own recent journey into the past came during the mad lunchtime rush in a packed midtown Chinese fast food joint. I was sitting over a bowl of chicken chow mein. Remember chow mein? The mushy vegetable concoction with your choice of meat  served on hard egg noodles?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Marcel Proust's ''Remembrance of Things Past,'' a stream of memories is  triggered by the taste of a madeleine  cookie, the kind the narrator used to eat in his childhood.</p>
        <p>My own recent journey into the past came during the mad lunchtime rush in a packed midtown Chinese fast food joint. I was sitting over a bowl of chicken chow mein. Remember chow mein? The mushy vegetable concoction with your choice of meat  served on hard egg noodles?</p>
        <p>That was my epiphany, my Rosebud. Sitting over the gooey, stewy rice mixture, the steam from the dish blurred my glasses like the memory scene segues in ''Gilligan's Island.'' Then a flood of childhood remembrances of Chinese meals past began to spill  forth.</p>
        <p>With each forkful they grew sharper: red tablecloths with heavy white napkins in a restaurant guarded by huge roaring dragon statues. A poker-faced waiter in a dark red tunic with black trim delivering, first, a shiny hot metal teapot and mugs with no handles, then a heaping bowl of crunchy noodles in a brown wood-paneled bowl, and twin bowls of duck sauce and hot mustard.</p>
        <p>But why this burst of nostalgia over a greasy serving dish of goopy vegetables? Why the regret over this dish, once the quintessential Chinese food in the city, and now slipping quietly from the consciousness of New Yorkers, just like some of the most treasured memories of childhood.</p>
        <p>Forget Joe DiMaggio. Where have you gone, chicken chow mein? What became of the days when La Choy made Chinese food swing American; when, once a week, Dad, a single parent, made us exotic dinners by mixing the chicken chow mein that came in one large can with the dry noodles that came in the other.</p>
        <p>Chow mein had a noirish feel: This steaming bowl of old-style Cantonese fare evoked those exciting old films where streetwise private eyes or slick criminals slipped out of a cold drizzle and into a mysterious velvet booth. After ordering rudely from an obsequious waiter, they would shovel down the food and plot how to hide a stiff or blow a safe.</p>
        <p>''Nothing like a stiff for making me crave Chinese food,'' says one homicide detective to his partner (Robert Duvall) in ''True Confessions,'' right after inspecting a woman who had been cut in two, in the movie about detectives in 1940's Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>See, those were the days before Chinese food caught an attitude. Before Hunan and Sichuan took over in the late 70's, Chinese food didn't mean sesame chicken and Buddha's delight, but chop suey, egg foo yung, moo goo gai pan and chow mein.</p>
        <p>''At one time, that's what Chinese food was,'' said Ken Hom, author of the cookbook ''Easy Family Recipes From a Chinese-American Childhood'' (Alfred A. Knopf, 1997). ''But people's tastes have moved on.''</p>
        <p>Where, I wondered, are the restaurants that play the role of preservationist to this endangered dish? My memories set me on an obsessive quest, from the trendiest regions of the East Side to basement dives down dark winding Chinatown streets, to try to find the perfect bowl of chow mein. In the search I may have set a world gluttony record. (Has anyone ever eaten four full  meals of chow mein in less than 24 hours?)</p>
        <p>I had some leads. I knew the meal was a noodle dish (the name means fried noodles) and may have originated in Canton. There it was served topped with cabbage, celery, onions, mushrooms or bean sprout shoots in a thin clear sauce. But to appeal to American tastes, chow mein evolved, in its most extreme form, into a meat dish with a heavy gravy over crunchy, deep-fried egg noodles.</p>
        <p>Chinese-Americans and chow mein aficionados still prefer the original pan-fried noodles, but the Americanized version became standard fare in the 50's and 60's. How many bottles of Blue Nun or Mateus rose were opened for a bowl of chow mein in suburban households?</p>
        <p>''It was convenient and was like eating a bit of exotica without having to leave home,'' Mr. Hom said.</p>
        <p>In New York, many Chinese immigrants found they could open restaurants with limited culinary expertise, Mr. Hom said.</p>
        <p>''Even if they didn't know how to cook, they could put something together,'' he said. ''Since they knew Americans like crunchy and fried things, they said, 'Hey, it's a good way to sell this stuff.' ''</p>
        <p>I started with the phone. A few calls uptown and downtown presented nothing but dead ends. ''It's old fashioned,'' Alice Chen said. ''We don't even have it on the menu.'' Ms. Chen, manager of China Fun at Second Avenue and 65th Street, said chow mein was made only on occasion.</p>
        <p>''Nobody requests it, so what are we gonna to do?'' she said. ''It's only good if you are sick or for the old people who are used to it.''</p>
        <p>But the words of Eileen Leong, who has managed Canton restaurant at 45 Division Street in Chinatown for 40 years, were encouraging. ''Some people still ask for it,'' Ms. Leong said. ''They remember having it as a kid and they order it, but, at the new places, the chefs don't know how to really cook it.'' She does serve it, she said.</p>
        <p>So, armed with a Zagat's guide and a pack of Lucky Strikes (O.K., so I'm corny), I set out on foot. At first there was nothing but glittering purple chain restaurants offering cold noodles and sauteed string beans, but no chow mein. I was beginning to feel like Rip Van Winkle. Where were the neon  ''Chow Mein'' signs that once seemed to hang in every Chinese restaurant window? Gone, it seemed, from the urban landscape.</p>
        <p>Then, at Second Avenue and 12th Street, two stories above a dingy joint called Jade Mountain, the magical words appeared like a beacon, a neon sign whose dull red glow seemed to give an eerie mist to the air. I entered. Jackpot. Called by some of its customers ''the last Chinese food restaurant in New York,'' Jade Mountain has nine different chow mein entries on its menu.</p>
        <p>But this was no noir scene. Punkers and Gen-X'ers as well as old Chinese and Jewish couples sat in drab booths devouring fat egg rolls and egg foo yung all served in shiny metal dishes. The menu even boasted selections from Column A and Column B. This was too good to be true.</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of old customers used to the old Cantonese style,'' said the owner, Reggie Chan. ''They grew up with it. Now they bring their grandchildren in, and they're growing up with it.''</p>
        <p>Jade Mountain opened in 1931. Here, as in Chinatown, chow mein is served two basic ways. Cantonese style means a thin stew of vegetables served on a large expanse of yellow pan-fried noodles. ''This is the way the Chinese eat it,'' Mr. Chan said.</p>
        <p>For the other way, he then pointed to a mushy goop of shredded chicken and celery with a thick, clear gravy. Underneath are once-hard noodles getting soggier by the second. ''This is American chow mein.''</p>
        <p>At the cash register, Man Bun Ho, a 34-year-old computer consultant, held a takeout order of Cantonese chow mein.</p>
        <p>''I've been getting this here since I was a kid,'' Mr. Ho said. ''They make it better here than in Chinatown.''</p>
        <p>Veronica Pimpalone, 23, a teacher's assistant from the Lower East Side, had just  polished off a plate of chow mein and bowls of won-ton soup. Ms. Pimpalone was virtually weaned on Jade Mountain's chicken chow mein ''My parents came here on their first date,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But my journey had not ended. The more questions I asked, the more I realized that authenticity is an issue in the tiny chow mein community. And I learned that the real deal may lie farther downtown.</p>
        <p>At the Big Wong restaurant at 67 Mott Street, Karen Chan, the manager, said the chow mein there is ''as authentic as you can  get.'' She serves a Cantonese-style chow mein, without meat, in a thin sauce. She sniffed at the dish served uptown.</p>
        <p>''Unless you come down to Chinatown, you're not going to get the real chow mein,'' she declared. ''When an American comes in and asks for chow mein, I warn them, 'It's not the kind you get uptown.' ''</p>
        <p>As I walked farther, my fantasy of fedoras and tan overcoats tracking chow mein through Chinatown's drizzly, treacherous streets deflated quickly when pricked by  urban realities like a waiter's dreaded words ''We don't accept Mastercard.''</p>
        <p>I refused to relent.</p>
        <p>Down a stairway on Mott Street, the scene in Hop Kee was more like it. Waiters sat at a rear table stuffing small fish into their mouths with chopsticks. A cook leaned  against the kitchen wall, smoking a cigarette. At a table cluttered with silvery serving dishes, large men in suits in loosened ties and rolled-up shirtsleeves shoveled down forkfuls of food while talking nonstop.</p>
        <p>Several knowledgeable sources had said  Hop Kee had some of the best chow mein in Chinatown. But its manager, Peter Lee, said it just isn't a big seller. ''We just have it on the menu for old times' sake,'' Mr. Lee said. Since the early 80's, he said, demand has declined to about one order a day. ''Usually to senior citizens,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The waiter plunked down a plate and utensils and then a huge dish of chicken chow mein with such disregard I assumed  he'd return to serve it properly after unloading the other dishes balanced on his arms. (He didn't.) The Cantonese dish was almost identical to Jade Mountain's, but the American selection at Hop Kee had dry shredded chicken atop a soupy stew, and the hard egg noodles, down in the cone of the tray, were hopelessly soggy.</p>
        <p>Time to head back uptown. Things were different at Bruce Ho's Four Seas at 116 East 57th Street. In this plush dining room, the chow mein, arrived in style in a shiny platformed metal dish. A conscientious waiter spooned dry noodles and rice (say when) onto the plate, and deftly used two spoons in one hand to pile the stew atop.</p>
        <p>Bruce Ho's clients are mostly old-time New Yorkers, like Steve Godsick, 65, who handles public relations for the New York City Police Foundation. He was once a regular at Ruby Foo's, one of several Chinese restaurants that thrived on bustling West 52d Street after World War II.</p>
        <p>''This is what I grew up on,'' said Mr. Godsick over a plate of chicken chow mein.</p>
        <p>''It used to be, every place you went was Cantonese, and the only thing they had was chow mein, won-ton and egg drop soup, egg foo yung, hot and sour sauce, dumplings, lobster Cantonese, shrimp in lobster sauce. Now you got these places, wok one, wok two, wok three. It's too spicy. I don't like it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ho said: ''Not too many places serve it anymore. The younger waiters don't even know what it is.''</p>
        <p>What, I wondered, caused chow mein's decline and fall?</p>
        <p>''People grew up,'' said Henry Nuesch, manager of Shun Lee at 43 West 65th Street. ''It's an evolution thing. People grew out of it. The people who still order it are old Jewish people from Long Island who had it when they were kids. They cover the whole thing with duck sauce and soy sauce and think it's Chinese food. It's got nothing to do with China, but hey, you're in a Chinese restaurant, and that's good enough.''</p>
        <p>I considered these thoughts as I stopped at a midtown pay phone, Zagat's in hand. I still wasn't satisfied. Frustrated and out of quarters, I spied a flapping white canvas sign down a side street bearing the red stenciled words ''Chinese Food.'' Though this inauspicious storefront at 11 East 31st Street was not on my dwindling list of suspects, I was drawn to it.</p>
        <p>My search was over. I had stumbled upon a revelation: the chow mein dish, at Kin Yip Express Chinese, a succulent seafood and vegetable stew over a thin bed of fried angel hair noodles. Standing proudly on the tables are containers of Kikkoman Soy Sauce, squeeze bottles of hot mustard and duck sauce and a greasy teapot with worn teacups.</p>
        <p>Not only did it taste superb, but I had also stumbled upon a genuine scene, a mecca for chow mein addicts. Since a radio review praised its chicken chow mein six years ago, customers have been pouring in.</p>
        <p>Chow mein is alive and well at Kin Yip.</p>
        <p>''We sell four big pots of it every lunch hour,'' said its owner, Chris Fong. ''They're looking for good chicken chow mein that you can't really find in the city.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fong has a B.A. in biology but would  rather ladle out bowls of memories in this narrow room with top-40 music, fluorescent lights, bare walls and simple tables. ''Everyone who eats it says it reminds them of their parents at home. It brings out good feelings and warm memories.''</p>
        <p>It works for me.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
