<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Milestone in Inquiry, Rove, and the G.O.P., Breathe a Bit Easier</title>
    <meta content="29rove" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/29/politics/29rove.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1713251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE LEAK INQUIRY: THE PRESIDENT'S ADVISER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Republican Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rove, Karl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Libby, I Lewis</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Fitzgerald, Patrick J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D71E3FF93AA15753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Milestone in Inquiry, Rove, and the G.O.P., Breathe a Bit Easier</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Milestone in Inquiry, Rove, and the G.O.P., Breathe a Bit Easier</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE E. KORNBLUT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of uncertainty and four grand jury appearances, Karl Rove escaped the worst possible outcome on Friday, and a collective sigh of relief swept the Bush administration and the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove remained under a legal cloud: not indicted, but still at the center of the unfinished business in the C.I.A. leak case. He was absent from public view for most of the day, and conspicuously avoided giving any appearance that he had begun to celebrate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After months of uncertainty, Karl Rove escaped the worst possible outcome on Friday, and a collective sigh of relief swept the Bush administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After months of uncertainty and four grand jury appearances, Karl Rove escaped the worst possible outcome on Friday, and a collective sigh of relief swept the Bush administration and the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove remained under a legal cloud: not indicted, but still at the center of the unfinished business in the C.I.A. leak case. He was absent from public view for most of the day, and conspicuously avoided giving any appearance that he had begun to celebrate.</p>
        <p>But several friends and colleagues said he had resumed his role as the ubiquitous adviser who has guided George W. Bush's political career since before Mr. Bush's days as Texas governor. Even as the administration somberly accepted the resignation of I. Lewis Libby Jr., Vice President Dick Cheney's chief of staff, a pall that had fallen over Mr. Rove's section of the West Wing seemed to lift. And Mr. Rove, who just two weeks earlier had seemed in grave danger of being charged with a crime, took comfort in having survived this important point in the case.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing has been no fun, and debilitating, but not indicted is not indicted,'' said Ed Rogers, a Republican consultant and lobbyist. ''It's binary: being indicted is real bad, and not being indicted is real good.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear why the special counsel in the case, Patrick J. Fitzgerald, who was investigating Mr. Rove's statements up until the final hours of the grand jury's term, ultimately decided not to seek an indictment of him, at least for now. If he had evidence against Mr. Rove, he did not present it in the indictment of Mr. Libby or in his news conference at the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove, a cheerful, sharp-witted operative fond of sparring with reporters off the record, was drawn into the case because of conversations he had had with two reporters about the wife of former Ambassador Joseph C. Wilson IV, who had attacked the administration's account of intelligence to justify war in Iraq.</p>
        <p>On July 9, 2003, Mr. Rove confirmed to the columnist Robert D. Novak that he had heard that Mr. Wilson's wife, Valerie, was a C.I.A. officer; Mr. Novak revealed her identity in his column several days later. Referring to an ''Official A,'' whom people briefed on the case have identified as Mr. Rove, the indictment recounted those events, as well as a conversation that Official A had with Mr. Libby about the subject. Mr. Rove also tipped off Matthew Cooper of Time magazine to Ms. Wilson's identity in a phone conversation on July 11, two days after he spoke to Mr. Novak.</p>
        <p>The circumstances surrounding those conversations have fueled outrage from Mr. Rove's political adversaries, who have long viewed him as a take-no-prisoners renegade who will stop at nothing to ruin his critics. Mr. Wilson has called Mr. Rove's actions an ''outrageous abuse of power'' that was ''certainly worthy of frog-marching out of the White House.''</p>
        <p>That did not come to pass on Friday. A Republican official who had heard from Mr. Rove's friends said he seemed ''relieved'' though chastened by the five counts brought against Mr. Libby. The official said Mr. Rove and White House colleagues did not want to make any statements that would provoke Mr. Fitzgerald.</p>
        <p>''He's been his usual self here at the White House, the kind of Karl we've always seen busy at work, generally upbeat and positive,'' said a senior administration official, speaking on condition of anonymity because staff members had been prohibited from talking about the case.</p>
        <p>Mark McKinnon, an adviser close to the administration, said, ''I think Karl is right back in the middle of the picture, and will be for the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>Before dawn on Friday, the lights were on at the Rove household in upper Northwest Washington, where three Secret Service agents stood watch out front. But Mr. Rove did not leave the house until after 7:30, much later than usual. He gave a chipper response to reporters at the edge of his yard who shouted questions about how he felt.</p>
        <p>''A very good mood today,'' he said. ''I'm going to have a very good day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove appeared in similarly high spirits the night before, dropping by a party of tribute for a former congressman and interior secretary, Manuel Lujan Jr., at the law firm of Jones Day. He betrayed no anxiety as he made remarks and posed for photographs with other guests, even though nearly everyone in the room was aware of the deadline of Friday, when the grand jury's term was due to expire. During the half-hour Mr. Rove spent at the party, he seemed ''very relaxed,'' said Representative Steve Pearce, Republican of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Rove had reportedly been distracted by the investigation, several of his colleagues said Friday that in fact he had been engaged in his work all along. They denied that the case had caused any preoccupation contributing to the two central political disasters of recent weeks: the federal response to Hurricane Katrina and the crash-and-burn of Harriet E. Miers's nomination to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Still, they acknowledged that if Mr. Rove's legal troubles were indeed starting to fade, his prospects for helping the administration regain its footing were greater.</p>
        <p>''Now we start digging out,'' a Republican close to the White House said.</p>
        <p>Now, agreed Mr. Rogers, the Republican consultant, ''he can get back to work.''</p>
        <p>THE LEAK INQUIRY: THE PRESIDENT'S ADVISER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
