<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="790520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DE123AF937A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WESTCHESTER GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FUN AT THE JAYS'</p>
        <p>Friends of the 64-acre John Jay Homestead in Katonah are holding their third yearly Old-Fashioned Country Fair today from 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. with dozens of attractions for children and adults.</p>
        <p>The $10-a-car admission will be used to support the historic site's educational programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FUN AT THE JAYS'</p>
        <p>Friends of the 64-acre John Jay Homestead in Katonah are holding their third yearly Old-Fashioned Country Fair today from 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. with dozens of attractions for children and adults.</p>
        <p>The $10-a-car admission will be used to support the historic site's educational programs.</p>
        <p>Of special interest to animal lovers is a 4-month-old, 40-pound Siberian tiger cub -- one of several nonpettable animals to be admired. Its handler, Andrew Simmons, will also bring along an 8-month-old bear cub, an alligator snapping turtle, a python, a European eagle owl and a peregrine falcon.</p>
        <p>While children will have to observe the creatures from a distance, they will be able to pet the goats, sheep, geese and a donkey in the homestead's farm-animal compound.</p>
        <p>There will be pony rides, rides on wagons drawn by Belgian draft horses, three-legged races, egg tosses, demonstrations by artisans, an antique car and tractor display, storytelling, numerous games, music by the New York Blue Grass Authority, lots of food and many door prizes rounding out the agenda.</p>
        <p>In addition, anyone with a home-baked apple pie may submit it for judging. The winner will get a free dinner for two at the Monkey Bar in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The Homestead is on Route 22. For more information call 232-5651. ARMONK ART OUTDOORS</p>
        <p>Nearly 170 artists representing 17 states from coast to coast will take part in the 34th Annual Armonk Outdoor Art Show on Saturday and Sunday from 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. It will be held at the American Legion Field behind the North Castle town offices on Bedford Road. Admission will be free, but a donation will be appreciated to support projects at the North Castle Library.</p>
        <p>It was the Friends of the library that started the show years ago, bringing it to a stage where it is now rated among the top 200 exhibitions of its kind in the country by the professional artists publication Sunshine Artist Magazine.</p>
        <p>Judged in six categories, the entrants are well known in their fields of oil, watercolor and acrylic painting, sculpture, mixed media, graphics, and handcrafts. Prices range from $35 to $9,000, and six works -- one in each category -- will be distributed as prizes in a raffle for visitors.</p>
        <p>Among the artists represented are Michael Patterson, Peter Bramhall, Laura Breitman, Albert Drogin, Guenther Riess, Sue Phalieros and Carol Turentine.</p>
        <p>For more information, call 666-7544. A SMITHY AT MUSCOOT</p>
        <p>William Fitzgerald is a seventh-generation blacksmith, the first of his family to be born here or anywhere outside of County Limerick in Ireland.</p>
        <p>He will lead four blacksmithing workshops at Muscoot Farm in Somers for anyone who wants to learn the craft.</p>
        <p>The first of the five-hour sessions will take place next Saturday from 9 A.M. to 2 P.M.; the others are scheduled on Oct. 7 and 28 and Nov. 4 during the same hours. Each session costs $65 and is limited to five students.</p>
        <p>"We have five forges, five anvils and five sets of tools for them to work with," Mr. Fitzgerald said. "And this is not a situation where people come and watch me demonstrate. They do all the work, I just guide them through it."</p>
        <p>In addition to running his own ironworks where he makes horseshoes, ornamental objects, gates, fireplace tools, and provides decorative items for churches and building contractors, he has held the classes at Muscoot for a dozen years.</p>
        <p>Many of his students come back for increasingly advanced instruction. The most popular items for first-time students are fireplace pokers and nails, but each student can make whatever he or she likes.</p>
        <p>"Making a nail is very difficult because it's so small," he said. "The iron heats up and cools down quickly, before you have a chance to draw the point or make the head." Fires are stoked with soft coal and the forges are hand cranked the old-fashioned way.</p>
        <p>Hard-soled shoes, not sneakers, are to be worn, with jeans, sweatshirts or other sturdy clothing. Leather aprons are provided for protection.</p>
        <p>To register or obtain more information, call 232-7118. BIG POWER BREAKFAST</p>
        <p>The first suburban breakfast to be held by the 240,000-member National Association for Female Executives will have as its theme "The Big News in 'Big' Business -- Thinking Small."</p>
        <p>It is scheduled on Tuesday from 8 to 10 A.M. at the Nestle Building, 100 Manhattanville Road in Purchase, and registration is $30.</p>
        <p>Planned in conjunction with the Entrepreneurial Center of Purchase, the event will be attended by members of the two organizations and the public from Fairfield, Rockland and Bergen Counties as well as Westchester.</p>
        <p>Marge Lovero, president of the Entrepreneurial Center, will moderate a panel discussion by Maurice Cox, vice president of Pepsico in Somers; Dee DelBello, publisher of Westfair Communications and the wife of Alfred DelBello, a former Westchester County Executive, and Joanne Reilly, senior vice president of National Westminster Bank.</p>
        <p>Billed as a "not for women only" event, the program is aimed at executives and owners of small businesses, focusing on the demand by big businesses for outside entrepreneurial ideas and services.</p>
        <p>Call (212) 477- 2200, extension 334, to register or obtain more information. BUSINESS AND ASIA</p>
        <p>Sharon Russell FitzSimmons, international finance and treasury executive for Philip Morris International, will be the speaker at the Westchester County Association lunch on Wednesday at the Rye Town Hilton in Rye Brook.</p>
        <p>Her topic will be "Is the Time Right for You to Be Doing Business in Southeast Asia?"</p>
        <p>She will outline opportunities in the markets of Brunei, Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam, where a population of 425 million generates a gross domestic product worth $570 billion and the per capita income is $1,400 a year. As a result, those markets are beginning to compete strenuously with the developed economies of Japan, Taiwan, South Korea and Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>Ms. FitzSimmons is a graduate of the Harvard Business School who spent four years in management positions at Philip Morris's Australian operations before becoming involved in the company's Asian expansion.</p>
        <p>A reception will begin at 11:30 A.M., followed by the lunch and presentation at 12:15. Reservations at $50 may be made by calling 948-6444. ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
