<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="10QNA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/10/travel/10QNA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1300245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Proust, Marcel (1871-1922)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freireich, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Normandy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia/Bali</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Pittsburgh</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Chartres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pittsburgh (Pennsylvania)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Normandy (France)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Chartres</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Trouville</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Singapore</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Bali</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Secaucus (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Asia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Chinatown</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Grand Hotel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florent</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Changi Airport</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Spirit</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Raffles Hotel</org>
        <org class="online_producer">State Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, Joseph</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EFD6153FF933A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL FREIREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freireich, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel Q&amp;A on Proust sites in Paris area, eight-hour layover in Singapore and weather Web sites (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Proust's Footsteps</p>
        <p>Q. Can you give me the names of organizations that conduct guided tours of the places in and near Paris where Marcel Proust worked and spent his time? -- Terri F. Gould, Pittsburgh</p>
        <p>A. There's no regularly scheduled Proust tour, but you can do it yourself or get in touch with a guide. In Paris, Proust's former apartment is at 102 Boulevard Haussmann, now an office in a bank called the SNVB. From 2 to 4 p.m. on Thursday, a guide is available to describe Proust's life while he resided there. Admission is free. Information: (33-1) 44.90.40.00.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Proust's Footsteps</p>
        <p>Q. Can you give me the names of organizations that conduct guided tours of the places in and near Paris where Marcel Proust worked and spent his time? -- Terri F. Gould, Pittsburgh</p>
        <p>A. There's no regularly scheduled Proust tour, but you can do it yourself or get in touch with a guide. In Paris, Proust's former apartment is at 102 Boulevard Haussmann, now an office in a bank called the SNVB. From 2 to 4 p.m. on Thursday, a guide is available to describe Proust's life while he resided there. Admission is free. Information: (33-1) 44.90.40.00.</p>
        <p>On view at the Musée Carnavalet, 23, rue Sévigné, (33-1) 44.59.58.58, is Proust's bedroom, reassembled with his original bed, desk and a painting of his father. Admission: $4, at 7.5 francs to the dollar. Open 10 a.m. to 5:40 p.m.; closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Before leaving Paris, you'll want to stop at Proust's grave at the Père Lachaise cemetery, 15, rue du Repos; (33-1) 55.25.82.10.</p>
        <p>Then you'll need to rent a car for a two-day trip to Normandy. The first stop would be 16 miles southeast of Chartres in Illiers Combray, called Combray in Proust's novels. It's the site of the Musée Tante Léonie, mentioned in ''Remembrance of Things Past,'' and the Musée Marcel Proust, both at 6, rue du Docteur Proust, (33-2) 37.24.30.97; closed Monday.</p>
        <p>A two-hour drive from Illiers will take you to Cabourg (Balbek in ''Remembrance of Things Past''), where you stay at the four-star Grand Hotel on the Promenade Marcel Proust and request Proust's own bedroom, at $187 a night. Madeleines are served at breakfast, naturally. The bedroom has been decorated exactly as Proust described it, with heavy red and mauve curtains and a big brass bed. The view of the sea is spectacular. Telephone (33-2) 31.91.01.79, fax (33-2) 31.24.03.20.</p>
        <p>A nice drive along the coast east from Cabourg will take you to Houlgate and Trouville, where Proust often went in the summer.</p>
        <p>If you prefer the help of a guide or local tourist office, it's best to plan several weeks in advance. In Paris, Catherine Leblanc at the Association des Conferienciers Officiels can set up a tour in English, for about $107. Telephone: (33-1) 43.36.05.56; e-mail catherine.leblanc1@libertysurf.fr.</p>
        <p>A tour to Illiers Combray can be arranged at the Office du Tourisme de Chartres, 10, rue du Docteur Maunoury, B.P. 67, 28 002 Chartres; e-mail cdt28@wanadoo.fr. The cost is $266 for four people, including an English-speaking guide for the day, round-trip taxi from the Chartres train station, and lunch at Le Florent, 13, place du Marché; (33-2) 37.24.10.43, fax (33-2) 37.24.11.78.</p>
        <p>In Cabourg, you can contact the Cercle Littéraire Marcel Proust, La Bergerie, 22 bis, boulevard des Belges; (33-2) 31.91.06.69, fax (33-2) 31.91.16.00.</p>
        <p>The Eure-et-Loir tourism department, (33-2) 37.84.01.00, can help with a Proust visit in the Loir Valley around Illiers Combray. For $84 a person, a package includes tickets for both Proust museums in Combray, a night and a dinner at the three-star Hostellerie du Bois Guibert in Bonneval (nine miles from Illiers) and a stroll along the River Loir.</p>
        <p>Layover in Singapore</p>
        <p>Q. I am returning from Bali with an eight-hour layover at Changi Airport in Singapore in October. What do you recommend to help pass the time? -- J. S. K., Secaucus, N.J.</p>
        <p>A. Passengers with a layover of at least five hours can take a two-hour tour from the airport without charge.</p>
        <p>Actually, there are two tours: the Spirit of New Asia and the Heartlands. And American citizens taking them do not need a visa, according to the Singapore Tourism Board.</p>
        <p>The New Asia excursion visits the city center, the Colonial district (site of Raffles Hotel), the old Parliament House, Merlion Park as well as two areas along the Singapore River with restaurants and bars -- Boat and Clarke Quays and the Asian Civilizations Museum. Included in the tour is a 20-minute ride in a small vessel known as a bumboat.</p>
        <p>The Heartlands Tour takes in such ethnic areas as Little India, including the Sri Veeramakalimman Temple; Chinatown; Geylang Serai, the Malay district; and Arab Street, the Muslim area. Also on the tour is the Changi Prison Chapel and Museum.  Information: (212) 302-4861 or www.newasia-singapore.com.</p>
        <p>The State Department (see www.state.gov) advises visitors to be aware of Singapore's strict penalties for such offenses as jaywalking, littering and spitting, as well as importing and selling chewing gum.</p>
        <p>Weather on the Web</p>
        <p>Q. For planning vacations, I would like to know a really cool Web site with the average monthly temperature and average precipitation in major cities around the world. -- Joseph Green, New York, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A. Accuracy should, of course, be a given. Beyond that, a good site will have a big database and yield information clearly and with a minimum number of clicks. Useful links are always a bonus.</p>
        <p>At weather.com, you will find historical data for 7,462 locations plus current conditions and 10-day forecasts for 77,000 locations worldwide. (Just enter a city and then click on Averages and Records.)</p>
        <p>In addition to mean temperatures, precipitation and maximum lows and highs by the month or day, you get times of sunrise and sunset. And for American cities, a record low and high temperature for each day and the year that record was achieved is given. You'll also find flight arrival times and flu and pollen reports on this site.</p>
        <p>Monthly data for 10,200 cities are provided at weatherbase.com. Though there are fewer places covered here than, say, at weather.com, there are more categories of data -- typically, a sampling showed, 10 to 18 categories, including the number of days below 32 degrees, average morning humidity and lowest and highest recorded temperature.</p>
        <p>You will find a warehouse of weather information, primarily about the United States, at www.ncdc.noaa.gov. A good way to start is to click on Most Popular Products.</p>
        <p>Among the choices are Comparative Climatic Data (for over 250 United States cities) and a 40-page document called Climates of the World (for about 800 stations worldwide). These two documents of wide interest are tough on the eyes; others are quite clear.</p>
        <p>Whatever site you choose in planning a vacation, remember the boilerplate so familiar to investors: Past performance is no guarantee of future results.</p>
        <p>PAUL FREIREICH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
