<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OPENING OF SCHOOL IN NEW YORK CITY DRAWS OPPOSITION</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASBESTOS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOARD OF EDUCATION (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CORTINES, RAMON C (CHANCELLOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asbestos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D6163DF93BA2575AC0A965958260" item-length="1614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OPENING OF SCHOOL IN NEW YORK CITY DRAWS OPPOSITION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the first day of school finally approaches in New York City after an 11-day delay caused by the asbestos crisis, school officials face pockets of revolt across the system from parents, teachers and local district officials who are threatening not to participate in the opening of the city's schools.</p>
        <p>Two local school boards have voted to close their schools on Monday in defiance of orders from the Board of Education and the new Schools Chancellor, Ramon C. Cortines. Another, on Staten Island, grudgingly agreed yesterday to open its schools after Mr. Cortines offered his help in getting results of asbestos tests in their schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the first day of school finally approaches in New York City after an 11-day delay caused by the asbestos crisis, school officials face pockets of revolt across the system from parents, teachers and local district officials who are threatening not to participate in the opening of the city's schools.</p>
        <p>Two local school boards have voted to close their schools on Monday in defiance of orders from the Board of Education and the new Schools Chancellor, Ramon C. Cortines. Another, on Staten Island, grudgingly agreed yesterday to open its schools after Mr. Cortines offered his help in getting results of asbestos tests in their schools.</p>
        <p>At one school in the Bronx, teachers have vowed to show up but not to teach because of the conditions there. And across the city, scores of parents have vowed to keep their children at home. 'Grass-Roots Explosion'</p>
        <p>"I think it's a spontaneous, grass-roots explosion," said John C. Fager of the Parents Coalition for Education, an advocacy group. "It's not being ordered, manipulated or led. How widespread it's going to get I don't think anyone can predict until Monday."</p>
        <p>To reassure parents and help ease confusion, Mr. Cortines has promised to release status reports for each of the city's 1,069 schools and 97 other alternative programs by today, identifying which schools would have to be closed as well as announcing arrangements for double or shortened schedules at those that can open.</p>
        <p>His office released the status reports yesterday for the city's 175 high schools and specialized secondary programs, as well as classrooms for special education students. The reports showed that 129 high schools would open with normal schedules and 40 with altered schedules, including double sessions of students. Six other high schools were in jeopardy of not opening, though officials still could not be certain three days before school starts. Anger and Frustration</p>
        <p>Whatever the impact of the acts of defiance -- some individual acts, others more organized -- they clearly reflect the depth of the anger and frustration toward the school system as it lurches toward what promises to be the most chaotic first day of school ever.</p>
        <p>And they could present political and financial problems for the Board of Education and Mr. Cortines, who since taking over this week has shifted the priority of the asbestos crisis from declaring all schools free of hazards to getting school started in those classrooms that are safe.</p>
        <p>A prolonged absence by large numbers of schoolchildren would mean that the system could lose millions of dollars in state aid, which is based on average attendance. And any rebellions by teachers or administrators could also add to the confusion of what Mr. Cortines and others have acknowledged will be a chaotic start.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cortines took a conciliatory approach toward the two defiant school boards, in District 30 in Queens and District 12 in the Bronx, offering legions of officials from his office to smooth the way for more asbestos test results and to help make other arrangements.</p>
        <p>But beyond repeating that schools would be safe and urging the cooperation of local boards, parents and teachers, Mr. Cortines appeared to have little defense for a sweeping parental revolt.</p>
        <p>"We're trying to make the best of a difficult situation," said Frank Sobrino, a spokesman for the Board of Education, acknowledging that school officials realize that at least some parents will not let their children start school as scheduled. "At any rate, we're optimistic that we can work to have as many schools open as smoothly as possible." Busing and Double Sessions</p>
        <p>The anger behind the defiance appeared to grow not only from the health hazards of asbestos contamination -- which city health officials say are not serious -- but also from the alternatives that are still being planned to find other places for thousands of students whose normal classrooms or schools will remain closed on Monday.</p>
        <p>In many cases, students face busing to other schools. In some, they will attend school in double or shortened sessions. In others, principals have told parents that as many as two or three classes will have to cram into one classroom.</p>
        <p>And many parents complained that the chaotic arrangements left little hope that the first days of school, or even weeks, would offer anything in the way of education.</p>
        <p>While many of the parents' complaints may be resolved as more schools are cleared for opening by Monday, negating the contingencies, the anger and frustration appeared to be deeply felt and lasting.</p>
        <p>Even as superintendents continued to make plans, scores of parents remained unsatisfied, distrustful of school officials' reassurances and determined not to let their children attend school at all until they are satisfied, according to parents, parents groups and school officials.</p>
        <p>"I wouldn't say there is an uprising of major proportions," said Lillian Lopez, a school board member in District 15 in Brooklyn with three children in the system. "But there is an element of that out there. There are a lot of angry parents who have had enough." 'We'll See'</p>
        <p>Even Ms. Lopez, as a board member, said she could not say for certain whether she would send her children to school on Monday. "Let me put it this way," she said. "I'm going to go with my kids on Monday and we'll see what I'm going to do after that."</p>
        <p>Ayo Harrington, the president of the United Parents Association, said her organization had received many calls from parents weighing the decision to keep their children out. The organization, one of the city's largest parent groups, has not recommended that parents boycott, but it has not urged them to go, either. Instead, she urged calm.</p>
        <p>"It feels like, sounds like, parents need to take a step back and make some calm decisions," she said.</p>
        <p>In District 24 in Queens, the volatile emotions became clear when a parents meeting at Intermediate School 93 in Ridgewood on Thursday night to discuss the double session being planned at the school became so heated that police officers had to restore order. No arrests were made.</p>
        <p>"Emotions ran very, very high," said Kathy Masi, who attended as the president of the Presidents Council, which represents parent leaders at each of the district's schools.</p>
        <p>Echoing many other parents, Mrs. Masi said yesterday that the biggest problem has been a lack of information about the alternatives being arranged and a deep mistrust of the crash inspection of the city's schools, which began after investigators reported last month that the board's asbestos inspections in the late 1980's were fundamentally flawed. 'The Worst Nightmare'</p>
        <p>"This is the worst nightmare becoming a reality, and feel it's entirely the Board of Education's fault," Mrs. Masi said. "We still don't have the answers to our questions. We still don't have the results from our schools. It's virtually impossible for any parent to feel reassured."</p>
        <p>In District 25 in Queens, the anger has turned into organized defiance. In a drizzle outside of Public School 154 in Flushing, two dozen parents gathered yesterday to object to a plan to bus their children from their school, which officials still have not decided can open, to Public School 29 in College Point, saying they would boycott if that is the case.</p>
        <p>"We don't want our children to leave this area," said Valerie Cohen, whose daughter is entering kindergarten and whose son is starting second grade.</p>
        <p>Parents at three other schools that closed in the district -- Public Schools 165, 200 and 201 -- have also loosely banded together to call for a boycott.</p>
        <p>One of them, Jill Gross, said she decided to keep her two children home on Monday and possibly longer because, with their schools closed, they would have to board buses to take them to two other schools miles from their home -- one in the morning, one in the afternoon.  'Children in Danger'</p>
        <p>The hazards in her children's schools were bad enough, she said, but the makeshift alternatives have simply become unacceptable.</p>
        <p>"We're afraid somebody will get hurt," said Mrs. Gross, whose daughter was to have started the third grade on Monday, her son the second. "We're not willing to put our children in danger for baby-sitting -- which is all this could be."</p>
        <p>At Public School 83 in the Bronx, the teachers have vowed not to teach on Monday morning unless they have been assured that it is safe. The school, which has been undergoing renovation, had 36 of its 42 rooms and two stairwells sealed by the visual inspections Mr. Cortines ordered this week.</p>
        <p>"We need a safe situation for ourselves and our children," said Philip Mailman, a fourth-grade teacher at the school, which is in Morris Park. "At the moment, there doesn't seem to be a safe situation."</p>
        <p>Mr. Cortines has sought to quell the rising anger by reaching out to parents, teachers and local districts. As Chancellor, he has the authority to overrule the defiant school boards and send in trustees to open the schools. So far, though, he has offered special assistance to those districts, trying mostly to speed the flow of test results, saying on Thursday that "this is not the time to use a sledgehammer to kill a fly."</p>
        <p>In District 30 in Queens, the board voted on Tuesday night to shut down until it had written assurances that its 25 schools were safe. Signs posted on several schools said, "Closed until further notice."</p>
        <p>Mr. Cortines's staff has arranged several meetings between the district superintendent, Angelo Gimondo, and officials heading the crash inspection. And the district now has results on 23 of its 25 schools, showing only one, Public School 85, entirely closed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
