<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ensemble Opens School's Baroque Festival</title>
    <meta content="24MUSI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020303T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1370332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hoff-Barthelson Music School (Scarsdale, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherman, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DC123EF937A15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ensemble Opens School's Baroque Festival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sherman, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on upcoming concerts in Westchester County, NY, including Hoff-Barthelson Music School's 37th annual Baroque and Beyond Festival featuring Hoff-Barthelson Orchestra; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Hoff-Barthelson Orchestra opens the school's 37th annual Baroque and Beyond Festival next month, it will arrive with high praise -- not to mention a $7,000 grant -- from the New York State Council on the Arts. The council's director, James Jordan, called its programs ''outstanding,'' noting that the judging panel found the ensemble ''ranked among the top community school orchestras in the country.''</p>
        <p>The orchestra includes about 60 advanced students, ages 13 to 18, and the results of their weekly rehearsals, under music director, Jun Nakabayashi, will be on display three times during the festival. The opening night concert, on March 9 at 8 p.m. in First Presbyterian Church of Mount Vernon, includes Haydn's ''Military'' Symphony No. 100 and, with the Festival Chorus, Bach's Cantata No. 140. The Cantata gets an encore the next evening at 7 in the Community Unitarian Church of White Plains, along with performances by smaller school ensembles. At the finale, on March 17 at 7 p.m. again in Community Unitarian, an encore of the Haydn prefaces a performance of Bach's B minor Suite, with the flutist Paula Robison as guest soloist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Hoff-Barthelson Orchestra opens the school's 37th annual Baroque and Beyond Festival next month, it will arrive with high praise -- not to mention a $7,000 grant -- from the New York State Council on the Arts. The council's director, James Jordan, called its programs ''outstanding,'' noting that the judging panel found the ensemble ''ranked among the top community school orchestras in the country.''</p>
        <p>The orchestra includes about 60 advanced students, ages 13 to 18, and the results of their weekly rehearsals, under music director, Jun Nakabayashi, will be on display three times during the festival. The opening night concert, on March 9 at 8 p.m. in First Presbyterian Church of Mount Vernon, includes Haydn's ''Military'' Symphony No. 100 and, with the Festival Chorus, Bach's Cantata No. 140. The Cantata gets an encore the next evening at 7 in the Community Unitarian Church of White Plains, along with performances by smaller school ensembles. At the finale, on March 17 at 7 p.m. again in Community Unitarian, an encore of the Haydn prefaces a performance of Bach's B minor Suite, with the flutist Paula Robison as guest soloist.</p>
        <p>In between those events come free recitals at the school by Hoff-Barthelson soloists and groups, March 14 and 15 at 8 p.m., and March 16 at 2, 4 and 8 p.m. The pianist Edward Aldwell gives a baroque recital and master class at 1 p.m. on March 17. Information: (914) 723-1169.</p>
        <p>Haydn's ''Military'' Symphony also opens Philharmonia Virtuosi's program at Purchase College next Sunday at 3 p.m., followed by the Stravinsky's ''Pulcinella'' Suite and the Schumann Cello Concerto, the latter featuring Carter Brey, moonlighting from his post as principal in the New York Philharmonic. Mr. Brey will also give the New York premiere of a ''Graciela y Buenos Aires,'' a concert tango by José Bragato, while the music director, Richard Kapp, will share podium duties with Paul Hostetter. Information: (914) 693-5595.</p>
        <p>Two other orchestral programs will feature outstanding pianists in blockbuster concertos when Albert Lotto plays Beethoven's ''Emperor'' with the Yonkers Philharmonic and when Jean-Yves Thibaudet is featured with the Westchester Philharmonic in the G major Concerto of his countryman, Maurice Ravel. The free Yonkers concert, March 10 at 3 p.m. in the Saunders High School Auditorium, has another soloist, the soprano Elena Malfitano, singing ''Voi che Sapete'' from Mozart's ''Marriage of Figaro.'' The program will also include the world premiere of ''A Requiem for Jerome Gino Sala,'' written by William Zinn, a longtime member of the Yonkers Philharmonic, in memory of the late music director, who ied last September. As the search continues for a successor, Alan Aurelia, artistic director of the Riverside Opera Company, leads orchestral favorites by Wagner, Schubert and Tchaikovsky. Information: (914) 476-3711.</p>
        <p>The Westchester Philharmonic has two performances at Purchase College, March 16 at 8 p.m and  March 17 at 3 p.m., plus an open rehearsal March 16 at 10 a.m. The prgram includes Bartok's Divertimento, the Ravel Concerto and Mozart's ''Prague'' Symphony, No. 38. Tickets: (914) 682-3707.</p>
        <p>Here's a how-de-do: a full production of ''The Mikado'' by the much-acclaimed New York Gilbert and Sullivan Players and a performance of Brahms' ''German Requiem'' by the much-admired New Choral Society are both set for next Saturday at 8 p.m. One possible solution is to join Nanki-Poo and friends on Saturday night at the Fox Lane School in Bedford, then hear the Brahms when it gets an encore next Sunday at 3 p.m. at Hitchcock Presbyterian Church in Scarsdale.</p>
        <p>For ''Mikado'' tickets, call the sponsoring Mount Kisco Concert Association at (914) 666-9181; to attend either of the Requiem performances, call (914) 725-1678.</p>
        <p>Bizet's ''Carmen'' is the next production of Taconic Opera, with two casts and no bull, since the time and place have been changed from 19th century Spain to modern-day New York. The company remains true to the original score, though, so the opera will be sung in French, with English supertitles. Carter Scott takes the title role March . 8 at 8 p.m., Kerry Grubel the next evening at 8, with Ms. Scott returning March. 10 at 2 p.m.. Drew Slatton and Tom Roche alternate as Don Jose (in this version, one of New York's finest) with Wes Garrison and Robert Stafford as Escamillo, Holly Boaz and Rebecca Todd Bixler as Micaela. All performances are at the Yorktown Stage in downtown Yorktown Heights. Reservations: (914) 739-2165.</p>
        <p>Jewish vocal music gets a double showcase in March. Next Sunday at 3 p.m. in the Bendheim Arts Center, Harold Rosenbaum conducts the Canticum Novum Singers, with Cantor Gerald Cohen. The program includes cantorial and other liturgical settings, Yiddish folk songs and several selections from Mendelssohn's oratorio ''Elijah.''</p>
        <p>The following weekend, on March 9 at 8 p.m., a gala is planned to mark the 10th anniversary of the Legacy Series of concerts at Temple Israel Center in White Plains. The event honors Linda Hall Gerson, an assistant conductor and coach at the Metropolitan Opera (and a Westchester resident) who has organized the events through the years.</p>
        <p>The artists on the program include the tenor Neil Shicoff, himself the son of a cantor, who will be taking the role of Eléazar in the Met's first new production of Halévy's ''La Juive'' since Caruso sang it there in 1920; he has promised to perform that opera's most famous aria, ''Rachel, Quand du Seigneur'' at the gala. Other participants include Mr. Shicoff's younger colleague at the Met, Alexandra Deshorties; Jodie Langel, a Broadway musical performer, and Cantor Fredda Rakusin Mendelson, with Martin Bookspan the master of ceremonies. Information: (914) 948-2800.</p>
        <p>The America-Israel Cultural Foundation is presenting the Jerusalem Trio next Saturday at 8 p.m. in the Emelin Theater. This ensemble -- the violinist Roy Shiloah, the cellist Ariel Tushinsky and the pianist Yaron Rosenthal -- is offering works of Mendelssohn, and Shostakovich, plus ''Variations on a Hebrew Melody'' by the Israeli composer Paul Ben-Haim. Box office: (914) 698-0098.</p>
        <p>The Salon Chamber Soloists -- otherwise known as the violinist Eriko Sato, her pianist-husband David Oei, and the cellist Maria Kitsopoulos -- give a free recital for the Pleasantville Chamber Music Society, playing Beethoven, Schumann and Ravel  on March 10 at 3 p.m. in the Presbyterian Church. (914) 769-1827. Schumann and Ravel will be featured when the Apollo Trio (of Curtis Macomber, Michael Kannen and Maria Stroke) performs for the Hudson Valley Music Club, March 25 at 1 p.m. in the Club's 54 Clinton Avenue hall in Dobbs Ferry. (914 591-8270).</p>
        <p>The Talich String Quartet from the Czech Republic has chosen an all-Beethoven program for its Purchase College visit next Sunday at 3 p.m. (914) 251-6200. The St. Petersburg String Quartet will perform, in a program presented by the Westchester Chamber Music Society, on March 16 at 8 p.m. in Congregation Emanu-El of Rye. (914-948-6333).</p>
        <p>MUSIC  Correction:  March 3, 2002, Sunday  An article about March music events last Sunday misstated the date of a performance  by the St. Petersburg String Quartet, sponsored by the Westchester Chamber Music Society. The concert will be March 17, not March 16, at 8 p.m. at Congregation Emanu-El of Rye. Information: (914) 723-0222.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 3, 2002, Sunday  An article about March music events last Sunday misstated the date of a performance  by the St. Petersburg String Quartet, sponsored by the Westchester Chamber Music Society. The concert will be March 17, not March 16, at 8 p.m. at Congregation Emanu-El of Rye. Information: (914) 723-0222.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 3, 2002, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article about March music events last Sunday misstated the date of a performance  by the St. Petersburg String Quartet, sponsored by the Westchester Chamber Music Society. The concert will be March 17, not March 16, at 8 p.m. at Congregation Emanu-El of Rye. Information: (914) 723-0222.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: March 3, 2002, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article about March music events last Sunday misstated the date of a performance  by the St. Petersburg String Quartet, sponsored by the Westchester Chamber Music Society. The concert will be March 17, not March 16, at 8 p.m. at Congregation Emanu-El of Rye. Information: (914) 723-0222.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
