<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Economists Share a Prize for Insights Into How Rivalries Function; Reinhard Selten</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="717579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SELTEN, REINHARD (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DB163CF931A25753C1A962958260" item-length="349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Economists Share a Prize for Insights Into How Rivalries Function; Reinhard Selten</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reinhard Selten says that he plays no sports, except perhaps hiking, "if one can say that is a sport."</p>
        <p>He lives outside Bonn and says he hikes deep into the hills for three to five hours each Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reinhard Selten says that he plays no sports, except perhaps hiking, "if one can say that is a sport."</p>
        <p>He lives outside Bonn and says he hikes deep into the hills for three to five hours each Saturday.</p>
        <p>"It's very productive scientifically; I often get some very good ideas for my research while hiking," said the 64-year-old professor of economics at the University of Bonn.</p>
        <p>Though Professor Selten is not widely known in Germany outside of academia, he became a national hero today, because he is the first German to win the Nobel economics prize since the award was first presented in 1969.</p>
        <p>"But while I may be well known today -- next week, they probably won't remember my name," he said in a telephone interview today.</p>
        <p>The son of a bookseller, he was born in Breslau in 1930 and has been a professor at the Free University of Berlin, the University of Bielefeld and since 1984 at the University of Bonn. He spent two years as a visiting professor at the business school of the University of California at Berkeley in the late 1960's. He is also a mathematician by training.</p>
        <p>In addition to speaking German, French and English, he says he also speaks Esperanto, an artificial language invented in the 19th century and intended to be a universal language. He describes himself as an idealist and a member of the Esperanto movement.</p>
        <p>Professor Selten said he became interested in game theory in the late 1940's, when he read an article about it in Fortune magazine. "I was always interested in politics and psychology, learning beyond just the natural sciences, and this enabled me to expand economic thinking to include these areas," he said.</p>
        <p>Critical to game theory is contemplating what an opponent -- be it a chess or poker player or a competing business executive -- might be planning.</p>
        <p>"It's like playing chess," he said. "You have to think hard about what you think your opponent will do, and then you plan your own strategy based on that. You may not always be right, but such thinking probably makes you play better and keeps you from making as many dumb moves."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
