<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; He Reshaped The Places We Live</title>
    <meta content="24MATT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Logue, Edward J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DF1530F937A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; He Reshaped The Places We Live</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column discusses career of urban planner Edward Logue following his death on January 27 at age 78; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a significant figure dies, somebody somewhere will inevitably invoke that hackneyed phrase, ''the end of an era,'' and while most of us won't know exactly what ended, we will be dutifully impressed.</p>
        <p>Edward Logue, the bold master planner who died Jan. 27 in his home on Martha's Vineyard at the age of 78, would probably have scoffed at cosmic language about his role in life. But in fact he did represent a way of doing things that is long gone, as is the generous era that allowed him to realize his big visions and do what he did best: rebuild cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a significant figure dies, somebody somewhere will inevitably invoke that hackneyed phrase, ''the end of an era,'' and while most of us won't know exactly what ended, we will be dutifully impressed.</p>
        <p>Edward Logue, the bold master planner who died Jan. 27 in his home on Martha's Vineyard at the age of 78, would probably have scoffed at cosmic language about his role in life. But in fact he did represent a way of doing things that is long gone, as is the generous era that allowed him to realize his big visions and do what he did best: rebuild cities.</p>
        <p>As Saturday's memorial service for him in Boston reminded us, there really could not be an Ed Logue today. He was a powerful, headstrong urban planner in the 1950's and 60's who, figuring out how to grab every available penny of urban renewal money -- remember urban renewal? -- reshaped New Haven and Boston, then put his talents to work in New York in the late 70's and 80's.</p>
        <p>As head of the state's Urban Development Corporation from 1968 to 1975, he built housing, stadiums and more housing from Buffalo to Roosevelt Island, working free of local zoning and building rules thanks to his powerful mentor, Nelson A. Rockefeller, and using federal and state largess as his checkbook.</p>
        <p>Today, urban renewal means Donald Trump building towers of affluence on the Hudson and East Rivers. Federal dollars that built thousands of apartments for the poor and middle class have all but dried up.</p>
        <p>''We have no national housing policy that's worth a damn, in my view,'' Mr. Logue said three years ago, when the country was already scornful of big government -- the munificence of the New Deal and Great Society.</p>
        <p>''Ed played those federal housing grant programs like a zither,'' recalled Stephen Lefkowitz, a lawyer who worked for the state. ''He did what he wanted to do and trusted that the Lord would make it work.'' The Lord and some optimistic accounting.</p>
        <p>Instead of financing each project individually, securing the money before beginning construction, Mr. Logue would get financing for one project and start three. There was always more money on the way. And then in 1975 the government put a freeze on federal housing subsidies, the banks called in outstanding loans and the Urban Development Corporation went bankrupt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Logue was fired and didn't make his New York comeback until 1978, when Mayor Edward I. Koch brought him back to rebuild the South Bronx, a national symbol of urban decline.</p>
        <p>He went way over budget as he turned the South Bronx's infamous Charlotte Street into Charlotte Gardens, a new community of private homes. The original idea was to build a large apartment building, but Mr. Logue thought home ownership was a better idea, and, while negotiating the political shoals of the Bronx, he built 90 subsidized homes. ''As we were getting dragged in, I was saying to myself, 'What am I getting into?' '' Mr. Koch recalled. ''But it was the best thing we could have done. It anchored the community.''</p>
        <p>Charlotte Street has come back, and swaths of the Bronx have come back with it. Would that happen today, without a determined, rule-breaking Ed Logue? Probably not.</p>
        <p>Many lump him with Robert Moses, and there were strong similarities. But unlike Mr. Moses, Mr. Logue was a proud liberal who brought his social conscience to his projects -- trying (unsuccessfully) to build integrated housing in Westchester, and staying for days in his housing projects in Coney Island, Harlem and elsewhere, asking his staff members to do the same.</p>
        <p>''They were called live-ins,'' said Mr. Lefkowitz. ''It was supposed to give people who were doing the planning a better appreciation of how a project functioned, what people wanted, what it felt like to live there.''</p>
        <p>CRITICS, chief among them Jane Jacobs, an urban expert, considered Mr. Logue to be a ruthless figure who imposed his will on communities, in the Moses fashion. Headstrong and willful he certainly was.</p>
        <p>But thousands of New Yorkers can afford decent places to live because of his public housing projects. Roosevelt Island, once an abandoned island in the East River, is now a thriving community because of the Logue stubbornness. He unstuck a plan stalled for 20 years and built a diverse, successful community where only weeds and old hospitals stood.</p>
        <p>He'd seen the bedraggled island from the window of his apartment on East End Avenue, and that was that. He used to say that he loved nothing more than a cleared lot so that he could build big.</p>
        <p>''God knows,'' Mr. Koch said with a laugh, ''heaven is going to be a different place 10 years from now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
