<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Birdcage' Shows Growth In Older Audience's Power</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGE, CHRONOLOGICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOTION PICTURE ASSN OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD ROBIN WILLIAMS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BIRDCAGE, THE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MR HOLLAND'S OPUS (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">UP CLOSE AND PERSONAL(MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Organizations/Motion Picture Association of America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDA1639F931A25750C0A960958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Birdcage' Shows Growth In Older Audience's Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD ROBIN WILLIAMS;</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, March 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robin Williams, the star of "The Birdcage," voiced one reason for the resounding -- and unexpected -- success of the film, which opened last Friday. "It's basically very funny, and now, with all the primaries in the news, people  want some kind of antidote," he offered. "You know, laughter as medication."</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, "The Birdcage" seems to have met the needs of moviegoers, who bought $18 million worth of tickets in its opening weekend, far  more than Mr. Williams, the studio, MGM/UA, or most of Hollywood anticipated. The film, a retelling of the 1979 French-language import "La Cage aux Folles," received mixed reviews, but has clearly struck a chord among older audiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robin Williams, the star of "The Birdcage," voiced one reason for the resounding -- and unexpected -- success of the film, which opened last Friday. "It's basically very funny, and now, with all the primaries in the news, people  want some kind of antidote," he offered. "You know, laughter as medication."</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, "The Birdcage" seems to have met the needs of moviegoers, who bought $18 million worth of tickets in its opening weekend, far  more than Mr. Williams, the studio, MGM/UA, or most of Hollywood anticipated. The film, a retelling of the 1979 French-language import "La Cage aux Folles," received mixed reviews, but has clearly struck a chord among older audiences.</p>
        <p>There are a lot of serious films in the marketplace, and there are a couple of comedies only with youth appeal," said Gerry Rich, president of worldwide marketing for MGM/UA, by telephone. "There's not an intelligent comedy out there for an adult audience, and that's what this film is."</p>
        <p>The success of "The Birdcage" follows two other recent movies that have shown strong appeal to adult audiences: "Mr. Holland's Opus," starring Richard Dreyfuss as a schoolteacher who sees his life as a failure, and "Up Close and Personal," a sudsy love story about a pair of news broadcasters, starring Robert Redford and Michelle Pfeiffer.</p>
        <p>"A huge group of people, the whole baby-boomer group, is supporting these films, and this audience is getting bigger," said Joe Roth, chairman of the Walt Disney Motion Picture Group, which released the Dreyfuss and Redford films. "There's no way that these movies, five years ago, appealing to older audiences, would do this kind of business. That audience is growing."</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth's assessment echoed Jack Valenti, president of the Motion Picture Association of America, who last week told theater exhibitors at a convention in Las Vegas, Nev., that a study by his group indicated that older moviegoers were  emerging as an increasingly powerful force.</p>
        <p>But Robert Daly, co-chairman of Warner Brothers, said he believed that only certain kinds of movies appealing to adults worked at the box office: romances,  like Warner Brothers' "Bridges of Madison County," or comedies. Hard-edged films, like "Leaving Las Vegas" and "Dead Man Walking," generally face an uphill struggle, he said, although United Artists released "Leaving Las Vegas" and the  movie has performed moderately well.</p>
        <p>"The right movie will bring out the older audience, but the ones that work aren't too tough," Mr. Daly said in an interview. "As to 'Birdcage,' it's just very funny and Robin Williams is a big star."</p>
        <p>The movie is about two gay men (played by Mr. Williams and Nathan Lane) who have lived together happily for years, and the problems that ensue when Mr. Williams's son, whom they have reared, tells them he wants to marry the daughter of an an arch-conservative senator.</p>
        <p>The central setting is a drag club in the South Beach section of Miami Beach, run by Mr. Williams. The club's leading attraction is his companion, Mr. Lane. The film is the first big hit in years for Mike Nichols, after disappointments like "Regarding Henry" and "Wolf." It was adapted by Elaine May, his former comedy partner.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Nichols and the studio wanted Mr. Williams to play the flamboyant role of Albert, the queen of drag queens, the comedian opted for the  more restrained partner, Armand. A key reason, Mr. Williams explained, was that  he had already appeared in drag in "Mrs. Doubtfire."</p>
        <p>"I thought, 'No, I want to try something different, something more elegant,'  " said Mr. Williams. "People expect me to be the more flamboyant one. I wanted something new." Mr. Nichols then offered the part of Albert to Mr. Lane, who has appeared on Broadway in "Guys and Dolls," "Love, Valour, Compassion!" and "Laughter on the 23d Floor."</p>
        <p>John Calley, president of United Artists, and the studio executive most responsible for "The Birdcage," said that Mr. Nichols, a longtime friend, had told him years ago that "La Cage aux Folles" had a classic comedy structure and  that Ms. May, too, was dazzled by it. Mr. Calley recalled that Mr. Nichols was the original director of the Broadway version of the French film, but left after disagreements with the producer, Allan Carr. ).</p>
        <p>"When I got this job, one of the tasks was to attract major-league talent," said Mr. Calley, a prominent studio executive in the 1960's and 1970 who went into semi-retirement in the 1980's. "I asked Mike if there was anything we owned that interested him. And he said, 'You own a project that has one of the greatest comedy structures.' We got the rest of the rights, and he said he wanted to call Elaine and ask her to do it. The next day she said yes."</p>
        <p>What surprised him, Mr. Calley said, was that the film had an undercurrent of deep morality. "It's curiously about family values," he said. "While the family  is obviously eccentric, there's a sense of decency and honor; the relationships  are very warm, very loving." (Mr. Rich of MGM/UA described the material in the film as "incredibly mainstream.")</p>
        <p>Mr. Calley said the studio was, initially, a bit concerned about the politics of the film, especially the portrayals of some of the arch-conservatives as buffoons or hypocrites. "We had a twinge about this," he said. "But Mike anticipated it eight or nine months ago. He said, 'By the time the movie comes out, you won't be able to parody these guys anymore; they'll be parodying themselves.' He said the political climate would become so eccentric to make the film accurate. And he was right, wasn't he?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
