<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sitting Out the Dance of Politics</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: VOICES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MISSISSIPPI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5D91639F931A25750C0A960958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sitting Out the Dance of Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
      <dateline>TUNICA, Miss. March 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hard by the highway mix of gambling casinos and tarpaper-shack poverty, Carla King, a waitress at the Blue and White diner, said she had finally heard someone mention that today was the eve of primary voting day.</p>
        <p>"What was his name?" she said, pausing by the short-order window, then remembering. "Carricker. Clarence Carricker, running for levee commissioner. He  was here giving out these little cards."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hard by the highway mix of gambling casinos and tarpaper-shack poverty, Carla King, a waitress at the Blue and White diner, said she had finally heard someone mention that today was the eve of primary voting day.</p>
        <p>"What was his name?" she said, pausing by the short-order window, then remembering. "Carricker. Clarence Carricker, running for levee commissioner. He  was here giving out these little cards."</p>
        <p>Ms. King wrinkled her nose in dismissal at the mention of the larger primary, the one for Presidential candidates, saying she had heard of absolutely no interest in that lately in serving up the blue-plate specials. "Even though that thing is on TV every three seconds," she complained, lumping all the Presidential campaign advertisements together as mere background noise.</p>
        <p>"I myself am so tempted not to vote at all in November," Ms. King added, anticipating an even longer season of political ennui hereabouts once the primary dance moves on.</p>
        <p>Whatever the civic expectations raised by multimillion-dollar electronic electioneering and nonstop news coverage-cum-metaphysical-analysis of Presidential politics, Ms. King might be offering the more realistic national vox pop. As usual, the primary process around the nation has so far been indulged in by a decided minority of the voting population, and Mississippi's vote on Tuesday seems in no danger of breaking that trend.</p>
        <p>In fact, there seems measurably more interest in Mr. Carricker's campaign to  retain his seat on the Yazoo Mississippi Delta Board, one of two seats for which six contenders are vying in the 10-county primary. The surge of millions of dollars in casino revenue into the board's coffers and the board's role in providing levee access and parking space to the casinos is altering local politics, even if the national contests become increasingly boring.</p>
        <p>"It seems to me there's a risk of developing greed and power," said Bobby Leatherman, a retired farmer who is running for a seat, "and that was not the levee board's original intention of flood protection."</p>
        <p>Mr. Leatherman remains far more concerned about the outsized political effects of casino gambling here than about the Presidential primary caravan's brief local stop. The idea of a casino's paying $2 million for a parking lot on  levee land is more enthralling, to Mr. Leatherman's way of thinking, than is Senator Bob Dole's daily search for an evocative message to summon voters to what is likely to be a minor public exercise.</p>
        <p>"It takes a sheriff's fight to get any turnout around here," said Mr. Leatherman, who predicts that neither the levee election nor the Presidency will prove much of a draw.</p>
        <p>In the Presidential primary, the nation's high-participation mark has so far  come in New Hampshire, where fewer than 1 in 4 eligible voters went to the polls last month. Little more than 8 percent of that state's eligible voters then united to ignite the candidacy of Patrick J. Buchanan across America, it seemed. Only a few weeks later, about 1 in 10 eligible voters in South Carolina bothered to turn out, and fewer than half of them delivered what most analysts now point  to as the decisive reversal of the New Hampshire vector, by endorsing Senator Dole and giving a crushing blow to Mr. Buchanan's national hopes.</p>
        <p>That political action was not much faster or the odds quirkier than here along Highway 61. The new casino boom-town attractions appear to be registering  more popular enthusiasm than either the Presidential or levee board candidates.  Single-deck blackjack, $2 craps, and 25-cent roulette are only some of the items vying with the candidates and their offerings on family values, the future of America and assorted warnings about taxation.</p>
        <p>"Most people are saying, Let it ride and whoever wins, that's it,' " said a visitor, Irving Butrica, a nonparticipant in Georgia's primary last week who made the roving state Presidential primary process sound as fatalistic as a roulette game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butrica's wife, Yvonne, offered few apologies for the couple's acknowledged lack of interest in the primary as she jingled a cup of quarters and headed for the slots at Fitzgerald's casino on a nearby levee. "The politicians aren't answering the questions we'd like to see answered," she said, moving toward the brighter action.</p>
        <p>Down the levee at Sam's Town casino, Freeman Brown, a retired aerospace worker, gauged politicians as if he were watching the blackjack dealer's hands.  "One reason no one goes out for the primaries is people just don't trust politicians," he said. "Don't trust the things they say, or do after they get in."</p>
        <p>Jim Ponca, a fireman from Oklahoma trying his luck here, hardly regrets that  he will not get home in time for his state primary on Tuesday. "People are too busy to bother with the primary," he said. "A lot of people probably think the whole thing is predecided."</p>
        <p>At the Blue and White diner, A. E. Pardue, a retired merchant, meticulously mopped his lunchtime gravy with a crust of bread and said that, unlike many of the gamblers hurrying by, he would vote in the primary. But not so much because  of the Presidential contenders -- "I find those Republicans too boisterous," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pardue said he would vote because the politics of the levee were growing  murkier and ought to be watched.</p>
        <p>"Those casinos are scalping all the money off the poor working man," said Mr. Pardue, the lone likely voter in the diner.</p>
        <p>POLITICS: VOICES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
