<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Belcher and Reds Continue Surges</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DC163EF930A35755C0A964958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Belcher and Reds Continue Surges</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reds 2, Cardinals 1</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI, June 2 (AP) -- Tim Belcher won for the fourth time in five decisions, and the surging Cincinnati Reds cashed in on two St. Louis mistakes to beat the slumping Cardinals, 2-1, tonight. Cincinnati won for the seventh time in eight games by scoring two unearned runs off Jose DeLeon (2-5), who has lost his last three starts. Tom Pagnozzi's passed ball let in a run in the second inning, and right fielder Felix Jose's error set up Bip Roberts's sacrifice fly in the fifth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reds 2, Cardinals 1</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI, June 2 (AP) -- Tim Belcher won for the fourth time in five decisions, and the surging Cincinnati Reds cashed in on two St. Louis mistakes to beat the slumping Cardinals, 2-1, tonight. Cincinnati won for the seventh time in eight games by scoring two unearned runs off Jose DeLeon (2-5), who has lost his last three starts. Tom Pagnozzi's passed ball let in a run in the second inning, and right fielder Felix Jose's error set up Bip Roberts's sacrifice fly in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Belcher (5-5) scattered seven hits over eight innings, losing his shutout and ending his scoreless streak at 15 innings when Ozzie Smith scored on Jose's grounder in the eighth. Pirates 1, Dodgers 0</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH (AP) -- Pinch-hitter Dave Clark drew a walk in the seventh inning off Tom Candiotti to force in the only run, and Pittsburgh stopped Los Angeles' winning streak at six games. The Pirates won for just the fourth time in 17 games.</p>
        <p>Randy Tomlin (6-3), who had a 7.33 earned run average in his previous six starts, allowed five hits over seven shutout innings for only his second victory since April 25.</p>
        <p>Candiotti (5-4) permitted only one runner as far as third base until the seventh. Braves 5, Phillies 3</p>
        <p>ATLANTA (AP) -- Terry Pendleton hit a two-run home run off Mitch Williams (2-2) in the ninth inning to give Atlanta its fifth consecutive victory. Pendleton hit his 10th homer of the season after Otis Nixon had singled and stolen second base. The Phillies had tied the game in the top of the inning when John Kruk scored on a wild pitch by Mike Stanton (1-2). Cubs 3, Padres 2</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (AP) -- Andre Dawson hit a two-run homer in the ninth inning and Mark Grace drove in the winning run with a single in the 13th for Chicago.</p>
        <p>Frank Seminara, a 25-year-old right-hander, made his major league debut for the Padres and became just the second player from Columbia University in the majors since Lou Gehrig, following Minnesota's Gene Larkin. Seminara had a three-hit shutout when he left in the eighth after he was hit by a line drive.</p>
        <p>In the 13th, Joe Girardi singled off Gene Harris (0-1) with one out and took second on Sandberg's infield single. Dawson bounced out, Pat Clements relieved and Grace pulled a single to right. Astros 6, Expos 0</p>
        <p>HOUSTON (AP) -- Mark Portugal extended his Astrodome winning streak to four games with a six-hitter, and his Houston teammates helped with sparkling defense. Portugal (5-2), who struck out three and walked four, benefited from a bases-loaded double play that ended the second inning and Steve Finley's leaping catch off the wall that prevented Archi Cianfrocco from getting a hit in the fourth. Finley victimized Cianfrocco again in the seventh with a diving catch. Indians 4, Mariners 3</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND (AP) -- Glenallen Hill put Cleveland ahead to stay with a two-run homer in the seventh inning as the Indians won for the sixth time in seven games. Eric Hanson (2-8) had a 3-2 lead before Sandy Alomar singled with one out and Hill followed with his second home run of the season. Royals 2, White Sox 1</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) -- Kevin McReynolds hit the first home run off Scott Radinsky in almost a year, a two-run drive in the eighth inning to lift Kansas City to victory.</p>
        <p>Frank Thomas hit a sacrifice fly off Mark Gubicza (6-3) that gave Chicago the lead in the eighth. Jack McDowell walked Gregg Jefferies leading off the bottom of the inning and Radinsky (2-2) relieved. McReynolds followed with his eighth home run, the first off Radinsky in 50 innings since last July 27.</p>
        <p>Jefferies was 0 for 3, snapping his hitting streak at 18. Brewers 5, Tigers 4</p>
        <p>MILWAUKEE (AP) -- Scott Fletcher singled in the go-ahead run with two out in the seventh for the second successive game as Milwaukee beat Detroit after wasting a four-run lead. Detroit has lost six in a row, matching its worst skid this season, and dropped a season-low nine games under .500.</p>
        <p>Fletcher, extending his hitting streak to 10 games, drove in Jim Gantner, who doubled with two out off Mark Leiter (3-3). Blue Jays 7, Twins 5</p>
        <p>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) -- Derek Bell broke a 13th-inning tie with a sacrifice fly as Toronto rallied and beat Minnesota for its fifth consecutive victory. With the score tied at 5-5, Kelly Gruber led off the 13th with a double off Gary Wayne (1-2), took third on John Olerud's sacrifice and scored easily on Bell's fly to deep center. Pinch-hitter Pat Borders doubled and scored on Manuel Lee's single. Orioles 4, Angels 2</p>
        <p>ANAHEIM, Calif. (AP) -- Cal Ripken Jr. had a two-run homer and Jeff Tackett added a bases-empty home run as Baltimore gained its fourth consecutive victory. Mike Mussina, coming off his only loss of the season, went five innings for Baltimore, allowing six hits and one walk with two strikeouts.</p>
        <p>The loss was the ninth in 10 games for the Angels, who have won just 3 of their last 17. Athletics 5, Red Sox 4</p>
        <p>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) -- Mike Moore ended his losing streak against Boston at 10 games, and Terry Steinbach tripled home two runs in a four-run sixth inning as Oakland overtook Boston. Moore (7-3), pitching on three days' rest, gave up one earned run and seven hits in six and one-third innings, struck out five and walked three. Dennis Eckersley, Oakland's fourth pitcher, got five outs for his 19th save.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
