<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>France's Allegiance: To Things French, Like Hypocrisy</title>
    <meta content="24COHE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The World" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="The World"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DA103EF937A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>France's Allegiance: To Things French, Like Hypocrisy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>France has taken over Britain's role as faintly risible archetype of failed European economy, with its socialist government trying to create state-sector jobs by the hundreds of thousands, its record unemployment, its diatribes against globalization, its quaint plans for 32-hour work weeks and its defense of apparently unaffordable welfare state; in fact, modernization is taking place, but it is being done on the quiet because change, adaptation and modernization have little to do with country's self-image (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES de GAULLE, who knew his people well, once said: ''Every Frenchman wants to benefit from one or several privileges. It is his way of affirming his passion for equality.''</p>
        <p>It was the general's way of gently capturing an essential French duplicity. Perhaps in no other country are form and substance so divergent. Formal discourse is full of grand principles: equality, solidarity or, more recently, the iniquities of American-driven globalization. But the substance may have more to do with the defense of privilege or the concealment of pragmatic acts in the robes of idealism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES de GAULLE, who knew his people well, once said: ''Every Frenchman wants to benefit from one or several privileges. It is his way of affirming his passion for equality.''</p>
        <p>It was the general's way of gently capturing an essential French duplicity. Perhaps in no other country are form and substance so divergent. Formal discourse is full of grand principles: equality, solidarity or, more recently, the iniquities of American-driven globalization. But the substance may have more to do with the defense of privilege or the concealment of pragmatic acts in the robes of idealism.</p>
        <p>A French politician's art thus lies in offering splendid ideals while insuring the people get fed. Francois Mitterrand, the late President, was a master of the art. After a brief and calamitous experiment with textbook socialism, he opted to defend only principles lofty enough that they would never affect the franc's strength. Goodbye, Albania; hello, the bourse. By the end of his second term in 1995, he had elevated the riddle to the heart of his governance.</p>
        <p>All this may be worth remembering at a time when France is taken very much at its word. During the cold war, French posturing was an irritant, but seldom more, to the United States. In its aftermath, a very public French stand against the harsh capitalism of America's boom and the dangers of a world driven by the American quest for profit has given a new edge to the allies' old sparring. At times, as at the summit of major industrialized nations last month in Denver, it has looked like real rivalry.</p>
        <p>France has become America's favorite European basket case. With its socialist government trying to create state-sector jobs by the hundreds of thousands, its record unemployment, its diatribes against globalization, its quaint plans for 32-hour work weeks and its defense of an apparently unaffordable welfare state, France has taken over Britain's role as the faintly risible archetype of the failed European economy. It is the Titanic-with-piano-still-tinkling adrift on a sea of global competition.</p>
        <p>There is, of course, much substance to this vision of France. Fewer and fewer businesses want to hire because it costs too much to do so, and many of the 3.6 million unemployed have settled into a way of life based on perennial state financial assistance combined with odd jobs on the black market. Initiative is quashed and dependence encouraged. Disillusionment spreads.</p>
        <p>But the French reality is rather more complex. It has to do with the fact that change, adaptation and modernization must be masked because they have little to do with the country's self-image.</p>
        <p>That image is attached to notions of equality, a strongly centralized Jacobin state and change, if it all, through revolution alone. Evolution is a kind of anathema in the land of 1789 and 1968. As Pierre Birnbaum, a sociologist, said, ''We have not found the way to modernize while preserving our imagined community.''</p>
        <p>So modernization takes place on the quiet. Thus, in the past decade alone, France has turned a currency that was a laughing stock into one virtually as strong as the German mark. It has freed capital movements, an idea once unthinkable in the home-par-excellence of the secret Swiss bank account.</p>
        <p>It has sold off great swaths of state industry, including the automaker Renault, the oil company Elf Aquitaine, the chemicals giant Rhone-Poulenc and the manufacturer of Gauloise cigarettes, Seita.</p>
        <p>Creeping Retail</p>
        <p>It has littered the countryside with Americana: more than 600 McDonald's restaurants, Toys ''R'' Us in countless malls, Haagen-Dazs on fashionable Paris streets. It has adopted American habits, cutting way back on the leisurely lunch and banning smoking in the Metro. It has allowed St. Germain-des-Pres, sanctuary of the Left Bank intellectual, to turn into a glitzy -- and depressing -- home to international fashion.</p>
        <p>Its national airline, Groupe Air France, no longer flies to even major cities where it cannot make a profit. The profit motive, pure and simple, has also driven numerous private companies -- including Michelin, L'Oreal, Carrefour and the luxury-goods conglomerate LVMH -- to adapt and remain highly competitive throughout the world. These have contributed to the country's huge trade surpluses, and to the fact that France is the world's fourth-largest exporter.</p>
        <p>Drive out of Paris in the direction of Rambouillet, and you will soon find the town of Coignieres. A decade ago there were wheat fields there; today it is a hymn to the American way of life. A busy highway cuts through a landscape dominated by McDonald's and other hamburger restaurants, Pier 1 Imports, warehouse-stores selling bathroom fittings, and advertisements full of words like ''light'' and ''cool.'' Coignieres is globalization incarnate.</p>
        <p>Nothing to Be Done</p>
        <p>''I suppose all this is inevitable,'' said Jacques Eperon, who runs a small choucroute tavern opposite the Coignieres McDonald's. ''I don't like it much, but in the end you have to accept it.''</p>
        <p>So change is accepted and not much liked. And more than ever, politics becomes the art of concealing change behind anti-American slogans and the like.</p>
        <p>Lionel Jospin, the new socialist Prime Minister, seems to be aware of this. The Government talks a lot about the 32-hour week and jobs in the state sector and American economic arrogance while it gets on with preparing new privatizations and the austerity measures needed to qualify for the planned adoption of a single European currency, the euro, at the end of next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jospin knows that the French still want to dream of ''du pain et des roses'' -- ''bread and roses,'' or a salary and poetry. In this he has proved more adept than President Jacques Chirac, who sometimes seems insufficiently shrewd for the divided French heart.</p>
        <p>A lot is heard today about French roses. The country wants to offer some poetry and compassion to a globalized world where it often seems the rich get richer and the poor poorer. That can be an irritant to America. But it should not be forgotten that France also has an eye on its bread.</p>
        <p>The World</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
