<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Call Them Biker Babes</title>
    <meta content="24PERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="IN PERSON" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="IN PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jersey Girls (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DD153EF937A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="1667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Call Them Biker Babes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KENT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kent, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Jersey Girls, New Jersey's first women-only motorcycle club, and some of its members; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT NOON today, the 42 members of the Jersey Girls, New Jersey's first women-only motorcycle club, are to gather at Geets Diner in Williamstown, then climb on their Harleys and Hondas and roar off down on the Black Horse Pike toward Uncle Mike's, the tavern in Mays Landing that is considered the capital of South Jersey biker chic.</p>
        <p>''We're going to say hello to the guys, shoot some pool and have a great time,'' said Linda Young, a computer operator from Port Republic, who met her husband at Uncle Mike's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT NOON today, the 42 members of the Jersey Girls, New Jersey's first women-only motorcycle club, are to gather at Geets Diner in Williamstown, then climb on their Harleys and Hondas and roar off down on the Black Horse Pike toward Uncle Mike's, the tavern in Mays Landing that is considered the capital of South Jersey biker chic.</p>
        <p>''We're going to say hello to the guys, shoot some pool and have a great time,'' said Linda Young, a computer operator from Port Republic, who met her husband at Uncle Mike's.</p>
        <p>The fact that a majority of people who ride motorcycles are male does not concern Paula Palmo of Washington Township, a motorcycle saleswoman who founded the Jersey Girls with Debbie Musfalli of Deptford in June. ''There was a survey done this year that said 1 in every 12 riders in America is a woman,'' Ms. Palmo said. ''I know that there's a lot more than that from selling bikes. I'd thought of starting a club but never really got around to it until Debbie walked into the store one day and started talking about Women in the Wind.''</p>
        <p>About one of every five motorcycle buyers is a woman, Ms. Palmo said. ''Their primary concern is being able to handle the bike,'' she said. ''A lot of bikes are simply too big and, with an average weight of 600 pounds, too heavy. You can find enough in the 450-pound range that are close to ground, but no manufacturer has yet had the guts to make a bike specifically for women.''</p>
        <p>The larger of two all-female motorcycle associations in the United States, Women in the Wind, based in Toledo, Ohio, was founded in 1979 by Becky Brown, a motorcycling enthusiast who led 20 women on an impromptu ride along the Maumee River. The group now has 50 regional chapters throughout the United States and in Canada and Britain, Ms. Brown said.</p>
        <p>''Women are getting into riding because more of us are working and have the money and the time to spend on ourselves,'' she said. ''Riding also represents independence in a way that nothing else does.''</p>
        <p>She added that the Jersey Girls, Women in the Wind's newest chapter, is also among the largest. The Jersey Girls are ''probably the fastest-growing women's riding group in the country right now,'' Ms. Brown said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Palmo said: ''Every week since we started the club, my phone has been ringing with women wanting to join. It's word of mouth, mostly. We're all ages, all occupations, single, married, widowed, divorced, whatever. We have one thing in common: we like to ride.''</p>
        <p>Beyond scheduling monthly group rides for members (men are permitted to go along ''as long as they stay in the back and don't make trouble,'' Ms. Palmo said), the club also hopes to raise funds for breast cancer research.</p>
        <p>Riding means different things to different women: sport, travel, camaraderie, independence. Here are four of their stories.</p>
        <p>Someone Rode By, And Her Eyes Lit Up</p>
        <p>Debbie Musfalli, a mental health counselor, said she wasn't looking forward to today's jaunt as much as she had to last month's trip to the Eastern Shore of Maryland. ''Uncle Mike's is a biker bar, and I personally don't like the Pagans and their attitude,'' Ms. Musfalli said. ''Guys with big beards and tattoos are a turnoff.''</p>
        <p>But she is willing to let the majority rule. ''The club voted on it, so I'm going along with it,'' she said. ''That's why we started this club: to do things together. There are plenty of guys' groups, but if you're like me and your husband doesn't ride and you join a guys' group, the first thing they think is that you're after something romantic. I don't want to meet somebody. I want to ride.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Musfalli said she couldn't remember a time when she wasn't fascinated by motorcycles. ''As a little kid, when you're in the car with your parents and somebody drives by on a motorcycle, your eyes light up,'' she said. ''I kept talking about how much I wanted one until my grandmother got me a Honda mini-bike when I was 9 and my parents hit the ceiling. But nobody could get me off it. We grew up near some woods in Paterson, and I'd be out exploring every chance I got. It give me a feeling for independence that I've cherished all my life.''</p>
        <p>She bought her first real bike when she graduated from Douglass College of Rutgers University in New Brunswick: a Honda CM Custom. ''I rode that down to the University of South Carolina, where I did my master's in social work,'' she said. ''The idea of a woman alone on a bike -- not holding on to some guy, but riding the bike by herself -- was pretty strange down there.</p>
        <p>''People still can't get it that it's possible to just enjoy riding and not have some kind of weird streak or antisocial tendency. I'm not antisocial. I'm not obnoxious. I have nothing to prove. I keep under the speed limit. I'm married. I love dogs. I play Scrabble and racquetball, and I own a Suzuki 800 Intruder that's as quiet as can be.''</p>
        <p>The Big 4-0 Loomed, So She Bought a Harley</p>
        <p>Joanne Franco, who owns a Brooklawn bowling alley, sees women as ''a positive presence on the road.''</p>
        <p>''We're into safety, keeping speed limits, helping people out,'' she said. ''We've let the guys come along on some of our rides, and they're the ones who are always getting lost and having the breakdowns. You hear about the bad apples spoiling the barrel, but it's always the guys who are having problems.''</p>
        <p>She started riding dirt bikes when she was 8, graduated to mopeds and motorcycles at 18 but ''gave up the bike because I thought the boys were supposed to be on the bike.''</p>
        <p>She married, had three children, ran the bowling lanes and ''did mom things for 20 years,'' she said. ''My son was in college; I was getting close to my 40th birthday when I decided that I wanted a Harley.''</p>
        <p>She took a motorcycle safety course at Rowan College in Glassboro ''just so I knew what I was getting into.''</p>
        <p>In the course, she learned that riding in groups is much safer than riding solo. ''But there really weren't many groups around, and those I heard about were, you know, bikers,'' she said. ''My husband, Mike, felt that whatever I wanted to do was O.K. by him, so I went out and just this March I bought myself a Harley Hugger. It's the smallest one they make. It isn't even loud. But it's fun.''</p>
        <p>When she isn't on monthly group rides with the Jersey Girls, Ms. Franco rides with her sister, Daria Giles, another Jersey Girl. This summer, the sisters have ridden back roads to Sunset Beach in Cape May Point and in rural areas in southern Gloucester and Cumberland counties.</p>
        <p>''You get a new appreciation for where you live when you start to ride,'' she said. ''You're not boxed in, in a car. You feel like you're in closer touch with everything around you.''</p>
        <p>Shipboard Love, No. Biker Bar, Yes.</p>
        <p>For Linda Young, 46, a motorcycle was a symbol of freedom. ''Guys would take me for rides on their bikes when I was a teen-ager,'' she said. ''The first guy I married didn't ride. I was 23 when I divorced him, and from the settlement I had some money to spend on myself. I wanted to put everything behind me, so I went out and bought a Honda Custom.''</p>
        <p>She rode her motorcycle up and down the Jersey Shore and into the surrounding states, but she could never find other women to accompany her. ''So I gave it up,'' she said. ''I got into going on cruises.''</p>
        <p>Then, about five years ago, on a dare, Ms. Young accompanied a girlfriend to Uncle Mike's. ''This guy starts talking to me about his bike,'' she said, ''and he only had a little beard, and he was as nice as could be.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after, they were married, and since then Ms. Young and Robert, an engineer at the Tropicana Casino in Atlantic City, have ridden from New Hampshire to Florida. They hope to go to Arizona in the next two years. Although Ms. Young prefers the company of her husband, she said she also enjoys the occasional long ride alone.</p>
        <p>''It's something I do just for me,'' she said. ''It's my independence.''</p>
        <p>The Wind, the Speed And the Safety Factor</p>
        <p>In 10 years of riding, Paula Palmo has had her share of spills. ''Nothing serious, though,'' she said. ''Once a bug flew into my helmet, and while I was pulling over to the shoulder, I went into a ditch.''</p>
        <p>Most of her injuries ''have been to my pride,'' she said. ''You have to be a little aggressive on the road. You have to learn when not to give ground.''</p>
        <p>She advises those interested in the sport to start by taking one of the motorcycle safety courses sponsored by the state Department of Transportation. And she tells all women riding motorcycles to carry cell phones so they can summon help if needed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Palmo said her parents discouraged her from going anywhere near motorcycles, so she didn't get her first ride until she was 21, on the back of her brother-in-law's Yamaha Virago.</p>
        <p>''I was totally amazed,'' she said. '' The wind, the speed, the sound -- everything appealed to me. My mother had always told me that women aren't supposed to ride motorcycles. She's eating her words now.''</p>
        <p>Information on the Jersey Girls and Women in the Wind: (609) 218-1417.</p>
        <p>IN PERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
