<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cremins, Back on the Court, Finds His Old Bounce</title>
    <meta content="28cremins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/28/sports/ncaabasketball/28cremins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1807912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">College of Charleston</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Georgia Tech</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cremins, Bobby</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7D6103EF93BA15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cremins, Back on the Court, Finds His Old Bounce</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Back on the Court, Cremins Has a New Bounce</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIV BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Viv</byline>
      <dateline>CHARLESTON, S.C.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A walk on the beach, a dip in the ocean, a swim in the pool, a round of golf. Bobby Cremins had surely found the Lowcountry easy life in Hilton Head, S.C., after walking away from the high-pressure coaching grind at Georgia Tech in 2000.</p>
        <p>But maybe it was a little too easy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six and a half years after leaving as coach of Georgia Tech, Bob Cremins finds himself back on the basketball court at the College of Charleston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A walk on the beach, a dip in the ocean, a swim in the pool, a round of golf. Bobby Cremins had surely found the Lowcountry easy life in Hilton Head, S.C., after walking away from the high-pressure coaching grind at Georgia Tech in 2000.</p>
        <p>But maybe it was a little too easy.</p>
        <p>''My body kind of changed on me,'' Cremins said recently, ''and my body told me that what I was doing I couldn't do for the next 20 years if I was going to live another 20, 25 years.''</p>
        <p>So Cremins has made it hard on himself again. Six and a half years after leaving the Yellow Jackets, a program he coached to national prominence with players like Mark Price, Kenny Anderson and Stephon Marbury, Cremins finds himself back on the basketball court.</p>
        <p>In a twist, Cremins, 59, emerged last July as the new coach of the Division I College of Charleston program. [The team is 3-2 with a matchup against powerful Kentucky on Tuesday.]</p>
        <p>As he watched his players practice at John Kresse Arena, even Cremins laughed about how it all played out. In June, College of Charleston officials hired Gregg Marshall of Winthrop University to replace Tom Herrion, who was fired two weeks earlier. But Marshall, a longtime assistant to the beloved Charleston Coach John Kresse, backed out on June 28 -- a day after the announcement -- and decided to remain at Winthrop.</p>
        <p>''He pulled a Bobby Cremins,'' Cremins said, joking about his own reversal in 1993. At the time, he had accepted the coaching job at his alma mater, South Carolina, before backing out to remain at Georgia Tech.</p>
        <p>That was back in Cremins's heyday at Georgia Tech, where he won three Atlantic Coast Conference championships and took the Yellow Jackets from the bottom of the conference to the Final Four in 1990. In 19 years there, Cremins had become the white-haired, mop-top image of the program.</p>
        <p>But by 2000, having gone to one N.C.A.A. tournament in his previous seven seasons, Cremins resigned.</p>
        <p>At the time, he planned to make it a short break.</p>
        <p>''When I first left Georgia Tech, I thought I would get back in within a year,'' Cremins said. ''That was my original game plan. I was very young. I was 53. But I was burned out. The ending was a little tough because our teams weren't playing really well. And I had a lot on my mind. We had lost our edge and I knew it. I knew it was time to go.''</p>
        <p>A year later, there were some knocks on the door but nothing that inspired Cremins to leave the beaches and golf courses of Hilton Head. And then the calls stopped coming. Cremins kept busy as a part-time broadcaster. He worked at basketball camps, was a frequent competitor in charity golf tournaments and was writing a book.</p>
        <p>As the years passed, Cremins felt his chance to return to coaching was slipping away.</p>
        <p>''I really started to believe I was done,'' said Cremins, a Bronx native who never left the South after playing for the legendary Frank McGuire at South Carolina.</p>
        <p>That is when Charleston, snubbed by Marshall, reopened its coaching search and Cremins sent word through friends that he was interested. University officials listened.</p>
        <p>''He came up and spoke to the committee and honestly just kind of blew everybody away,'' the athletic director, Jerry Baker, said. ''It was very, very clear that he had the desire, the energy, the zest again to get back into coaching, and when he turns that on, it's hard not to be impressed. He's a very energetic, positive person.</p>
        <p>''We're sitting there going, 'We have a chance to get a national coach of the year that's won A.C.C. championships, been to the Final Four.' You ask yourself the question, why wouldn't you want him? And you can't come up with a good answer for that except we've got a chance to get Bobby Cremins.''</p>
        <p>That quickly, it was done. Cremins was back.</p>
        <p>But back to what? Georgia Tech and the A.C.C. are more successful and prestigious than College of Charleston and the Southern Conference. Cremins has gone from charter flights to buses.</p>
        <p>Still, he jumped at the chance. Cremins said he had lost a close friend in Hilton Head to cancer just days before Marshall backed out. At that point, he knew it was time to put down the golf clubs.</p>
        <p>''I just felt like it was now or never,'' Cremins said. ''I just decided the heck with it. It's time to do something else.</p>
        <p>''You never know if what you're doing is the right thing. But for me, I knew I had to do something different. This is my passion. Basketball is my passion. It's my love. Without basketball, without having basketball in my life, I probably would have wound up in New York either a cop or fireman, or a gangster.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he is a salesman. Cremins has shaken every outstretched hand in Charleston since accepting the job, a public-relations boon for a program that has seen sagging attendance and community relations under Herrion despite his 80-38 record.</p>
        <p>Cremins sold himself to the players, too.</p>
        <p>''I was real worried,'' the sophomore forward Jermaine Johnson said as he watched from his home in California as Herrion was fired and Marshall accepted and then declined. ''At that point, I half made up my decision. I was like, you know what, I'm not coming back. This place is a little too hectic, a little too weird for me.''</p>
        <p>Johnson said he decided to return after Cremins flew to California to meet with him and his mother last summer.</p>
        <p>Cremins has been on the go almost every day since then. He has been so busy that he said he had been back to Hilton Head just once since accepting the job.</p>
        <p>But leaving paradise was a small sacrifice.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, I'm back in the rat race,'' Cremins said. ''I'm back in the mix.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
