<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Observer; Could Be A Long Season</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, RUSSELL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STENGEL, CASEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DF173AF937A15757C0A965958260" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Observer; Could Be A Long Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUSSELL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BAKER, RUSSELL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton's bad week at the Capitol brings to mind Casey Stengel, Franklin Roosevelt and Lyndon Johnson. "Can't anybody here play this game?" asked Stengel when he was put in charge of a major league baseball team on which nobody could.</p>
        <p>It was the New York Mets, a brand-new expansion team, that provoked Stengel's cry of anguish. The Clinton Administration is also brand-new. What's worse, it is beginning to look like a typical baseball expansion team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton's bad week at the Capitol brings to mind Casey Stengel, Franklin Roosevelt and Lyndon Johnson. "Can't anybody here play this game?" asked Stengel when he was put in charge of a major league baseball team on which nobody could.</p>
        <p>It was the New York Mets, a brand-new expansion team, that provoked Stengel's cry of anguish. The Clinton Administration is also brand-new. What's worse, it is beginning to look like a typical baseball expansion team.</p>
        <p>That means, in case baseball is not your dish, a comical bunch of greenhorns and tired old-timers who don't win very often. Thus: Because the President couldn't change four votes in the Senate, he lost his economic stimulus program Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The three television reporters I happened to catch pronounced it a "major defeat," and even The New York Times called it "serious." What makes it serious, and possibly even major, is that new Presidents shouldn't lose showdowns like this during their first hundred days.</p>
        <p>This is when a new President ought to be proving he is a winner, somebody you mess with only if you don't mind getting your block knocked off. In the fight over the economic stimulus program, it was the President who got his block knocked off.</p>
        <p>The reason: He couldn't buy four senators. He had 56, which is a majority, but he needed 60 because a Republican filibuster was preventing the Senate from voting, and the quaint Senate rule says a majority isn't enough to squelch a filibuster. It takes 60.</p>
        <p>Which is why Lyndon Johnson comes to mind. Johnson's demonizers have done such a good job blackening his name that people have forgotten he was the last President who understood the science of domestic politics. It is inconceivable that L.B.J. would have accepted a Senate defeat for lack of four votes.</p>
        <p>Without cataloguing Johnson's full line of equipment for changing senatorial minds, I merely point out that the most formidable part of it was knowledge: he knew what every senator most needed, and what every senator most desired.</p>
        <p>And every senator, like every other politician, is a mass of needs and desires, some of which are of absolute urgency, and most of which Presidents can happily fulfill. Or frustrate.</p>
        <p>In "The Best and the Brightest" David Halberstam tells of Frank Church, Senator from Idaho and critic of Johnson's Vietnam policy, meeting with L.B.J., and Johnson asking where Church was getting material for his powerful anti-war speeches. Getting it from Walter Lippmann, the newspaper columnist, said Church.</p>
        <p>And L.B.J. said: Next time you want a new dam out in Idaho, Frank, just ask Walter Lippmann for it.</p>
        <p>Such is a President's power to sway senators' minds once he understands what makes them swayable. Cynics, who are often right anyhow, say that almost everything in politics has its price, including senators.</p>
        <p>It is a graceless way to state the matter, but a President who can't buy a few senators when a few mean the difference between triumph and embarrassment probably didn't do his homework in President's school.</p>
        <p>Which is why Franklin Roosevelt comes to mind, and a story I heard told at a long-ago Washington dinner by Thomas (Tommy the Cork) Corcoran, once one of Roosevelt's bright young men:</p>
        <p>Counting votes on an important bill, F.D.R. was astonished when an adviser warned him that he would have to do a large favor for a distinguished Senator from the cactus belt or lose his vote. Roosevelt observed that he had just recently granted this statesman a considerable boon.</p>
        <p>"How often do we have to buy him?" he asked. And was told: "Every time, Mr. President. Every time."</p>
        <p>What efforts more persuasive than collegial discourse President Clinton may have made to win four crucial senators have not been publicly disclosed. One hesitates to assume there was an attempt to buy a few. The mere suggestion sounds brutally uncouth for an Administration rich in young Ivy League lawyers come to Washington to do good.</p>
        <p>Which brings Franklin Roosevelt again to mind, for he too was surrounded by brilliant young lawyers who, as the old Washington wheeze has it, "came to do good, and stayed to do well." The present crop will do neither unless they learn that senators, even the Republican kind, are as human as the rest of us.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
