<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Important Job, Impossible Position</title>
    <meta content="09POSN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/09/opinion/09posner.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1648535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Intelligence Services</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Posner, Richard A (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Intelligence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Posner, Richard A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD71F3BF93AA35751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Important Job, Impossible Position</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Important Job, Impossible Position</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard A. Posner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Posner, Richard A; Posner, Richard A (Judge)</byline>
      <dateline>Chicago</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Richard A Posner Op-Ed article says Bush administration may be having trouble finding qualified candidate to serve as first director of national intelligence because law that created position does not give director authority to prevent intelligence failures for which he or she will be blamed in event of new attack on US; says intelligence agencies cannot be forced to follow director's policies and guidelines; says director has been give three full-time jobs rather than one</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROBERT M. GATES, a highly regarded former head of the C.I.A., announced last week that he would not leave his job as president of Texas A&amp;M University to become the first director of national intelligence. This is evidence that the Bush administration may be having trouble finding a qualified candidate who is willing to take the job. It is now close to two months since President Bush signed the law that created the position -- almost as long as it took Congress to pass it.</p>
        <p>The delay may be attributable to a fundamental structural defect in the law, a consequence of the haste with which it was passed. The publication last July of the report of the 9/11 commission started a political stampede. Within days both presidential candidates had endorsed most of the commission's recommendations; within weeks there were bills in Congress; within months the president had signed the Intelligence Reform and Terrorism Prevention Act of 2004. The core of the new act, which reflects the commission's principal recommendation, is the creation of the post of director of national intelligence; the director would be the presiding deity of the nation's intelligence system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The difficulty in finding a candidate for the job of U.S. "intelligence czar" may point to a flaw in the job itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROBERT M. GATES, a highly regarded former head of the C.I.A., announced last week that he would not leave his job as president of Texas A&amp;M University to become the first director of national intelligence. This is evidence that the Bush administration may be having trouble finding a qualified candidate who is willing to take the job. It is now close to two months since President Bush signed the law that created the position -- almost as long as it took Congress to pass it.</p>
        <p>The delay may be attributable to a fundamental structural defect in the law, a consequence of the haste with which it was passed. The publication last July of the report of the 9/11 commission started a political stampede. Within days both presidential candidates had endorsed most of the commission's recommendations; within weeks there were bills in Congress; within months the president had signed the Intelligence Reform and Terrorism Prevention Act of 2004. The core of the new act, which reflects the commission's principal recommendation, is the creation of the post of director of national intelligence; the director would be the presiding deity of the nation's intelligence system.</p>
        <p>The beguiling premise of the commission's report was that the 9/11 attacks occurred because there wasn't enough sharing of intelligence data among America's 15 or so federal intelligence agencies. The report's reassuring conclusion is that we can solve the problem by centralizing the control of the intelligence system. The premise is doubtful; only in hindsight do the scattered clues gathered in the summer of 2001 point to the attacks that took place.</p>
        <p>And slotting in a new bureaucracy (the director is authorized a staff of 500) above the existing agencies will not increase information sharing. Instead, by adding a layer to the intelligence hierarchy, it will delay and diminish the flow of information to the president.</p>
        <p>The 9/11 commission wanted the director to be like a corporate chief executive, who is charged with ultimate responsibility for the performance of the corporation's multiple divisions and is given commensurate power. (Hence the term -- though it is not the commission's -- ''intelligence czar.'') As the commission's proposal moved through Congress, however, the director's responsibility waxed and his powers waned. The act piles duties on him but withholds the authority he would need to perform them in the face of predictably recalcitrant bureaucracies.</p>
        <p>He is to be the head of the intelligence community and the president's principal intelligence adviser. He is to prepare a consolidated budget; overhaul the community's personnel, security and technology policies; coordinate the agencies and ensure that information is shared among them; monitor the agencies' performance; interact with foreign nations' intelligence services; and eliminate waste and duplication. So broad is his mandate that should intelligence failures open the way to a new attack on the United States, he will be blamed.</p>
        <p>Yet he has not been given the wherewithal to prevent such failures. He can make a budget, true, but it is subject to the approval of the president and Congress. He can move some money and a few employees among agencies, and he can veto the appointment of some second-tier intelligence officials. But he cannot hire or fire the agency heads and he has no command authority -- that is, he cannot tell an agency what to do. He has much less authority over the intelligence agencies than the secretary of the Homeland Security Department has over the agencies in his purview -- yet after two years, no progress in molding those agencies into an organic unity is discernible.</p>
        <p>In short, the director of national intelligence can issue policies and guidelines to his heart's content. But if the agencies ignore (subvert, ''interpret'') them, he is helpless.</p>
        <p>Well, not quite helpless. For there is that 500-member staff he's been authorized. He can lay it like a blanket of fog over the intelligence community and allow the agencies beneath it to breathe only if they make reciprocal concessions.</p>
        <p>To complete his journey into misery, he has been given three full-time jobs rather than just one. He is to be the president's chief intelligence adviser, responsible for identifying and prioritizing threats to the nation. He is to coordinate the intelligence agencies. And he is to create the office of the director of national intelligence ex nihilo, a task that alone could consume many months.</p>
        <p>To avoid becoming a helpless figurehead -- and a scapegoat if the United States is attacked again on the scale of 9/11, as is entirely possible -- he will have to impose on the act a feasible conception of his role. It should be that of a coordinator or facilitator, albeit one who will not require a staff of 500, who will manage (but with a light hand) the complex and often tense relationships among the intelligence agencies. It should not be that of a substantive intelligence official.</p>
        <p>The director of national intelligence won't be able to do both jobs, and if he chooses the substantive path he will, by treading on the C.I.A. director's turf, invite the kind of bitter conflict that paralyzes government. And then intelligence ''reform'' will have made America less safe.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Richard A. Posner, a judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, is the author of the forthcoming ''Preventing Surprise Attacks: Intelligence Reform in the Wake of 9/11.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard A. Posner, a judge on the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, is the author of the forthcoming ''Preventing Surprise Attacks: Intelligence Reform in the Wake of 9/11.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
