<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Isn't Love, but for Rangel, Peace in Political Family Will Do</title>
    <meta content="09DEMS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/09/nyregion/metrocampaigns/09DEMS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1422322"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Andrew M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rangel, Charles B (Rep)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rangel, Charles B</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCall, H Carl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rangel, Charles B</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCall, H Carl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Cuomo, Andrew M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2DC1F3EF93AA3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Isn't Love, but for Rangel, Peace in Political Family Will Do</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">It Isn't Love, but for Rangel, Peace in Political Family Will Do</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Charles B Rangel played key role in mediating Andrew M Cuomo's withdrawal from Democratic primary for governor in New York in order to unify party behind H Carl McCall; he and other top Democrats did not believe that party could stand another racially charged battle; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles B. Rangel didn't get everything he wanted, though it seemed that way.</p>
        <p>In the end, he could not persuade H. Carl McCall to share the stage with Andrew M. Cuomo for Mr. Cuomo's withdrawal speech last week. ''If the decision were mine,'' Mr. Rangel said, then Mr. McCall would have been there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles B. Rangel's political standing made him one of the few officials who could mediate between the Andrew M. Cuomo and H. Carl McCall camps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charles B. Rangel didn't get everything he wanted, though it seemed that way.</p>
        <p>In the end, he could not persuade H. Carl McCall to share the stage with Andrew M. Cuomo for Mr. Cuomo's withdrawal speech last week. ''If the decision were mine,'' Mr. Rangel said, then Mr. McCall would have been there.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rangel, in his 16th term as a congressman from Harlem, got what he needed, and so did the Democratic Party: a bloodless primary in the race for governor that at least superficially unites the party behind Mr. McCall, the state comptroller.</p>
        <p>The party gets the formality of a primary tomorrow, but one that will bear little resemblance to others -- like the brutal New York City mayoral primary last year or the four-way Senate primary in 1992 -- that left unity in shambles and loyalties scattered just months before the general election.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. McCall has a clear shot as he runs to become the state's first black governor, and Mr. Rangel, Bill Clinton and Hillary Rodham Clinton -- who sent signals that they were leaning toward Mr. McCall despite their stated neutrality -- and Senator Charles E. Schumer, who endorsed Mr. McCall more than a month ago, can all be seen as contributing to keeping the party focused on defeating Gov. George E. Pataki in his re-election bid.</p>
        <p>It is a matter of debate if Mr. Rangel, 72, stepped up or merely filled a void. But indisputably his power and standing as the pre-eminent black politician in the state made him one of the few officials who could mediate between the Cuomo and McCall camps. Upon leaving the race, Mr. Cuomo, who is white, said that to win he would have had to have been more negative, which he said could have created ''racial problems.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo's withdrawal was set in motion by a phone call to Mr. Rangel from one of his supporters, Bill de Blasio, a New York City councilman who managed Mrs. Clinton's Senate campaign, both sides said. Mr. de Blasio, acting on behalf of Mr. Cuomo, told Mr. Rangel that Mr. Cuomo was exploring a graceful exit from the race.</p>
        <p>''I called some of the McCall people and they said find out more info, and I did,'' Mr. Rangel recalled. ''I then called de Blasio back and said they were willing to discuss it; I was authorized to talk.''</p>
        <p>From there, the talks expanded to include top McCall and Cuomo advisers, with Mr. McCall's people saying Mr. Cuomo asked for conditions, like a prominent role in the campaign, and Cuomo partisans saying such ideas were merely floated, not stipulations.</p>
        <p>There is no dispute that Mr. Rangel was seen on both sides as the person with credibility. ''He had an immense amount of personal and positive history with Andrew,'' Mr. de Blasio said. ''He has a particular role and a power that really transcends his party leadership role.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats' state chairman, Assemblyman Herman D. Farrell Jr. of Manhattan, said all along that he would not stand in the way of a primary contest.</p>
        <p>''I still think primaries aren't a bad thing, but I think this was a very good solution,'' said Mr. Farrell, who had publicly endorsed Mr. McCall. ''It's the aftermath of the primary, not the primary themselves, that were the problem.''</p>
        <p>But some Democrats, including Judith Hope, a former chairwoman, suggested the party did not need another bruising primary going into a fight with Mr. Pataki. And they had vivid memories to support their belief.</p>
        <p>The party has been especially haunted by the 1992 Senate primary among Robert Abrams, who was then the state attorney general; Geraldine A. Ferraro; Elizabeth Holtzman, the New York City comptroller; and the Rev. Al Sharpton.</p>
        <p>After winning that bitter four-way fight, Mr. Abrams said recently, ''there was little time'' to heal wounds and raise money to mount a winning campaign against the Republican incumbent, Alfonse M. D'Amato, who had no primary and $20 million and ''a smile like a Cheshire cat after the blood bath was over.''</p>
        <p>The 1992 primary lacked the racial overtones of last year's New York City mayoral or this year's gubernatorial primaries, but Democrats see parallels in the advantage in money and popularity that Mr. Pataki enjoys. His campaign strategy had been largely to hang back while Mr. Cuomo and Mr. McCall went at it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and other top Democrats said they did not the believe the party could withstand another racially charged battle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel had long supported Mr. McCall; they share political roots in the same Harlem Democratic club. And Mr. Rangel tried several times to dissuade Mr. Cuomo, meeting with him several times in the past year.</p>
        <p>Some Cuomo supporters said Mr. Rangel's recent antagonism toward the Cuomo camp hardly paved the way for unity. In recent months Mr. Rangel had criticized Kerry Kennedy Cuomo, Mr. Cuomo's wife, as a lightweight among Kennedys, and at one point suggested he might vote for Mr. Pataki if Mr. McCall lost.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rangel also carried with him the aura of the Clintons -- he had supported Mr. Clinton during impeachment and helped engineer Mrs. Clinton's Senate bid. But often forgotten is his close relationship with Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts and Mr. Cuomo's father, former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, whom Mr. Rangel had supported.</p>
        <p>So, when Mr. Rangel publicly called on Mr. Cuomo to step out of the race two weeks ago, it was taken as more than just trash talk.</p>
        <p>''I think Andrew saw that as a heartfelt and honest message and I think he felt comfortable with having us reach out to Rangel,'' Mr. de Blasio said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel and other people involved in the talks play down the role of the former president -- Mr. Rangel said he first spoke to Mr. Clinton last Monday, the day before Mr. Cuomo's withdrawal. But the negotiations climaxed with Mr. Cuomo, the former federal housing secretary in the Clinton administration, calling Mr. Clinton Tuesday and asking him to attend his concession speech.</p>
        <p>''Cuomo had the opportunity to do what Green's people did and he didn't do it,'' Mr. Rangel said, referring to a television commercial and fliers for Mark Green that supporters of his opponent called racially divisive in the closing weeks of last year's Democratic runoff. ''The difference is somebody dropped a bomb in the Green campaign and that did not happen in the Cuomo campaign.''</p>
        <p>Some Democrats worry that party leaders will use their influence to discourage primaries altogether, especially if they involve minority candidates. But Mr. Rangel and others said that was not the case. ''I don't remember a campaign where we did not have some divisions,'' he said. ''It's just that we have to make the effort to build bridges.''</p>
        <p>Is Mr. Rangel the chief engineer?</p>
        <p>''Longevity allows you to have friendships,'' Mr. Rangel rasped, rattling off all his connections to the varied players in both camps. ''Having said that, we all have to reach out. Hey, let's come together.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
