<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="692024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEFDB173AF934A35755C0A962958260" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALBANY EXPANDS WELFARE FINGERPRINTING</p>
        <p>The Governor and legislative leaders have agreed to expand a contentious program for fingerprinting welfare recipients to a total of 12 New York counties. But top officials said that the plan, part of an evolving deal on the state budget, excludes New York City, where two-thirds of the state's welfare recipients live. A1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALBANY EXPANDS WELFARE FINGERPRINTING</p>
        <p>The Governor and legislative leaders have agreed to expand a contentious program for fingerprinting welfare recipients to a total of 12 New York counties. But top officials said that the plan, part of an evolving deal on the state budget, excludes New York City, where two-thirds of the state's welfare recipients live. A1.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY  MAN KILLS WIFE AS CHILDREN WATCH</p>
        <p>After weeks of quarreling with his wife, Thomas Rodriguez surprised her at the elevator outside her Bronx apartment and fatally shot her as she cradled an infant in her arms, a toddler at her side, the police said. The woman, Joselina Quezada, dropped the infant and collapsed with four shots in her body. Mr. Rodriguez then raised his .38-caliber revolver to his temple and killed himself with a single shot. B3. CITY PUTS U.N. PLAZA HOTEL ON THE BLOCK</p>
        <p>For nearly 20 years the city has owned the glass-and-steel towers above the East River known as the United Nations Plaza Hotel. The four-star hotel, which was given to the city, has turned a profit every year, with the city's share amounting to roughly $1 million. And now the city wants to sell it. B3. 3 FIRES MAY BE WORK OF ARSONIST</p>
        <p>Investigators said that one person may have been responsible for setting three recent fires in lower Manhattan, including a blaze Sunday night in which the authorities said an arsonist deliberately set out to injure firefighters. B3. FIGHT LOOMS OVER PLANS TO CURB SMOKING</p>
        <p>Opening what is likely to be a bitterly fought battle, the tobacco industry began its campaign to challenge proposals that would ban smoking in virtually all public places in the city. B3. POINT MAN IN POLICE REORGANIZATION</p>
        <p>Some police veterans view John F. Timoney's appointment as Chief of Department as symbolic of the new Commissioner's desire to get rid of the old guard. Chief Timoney has been charged with reorganizing the department, including changes in community policing, giving more authority to field commanders and affecting a merger with the Transit Police and Housing Police departments. B4. REGION  GRAND JURY WILL REVIEW CASE</p>
        <p>A grand jury will look into a party attended by the Police Chief of Goshen, N.Y., shortly before he was involved in a car crash and shot himself in the jaw, the Ulster County District Attorney said. Liquor was served at the party, which was sponsored by F.B.I agents and a police chiefs' association. B4. NEWBURGH POLICE CHIEF IN TROUBLE AGAIN</p>
        <p>Skull shaved bare and armed with a badge, Christopher P. Gershel is a dead ringer for Kojak. And like the detective in the 1970's television series, Mr. Gershel, the Police Chief of Newburgh, N.Y., has a knack for flamboyance and speaking his mind. Now he is engaged in a political war that could cost him the job he has held for 14 years. B5. JOB AGENCY HEAD RESIGNS AMID CRITICISM</p>
        <p>The president of the New York State Job Development Authority announced her resignation after the state Inspector General criticized her for spending about $10,000 in agency money on personal expenses like credit card bills. B5. Chronicle B2  Our Towns by Evelyn Nieves B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
