<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Votes in Congress</title>
    <meta content="22VOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030626T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1498957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D7173BF931A15755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Votes in Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tally Last Week in Connecticut, New Jersey and New York.</p>
        <p>Senate</p>
        <p>1. Federal Role: Vote on an amendment to Medicare legislation that would strengthen the role of the federal government in delivering a new prescription drug benefit. The proposed bill would offer new prescription drug coverage to Medicare beneficiaries, but it would be provided, by and large, through private insurers. Rejected 58 to 37, June 18.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tally Last Week in Connecticut, New Jersey and New York.</p>
        <p>Senate</p>
        <p>1. Federal Role: Vote on an amendment to Medicare legislation that would strengthen the role of the federal government in delivering a new prescription drug benefit. The proposed bill would offer new prescription drug coverage to Medicare beneficiaries, but it would be provided, by and large, through private insurers. Rejected 58 to 37, June 18.</p>
        <p>2. Premiums: Vote on an amendment to Medicare legislation to limit the premiums that could be charged for the new prescription drug benefits so that the premiums could not exceed the national average by more than 10 percent. Rejected 56 to 39, June 19.  3. Generic Drugs: Vote on an amendment to Medicare legislation that would give consumers swifter access to low-cost copies of brand-name prescription drugs. Approved 94 to 1, June 19.  4. Prescription Drugs From Canada: Vote on an amendment to Medicare legislation that would allow American pharmacists to buy prescription drugs in Canada, where their prices are lower, and resell them in the United States. Approved 62 to 28, June 20.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Connecticut</p>
        <p>Dodd (D)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Lieberman (D)</p>
        <p>A</p>
        <p>A</p>
        <p>A</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
        <p>Corzine (D)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Lautenberg (D)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>New York</p>
        <p>Clinton (D)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Schumer (D)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>KEY: (A) Absent or did not vote; (P) Present.</p>
        <p>House</p>
        <p>1. Estate Tax: Vote to permanently end the federal estate tax, which is currently scheduled to phase out in 2010 and then revert to its old top rate of 60 percent in 2011. Approved 264 to 163, June 18.</p>
        <p>Connecticut  1. Larson (D): Nay  2. Simmons (R): Yea  3. DeLauro (D): Nay  4. Shays (R): Yea  5. Johnson (R): Nay</p>
        <p>New Jersey  1. Andrews (D): Nay  2. LoBiondo (R): Yea  3. Saxton (R): Yea  4. Smith (R): Yea  5. Garrett (R): Yea  6. Pallone (D): Nay  7. Ferguson (R): Yea  8. Pascrell (D): Nay  9. Rothman (D): Nay  10. Payne (D): Nay  11. Frelinghuysen (R): Yea  12. Holt (D): Nay  13. Menendez (D): Nay</p>
        <p>New York  1. Bishop (D): Nay  2. Israel (D): Yea  3. King (R): Yea  4. McCarthy (D): Yea  5. Ackerman (D): Nay  6. Meeks (D): Nay  7. Crowley (D): Nay  8. Nadler (D): A  9. Weiner (D): Nay  10. Towns (D): Nay  11. Owens (D): Nay  12. Velázquez (D): Nay  13. Fossella (R): Yea  14. Maloney (D): Nay  15. Rangel (D): Nay  16. Serrano (D): Nay  17. Engel (D): Nay  18. Lowey (D): Nay  19. Kelly (R): Yea  20. Sweeney (R): Yea  21. McNulty (D): Nay  22. Hinchey (D): Nay  23. McHugh (R): Yea  24. Boehlert (R): Yea  25. Walsh (R): Yea  26. Reynolds (R): Yea  27. Quinn (R): Yea  28. Slaughter (D): Nay  29. Houghton (R): Nay</p>
        <p>KEY: (A) Absent or did not vote; (P) Present.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 26, 2003, Thursday  The Votes in Congress chart on Sunday gave incorrect positions in some copies for Senators Jon S. Corzine and Frank R. Lautenberg of New Jersey and Hillary Rodham Clinton and Charles E. Schumer of New York on a failed Democratic amendment to a bill creating a Medicare prescription drug benefit. They voted yea, not nay. The amendment would have strengthened the federal government's role in delivering the benefit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 26, 2003, Thursday</p>
        <p>The Votes in Congress chart on Sunday gave incorrect positions in some copies for Senators Jon S. Corzine and Frank R. Lautenberg of New Jersey and Hillary Rodham Clinton and Charles E. Schumer of New York on a failed Democratic amendment to a bill creating a Medicare prescription drug benefit. They voted yea, not nay. The amendment would have strengthened the federal government's role in delivering the benefit.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
