<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Embraces an Author Named Cuomo</title>
    <meta content="20CUOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/08/20/nyregion/20cuomo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1605224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Albany (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cuomo, Mario M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Why Lincoln Matters: Today More Than Ever (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Albany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cuomo, Mario M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D91F3FF933A1575BC0A9629C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Embraces an Author Named Cuomo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Albany Embraces an Author Named Cuomo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Aug. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former New York State Gov Mario Cuomo travels to Albany to promote his new book Why Lincoln Matters: Today More Than Ever; trip is also long-awaited homecoming; Cuomo has never returned to Capitol since he lost governorship in 1994; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frank M. Calabria clutched the two books on his lap as if they were live rabbits. He and his wife were seated outside a bookstore in the shopping concourse under the Capitol, waiting for the day's featured author to arrive for a midday book signing.</p>
        <p>They had been planning this trip from their home in Schenectady, N.Y., for a week. ''I saw it in the paper,'' Mr. Calabria, 79, said Thursday. ''My eyes nearly bugged out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Gov. Mario Cuomo was in Albany to promote his book, but the trip was also something of a long-awaited, if reluctant, homecoming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frank M. Calabria clutched the two books on his lap as if they were live rabbits. He and his wife were seated outside a bookstore in the shopping concourse under the Capitol, waiting for the day's featured author to arrive for a midday book signing.</p>
        <p>They had been planning this trip from their home in Schenectady, N.Y., for a week. ''I saw it in the paper,'' Mr. Calabria, 79, said Thursday. ''My eyes nearly bugged out.''</p>
        <p>The author was running late -- by about half an hour -- and neither the publisher's representative nor the bookstore owner knew where he was, though they knew he could not possibly be lost.</p>
        <p>Their tardy charge was former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, for whom this place was once his estate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo was in town to promote his book ''Why Lincoln Matters: Today More Than Ever,'' but the trip was also something of a long-awaited, if reluctant, homecoming. During his 12 years in office, he was famous for never leaving Albany. But since his defeat by George E. Pataki in 1994, he had mostly stayed away, and had never returned to the Capitol. The crowd outside the Book Outlet, which numbered about 200, included former staffers and current government workers, who lent the event the air of a family reunion. Even for those who had never met him, feelings bordered on the intimate.</p>
        <p>''Cuomo has always been an inspiration,'' said Mr. Calabria, a retired psychology professor who was holding a copy of Mr. Cuomo's book as well as his own autobiography to give to the governor. ''Beyond his eloquence, it's his integrity. He's certainly engaged me back in the political arena, especially with this election. I'm pretty fired up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo finally arrived at 12:10; he had been holding court in the offices of the legislative reporters, telling stories and talking about the presidential campaign, the death penalty, the dysfunction of the Legislature and his belief that a constitutional convention could fix it.</p>
        <p>As he ambled into view of the gathering throng, the concourse thundered with applause. Mr. Cuomo, dressed in a black suit and patterned gray tie, hugged his former secretaries and hailed old colleagues.</p>
        <p>Then he got down to the business of the day: signing books and being the famously garrulous Mario Cuomo, chatting with everyone -- about politics, growing up in Queens, common acquaintances, bocce.</p>
        <p>One fan brought him a panoramic photograph of Yankee Stadium. Another showed him two photographs of her brother, who had played basketball with Mr. Cuomo when they were young men living in Queens. Three hours later, with his former secretary, Pamela Ulmer Broughton, tugging on his arm -- they were running late for a luncheon, followed by another signing at a bookstore across town -- Mr. Cuomo signed the last of about 275 books.</p>
        <p>Later, as he ambled through the gilded halls of the Capitol while Ms. Broughton and the publisher's representative sprinted ahead to corral the limousine driver, Mr. Cuomo, 72, who is now a lawyer in New York, reflected on his years in elected office and the changes he encountered during this trip to Albany. (Before Thursday's visit, Mr. Cuomo had been in Albany only twice since attending Governor Pataki's inauguration in 1995: to make a speech to a librarians' group, and to testify in a friend's lawsuit. He made this latest trip only at the insistence of local booksellers and his publisher.)</p>
        <p>''It brings back a lot of memories, not all of them pleasant,'' he admitted. He added, self-deprecatingly, ''It's nostalgia.''</p>
        <p>Albany has become more famous in recent years for gridlock than for governing. The Legislature that just passed the latest budget in state history was rated the worst in America by the Brennan Center for Justice at New York University School of Law. Even the landmark hotel where he stayed as a young lawyer in 1956 was crumbling, closing a major street to traffic and leading the mayor of Albany to consider demolishing it. ''They said it was going to be renovated and instead they let it die,'' Mr. Cuomo grumbled.</p>
        <p>But he went out of his way to be magnanimous toward his successor and told reporters he thought a logical next step for Mr. Pataki would be to seek the presidency.</p>
        <p>He allowed that he missed governing. The visit had reawakened something dormant in him.</p>
        <p>''Coming back, it's a little bit like going back on the baseball field,'' he said. ''You remember all the fun you had, all the games, all the big victories, all the heartbreak, and you wish you could play one more game. You think, wouldn't it be great if I could get in that batter's box one more time?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
