<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Battle: A Soviet Portrait</title>
    <meta content="31GOLD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Vicki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khaldei, Yevgeny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD6173DF932A05752C0A961958260" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Battle: A Soviet Portrait</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICKI GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Vicki</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicki Goldberg reviews exhibit A Witness to History: Yevgeny Khaldei, Soviet Photojournalist at Jewish Museum, NYC; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE look of war, the face it wears back home, changes for reasons beyond technology and strategy. World War I was a deluge of blood and death, but censorship kept it from appearing that way in the papers. Photographs and paintings of World War II grew more fierce and explicit, though for a long while whatever horrors were represented had been visited on our enemies alone.</p>
        <p>That war also saw photographic attention shift a bit toward civilians and the ruinous effects of combat on their lives. This was not a new subject, only newly important. Like other aspects of that conflict, it had had a trial run during the Spanish Civil War, when Robert Capa registered war's inhumanity in the plight of noncombatants threatened for the first time by aerial bombardment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE look of war, the face it wears back home, changes for reasons beyond technology and strategy. World War I was a deluge of blood and death, but censorship kept it from appearing that way in the papers. Photographs and paintings of World War II grew more fierce and explicit, though for a long while whatever horrors were represented had been visited on our enemies alone.</p>
        <p>That war also saw photographic attention shift a bit toward civilians and the ruinous effects of combat on their lives. This was not a new subject, only newly important. Like other aspects of that conflict, it had had a trial run during the Spanish Civil War, when Robert Capa registered war's inhumanity in the plight of noncombatants threatened for the first time by aerial bombardment.</p>
        <p>Capa usually gets prime credit for turning the world's eyes ever more often to events off the battlefield. The shift was widespread, either because World War II was more purposefully directed against civilians than previous wars or because the press was already so global that ideas passed from country to country by osmosis. Soviet photographers, too, focused their lenses on the side effects and aftermath of war.</p>
        <p>Yevgeny Khaldei, a leading photojournalist whose work from 1941 to 1946 is now on view at the Jewish Museum, followed the war as both combat lieutenant and photographer for Tass, the Soviet news agency. Yet only one image in the show, ''A Witness to History: Yevgeny Khaldei, Soviet Photojournalist,'' the first major exhibition of his work in the United States, was taken during actual combat. Susan T. Goodman, chief curator of the museum and the organizer of the show, had access to Mr. Khaldei's archive and says the selection on display reflects the general tenor of the work. Perhaps Mr. Khaldei was too busy fighting to concentrate on the appearance of the maelstrom while he was in the middle of it. Unlike American correspondents, who were not permitted to carry arms, Soviet photojournalists could and did shoot with both gun and camera.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khaldei, now 79 years old, is best known for an image that has achieved fame far beyond his own country: ''Raising the Flag Over the Reichstag, May 2, 1945.'' It is a stunning version of a stunning moment, as a Soviet soldier raises the billowing flag over the seat of Nazi Government and the smoldering capital, while stone figures of Germany's past glories look on from the roofline. Nearly 20 million Soviets had died in World War II; the raising of the flag in Berlin was a national (and worldwide) symbol of triumph, justice, revenge. And Mr. Khaldei did not just  memorialize this symbolic moment: he created it.</p>
        <p>Men have long raised national flags as signs of conquest; so far as we know, an American flag remains where Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong planted it on the moon. Mr. Khaldei had seen Joe Rosenthal's photograph from Iwo Jima, ''Old Glory Goes Up on Mount Suribachi,'' and knew what he wanted to photograph. After the Soviet Army reached Berlin, he rushed to Moscow, but in that war-torn capital no flags were to be found. He remembered that Tass used red tablecloths and convinced his uncle, a tailor, to stay up all night sewing hammers and sickles and stars on red cloths meant for diners.</p>
        <p>Back in Berlin, Mr. Khaldei crossed the burning city, took three soldiers with him up the bloody Reichstag steps, and directed them into positions to mark one of the great victories of the 20th century. He took a whole roll of film, flew to Moscow the next night, and saw the picture published immediately.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khaldei is probably the only photographer ever to arrange for, choreograph and then record such a significant event. (The museum's wall labels repeat a common error: that Rosenthal staged the Iwo Jima picture. He did not.) Tass proceeded to manipulate the Soviet document yet again. The lower soldier had a watch on each wrist, which officials thought made him look like a criminal; one had to be removed in the negative. Mr. Khaldei himself later played around with clouds and smoke to change the drama quotient. Even history is not always what it seems.</p>
        <p>History in Mr. Khaldei's photographs could be wrenching, poignant and surprising, and the museum labels that quote his recollections amplify the power of his images. He photographed Soviet women who were pilots and snipers; Jews suddenly freed from ghettos; people carting a bit of this and a bit of that out of bombed-out homes; Nazi officials who murdered their families and then committed suicide rather than fall into Soviet hands.</p>
        <p>He photographed handsome young Soviet men and women in bathing suits happily taking the sun before the liberated, devastated remnants of Sevastopol. In Berlin in 1945, he found a blind man and his guide sitting amid rubble. He recalled speaking to them: ''Where are you coming from? They did not know. Where are you going? That, too, they did not know. They had arrived at the end of the world.''</p>
        <p>He took another photograph revered and remembered by millions, but only in his own country: a moment in the victory parade in Red Square on June 24, 1945, when hundreds of servicemen holding captured Nazi banners tilted them down to the ground before Stalin and other leaders. Bold as this image and others were, Mr. Khaldei remained virtually unknown abroad for decades during the cold war, though he had covered 1,481 days of World War II as well as major conferences and the Nuremberg trials afterward. War pictures appeared without attribution in the Soviet Union, but that was scarcely unique. Today in the United States, many photographs are still published with the name of an agency but not of an individual.</p>
        <p>Back in 1945, Mr. Khaldei's abilities were recognized by Robert Capa, who was so appalled to see such meager equipment that he procured a better camera for his Soviet counterpart. In fact, that meager equipment had taken some eloquent images. The person behind the camera really counts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khaldei's personal history traces the sad path of a Ukrainian Jew. Born in 1917, he was in his mother's arms when she was killed in a pogrom in 1918. The bullet passed through her body and gravely wounded Yevgeny, who survived and later learned to live on grass during the Soviet famines. His father and sisters were killed in a Nazi massacre of Russian Jews during World War II.</p>
        <p>In 1948, he was dismissed by Tass, probably because of resurgent anti-Semitism, and barely scraped by. Later he worked for the newspaper Pravda, which dismissed him in 1972 when official anti-Semitism was once more on the rise. He continued working as a photojournalist wherever he could until he retired in 1991. He now receives a Government pension equal to $35 a month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khaldei, whose photographs of victory have a mythic quality, had personally experienced the effectiveness of wartime myths. When the Germans invaded in 1941, he went into the field for Tass with a mere 160 feet of film because his editor was convinced that Germany would be defeated within two weeks. In 1945, he photographed Germans watching the arrival of Soviet tanks in Berlin. A woman asked him whose tanks those were, and when he told her they were Russian, she said that couldn't be so, because Goebbels, the German propaganda minister, had said the Russians would never make it to Berlin. ''Who do you think I am?'' he asked -- and then she understood. The old belief, the big lie so cherished by the Nazis, at last made way for an overwhelming reality.</p>
        <p>''A Witness to History: Yevgeny Khaldei, Soviet Photojournalist'' remains at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92d Street, through April 13. ''Russia in Black and White: The Photojournalism of Yevgeny Khaldei,'' will be at the Jewish Museum San Francisco from Feb. 24 to July 17.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
