<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brabham-Nissan Team Earns a Timeout to Bask</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="168684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="AUTO RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILE RACING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NISSAN MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POTTER, STEVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRABHAM, GEOFF</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3DD1526E133BC4053DFBE6E958A" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brabham-Nissan Team Earns a Timeout to Bask</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POTTER, STEVE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: This is an open weekend on the International Motor Sports Association's Camel GT sports car racing circuit, and with one exception all of the teams that contest the races are breathing a collective sigh of relief and using the spare time trying to figure out how to coax more speed out of their cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: This is an open weekend on the International Motor Sports Association's Camel GT sports car racing circuit, and with one exception all of the teams that contest the races are breathing a collective sigh of relief and using the spare time trying to figure out how to coax more speed out of their cars.</p>
        <p>This is an open weekend on the International Motor Sports Association's Camel GT sports car racing circuit, and with one exception all of the teams that contest the races are breathing a collective sigh of relief and using the spare time trying to figure out how to coax more speed out of their cars.</p>
        <p>That one exception is the Electramotive team of El Segundo, Calif., whose driver, Geoff Brabham, drove the team's Nissan GTP ZX Turbo to his seventh straight Camel race victory last weekend at Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>That feat established a record for consecutive victories in America's top road-racing series, stretched Brabham's existing lead in the drivers' championship point standing, and vaulted Nissan into the lead in the manufacturers' title standing. Unheralded Reputation</p>
        <p>The 1988 Camel GT season wasn't supposed to turn out like this. At the beginning of the year the Electramotive team, which is headed by Don Devendorf, an electronics engineer with Hughes Aircraft, had won only one race in the three previous seasons, and their Nissan racer - the only one on the circuit - had developed a reputation for occasional speed and poor reliability.</p>
        <p>At most, pit insiders figured, the Nissan might find its way to the winners' circle once or twice during the 16-event campaign.</p>
        <p>Porsche, the West German automaker whose cars had taken the title in 14 of the last 15 seasons, expected a tough fight this year. But it was supposed to come from the British luxury car manufacturer, Jaguar, which had sent its 1987 world championship-winning Tom Walkinshaw Racing team to North America. Jubilation in Jaguar Camp</p>
        <p>Walkinshaw, a Scot who runs his transportation and racing businesses in a fashion reminiscent of America's Roger Penske, established a branch of his team in Valpariso, Ind., and furnished it with a trio of V12-powered Jaguar XJR-9 prototype racers.</p>
        <p>The season-opening Daytona 24-hour race has been a long-time preserve for the reliable Porsche cars, and was expected to be Jaguar's toughest challenge. When the red, white and green Castrol-sponsored cars finished first and third, there was jubilation in the Jaguar camp.</p>
        <p>Porsches won the next two races, but the Electramotive team had stayed home, victim to budget constraints that ruled out racing in the expensive Daytona and Sebring endurance tests. The British optimism and German hope have turned to gloom as the Electramotive team, which receives its financing from Nissan, has swept to victory in every race since. Promoting Equality</p>
        <p>It is I.M.S.A.'s stated policy to promote equality of competition among different types of power plants, including the turbocharged Nissan, Porsche and Ford, and the nonturbocharged Jaguar, Chevrolet and Pontiac engines.</p>
        <p>There has been some dissatisfaction with the sanctioning body's rule-making, principally from Jaguar. ''It has become increasingly clear that this continues to be a series for turbocharged engines,'' a Jaguar executive, Mike Dale, said last month as Brabham's Nissan was heading to its fourth triumph at Watkins Glen.</p>
        <p>But Price Cobb, who drives for the best-placed Porsche team in the championship chase, Dyson Racing, says that it is in the corners, not on the straightaways, that the Nissan shows an advantage. At Watkins Glen the figures seemed to bear him out; the Nissan's velocity through the radar speed trap was 10 miles per hour slower than its closest competitors. 'Stop Crying and Work Harder'</p>
        <p>''It's just a lot of complaining on their part,'' said Brabham, an Australian who is the son of a three-time Formula One world driving champion. ''If we really had so much horsepower we'd be fast through the corners and still fastest on the straights. I think the Jaguar people ought to stop crying and work harder on racing.''</p>
        <p>Brabham is realistic about the victory streak. ''We're not going to win all the rest of the races,'' he said after Watkins Glen. But he has won two more since then. And when Electramotive entered a second car at Portland for John Morton, Brabham's usual co-driver in the longer races, that car finished second.</p>
        <p>At Sears Point, in Sonoma, Calif., next weekend, where there will again be a second Nissan entered, it will be hard to find a lot of other people who don't see the Brabham-Nissan combination as invincible.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
