<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vivid Color In a World Of Black And White</title>
    <meta content="28COLO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/28/arts/28COLO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1288803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Batchelor, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boxer, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chromophobia (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wizard of Oz, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kansas</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Berlin</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hamburg</location>
        <location class="online_producer">ellsworth</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Klein, Yves</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wittgenstein, Ludwig</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Kandinsky, Wassily</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Stella, Frank</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Rauschenberg, Robert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Judd, Donald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Flavin, Dan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DA1039F93BA15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vivid Color In a World Of Black And White</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BOXER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boxer, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Boxer comment on David Batchelor's premise, expressed in new book Chromophobia, that color has always been subordinate to line in Western culture; book gives examples from art and architecture, and from movie The Wizard of Oz, in which Dorothy drifts into brilliant Technolor world but home is Kansas in black and white; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Yellow,'' a book of short stories, ''Blue,'' a novel, and ''Mauve,'' a book about the invention of a color, have all just been published. A few years ago, Alexander Theroux wrote ''Secondary Colors'' and, before that, ''Primary Colors.'' There is William Gass's ''On Being Blue'' and the Polish director Krzysztof Kieslowski's trilogy of films, ''Blue'' (1993), ''White'' and ''Red'' (both 1994). This month the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History put up an exhibition of paint-by-number paintings.</p>
        <p>You probably couldn't guess from all this that the Western world is plagued by chromophobia, the fear and loathing of color. But according to David Batchelor's new book ''Chromophobia'' (Reaktion Books, 2000), it is.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Yellow,'' a book of short stories, ''Blue,'' a novel, and ''Mauve,'' a book about the invention of a color, have all just been published. A few years ago, Alexander Theroux wrote ''Secondary Colors'' and, before that, ''Primary Colors.'' There is William Gass's ''On Being Blue'' and the Polish director Krzysztof Kieslowski's trilogy of films, ''Blue'' (1993), ''White'' and ''Red'' (both 1994). This month the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History put up an exhibition of paint-by-number paintings.</p>
        <p>You probably couldn't guess from all this that the Western world is plagued by chromophobia, the fear and loathing of color. But according to David Batchelor's new book ''Chromophobia'' (Reaktion Books, 2000), it is.</p>
        <p>In Western culture, color has always been subordinate to line. Whenever the two are discussed together, color is put down, linked with ''the feminine, the oriental, the primitive, the infantile, the vulgar,'' Mr. Batchelor writes. And when color is not denigrated that way, he says, it is ''relegated to the realm of the superficial, the supplementary, the inessential or the cosmetic.''</p>
        <p>Take the ''The Wizard of Oz.'' As Mr. Batchelor writes, ''this movie's great set piece is a spectacular descent into brilliant Technicolor.'' Dorothy's ''drift into color'' is ''a result of her fall into unconsciousness.'' She tumbles out of the black and white Kansas sky into the colorful world of ruby slippers, yellow brick roads and green Oz. But home is black and white Kansas. And there's no place like it.</p>
        <p>The same thing happened to the architect Le Corbusier in ''Journey to the East,'' where he writes of giving ''way to the slow intoxication of the fantastic glazes, the bursts of yellows, the velvet tones of the blues'' in the East before he finally returns to his rational senses, sees the Acropolis, declares that color is ''suited to simple races, peasants and savages'' and vows to ''crusade for whitewash.''</p>
        <p>The art historian Bernard Berenson, whom Mr. Batchelor calls the ''chromophobe's chromophobe,'' declared that line, not color, carries the ideas of a work of art. To look at medieval stained glass without its architectural skeleton, Berenson said, is ''not so different from the Rajah's gloating over handfuls of emeralds, rubies and other precious stones.''</p>
        <p>Who came up with the idea that black and white line is high-minded and homey, while color belongs to an exotic, druggy dreamland? Apparently, Plato.</p>
        <p>In ''The Eloquence of Color'' (University of California, 1993), Jacqueline Lichtenstein points out that Plato attacked color painting for the same reason that he attacked rhetoric. He associated both with ''makeup and polish and clothes.'' He saw them as ''ornaments'' that obstruct truth. For Plato, Ms. Lichtenstein writes, color painting has ''all the contradictory qualities of the pharmakon,'' a ''magic and maleficent'' drug that is both a remedy and a poison. Color colors the truth.</p>
        <p>Aristotle picked up the chromophobic flag in ''The Poetics.'' There he argued that in drama character is subservient to plot the way that in painting color is subservient to form. As Aristotle put it, ''a random distribution of the most attractive colors would never yield as much pleasure as a definite image without color.'' In the Renaissance, the Aristotelian opposition of line and color -- of disegno and colore -- and the favoritism of line over color were born again.</p>
        <p>Even the word ''color'' contains a slight against it, Mr. Batchelor suggests. ''The Latin colorem is related to celare, to hide or conceal; in Middle English 'to colour' is to embellish or adorn, to disguise, to render specious or plausible, to misrepresent.''</p>
        <p>And the charge of superficiality is only part of the culture's case against color. Color is equally disliked and distrusted for its unfathomable, undefinable depths. Color has often been described as belonging to a primitive world that was here before language or line and that cannot be tamed by it.</p>
        <p>For many painters, this is part of color's appeal. Mr. Batchelor writes, for instance, that Cézanne, who thought that the painter's task was ''to imagine the world as it was before it had been converted into a network of concepts and objects,'' tried to see and paint the world in ''patches of color.'' As Debora Silverman writes in ''Van Gogh and Gauguin,'' (Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 2000), Gauguin used unnatural colors to ''navigate across the divide of the natural and supernatural,'' and van Gogh used them to ''say consoling things'' that couldn't be said with words.</p>
        <p>In 1954, the painter Yves Klein imagined the world of color as a primeval place. He drew up a storyboard for an animated film about the ''war between line and color,'' Mr. Batchelor writes. Before the war, Klein imagined, there was a color paradise, ''a remote and original state of being'' that had no lines. Klein, a chromophile, believed that ''we have fallen out of color and into line, writing and language.''</p>
        <p>But color's primitivism and exoticism, Mr. Batchelor suggests, may also explain the culture's grudge against it. The problem is that color eludes language and culture. While lines collude in language (written language, after all, is made up of lines), color has always remained beyond the powerful, organizing grip of language. Words have never been able to capture the experience of color.</p>
        <p>It is not for want of trying. As John Gage writes in ''Color and Culture'' (Bulfinch, 1993), countless attempts have been made to systematize language about color: color wheels, color spheres, color spectrums.</p>
        <p>Ludwig Wittgenstein spent the last 18 months of his life asking questions like these: ''What does it mean to say that 'Brown is akin to yellow'?'' ''To what extent can we compare black and white to yellow, red and blue, and to what extent can't we?'' ''What advantage would someone have over me who knew a direct route from blue to yellow?'' In these questions, collected posthumously in ''Remarks on Color,'' Wittgenstein looks for some logical order, some hierarchy within the world of color.</p>
        <p>In 1969, Brent Berlin and Paul Kay, after comparing the color words from 98 languages, ''proposed a model for the universal development of color-vocabularies,'' Mr. Gage writes. From this they created a hierarchy of colors. Black and white are most basic, followed by red. Then comes either green or yellow, then blue and brown, and finally purple, pink, orange and gray.</p>
        <p>Even some painters have tried to make sense of colors by equating them with other things. Philipp Otto Runge, a painter from Hamburg, linked different colors with different times of day. Franz Marc, following Goethe's color theory, gave colors gender (yellow is female, blue is male). And Wassily Kandinsky, a synesthete, wed certain colors to certain sounds.</p>
        <p>But despite all attempts to organize color, color has remained unruly. So, Mr. Batchelor suggests, maybe the way out of chromophobia is to keep language and color apart. ''The obvious thing to say is that color speaks silently for itself in art, and that any attempt to speak on its behalf is bound to fail.''</p>
        <p>That was the revelation of the 1960's. In 1964, Mr. Batchelor writes, the painter Frank Stella articulated ''an entirely new conception of color'' that freed it from line and language. He quoted a friend joking about the Abstract Expressionists: ''They would be good painters if they could only keep the paint as good as it is in the can.'' Then Stella added: ''And that is what I tried to do. I tried to keep the paint as good as it was in the can.''</p>
        <p>In the 1960's, Mr. Batchelor argues, artists started thinking that the colors they were using, especially those synthetically produced, were more interesting than anything that could be done with them. Robert Rauschenberg painted monochromes. Gerhard Richter and Ellsworth Kelly did color-chart paintings. Andy Warhol reveled in the superficiality and artificiality of color with his portraits of Marilyn and Jackie and in his series of paint-by-number, or do-it-yourself, pictures. Donald Judd made works of colored plastic, and Dan Flavin used colored lights.</p>
        <p>Now the art world is shiny with colored plastics, colored house paints, colored lights and computerized colors. Color is wriggling free from line, and free from chromophobia. It is the victory of ''impurism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
