<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Orleans Mayor Thrives on Lower Crime and Lifted Spirit</title>
    <meta content="Y17MOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Marc Morial</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morial, Marc (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DF173FF934A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="1683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Orleans Mayor Thrives on Lower Crime and Lifted Spirit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Feb. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Orleans Mayor Marc Morial is enjoying surge in popularity, winning 93 percent of black vote in bid for second term and 43 percent of white vote; popularity attributed to lowering of city's legendary crime rate, making city safer place to live, as well as to improved economic conditions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the B. W. Cooper housing project, where politics and bullets alter lives, Marc Morial's performance as a mayor can be measured, quite literally, with a yardstick.</p>
        <p>Here, as in other inner-city New Orleans neighborhoods, some worried mothers routinely had children sleep on the floor to protect them from stray bullets. Now, say people who live here, more of them sleep in their beds and even venture outside, with less risk, less fear.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the B. W. Cooper housing project, where politics and bullets alter lives, Marc Morial's performance as a mayor can be measured, quite literally, with a yardstick.</p>
        <p>Here, as in other inner-city New Orleans neighborhoods, some worried mothers routinely had children sleep on the floor to protect them from stray bullets. Now, say people who live here, more of them sleep in their beds and even venture outside, with less risk, less fear.</p>
        <p>A lot of dignity is gained, in the distance of a few feet.</p>
        <p>''I see people coming out more; they're not on the floor as much,'' said Donna Johnigan, who lives in the neighborhood. She credits Mr. Morial's reform of the legendarily corrupt Police Department, and the fact that he actually seems to care whether the people here live or die, with making it a safer place to live.</p>
        <p>''There's not a time we call him for a meeting that he doesn't come,'' Ms. Johnigan said. ''He's there and he listens. That means everything to poor people.''</p>
        <p>With loyal support from such poor pockets in this majority black city -- Mr. Morial, a Democrat, won 93 percent of the black vote in his re-election here last week -- it was no wonder that this 40-year-old black Mayor's run for a second term was more like an evening stroll along the Mississippi riverfront.</p>
        <p>But what is remarkable, as the demographics of his easy re-election have become clear, is how much support he pulled from all colors and economic corners of what had come to be seen as a city in trouble, especially in influential white communities and business circles that were, historically, color-conscious.</p>
        <p>Combine that history-making white support -- he drew an estimated 43 percent of the white vote this time, almost five times the 9 percent that he won four years ago -- with that almost blanket support among black people, and the painfully neat, highly starched and smooth-talking Mr. Morial finds himself with the widest and deepest mandate in this contentious city in four decades. Almost 9 out of 10 people who bothered to vote, voted for him.</p>
        <p>''This city was in the prone position,'' said Mr. Morial, who ran nonstop in the last four years not only to put in place programs to protect the people most at risk but also to rebuild this city's battered, bullet-riddled image as a dangerous place to live and visit. ''It was like a patient and the family was sitting around, trying to decide whether to pull the plug. It was plagued by this coffee table rhetoric of, 'I'm frightened, I'm getting out.' Well, you don't hear that anymore.''</p>
        <p>Not even his legendary father, Dutch Morial, a two-term Mayor, ever had anything close to his son's mandate. The city's government now includes only friendly faces -- people Marc Morial supported -- on the City Council.</p>
        <p>Mayor Morial's political coattails, at first suspect in an election in which he was confronted by two political unknowns, proved powerful enough to unseat a last significant nemesis, Councilwoman Peggy Wilson, a Republican. It is a long way from past races in which even token white candidates carried a huge white majority.</p>
        <p>Times, from an improving economy to a significantly reduced crime rate, are just too good. And while some will argue that national trends have as much or more to do with that as anything Mr. Morial has done, others say no, he can take a bow. His re-election bid did not draw one single serious challenger.</p>
        <p>Bill Metcalf, chairman-elect of the New Orleans Chamber of Commerce and publisher of New Orleans Daily Business, endorsed him this time, but had not done so in 1993, when Mr. Morial defeated a white candidate, Donald Mintz, in what turned out to be an ugly, racially charged campaign.</p>
        <p>''I was not sure if Marc Morial had the fire in his belly,'' Mr. Metcalf said. ''I was wrong.''</p>
        <p>The fact is, Mr. Morial has been good for business.</p>
        <p>The city's most destructive demon was its image. From front page stories in national newspapers to vivid images on national televison, it was one of runaway crime: people murdered in armed robberies outside popular restaurants; bullets fired into the air that killed tourists when they came down; a Miss Louisiana carjacked.</p>
        <p>And there was nothing being done about it, because, residents here say, the police were committing some of the most soul-killing of those crimes: a police officer murdered her own partner and two young Vietnamese immigrants in a robbery; an officer ordered the contract killing of a woman who reported his drug dealing to Internal Affairs; officers were caught in a sting in which they were hired to guard a warehouse of drugs.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Johnigan said her crime-ridden neighborhood went virtually unprotected.</p>
        <p>People there were ''tired of burying our children every day,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Any resurrection of New Orleans had to begin with the Police Department. Mr. Morial brought in Richard Pennington, a veteran with the Washington force, to serve as police chief.</p>
        <p>Higher standards were established for officers, and a new ''public integrity'' unit replaced the comically ineffective Internal Affairs division.</p>
        <p>But for the poorer people of New Orleans, it was the simple installation of mini-precincts in the housing projects themselves that began, immediately, to save lives.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Morial took office in 1994, there were 425 killings in New Orleans, such an amazing rate in a city of about 484,000 people that National Geographic magazine dispatched a reporter to chronicle the city's culture of death.</p>
        <p>But by 1996, that number had fallen to 350. And by the end of 1997, it had dropped again, this time to 266. That means that in Mr. Morial's first term, the murder rate fell about 38 percent.</p>
        <p>From 1996 to 1997, the city's violent crime rate -- murder, rape, armed robbery and assault -- fell 24 percent.</p>
        <p>''People trust the police force a lot more than they used to,''said James Wright, a sociologist at Tulane University here.</p>
        <p>Such declines in violent crime were also seen in other major cities, but experts on crime, as well as the people who endured it here, said that Mr. Morial was not just the beneficiary of a national trend.</p>
        <p>''You can argue that he was in the right place at the right time, but he made some very visible decisions that panned out,'' said Wayne Parent, a political science professor at Louisiana State University in Baton Rouge.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morial's critics, and they are largely quiet now, say there is a danger in his popularity. Some of them jokingly call him ''the czar.'' A political cartoon in The Times-Picayune here recently showed the new City Council as just a row of Morials.</p>
        <p>Some politicians who have been adversely affected by Mr. Morial's popularity have even accused his political organization of stealing one election. When Mary L. Landrieu, a Democrat, defeated Louis (Woody) Jenkins, a Republican, for a United States Senate seat, Mr. Jenkins attributed his loss to Ms. Landrieu's connection to Mr. Morial and voter fraud. A Senate panel found some irregularities but none that warranted reversing the outcome.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morial has always been one of the crown princes of this city, a lawyer whose father, often at odds with the white establishment, served as mayor from 1978 to 1986 and is one of its political legends. But Mr. Morial's popularity has eclipsed his father's.</p>
        <p>He has not so much evaded scandal as he has just ignored it.</p>
        <p>He has never been married, but has a 16-year-old daughter, Kemmah, whom he calls his ''shining light.'' Efforts by political foes to use that against him have fallen flat.</p>
        <p>In the previous election, news reports -- which he denied -- that he had once been admitted to a hospital for an emergency related to cocaine use never seemed to hurt him.</p>
        <p>''The scandals were highly publicized, and he still won,'' said Ed Renwick, a political science professor at Loyola University.</p>
        <p>In this most recent election, his popularity just buried any hint of scandal, Mr. Renwick said, adding, ''It was never mentioned.''</p>
        <p>But now, as Mr. Morial ponders his future in a state that has been unashamedly racial, and some would say racist, in its attitudes, the young, wildly popular Mayor must wonder if his political career is at an end.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to step from New Orleans to Louisiana as a whole,'' said Mr. Parent, the Louisiana State professor. ''He would have to confront the politics of race.''</p>
        <p>Other political scientists say it is all but impossible for Mr. Morial to win a statewide race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morial is painfully realistic.</p>
        <p>''New Orleans has evolved,'' he said, giving him the greatest mandate since 1961, when Victor Schiro drew 81 percent of the vote against a virtually unknown Republican. ''I think the South has evolved. How far is hard to say.''</p>
        <p>He could wind up in a President's Cabinet -- he is that popular, too, among national Democrats. Or he could pull off something his father never could, and, with the weight of that popularity, force a change in the way the city elects its mayors.</p>
        <p>Now, there is a two-term limit. He concedes that it is possible that he could try to change the city's charter and extend his career as Mayor for a few more years. Surveys have shown that, if he asks, a majority of voters would support such a change.</p>
        <p>''Otherwise, his options are limited,'' Mr. Parent said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
