<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Years After Beating Outside Nightclub, a Trial Is Set to Begin</title>
    <meta content="17OFFE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westhampton Beach (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcquiston, John T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Offen, Austin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daniels, Shane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chronis, Constantine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DE173FF934A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Years After Beating Outside Nightclub, a Trial Is Set to Begin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcquiston, John T</byline>
      <dateline>RIVERHEAD, N.Y., Feb. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jury selection is set to begin in trial of Austin Offen, charged with attempted murder and assault in near-fatal May 1996 beating of Shane Daniels, black man, outside Long Island nightclub; Constantine Chronis, who was New York City police officer at time of incident, will be tried separately on charges of official misconduct and menacing; trials were delayed because of efforts by Suffolk County District Attorney's office to have both defendants tried together; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly two years ago, an off-duty New York City police officer and a drinking companion became involved in a brawl in the parking lot of a Long Island nightclub that ended in the near-fatal beating of a young black man.</p>
        <p>The brutality of the attack, and the suspected involvement of the two defendants, both of whom are white,  drew widespread attention to the case. But a protracted legal battle over whether the two men should be tried together delayed their trials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly two years ago, an off-duty New York City police officer and a drinking companion became involved in a brawl in the parking lot of a Long Island nightclub that ended in the near-fatal beating of a young black man.</p>
        <p>The brutality of the attack, and the suspected involvement of the two defendants, both of whom are white,  drew widespread attention to the case. But a protracted legal battle over whether the two men should be tried together delayed their trials.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, however, jury selection is scheduled to begin for one of the defendants, Austin Offen, a 27-year-old weight lifter from Floral Park, Queens, who is charged with attempted murder, assault and criminal possession of a weapon.</p>
        <p>The victim of the attack, Shane Daniels, now 23, of Riverhead, remained in a coma for several weeks after the May 26, 1996, incident. He eventually regained consciousness and recovered from the severe blows to his head, which were made with a steering wheel locking device known as the Club, but his vision is still blurry, family members said.</p>
        <p>A fingerprint of Mr. Offen's was found on the Club, according to statements by prosecutors from the office of the Suffolk County District Attorney, James M. Catterson Jr. Prosecutors also told the court during pretrial hearings that blood found on the security device was consistent with the victim's, and indicated that they would call witnesses to the beating.</p>
        <p>A second suspect, Constantine Chronis, 36, of Hicksville, who was a New York City police officer at the time of the incident, is to be tried separately, possibly as early as next month, on charges of second-degree official misconduct and second-degree menacing. Mr Chronis resigned from the Police Department and has been free on $200,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Mr. Offen has spent the last 20 months in the county jail in Riverhead, unable to raise bail, which Judge Joel Lefkowitz of Suffolk County Court set at $500,000. Both defendants have pleaded not guilty, with each man claiming that the other struck Mr. Daniels.</p>
        <p>The delay in bringing the case to trial was due, in part, to an effort by the District Attorney's office to have both defendants tried at the same time before the same jury. Assistant District Attorney John B. Collins argued that a single trial would save the taxpayers money and reduce the burden on jurors and witnesses. After Judge Lefkowitz denied the motion, Mr. Collins returned to court and sought to have a single trial, but with two separate juries.</p>
        <p>The lawyer for Mr. Chronis, who fought for a separate trial for his client, said that if the two defendants were tried together, he would have to question Mr. Offen about a previous conviction for assaulting a police officer and other allegations of criminal conduct, which is information the prosecution is barred from asking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Offen's lawyer, Bruce A. Barket, who also sought a separate trial for his client, told the court that Mr. Offen had a right to keep jurors from hearing about other allegations of criminal activity that Mr. Barket said had no bearing on whether he beat Mr. Daniels.</p>
        <p>Judge Lefkowitz later decided that he did not want to become a referee determining the rights of Mr. Offen against those of Mr. Chronis and ordered separate trials. In his decision, the judge said that to do otherwise would risk a possible mistrial.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barket said last week that his client is ready to go to trial.</p>
        <p>''He's been in jail for 20 months and is ready to prove that he is innocent,'' Mr. Barket said. If all the prosecution has is a fingerprint, Mr. Barket said, ''then I guarantee an acquittal.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
