<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>There's No Place Like Home</title>
    <meta content="28SUBU$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7DB153EF93BA15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="3008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>There's No Place Like Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on anti-urban sentiment of some suburbanites living close to New York City; they are strangers to city and rarely visit there; some say getting into and around New York is too inconvenient, they have no need or desire to go there or shun it for variety of other reasons, including fear; suburbs now sport their own cultural venues and proliferation of suburban office parks allows many commuters to work in suburbs; Westchester County residents comment; drawing; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICHELLE CAPUTO, 28, has visited New York City a half-dozen times in her life. On its face, this would hardly seem unusual. She prefers to take getaway vacations to more tranquil locales, most recently to Florida, Cancun and the Bahamas.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Caputo has lived her entire life in Rutherford, N.J., a 15-minute drive into Midtown Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICHELLE CAPUTO, 28, has visited New York City a half-dozen times in her life. On its face, this would hardly seem unusual. She prefers to take getaway vacations to more tranquil locales, most recently to Florida, Cancun and the Bahamas.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Caputo has lived her entire life in Rutherford, N.J., a 15-minute drive into Midtown Manhattan.</p>
        <p>She doesn't even pop into Manhattan for a night out. For her, the city's bother -- traffic, crowds, expense, parking problems -- outweigh its benefits.</p>
        <p>''Honestly? It's just inconvenient,'' said Ms. Caputo, who is a billing auditor at a Paramus telecommunications company. ''You have to deal with getting there and getting back. You're surrounded by people and you can't do anything. I hate standing in line. I don't want to wait a half-hour in a station for some train. Here, I can get into the car and go where I want in a half-hour, park right in front, and not deal with a million people.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Caputo is not alone. Sure, there are tourists who travel thousands of miles and spend thousands of dollars to visit New York City. There are young people in small towns all over America for whom New York is a mecca, whose fervent dream is to move to the city to live, to work, to reinvent themselves. Yet many suburbanites within clear view of the Manhattan skyline remain virtual strangers to the city, rarely venturing in. For many of them, visiting New York City was something you did as a child, going to see the Christmas spectacular at Radio City Music Hall or taking out-of-town relatives to the Empire State Building.</p>
        <p>Easy access to Manhattan is something people pay dearly for. The city bestows upon its suburbs -- north in Westchester and Connecticut, east on Long Island, and north, west and south in New Jersey -- some of the highest housing prices, taxes and costs of living in the world. And indeed, most suburbanites are on familiar terms with that place known to all simply as the City. Yet there are people who do not know the Bronx from the Battery and do not care to. There are plenty of suburbanites, sane, sociable, sophisticated, who will look you in the eye and tell you they simply do not see what the fuss is over Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Dan Rattiner, editor and publisher of Dan's Papers, a free weekly newspaper distributed on eastern Long Island and in parts of Manhattan, moved from Greenwich Village to eastern Long Island in the early 1980's and did not return to the city for 10 years.</p>
        <p>''I decided I didn't need to go back at all, I was so happy here,'' Mr. Rattiner recalled. ''The closest I'd get was J.F.K. Airport. I traveled all over the world but never to New York. I would fantasize that it didn't exist at all, that it was just a big, cardboard skyline.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rattiner said that he now visits the city about every three weeks, but added, ''I know people, adults, who've never been out of the Hamptons, much less to New York City.''</p>
        <p>Avoiding Manhattan was understandable during the city's more dismal days, when its streets were dirty and crime-ridden, when arriving in Manhattan meant fending off squeegee men, when the subway was scrawled with graffiti, and the sidewalks were full of stereotypically rude, rushing New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>The image of the pushy New Yorker may never change, but the city has. Manhattan is much safer and visitor-friendly now. Since Sept. 11 many now regard the city with greater sympathy. But for many of those who once shunned or feared it, the disaster has reinforced their aversions to New York.</p>
        <p>Many experts say a suburbanite tendency to avoid the city may be more pervasive than ever. Partly, it is a reflection of societal shifts over recent decades. As the city's economy has decentralized, more jobs have spread to the suburbs. It is no longer so necessary to commute to the city. Many services, once considered the exclusive domain of Manhattan, including fine restaurants and shopping, cultural and fine arts offerings and state of the art hospitals, are now suburban staples as well.</p>
        <p>But avoiding New York City seems to have more to do with mindset. Those who shun the city offer various reasons: Some don't want to go; some don't need to; others are afraid to. Some lack the time, others the money. Some have been unnerved by bad city experiences or the terrorist attacks. Certainly, many suburban families have tight schedules, and Manhattan winds up getting pre-empted by a regimented lineup of children's soccer games, karate practice and birthday parties.</p>
        <p>This is the case with Nancy and Stephen Pryor who live in Rye with their four children, ages 5 through 13. Mrs. Pryor said that several times a year -- ''when we want to do something special'' -- the family piles into the S.U.V. (never the train) and takes the 40-minute drive into Midtown Manhattan. That includes the annual Thanksgiving Day parade with the family, and the annual night out for dinner and swing dancing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pryor, an accountant with a practice in Port Chester, grew up in Rye and Mrs. Pryor grew up in New Rochelle. Neither were ever big city people.</p>
        <p>''It's not that we don't want to go in more, but we don't really have the time,'' said Mrs. Pryor. ''We have four kids and we're involved in our community, so we tend to socialize around here.''</p>
        <p>Strange People, Tall Buildings</p>
        <p>Psychologists who practice in the suburbs say fear of New York is a common condition among their patients. Fears range from becoming lost or trapped or mugged in the city to being surrounded and suffocated by crowds of strange people and tall buildings. Some patients have been taught by their parents to be wary of the city, and speak of New York as a terrifying foreign land, said Peter S. Kanaris, a Smithtown psychologist who uses various techniques, including relaxation and meditative breathing, to get patients to be able to travel into Manhattan. ''When you think of the city, you think of this great diversity of people,'' Mr. Kanaris said, adding that a typical patient's reaction to that is: ''It's a place where I'm going to encounter many types of different people and that feels dangerous to me.''</p>
        <p>Beth Wilson, 57, of Amityville, said she has visited the city about 10 times in the past 10 years. Each visit has caused panic attacks, she said, a vertigo that can be relieved only by staring down at the pavement and running ''in the direction of Long Island.''</p>
        <p>''It's a claustrophobic thing,'' said Mrs. Wilson, a program administrator for Cablevision in Bethpage and a lifelong Long Islander. ''I feel like Superman when he has the Kryptonite.''</p>
        <p>Nina K. Thomas, a clinical psychologist who practices in Morristown, N.J., said that some suburbanites may become so cloistered that ''traveling to Manhattan takes on the air of a major trip, as if to a foreign country.''</p>
        <p>This is the case for Victoria Linefsky, 44, who has basically avoided New York City since childhood. Mrs. Linefsky, who works part time both in a law office and a preschool, lives in Massapequa, just west of Amityville. The city is an hour's drive to Manhattan in light traffic, but it is worlds away for Ms. Linefsky, who said she has ''no clue'' how to navigate Manhattan, or even hail a cab. ''I don't know my way around,'' she said. ''What's uptown? Downtown? What's a good section?'' Her three children, ages 18, 14 and 9, are Long Islanders, and she has no intention of making them New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''My parents never raised me very culturally,'' she said. ''I've never been to a play in the city. I've never been to Broadway.''</p>
        <p>Glenville, Conn., said of New York City: ''Why would you want to go down there? To pay $6.50 for a beer?'' The club charges a decidedly less metropolitan price of $2.25 for a bottle of Budweiser. Mr. Brown, 55, known locally as J. B., is a maintenance worker for the town of Greenwich, but is out on disability. He lives in Byram, Conn., and his last visit to Manhattan occurred about 20 years ago, he said, and that was for his job.</p>
        <p>The bartender, Joseph Salvatore, 61, of Greenwich, said he has only begun visiting the city again in recent years, to take his two young daughters who are learning about Manhattan in school. Mr. Salvatore, a local cemetery caretaker, said before that, he had not been to the city in about 15 years, ''and if I wasn't taking them, I wouldn't be going down there.''</p>
        <p>The Metropolis in the Backyard</p>
        <p>Anti-urban sentiment is not new. After all, the suburbs sprang up largely as an alternative to city life, an escape from crowding, pollution and strangers. Immigrants who came to New York through Ellis Island worked their way from gritty urban tenements to modest, grassy plots in Levittown or New Rochelle. Many of them, and the generations they begot, have never felt the need to look back.</p>
        <p>''I can't tell you how many students I've asked, 'When was the last time you were in the city?' and they've said, 'When I was 5,' '' said Gail Satler, a sociology professor at Hofstra University who teaches urban planning and design.</p>
        <p>Most of Ms. Satler's students have grown up on Long Island within an hour of the city. But few students were even remotely familiar with New York City, so she began planning class trips into Manhattan to introduce them to the metropolis in their backyard.</p>
        <p>''We were talking about it like it's so far away and it's not,'' she said. ''Unless I make them go, most of them won't.''</p>
        <p>In March, the class visited St. Patrick's Cathedral and Times Square.</p>
        <p>''Half of them had never seen Central Park,'' Ms. Satler said. ''Some are embarrassed and some are proud. Their attitude is: They've never been in, and they don't have to be.''</p>
        <p>For 20 years, Mineola High School in Nassau County, has offered its senior-year students a one-semester class on New York City. The curriculum covers everything from night life to architecture. Students are taken on monthly trips into the city.</p>
        <p>Paul Pereira, a social studies teacher, who teaches the class, understands the suburban mindset from firsthand experience. ''The only time I went in as a kid is when I went in on a bus for a school trip,'' he said. ''Most of these kids think it's scary and dangerous and dirty like they see in the movies, and that's why we teach the course.''</p>
        <p>His own parents were from Portugal. ''They were happier sending me in my teens the 3,000 miles to see Portugal than sending me 30 minutes on the train to the city,'' Mr. Pereira said. ''A lot of kids pick up stereotypes about the city from their parents who were born and bred here. For them the suburbs equals a better quality of life. But culture's not out in Mineola or Massapequa. It's just lawns and shopping malls and storefronts here. There's no character.</p>
        <p>''I get parents coming up and asking, 'Do you offer this class for adults?' Even parents who work in Manhattan, a lot of them just go in and come right out again.''</p>
        <p>The Suburb to Suburb Commute</p>
        <p>Over recent decades, the activity that was once the sole province of New York City has decentralized, allowing people to settle in the suburbs and shun the city, said James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers University in New Brunswick, N.J.</p>
        <p>''The suburbs have become self-contained universes,'' he said. ''There are very few unique things in the city now that suburban people feel they have to access on a regular basis.''</p>
        <p>Professor Hughes noted, for example, that in 1950, New York City had 3.4 million jobs, and the state of New Jersey had 1.7 million. But in 2000, New Jersey had 4 million jobs compared to the city's 3.7 million. The trends were similar in Long Island, Westchester and lower Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The proliferation of suburban office parks in the 1980's allowed many commuters to the city to work in the suburbs instead. Mr. Hughes said that the network of office parks in New York's suburbs, including north-central New Jersey, Fairfield County and Stamford in Connecticut, the White Plains area in Westchester, and Route 110 on Long Island has the third largest amount of office space in the country, behind New York City and Chicago.</p>
        <p>''The suburbs have really evolved into horizontal cities, replicating the urban market place,'' Professor Hughes said.</p>
        <p>Now most people, he continued, are commuting from one suburb to another. Most people now work in the county in which they live or in an adjacent one. There are now about 50 large regional malls outside Manhattan, accounting for roughly 50 million square feet of retail space. And some New York City dwellers now even travel to the suburbs to shop at big box stores like Ikea in Elizabeth and Home Depot in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>'Everything I Need Is Here'</p>
        <p>Some simply stay in the suburbs because of the comforts: the grass, the trees, the space, the privacy -- and the familiarity.</p>
        <p>Patrick Driscoll lives in Millburn, N.J., a half-hour drive from Manhattan. Mr. Driscoll co-owns a bicycle shop in Millburne. His wife, Amy, is pregnant with their third child. Apart from a few business obligations, he has hardly visited the city in the last five years. ''I really don't go in any more of my own accord,'' he said. ''The city is just not something we really think about much. I'd rather not deal with that many people. I like a slower environment and having a million people waking around you on the sidewalk, I'd rather be sitting in the backyard in a small town, relaxing.''</p>
        <p>Taking the trains can be a deterrent, especially negotiating transfers. ''It's not just the people you don't know,'' he said. ''It's a whole system you don't know.''</p>
        <p>Suburbanites are used to the privacy of their cars, essential in suburbia but often an impediment to navigating Manhattan, where there are more aggressive drivers and fewer parking spaces. But mass transit looms large as an obstacle to those who don't go regularly to the city.</p>
        <p>Dena Mosiello, 22, a student at Pace University who lives on campus, says she only goes into Manhattan about once a year because 'It's a great place, but there are so many obstacles that stop me from going.'</p>
        <p>It is only an hour's drive into downtown Manhattan, she said, but there is often traffic, and she refuses to chance parking her 2002 Jeep Wrangler on most city streets.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult to get there and there's nowhere to park unless you have $30 for a garage,'' she said. ''The last train at night leaves around 1, so you're trapped down there because I'm not leaving a club before 1 a.m.''</p>
        <p>Many Pace students are more likely to go to the nightclubs in New Rochelle or the bars in Pleasantville or White Plains, and the fear caused by the Sept. 11 attacks has meant even fewer venture into the city.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mosiello's father, Alfred Mosiello, lives in Putnam Valley and is a lieutenant in the Pelham Manor Police Department. He goes into Manhattan maybe once a year.</p>
        <p>''Manhattan is great if you're into the arts and museums,'' he said. ''It's all down there. I happen to like the wide, open spaces.''</p>
        <p>''It's got to be in your life style,'' he said. ''There are people living there who wouldn't go anywhere else either.''</p>
        <p>Burta E. Smith, 70, a retired accountant, lives in Fairfield, Conn., a 75-minute train ride to Grand Central Terminal. She is active (she baby-sits full time) and adventurous (last summer, she drove her car to Texas), but she has visited Manhattan only about four times since she moved to the East Coast in 1991 from the Los Angeles area. Once, she was ''bribed'' to visit the city with tickets to ''Cats,'' she said, and the other times she agreed to accompany sightseeing relatives.</p>
        <p>''I would never go into the city on my own, either by car or train,'' she said. ''I'm really not a city girl. It's nothing personal. I just like my peace and quiet. I have pretty much everything I need here.''</p>
        <p>Those who do go into the city regularly, just because they want to, not because they work there, are sometimes met with surprise. Geoff Thompson of Briarcliff Manor in Westchester co-owns a public relations firm there whose clients are almost exclusively Westchester businesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said he travels regularly into Manhattan to attend New York Rangers games, Broadway shows and films. It never fails to amaze the neighbors, he said. ''When I tell them we went into the city, they say, 'Jeez, you did? We haven't gone in for years,' '' he said. ''I'm always astounded. There are many people who would drive to Cape Cod more readily than drive into the city and see a film.</p>
        <p>''You can see the Manhattan skyline from here, but for many people here, it might as well be the Land of Oz,'' he said. ''It's funny, because so many people in Westchester originally came from New York City, and they talk about it like they moved to Vermont, instead of just Katonah.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
