<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Themes Are Universal In Artworks By Women</title>
    <meta content="28ART.$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1387795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey State Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB153EF93BA15757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Themes Are Universal In Artworks By Women</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews Women's Works: Fine Arts from the Museum's Collection at New Jersey State Museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE exhibition ''Women's Works: Fine Art from the Museum's Collection'' at the New Jersey State Museum is more than an overview; it is out to prove a point.</p>
        <p>The museum's art curator, Margaret O'Reilly, is going against the conventional wisdom that art made by women usually wears that fact on its sleeve. The contention here is that, in the big picture, art made by women covers the same ground as that made by men. The show, drawn from the museum's collection, covers most traditional genres. The earliest piece is from the mid-19th century and the latest pieces are from the 1990's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE exhibition ''Women's Works: Fine Art from the Museum's Collection'' at the New Jersey State Museum is more than an overview; it is out to prove a point.</p>
        <p>The museum's art curator, Margaret O'Reilly, is going against the conventional wisdom that art made by women usually wears that fact on its sleeve. The contention here is that, in the big picture, art made by women covers the same ground as that made by men. The show, drawn from the museum's collection, covers most traditional genres. The earliest piece is from the mid-19th century and the latest pieces are from the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Hanging outside the entrance to a show is ''Synthetic Thunder,'' (1992) by Ellen Levy. It embodies the purpose of the show. This painting is almost an abstraction, although the shapes are bold ones inspired by factories. Paintings about industry are a subject long associated with New Jersey, and they're traditionally a male preserve.</p>
        <p>Viewers land first in a room devoted to abstraction, and the paintings here are masterly and inventive. Andrea Belag's ''Snakes and Ladders'' (1978) is a large concoction primarily in red of short, sinuous lines arranged in vertical columns. Nearby, Helen Soreff's ''Darkly Conversant'' (1990) flirts with being a Minimalist painting, but the many black bar-like shapes leave traces as they scoot across the white surface. ''Wind Tossing Late Autumn Leaves'' (1976) by Alma Thomas is an animated mark-filled companion to the other two.</p>
        <p>Next to the Soreff is ''Dawnscape'' (1975), a print by Louise Nevelson, in which the raised contours of her familiar blocky forms are made with cast paper and become a white-on white relief sculpture. Lee Krasner's lithograph from her ''Blue Stone Series'' (1969) is, in contrast, a mysterious web. ''Lavender Image'' (1955) by the quirky Japanese artist Yayoi Kusama resembles a cell seen under a microscope.</p>
        <p>Tova Beck-Friedman's towering sculpture from 1995 out of recycled paper pulp is titled ''The Soul Selects Her Own Society,'' after a poem by Emily Dickinson. There is a noticeable gap between the two pinnacle shapes of this piece, as if each is going its own way. If this sculpture dominates the room size-wise, the small round ceramic bottle by Toshiko Takaezu made in the 1960's holds its own by being a quiet presence.</p>
        <p>Between this gallery and one devoted to representation hang two photographs that couldn't be more different. Dorothea Lange, who is known for her photographs of poor people during the Depression, is represented by a silver print with a vivid descriptive title, ''Woman with Child in Front of a Tent in the South'' (1936). Next to it is the simple ''Flax,'' slender plant forms bisecting the picture's surface, taken during the 1920's by Imogen Cunningham.</p>
        <p>The representational work includes more comments on industry, including Valeri Larko's small ''Industrial Debris in Winter,'' (1995) along with a painting on wood that seems nostalgic, even paradisical, today.</p>
        <p>''The Monongahela at Morgantown'' (1934) by Blanche Lazzell depicts factories and the hilly landscape in perfect coexistence. Elsie Driggs, whose reputation rests mainly on especially gritty paintings of industrial forms, is represented by a winsome watercolor from 1924, ''Oriental Diplomats.''</p>
        <p>Two contemporary painters known for their devotion to depicting ordinary life are Grace Graupe-Pillard and Catherine Murphy. Ms. Graupe-Pillard's large-scale ''Doc Wallace on Sunday'' (1980) is a portrait of a man who looks exhausted, but is ready to tend to a patient at a moment's notice. Ms. Murphy's ''Backyards, Jamaica, NY'' (1970) is a row of almost identical dwellings, but the artist is also saying that individuals live in them.</p>
        <p>This gallery affords a real look back. The earliest work in the show is a small undated bronze sheep by Rosa Bonheur, a 19th-century French painter who is best known for her gigantic, thundering painting ''The Horse Fair'' in the Metropolitan Museum.</p>
        <p>Mythological subjects are well represented here. ''Diana of the Hunt'' by Anna Hyatt Huntington from around 1922 is taller than Ms. Beck Friedman's piece next door, and the body has an interesting twist. Gladys Edgerly Bates's ''Pan of the Laurentians'' (circa 1930) is a lead sculpture of a small boy. ''David'' (1945) by Dorothea Greenbaum is a small boy, too. But his trousers make him an actual child and not a figure out of mythology or the Bible.</p>
        <p>Viewers will snap out of any reveries these sculptures might induce when they come upon Käthe Kollwitz's dark etching, ''Battlefield'' from 1907. Graphic art with antiwar themes became her constant subject in the two world wars that followed.</p>
        <p>A third gallery contains several pieces that comment directly on being a woman. Judith K. Brodsky's intaglio print, ''Dishrag Diagrammatic'' (1978) is a colorful ode to this indispensable object. ''Double Breasted Arch,'' a 1980 painting by Joan Semmell, is a deliberately confusing concatenation of body parts. Rivaling it in exuberance is the trio of arch shapes on a green field by Kay Walkingstick from 1976, ''Sacajawea, Leader of Men.''</p>
        <p>''Women's Works: Fine Art from the Museum's Collection'' is at the New Jersey State Museum through May 5. Information: (609) 292-6464 or www.newjerseystatemuseum.org</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
