<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>16 Countries And Still Speaking</title>
    <meta content="27REEV$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Travel; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BACK HOME WITH: The Reeves-O'Neill Family" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BACK HOME WITH: The Reeves-O'Neill Family"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Around-the-World Trips</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reeves, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Catherine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Patricia Leigh</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Family Travels: Around the World in 30 (Or So) Days (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DC163AF934A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>16 Countries And Still Speaking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA LEIGH BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Patricia Leigh</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Richard Reeves and his wife, Catherine O'Neill, authors of book Family Travels: Around the World in 30 or So Days; they discuss how family visited 16 countries in 35 days; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR some people, the definition of a family outing is hauling a pack of Oscar Mayers and a bag of charcoal to the beach. But if you are intellectually ambitious, sophisticated New Yorkers -- like Richard Reeves, an author and syndicated political columnist, and his wife, Catherine O'Neill, a refugee advocate and founder of the Women's Commission for Women and Children Refugees -- you recruit your extensive family, including children from previous marriages, and take off for the great, global beyond.</p>
        <p>You travel around the world, laptop and bubble wrap at the ready, visit 16 countries in 35 days, and then write a book: ''Family Travels: Around the World in 30 or So Days'' (Andrews &amp; McMeel, $$22.95).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR some people, the definition of a family outing is hauling a pack of Oscar Mayers and a bag of charcoal to the beach. But if you are intellectually ambitious, sophisticated New Yorkers -- like Richard Reeves, an author and syndicated political columnist, and his wife, Catherine O'Neill, a refugee advocate and founder of the Women's Commission for Women and Children Refugees -- you recruit your extensive family, including children from previous marriages, and take off for the great, global beyond.</p>
        <p>You travel around the world, laptop and bubble wrap at the ready, visit 16 countries in 35 days, and then write a book: ''Family Travels: Around the World in 30 or So Days'' (Andrews &amp; McMeel, $$22.95).</p>
        <p>If it's Tuesday, this must be Borobudur. Or maybe Bali, Islamabad or Berlin.</p>
        <p>Many families might fantasize about such an adventure. But the Reeves-O'Neill clan, a Brainy Bunch of seven vagabonds, actually did it. They were led by Ms. O'Neill, the Ernest Hemingway of bargain hunters, whose militarily precise organizational abilities cause her husband to describe her as ''a force of nature.''</p>
        <p>''Not to be obnoxious about it,'' Ms. O'Neill, 55, explained, only a touch obnoxiously, one recent evening over dinner at Le Colonial, a Vietnamese restaurant in midtown Manhattan. ''But we thought of the trip as a base line, a picture of the world at this point in time.''</p>
        <p>Her son Conor O'Neill, a rock musician in Los Angeles, speaking by telephone, put it another way: ''It wasn't exactly a relaxing vacation. I thought of it as a pu pu platter.''</p>
        <p>The idea for traveling the world en famille was hatched three years ago by the couple in a taxi on the road from Haiphong to the Gulf of Tonkin in Vietnam. Listening to the young taxi driver talk about his family's experiences during the Vietnam War, Ms. O'Neill couldn't help wishing her own sons were with her. She and Mr. Reeves had taken a round-the-world expedition in 1981. No sooner had she said, ''Let's do it again, with the children!'' than the ''Dear family'' letters went out.</p>
        <p>The concept: invite the brood to globe-gallop for a month at Mom and Dad's expense. The motive: a rare chance for the far-flung family to get together while infusing them with a 21st-century geopolitical perspective, a grand tour for wonks.</p>
        <p>''More than anything,'' Mr. Reeves wrote in the book, ''we wanted to create or nurture this little circle of people born 25 years apart to hold together and look inward to each other when we are no longer cajoling and nagging at the center.''</p>
        <p>The family converged at the Reeves-O'Neill home in Sag Harbor, L.I., in the summer of 1994, sticking colored pins into a map as they plotted, and bartered, their route. On hand were Ms. O'Neill's two sons, Colin, now 30, and Conor, 27, Mr. Reeves's daughter Cindie Reeves Fyfe, 36, and son-in-law Thomas Fyfe, 40, and the Reeveses' daughter, Fiona O'Neill Reeves, 12. Cindie agreed to vote for Papua New Guinea if Fiona voted for Bali.</p>
        <p>The catch was that everyone had to spend 15 minutes a day writing his or her impressions. The participants also had to answer questionnaires written by Ms. O'Neill that asked things like ''Are there jobs in this country which don't exist in the U.S.?'' The book was part of the trip from the start, the advance helping to defray the cost -- $29,700.</p>
        <p>Fun, huh? ''At first I didn't like it, because it was my vacation,'' said Fiona, noting: ''My mom and dad are a business, sort of. But then, it was fun to have my parents know my thoughts.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. O'Neill and Mr. Reeves, the trip was an attempt to give their children something more lasting than a car. When Mr. Reeves, now 60, was a young reporter for The New York Times, Pat Brown, the Governor of California at the time, told him how he arranged irresistible vacations to get his family together.</p>
        <p>''At the time, it didn't seem relevant,'' the now silvery-haired writer recalled over beer and spring rolls. ''But when that switch comes,'' he said, referring to parenthood, ''and it's hard to get your kids on the phone, you think about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reeves and Ms. O'Neill bought five around-the-world tickets for $2,628.65 each, usable over a six-month period for travel in the same direction, with a third off for Fiona. (As it turned out, Cindie and Tom needed only round-trip tickets to Berlin; they had their first child, Ian, shortly before the trip, and the three hooked up with the family there.)</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Neill booked the trip herself, madly dialing 800 numbers into the night between a trip to Rwanda and writing guest editorials for The Los Angeles Times. Then she brokered a deal with her travel agent that allowed her to finalize the arrangements in exchange for the agent's  discount and half the commission. ''Even Richard, who would never have asked himself, was impressed this time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''Very impressed,'' her husband agreed. ''Usually I leave the room when she starts talking about money, the same way I look away from beggars in India and New York.''</p>
        <p>The perceptions of the family's three age groups, in their own words and seemingly unexpurgated, form the basis for the book, which also weaves in articles from newspapers around the world and the parents' considerable knowledge of international affairs.</p>
        <p>There are also travel tips. One of their more singular approaches abroad is visiting local real estate offices.</p>
        <p>''Agents are extremely knowledgable guides,'' Mr. Reeves said. ''And you find yourselves in people's homes hearing how much things are worth.''</p>
        <p>In the book, the children often provide welcome comic relief. Witness Conor's first impression of Israel: ''Wow, a lot of babes with guns!''</p>
        <p>The trip, in June of 1995, was weighted heavily toward Asia, starting with a flight from Los Angeles to Tokyo. The Asian leg ended in Pakistan, where the family had lived briefly in 1983 and where Conor ''almost died of hamburger deprivation,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>From there it was on to Dubai (''where there was a wider assortment of black fabric than I imagined existing in the world,'' Ms. O'Neill said), and Cairo, Jerusalem, Berlin and a week's decompression in the French countryside.</p>
        <p>The average family vacation would probably not include tete-a-tetes with ambassadors (Walter F. Mondale in Tokyo) or tea with Benazir Bhutto, the Prime Minister of Pakistan at the time.</p>
        <p>Not that it impressed their children. To the couples' apparent astonishment, Mr. Reeves discovered, ''that was our life, not theirs.''</p>
        <p>The children often prick the balloon of their parents' earnestness. When a muckety-muck in Taipei offered Fiona a State Department briefing book, she replied, ''I'm not interested in reading about underwear.''</p>
        <p>Colin, a television producer in Los Angeles, wrote that a hellish overnight train trip in Indonesia was like ''trying to sleep in the refrigerated ice-cream trough of a supermarket, sitting upright on a stack of Breyer's, during an earthquake.''</p>
        <p>Being sequestered with one's family has its moments. War nearly broke out over Ms. O'Neill's shopping excursions, during which Fiona learned to bargain ''the way a bear cub would watch Mama Bear swat a salmon out of the river,'' Mr. Reeves wrote. Ms. O'Neill was determined to accumulate ''visual expressions'' of Indonesia, even if that meant buying an extra batik suitcase and causing near-revolt among her filial Sherpas.</p>
        <p>Such stressful encounters caused ''everyone's character defects to shine brightly,'' Conor wrote in Hong Kong. But as travelers they also found much common ground. ''It wasn't just squeamish Mom,'' Ms. O'Neill said. ''The kids didn't like the flies and dirt, either.''</p>
        <p>The children soaked up popular culture, from Freak Street in Katmandu to body piercers in Berlin, and rediscovered their parents and siblings from a more adult perspective. Fiona, for instance, had not lived with her big brothers since she was a baby.</p>
        <p>''It made me closer to my dad and made me like my brothers more,'' she said. ''It made me realize my mom is a little more powerful than your average person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reeves recalled a pivotal conversation with Colin and Conor that took place in Jakarta in the back of a taxicab (the Reeves-O'Neills have a predilection for epiphanies in taxicabs) in which the boys talked about being left behind as children because of their parents' travels.</p>
        <p>''Some of that came back to me, and it became obvious that they thought we took parenting too casually,'' Mr. Reeves said. ''Then you immediately think, 'God, I wish I could do that over.' They saw our strengths and weaknesses, and I was dazzled. They saw us in more complexity than I would have guessed.''</p>
        <p>In the end, of course, despite noble liberal parental goals about ''riding the learning curve'' and giving your children global insight, countries can ultimately be judged on ''whether you like the people,'' Mr. Reeves wrote. So can family.</p>
        <p>''You have to change your thresholds when you do something like this with your family,'' Colin observed, speaking by telephone. ''You're going to be annoyed with certain things, and you're going to annoy. You have to acknowledge that such close quarters put a strain on relationships. But I do know that when we've gotten together since, it's an experience we share. It's like Outward Bound. I couldn't be in a room with them and not think about that month.''</p>
        <p>Still, his parents may get the last word. Ever the organizer, Ms. O'Neill rewrote her will recently, bequeathing to her sons all those ''repulsively heavy carvings'' they complained so bitterly about.</p>
        <p>BACK HOME WITH: The Reeves-O'Neill Family</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
