<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baseball;   The Game That Is Forever Young</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LITTLE LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORAN, MALCOLM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC123DF935A35756C0A966958260" item-length="1785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baseball;   The Game That Is Forever Young</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORAN, MALCOLM</byline>
      <dateline>LEVITTOWN, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The middle-aged men stood along the first-base line on Opening Day, soon after the parade that led all the children to the start of the 1990 Little League season at Michael Yatsko Field. Beyond the center-field fence, the electronic scoreboard had been set to the moment that connected the lives of those men and this town three decades before; the home team winning, 5-0, in the final inning of the championship game of the 14th Little League World Series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The middle-aged men stood along the first-base line on Opening Day, soon after the parade that led all the children to the start of the 1990 Little League season at Michael Yatsko Field. Beyond the center-field fence, the electronic scoreboard had been set to the moment that connected the lives of those men and this town three decades before; the home team winning, 5-0, in the final inning of the championship game of the 14th Little League World Series.</p>
        <p>The middle-aged men stood along the first-base line on Opening Day, soon after the parade that led all the children to the start of the 1990 Little League season at Michael Yatsko Field. Beyond the center-field fence, the electronic scoreboard had been set to the moment that connected the lives of those men and this town three decades before; the home team winning, 5-0, in the final inning of the championship game of the 14th Little League World Series.</p>
        <p>More suddenly than anyone could have imagined, Levittown, then a seven-year-old community, one of William Levitt's post-war collections of look-alike suburban houses, would become known for its adolescent heroes. By the age of 12, the children of a place created to house the American dream achieved an international success symbolized by a parade of open-topped convertibles and a trip to Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>Three decades later, as the institution of Little League baseball has achieved stability and embarked upon expansion, its early generations, middle-aged and beyond, have been coming home to celebrate the experience. The 1965 champions from Windsor Locks, Conn., who have scattered as far as California, were honored last Friday by the Connecticut State Senate and House of Representatives, and held a 25th anniversary reunion last night that was attended by 15 of the 16 teammates. The 16th, who died of Hodgkin's disease in 1975, was represented by a 10-year-old nephew who wore his uncle's hat and T-shirt.</p>
        <p>The participants in Levittown's recent Opening Day parade were part of a system that now involves 2.5 million athletes and 750,000 adult volunteers in 36 countries. They will all create another year of links from parent to child and teammate to teammate, and they will have access to another series of lessons on the unfairness of life in the form of that final-inning, bases-loaded, two-out, two-strike, chest-high fastball in on the fists.</p>
        <p>Little League has endured the problems of a decreasing population of children and the threat of competing activities, and it has acknowledged the interest of young female athletes and devised a way to accommodate those children whose enthusiasm exceeds their disabilities.</p>
        <p>In the past six weeks, leagues have been chartered in Yugoslavia and Czechoslovakia, and discussions continue with officials of the baseball federation in the Soviet Union. A Challenger Division, for disabled children, has increased from five leagues last summer to 275 this spring and will include at least 5,000 athletes.</p>
        <p>After a succession of one-sided American losses to superior teams from the Far East, the Trumbull, Conn., World Series triumph last summer became the first victory for a United States-based team since 1983 and produced the highest television rating of a championship game in the past six years. When the end of summer nears, each of the 7,000 leagues will enter an all-star team in an attempt to reach one of the eight spots in the tournament at Lamade Stadium in Williamsport, Pa., where thousands sit in the grandstand and on the hill beyond the outfield fence to watch moments that are preserved for decades.</p>
        <p>''The big saying then was, 'You put Levittown on the map,' '' said Joe Mormello, who on Aug. 27, 1960, pitched a no-hitter in the championship victory over Fort Worth, struck out a record 16 hitters in the six-inning game, and hit a 225-foot home run.</p>
        <p>''We thought, 'It's always been here,' '' Mormello said, and laughed. ''As we got older, we understood what they were talking about.''</p>
        <p>He and his former teammates were brought together several weekends ago by the laughs that they shared, the stories they could trade, and the details that had temporarily been misplaced in their minds. Levittown's champions stood in a line with boutonnieres fastened to their chests, and the 1960 world championship banner was displayed again. Nearby the 27 current teams of the Levittown American Athletic Association stood, in uniform, on the field: Eggert Fuels and Trenton Road Takeout, Lee's Dog Grooming and Lee's Hoagies, Chipper's Ice Cream and Thornridge Hardware, Marty's Beauty Salon and D&amp;D Ceramic Tile, Mormello Chiropractic and all the others.</p>
        <p>And the crowd was reminded or informed of a time when those men were young, and the hometown they made famous was even younger. ''It's like you're preserving history for us and memories for those guys,'' said Dave Gillman, the league president. ''In 1990, there are a lot of parents here that didn't know they pulled this thing off.''</p>
        <p>The group had not been together since high school graduation. The last Mormello had heard, his best friend on the team, Jules Kalkstein, was a veterinarian living in Vermont. At the reunion, Mormello learned that Kalkstein was an attorney living in Brooklyn. Rodger Barto, who was supposedly planning on a career in the Air Force, runs a bicycle shop and bakery in Ohio.</p>
        <p>But Joe Fioravanti, who with Mark Griffith and Mormello had formed the group that advanced from the Watson &amp; Schwartz team to the all-star group that represented the league in the tournament, held no surprises. Fioravanti had become a high school valedictorian. ''If you asked anybody what he was going to be, you'd figure an attorney,'' Mormello remembered, and he was right.</p>
        <p>Those were the mysteries that were solved two weekends ago. ''It was, 'What are you doing? Are you married? Do you have any children?' '' Mormello remembered. ''Then once that was out of the way, then we started: 'Remember this game? Remember that?' We rehashed all the old things. Then it was, 'What are you doing tomorrow?' ''</p>
        <p>He is 42 now, a volunteer coach in a game that made him famous, chased him away, and finally drew him back. His face is rounder than the one that smiled for cameras with big-leaguers back then, but the Yankee hat on his head helps preserve its youth.</p>
        <p>Mormello was sitting in the living room of his home in Langhorne, Pa., a community of new homes, carefully trimmed lawns and young voices just 2.1 miles from his chiropractic practice and the house of his childhood.</p>
        <p>He was 5 when his family moved to Levittown from a South Philadelphia neighborhood not far from where Veterans Stadium would rise a decade later. His father, also named Joe, who had played in the Cardinal system under the name Joe Miller, went to see this new development in lower Bucks County.</p>
        <p>''He found a house,'' the son remembered. ''He came up on a Sunday. He didn't have that much money with him, and he wanted to buy a house. And the salesman said, 'Well, just leave your watch. And when you get paid on Tuesday, just bring the money up.' So he left his watch there as a down payment on a house.''</p>
        <p>There were two-and-half-bedroom homes going for less than $10,000 in this brand-new place, a boom town just 30 miles north of Philadelphia and 60 miles south of New York City, a place with enough space for children to have room to grow.</p>
        <p>''If you wanted a baseball game,'' Mormello remembered, ''you just went over to the closest baseball field and waited, and before long you had enough for a team. The only time you couldn't would be lunch time and dinner time. There'd be nobody there. But you hurry up with your lunch, you hurry up with your dinner, you get back over to the field, and sure enough, they would all come drifting back.''</p>
        <p>Suddenly, they were celebrities. The town's celebration included three bands, baton twirlers, fire engines, and a color guard. Soon after, the boys were taken to Yankee Stadium, where Casey Stengel, the manager of the Yankees, spoke with Mormello on television in a conversation the 12-year-old failed to comprehend. That day, after Whitey Ford was taken out of the game, he asked for the kid pitcher to be brought into the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>''He more or less said, 'Don't get carried away with all this stuff going on,' '' Mormello remembered.</p>
        <p>Who could have known how important that advice would become? The group, or parts of it, went on to high school teams, Babe Ruth ball and American Legion play. Mormello, who had dreamed of the major leagues, who had been 5 feet 5 inches at the age of 12, grew just four more inches. He earned a scholarship to Rider College in Lawrenceville, N.J., where in his senior year, there was a slide into home, a badly injured left knee, and a sudden decision about surgery.</p>
        <p>''I thought, 'If I have this done, it's going to bother me the rest of my life,' '' Mormello remembered. '' 'Is it worth it? Isn't it worth it?' ''</p>
        <p>It wasn't worth it. Eight years removed from a celebration in Williamsport, a career was over. Cold turkey. For years, Mormello found watching a baseball game too painful. He would watch the Little League championship for a few innings, see the beginnings of another one-sided game, and turn the game off. It was not until last year, when his son Joey's coach asked if Mormello could help instruct the pitchers on his team, that an old glove was retrieved.</p>
        <p>Joey is 13, a catcher and third baseman on a Senior Little League team. When Joey went to a baseball camp at Williamsport, Joe Mormello stayed overnight in the same motel beyond the outfield hill of Lamade Stadium that his parents had occupied for the 1960 games.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think it was that big,'' Mormello said. ''But going back as an adult, you think this place is pretty big. And nice. It's like a major league field. The dugouts are just so. We didn't realize what they were doing back then.''</p>
        <p>He had been sitting in a dugout three decades before, three outs from a no-hitter, when a photographer approached him with a request. This was less than four years after Don Larsen's perfect World Series game, when Yogi Berra had leaped into the Yankee pitcher's arms. The photographer asked the pitcher if he and Brian Pennington, his catcher, could do that after the final out.</p>
        <p>''That's the next thing I remember, after the last out: 'I've got to do this thing,' '' Mormello said. ''I was starting to walk to the dugout, and I thought, 'Wait a minute. We've got to pose for this picture.' ''</p>
        <p>The moment is preserved in black and white images, complete with marching music in the background, recreated crowd noise, imitation cracks of the bat, and a deep, authoritative voice providing the narration:</p>
        <p>When Mormello goes to work in the last inning, he has a no-hitter on the line. And he sews it up with his 16th strikeout of the six-inning game. The Pennsylvania boys rush out to hail the hero of their 5-0 victory, who gave one of the best performances in the Little League's 14-year history. Hail to the Little League champs. . . .''</p>
        <p>The man watches the boy on the large screen run to meet his catcher, Yogi and Larsen, Mormello and Pennington, 12 years old forever.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
