<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gingrich Dodges Spotlight, He Is in Charge</title>
    <meta content="18GING" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047378"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE SPEAKER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DB1730F93BA2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gingrich Dodges Spotlight, He Is in Charge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Speaker Gingrich tries to assume pose of impartial observer working on people's business and waiting for House Judiciary Committee to sort out Pres Clinton's problems; fellow Republicans say that behind the scenes not a step is taken without Gingrich's approval; one lawmaker says it is important that 'Newt lie low' because he often comes across as strident and mean (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a news conference on education legislation, the first question put to Speaker Newt Gingrich this morning involved the White House scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich snapped at the questioner. ''We in the Congress are actually focusing on substance,'' he said. ''Yesterday, I spent less than 45 minutes total on the topic that interests you most.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a news conference on education legislation, the first question put to Speaker Newt Gingrich this morning involved the White House scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich snapped at the questioner. ''We in the Congress are actually focusing on substance,'' he said. ''Yesterday, I spent less than 45 minutes total on the topic that interests you most.''</p>
        <p>That is the pose the Speaker has tried to assume all week: the impartial observer waiting for his lawyers on the Judiciary Committee to sort out the facts and set the policy on how to deal with President Clinton's transgressions, while he deals with the people's business.</p>
        <p>But behind the scenes, other Republican lawmakers said, not a step is taken or a decision made without the approval of Mr. Gingrich, possibly the most partisan and certainly the most dominant Speaker in the last generation.</p>
        <p>''Look, the Speaker is the Speaker,'' said the chairman of an important committee who insisted on anonymity. ''He calls all the shots. If tapes are going to be released, it's his decision. If hearings are going to be held, he will decide. He consults with us. He listens to us. But he makes the calls.''</p>
        <p>At a closed meeting of House Republicans on Wednesday, Representative Nancy L. Johnson of Connecticut expressed concern about the release of sexually explicit portions of the videotape of the President's grand jury testimony.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich -- angry, according to the accounts of some who were there, or merely firm, according to those of others -- leapt to his feet and declared that the House had already voted to make the material public and that Republicans were not going to back down in the face of complaints from the White House and Democrats in Congress. Mr. Gingrich called the President a ''misogynist,'' a person who hates women.</p>
        <p>At the same meeting, Representative Gerald B. H. Solomon of upstate New York, the chairman of the Rules Committee, repeated a point Mr. Gingrich had made in a speech last week and reminded his colleagues that House rules did not permit language in floor debates that ridiculed or otherwise abused the President.</p>
        <p>There was a smattering of boos, clearly in jest, from the back of the room, said people who were there. Mr. Gingrich, they said, declared sternly that decorum in the House was not a laughing matter and that he would not allow the rules to be abridged.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gingrich walked out of the meeting and into a gaggle of reporters and cameras, he made a conspicuous show of talking about other issues -- trade and the economy -- and even praised Mr. Clinton's efforts to renew world economic growth.</p>
        <p>When reporters persisted in asking questions about impeachment and videotaped testimony, Representative John A. Boehner, Republican of Ohio, pushed the Speaker from the microphone so that staff members could usher him away.</p>
        <p>''It is very important to us that Newt lie low,'' said a Republican representative from the Southeast. This Congressman explained that Mr. Gingrich often came across to the public as strident and even mean and that if the Speaker allowed himself to stand at the forefront of the Clinton inquiry, the President and his allies would benefit by making him a lightning rod for their criticism of Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich is under conflicting pressures. The firebrands among the backbenchers want to go after President Clinton with all the artillery in the House's arsenal. But the Speaker's political advisers are telling him, a former staff assistant said, that if he has any ambition to become President, this is his opportunity to dispel a reputation as a hothead and adopt the mien of a statesman.</p>
        <p>One Republican Congressman suggested half-seriously that the most advantageous step the Speaker could take would be to save Mr. Clinton's Presidency.</p>
        <p>''It might not be best for the country,'' the Congressman said, ''but they would have a cripple as President going into the next election, and Newt would go down as a profile in courage.''</p>
        <p>With all that in mind, Mr. Gingrich tended carefully this week to the ceremonial and legislative aspects of his job.</p>
        <p>He spoke at a conference on missile defense, received a Hispanic Heritage Leadership Award and another award from the Community Antidrug Coalition, met with chief executives of some of the United States' largest companies, attended news conferences on education, agriculture policy and prayer in schools, appeared on the Capitol steps with representatives of Habitat for Humanity and taped an interview for a cable television documentary on the 100 people who have the most influence on American society.</p>
        <p>For the most part, Mr. Gingrich stayed on message, but occasionally he let slip oblique mentions of the subject that must be on his mind, too.</p>
        <p>Speaking extemporaneously at a news conference on Wednesday about a proposed constitutional amendment allowing organized prayer in public schools, he declared, ''In this city today, we have the specter of a scandal large enough that it should be driving all of us to prayer.''</p>
        <p>And this morning, to mark the 211th anniversary of the signing of the Constitution, he gave a one-minute speech on the House floor during the period set aside for members to address any subject of their choice. Mr. Gingrich said the framers of the Constitution had been determined to show ''once and for all that the age of kings was over, that all men and women are under the law -- none is above it, and none is below it.''</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE SPEAKER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
