<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Archer Daniels Executives Are Found Guilty of Price Fixing</title>
    <meta content="18ARCH$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980919T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cartels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lysine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Informers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whistle-Blowers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Archer Daniels Midland Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andreas, Dwayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andreas, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitacre, Mark E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Terrance S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichenwald, Kurt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cartels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4D91730F93BA2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Archer Daniels Executives Are Found Guilty of Price Fixing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eichenwald, Kurt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three former executives of Archer Daniels Midland Co, including son of powerful chairman Dwayne Andreas, are foundy guilty by Federal jury in Chicago of engaging in international conspiracy to fix prices of feed additive lysine; decision marks important victory for Government in its six-year effort to crack illegal corporate cartel involving grain giant; Andreas was unable to use enormous political influence on behalf of son and heir apparent, Michael Andreas; photo; other defendants are Terrance S Wilson and Mark E Whitacre; Whitacre was whistle-blower, but lost immunity for secretly taking millions of dollars from company while working as Government informant (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three former executives with the Archer Daniels Midland Company -- including the son of its powerful chairman, Dwayne Andreas -- were found guilty yesterday of engaging in an international conspiracy to fix the prices of a widely used additive for animal feed.</p>
        <p>The verdict by a Federal jury in Chicago marked an important victory for prosecutors, capping a six-year effort by the Government to crack an illegal corporate cartel and bring participants to trial. The investigation and trial have already been declared hallmarks by the Government, which said it upended a conspiracy that controlled the prices of $1 billion in commerce worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three former executives with the Archer Daniels Midland Company -- including the son of its powerful chairman, Dwayne Andreas -- were found guilty yesterday of engaging in an international conspiracy to fix the prices of a widely used additive for animal feed.</p>
        <p>The verdict by a Federal jury in Chicago marked an important victory for prosecutors, capping a six-year effort by the Government to crack an illegal corporate cartel and bring participants to trial. The investigation and trial have already been declared hallmarks by the Government, which said it upended a conspiracy that controlled the prices of $1 billion in commerce worldwide.</p>
        <p>But the case and yesterday's verdict have also had an enormous impact as well on Archer Daniels -- the self-proclaimed ''Supermarket to the World'' whose influence extends to virtually every grocery store aisle.</p>
        <p>For decades, the grain giant has been run as a virtual family fief under the iron-fisted control of Dwayne Andreas, one of the nation's most politically powerful executives who is known by presidents and prime ministers alike. Despite that influence, Mr. Andreas was unable to stop the weight of the judicial system from falling upon his son and onetime heir apparent, Michael.</p>
        <p>Over the seven-week trial, prosecutors presented evidence unlike any ever offered in court in a price-fixing case, including audio and video recordings of the illegal price-fixing meetings between the defendants and their international competitors who made the additive, known as lysine.</p>
        <p>The evidence, including testimony from co-conspirators, portrayed price fixing as far too common in the industry. Evidence was offered pointing to price fixing in at least one other product, and conspiracies among foreign competitors that dated back decades.</p>
        <p>The defendants were Michael D. Andreas, on paid leave from his position of vice chairman of Archer Daniels; Terrance S. Wilson, a former head of the company's corn-processing division, and Mark E. Whitacre, a former head of its bioproducts division, which manufactures lysine.</p>
        <p>Sentencing was set for Jan. 7. The men face a maximum penalty of three years in jail and a $350,000 fine. But the defendants could be forced to pay more, since under the law the Government is allowed to seek twice the amount gained in the crime or lost by the victims -- in this case, the purchasers of lysine.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Andreas nor Mr. Wilson showed any emotion when the jury of six men and six women announced their verdict. They left the courtroom without comment. Mr. Whitacre, who waived his right to attend the trial, was not in the courtroom.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Mr. Andreas and Mr. Wilson said that they would appeal the verdict. ''We've been fighting this for three years, and we are going to continue to fight it,'' said John Bray, a lawyer for Mr. Andreas. ''We're not through.''</p>
        <p>Bill Walker, Mr. Whitacre's lawyer, said that he believed that the jury had reached a conclusion on his client's guilt based in part on the recorded evidence against the other defendants. ''I hate to use the words 'guilt by association,' but that's the way it seems,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The conviction of Mr. Whitacre for price fixing is the latest turn in a series of events that has bedeviled this case from the beginning. It was Mr. Whitacre himself who first alerted the Government to price fixing at Archer Daniels in 1992. For the next two and a half years, he worked as a Government informant, secretly recording meetings with competitors and conversations at the highest reaches of the politically powerful company.</p>
        <p>But, soon after raids on Archer Daniels in 1995, Mr. Whitacre was discredited as a witness and eventually lost his immunity from prosecution when it was revealed that he had been secretly taking millions of dollars from the company, even while working as a Government informant. Mr. Whitacre contended that the money was provided as part of an under-the-table bonus plan at the company, but Government investigators concluded that was not true.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Whitacre pleaded guilty to fraud, and was sentenced to more than nine years in prison. Any additional sentence in the price-fixing case is likely to be concurrent, according to lawyers in the case, meaning it will not increase the time Mr. Whitacre spends in prison.</p>
        <p>Throughout the trial, attacking Mr. Whitacre's character was a central strategy of lawyers for Mr. Andreas and Mr. Wilson. They contended that no price fixing had ever occurred, and that Mr. Whitacre was an out-of-control informant who set up their clients. But almost all of the defendants' arguments were presented during cross-examination in the Government's case; the defense rested after little more than an hour.</p>
        <p>Despite the conviction, Mr. Walker said that Mr. Whitacre felt good about part of the verdict. ''He feels vindicated that they did prove there was price fixing,'' he said. ''But he didn't prove out the bonus plan. He is going to fight to prove out the bonus plan for the rest of his life.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors and agents with the Federal Bureau of Investigation expressed delight and relief at the verdict. ''It's been a very long time,'' said Brian Shepard, the F.B.I. agent who was most involved with Mr. Whitacre during the investigation. Mr. Shepard added that the case had ''completely dominated'' his life since 1992.</p>
        <p>James Griffin, the head of the Midwest office for the Justice Department's antitrust division, portrayed the victory as one that would help in the continued enforcement of antitrust laws. ''This verdict provides momentum for the division,'' he said. ''It proves juries will hold accountable business executives who engage in this kind of business activity that in effect defrauds Americans of millions of dollars a year.''</p>
        <p>At this time, Mr. Griffin said, the Justice Department has more than 30 grand juries looking into potential antitrust violations.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors said that both sides brought an enormous amount of resources to the case. ''This is one of the hardest-fought trials that I have ever been involved in, in terms of the firepower brought in by both sides,'' said Scott R. Lassar, the United States Attorney in Chicago. ''There was no stone left unturned by either the Government or the defense.''</p>
        <p>In part, the enormous legal firepower stemmed from the riches and influence won by the Andreas family during their decades at Archer Daniels. Since the time of Thomas E. Dewey -- the former New York Governor and Republican Presidential candidate who, when he was a lawyer in private practice, served as an adviser to Dwayne Andreas -- Archer Daniels has been a strong political force. With an ease that bred envy among other corporations, the $9.2 billion food industry giant navigated  between the Republicans and Democrats while helping to form this country's agricultural policies.</p>
        <p>During the trial, prosecutors portrayed Mr. Wilson, 60, as the man with the daily responsibility for the conspiracy. Michael Andreas, 49, was portrayed as providing approvals for strategy.</p>
        <p>But the prosecutors also said that Mr. Andreas was responsible for getting the conspiracy back on track when suspicions and cheating among the competitors led the prices to collapse. The central piece of evidence in support of that argument was a videotape, taken in October 1993, of a meeting between Mr. Andreas, Mr. Whitacre and the senior executives of the Ajinomoto Company, a Japanese competitor. Mr. Whitacre was acting as a Government informant at the time.</p>
        <p>On the videotape, Mr. Andreas appeared to be directing an effort to allocate shares of the lysine market in the coming year among competitors, a critical element of a price-fixing conspiracy. ''They can each have 2,000 tons more in 1994,'' Mr. Andreas said of the other lysine producers. ''And we get the rest between you and us.''</p>
        <p>That tape had impact not only on the jury, but on Archer Daniels itself. Once considered the most likely successor to his father, Mr. Andreas has since taken a paid leave of absence from the company. Had he been acquitted, Mr. Andreas had been widely expected to attempt a return to the company.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Archer Daniels said the company had no comment on the verdict.</p>
        <p>All told, the Government's investigation of the food and feed additive industries has resulted in eight criminal cases against nine corporations and 11 executives, almost all of whom pleaded guilty. Almost $200 million in fines have been imposed by courts or recommended as part of plea agreements with the Government. Archer Daniels itself pleaded guilty in 1996, and agreed to pay a $100 million fine.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 19, 1998, Saturday  A front-page article yesterday about three former executives found guilty of price fixing referred incorrectly in some copies to the full name of their company and the middle initial of one defendant. It is the Archer Daniels Midland Company, not Corporation; he is Terrance S. Wilson, not W.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 19, 1998, Saturday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about three former executives found guilty of price fixing referred incorrectly in some copies to the full name of their company and the middle initial of one defendant. It is the Archer Daniels Midland Company, not Corporation; he is Terrance S. Wilson, not W.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
