<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor and Medicaid: Old Puzzle, New Approach</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6D91338F933A15751C1A962958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor and Medicaid: Old Puzzle, New Approach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, ALISON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giuliani administration's call for sharp reductions in health and welfare benefits for the poor represents a new approach to an old problem: how to get New York City out from under the burden of Medicaid.</p>
        <p>With the cost of Medicaid steadily rising over the years, New York City mayors, Rudolph W. Giuliani included, have long battled for the state to pay the city's share of these health care costs for the poor.  But now Mr. Giuliani has opened a second front and is seeking state approval simply to slash city spending on the Federal program by nearly a third.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giuliani administration's call for sharp reductions in health and welfare benefits for the poor represents a new approach to an old problem: how to get New York City out from under the burden of Medicaid.</p>
        <p>With the cost of Medicaid steadily rising over the years, New York City mayors, Rudolph W. Giuliani included, have long battled for the state to pay the city's share of these health care costs for the poor.  But now Mr. Giuliani has opened a second front and is seeking state approval simply to slash city spending on the Federal program by nearly a third.</p>
        <p>The shift in strategy, intended to appeal to the new Republican administration in Albany, was signaled last week when Mr. Giuliani's budget director wrote to all city commissioners that the Mayor's second fiscal plan for the city would rely more on cutting health and welfare benefits for the poor than on scaling back government bureaucracy to close a $2 billion gap.</p>
        <p>The memorandum by the budget director, Abraham M. Lackman, showed that the Mayor's single largest target was Medicaid, with the Department of Social Services instructed to draft proposals for cutting city spending on the program by $900 million.</p>
        <p>Why mayor after mayor has been concerned with Medicaid costs has to do with New York City's peculiar relationship with New York State.</p>
        <p>In most parts of the country, Federal and state governments split the costs of Medicaid. But in New York -- in a formula that was born of upstate reluctance to pay for New York City's poor -- the state and its localities share Medicaid costs that are not met by the Federal Government.</p>
        <p>The result has been that Medicaid, at a cost of $2.6 billion a year to the city, is now the second largest item in its budget behind education, and more costly than the Police Department.</p>
        <p>The growth in Medicaid expenses has far outstripped inflation or the overall growth of city spending. "It has been growing on average at about 12 percent a year for the last four or five years," Mr. Lackman said. "It is the single biggest budget buster."</p>
        <p>For more than a decade, New York's mayors sought relief from this burden. Gov. Hugh L. Carey, a Democrat, was the first to propose that the state assume the full local share of Medicaid, as most states do. But neither Mr. Carey nor Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, a fellow Democrat, who embraced the idea after him, was able to push a complete Medicaid assumption through a Republican Senate loath to see the state take on such a fiscal burden.</p>
        <p>George E. Pataki, who will be the state's first Republican Governor in 20 years, parting company with his Democratic predecessors, says the state's fiscal condition is too dire even to consider a state Medicaid pickup in the coming year. But he has expressed interest in freeing cities from state mandates to provide services and programs. He has also asked Elizabeth P. McCaughey, the incoming Lieutenant Governor, to find ways to cut Medicaid costs.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Giuliani says he has not abandoned the quest for the state to assume all local Medicaid costs, he is betting that Mr. Pataki will allow him to make vast reductions in the program, reductions that a Democratic governor would have blocked.</p>
        <p>How the administration would actually reduce Medicaid expenditures is unclear. Mr. Giuliani could follow the lead of Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, whose administration recently announced a 20 percent reduction in Medicaid payments to hospitals.</p>
        <p>He could propose that the city stop paying for anything besides the basic services required by the Federal Government, no longer picking up the bill for prescription drugs, elective abortions, eyeglasses and prostheses.</p>
        <p>He could require many more of the city's 1.8 million Medicaid recipients to use managed care, or require the middle-class elderly who turn assets over to children so they can qualify for Medicaid payments for nursing homes to contribute to their own care.</p>
        <p>The Mayor could propose that the city sharply cut the number of single adults allowed on Home Relief, a state welfare program that automatically qualifies its recipients for Medicaid. Mr. Lackman has already called for scaling back public assistance programs by $300 million, which would mean a reduction in the number of individuals who receive Home Relief.</p>
        <p>In fact, some analysts said Mr. Giuliani would have to use every cost-cutting option imaginable to achieve his goal of nearly $1 billion in Medicaid savings. "That's a 33 percent cut," said James R. Tallon, president of the United Hospital Fund. "To do that you would probably have to be implementing all of the strategies simultaneously."</p>
        <p>Success for such changes of policy are far from assured, with virtually all of them needing approval from Albany either through legislation or a change in regulations, and some also needing Washington's sign-off.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Pataki might embrace plans to scale back health services for the poor, it is far from clear that the Democratic-controlled State Assembly would. Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver said that without details he could not comment.</p>
        <p>Hospitals also maintain a strong lobbying presence in Albany.</p>
        <p>And even with state government support, Mr. Giuliani would still have to push plans through an already restive Democratic-controlled City Council.</p>
        <p>Opposition is already building. Penelope W. Pi-Sunyer, executive director of the City Project, a coalition of advocacy and labor groups, wrote in an angry open letter to the Mayor that Mr. Lackman had outlined the proposals for cutting health and welfare for the poor on the same day that Mr. Giuliani had unveiled a package of tax breaks for landlords in lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Yet by planning to make more than half the savings needed to close next year's budget gap through cuts in Medicaid and other public assistance, Mr. Giuliani was challenging those who might oppose him yet share a commitment to New York City's fiscal health. How else would they find such savings in the new city budget?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
