<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toyota's Tercel infomercial draws a significant response from its youthful, hungry audience.</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="732385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGE, CHRONOLOGICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TOYOTA MOTOR CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HUDSON STREET PARTNERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, IRVING A (AD EXEC)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1D91338F933A15751C1A962958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toyota's Tercel infomercial draws a significant response from its youthful, hungry audience.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Bennet</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Toyota Motor Corporation believes it may have hit on the right technique to get through to young people today: a combination of daytime television, computer software and free food.</p>
        <p>Groping for a fresh way to promote the 1995 model of its small car, the Tercel, Toyota decided to try its first infomercial, testing a 28-minute advertisement in New York and Los Angeles during November. Toyota was hoping for a way to make the Tercel stick out from among its numerous competitors, which include Honda's Civic, Chrysler's Neon and General Motors' Saturn. The results were so encouraging that last week Toyota began broadcasting the advertisement in 15 markets around the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Toyota Motor Corporation believes it may have hit on the right technique to get through to young people today: a combination of daytime television, computer software and free food.</p>
        <p>Groping for a fresh way to promote the 1995 model of its small car, the Tercel, Toyota decided to try its first infomercial, testing a 28-minute advertisement in New York and Los Angeles during November. Toyota was hoping for a way to make the Tercel stick out from among its numerous competitors, which include Honda's Civic, Chrysler's Neon and General Motors' Saturn. The results were so encouraging that last week Toyota began broadcasting the advertisement in 15 markets around the country.</p>
        <p>The infomercial features brief comments from unidentified young Tercel buyers and customers in dealerships describing what they're looking for, and from youthful Toyota product specialists describing features of the car. It also includes interviews out on the street with young people, some of whom, Toyota said, were actors.</p>
        <p>A highly caffeinated hostess, Molly Scott, periodically bounced into the picture to urge callers to telephone a toll-free number for more information, and to sum up the ad's message.</p>
        <p>"You know what is so amazing about what we're seeing?" she asked at one point. "We're seeing that you can finally have the best of all worlds."</p>
        <p>The infomercial proved to be a superb vehicle for reaching the target audience, 18- to 35-year-olds, said Irving A. Miller, corporate advertising manager for Toyota Motor Sales, U.S.A. "They're a tough demographic to reach, and they also tend to watch television, when they do, at off hours," he said.</p>
        <p>Other auto makers have experimented with infomercials, but none has invested heavily in the format yet. As a result, the Tercel ad has the virtue of standing out from the crowd of 30-second spots showing cars racing through deserts. Mr. Miller said infomercials might be better suited to small cars for young people than to Toyota's more upscale products, like the new Avalon sedan.</p>
        <p>Toyota broadcast the advertisement on network affiliates on weekends, in the early morning hours or the middle of the afternoon, when ad time is cheaper. The infomercial, called "I want a car," was produced by Hudson Street Partners, a subsidiary of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi's Kobs &amp; Draft Worldwide direct marketing agency.</p>
        <p>While the effects of normal television advertisements are hard to measure, Toyota started tracking the infomercial's results immediately. About 7,000 people in the two markets called to order more information during the three-week tests, a result that Mr. Miller said delighted Toyota. A few months from now, Toyota plans to compare vehicle registration data with the addresses provided by callers to see how much of the curiosity resulted in sales.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles test drew more responses than the one in New York, because in Los Angeles Toyota also offered a free "night on the town" to anyone who requested the brochure and then visited a dealer to test-drive a Tercel.</p>
        <p>The evening out, the infomercial explains, consists of two movie tickets and dinner for two at "one of America's favorite restaurants" -- a Chili's Grill and Bar, in Los Angeles. Ads with the offer garnered twice the response of those without, so Toyota incorporated it into its general campaign. "They went for the burger every time," Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps a more surprising result came from the New York test, where Toyota offered to send information either in a brochure or on a computer disk. Sixty percent of the people who called requested the disk.</p>
        <p>The advertisement is broken down into seven segments, each for a specific aspect of the car: its styling, performance, interior, and so on. The ad does not dwell on price, but it does mention that the car starts at less than $10,000, and sells "nicely equipped at around $13,000."</p>
        <p>Interspersed with the product information are snippets from twentysomethings commenting on what they look for in a car.</p>
        <p>"I want my car to say that I'm 25," said one man, wearing a tie and what appears to be a leather jacket.</p>
        <p>Since none of the young people are identified, their observations do not always seem credible and occasionally they seem off the wall. One young man said he was concerned about fuel economy because "the cost of fuel has just skyrocketed."</p>
        <p>In another, more poignant moment, a young woman, who Toyota said was not an actress, explained why she becomes tearful when describing driving away from the lot in her Tercel, her first new car. "I've worked really hard to get to the point in my life where I could do something like this, she said, "so I feel pretty fortunate."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
