<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC Takes Aim at Tuesday Nights</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="703422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO (NBC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, BILL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ROSEANNE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FRASIER (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFD71431F932A3575BC0A962958260" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC Takes Aim at Tuesday Nights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARTER, BILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It will be the most anticipated face-to-face confrontation on television since Tonya vs. Nancy. But for the networks involved, the stakes will be much higher next month when "Frasier" takes on "Roseanne."</p>
        <p>"Frasier," an NBC series about a radio psychiatrist and his dysfunctional family, was the strongest new comedy on network television last year; "Roseanne," ABC's chronicles of the blue-collar Connor family of Lanford, Ill., has been the most consistently popular television program of the last six years. When both return for a new season next month, they will battle each other on Tuesdays at 9 P.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It will be the most anticipated face-to-face confrontation on television since Tonya vs. Nancy. But for the networks involved, the stakes will be much higher next month when "Frasier" takes on "Roseanne."</p>
        <p>"Frasier," an NBC series about a radio psychiatrist and his dysfunctional family, was the strongest new comedy on network television last year; "Roseanne," ABC's chronicles of the blue-collar Connor family of Lanford, Ill., has been the most consistently popular television program of the last six years. When both return for a new season next month, they will battle each other on Tuesdays at 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>At risk is one of the seven most cherished prizes in network television: a night. When one network dominates a night in prime time, it means millions of dollars of additional advertising revenue. Since "Roseanne" made its premiere in 1988, ABC has owned Tuesday night, in the same way NBC has owned Thursday night for longer than a decade.</p>
        <p>NBC is moving one of its powerful Thursday night programs ("Frasier" became a hit last season, sitting at 9:30 behind "Seinfeld") to Tuesdays with one goal in mind: to establish a beachhead on ABC's Tuesday territory.</p>
        <p>For ABC, the threat is serious enough for its programming department to have considered shifting "Roseanne" to Wednesdays at 9 P.M. while bringing in the network's biggest weapon, "Home Improvement," the top-rated program in all of television, to counter "Frasier" on Tuesdays.</p>
        <p>In a news conference two weeks ago, Ted Harbert, the president of ABC Entertainment, said that "all the options are open." But he said later in an interview that he would stick with "Roseanne" on Tuesdays, adding that he was confident it would easily brush off the "Frasier" challenge.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, ABC renewed its contract for "Roseanne" for three more seasons, at a price that has been estimated between $2 million and $3 million an episode. That is almost three times as much as a network usually pays for an established sitcom.</p>
        <p>"ABC is really at risk," said a senior executive of CBS, speaking on condition of anonymity. CBS was seriously pursuing "Roseanne" last winter, hoping to pry the series away from ABC.</p>
        <p>"We would have even paid more than ABC," the executive said. "But with NBC putting 'Frasier' against it, we could have lost our shirt. 'Frasier' has become a really strong show." A Shift in Momentum</p>
        <p>NBC drew criticism in the industry when it announced the move last May, because "Frasier" seemed too new to take on the mighty "Roseanne."</p>
        <p>Betsy Frank, senior vice president of Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Inc., was one of several advertising executives who questioned the wisdom of breaking up a hit night like NBC's Thursday and risking so strong a new show as "Frasier" against a proven hit like "Roseanne."</p>
        <p>But this summer, repeats of "Frasier" have consistently had higher ratings than those of "Roseanne" (though the two series are not yet head to head). And two weeks ago, "Frasier" was the highest-rated program in all of television.</p>
        <p>"Frasier" is also a serious contender for most of the comedy prizes at next month's Emmy Awards. "Roseanne," however, was not nominated for best comedy and received no nominations for comedy writing.  The Emmy Awards are often a signal of what the industry views as hot shows.</p>
        <p>Joel Segal, executive vice president of the McCann-Erickson advertising agency, said: "There is no question in my mind that 'Roseanne' is vulnerable. You have a show in its seventh season against a show in its second. The Roseanne that viewers saw at the end of last season is not the Roseanne they saw six years ago. She looks so physically different. She's not as likable."</p>
        <p>He added that " 'Frasier' won't win every week, but there will be weeks when he'll beat her."</p>
        <p>Ms. Frank has also backed away a bit from her initial opposition to the move. "NBC read me some financial information to prove they really don't have to do incredibly well for this to work out for them," she said. But she said the network was still risking damage on Thursday by setting up "Frasier" on Tuesday. A Programming Shuffle</p>
        <p>Replacing "Frasier" at 9:30 P.M. Thursdays on NBC is "Madman of the People," a new comedy about an irascible newspaper columnist. Ms. Frank considers the show weak, although she expects it to have high initial ratings because of its scheduling after "Seinfeld," NBC's biggest hit.</p>
        <p>In addition, other parts of NBC's Tuesday night attack, including a new comedy called "The Martin Short Show," are considered questionable. While Mr. Short is an established star, some industry executives wonder if the program's "show within a show" format, featuring some of his familiar characters like Ed Grimley, will be accepted by viewers.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Short's series will be broadcast at 8:30, its performance could have a big impact on the chances of "Frasier" at 9.</p>
        <p>"You have to look at the overall picture," said Mr. Harbert of ABC. He pointed to previous NBC moves of successful programs to other nights, like "Night Court" moving from Thursday to Wednesday and "Midnight Caller" moving from Tuesday to Friday. "NBC has a history of taking successful shows and moving them places where they're not as successful," Mr. Harbert said.</p>
        <p>One result of the moves, he said, is that NBC has marginal improvement on the new nights but suffers in the old time periods.</p>
        <p>NBC, however, is already selling the move of "Frasier" as a success. The program has bolstered overall advertising sales for Tuesday nights, NBC executives said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Frank said the shift could be good for advertisers. "I would say," she said, "that the move has given advertisers another potentially good night to reach urban, upscale viewers, people like Lexus buyers. They'll watch 'Frasier' more than they watch "Roseanne,' so they'll come to NBC on Tuesday night."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
