<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Blue Yonder, and Make It Wild</title>
    <meta content="05POSS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/05/fashion/05POSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1632229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="POSSESSED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Colman, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cavalli, Roberto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Italy</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Cavalli, Roberto</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDC1F3EF936A35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Blue Yonder, and Make It Wild</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Blue Yonder, and Make It Wild</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID COLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Colman, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Colman Possessed column discusses extravagant lifestyle of fashion designer Roberto Cavalli; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF God had wanted fashion designers to keep their heads out of the clouds, surely he would not have invented helicopters. At least that's the only logic that can explain why an outlandish Italian named Roberto Cavalli is flying around loose over the green hills of Tuscany, and has been for 25 years.</p>
        <p>Given Mr. Cavalli's larger-than-life proclivities, it does not come as a surprise that he should name as his favorite object a noisy and extravagant piece of machinery worthy of a newly minted Texas oil baron. ''It's my sixth child,'' Mr. Cavalli, the father of five, boasted cheerily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roberto Cavalli, the fashion designer, has been flying around loose over the green hills of Tuscany for 25 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF God had wanted fashion designers to keep their heads out of the clouds, surely he would not have invented helicopters. At least that's the only logic that can explain why an outlandish Italian named Roberto Cavalli is flying around loose over the green hills of Tuscany, and has been for 25 years.</p>
        <p>Given Mr. Cavalli's larger-than-life proclivities, it does not come as a surprise that he should name as his favorite object a noisy and extravagant piece of machinery worthy of a newly minted Texas oil baron. ''It's my sixth child,'' Mr. Cavalli, the father of five, boasted cheerily.</p>
        <p>This 64-year-old designer, beloved of rock stars and the handmaidens who style them, has never met an animal whose coat he didn't envy. (It is eerily perfect that he should be sponsoring ''Wild,'' the show of animal-theme fashion at the Costume Institute of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, which opens Tuesday.)</p>
        <p>''I love to live intensively,'' said Mr. Cavalli, who fell in love with the state-of-the-art French helicopter the instant he saw it at an unveiling in Italy in 1979. ''I knew I had to make a decision. If I waited five minutes more, I wouldn't do it.'' At a price of about $500,000, it was not a checkout-counter impulse buy; but then, this is a man who, two years earlier, fell in love with a contestant at a Miss Universe pageant at which he was a judge -- she was first runner-up -- and pursued and married her.</p>
        <p>But as conspicuous as Mr. Cavalli and his designs are -- this is a man for whom zebra print is a neutral -- he insists that the flashy show of taking off into the wild blue yonder is actually about introversion, not extroversion. For one thing, what distinguishes him from the throng of millionaire copter enthusiasts is that he pilots it himself. Because a helicopter is among the hardest aircraft to fly -- stability being crucial, you really can't take your hands off the controls -- he took lessons for a year and a half before he assumed ownership.</p>
        <p>For years Mr. Cavalli has used the copter to hop among Florence, where he lives and where his business is based, Milan and Paris (he has another house, a vineyard and a horse-breeding farm outside Siena), but he said that the Squirrel, as the Aerospatiale AS 350 is known, is now more pleasure craft that anything.</p>
        <p>''You definitely expect to see a businessman in this thing,'' he allowed. ''For me it's a completely different feeling. I love to be in the sky, closer to God.'' An airplane, he said, has no allure for him. ''With this, you can stop and hover, or land anywhere you want. It's like scuba diving in the sky.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavalli, who also has three Ferraris, is a bit inconsistent when it comes to whether he actually communes with nature in the machine, which is painted an iridescent color that changes from red to green to gold depending on the light. ''God didn't make man with wings,'' he said. ''So when man is able to do something that's against nature, it feels very special.''</p>
        <p>With such a dichotomy whirling in his head, it is fitting that Mr. Cavalli should love the helicopter, with its sublimely artificial access to the natural world. It is also a fitting match for his clothes, which in their leopard-spotted, loony splendor are, if anything, antigravity devices of their own.</p>
        <p>POSSESSED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
