<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For This Publisher, the East End Is a Profitable Subject</title>
    <meta content="05LIBOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1632202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hamptons (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abrams, Harry N, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mead, Julia C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Himmel, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E3DA1E3EF936A35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For This Publisher, the East End Is a Profitable Subject</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIA C. MEAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mead, Julia C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harry N Abrams Inc, publishing house noted for coffee-table books on art, photography, architecture, decor and gardening, produces steady of books about Long Island's East End or books by Long Islanders; Eric Himmel, editor in chief, comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT does a book editor do when he can't find a decent source on seaside gardening to help tame his scrappy corner of a Fire Island salt marsh? He publishes one himself, of course.</p>
        <p>That's what Eric Himmel, vice president and editor in chief at Harry N. Abrams Inc., did in 1994. The result, ''Seaside Gardening,'' by Ted James and Harry Haralambou of the North Fork, capitalized on what was then a blossoming interest in using beach grass and other native plants to landscape Long Island's waterfront. The book sold well and will be rereleased next year in an updated edition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT does a book editor do when he can't find a decent source on seaside gardening to help tame his scrappy corner of a Fire Island salt marsh? He publishes one himself, of course.</p>
        <p>That's what Eric Himmel, vice president and editor in chief at Harry N. Abrams Inc., did in 1994. The result, ''Seaside Gardening,'' by Ted James and Harry Haralambou of the North Fork, capitalized on what was then a blossoming interest in using beach grass and other native plants to landscape Long Island's waterfront. The book sold well and will be rereleased next year in an updated edition.</p>
        <p>The Abrams publishing house is 55 years old, and highly regarded for its quality, coffee-table tomes on art, photography, architecture, décor and gardening. But for as long as anyone there can remember, the company has also produced a steady stream of books about the Island or by Long Islanders. No one at the company planned this sub-specialty; most of the books, ''Seaside Gardening'' among them, arose separately and serendipitously, Mr. Himmel said in a telephone interview from his Manhattan office.</p>
        <p>An editor interested in sports photography signed Walter Iooss Jr., the Sports Illustrated photographer and a Montauk resident, to a three-book contract. His ''Classic Baseball'' was released last year, and his ''Classic Golf'' came out this year.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Abrams published ''The Art of Peter Max'' by Charles A. Riley II, a Baruch College professor who has a house in Cutchogue. Mr. Riley's third book, ''The Jazz Age in France,'' also published by Abrams, will be out this month.</p>
        <p>The company has also published books about Guild Hall Museum, in East Hampton, and the Parrish Art Museum, in Southampton, among other local cultural institutions.</p>
        <p>''In a sense, the East End is an obvious source for us, with its concentration of people who care about art, décor and gardening,'' Mr. Himmel said. ''And they're also trendsetters, influential on lifestyle elsewhere.''</p>
        <p>''Virtually everyone in the New York art world spends summers, or part of the summer there,'' he added. ''And you could say that about Abrams executives as well.''</p>
        <p>As a result, most of Abrams's Island books have dealt with East End subjects.</p>
        <p>''A publisher looks for interesting regions that will sustain strong sales,'' Mr. Himmel said. ''The Adirondacks have an interesting history and culture, but not a hell of lot of bookstores.''</p>
        <p>The Island has a robust market of independent and big-chain bookstores, and consumers willing to pay $50 or more for a coffee table book, he said. And Manhattan, thick with part-time Hamptonites, is a strong market for books about the South Fork, he added.</p>
        <p>Still, ''The Natural History of Long Island,'' published in 1997, failed to sell. Mr. Himmel attributed this to the fact that the book dealt with the entire Island's ecosystem. Between the East River and the Eastport-Manorville Road, the gateway to the East End, the Island lacks the cohesive regional identity, at least in terms of book sales, that makes the Hamptons so marketable, he said.</p>
        <p>''People who live on the East and West Coasts call everything else 'fly-over country,' and much of the Island is drive-through country for people from the city,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he has high expectations for a book on the North Fork wine country that is due out next year. For decades the quieter, more rural, and far less hyped sister of the South Fork, the North Fork has only recently begun to draw enough attention to sustain a book, he said.</p>
        <p>One of the more recent Island titles is ''Hamptons Pleasures'' by Susan P. Meisel and Ellen Harris, published this year. The book is their second for Abrams; the first was ''The Hamptons: Life Behind the Hedges.'' Both are lushly photographed homages to the natural and landscaped beauty of the South Fork.</p>
        <p>A third work is in progress, also to be published by Abrams.</p>
        <p>''We're hoping for a boxed set of six,'' Ms. Meisel said with a laugh, signing copies of the latest book at a bookstore in Sag Harbor. Both she and Ms. Harris have summer homes in Sagaponack.</p>
        <p>The authors brought their first manuscript to Abrams when Paul Gottlieb was the editor in chief. Mr. Gottlieb was a longtime friend of Jack Lenor Larsen, the textile designer, who founded the manufacturer Larsen International and created the LongHouse Foundation in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>One outcome of their friendship was Mr. Larsen's ''A Weaver's Memoir,'' equal parts autobiography, career retrospective and design how-to, published by Abrams in 1998.</p>
        <p>In 2002, Abrams released ''Studios by the Sea: Artists of Long Island's East End,'' written by Bob Colacello and photographed by Jonathan Becker, both of Vanity Fair magazine. Mark Magowan, Abrams's former publisher, has a house in Southampton, and brought Mr. Becker to the project, Mr. Himmel said.</p>
        <p>Drawing from the region's longstanding reputation as an artist's haven, the book juxtaposes 200 color photographs of famous artists and their studios against anecdotes about the more famous among them.</p>
        <p>The studios of Willem de Kooning, Childe Hassam and Roy Lichtenstein are shown preserved as the late artists left them. Green River cemetery, in Springs, where the giants of Abstract Expressionism -- notably Jackson Pollack -- and other artists are buried, is featured.</p>
        <p>Artists of the present -- David Salle, April Gornick, Larry Rivers, Julian Schnabel, Ross Bleckner, Eric Fischl and others -- muse on why the East End has become sacred artistic ground.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schnabel lives in Montauk, in a century-old landmark house that appears in the book. A year after ''Studios'' was published, Abrams released ''Julian Schnabel,'' a six-pound, 368-page, $75 chronicle of his 30-year career as painter, photographer, sculptor and filmmaker.</p>
        <p>A surfer, Mr. Schnabel introduced Michael Dweck, a photographer and fellow surfer, to Abrams. From that came ''The End: Montauk, N.Y.,'' Mr. Dweck's depiction of that scruffy, colorful hamlet and its history as a surfing spot. Published this year, ''The End'' sold out its first printing of 5,000 books in less than three weeks and is going into a second printing.</p>
        <p>And just last week, Abrams released a lavish monograph on the artist Jane Freilicher, celebrating her 50-year career. The text is by Klaus Kertess, who has a summer house in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
