<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rich Fabrics, and Remnants of the Past</title>
    <meta content="05COLM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/05/nyregion/thecity/05colm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1632336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Carolina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scalamandre (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">South Carolina</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Smithsonian Institution</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York State Museum</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Anthropologie</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2D81631F936A35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rich Fabrics, and Remnants of the Past</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rich Fabrics, and Remnants of the Past</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anemona Hartocollis Coping column on move of luxury fabric maker Scalamandre from New York to South Carolina and sale of its looms, warping wheels and other decades-old machinery; these artifacts of bygone industrial era are attracting decorators, bargain-hunters, artists and prop-stylists to Scalamandre factory in Long Island City; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHARLES DICKENS might have felt at home the other day wandering the Scalamandré factory in Long Island City, Queens, perhaps incognito among the decorators, bargain-hunters, artists and prop-stylists attracted to what was billed as the Scalamandré artifact sale. Not because the Victorian-style factory is a center of oppression. On the contrary, generations of the same families have worked there happily making textiles and wallpaper fine enough to hang in the best rooms on Park Avenue, in East Hampton and in the White House.</p>
        <p>Dickens would have felt at home simply because Scalamandré is a true-life, old-fashioned factory, not a museum piece but a living, breathing, though vanishing form of production in New York, where the Industrial Revolution increasingly seems as vestigial as its ideological soul mate, Marxism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Scalamandré factory in Long Island City, Queens, which has made fine textiles and wallpaper for generations, is moving to South Carolina.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHARLES DICKENS might have felt at home the other day wandering the Scalamandré factory in Long Island City, Queens, perhaps incognito among the decorators, bargain-hunters, artists and prop-stylists attracted to what was billed as the Scalamandré artifact sale. Not because the Victorian-style factory is a center of oppression. On the contrary, generations of the same families have worked there happily making textiles and wallpaper fine enough to hang in the best rooms on Park Avenue, in East Hampton and in the White House.</p>
        <p>Dickens would have felt at home simply because Scalamandré is a true-life, old-fashioned factory, not a museum piece but a living, breathing, though vanishing form of production in New York, where the Industrial Revolution increasingly seems as vestigial as its ideological soul mate, Marxism.</p>
        <p>Walking up the iron staircase to the second floor, the writer might have met people like Donata Restaino, who was bending over her warping wheel, and Ameer Baig, who was twisting 34-foot strands of silken thread into cords up to two inches thick by hand.</p>
        <p>The author might have heard how one of the people lured by the sale cast a covetous eye on Ms. Restaino's wheel when she had stepped away and an obliging sale manager slapped a ''SOLD'' sticker on it. Ms. Restaino, heartbroken, went straight to Robert F. Scalamandré Bitter, the grandson of the company's founder.</p>
        <p>''Bob, they put a 'sold' sticker on my warping wheel,'' she said, eyes watering.</p>
        <p>''Donna, you take that sticker off,'' Mr. Bitter replied. ''That was a mistake.''</p>
        <p>He was merely postponing the inevitable. Just before Christmas, after the place has been scavenged by artifact hunters, tools like Ms. Restaino's warping wheel, the clattering cast-iron and wooden looms, and much of the other machinery that has been operating at this factory since 1929 will be cleared out so the building can be sold to a Manhattan developer. Scalamandré is moving its manufacturing to South Carolina.</p>
        <p>In what Mr. Bitter hopes will be some consolation, many of his 100 workers will go home with pockets fat with severance and holiday pay. A few will remain in Queens filling custom orders for trim. A few more will move to the factory's new location.</p>
        <p>If Dickens were around, he might be in the startling position of wanting to write a morality tale not about the oppression of factory workers but about New York's transition from industrial to post-industrial. Who could have envisioned a time when all those quaint old Victorian enterprises -- the fish market, the flower market, the meat market, the silk mill -- would be closing, shrinking or moving, and industrial zoning changed to entice luxury condos, restaurants and shops?</p>
        <p>Call him sentimental, but Mr. Bitter had to pause for a moment to regain his composure as he wondered aloud whether a city could survive on the strength of hyperventilating real estate prices, could sustain creative people, like his designers, disconnected from the means of production. ''There might be other societies and cultures that have done it,'' he said. ''But I strongly think manufacturing needs to be part of the mix.''</p>
        <p>Scalamandré's customers, the people living in the city's proliferating luxury apartments, need not worry. The lustrous fabrics that inspired Jacqueline Kennedy to write a thank-you note from the White House in 1961 (''Dear Mr. Scalamandré: The soft green taffeta and fringe are divine.'') will still be sold at the new Scalamandré showroom on East 59th Street.</p>
        <p>Those who cannot afford Scalamandré can see its looms preserved in the Smithsonian Institution or perhaps at the New York State Museum in Albany, which sent two history curators, Craig Williams and Geoff Stein, to the artifact sale. ''We're looking for things that represent the production here,'' Mr. Williams said.</p>
        <p>Truly discerning New Yorkers might also spot Scalamandré artifacts at Anthropologie, the purveyor of clothing and decorative items inspired by flea markets and travel. Tami Lee, a member of what is called the Anthropologie visual team, made repeat visits to the artifact sale, her eyes aglow. She bought bundles of punch cards used to guide yarns, along with battered and paint-spattered wooden ladders, stools and easels; silk-screens of vintage Scalamandré designs like cupids and flowers; and roll upon roll of fringes and tassels. These items will be used as props in the company's stores.</p>
        <p>''It has a decadence to it,'' Ms. Lee said of the pieces she acquired. ''Aesthetically, the whole feeling of everything they do here is kind of the whole feeling of Anthropologie.''</p>
        <p>In short, anthropological.</p>
        <p>COPING E-mail: amh@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: amh@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
