<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Sinead O'Connor, Songs to Answer Her Own Prayers</title>
    <meta content="11POPL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE POP LIFE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="936207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE POP LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">X-Men (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Invisibl Skratch Picklz (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, Sinead</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/The Pop Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3DC113CF932A25755C0A961958260" item-length="1351" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Sinead O'Connor, Songs to Answer Her Own Prayers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pop Life column interviews Sinead O'Connor, whose new album, Gospel Oak, represents shift from angry and indignant lyrics to style that is more soothing; also interviews members of Invisibl Skratch Picklz and X-men, disk jockey collectives currently appearing in concert at Wetlands; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last month, Sinead O'Connor gave one of her friends a copy of her new mini-album, ''Gospel Oak.'' The friend decided to listen to it on her car stereo on the way to the park with her dog, who was overexcited and rambunctious, making driving difficult. But as soon as the music began, Ms. O'Connor said, ''the dog just totally fell asleep, passed over on the seat like a human.''</p>
        <p>Was Ms. O'Connor insulted? No, she said, she was rather proud. It let her know that the album works.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last month, Sinead O'Connor gave one of her friends a copy of her new mini-album, ''Gospel Oak.'' The friend decided to listen to it on her car stereo on the way to the park with her dog, who was overexcited and rambunctious, making driving difficult. But as soon as the music began, Ms. O'Connor said, ''the dog just totally fell asleep, passed over on the seat like a human.''</p>
        <p>Was Ms. O'Connor insulted? No, she said, she was rather proud. It let her know that the album works.</p>
        <p>''What I hope to do with my songs, besides making a living, is to provide some kind of soothing,'' she said. ''They have that effect on me, and the life that they give me has that effect on me.''</p>
        <p>In a way, Ms. O'Connor's entire career has been about trying to soothe herself. Even the angry and indignant songs on her first album 10 years ago and controversial acts like refusing to perform after ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' at one concert and tearing up a picture of the Pope on ''Saturday Night Live'' have been attempts to make peace with herself and her active conscience, even if no one gave her much peace about those actions.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connor is performing on Saturday at the Guinness Fleadh, a weekendlong festival of Irish culture scheduled to take place on three stages on Randalls Island; some 40,000 people are expected to show up to hear an enormous roster of mostly Irish and Irish-American performers. Her own hourlong set should be controversy-free.</p>
        <p>When asked if she had any political or religious messages planned, Ms. O'Connor replied: ''I think I'll let the music say that. I've put the strength of how I feel in my lyrics.'' Her performance, she said, will focus on Irish themes, which includes most of the songs on ''Gospel Oak.''</p>
        <p>''I think there are about four levels to them,'' she said of her new songs. ''They're lullabies that I wrote for myself. They're lullabies for other people. They're all love songs. And they're also what I would call Irish nationalist songs.''</p>
        <p>If ''Universal Mother,'' her previous album, ''was a prayer, then these are the answers,'' she said. ''In that sense, the songs are also hymns. I also like the idea of calling it 'Gospel Oak,' because the oak is a symbol of the worship of the mother. So it's the gospel of the mother.''</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connor said that when not performing at the Fleadh, she would try to catch performances by, among others, Christy Moore, Luka Bloom, Van Morrison and Davy Spillane. There are more than 40 other acts on the bill, including Richard Thompson, Shane MacGowan, Black 47, Mary Black, Saw Doctors and Altan.</p>
        <p>As demonstrated by the Guinness Fleadh and other recent events, like a compilation of Irish artists setting poetry by Yeats to music, Ireland has a cohesive musical community. And although Ms. O'Connor lives in England and has swapped Christianity for Rastafarianism, she feels part of it. ''It's an amazing thing,'' she said of the sense of camaraderie and collaboration. ''I think it exists in Jamaican music also. There is a friendship almost, a ring.''</p>
        <p>Enter the Turntablists</p>
        <p>With the rallying cry ''Give the drummer some,'' James Brown back in the 60's returned the spotlight to one of the most important and fundamental but often overlooked components of rhythm-and-blues. In the last year in hip-hop, his battle cry has been updated to ''Give the D.J. some.'' At Wetland's on Sunday night, the D.J. got some, in an all-night performance that featured two of the world's best disk-jockey collectives, Invisibl Skratch Picklz, of San Francisco, and the X-Men, of New York, plus a battle among 10 local disk jockeys.</p>
        <p>Unlike radio disk jockeys, who broadcast entire songs, and those in clubs, who seamlessly mix singles together, these performers do not just play records. They play with records, using the turntable as an instrument to create all kinds of sounds and effects, scratching the needle back and forth over a portion of a record and bouncing beats back and forth from one record to another. They are often called turntablists, to distinguish them from regular disk jockeys, though some of them, like D-Styles of the Skratch Picklz, prefer to think of what they do as turntable jazz.</p>
        <p>''I have routines that are similar to jazz songs with a set chorus and improvisation,'' he said. ''A lot of the times, I'll model myself after Miles Davis and Coltrane.''</p>
        <p>Compared with the first scratchings and battles that appeared at the dawn of rap, the art form and its practitioners have gotten a lot more sophisticated, most likely as a result of having to invent new turntable tricks to outdo competitors. At Wetlands, D-Styles made some slow, soulful, very un-turntable-like sounds that had the entire audience gasping and applauding. And when Rob Swift and D.J. Total Eclipse of the X-Men (who sometimes perform as a four-turntablist band) created fast, complex new beats using just two sounds on two records -- their hands moving so fast they were blurs -- they were rewarded with rapturous applause.</p>
        <p>Because of such talent and the inclusion of scratching and other turntable effects on albums by Portishead, Tricky, Dr. Octagon and others, the style is attracting a bigger, more diverse audience.</p>
        <p>''I remember around '92 I started feeling like the whole art form was dying, because at most battles the attendance was real low,'' said Mr. Swift, 25, who recently released a double-album of turntable music, ''Soulful Fruit'' (Stone Throw Records). ''But in the last year it's taken off again. This whole hip-hop thing started with the D.J., and it's returning to that.''</p>
        <p>At Wetlands, new and younger disk jockeys tried to distinguish themselves in a three-round competition in which each performer was given 90 seconds to make an impression. That may not sound like a lot of time, but from the first two seconds or so, it was evident who had skills and who didn't. Often, just watching the way they used their hands before a performance was an indication of their dexterity on the turntables.</p>
        <p>Some competitors tried juggling old-school beats, others scratched verbal taunts by L. L. Cool J and Big Daddy Kane, and others tried to impress the crowd with their stylistic flourishes like mixing behind their backs or with their noses. D.J. Gabbie even followed a lyric on one of his records, ''straight no chaser,'' by drinking a shot as part of his 90-second routine. Part of the beauty of a disk jockey battle is watching how  two hands deal with three instruments -- two turntables and a mixer -- not to mention all the records that must be quickly changed. In the finals, Do Boy played a routine so tight and musical that by the frightened, almost queasy look on the face of his competitor, Roli Rho, it was obvious who the winner would be.</p>
        <p>In the future, chances are that music fans will be hearing a lot more from these and other turntable artists as they release their first albums (the Skratch Picklz and the X-Men both have debut albums due on Asphodel Records later this year); collaborate more (the Skratch Picklz will be performing with Dr. Octagon on Lollapalooza this summer and D.J. Disk of the Picklz will be with Bill Laswell's Praxis at the Anchorage under the Brooklyn Bridge on Friday night), and, of course, as they keep innovating.</p>
        <p>''Every day I ask myself, what can I do that I haven't done yet?'' said  Mr. Swift of the X-Men. ''How can I express myself in a new way through the turntable?''</p>
        <p>THE POP LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
