<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investors Punish Centocor for More Bad News</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="584118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEPTIC SHOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENTOXIN (DRUG)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUGS (PHARMACEUTICALS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTOCOR INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LILLY, ELI, &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D6143CF93AA25752C0A965958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investors Punish Centocor for More Bad News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street can be unforgiving of biotechnology stocks that fail to deliver on their promises.</p>
        <p>That was quite evident yesterday when Centocor Inc. disclosed that it was stopping clinical trials in the United States on its leading new drug for the treatment of sepsis, an often-fatal bacterial infection, and was temporarily suspending sales in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wall Street can be unforgiving of biotechnology stocks that fail to deliver on their promises.</p>
        <p>That was quite evident yesterday when Centocor Inc. disclosed that it was stopping clinical trials in the United States on its leading new drug for the treatment of sepsis, an often-fatal bacterial infection, and was temporarily suspending sales in Europe.</p>
        <p>The move follows an outside review of interim data showing a higher death rate among patients receiving the drug than among those who received a placebo.</p>
        <p>Investors reacted with a vengeance to the announcement, which was made before the stock market opened yesterday. Centocor's stock plummeted by two-thirds when trading began and ended the day at $6.625, down $11.125, on extremely heavy over-the-counter trading of nearly 14 million shares.</p>
        <p>The stock is now down nearly 90 percent from its all-time closing high of $59.75 almost exactly a year ago. Since then, Wall Street has been repeatedly surprised by problems with the Centocor anti-sepsis drug, Centoxin.</p>
        <p>Centocor's plunge yesterday also depressed the stock of Eli Lilly &amp; Company, which has invested $100 million in the Malvern, Pa., company. Lilly's shares fell $1.50, to $59.875, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Centoxin was once considered the leading candidate for an effective treatment of sepsis, which strikes about 200,000 Americans a year, killing about half of them. But in April, the Food and Drug Administration turned thumbs down on Centoxin, despite an advisory panel's recommending its approval, when the agency learned that Centacor had changed the parameters of its clinical trials after viewing interim results, possibly skewing the outcome.</p>
        <p>Centacor began a second trial in June, in hopes of salvaging the drug. But those hopes seemed dashed yesterday.</p>
        <p>"I think Centoxin is done as a product," said James McCamant, editor of the Medical Technology Stock Letter, an industry publication based in Berkeley, Calif. "I'm surprised the bad news came this quick," he said, "but I thought the odds were high they wouldn't have positive results." Safety Not Previously at Issue</p>
        <p>In its first trial, Centoxin was stymied by its inability to show a statistically significant reduction in deaths among the broad group of patients. Only in a subgroup, whose sepsis was caused by so-called gram-negative bacteria, did the drug prove effective.</p>
        <p>Given the drug's high cost -- $3,750 a dose in countries where it has been approved -- doctors might be reluctant to prescribe it without evidence it could help most patients. There is no timely way to determine which bacteria are the cause of sepsis before administering the drug.</p>
        <p>Safety of the drug was not previously in question. But the interim review of data from the second trial now show a higher death rate among patients who were treated with Centoxin but turned out not to have gram-negative bacteria, compared with patients in the same group who received a placebo.</p>
        <p>David P. Holveck, Centacor's president and chief executive, said the company would now review the data to try to determine the cause of the higher mortality among these patients. "We did not see it in the first clinical study," he said.</p>
        <p>Possible causes could include underlying diseases in the patients, mishandling of the drug in one or more of the more than 500 hospitals enrolled in the study, or defects in the start-up of drug production. "These are questions we need to answer," he said.</p>
        <p>Answers, however, may be difficult to get. With several hundred hospitals involved, it is certainly possible for slip-ups to have occurred. But determining where and when could prove impossible, because in the trial the doctors did not know at the time whether they were administering Centoxin or the placebo.</p>
        <p>And because sepsis is usually brought on by a previous injury, surgery or severe burns, death from other causes is also possible, but again difficult to prove. Still, the burden is on Centocor to prove some other cause of death, or Centoxin has no future. Lilly's Investment</p>
        <p>Many analysts, in fact, had been saying since April that the drug had no future, although some took heart in a deal Centocor struck with Lilly after Centoxin's rejection by the F.D.A. For a $100 million investment, Lilly obtained marketing rights to Centoxin, as well as the option to market Centorx, a drug currently awaiting F.D.A. approval. Centorx is intended to prevent the reclogging of cardiac arteries following surgical or medical procedures.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the deal, if Centoxin is approved in 1993, Lilly could acquire rights to Centorx for $25 million; if Centoxin is not approved, Lilly is to acquire the rights to Centorx for free.</p>
        <p>"Charitably, even if Centoxin is not harmful, it does not appear to be effective either," said Viren Mehta, an analyst with Mehta &amp; Isaly Worldwide Pharmaceutical Research, who has long held a bearish view on Centacor.</p>
        <p>Centoxin, if successful, would have been highly complementary with Lilly's strong position in antibiotics. Now, "Centorx is essentially the only drug left for Lilly to save some face," Mr. Mehta said.</p>
        <p>Wole M. Fayemi, an analyst with Hambrecht &amp; Quist, said a case could be made for Centocor to survive, even without Centoxin. "If they do pull the trial and pull this product, you'll see a reduction in costs going forward," he said. That would allow the company to survive longer on the $150 million in cash it now has.</p>
        <p>As recently as last week, Mr. Fayemi recommended Centocor shares, saying the company was "poised to make a dramatic comeback."</p>
        <p>Mr. Holveck said the deal with Lilly and a trimming of Centacor's work force last summer were intended to make the company viable with or without Centoxin. "The whole aim from last April was to position and build the company with a broad array of products," including Centorx and some diagnostic agents, he said. "Unfortunately, we get labeled as the Centoxin company."</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
