<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Air Redoing Plan With USAir</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="584049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">USAIR GROUP INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH AIRWAYS PLC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DA1E3BF93AA25752C0A965958260" item-length="476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Air Redoing Plan With USAir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>British Airways and USAir are said to be preparing a new plan of combined operations in an attempt to overcome opposition of United States carriers to an agreement that was withdrawn last month.</p>
        <p>The Financial Times of London reported yesterday that the two airlines would announce an agreement at the end of the week that would give British Airways about a 20 percent voting stake in USAir for an investment of $340 million. The British carrier is also said to be willing to drop its insistence on veto power over large expenditures by USAir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>British Airways and USAir are said to be preparing a new plan of combined operations in an attempt to overcome opposition of United States carriers to an agreement that was withdrawn last month.</p>
        <p>The Financial Times of London reported yesterday that the two airlines would announce an agreement at the end of the week that would give British Airways about a 20 percent voting stake in USAir for an investment of $340 million. The British carrier is also said to be willing to drop its insistence on veto power over large expenditures by USAir.</p>
        <p>One airline executive said such an agreement would not need the approval of the Department of Transportation because it would basically be a joint marketing agreement rather than a large ownership stake. The Government must approve any foreign stake in a domestic airline that exceeds 25 percent.</p>
        <p>John Lampl, a spokesman for British Airways in New York, said the carrier would have no comment on speculative reports.</p>
        <p>British Airways said earlier this month that it was trying to negotiate a new deal with USAir and that it hoped to fashion an agreement that would satisfy regulators in the United States. Talks Are Continuing</p>
        <p>In London, a spokeswoman for British Airways said talks with USAir were continuing, but declined to confirm that an agreement was near. "No deal has been finalized," she said.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for USAir, Patricia Goldman, said discussions were continuing but would not comment on the Financial Times reports.</p>
        <p>Under the original agreement, British Airways would have invested $750 million in USAir for a 44 percent stake. It would have had extensive authority on important decisions at USAir and would have been able to feed its international passengers into USAir's domestic route system. USAir would have gained access to British Airways' international system.</p>
        <p>But four United States airlines -- American, United, Delta and Federal Express -- lobbied the Government to squelch the deal. The airlines objected to the unwillingness of British Airways and the British Government to allow American carriers greater access to Britain.</p>
        <p>The proposed changes in the British Airways deal with USAir, however, would probably not be enough to satisfy American carriers. The competitors are less concerned about a foreign airline creating ties to an American carrier than they are about gaining greater rights abroad. But if a deal is structured in such a way that it does not require Government approval, the domestic carriers would not have a forum to oppose it.</p>
        <p>British Airways has been buffeted by bad publicity for the last week, since it apologized to Virgin Atlantic Airways and its chairman, Richard Branson, for a dirty-tricks campaign.</p>
        <p>Virgin has called on the British Government to strip British Airways of some of its landing slots at Heathrow Airport.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
