<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roshangarh Journal; As India Seethes, Old Rhythms Soothe a Village</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="584152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HINDUISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RURAL AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROSHANGARH (INDIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARGAN, EDWARD A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DA113FF93AA25752C0A965958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roshangarh Journal; As India Seethes, Old Rhythms Soothe a Village</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD A. GARGAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GARGAN, EDWARD A</byline>
      <dateline>ROSHANGARH, India</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sabir Ali combed his cream-white beard with his gnarled fingers and broke into a toothless grin. "Oh, yes," he said, "I'll plow fields for Hindus this year, just like every year."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ali, a Muslim, has lived in this village of 3,000, half Hindu, half Muslim, his whole life, "50 or 60 years," he said, shaking his head slightly at the blur of years that makes precision unnecessary, and impossible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sabir Ali combed his cream-white beard with his gnarled fingers and broke into a toothless grin. "Oh, yes," he said, "I'll plow fields for Hindus this year, just like every year."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ali, a Muslim, has lived in this village of 3,000, half Hindu, half Muslim, his whole life, "50 or 60 years," he said, shaking his head slightly at the blur of years that makes precision unnecessary, and impossible.</p>
        <p>"I was born here," Mr. Ali said, "but I'm not an educated person, so I don't know much. I'd say earlier on it was very good in terms of brotherhood. But now it may not be so good. But it is not the worst either."</p>
        <p>It is in villages like this, one of thousands scattered across northern India, the so-called cow belt of Hindi-speaking, largely believing Hindus, where the future of relations between the country's Hindus and Muslims will be decided.  Thousands Are Killed</p>
        <p>After the destruction of a 16th-century mosque in Ayodhya by Hindu militants, Muslims in dozens of towns and cities vented their rage at Hindus, and Hindus retaliated in kind. Thousands died. But in villages away from the density and tensions of urban life, the rhythms of agricultural life bring Hindus and Muslims together, out of necessity surely, and even sometimes out of affection.</p>
        <p>Between pulls on the stem of a water-filled hookah, the new village headman in Roshangarh, Chaudri Dharamveer Singh, a Hindu, spoke about his knowledge of the events in Ayodhya.</p>
        <p>"I heard there was a temple that was demolished," he said. "There was a structure called gumbadh," or dome, "and inside there are idols of god and worship was going on. On Dec. 6, those domes were destroyed and in the process more and more idols of Hindu gods were recovered. This is what we heard."</p>
        <p>There was a bit of discussion between Mr. Singh and the other men who had gathered to share the hookah over whether the domes were built during the time of the Mogul emperors Akbar or Babur -- the mosque was built in Babur's reign in 1528 -- but no one seemed to know for sure.</p>
        <p>"The point," Mr. Singh finally said, "is that the Hindus feel it is a temple. The Muslims see a mosque. We say if there are idols in it it's a temple. The Muslims say if there were domes it was a mosque. That is why it was destroyed." A Tradition of Brotherhood</p>
        <p>"It was widely talked about in the village," he went on. "It's still an issue to talk about. Of course the Hindus don't agree with the Muslims and the Muslims don't agree with the Hindus."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Singh, who became headman last month when his predecessor, a Muslim, died of old age, said that village traditions prevented things from getting out of hand.</p>
        <p>"Of course we talk about these things like Ayodhya," he said, "but usually there is a relationship of brotherhood and we deliberately do nothing to destroy this atmosphere. I'm 37 years old and I don't remember any incident of violence here."</p>
        <p>This is not to say that there are not arguments that strain village concord, but these are more likely to rage over the cow chewing up a neighbor's crop than differences over religious squabbles hundreds of miles away. Still, as in all northern Indian villages, tradition dictates that Muslims live on one side of the community and Hindus on another.</p>
        <p>More prosperous than some villages, Roshangarh has convex brick lanes that weave between brick houses and mud huts. At communal wells, women fill large drums with water and deliver them to houses around the village. Rubber-wheeled carts hauled by snorting black water buffaloes squeeze down lanes.  Complaints Are Aired</p>
        <p>In Rajendra Kumar's house, a group of men wrapped in rough wool blankets against the morning cold lounged around, some trying out complaints about their Muslim neighbors.</p>
        <p>"There is a trend among Hindus to have two or three kids," Mr. Kumar said. "After that, that's enough.  These Muslims will not stop. They will keep producing and producing."</p>
        <p>A few murmurs of approval appeared as clouds of steam in the chilled air.</p>
        <p>"Earlier this sense of brotherhood was very strong," Mr. Kumar continued. "We treated them as family. But at times we think of them as enemies."</p>
        <p>At that point a short man with a beard, a soiled cap and a checked blanket shuffled into the room. It was Abdus Sattar, the village teacher.  One of the Hindus rose to give Mr. Sattar, a Muslim, the seat of honor.</p>
        <p>"If people had been religious this would not have happened," Mr. Sattar said. "No religion paves the way toward violence."</p>
        <p>"On the surface here," he continued, "everything seems to be all right. But whenever people discuss these issues, real feelings come to the surface and there is a clear-cut division of opinion. Yes, it is very serious, not now, but maybe in the future." But a goodly measure of brotherhood still seems to prevail in Roshangarh. Two weeks after the destruction of the mosque, Mr. Sattar was arrested for belonging to the Islamic Society, a fundamentalist group. Four days later, his Hindu neighbors helped gather enough bail to get him out of jail.</p>
        <p>"Our Hindu brothers came forward to help," Mr. Sattar said matter of factly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kumar concluded: "There are no specific problems really. Village life goes on."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
