<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comeback for Capek</title>
    <meta content="22HAMPLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/22/books/review/22HAMPLT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1450535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampl, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klima, Ivan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capek, Karel</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Carel Capek: Life and Work (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cross Roads (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic/Prague</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Czech Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Prague (Czech Republic)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Capek, Karel</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Klima, Ivan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDE133AF931A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comeback for Capek</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Literary Comeback for Karel Capek</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Patricia Hampl</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hampl, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Hampl reviews following books: Karel Capek: Life and Work by Ivan Klima; and Cross Roads by Karel Capek; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KAREL CAPEK</p>
        <p>Life and Work.</p>
        <p>By Ivan Klima.</p>
        <p>Translated by Norma Comrada.</p>
        <p>224 pp. North Haven, Conn.:</p>
        <p>Catbird Press. $23.</p>
        <p>CROSS ROADS</p>
        <p>By Karel Capek.</p>
        <p>Translated by Norma Comrada.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Paul Hoffman.</p>
        <p>256 pp. North Haven, Conn.:</p>
        <p>Catbird Press. Paper, $14.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Famous long ago, a Czech literary figure is being resurrected by his fans, including Ivan Klima, the author of a new biographical study.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KAREL CAPEK</p>
        <p>Life and Work.</p>
        <p>By Ivan Klima.</p>
        <p>Translated by Norma Comrada.</p>
        <p>224 pp. North Haven, Conn.:</p>
        <p>Catbird Press. $23.</p>
        <p>CROSS ROADS</p>
        <p>By Karel Capek.</p>
        <p>Translated by Norma Comrada.</p>
        <p>Illustrated by Paul Hoffman.</p>
        <p>256 pp. North Haven, Conn.:</p>
        <p>Catbird Press. Paper, $14.</p>
        <p>Literary fame is nothing if not capricious. Franz Kafka, virtually unknown beyond his devoted Prague circle when he died in 1924, has achieved the ultimate celebrity of becoming an adjective. ''That's totally Kafkaesque!'' people cry, knowing exactly what they mean, whether they've read a word of his work or not.</p>
        <p>Karel Capek (1890-1938), Kafka's Czech-speaking contemporary in Prague, has traveled the opposite route, from early fame to relative obscurity. Yet, as Ivan Klima says in his new, welcome biographical study, Capek was, with Kafka and Jaroslav Hasek (the author of ''The Good Soldier Svejk'') ''among the greatest figures of modern world literature.''</p>
        <p>It's a grand claim, and Klima, a notable international writer himself, makes it stick in ''Karel Capek: Life and Work.'' So does Capek's remarkable body of work, much of it recently made available in English (sometimes for the first time, often in fresh translations) by Catbird Press, whose publisher, Robert Wechsler, seems to be on a mission to bring Capek back to his rightful prominence in world literature.</p>
        <p>''Cross Roads,'' incorporating two early Capek story collections, is the latest in this ambitious publishing project, which includes Capek's brilliant dystopia, ''War With the Newts,'' and ''Tales From Two Pockets'' (generally considered his best story collection), as well as the biographical treasure, ''Talks with T. G. Masaryk.'' Wechsler also commissioned the Klima biography, the first biography of Capek in any language. Klima wrote it in Czech, but Norma Comrada's graceful English translation is its first appearance.</p>
        <p>From his early 20's, Capek was an indispensable figure in Czech literature and journalism. Thomas Mann, responding to ''War With the Newts'' during the downward spiral of the 1930's, told Capek that ''your satirical view of the abysmal craziness in Europe has something absolutely magnificent about it, and one suffers this craziness with you in following the story's grotesque and horrible events.''</p>
        <p>''R.U.R,'' the science fiction play that gave the world the word ''robot'' (coined not by Karel Capek, but by his beloved artist brother Josef), made him internationally famous in his early 30's. After that debut, his novels and plays were quickly translated and reviewed in England and America. In his relatively short life (he died just months after the Nazi takeover of Czechoslovakia in 1938) he produced plays, volumes of short stories, novels, political and literary essays, biography, travel and gardening pieces, and quantities of feuilletons, a newspaper form popular with the Czechs, akin to the elegant ''casual'' of The New Yorker, though Capek often gives it a sharp narrative twist, creating, as Klima notes, ''his own genre -- often on the borderline between short story and feuilleton,'' what today we might simply call the personal essay.</p>
        <p>The decline of Capek's reputation in this country probably says more about the fate of a great writer working in a small language than it does about the merit of his work. This slippage may also be proof of the disinclination of an imperial culture to sustain interest in ''smaller'' literatures.</p>
        <p>Also, it didn't help Capek's national or international reputation that his work was effectively banned during four decades of Communist rule. His intense meditations on democracy and culture and his close association with Tomas Garrigue Masaryk, the brilliant (but also banned) philosopher/president of the First Republic, were hardly the models of writerly behavior the regime wished to encourage. There was more. As Klima makes clear, ''no writer in Czechoslovakia (and very few elsewhere in the world) reacted with such accuracy . . . and with such passion to the Nazi takeover.'' But in 1924 Capek had published an equally vivid essay titled ''Why Am I Not a Communist?'' Not exactly ingratiating political moves.</p>
        <p>Czech writers like Milan Kundera and Klima read and admired Capek, and indeed learned from him, but, given the repressive political climate, they could not publish about him, and the next generation had great difficulty even finding his books. Czech scholarship was silent as well, and scholarship, after all, grooms dead writers for immortality -- for ''world literature.'' Internationally, Capek was relegated to the status of an entre deux guerres writer; he had not experienced World War II, the great conflagration of the West, and thus could seem irrelevant to Cold War concerns.</p>
        <p>Kafka, also a nonperson in Czechoslovakia during much of the Communist period, wrote in German, a ''world'' language, and so his work was spared the fate of his Czech-speaking countryman. It would be fascinating to know whether Kafka, whose Czech was very good and who was a devotee of the feuilleton, read Capek, given the uncanny (or inevitable?) parallels between these two Prague writers. Both were hypochondriac, given to deadpan fictions set in dreamscapes that feel weirdly real, using rigorously ordinary settings and circumstances to render profoundly inward experiences that crackle with political and even prophetic acuity. Both were drawn to detective and science fiction models for some of their best work, and both were the tortured authors of exquisitely anguished letters to fiancées they could not bring themselves to marry (though Capek, late in life, finally caved in and married his Olga).</p>
        <p>But small languages and world literature aside, the fact remains that, unlike the purist Kafka, Capek was a writer who was not wholly ''literary.'' As Klima helpfully notes, Capek wrote a great deal for the newspapers -- the highly literate, essay-hungry newspapers of Prague's vibrant First Republic during the period between the two world wars. Much of what he published was high journalism. He even titled one of his collections of essays and feuilletons ''In Praise of Newspapers and Other Essays.'' None of this boded well for an exalted posthumous literary reputation, in spite of his prodigious output of novels, stories and essays.</p>
        <p>Yet now, when nonfiction, and even a willful confusion of nonfiction and fiction, have become central literary preoccupations, Capek, with his mixed bag of forms, borrowings from pop culture and urgent voice, begins to sound very contemporary. His essays on the rise of National Socialism and racism, ''analyzing the causes of the deepening crisis of democracy in Europe in the 1930's, belong,'' as Klima points out, ''to the best of Czech or even European essay writing.'' They are also striking cautionary meditations on global tensions today.</p>
        <p>In his fiction, Capek also sounds a fresh note. In addition to the attractive swagger some of his protagonists derive from detective fiction, Capek finds in science fiction and crime fiction forms that allow his passion for ideas to take on flesh. He is not a writer interested in ''character'' in the realist sense. He is captivated by circumstance and chance.</p>
        <p>One of the curiosities of Czech culture during Capek's era was its exceptional embrace of Cubism. The Czechs were alone in treating Cubism as a full-spectrum movement, not simply a method for the canvas but a liberating revolution for virtually all the arts, and for perception itself. In Prague it is possible, for example, to take a walking tour of Cubist architecture, to drink from a Cubist teacup, to sit on a Cubist sofa. Capek, along with his brother Josef (a major figure in Czech art), saw in Cubism a freeing method for narrative as well. The stories in ''Cross Roads'' reveal shifts of tense and point of view, narrative jumbles and eloquent, spare images. It is tempting to claim them as postmodern in their trust of the fragment and their deft placement of image.</p>
        <p>Far from becoming brittle abstractions, Capek's abiding preoccupations with truth, justice and the apprehension of reality become poetic meditations in his stories. He earnestly pursues the ordinary, and this, together with his stylistic innovations, gives the parable-like stories in ''Cross Roads'' great resonance.</p>
        <p>''I don't solve anything,'' the police examiner in ''The Mountain'' explains to the story's frustrated protagonist, who is seeking to get to the bottom of an apparent murder. ''I cannot solve anything. I act in the name of the law, which rather than finding solutions makes decisions. The law only makes decisions about cases, and in its irrefutable procedures lies its strength.''</p>
        <p>It is a passage Kafka might have pondered -- or written.</p>
        <p>Patricia Hampl's most recent books are ''I Could Tell You Stories'' and a new edition of ''A Romantic Education.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patricia Hampl's most recent books are ''I Could Tell You Stories'' and a new edition of ''A Romantic Education.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
