<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Detains Cleric Linked to Militants</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="619102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THREATS AND THREATENING MESSAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEPORTATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ILLEGAL ALIENS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EGYPT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OTISVILLE (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABDEL RAHMAN, OMAR (SHEIK)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RENO, JANET (ATTY GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'AMATO, ALFONSE M (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE163BF930A35754C0A965958260" item-length="1439" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Detains Cleric Linked to Militants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, ALISON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surrounded by chanting supporters, Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, the Islamic fundamentalist whose followers have been linked to two bombing conspiracies, emerged from a Brooklyn mosque and surrendered to Federal authorities last night, ending a months-long Federal debate over the danger he posed as a free man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdel Rahman walked on the arm of his lawyer shortly after 6 P.M. from the Abu Bakr Elseddique mosque across the street to a firehouse that had become a Federal command post, after a day of negotiations over his detention on immigration charges. He was greeted cordially by Federal agents and lightly frisked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surrounded by chanting supporters, Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, the Islamic fundamentalist whose followers have been linked to two bombing conspiracies, emerged from a Brooklyn mosque and surrendered to Federal authorities last night, ending a months-long Federal debate over the danger he posed as a free man.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdel Rahman walked on the arm of his lawyer shortly after 6 P.M. from the Abu Bakr Elseddique mosque across the street to a firehouse that had become a Federal command post, after a day of negotiations over his detention on immigration charges. He was greeted cordially by Federal agents and lightly frisked.</p>
        <p>His supporters formed a human chain across the street and chanted, "God is the greatest" in Arabic. A handful of Hasidic Jewish onlookers from the ethnically mixed Midwood neighborhood shouted back, "Drop Dead! Drop Dead!"</p>
        <p>Officials said a helicopter was ready to fly Mr. Abdel Rahman to the Federal prison at Otisville in Orange County, N.Y. But they agreed to drive him the 75 miles after he said he did not want to fly. He arrived at 9:30 P.M., a prison spokesman said. 'We Are Not Conspiring'</p>
        <p>The cleric's decision to give himself up came after midday and evening prayer services for the Muslim Sabbath. "I might not stand in front of you again," a Saudi journalist who watched midday prayers quoted him as telling sobbing supporters. "We are not conspiring against America, even though we disagree with American policy."</p>
        <p>The apprehension of the blind, self-exiled Egyptian marked a change in policy for the Clinton Administration. Federal officials said they decided to take him into custody because they feared he would flee after his van eluded the Federal agents following him Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>But political pressures were also bearing down on Attorney General Janet Reno in the form of hostile editorials and the criticism of lawmakers like Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, the New York Republican who was reported to be a target of a bombing and assassination conspiracy disrupted last week.  [ Page 22. ]</p>
        <p>Federal officials had insisted for a week that they had no plans to arrest Mr. Abdel Rahman, citing weak evidence against him and a desire to leave him free as a surveillance tool to watch those drawn to him. Although investigators said they were convinced the cleric had been aware of a conspiracy to bomb the United Nations, 26 Federal Plaza and the Holland and Lincoln Tunnels, they called their evidence "fuzzy." Siddig Ibrahim Siddig Ali, identified by Federal officials as the ringleader of the latest bombing plot, had been Mr. Abdel Rahman's interpreter.</p>
        <p>A State Department official said last night that the United States had advised Egypt of its plan to detain Mr. Abdel Rahman but described the notification as a routine matter.</p>
        <p>In Egypt, the cleric's followers in the Islamic Group vowed a campaign of terror striking at Americans abroad and targets in the United States. Some law-enforcement officials also expressed concern that the sheik's detention could lead to revenge attempts by militant supporters in Brooklyn and New Jersey. Two Bomb Threats</p>
        <p>The State Department cautioned American travelers last night that the detention of Mr. Abdel Rahman "may precipitate strong reactions" among followers in Egypt and various degrees of disapproval elsewhere in the Islamic world.</p>
        <p>And while it said it had no specific information about potential incidents, it added that Americans who are overseas, especially those in the Middle East, "should be alert to continuing developments." Americans abroad should refer, it said, to the State Department's country-specific warnings, consular information sheets and regional travel brochures.</p>
        <p>On Thursday night two bomb threats disrupted traffic in the edgy city, as police removed a suspicious object from the Brooklyn Battery Tunnel and checked an abandoned car at Kennedy International Airport. The police said yesterday that the object recovered from the tunnel turned out to be only rope wrapped in a garbage bag. The bombing plot disrupted last week had been set symbolically for the Fourth of July, Federal investigators said.</p>
        <p>The detention of Mr. Abdel Rahman was hailed by New York political figures who had issued repeated calls for the immigrant's incarceration or deportation since the World Trade Center bombing on Feb. 26.</p>
        <p>The 55-year-old religious figure was not charged in either of the bombing plots, but was instead taken into detention by the Immigration and Naturalization Service, which found him deportable last March. Mr. Abdel Rahman has appealed the ruling, and until now the Justice Department had said it saw no need to incarcerate him. He will now be held in detention as the appeals process continues. 'I'm Grateful'</p>
        <p>Yesterday Mr. D'Amato praised the change in course. "I'm grateful," he said. "I think the American people are grateful. The fact is, it sends the kind of message that is important: that we're not going to let the terrorists hold us hostage in our own homes."</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato, who has been crusading against the cleric for months, also used the occasion to feed speculation that he might run for governor. "The terrorists are laughing at us," he said. "While New York sends jobs to New Jersey they send us their terrorists. We need the death penalty. Mario Cuomo just doesn't get it."</p>
        <p>Federal agents began staking out Mr. Abdel Rahman's Jersey City apartment building on Thursday night as well as the Al-Salam mosque in Jersey City and the Abu Bakr Elseddique mosque in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>At times the scene was almost comic. Early yesterday morning, the cleric's followers sent out a decoy sheik in a maroon van, wearing Mr. Abdel Rahman's trademark white robes and red and white cap. Federal agents, with guns drawn, surrounded the vehicle, shouting, "Get out! Get out!" But they turned out to have the wrong quarry.</p>
        <p>Law-enforcement officials remained tense as negotiations over Mr. Abdel Rahman's fate produced a near-24-hour standoff, the cleric once again frustrating the Government authorities he had eluded repeatedly since first slipping into the country in the summer of 1990. Surrender Is Offered</p>
        <p>Barbara Nelson, the cleric's lawyer, called immigration officials at 8:15 A.M. yesterday and offered her client's surrender. She said Mr. Abdel Rahman had volunteered to turn himself in to immigration officials in Newark, where his appeal for political asylum was heard and denied.</p>
        <p>But she said immigration authorities said they wanted to apprehend him "very close to the mosque." Only after 6 P.M., and with a second lawyer, Michael Warren, involved at the scene, did Mr. Abdel Rahman give himself up in the firehouse of Engine Company 250.</p>
        <p>In a paradoxical touch, the long standoff took place a five-minute walk from where Rabbi Meir Kahane lived during the heyday of the Jewish Defense Leaque 20 years ago. El Sayyid A. Nosair, an Egyptian follower of Mr. Abdel Rahman, was charged with the assassination of Mr. Kahane in a midtown hotel in 1990. He was acquitted but convicted on related charges.  Arrested in Egypt</p>
        <p>As the spiritual leader of a coalition of Islamic militant groups, Mr. Abdel Rahman was tried but acquitted in the assassination of Egyptian President Anwar el-Sadat in 1981. In the summer of 1990, despite being on a State Department watch list of undesirables, Mr. Abdel Rahman received a visa from the U.S. Embassy in Khartoum, the Sudan, and slipped into the United States. The State Department said the visa was issued by mistake. The I.N.S. said it made a second blunder when it granted him permanent resident status as a religious worker in 1991.</p>
        <p>Immigration officials revoked Mr. Abdel Rahman's residency status in March 1992, contending that he had failed to disclose that he was a polygamist and that he had been convicted in Egypt for falsifying a check. Last March, a Federal immigration judge found that Mr. Abdel Rahman could be deported.</p>
        <p>But the Justice Department said he could remain free pending his appeal, contending that he had not been implicated in a terrorist conspiracy and that his upkeep would be too costly. It emerged only last week that the Justice Department had an informant watching and recording the cleric and his inner circle.</p>
        <p>As the cleric was led away last night, the passions of the Middle East still reverberated outside the mosque. A Palestinian man asked City Councilman Noach Dear, who is Jewish, about the plight of Palestinians and then told him, "You should all be killed one by one." The councilman retorted, "If this mosque is a house of terrorism, we should close it down."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
