<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>America's Cup: At Last, an All-Female Crew</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="YACHT RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMERICA'S CUP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">America's Cup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDD143DF933A25750C0A962958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>America's Cup: At Last, an All-Female Crew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT McG. THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One hundred and forty-two years after the schooner America left the best of the British fleet in her wake in a race around the Isle of Wight, the America's Cup competition became a full-fledged sport yesterday.</p>
        <p>Bill Koch, who successfully defended the cup off San Diego in 1992, announced that his entry in the 1995 competition would be entirely manned by women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One hundred and forty-two years after the schooner America left the best of the British fleet in her wake in a race around the Isle of Wight, the America's Cup competition became a full-fledged sport yesterday.</p>
        <p>Bill Koch, who successfully defended the cup off San Diego in 1992, announced that his entry in the 1995 competition would be entirely manned by women.</p>
        <p>"This will be an historic event," he said at a New York news conference as he introduced eight of the nine women who will form the nucleus of what will eventually be a team of 22 women, 16 of whom will actually sail the Koch yacht in the defender trials next January.</p>
        <p>The initial crew members include five Olympic medalists and six experienced yacht racers: Betsy Alison, J. J. Isler, Allison Jolly, Linda Lindquist, Lynne Jewell-Shore and Dawn Riley, who had an acceptable excuse for missing the announcement. She was sailing around Cape Horn as the skipper of an all-woman team in the Whitbread around-the-world race. 3 From the Rowing Ranks</p>
        <p>Three, Stephanie Maxwell-Pierson, Anna Seaton and Alison Townley, have no sailing experience, but have excelled in rowing, the same brawny sport that has supplied male crew members to previous America's Cup entries. Their lack of yacht racing experience is irrelevant, Koch said. "Two of the crew members in the 1992 race had never seen a sailboat before they came to us," he said.</p>
        <p>Although Maxwell-Pierson denied a teammate's contention that she had actually bench-pressed her 160-pound husband, Greg Pierson, she admitted she was very adept at working rapidly with lesser weights, a skill Buddy Melges, an America</p>
        <p>team coach, said was more valuable than brute strength.</p>
        <p>"Fast hands, which most girls have, are very important in the pit," he said.</p>
        <p>All nine will compete for their positions against as many prospects as a nationwide recruiting campaign can attract through a multicity publicity tour and a toll-free number: (800) WOMENA3.</p>
        <p>Why women? "I like to do things differently," Koch said. "I like to see the sport enhanced. I like to see respect for women's competitive abilities enhanced. I think this is a win-win situation for everybody." This Crew Is Not a Gimmick</p>
        <p>Indeed, Koch, who is donating several million dollars of seed money toward the $20 million budget, dismissed the notion that an all-woman crew was merely a gimmick.</p>
        <p>"It's very serious," he said, "We think that with the right focus, attitude, dedication, fast boats and infrastructure they cannot only compete with the very best in the world in a man's sport where women have been considered bad luck to be on boats, we think they cannot only compete very effectively but also win."</p>
        <p>Part of his confidence stems from his belief that in a race in which technology is the critical factor, crew efficiency accounts for only 20 percent, and part stems from his conviction that the critical factor in crew efficiency is dedication and teamwork, attributes he believes women have in abundance.</p>
        <p>He also knows that the women will have the full backing of his America  Foundation, including a dozen experienced male executives and "the two fastest boats in the world," America</p>
        <p>and Kanza, which will be supplanted by a new boat to be built. Conner Is One to Beat</p>
        <p>To win the right to defend the cup against the ultimate foreign challenger, the Koch team must beat two other American teams, one headed by Dennis Conner and one by Kevin Mahaney.</p>
        <p>Although both groups are farther along in developing new boats, Koch clearly stole a march on his rivals in the key promotional area of attracting donations and sponsorship dollars.</p>
        <p>As David Dellenbaugh, the chief tactician put it in what sounded suspiciously like a Madison Avenue sales pitch: "What you're going to see in the next year is unlike anything that you've ever seen: a team of women competing with men at the top level of an international sport. That idea is unique. It's exciting. It'll attract a lot of attention and it will make history. The impact of all that will be great for women. It'll be great for sport. It'll be great for sailing and it'll be great for all the sponsors who chose to come on board."</p>
        <p>If enthusiasm counts, the Koch crew should start stocking up on champagne.</p>
        <p>Seaton, an Olympic bronze medal rower who got her first exposure to America's Cup racing during a recent trip to San Diego, came away hooked.</p>
        <p>"I loved it," she said. "I absolutely loved it. It's scary how much I loved it."</p>
        <p>YACHT RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
