<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pentagon Offers New Way to Verify Disarmament</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORDON, MICHAEL R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFD8173DF933A25750C0A962958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pentagon Offers New Way to Verify Disarmament</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GORDON, MICHAEL R</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States has devised a novel means to verify the dismantling of American and Russian warheads and the Pentagon wants to propose it to Moscow, Pentagon officials said today.</p>
        <p>The monitoring would be intended to fill a gap in American and Russian arms control agreements. While the two sides have extensive procedures to monitor the number of missiles and bombers they have deployed, they have not allowed each other to observe the dismantling of warheads or measure the fissionable material that has been extracted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States has devised a novel means to verify the dismantling of American and Russian warheads and the Pentagon wants to propose it to Moscow, Pentagon officials said today.</p>
        <p>The monitoring would be intended to fill a gap in American and Russian arms control agreements. While the two sides have extensive procedures to monitor the number of missiles and bombers they have deployed, they have not allowed each other to observe the dismantling of warheads or measure the fissionable material that has been extracted.</p>
        <p>Under the new plan, each side would be allowed to dismantle its warheads in private, in order to keep their design secret. The other side would then be allowed to measure the amount of plutonium removed to determine the number of warheads demolished.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon has already signed contracts for some $800 million in assistance to speed disarmament efforts in the former Soviet Union and is seeking Congressional approval for another $800 million in aid through 1995.</p>
        <p>In testimony today, Pentagon officials said their disarmament program had three main thrusts. One is to develop a way to verify that the Russians are dismantling their weapons.</p>
        <p>"We have developed concepts for monitoring and auditing the warhead dismantlement and fissile materials disposition process without revealing sensitive warhead design features," Harold P. Smith Jr., the top assistant to Defense Secretary William Perry on atomic energy matters, told a House panel. "And we will continue to press for Russia's acceptance and implementation of such measures."</p>
        <p>Under the Pentagon plan, the plutonium core of the weapons would be removed, put in special containers and transported to a storage site. Each side would then use special radiological instruments to measure the amount of plutonium in the containers without opening them.</p>
        <p>The Russians would be invited to see a demonstration of the technology at the Pantex plant in Texas, where warheads are dismantled. In return, American experts would use the technology at similar Russian installations.</p>
        <p>While the Pentagon believes the plan is feasible, it has yet to be formally approved by the Clinton Administration and presented to the Russians.</p>
        <p>Another Pentagon-backed initiative would spur Russia's efforts to destroy its chemical arsenal by helping build a pilot plant for destroying poison gas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said the project could cost $300 million or more and could take eight years to complete. American officials have told the Russians that the aid would be provided on the condition that Moscow agrees to destroy its most modern chemical bombs there.</p>
        <p>The Russians have said they cannot comply with a global treaty banning poison gas without substantial American aid. The Clinton Administration has submitted the chemical treaty to the Senate for approval, and it is unclear whether the Senate would approve the agreement if the Russian ability to destroy their stocks and carry out the accords is in doubt.</p>
        <p>The third main thrust of the Pentagon effort is to insure that the non-Russian republics give up the nuclear weapons they inherited when the Soviet Union broke up.</p>
        <p>Aston B. Carter, the Assistant Defense Secretary for Counterproliferation, said Ukraine, with American assistance, shipped 60 warheads back to Russia last week, the first step in eliminating its arsenal of 1,200 warheads.</p>
        <p>The Russians say they are dismantling about 2,000 warheads a year, but have not let American experts monitor the process. Pentagon officials, however, said the monitoring is needed to insure that nuclear weapons materials are not diverted from the Russian stockpiles.</p>
        <p>In Congressional testimony today, Pentagon officials defended the aid the United States is providing to help dismantle Russian weapons, describing it as a key step to prevent the spread of weapons of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>Since the Ames espionage case broke last month, some lawmakers have questioned why the Clinton Administration is providing aid to Russia when Moscow and Washington continue to spy on each other.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
