<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Inspector's Specialty: How Iraq Hides Weapons</title>
    <meta content="14INSP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iraq-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shenon, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ritter, William Scott Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D71039F937A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Inspector's Specialty: How Iraq Hides Weapons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shenon, Philip</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Scott Ritter Jr, leader of United Nations arms inspection team barred by Iraq, is former Marine captain responsible for investigating methods used by Iraqis to hide their stockpiles of weapons (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the dozens of United Nations arms inspectors who travel into and out of Iraq in the search for poison gas and other weapons of mass destruction, William Scott Ritter Jr. was bound to be a special thorn in the Iraqis' side.</p>
        <p>Some of his United Nations colleagues are specialists in chemical arms, while others have backgrounds in the science of germ warfare or nuclear weapons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the dozens of United Nations arms inspectors who travel into and out of Iraq in the search for poison gas and other weapons of mass destruction, William Scott Ritter Jr. was bound to be a special thorn in the Iraqis' side.</p>
        <p>Some of his United Nations colleagues are specialists in chemical arms, while others have backgrounds in the science of germ warfare or nuclear weapons.</p>
        <p>The 36-year-old former Marine captain is responsible for investigating the methods used by the Iraqis to hide their stockpiles of weapons from international inspection.</p>
        <p>And so it is no surprise, his colleagues say, that the Iraqis would level allegations that Mr. Ritter, who has worked for the United Nations Special Commission on Iraq since he left the Marines in 1991, is an American spy.</p>
        <p>''A lot of what Ritter does has focused on the area that the Iraqis are most sensitive about: what we consider to be their concealment activities,'' said Charles Duelfer, the deputy director of the commission, which is responsible fo the arms inspections imposed on Iraq after the 1991 Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Duelfer said the idea that Mr. Ritter might be a spy for the Central Intelligence Agency ''is a joke -- everybody around here finds that terribly amusing.'' He added: ''The truth is that Ritter is a man who is very dedicated to his job. He's a very energetic, tough-minded inspector.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritter has repeatedly infuriated the Iraqis, notably last month when he led a team on a surprise inspection of a lakeside resort often used by President Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>The inspection, which resembled a commando raid, led to fierce protests from the Iraqi Government, which has insisted that it is concealing nothing from the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The Iraqi Foreign Minister, Tariq Aziz, has called Mr. Ritter a troublemaker, while the official Iraqi news agency accuses him of ''falsifying facts, inventing lies, deliberately prolonging the process and sending false reports to the Security Council.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritter, who has described the Iraqi spying allegations against him as ''absolutely untrue'' and ''insulting,'' has a background in military intelligence.</p>
        <p>During the gulf war, he was assigned to American military headquarters in Saudi Arabia as an intelligence analyst.</p>
        <p>He joined the Marines in 1984 after graduation from Franklin and Marshall College in Lancaster, Pa., and was first assigned to the Seventh Marine Amphibious Brigade in Twenty-Nine Palms, Calif. Just before his assignment to Saudi Arabia in 1990, he was stationed for two years at the Defense Nuclear Agency, which studies nuclear-weapons and atomic-energy issues for the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>''A lot of our inspectors either come from military backgrounds or are active-duty military,'' said Mr. Duelfer of the United Nations Special Commission. That makes sense, he said, ''because in some ways our inspections are a little bit like military operations.'' He added: ''There has to be a lot of planning. It's a lot of Sherlock Holmes work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritter, who has taken part in 35 inspection tours of Iraq, works out of the offices of the Special Commission at United Nations headquarters in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
