<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Minimalist; Two Starches From Naples</title>
    <meta content="14MINI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bittman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3DC1239F937A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Minimalist; Two Starches From Naples</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bittman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bittman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Bittman column on making pasta with potatoes, a Neopolitan dish; recipe (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I first encountered pasta with potatoes, it struck me as about the most unlikely dish ever, a stewlike combination of little more than the two main ingredients and canned tomatoes. Starch on starch, like a bread sandwich.</p>
        <p>But in fact, it is a satisfying, traditional Italian dish (Neapolitan, said Andrea Graziosi, a friend who taught me how to prepare  and appreciate it). It is all the more enjoyable because it breaks the rules. If you can believe it, this dish is best when the pasta is cooked until it is fat, juice-laden and quite soft. So there's no need to seize the ideal al dente moment, and it's acceptable for the pasta to sit for a while, even overnight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I first encountered pasta with potatoes, it struck me as about the most unlikely dish ever, a stewlike combination of little more than the two main ingredients and canned tomatoes. Starch on starch, like a bread sandwich.</p>
        <p>But in fact, it is a satisfying, traditional Italian dish (Neapolitan, said Andrea Graziosi, a friend who taught me how to prepare  and appreciate it). It is all the more enjoyable because it breaks the rules. If you can believe it, this dish is best when the pasta is cooked until it is fat, juice-laden and quite soft. So there's no need to seize the ideal al dente moment, and it's acceptable for the pasta to sit for a while, even overnight.</p>
        <p>Nor is there any need to worry about the ''correct'' pasta shape; pasta with potatoes is best with several different shapes, in varying quantities, preferably broken.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graziosi, who grew up in Naples, said the dish ''began, I suppose, as a simple way to use up the bits and pieces of dried pasta that accumulated during the week.''</p>
        <p>It's a warming, homey creation. Just don't plan to impress anyone with your  presentation; this dish is not gorgeous.</p>
        <p>PASTA WITH POTATOES  Total time: at least an hour</p>
        <p>2  tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>1/2  cup minced pancetta or bacon, optional</p>
        <p>3  or 4 potatoes, about 1 1/2 pounds, peeled and cut into bite-size chunks</p>
        <p>1  tablespoon chopped garlic</p>
        <p>3  or 4 small dried hot red chiles, or to taste (or substitute about 1 teaspoon crushed red pepper flakes)</p>
        <p>1  28-ounce can whole plum tomatoes, not drained</p>
        <p>1 1/2  pounds assorted dried pasta</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Put several cups of water in a pot on stove, and keep it at a simmer. Place olive oil in a large saucepan, and turn heat to medium. If you're using pancetta or bacon, add it to the oil and cook, stirring occasionally, until it becomes slightly crisp, about 10 minutes. (If you are omitting the meat, proceed to the next step.)</p>
        <p>2. Add potatoes, garlic and chiles and raise the heat to medium-high. Cook, stirring occasionally, until potatoes begin to brown all over, about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Add tomatoes and their juice, along with 2 cups of the simmering water, and bring to a boil. Turn heat down to medium-low, and cook uncovered, stirring occasionally to break up the tomatoes and prevent sticking.</p>
        <p>4. While potato mixture is cooking, break long dried pasta, like spaghetti, into several lengths; place cut pasta, like ziti, in a bag, and break it up with the back of a pot or a hammer. After potato mixture has simmered for about 10 minutes, add pasta and plenty of salt and pepper to pot. Simmer,  stirring and adding the simmering water as necessary; mixture should remain thick and stewy, never dry.</p>
        <p>5. When potatoes are tender and pasta quite tender -- this will take 20 minutes or more -- the dish is done. (It may be covered and refrigerated for a day or two, or put in a closed container and frozen for several weeks; it's likely that you will need to add more liquid when you reheat.) Check the seasoning, and add some crushed red pepper flakes, black pepper or salt if needed. Serve hot, in bowls.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
