<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gallup Shifts Emphasis Toward Market Studies</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="332255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARKET RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GALLUP ORGANIZATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SELECTION RESEARCH INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BELKIN, LISA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLIFTON, JIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Market Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD113BF935A35750C0A966958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gallup Shifts Emphasis Toward Market Studies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BELKIN, LISA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Gallup Organization, which helped invent the public opinion poll more than 50 years ago, is scaling down that business and taking on more market research instead, several current and former Gallup employees said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Gallup Organization, which helped invent the public opinion poll more than 50 years ago, is scaling down that business and taking on more market research instead, several current and former Gallup employees said.</p>
        <p>The Gallup Organization, which helped invent the public opinion poll more than 50 years ago, is scaling down that business and taking on more market research instead, several current and former Gallup employees said.</p>
        <p>Since Gallup was bought 18 months ago, its new owner, Selection Research Inc., a market research company based in Lincoln, Neb., has been slashing staff at Gallup's office in Princeton, N.J., and de-emphasizing research on social issues, former and current employees say.</p>
        <p>The company's new owners concede there have been structural changes.</p>
        <p>Jim Clifton, a former SRI executive and now the president and chief executive of Gallup, said the ratio of public opinion polling to market research polling was 50-50 when his group bought Gallup. Now, he said, 30 percent of the work is in public opinion research, and the rest is work for health-care companies, hospitals, banks and insurance companies, trade associations and newspapers. But he said the commitment to public opinion research remains the same.</p>
        <p>How to Pay for It</p>
        <p>George Gallup Jr., co-chairman of Gallup with his brother Alec, and son of the founder, who died in 1984, said: ''My father would have understood. The Gallup Organization remains dedicated to public opinion research on a broad scale. Market research is a way of paying for it.''</p>
        <p>Many longtime Gallup employees disagree with that view, and in recent months four top executives have left and formed their own polling companies. One hundred and fifty people were working at Gallup's headquarters when the company was bought in September 1988; now there are fewer than 60.</p>
        <p>''When they bought Gallup, what they were really doing was buying the name,'' said Neil Upmeyer, a former vice president of public affairs research and one of several senior employees to leave the company recently. ''My feeling is that six months from now, there won't be anything left of Gallup as it used to be.''</p>
        <p>''The culture inside Gallup has changed,'' said Andrew Kohut, who was president of the Gallup Organization before the acquisition and division president afterward, until his departure.</p>
        <p>Change Is No Surprise</p>
        <p>Observers say the new emphasis is not surprising in an industry where profits have been flat in recent years. ''It's very difficult to make money in the public polling business,'' said Norman M. Bradburn, director of the National Opinion Research Center at the University of Chicago. ''You make money essentially in the commercial side of it.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the unrest at Gallup concerns many in the opinion field.</p>
        <p>''I think that Gallup has lost the people who are strong in the public opinion area, and I don't see who is going to do the kind of work that made them what they are,'' said Warren Mitofsky, the executive director of voter research and surveys for the newly combined exit-polling efforts of the three major over-the-air television networks and the Cable News Network.</p>
        <p>Both Gallup and SRI are privately held, and neither SRI nor Gallup officers would reveal the purchase price. Mr. Gallup said his company ''was not in the black'' when it was sold.</p>
        <p>SRI was founded in 1969 to develop psychological screening tests that help employers find employees for particular jobs.</p>
        <p>When SRI offered to buy Gallup, Mr. Clifton spoke to the company's employees and assured them nothing would change. But change did come.</p>
        <p>Phone Interviewers Dismissed</p>
        <p>First the company moved from its old building to a suite in a new office building nearby. Then the entire staff that conducts telephone interviews, about 40 people, was dismissed and all telephone work was assigned to the 800 SRI interviewers in Nebraska.</p>
        <p>''We expected that,'' said Diane Colasanto, former senior vice president for opinion research at Gallup who has joined Mr. Kohut and formed a new company that does business with Gallup. ''Their strength is telephone interviewing.''</p>
        <p>In another change, the SRI marketing staff in Nebraska has now become the marketing staff for Gallup, Mr. Clifton said.</p>
        <p>The personal-interviewing staff -people who went to homes for in-depth interviews - was cut, Mr. Upmeyer said, from 15 employees to two or three. He said the coding staff -trained to interpret answers to open-ended questions - was also cut.</p>
        <p>These methods, particularly personal interviewing, can sometimes be more effective. But personal interviewing is much more expensive than a standard telephone poll, and companies are cutting back on the practice.</p>
        <p>In Some Ways the Same</p>
        <p>The Gallup Poll has stayed essentially the same, although it was assigned a new chief last month. It still comes out once a week and is syndicated to 100 newspapers around the country.</p>
        <p>It is the Poll that most people think of when they think of Gallup, and it has been described as the ''public face'' of the company. But that department is only one of several in the organization.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Gallup has always worked for corporate clients. Sometimes the clients wanted to know which colors or flavors the public prefers. That was considered market research. Sometimes the questions were broader - for instance, an airline seeking information on public safety issues, or a newspaper wanting to gauge opinion on abortion for a series of articles. That was considered social public opinion research.</p>
        <p>The Opinion Research division of Gallup, headed by Mr. Kohut, was responsible for the latter. Although its staff remained intact after the purchase, employees say they saw a blurring of the traditional line between the two types of work done for corporate clients.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohut left Gallup last autumn, and Ms. Colasanto followed soon after. The two were credited in polling circles as being the backbone of the organization.</p>
        <p>No one has been named to fill Mr. Kohut's job. Mr. Upmeyer, who left Gallup last week, said Mr. Kohut's Public Opinion division has been ''dismantled'' into smaller groups.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clifton of SRI said the complaints by former employees are out of proportion. ''There is nothing wrong with making money,'' he said. ''The changes allowed us to be profitable. And being profitable is the only way any to get any research done.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
