<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Briefing; Second Thoughts By Oregon G.O.P.</title>
    <meta content="Y15POL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oregon</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kitzhaber, John (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sizemore, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED81330F936A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Briefing; Second Thoughts By Oregon G.O.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oregon Republicans are seen concerned that their likely gubernatorial candidate, Bill Sizemore, would make such a weak candidate against Democratic Gov John A Kitzhaber that they are seeking ways to get Sizemore to drop out of race, as soon as he is nominated, to clear way for Republican State Central Committee to pick replacement nominee with higher and less-tarnished political profile; photo of Kitzhaber (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. John A. Kitzhaber is so well regarded by his Oregon constituents, fellow Democrats as well as Republicans, that for a while Republican leaders had trouble finding someone willing to challenge his re-election bid. But eventually the state's leading anti-tax crusader, Bill Sizemore, the executive director of the Oregon branch of Taxpayers United, stepped forward and top Republican officials, taking what they could get, figured that at least he would keep the flag flying against the popular Governor.</p>
        <p>Now they are not so sure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. John A. Kitzhaber is so well regarded by his Oregon constituents, fellow Democrats as well as Republicans, that for a while Republican leaders had trouble finding someone willing to challenge his re-election bid. But eventually the state's leading anti-tax crusader, Bill Sizemore, the executive director of the Oregon branch of Taxpayers United, stepped forward and top Republican officials, taking what they could get, figured that at least he would keep the flag flying against the popular Governor.</p>
        <p>Now they are not so sure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sizemore is still an easy favorite in the Republican primary on Tuesday, since the three other candidates in the contest are perennial political also-rans, inexperienced, out of money or all of the above. So Mr. Sizemore is almost guaranteed a spot on the fall ballot opposite Governor Kitzhaber, who faces no serious primary opposition.</p>
        <p>But many top Oregon Republicans  now fear that Mr. Sizemore will run so poorly against the Governor that he will drag down the rest of the party. Last month, The Portland Oregonian reported that for a candidate who touts his honesty and prudent financial ways, in the years before he got into politics Mr. Sizemore piled up a series of business failures and bad loans that left creditors crying they had been misled.</p>
        <p>Some Republican leaders are already privately talking up a post-primary scenario that they believe might head off political disaster. They want Mr. Sizemore to drop out of the race as soon as he is nominated, thereby clearing the way, under state law, for the Republican State Central Committee to pick a replacement nominee with a higher and less-tarnished political profile.</p>
        <p>Their candidate: the president of the State Senate, Brady Adams, who has said he would take on the Governor if Mr. Sizemore dropped out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sizemore, who denies any wrongdoing, insists he is in the race all the way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
