<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Homer: Works at a Price</title>
    <meta content="15INSI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alliance for Downtown New York</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rhode Island School of Design</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, William H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Homer, Winslow (1836-1910)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Phillip M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bolger, Doreen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DE1330F936A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Homer: Works at a Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News that William H Gates paid more than $30 million for major seascape by Winslow Homer sets off speculation about prices for American art at important upcoming auctions, at Sotheby's and Christie's; photo; Alliance for Downtown New York sponsors Art Exchange event in financial district; Rhode Island School of Design names Phillip M Johnston director; Doreen Bolger left post to head Baltimore Museum of Art (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>News that William H. Gates, chairman of the Microsoft Corporation, paid more than $30 million for a major seascape by Winslow Homer last week has set off debate among American art collectors and dealers over whether the already heated market for American paintings will rise even more -- perhaps another 25 percent -- at the important auctions at Sotheby's and Christie's next week. Not only was the price a record for an American painting, but it also catapulted American fine art into the same financial stratosphere as European paintings.</p>
        <p>''It's going to have an impact, but it's not something you can quantify in percentages,'' said Dara Mitchell, director of American paintings at Sotheby's. ''We're in the midst of an expanding market, and the sale of the Homer will certainly raise people's awareness of American paintings.''</p>
        <p>Not just major American masters like Homer are getting attention. Even at small sales, the work of second-tier American artists are achieving what seem to be unbelievably high prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>News that William H. Gates, chairman of the Microsoft Corporation, paid more than $30 million for a major seascape by Winslow Homer last week has set off debate among American art collectors and dealers over whether the already heated market for American paintings will rise even more -- perhaps another 25 percent -- at the important auctions at Sotheby's and Christie's next week. Not only was the price a record for an American painting, but it also catapulted American fine art into the same financial stratosphere as European paintings.</p>
        <p>''It's going to have an impact, but it's not something you can quantify in percentages,'' said Dara Mitchell, director of American paintings at Sotheby's. ''We're in the midst of an expanding market, and the sale of the Homer will certainly raise people's awareness of American paintings.''</p>
        <p>Not just major American masters like Homer are getting attention. Even at small sales, the work of second-tier American artists are achieving what seem to be unbelievably high prices.</p>
        <p>Last month, for example, a portrait of a woman standing in a tulip field by the American expatriate George Hitchcock was sold for more than $600,000 at a small auction in West Sussex, England. Previously no one had paid more than $60,000 for a work by Hitchock, who spent his winters in France and his summers in Holland and is considered a secondary American artist.</p>
        <p>The buyer was Richard Manoogian, a Manhattan collector. The Antiques Trade Gazette, an industry publication, reported that 11 telephone bidders had vied for the painting, and they weren't all American. Even Richard Greene, the London dealer, tried to buy it.</p>
        <p>''I don't consider myself an American picture dealer, but we do have plenty of American clients,'' Mr. Greene said. ''When we get American paintings we have no trouble selling them.''</p>
        <p>Many dealers say it is not buyers like Mr. Gates who cause prices to soar. ''It's the old law of supply and demand,'' said Stuart Feld, president of Hirschl Adler, the Manhattan gallery. ''The Americans turned out a much more limited number of paintings than the French.''</p>
        <p>When Christie's tried selling fine art in Los Angeles for the first time two weeks ago, its California, Western and American paintings, drawings and sculpture were an astounding success, bringing in $2.8 million, $1 million over its high estimate.</p>
        <p>And not everyone was able to buy what they wanted. Vance Jordan, a Madison Avenue dealer, was outbid when he tried to purchase a still life by Charles Caryl Coleman for an unidentified major American museum. The painting, which was eventually bought by an unidentified collector, went for $706,500, more than 10 times its high $60,000 estimate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan offered the stock market as an analogy. '' People are starting to look at the better examples of the smaller cap stocks and are paying extremely high prices for those,''  he said.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Goldberg, the Christie's painting expert who put the Los Angeles sale together, attributed its success to the nature of the art. ''It's accessible, easy to understand and less intimidating than 20th-century art,'' she said. ''Mr. Gates's purchase certainly doesn't hurt, but it's not enough to boost an entire market. It may have helped to nudge it up another notch.''</p>
        <p>So, some experts believe, will a group of 31 works that Christie's is selling privately for Irwin Goldstein, a retired doctor from New Jersey. Among them are works by Winslow Homer and watercolors by Charles Demuth as well as a still life by James Peale, all of which carry unusually high prices. The auction house is even getting dealers to help find them buyers.</p>
        <p>''We are working with a couple of dealers,'' said Andrew Schoelkopf,  who is in charge of Christie's American paintings department. ''We've already sold about a third of the collection, which suggests the prices aren't too aggressive.''</p>
        <p>What will happen next week when both Sotheby's and Christie's hold their sales of American art is anyone's guess. Some experts are betting that works by artists like Frederick C. Frieseke, Childe Hassam and Georgia O'Keeffe will set world records.</p>
        <p>Richard York, a Manhattan dealer, worries that all the excitement may mislead people to believe that an American painting that has been in their family for generations may be worth a fortune.</p>
        <p>''They hear these big prices and think, 'Wow, I have a family treasure that could be worth millions,' '' Mr. York said. ''Sadly, that's not always the case.''</p>
        <p>Luring the Novice</p>
        <p>For the third year, the Alliance for Downtown New York is sponsoring The Art Exchange, an art fair primarily for younger and lesser-known  dealers that takes place in empty offices in Manhattan's financial district. This year's event, which opens on June 4 and runs through June 9, will take place at 2 Broadway, an early 1960's Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill building with breathtaking views of the New York Harbor. An international group of 40 dealers will be participating.</p>
        <p>''We will be doing a catalogue this year with the history of the high points of art in New York,'' said Jeanne Nathan, president of the Art Exchange. ''We consider ourselves to be cutting edge. Each year we keep changing locations, which always makes the event seem new.'' She said the fair was organized to reach a broad audience, including  people who might be too intimidated to walk into an art gallery or an auction house.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to break folks into the habit of buying art,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In Rhode Island</p>
        <p>The Rhode Island School of Design in Providence has appointed Phillip M. Johnston as the new director of its museum. Mr. Johnston, who will begin the job on July 1, has been the  vice president for museums and collections at the Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities  since September 1996. Before that he was director of the Carnegie Museum in Pittsburgh for eight years.</p>
        <p>He is replacing Doreen Bolger, who left in January to become the director of the Baltimore Museum of Art.  INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
