<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The God of Small Things</title>
    <meta content="10WILSONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1253805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amichai, Yehuda</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Open Closed Open: Poems (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D8133DF933A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The God of Small Things</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Wilson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilson, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Wilson reviews book Open Closed Open: Poems by Yehuda Amichai (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OPEN CLOSED OPEN</p>
        <p>Poems.</p>
        <p>By Yehuda Amichai.</p>
        <p>Translated by Chana Bloch and Chana Kronfeld.</p>
        <p>184 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OPEN CLOSED OPEN</p>
        <p>Poems.</p>
        <p>By Yehuda Amichai.</p>
        <p>Translated by Chana Bloch and Chana Kronfeld.</p>
        <p>184 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Harcourt. $25.</p>
        <p>It is the dream of most poets to become a vox populi without having to sacrifice the subtleties and complexities of their craft. Hardly anyone achieves this difficult dream. Once, in the mid-1970's, I attended a reading by Denise Levertov at an Oxford college. Levertov, clearly feeling oppressed by her environment, told the assembled students that what she really yearned for was to see her books carried in the back pockets of workmen's overalls. Yehuda Amichai, the great Israeli poet who died from cancer on Sept. 22 at 76, is one of very few contemporary poets to have reached a broad cross-section without compromising his art. He was loved by his readers worldwide (his poems have been translated into more than 30 languages) perhaps only as the Russians loved their poets in the early part of the last century. It is not hard to see why. Amichai's poems are easy on the surface and yet profound: humorous, ironic and yet full of passion, secular but God-engaged, allusive but accessible, charged with metaphor and yet remarkably concrete. Most of all, they are, like the speaking persona in his ''Letter of Recommendation,'' full of love: ''Oh, touch me, touch me, you good woman! / This is not a scar you feel under my shirt. / It is a letter of recommendation, folded, / from my father: / 'He is still a good boy and full of love.' ''</p>
        <p>Amichai's first book was published in 1955, and his last, ''Open Closed Open,'' appeared in this country a few months before his death. There are now more than a dozen books in English, the work of numerous translators drawn to his work like bears to honey. With such a broad readership it was inevitably Amichai's fate to become, in his lifetime, a poet of occasions, although his writing is not the least bit occasional. His poems are frequent guests at weddings, funerals and bar mitzvahs; Yitzhak Rabin read lines from an early poem, ''God Takes Pity on Kindergarten Children,'' as part of his Nobel Peace Prize acceptance speech (Amichai attended the ceremony). But what accounts for the popularity of his work is not that it is sentimental, lachrymose or conventionally ''appropriate'' -- it isn't at all -- but rather that the poems are intimately personal without being overly confessional. This intimacy is restorative, in the way Ted Hughes described in The Jerusalem Report, an English-language magazine in Israel, some years ago: ''The effect his poetry has on me is to give me my own life -- to open it up somehow, to make it all available to me afresh, to uncover all kinds of riches in every moment of it, and to free me from my mental prisons. When that's what I want I pick up a book by Yehuda.''</p>
        <p>Amichai's recurring subjects are love, war and its aftermath, and all manner of goings-on in the earthly city of Jerusalem. No poet, not even the biblical psalmist, gave more attention to the quotidian life of the city and its people.</p>
        <p>In the world of Amichai's poetry, those who are hanging up sheets to dry, or out in the market or closing a tailor's shop in a narrow alley of the Old City, get better than equal time with the ghosts of historical and biblical figures that haunt the place. Similarly, a clothesline or a market is a more important landmark than either David's Citadel or the Al Aqsa Mosque.</p>
        <p>''Open Closed Open,'' translated with great skill and expertise by Chana Bloch and Chana Kronfeld, is the fruit of a decade's labor, and in it Amichai satisfyingly repeats and advances his characteristic method of converting ordinary daily experience into the extraordinary via the power of his transforming resemblances, and of rendering the extraordinary -- larger-than-life biblical figures, for example -- as ''ordinary'' in the sense of highlighting their common, human frailties. But the book has an added poignancy: like Yeats in his ''Circus Animals' Desertion'' or Balzac, who called out for his characters from his deathbed, Amichai seems to have gathered for one last assessment the figures and places that dominated his imagination through almost half a century of poetry. The troubled Israelite kings, Saul and David, are back, as are the poet's father and Ruth, the friend of Amichai's youth who stayed behind in Germany and was murdered in the Holocaust, and of whom he writes: ''Will you come back to me the way the dead sometimes / come back to the living, as if they were born again? / Does the arrow celebrate its return to the bow, and what about / the ball that returns from the wall to the hands of the child at play?'' It is the lovely rhythm of Amichai's poetry to be forever turning stillness into movement and vice versa. As, for example, in the following short poem, where Jerusalem, landlocked on the fringe of the Judean desert, is magnificently released, while simultaneously bringing the poet to a moment of stasis and tranquillity:</p>
        <p>And there are days here when everything is sails and more sails,</p>
        <p>even though there's no sea in Jerusalem, not even a river.</p>
        <p>Everything is sails: the flags, the prayer shawls, the black coats,</p>
        <p>the monks' robes, the kaftans and kaffiyehs,</p>
        <p>young women's dresses and headdresses,</p>
        <p>Torah mantles and prayer rugs, feelings that swell in the wind</p>
        <p>and hopes that set them sailing in other</p>
        <p>directions.</p>
        <p>Even my father's hands, spread out in blessing,</p>
        <p>my mother's broad face and Ruth's faraway death</p>
        <p>are sails, all of them sails in the splendid</p>
        <p>regatta</p>
        <p>on the two seas of Jerusalem:</p>
        <p>the sea of memory and the sea of forgetting.</p>
        <p>''Jerusalem,'' Amichai wrote in one of his earliest poems, ''is the Venice of God.''</p>
        <p>He didn't shy away from politics, but neither was he dominated by them. His poems have a veteran's weariness but a lover's energy. He should have won the Nobel Prize in any one of the last 20 years, but he knew that as far as the Scandinavian judges were concerned, and whatever his personal politics, which were indubitably on the dovish side, he came from the wrong side of the stockade.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Wilson is chairman of the English department at Tufts University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Wilson is chairman of the English department at Tufts University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
