<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JUDGE FINDS BIAS IN HOME LOTTERY</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="763431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEPOTISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOTTERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISLAND PARK (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLASSER, I LEO (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARVAJAL, DOREEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCULLY, HAROLD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'AMATO, ALFONSE M (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CICCIMARRO, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lotteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED91639F93AA25756C0A963958260" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JUDGE FINDS BIAS IN HOME LOTTERY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARVAJAL, DOREEN</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, L.I., May 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a significant civil rights housing decision, a Federal judge has ruled that the virtually all-white village of Island Park rigged a housing lottery in the 1980's to exclude blacks from federally subsidized homes and to reward politically connected villagers. As a result, he found the village liable for millions of dollars in damages.</p>
        <p>Judge I. Leo Glasser of Federal District Court in Brooklyn ruled that the village of 4,000 had violated the Fair Housing Act by using "nepotism and word of mouth" to manipulate the sale of 44 federally subsidized houses built in the early 1980's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a significant civil rights housing decision, a Federal judge has ruled that the virtually all-white village of Island Park rigged a housing lottery in the 1980's to exclude blacks from federally subsidized homes and to reward politically connected villagers. As a result, he found the village liable for millions of dollars in damages.</p>
        <p>Judge I. Leo Glasser of Federal District Court in Brooklyn ruled that the village of 4,000 had violated the Fair Housing Act by using "nepotism and word of mouth" to manipulate the sale of 44 federally subsidized houses built in the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>"The village's pre-selection scheme discriminated against the group of all black residents," Judge Glasser wrote in his 78-page opinion.</p>
        <p>The decision, released today, singled out Anthony Ciccimarro, a cousin of Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, as an example of a homeowner who received "unjust enrichment" because he was allowed to buy a $40,000 home. Harold Scully, a former village clerk of 30 years and a onetime ally of the Senator, had testified that Mr. D'Amato ordered him to add the cousin to the list of participants who would get the opportunity to buy a subsidized house.</p>
        <p>Hours after the ruling was announced today, the United States Attorney's office, which had filed the civil rights lawsuit in 1990, claimed a "huge victory" because of the size of the penalties. The precise dollar amounts are to be calculated at another hearing before a magistrate.</p>
        <p>"Now that liability has been fixed by this decision, we will turn our attention to developing remedies for those who are denied housing by this scheme," the United States Attorney, Zachary W. Carter, said today.</p>
        <p>But Island Park's lawyer, William H. Pauley 3d, complained that the judge had blamed the village for the acts of Mr. Scully. "Obviously, my client is disappointed that it is being saddled with liability for the outlaw acts of its former renegade clerk," Mr. Pauley said. He said he had not read the decision yet and would soon discuss the next step with his clients.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scully, who was originally a defendant in the case and later became a witness, told Federal investigators that village officials rigged the selection for homes by tipping off politically connected villagers, who slipped their applications under the village hall door before office hours to guarantee a top spot on a first come, first served list.</p>
        <p>His testimony was publicly attacked by Mr. D'Amato, who once dismissed Mr. Scully as "fighting for his life." Mr. D'Amato, who is from Island Park, was not a defendant in the civil suit but was often ridiculed by political opponents because of it.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. D'Amato released a brief statement through a spokesman, Harvey Valentine. "The Senator was not involved," he said. "It doesn't involve the Senator."</p>
        <p>In his ruling, Judge Glasser noted that despite the attacks on Mr. Scully's credibility, no one had offered supporting evidence to undercut him. Village officials had failed to stop Mr. Scully, he said, adding that Michael Parente, a former mayor, had accepted credit for the program and gifts from grateful homeowners.</p>
        <p>What was undisputed, the judge wrote, is that "no blacks received any of the 44 homes constructed in Island Park."</p>
        <p>Along with violations of the Fair Housing Act, Judge Glasser found that the village broke provisions of the False Claims Act, a ruling that could sharply increase the penalties against Island Park. The judge ruled that the village violated the act, which essentially bars fraudulent claims for Government money, with each monthly check after 1984 from a homeowner that was subsidized by the Federal Government. Each violation carries a $2,000 fine.</p>
        <p>So if a person wrote 12 mortgage checks a year beginning in 1984, it is clear how quickly the fine totals could add up. "Easily, this could cost them millions," said Charles Kleinberg, an assistant United States attorney working on the case. "We would certainly hope that this sends a message to the community that the Government will not look lightly at this kind of behavior."</p>
        <p>The United States Attorney's office filed the civil rights lawsuit in 1990 after articles in The New York Times about official favoritism that were said to have guided the Island Park housing program. In 1993, the Government's lawyers filed a motion for a summary judgment on the case, arguing that the evidence was strong enough to merit a decision on the village's liability.</p>
        <p>Usually, such motions take less than three months for a decision, but Judge Glasser waited more than two years. In April, after conceding to a Times reporter that he mistakenly thought he had already decided the case, he resumed his review.</p>
        <p>Robert Begleiter, who initiated the lawsuit for the United States Attorney's office and is now in private practice, said the ruling could have an impact on other municipalities. "In administering these Government funds, people had better watch out and spend it correctly," he said.</p>
        <p>As an original condition for participating in the Federal housing program, Island Park had pledged to set aside 17 of the 44 homes for blacks, though no black families actually got homes. Judge Glasser did not rule on whether the village intentionally discriminated against blacks. Mr. Scully, the ex-clerk, had testified that several village trustees had confided concerns about the "potential that blacks would be brought into the community."</p>
        <p>A former trustee, James Brady, took the Fifth Amendment against self-incrimination when he was questioned in a deposition about whether he used the word, "nigger" in discussing the housing program with other village officials.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, the judge said the Government had relied too heavily on those statements and the question of intentional discrimination could probably not be settled without further inquiry. But as he noted, intent does not need to be proved to show that discrimination has taken place.</p>
        <p>The ruling carried mixed signals to the seaside village of Island Park.</p>
        <p>"Everybody seems to think if you're a Republican in Island Park, all you have to do is talk to someone and you get whatever you want," said Edward J. Targowski, 57, who owns a home in Island Park. "It's not the case at all."</p>
        <p>But an Island Park newcomer, Nancy Robertson, 43, said: "I'm not surprised. It's all politics."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
