<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Little More Money for Weapons and Repairs</title>
    <meta content="Y03DEFE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="992624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE CLINTON BUDGET: THE MILITARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDB1E3AF930A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Little More Money for Weapons and Repairs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The President's budget proposal, delivered to Congress today, increases the Pentagon's total spending only slightly, but it includes additional money for advanced weapons and new financing for spare parts and repairs to keep American forces better prepared for combat.</p>
        <p>The budget also revives the Administration's controversial proposal to hold two more rounds of base closings, in 2001 and 2005. Congress rejected the idea last year, and there are few signs that lawmakers have changed their views.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The President's budget proposal, delivered to Congress today, increases the Pentagon's total spending only slightly, but it includes additional money for advanced weapons and new financing for spare parts and repairs to keep American forces better prepared for combat.</p>
        <p>The budget also revives the Administration's controversial proposal to hold two more rounds of base closings, in 2001 and 2005. Congress rejected the idea last year, and there are few signs that lawmakers have changed their views.</p>
        <p>At a Pentagon news conference, Defense Secretary William S. Cohen said that closing an unspecified number of additional bases would save $3 billion a year. That money, he said, could be better spent on training personnel and modernizing the military's arsenal of weapons.</p>
        <p>Total military spending would rise to $270 billion in the next fiscal year, including $257 billion for the Department of Defense and $13 billion for the Department of Energy, which maintains the nation's nuclear stockpile.</p>
        <p>The proposal reflects an increase of $3 billion, or only 1 percent, from the current budget. That keeps the Pentagon's budget in line with last year's balanced budget agreement, which holds military spending relatively flat into the next century.</p>
        <p>One of the few areas slated for significant increases is weaponry. Spending on new weapons would increase to $48.7 billion, from $45 billion this year. By the year 2001, it would rise to $60 billion.</p>
        <p>The budget proposal sets aside $2.9 billion to buy 30 more F/A-18E/F fighter jets for the Navy and Marine Corps, despite nagging problems in fixing a flaw in the aircraft's wing. The budget would also pay for the first two F-22 Raptors, the Air Force's new ''stealth'' fighter, increasing spending on the overall program to nearly $2.4 billion, from $2 billion.</p>
        <p>The budget also includes smaller increases for helicopters, computer-guided missiles and bombs, as well as $800 million for equipment to detect and protect American forces from chemical and biological weapons attacks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen pointed to an increase in spending to address what he acknowledged was a shortfall in the ''readiness'' of American forces at a time when Iraq, Bosnia and other missions have stretched resources. The increase would include $1 billion for spare parts and maintenance, as well as extra benefits for pilots who are being lured away from the Air Force by commercial airlines.</p>
        <p>Addressing another area in which the Administration has faced criticism, the budget calls for a 3.1 percent increase in military pay in the next year and 3 percent in each of the following four years.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Pentagon's overall budget, the Administration will also ask Congress for a supplemental appropriation to pay for the extension of the NATO-led peacekeeping mission in Bosnia. President Clinton has already announced that American troops will continue to participate in the mission once the current mandate ends in June, but the Administration has not announced how many of the 8,500 Americans now there will remain.  THE CLINTON BUDGET: THE MILITARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
