<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Helping Guests With the Answers</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71239F931A15754C0A964958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Helping Guests With the Answers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pop sociology rides again. Barbara Walters is in the saddle tonight, whipping along eight attractive young men and women who have been selected to personify the 40 million or so Americans who were born in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters concedes at the start of "Twentysomething: What Happened to the American Dream?" that eight people can't speak for</p>
        <p>all</p>
        <p>those now in their 20's, but she adds that they can tell of "growing up, romance, sex, their hopes and fears and what the American dream means to them." All right. But she or her producers are evidently unwilling to settle for human interest; they want human interest with a social-science face. Despite her disavowal, Ms. Walters indulges in generational generalizing: "This is a generation that pursues the quality of life. They want time for family, friends, themselves. They want to enjoy life on their own terms." Unlike all other generations?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pop sociology rides again. Barbara Walters is in the saddle tonight, whipping along eight attractive young men and women who have been selected to personify the 40 million or so Americans who were born in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters concedes at the start of "Twentysomething: What Happened to the American Dream?" that eight people can't speak for</p>
        <p>all</p>
        <p>those now in their 20's, but she adds that they can tell of "growing up, romance, sex, their hopes and fears and what the American dream means to them." All right. But she or her producers are evidently unwilling to settle for human interest; they want human interest with a social-science face. Despite her disavowal, Ms. Walters indulges in generational generalizing: "This is a generation that pursues the quality of life. They want time for family, friends, themselves. They want to enjoy life on their own terms." Unlike all other generations?</p>
        <p>The show works this way: Ms. Walters tosses out a statistical snippet, and a guest confirms it. By age 20, the typical American has spent 23,000 hours in front of a television set; a woman admits cheerfully to being a television addict and there she is at home watching the tube. Recent graduates have been particularly hard hit by the recession; meet a woman who is looking for a job. Millions of women in their 20's are on welfare; see the unmarried mother caring for her baby.</p>
        <p>So it goes. Ms. Walters spurs her guests with leading questions: "Don't you think you are kind of serious as a group?" And perhaps flattered or awed at being in the presence of so famous a personality or just courteous or trying to perform as expected on national television, someone always comes through: "I think we're terribly serious for 20." Noting that divorce became more common in the 1970's and 80's, Ms. Walters prods, "It may make you more afraid when you grow up in a family where you see divorce." "Right." Ms. Walters informs them, "You are pretty turned off with politicians." "Absolutely."</p>
        <p>Disappointments keep popping up. Several of the young people, responding to hints from their hostess, ooze envy at past generations. For example, the fear of AIDS has taken some of the kick out of the famous sexual revolution. (That invites a discussion about the use of condoms, a sure-fire talk-show subject.) And there are references to lowered economic expectations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walters calls the twentysomething set, somewhat unoriginally, a lost generation. And the group is encouraged to advertise its moral superiority over what she dismisses as the me decade. She announces that this generation is more interested in "personal and fulfilling rewards" than in big salaries and big jobs, and, believe it or not, nobody proudly declares they are out mainly for the buck. A man who makes television commercials clucks that in the 80's "money became the end instead of the means to the end."</p>
        <p>The only safe generalizations from this exercise are that most groups are inclined to feel put upon and if given an opportunity will let the world in on their discontents. The one married man present tells of the burden of paying back big school loans and meeting all the other bills of a growing family. A black bank executive says he has to work harder than whites to win respect. The welfare mother tells of the difficulties of working her way off welfare.</p>
        <p>Any of these conditions might make for an illuminating hour. But Ms. Walters, like a schoolteacher determined to obtain the answers set down in her curriculum guide, elicits uplifting cliches. She asks what her sample would most like viewers to know about their generation. An A to the man who answers: "We are responsible and we are willing to take the torch."</p>
        <p>Given the amount of television these people admit to having watched, they ought by now to be wary of shows that pander to the latest consuming generation. "Twentysomething" is upscale Oprah. Categorizing eight men and women, if it is to be at all enlightening, takes a more sophisticated touch than is applied tonight. So it would be unfair, as you might be inclined to do at moments in this exasperating hour, to write 40 million people off as the kvetch generation. Twentysomething What Happened to the American Dream?  ABC, tonight. (Channel 7 at 10 in New York.)</p>
        <p>An ABC News special, directed by George Paul; David Doss, senior producer, for ABC News; Lionel Chapman, executive producer; Barbara Walters, host.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
