<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Securities Little Changed</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOND PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILPIN, KENNETH N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD1531F931A15754C0A964958260" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Securities Little Changed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILPIN, KENNETH N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congressional testimony by the Federal Reserve Board chairman, Alan Greenspan, contained few surprises for the credit markets yesterday, and prices of Treasury securities were little changed.</p>
        <p>In his remarks, Mr. Greenspan expressed confidence that the economy was expanding and that a sustainable recovery would be under way soon. This echoed the views he presented to the Senate Banking Committee a year ago, and again in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congressional testimony by the Federal Reserve Board chairman, Alan Greenspan, contained few surprises for the credit markets yesterday, and prices of Treasury securities were little changed.</p>
        <p>In his remarks, Mr. Greenspan expressed confidence that the economy was expanding and that a sustainable recovery would be under way soon. This echoed the views he presented to the Senate Banking Committee a year ago, and again in February.</p>
        <p>By law, the chairman of the Federal Reserve is required to testify before Congress semiannually on the economy and monetary policy. Mr. Greenspan will go before a subcomittee of the House Banking Committee today.</p>
        <p>For a day at least, traders interpreted his remarks to mean that the Fed has finished easing monetary policy.</p>
        <p>"He didn't say anything unexpected, but on balance it doesn't seem to be good news for the front end" of the maturity spectrum, one government securities trader said. "And in these politically uncertain times, nobody wants to buy bonds."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, some economists said they were disappointed that Mr. Greenspan was not asked how surprisingly bad June economic data fit into his mildly optimistic outlook.  Fed Raises Its Forecast</p>
        <p>Reflecting a rosier view, the Fed raised its 1992 growth estimates to a range of 2.25 percent to 2.75 percent, from the 1.75 percent to 2.50 percent range it forecast in February.</p>
        <p>But some economists wondered if the weaker June numbers were reflected in the forecast presented yesterday by Mr. Greenspan. Some noted that the Fed met to prepare its forecast before June employment data were released earlier this month.</p>
        <p>"I think June represented a rather dramatic event in the development of this recovery, because with the exception of car sales none of the numbers pointed in the direction of recovery, " said David H. Resler, chief economist at Nomura Securities International Inc. "Private sector forecasts have been lowered dramatically since those numbers came out."</p>
        <p>Joseph Coyne, a Fed spokesman, said Fed governors and bank presidents had the option of revising their forecasts after the June employment data were released. He said he did not know how many had chosen to exercise that option or how it might have affected the forecast.  Long Bonds Up Slightly</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for Treasury securities, the 8 percent 29 1/2-year bonds of 2021 were offered late yesterday at a price of 103 31/32, up 1/32, to yield 7.65 percent, unchanged from late Monday.</p>
        <p>Among outstanding Treasury note issues, the 7 1/2 percent 10-year notes were offered at 104 14/32, up 5/32, to yield 6.86 percent. The 6 3/8 percent five-year notes were offered at 102 17/32, up 3/32, to yield 5.77 percent. And the 5 percent two-year notes were offered at 101 11/32, down 1/32, to yield 4.26 percent.</p>
        <p>The sense that monetary policy is on hold pushed up rates on short-term Treasury bills.</p>
        <p>Three-month bills were offered late yesterday at a discount rate of 3.18 percent, up 4 basis points, or hundredths of a percentage point. Six-month bill rates rose by 2 basis points, to a late offered rate of 3.24 percent.</p>
        <p>A number of issues were priced in the investment-grade and tax-exempt municipal bond markets.  Utility Sells Notes</p>
        <p>By far the biggest issuer was the Tennessee Valley Authority, which offered a total of $1.25 billion worth of seven-year and 10-year notes at competitive bid. The sale was the largest competitive bid offering ever by an American utility company.</p>
        <p>Bids from a group led by Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company won both parts of the offering.</p>
        <p>The seven-year securities were reoffered to investors with a 6.25 percent coupon at a price of $98.47 to yield 6.526 percent, 15 basis points over the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 7 percent seven-year notes at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>The 10-year notes were reoffered with a 6 7/8 percent coupon at a price of $98.585 to yield 7.075 percent, 19 basis points over the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 7 1/2 percent 10-year notes at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>In the asset-backed securities market, FCC National Bank, a subsidiary of the First Chicago Corporation, priced $1 billion worth of certificates backed by credit card receivables through underwriters led by the First Boston Corporation.</p>
        <p>The securities, which have an average expected life of 5.07 years, carry a 6 1/4 percent coupon and were priced to yield 6.353 percent, 55 basis points over the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 6 3/8 percent five-year notes at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>The securities are rated AAA by both Moody's Investors Service and the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation.  New York Refunding Bonds</p>
        <p>An offering of more than $372 million worth of New York State general-obligation refunding bonds was well received by investors.</p>
        <p>Yields on the serial bonds sold range from 3.0 percent in 1993 to 4.90 percent in 1997, 5.75 percent in 2002, 6.05 percent in 2007 and 6.15 percent on bonds maturing from 2010 to 2015.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch &amp; Company acted as lead manager for the negotiated sale.</p>
        <p>The bonds are rated A by Moody's and A- by Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for investment-grade corporate bonds, traders said prices of most issues were unchanged.</p>
        <p>Participants in the tax-exempt municipal bond market said prices of most widely quoted securities had risen by an eighth of a point to a quarter of a point.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
