<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bird Hits Milestone; Celtics Extend Streak</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="405299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Boston Celtics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D81230F932A35751C1A966958260" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bird Hits Milestone; Celtics Extend Streak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Nov. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Bird became the 15th National Basketball Association player to pass the 20,000-point milestone and the Boston Celtics stretched their winning streak to eight games with a 123-95 victory tonight over the Washington Bullets.</p>
        <p>Bird's historic basket came with 3 minutes 40 seconds gone in the third quarter. Bird dribbled from right to left and, guarded closely by the 6-foot-3-inch Haywoode Workman, sank a fallaway jumper from the foul line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry Bird became the 15th National Basketball Association player to pass the 20,000-point milestone and the Boston Celtics stretched their winning streak to eight games with a 123-95 victory tonight over the Washington Bullets.</p>
        <p>Bird's historic basket came with 3 minutes 40 seconds gone in the third quarter. Bird dribbled from right to left and, guarded closely by the 6-foot-3-inch Haywoode Workman, sank a fallaway jumper from the foul line.</p>
        <p>That shot gave him 13 points for the game and 20,001 for his career. He finished the game with 21 points for 20,009 in his 12-year career.</p>
        <p>Bird joins Kareem Abdul-Jabbar, John Havlicek, Oscar Robertson and Jerry West as the only players with both 20,000 points and 5,000 assists. George Gervin is 14th with 20,708 points.</p>
        <p>Leading by 96-84, Boston broke the game open with a 13-0 run, started by Bird's third 3-pointer of the game with 7:22 left. Kevin Gamble had 6 points in the surge that gave Boston a 109-84 lead with 4:48 remaining.</p>
        <p>Robert Parish had 15 rebounds and Bird 14 as Boston held a 60-42 advantage off the boards.</p>
        <p>Kevin McHale and Dee Brown had 18 points each for Boston, which had eight scorers in double figures. Washington was led by Bernard King with 22 points and Harvey Grant with 21. Warriors 119, Magic 113</p>
        <p>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) -- Chris Mullin scored 28 points and Mitch Richmond scored 9 crucial fourth-quarter points as Golden State handed Orlando its sixth consecutive loss.</p>
        <p>Richmond, slowed by foul trouble most of the game, hit a turnaround jumper to snap a 109-109 tie with just under two minutes to play, then added four free throws down the stretch to enable Golden State to improve its record to 10-6, the team's best start since the 1975-76 season.</p>
        <p>Tim Hardaway scored 8 fourth-quarter points for the Warriors and finished with 18 points and 18 assists, while Richmond had 15 points in 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>Dennis Scott hit a team-record 6 of 10 3-point shots and led the Magic with 24 points. Cavaliers 101, Hawks 93</p>
        <p>ATLANTA (AP) -- Brad Daugherty scored 30 points and Larry Nance 22, including a crucial shot with 1:54 remaining, as Cleveland defeated Atlanta. The loss was the Hawks' ninth in a row.</p>
        <p>The losing streak is the longest for the Hawks since the 1981 team lost 10 in a row. They also have lost five consecutive games at home. Pistons 96, 76ers 94</p>
        <p>AUBURN HILLS, Mich. (AP) -- Joe Dumars scored 16 of his 24 points in the second half as Detroit survived a 13-point first quarter to win its 10th consecutive game.</p>
        <p>Charles Barkley led Philadelphia with 22 points before being ejected for elbowing Dennis Rodman in the face with 7:32 left in the game. Hersey Hawkins added 20 points for the 76ers. Jazz 96, Timberwolves 79</p>
        <p>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) -- Jeff Malone scored 14 of his 19 points in the third quarter to lead Utah.</p>
        <p>The Jazz, who won their fifth consecutive game, outscored Minnesota by 34-18 in the third period, turning a 1-point halftime lead into a 75-58 advantage going into the final 12 minutes. The Timberwolves got no closer than 9 points in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Pooh Richardson had 22 points and 10 assists for the Timberwolves. Bulls 124, Pacers 95</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (AP) -- Michael Jordan scored 20 of his 37 points on 10-for-11 shooting in the first quarter as Chicago routed Indiana.</p>
        <p>The victory was Chicago's fourth in a row, while the Pacers, 0-8 on the road this season, have lost four consecutive times.</p>
        <p>Vern Fleming led the with 14 points.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
