<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; Opulence Is Back: Fendi Lets the Fur Flow</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="747661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MILAN (ITALY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FENDI (CO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENNY (FASHION HOUSE)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MASKA (FASHION HOUSE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHIRO, ANNE-MARIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAGERFELD, KARL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fur</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF173BF93AA35750C0A963958260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; Opulence Is Back: Fendi Lets the Fur Flow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE-MARIE SCHIRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHIRO, ANNE-MARIE</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, Italy, March 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Luxury lives. At least for some. Both the Fendi and Genny collections shown today are intended for women who aren't afraid to wear their wealth on their backs. Maybe it isn't the 1960's or 70's but the 80's that are coming back.</p>
        <p>It was snowing -- a rare sight in Milan during fashion week -- as cars pulled up to the house where Fendi held its show this afternoon. How fitting for a collection that brought furs out of the closet with no apologies. Last winter, Fendi's furs were hidden as linings or mixed with fake fur to fool onlookers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Luxury lives. At least for some. Both the Fendi and Genny collections shown today are intended for women who aren't afraid to wear their wealth on their backs. Maybe it isn't the 1960's or 70's but the 80's that are coming back.</p>
        <p>It was snowing -- a rare sight in Milan during fashion week -- as cars pulled up to the house where Fendi held its show this afternoon. How fitting for a collection that brought furs out of the closet with no apologies. Last winter, Fendi's furs were hidden as linings or mixed with fake fur to fool onlookers.</p>
        <p>"I'm tired of being politically correct," Karl Lagerfeld, the designer who has been besieged by anti-fur activists, said today. "It's not illegal to make furs. We don't use any endangered species. And fur is better than anything else when it's cold."</p>
        <p>To illustrate, he opened the show with extravagant sable coats in rare pale shades. The models were dripping in fur. One wore her coat nonchalantly backward with a rope of pearls hanging down her back like a latter-day Zelda Fitzgerald.</p>
        <p>The sables streamed down the runway followed by chinchilla dyed shades of golden brown, mink tinged with green or blue, ermine dyed glossy black and a rabbit fur called orylag that had markings rather like sheared chinchilla.</p>
        <p>Everything was big and luscious and looked cuddly warm enough to brave the frozen tundra.</p>
        <p>There were coats that mimicked shearling in sheared mink and other furs with the leather side glazed with a metallic finish. There were fur-lined iridescent taffeta coats in shades of bronze, blue, green and gold. And there were furs randomly dyed with specks of peach and blue.</p>
        <p>Coats were mostly long and belted, sometimes featuring huge cape-like collars. There were also knitted or crocheted sweaters and capes trimmed with fur and separate collar-like scarfs added to fabric coats. Yes, there were fabric coats, too, and woolen suits and dresses to round out the collection.</p>
        <p>Skirts and dresses tended to be long and lean, a harbinger perhaps of what Mr. Lagerfeld has in mind for his Paris collections next week.</p>
        <p>There are no casual clothes at Genny. Even daytime suits in leather or fine wool have jeweled buttons to take a woman from lunch at Le Cirque to dinner at the Four Seasons. Jackets are mostly long and lean, skirts always straight as a pencil whether they skim the knees or brush the calves. Slits are not mere decoration. They are required for walking. Dresses cling to the body, often with draping to emphasize curves.</p>
        <p>The basic color is black, sometimes from head to pointy toe and other times punctuated by a jacket or coat in cerulean blue, chartreuse, orange, fuchsia or white. All the Italian houses are pushing white for winter. Could they be in league with the dry cleaners?</p>
        <p>Evening is when all-out opulence reigns. The simplest styles are satin suits in orchid or fuchsia. The majority of formal dresses are in shimmery, sheer, metallic fabrics or are almost totally covered with beads. Genny's designer, Rebecca Moses, may be American, but there was no Yankee understatement in the collection.</p>
        <p>"Understated" is definitely the word to describe the clothes of Maska, a newcomer to the Milan runways. To add a measure of excitement to its classic styles, the company relied on personalities rather than models to show the collection. So instead of Claudia, Nadja and Helena, there were Marisa Berenson, Janice Dickinson, Alba Clemente, Veruschka and a bevy of European performers that only the Italians in the audience recognized. One was a zaftig redhead named Milva who is scheduled to appear in "Sunset Boulevard" in Germany.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
