<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Attacks Kill 27 Iraqi Civilians and Policemen and Many Rebels</title>
    <meta content="04IRAQ$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/04/international/middleeast/04iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1632006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="REACH OF WAR: INSURGENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mosul (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DC1731F937A35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Attacks Kill 27 Iraqi Civilians and Policemen and Many Rebels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">27 Civilians Die in New Attacks by Iraq Rebels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT F. WORTH and RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr.; Khalid al-Ansary and Layla Isitfan contributed reporting from Baghdad for this article; Iraqi employees of The New York Times from Karbala and Basra; and Eric Schmitt from Washington.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert F; Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Dec. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Insurgents launch attacks in Baghdad and Mosul, striking at police stations, military bases and Shiite mosque; at least 27 Iraqi civilians and policemen and dozens of insurgents are killed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavily armed insurgents launched attacks here and in the northern city of Mosul on Friday morning, striking at police stations, military bases and a Shiite mosque. At least 27 Iraqi civilians and policemen and dozens of insurgents were killed.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, several dozen black-clad militants stormed a police station just after dawn, killing a dozen officers, police officials said. Almost simultaneously, a powerful car bomb detonated outside a Shiite mosque in the capital's Adhamiya neighborhood, killing 15 Iraqi civilians and wounding 18, mostly worshipers leaving the mosque.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heavily armed insurgents launched attacks in Baghdad and in Mosul, striking at police stations, military bases and a Shiite mosque.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heavily armed insurgents launched attacks here and in the northern city of Mosul on Friday morning, striking at police stations, military bases and a Shiite mosque. At least 27 Iraqi civilians and policemen and dozens of insurgents were killed.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad, several dozen black-clad militants stormed a police station just after dawn, killing a dozen officers, police officials said. Almost simultaneously, a powerful car bomb detonated outside a Shiite mosque in the capital's Adhamiya neighborhood, killing 15 Iraqi civilians and wounding 18, mostly worshipers leaving the mosque.</p>
        <p>In Mosul, insurgents struck at least three police stations, hit American bases with mortars and staged elaborate ambushes involving synchronized explosions of remote-controlled bombs. At least 22 insurgents were killed, while 7 American soldiers suffered minor wounds, according to American commanders.</p>
        <p>The violence, coinciding with several smaller-scale attacks throughout the country, demonstrated the continued power of the insurgency here and the ferocity of the militants' campaign against the fledgling Iraqi security forces as the January elections approach.</p>
        <p>Shortly after the police station attack, an Islamist Web site posted a message from the network of the Jordanian militant Abu Musab al-Zarqawi claiming responsibility. The statement was impossible to verify. But it suggested that Mr. Zarqawi, who claimed responsibility last week for attacks in Mosul that left 17 Iraqi national guardsmen and an American soldier dead, may still be capable of planning attacks here.</p>
        <p>American military officials have said that Mr. Zarqawi appears to be setting up new cells in the wake of the American-led offensive in Falluja last month, but that he has lost the ability to communicate effectively with cellphones and messengers.</p>
        <p>The Baghdad attacks began shortly after dawn, when several dozen men armed with mortars, rocket-propelled grenades and machine guns stormed a police station in the southern Baghdad neighborhood of Seydiya, destroying several police cars and freeing about 50 prisoners, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police inside the compound held off the attackers at first, but soon ran out of ammunition, survivors and witnesses said. They called for reinforcements, but when the new officers arrived, the guerrillas entered the compound with them. The insurgents, shouting ''God is great!'' in Arabic, quickly took over the station and pursued six fleeing officers to the roof, where they shot them all execution-style, with one bullet to the head.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, the car bomb detonated outside the mosque. Witnesses described two explosions, one that damaged the mosque but killed no one at about 6:15 a.m., and a second, larger, one 20 minutes later, just as worshipers were trying to help put out the flames.</p>
        <p>After the blast, human remains and metal shards lay scattered in the alleyway by the mosque's shattered front gate, and the air was filled with the cries of friends and relatives of the dead. Several cars and neighboring buildings were engulfed with flames, and it took firefighters nearly two hours to put them out.</p>
        <p>In Mosul, United States officials had received intelligence that a major attack was being planned. Insurgents there had largely avoided direct confrontations with the Americans since the uprising three weeks ago, when more than 100 guerrillas were killed.</p>
        <p>After the attacks began late in the morning, American troops shut down three of the five bridges over the Tigris River and sealed off much of western Mosul, as insurgents roamed the streets. Overhead, fighter jets and Apache attack helicopters swooped in.</p>
        <p>The Mosul attacks appeared to have been planned well in advance, according to American commanders. ''The terrorists told the civilians they were going to attack the Americans and to stay indoors,'' said Lt. Col. Erik Kurilla, the commander of the First Battalion of the 24th Infantry, which controls much of western Mosul. Shops near the biggest ambush closed just before the attack, the commanders said.</p>
        <p>The attacks started as a patrol of American Stryker armored vehicles chased insurgents who had fired mortars at an American base. Eight insurgents ambushed the patrol, and United States forces killed three.</p>
        <p>Traveling back to its base, the patrol was attacked in what American officials described as a milelong ambush along a main thoroughfare in western Mosul. According to Maj. Doug Sims, the operations officer for the brigade that controls Mosul, as many as 35 insurgents lined up on either side of the road, armed with rocket-propelled grenades, Kalashnikov rifles and other weapons.</p>
        <p>What made the ambush distinct was a string of very powerful bombs made from 152-millimeter artillery shells. At least 10 of the bombs were lined up 150 to 200 yards apart and detonated as the Americans drove past, according to Colonel Kurilla. The Stryker vehicles, which also received at least nine direct hits from rocket-propelled grenades, suffered only minor damage and were able to continue fighting, he said.</p>
        <p>Later, troops returned and killed 15 insurgents along the same route, he said. Iraqi troops also stormed a partly built mosque where insurgents had fired at American soldiers. Inside, they found five rocket-propelled grenade launchers and seven Russian-made machine guns among other weapons, military officials said</p>
        <p>The attacks in Mosul and Baghdad came as sporadic violence continued in other parts of the country. In the capital, an American soldier was killed and three were wounded when a roadside bomb detonated near their patrol. In the northern city of Kirkuk, one American soldier was killed and two were wounded by another roadside bomb.</p>
        <p>Near Basra, in southern Iraq, two insurgents were killed Friday while trying to plant a bomb near a voter registration center.</p>
        <p>In Karbala, south of Baghdad, an Iraqi National Guard captain was shot and killed as he walked with his father, witnesses said.</p>
        <p>The attacks in Mosul and Baghdad, following a brief period of relative calm after the American-led offensive in Falluja last month, made clear that the rebels' resources are far from spent.</p>
        <p>Senator Chuck Hagel, a Nebraska Republican and Vietnam veteran who met with American commanders in Iraq on Thursday, said Friday in a telephone interview that the insurgency's intimidation campaign was growing increasingly deadly.</p>
        <p>''I did not find one commander who said to me, 'We're winning,''' said Mr. Hagel, a member of the Foreign Relations Committee who in the past has criticized the Bush administration for not deploying more troops in Iraq. ''They're doing everything they can. But we have constantly underestimated the insurgency force and the vitality of the insurgency.''</p>
        <p>American military commanders have said they expect the violence to grow as January elections approach.</p>
        <p>The attack on the Shiite mosque in Baghdad appears to be part of another tactic by insurgents -- mostly Sunni Arabs -- to destabilize the country by provoking sectarian divisions, a United States official in Baghdad said Friday.</p>
        <p>That was the view of many victims and witnesses of the mosque attack in Adhamiya, a former bastion of support for Saddam Hussein where many insurgents are said to live. ''I think they targeted the mosque to create racism between the Iraqi people,'' said Abdul Ameer Khamis, who lives nearby. ''There are no important officials or facilities in this neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>REACH OF WAR: INSURGENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
