<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Crisis Hits Mexico's States, With Some Nearly Broke</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="761622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFAULTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEPALMA, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D7133AF933A25756C0A963958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Crisis Hits Mexico's States, With Some Nearly Broke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEPALMA, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The severe economic crisis that has thrown hundreds of thousands of Mexicans out of work and devastated the balance sheets of many Mexican companies is also taking its toll on the country's 31 states, which have asked the federal Government to help them avoid bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Soaring interest rates, which have hit 100 percent, have made it impossible for states and local communities to repay billions of dollars in loans that were used to finance public works projects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The severe economic crisis that has thrown hundreds of thousands of Mexicans out of work and devastated the balance sheets of many Mexican companies is also taking its toll on the country's 31 states, which have asked the federal Government to help them avoid bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Soaring interest rates, which have hit 100 percent, have made it impossible for states and local communities to repay billions of dollars in loans that were used to finance public works projects.</p>
        <p>President Ernesto Zedillo announced a $2.9 billion rescue program last Thursday that would allow the states to restructure their loans, lowering interest rates and spreading out the time for repayment to as long as eight years.</p>
        <p>In return, states that take part agreed to prepay part of their loans. They also accepted conditions imposed by the federal Government to overhaul their fiscal operations, possibly including the privatization of state-owned enterprises.</p>
        <p>The 31 Governors have generally accepted the need for such a program but the four who belong to the opposition accused the federal Government of assuming the same intrusive role that they said the United States did when it offered Mexico $20 billion in loans last March to deal with the economic crisis.</p>
        <p>Mexico then was forced to change its fiscal policies radically, and will have to report to the United States and international financial organizations on the progress of its restructuring before it can receive full use of the rescue money.</p>
        <p>Carlos Medina Plasciencia, opposition Governor of the central state of Guanajuato, said the program is simply "an aspirin," and another indication of the dependency of the states on the central Government.</p>
        <p>President Zedillo said the debt restructuring is part of his ongoing attempt to transform the relationship between the federal Government and the states, which he said has been marked by excessive reliance on the center.</p>
        <p>"Centralism is a drag on development that inhibits the deployment of social, economic and political energies of the states," Mr. Zedillo said in announcing the program.</p>
        <p>The opposition has so far been skeptical of Mr. Zedillo's efforts. Last month, the opposition Mayor of Ciudad Juarez set up his own toll booths on the international bridge connecting with El Paso to protest what he called the federal Government's unfair distribution of funds.</p>
        <p>Mexican states rely on the federal Government for about 80 percent of their funds, which have been cut by an average of 14 percent this year.</p>
        <p>The total debt of the 31 states is estimated by officials to be around 23 billion pesos, or almost $4 billion at current exchange rates. Most of the debt was incurred by states and local communities that took out commercial bank loans at variable interest rates -- Mexican states and municipalities do not float government bonds -- to pay their share of public works projects financed primarily by the federal Government.</p>
        <p>All 31 states have been hurt by the rising interest rates but some, including Nuevo Leon in northern Mexico and Jalisco in the center, have been pushed to the edge of bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>States that take part in the loan restructuring agree to prepay 10, 20 or 30 percent of their commercial loans. They will be allowed to use recent increases in sales taxes to make those payments.</p>
        <p>Interest rates will range from 7.5 percent to 9.5 percent, depending on the size of the prepayment. The loans will be restructured in such a way as to protect them from the effects of inflation, which is expected to exceed 50 percent this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
