<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks Continuing on Viacom Cable Channel</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="845953"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEAGRAM CO LTD</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TV LAND (PROPOSED CABLE CHANNEL)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCA INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">USANETWORK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REDSTONE, SUMNER M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRONFMAN, EDGAR JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIONDI, FRANK J JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0D71F39F937A15757C0A960958260" item-length="506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks Continuing on Viacom Cable Channel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman of Viacom Inc., and Edgar Bronfman Jr., the  chief executive of the Seagram Corporation, met again yesterday in an effort to  resolve their differences over the introduction of Viacom's new cable channel, TVLand, according to several executives close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Both men described the meeting as extremely amicable. One reason perhaps was  Mr. Redstone's unexpected decision on Monday to allow Frank J. Biondi Jr., whom  he had ousted as president and chief executive of Viacom in January, to become chief executive of Seagram's MCA unit, despite a one-year noncompete clause in his Viacom contract and despite the companies' differences over TVLand. Mr. Biondi was formally named to the MCA post yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sumner M. Redstone, the chairman of Viacom Inc., and Edgar Bronfman Jr., the  chief executive of the Seagram Corporation, met again yesterday in an effort to  resolve their differences over the introduction of Viacom's new cable channel, TVLand, according to several executives close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Both men described the meeting as extremely amicable. One reason perhaps was  Mr. Redstone's unexpected decision on Monday to allow Frank J. Biondi Jr., whom  he had ousted as president and chief executive of Viacom in January, to become chief executive of Seagram's MCA unit, despite a one-year noncompete clause in his Viacom contract and despite the companies' differences over TVLand. Mr. Biondi was formally named to the MCA post yesterday.</p>
        <p>Viacom and MCA are joint owners of USA Network, and under that agreement neither side can begin a new network without the other.</p>
        <p>Viacom argues that TVLand is not a new network but simply a spinoff of its successful Nick at Night service, these executives said.</p>
        <p>But MCA has taken the position that TVLand is in effect a new network, and that Viacom cannot begin it without offering MCA a stake. It is not clear whether MCA actually wants an ownership position in the service, according to one person close to the discussions.</p>
        <p>In introducing new channels today, time is of the essence. Many companies want the opportunity to promote their new services at a cable show that is to open in San Francisco next week. Moreover, by late this summer, the industry expects to introduce digital converters that will increase capacity to several hundred channels.</p>
        <p>Consequently, programmers are racing to "reserve electronic real estate," according to Larry Gerbrandt, a media analyst at the Paul Kagan Associates media consulting firm.</p>
        <p>At one point MCA indicated that it might take legal action, which could slow  Viacom's chances of getting TVLand into the marketplace.</p>
        <p>It had originally been reported that Viacom would not let Mr. Biondi out of his contract until the TVLand issue was resolved. Mr. Biondi had opposed MCA's becoming a partner in TVLand, and Mr. Redstone, executives said, argued that it  would difficult to have him now representing the other side.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Redstone relented, apparently without resolving the differences, according to executives close to the talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biondi declined to comment on the fight yesterday during a conference call with Ron Meyer, the president of MCA Inc. Although there have been rumors that the two men might not get along, they said they were looking forward to working together and would focus jointly on issues from budgets to strategy.</p>
        <p>Regarding the actual division of responsibilities, Mr. Biondi joked that it was "murky." Mr. Biondi said he would be based in Los Angeles but would travel to New York monthly.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
