<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Export Boom In Services Cuts Growth in U.S. Trade Deficit</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="845891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KANTOR, MICKEY (TRADE REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6D71F39F937A15757C0A960958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Export Boom In Services Cuts Growth in U.S. Trade Deficit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Erasing about half of a huge January increase, the nation's trade deficit shrank to $8.2 billion in February as sales of American services abroad rose to  records, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>Exports over all climbed 2 percent to the second-highest total on record while imports fell five-tenths of 1 percent. It was the first time since November that the deficit had narrowed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Erasing about half of a huge January increase, the nation's trade deficit shrank to $8.2 billion in February as sales of American services abroad rose to  records, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>Exports over all climbed 2 percent to the second-highest total on record while imports fell five-tenths of 1 percent. It was the first time since November that the deficit had narrowed.</p>
        <p>The deficit was about $400 million less than expected, and was accompanied by a downward revision of that amount for January. But private analysts noted two main reasons for the contraction and said that neither was likely to be repeated soon.</p>
        <p>One was a big drop in the cost of imported petroleum products, which tumbled  $1 billion, to $4 billion. The other was a surge in exports of civilian aircraft in the aftermath of a strike at the Boeing Company, which was settled in December.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the Clinton Administration seized on the results as an affirmation of its trade practices. In the early Presidential primaries, some of the Republican aspirants asserted that many American workers had been idled as a result of free trade policies.</p>
        <p>"Our improved trade picture reflects the ongoing improvement in the competitiveness of the U.S. economy, its productivity growth and innovation, and our own efforts to open the doors of foreign markets to American products,"  said Mickey Kantor, the former United States trade representative, whom President Clinton named to succeed the late Ronald H. Brown as Secretary of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Many economists said that the strong performance in trade, which accounted for much of the economy's skimpy growth in the final three months of 1995, would weigh down performance in the current quarter and might contribute little for the balance of the year.</p>
        <p>"The message is that U.S. exports are competitive but they are being held back by softness in some of our major markets," said Robert G. Dederick, economic consultant to the Northern Trust Company in Chicago. He said that European economies were "still wallowing around" and that the dollar's rise against the yen would limit further increases in exports to Japan.</p>
        <p>Still, today's report confirmed a marked recent improvement in the American deficit with Japan. It edged up $100 million, to $3.9 billion, in February, but  that was down from $4.7 billion in February 1995.</p>
        <p>Matthew Alexy, chief market strategist at CS First Boston, cited the lower deficit with Japan as a chief reason for the overall narrowing of the nation's trade imbalance in the last year.</p>
        <p>The deficit with China moved down $300 million, to $2.4 billion, in February, but that was up from $1.9 billion in February 1995. Unlike the aggregate figures, those for individual countries are not adjusted for seasonal fluctuations.</p>
        <p>Today's report also showed a $500 million narrowing of the deficit with Canada, the nation's biggest trading partner, to $1.4 billion; an unchanged deficit with Mexico at $1.3 billion, and a halving of the deficits with Western  Europe ($460 million) and four newly industrial Asian countries ($815 million).</p>
        <p>The rise in exports for the month was $1.3 billion, to $68.1 billion, with civilian aircraft accounting for just over half the increase, today's report showed. Imports eased $400 million, to $76.3 billion, dominated by the 20 percent drop in petroleum purchases. Imports of motor vehicles and parts were virtually unchanged.</p>
        <p>Economists said they would be watching closely to see how these goods sold. "It will either turn out that importers guessed right, and U.S. demand picks up  sharply, or they will have bet wrong and be facing another inventory problem later this spring," said David Orr, a senior economist for First Union National  Bank in Charlotte. "We'd bet on the latter."</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department said it now calculated the January deficit at $9.9 billion, down from $10.3 billion first reported late last month.</p>
        <p>February's record export performance in services -- financial, legal, educational, tourist, telecommunications and others -- provided a surplus of $18.4 billion, $600 million higher than in January.</p>
        <p>The American surplus in advanced technology products, which briefly disappeared in September and October, climbed to $1.9 billion in February from $560 million in January, the report showed.</p>
        <p>Asked at a briefing whether he favored merging the trade representative's office into the Commerce Department, Mr. Kantor replied flatly, "It's not an option."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
