<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Key Shoulders the Load, But Yanks Drop the Ball</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="845976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KANSAS CITY ROYALS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED71F39F937A15757C0A960958260" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Key Shoulders the Load, But Yanks Drop the Ball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Vitiello flicked the baseball off the end of his bat and it sailed lazily into medium center field. The ball stayed in the air long enough to be caught, but what looked like a third out turned into a devastating hit because Bernie Williams was playing deep in center and because Paul O'Neill slowed down in right after figuring that Williams would corral it.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had a sinking feeling as the ball plummeted toward the grass in the sixth inning tonight and Williams's sliding attempt at a catch fell inches short. The blooper that should have been snared glanced off Williams's glove for a double that scored the burly Patrick Lennon from first and gave the Royals a pivotal 3-2 lead in a game they ultimately won, 5-2, at Kauffman Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Vitiello flicked the baseball off the end of his bat and it sailed lazily into medium center field. The ball stayed in the air long enough to be caught, but what looked like a third out turned into a devastating hit because Bernie Williams was playing deep in center and because Paul O'Neill slowed down in right after figuring that Williams would corral it.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had a sinking feeling as the ball plummeted toward the grass in the sixth inning tonight and Williams's sliding attempt at a catch fell inches short. The blooper that should have been snared glanced off Williams's glove for a double that scored the burly Patrick Lennon from first and gave the Royals a pivotal 3-2 lead in a game they ultimately won, 5-2, at Kauffman Stadium.</p>
        <p>Even though the Yankees still had opportunities to rebound after the sluggish fielding display, it obviously deflated them and it helped to waste Jimmy Key's capable effort. Key did not allow a hit for three innings and he would have been locked in a taut 2-2 duel with Mark Gubicza if Williams, who had slugged a two-run homer in the fifth, had made the play on Vitiello, who had rocked Kansas City's first homer in 87 innings to score two in the fourth.</p>
        <p>"I should have caught that ball," said Williams, whose manager blamed O'Neill for the gaffe.</p>
        <p>Things turned ugly in a hurry for Key because he also received scant help from the bullpen and from a lineup that did not produce crucial hits, going 2 for 14 with runners on base. A two-out Kansas City rally against Key and Bob Wickman in the seventh yielded two insurance runs to make it 5-2, but the ball that eluded Williams dominated the post-game discussion as the Yankees' three-game winning streak fizzled against an inferior team.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, there were conflicting opinions about Vitiello's double. Manager Joe Torre somehow fingered O'Neill for the misplay, but Williams and O'Neill both said or implied that the center fielder should have caught the ball because the Yankees were playing straight away for the opposite-field hitter and the ball landed closer to center than to right. Torre saw it differently and tiptoed toward a possible controversy to climax a 3-4 road trip.</p>
        <p>"I thought Paul had a better shot at it than Bernie," Torre said. "Paul didn't get a good jump. I think Paul was waiting for Bernie to make the play. Bernie had to come too far for that."</p>
        <p>O'Neill, who is not nearly as fast as Williams, was startled when it was suggested that he should have made the play. Unfortunately for the Yankees, both outfielders had drifted back 10 feet before Key's 3-2 pitch to Vitiello to prevent an extra-base hit into the gap.</p>
        <p>"I looked at Bernie and he had a bead on it so I veered off," O'Neill said. "That's what I do when Bernie looks like he's got it. He said he had a problem with the lights." Then, with a dose of sarcasm, O'Neill said, "If someone says I should have gotten it, I guess I should have gotten it." After speaking with reporters, an animated O'Neill chatted with Key about the play.</p>
        <p>Williams merely added, "It got in the lights as it came down and I lost it."</p>
        <p>On a night when the Yankees succumbed to a pathetic team that had lost eight  of its last nine, they were somewhat buoyed by Key. Key's left shoulder will be  a constant concern for the Yankees after his rotator cuff surgery last July, but he pleased them by uncorking 104 pitches over six and two-thirds innings while yielding four hits and five runs, striking out four and walking two.</p>
        <p>The Yankees gave Key two extra days of rest after he was torched for 6 runs and 10 hits in three and two-thirds innings against the Brewers last Tuesday, and he responded with his highest pitch count in four starts. While Key is 1-3 with a 7.08 earned run average, he was upbeat after the loss and even tried accepting the blame for Vitiello's double by saying he should not have let the count go full.</p>
        <p>"The most important thing for me is I kept us in the game," said Key, whose shoulder did not trouble him. "That's what I get paid to do."</p>
        <p>The Yankees should not have been pleased with much else. They mishandled a second-and-third, no-out situation in the sixth against Gubicza and a first-and-third threat in the eighth when Tim Raines bounced into a double play  off Jeff Montgomery. So the Yankees had a losing road trip after losing to a team that Torre had likened to one of the lowly Mets clubs he once managed.</p>
        <p>"It's disappointing because we had the opportunities to do things and we had  a well-pitched ball game," Torre said. "You get that kind of performance from Jimmy Key and you feel you should win."</p>
        <p>At the very least, you should catch a fly ball to center.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>PAUL O'NEILL, who has 14 stolen bases in the last four seasons, was thrown out trying to steal third base when he went on his own in the fourth. "I guess I just stunk tonight," he said. . . . When SCOTT KAMIENIECKI is activated Wednesday, infielder ROBERT EENHOORN will be optioned to Class AAA. . . . The Royals swiped three bases so JOE GIRARDI has been victimized by 20 of 23 runners. . . . JOE VITIELLO's homer was the first against the Yankees in 50 innings. . . . The Yankees begin a five-game homestand Wednesday against Cleveland and play 21 of their next 26 games at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
