<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australian Director Is Thinking Globally</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="655357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OSTERMEYER, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENES, ANDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OSTERMEYER, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENES, ANDY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DC1538F931A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australian Director Is Thinking Globally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Australian baseball has a long way to go to reach the level of play in this country, but it has something major league baseball doesn't have: a commissioner.</p>
        <p>He is John Ostermeyer, and his role as executive director of the Australian Baseball Federation makes him the equivalent of major league baseball's commissioner. It also gives him a platform from which to speak about baseball around the world, and he has been doing that fervently and eloquently in his effort to drag major league club owners into the 21st century of world sports interest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Australian baseball has a long way to go to reach the level of play in this country, but it has something major league baseball doesn't have: a commissioner.</p>
        <p>He is John Ostermeyer, and his role as executive director of the Australian Baseball Federation makes him the equivalent of major league baseball's commissioner. It also gives him a platform from which to speak about baseball around the world, and he has been doing that fervently and eloquently in his effort to drag major league club owners into the 21st century of world sports interest.</p>
        <p>"The world no longer is flat," Ostermeyer said, echoing the title of a talk he gave to the Players Association executive board in Scottsdale, Ariz., last week. "A lot of the baseball hierarchy in the United States has the mentality that baseball stops in New York and Los Angeles. Baseball in its future has to be an international game. We're in deadly combat with soccer and basketball and we're losing the battle."</p>
        <p>The battle, Ostermeyer said, is for television opportunities, sponsors, fans. The major leagues, he said, have given the other sports an uncontested shot at those economic elements. Who's Dykstra?</p>
        <p>"Internationally," he said, "baseball is running a poor last to these sports. Ask people in Europe and Asia who Michael Jordan is, who Magic Johnson is, and everybody knows. You say to them, who is Lenny Dykstra, and they don't have an idea."</p>
        <p>The large Australian, a businessman himself, criticized the major leagues for "a lack of leadership and vision," adding: "Major league baseball has no global vision, no global plan. I'm not even sure they have a comprehensive plan for themselves."</p>
        <p>Ostermeyer found the seeming absence of an international plan especially peculiar in light of the owners' lament that their national television revenue will be slashed to less than half of what it was this year. If they seek other sources of revenue, he said, they should look beyond this country's borders.</p>
        <p>"There are more opportunities offshore than in the U.S.," Ostermeyer said. "If you develop the game as a global game, you can double, triple your revenue. You have enormous potential. I strongly believe the future is going to be Europe and Asia. We should be saying where do we want to be by 2005. I don't think the owners think about it. They think about what are we going to do in spring training."</p>
        <p>Four years ago, the major leagues created Major League Baseball International to open markets, but Ostermeyer said the subsidiary's bottom line is commercial.</p>
        <p>"It seems to me major league baseball is more interested in short-term commercial gain than long-term development," he added. Widening the World Series</p>
        <p>Baseball has developed well enough in other countries, said the former Australian rules football player, that the major leagues should shed what he called the arrogance of playing the World Series with teams from only two countries.</p>
        <p>"We should have both a World Series of clubs and a World Cup of Nations," he said. "It would be bigger than the Olympics."</p>
        <p>A World Series-World Cup, he suggested, could include the Dominican Republic, Puerto Rico, Venezuela, Cuba, Mexico and Japan with other countries added later. Asians generally, he said, "are improving themselves dramatically."</p>
        <p>"Most people see baseball as an American game played internationally," Ostermeyer said. "You should strive to make it an international game played in America. That's when baseball will be successful."</p>
        <p>Australia, he said, is probably 10 years away from reaching the level of play other countries have achieved. His federation is an amateur group but also operates a semipro league that eventually will be a full-scale professional league.</p>
        <p>If major league clubs haven't discovered international opportunities, they at least have discovered budding talent in Australia. Three or four years ago, Ostermeyer said, maybe three or four Australian players a year would have been signed by major league clubs. But 35 have been signed in the last two years.</p>
        <p>Five Australians played in the majors this year: pitcher Graeme Lloyd and catcher Dave Nilsson of Milwaukee, infielder Craig Shipley and pitcher Mark Ettles of San Diego, and pitcher Mark Hutton of the Yankees.</p>
        <p>"Australia is the most scouted country outside Latin America," Ostermeyer said. Benes Resigns Himself</p>
        <p>Andy Benes is one-half of an endangered species, but he doesn't want to hold that distinction for long. He was one of only two players -- Tony Gwynn was the other -- who earned more than the major league average salary and finished the season with the San Diego Padres.</p>
        <p>"Right after the All-Star break, Randy Smith asked me if I was interested in signing a long-term contract," Benes said, referring to the Padres' then newly appointed general manager. "If I was, he said they would try to come up with something. They said they'd like to sign me but not for what I would be worth in the market. I said that's not what it's about; it's not about money. It's about a commitment to winning. There has to be a commitment to winning, and I haven't seen that. I don't think anyone else has seen that commitment."</p>
        <p>The team's No. 1 pitcher, Benes has been sought in trades this off season, but no one has acquired him because no one has been willing to pay the Padres' price.</p>
        <p>"We weren't looking to trade the guy," Smith said. "If somebody wanted to come in and knock us over, we'd consider it. But we haven't talked to anyone on Andy in at least three weeks."</p>
        <p>Benes, who needs two more seasons before he can be a free agent, recalls that it wasn't long ago that the Padres were close to being a contender, how entering the final month of the 1992 season they actually had a chance to win.</p>
        <p>"We had five All-Stars and we didn't have a bad pitching staff," he said. "It's going to be real hard to recover."</p>
        <p>Gone are Fred McGriff, Gary Sheffield, Benito Santiago, Tony Fernandez, Darrin Jackson, Bruce Hurst, Greg Harris. In their place are players who earned the minimum salary this year; in fact, 14 of the 28 players on the Padres' roster and disabled list Aug. 31 earned the minimum of $109,000.</p>
        <p>"I don't buy the fact that we just want to be competitive," said Benes, a right-hander who had a .500 record (15-15) for a team that had a .377 record (61-101). "They're asking an awful lot out of the personnel we have to play .500, and .500 isn't going to be close to the top of the pack. It doesn't matter if there are eight wild-card spots. That's not going to cut it."</p>
        <p>Benes has resigned himself to remaining with the Padres for now, although he would like to pitch for a team with an opportunity to win.</p>
        <p>"I won't sign for more than a year," he said. "I thought I was going to be traded during the winter, most likely to the Orioles or the Yankees, but now maybe I'll be traded during the season. I'll be in a situation like McGriff and Sheffield. I want to be in an environment where they will make every effort to win. That's what it's about." Sign of the Times</p>
        <p>Teams aren't the only entities affected by off-season player movement. The Players Association, whose legal efforts created free agency 18 years ago, convened its executive board meeting in Scottsdale, Ariz., last week, and more than one-sixth of the players present, 7 of 39, either had already changed teams since the end of the season or were unsigned free agents.</p>
        <p>Charlie O'Brien, the Mets' player representative last season, was at the meeting but not representing the Mets because he has signed with the Atlanta Braves. Rich Monteleone, the Yankees' representative, was there, but he now is a member of the San Francisco Giants.</p>
        <p>Casey Candaele (now with Cincinnati) and free agents Scott Sanderson, Walt Weiss, Greg Cadaret and Dennis Rasmussen also are no longer with their 1993 teams. Cuomo's Cap Not in Ring</p>
        <p>With Bud Selig refusing to run if nominated and serve if elected, the owners' search committee presumably continues its search for a commissioner -- 15 months after the owners forced Fay Vincent to abdicate. The committee has not asked Mario M. Cuomo to be a candidate. Cuomo has discouraged any discussion about his being a candidate.</p>
        <p>The name of the governor of New York has arisen because he has not declared himself a candidate for re-election next year. But now he has declared himself a noncandidate for the baseball job. In so doing, however, the former minor league center fielder raised a series of relevant questions. The answers or lack of answers to some of them might explain why no eye-catching names have surfaced as candidates.</p>
        <p>"There are some important questions anybody would have to ask," Cuomo said. "Do you really want a commissioner? What is a commissioner? What does he or she commission? What is the authority? What is the mission? Are you to be Landis or what?"</p>
        <p>"That's the basic problem, if there is one," Cuomo added. "As with most of life, you endanger the chance of success if you dont define the mission."  NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
