<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beneath Moscow, a Piece of Its Soul</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="655452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBWAYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBWAYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOSCOW (RUSSIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">USSR (FORMER SOVIET UNION)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WREN, CHRISTOPHER S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WREN, CHRISTOPHER S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Moscow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB133BF931A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1352" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beneath Moscow, a Piece of Its Soul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WREN, CHRISTOPHER S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE turbulence afflicting Russia these days can disorient even a frequent traveler to Moscow. For one thing, you can't find Feliks Dzerzhinsky. The statue of the founder of the Soviet secret police was toppled by demonstrators against the failed coup in August 1991. His pedestal in Lub yanka Square is adorned now by a simple wood cross.</p>
        <p>Once you could set your watch by the honor guard that goose-stepped to Lenin's tomb on the hour. The ritual has been canceled. And what about all those statues and other monuments paying public homage to Lenin and his Bolshevik cronies? They are vanishing even as the onion domes are being repainted on the old churches once closed under the Communists. Moscow's streets, whose names evoked a pantheon of Soviet heroes, have reverted to names that predate, and puzzle, the city's current inhabitants. But my favorite landmark has been left virtually untouched, and it's still affordable. The Moscow Metro, or subway system, survives as an island of rational continuity in the sea of economic and social upheaval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE turbulence afflicting Russia these days can disorient even a frequent traveler to Moscow. For one thing, you can't find Feliks Dzerzhinsky. The statue of the founder of the Soviet secret police was toppled by demonstrators against the failed coup in August 1991. His pedestal in Lub yanka Square is adorned now by a simple wood cross.</p>
        <p>Once you could set your watch by the honor guard that goose-stepped to Lenin's tomb on the hour. The ritual has been canceled. And what about all those statues and other monuments paying public homage to Lenin and his Bolshevik cronies? They are vanishing even as the onion domes are being repainted on the old churches once closed under the Communists. Moscow's streets, whose names evoked a pantheon of Soviet heroes, have reverted to names that predate, and puzzle, the city's current inhabitants. But my favorite landmark has been left virtually untouched, and it's still affordable. The Moscow Metro, or subway system, survives as an island of rational continuity in the sea of economic and social upheaval.</p>
        <p>I confess a fondness for subways, whose condition can reveal a great deal about a city to a traveler. I have sought out subway systems in Hong Kong, Montreal, London, Paris, Madrid, Lisbon and, not least, Boston and Washington, because they offer not merely rapid, cheap transport but also a chance to rub shoulders, quite literally, with the natives. Yet Moscow's Metro, short for Metropolitan, tops my list. During the four years I lived in Moscow as a foreign correspondent, I rode the Metro to visit Russian friends at a time when the K.G.B. labored to isolate Western journalists from our sources. In the Metro's underground passages, I discovered that the tails assigned by the K.G.B. to follow me were stocky middle-aged women with shopping bags. Today, the Russian Government doesn't seem to care where you go or whom you talk to.</p>
        <p>On two trips to Moscow within the last 14 months, the Metro was my tunnel to those old memories. It assured me that a Moscow mired in commercial rapaciousness today no more reflects the Russian soul than did those fading three-quarters of a century under Communism.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Moscow, I ran up against the kind of buccaneer capitalism that Karl Marx warned us about. I encountered it at the Metropol Hotel in June. My wife and I first stayed at the Metropol in 1967, back when you could still find a Russian willing to defend Marxism. Our double room at the Metropol was, I recall, cramped and dark, with two narrow beds, a grim reading light, a musty carpet and a view of what looked like a junkyard. We didn't complain. This was the Soviet Union, after all, and our room, I recall, cost about $35 a night with some meals and other perks thrown in.</p>
        <p>When I checked into the Metropol again in June, the room they assigned me looked as small and gloomy as the other had 26 years earlier. True, the bathroom was new and my window framed the same junkyard from a slightly different angle. But I found myself again with narrow beds, a dim reading light, a drab carpet. The biggest change, beyond the refurbished lobby, was that the Metropol now cost $310 a night. I never paid so much for a hotel in my life, not even in overpriced cities like Tokyo or Riyadh. I shouldn't grumble since the Metropol favored me with its corporate rate. I eavesdropped on another arriving foreigner who timidly inquired about the price of his room. The clerk announced that his rate was $370 a night, which is more than most Russians could hope to earn in a month.</p>
        <p>And meals were extra. Breakfast at the Metropol cost $22, though the buffet included fresh omelets and a harpist in attendance. My bill for three days' worth of laundry -- mundane shirts, underwear and socks -- ran $45. And the Metropol is not Moscow's priciest hotel; others like the Savoy and Penta can charge more.</p>
        <p>In the old days, the Soviet regime segregated tourists for ideological motives, lest our bourgeois decadence derail the happy march of the Russian people toward Communism. With Marxism looking as dead as Lenin in his air-conditioned mausoleum, exorbitant prices now constrict the foreign visitor in a dollar cocoon.</p>
        <p>When I lived in Moscow, Russians trafficking in American dollars risked being sent to a Siberian labor camp. Today, everybody does it. In fact, the dollar has replaced the ruble as Moscow's commercial currency. Taxi drivers ignore their ruble meters and the shortest ride can cost a foreigner $10. Before climbing into one taxi, I proposed paying in rubles. The driver took umbrage and went in search of a more malleable tourist.</p>
        <p>That may be why I greet the Metro as an old friend. It still accepts only rubles, though the handsome brass tokens have been replaced by flimsy yellow plastic disks. And it still works when so much of Moscow does not. An electronic clock on the platform tells you precisely when the last train left. The wait between trains, once 90 seconds at rush hour, can stretch now to three minutes, not bad for a society in collapse. Each station and the next get announced over a public address system that is, yes, actually comprehensible.</p>
        <p>It may be a cheap shot to compare the clean, safe Metro with New York's grimy, menacing subways. Moscow has 120 stations radiating out from a central ring, compared with 469 stations scattered across New York. The Metro closes from 12:30 A.M. to 6 A.M. for cleaning and repairs, while the subway runs around the clock. And the Metro has fewer decades to show its age, having opened in 1935 compared to 1904 in New York.</p>
        <p>Yet the difference runs deeper. Muscovites, for all the disillusionment bred by Communism's collapse, display a proprietary pride in their Metro. Musicians, hawkers and beggars encroach on its subterranean approaches (though one of the best jazz combos I've heard in Russia performs nightly at the Metro's entrance off Red Square). But inside, panhandling, littering and graffiti seem not to happen because riders would not tolerate it. Seats are still reserved for elderly, disabled or pregnant passengers in every car.</p>
        <p>Riding the Metro during rush hour a year ago, I found a middle-aged Russian glaring at me. I wondered whether he was xenophobic but, no, he pointed sternly to the floor under my seat, where some inconsequential receipt had fallen from my pocket. I dutifully picked up the paper and he nodded approval.</p>
        <p>The art inside the Metro has survived the ideology that produced it. Perhaps the finest Stalinist architecture was built underground as Metro stations, sometimes with ornate chandeliers.</p>
        <p>The official tourism agency Intourist used to market the Metro as evidence of the superiority of socialism. It dispatched tourists to marvel at bronze statues of workers, peasants and soldiers at the Revolution Square station, stained glass at Novoslobodskaya, mosaics at the Kiev station, and ceiling murals at Mayakovsky station. Today, these constitute poignant artifacts of that idealistic, savage epoch.</p>
        <p>IN taking visitors for a ride but not ripping them off, the Metro still offers Moscow's best bargain. The Metro costs Russians more but not foreigners, thanks to the falling ruble.</p>
        <p>When I visited Moscow five years ago, a ride cost only 5 kopeks, or about 7 cents at the prevailing official ruble rate of $1.45. Last June, I found the fare at 6 rubles; by October, inflation had pushed it up to 30 rubles. But with the ruble scraping around 1,200 to the dollar, this still works out to 2 and a half cents. A visitor can ride the Metro 50 times for the cost of a single trip -- $1.25 -- on the New York City subway.</p>
        <p>Much of the old Moscow I do not miss, not the pretense and pomposity of a bankrupt ideology and certainly not Feliks Dzer zhinsky's statue. But the link between the old and the new that was severed elsewhere can be observed on the Metro. If you want to know what Moscow is really like, pass up the $22 breakfast at the Metropol and, for a fraction of the price, treat yourself to a ride on the Metro. Unlike most of what Moscow offers these days, it's an experience you can afford.  CHRISTOPHER S. WREN is a former foreign correspondent for The Times based in Moscow from 1973 to 1977. As editor of new projects, he supervises The Times's Russian-language edition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">CHRISTOPHER S. WREN is a former foreign correspondent for The Times based in Moscow from 1973 to 1977. As editor of new projects, he supervises The Times's Russian-language edition.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
