<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Stock Sale Is Considered By Hambrecht</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">HAMBRECHT &amp; QUIST INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0DF1339F935A25756C0A960958260" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Stock Sale Is Considered By Hambrecht</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER TRUELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hambrecht &amp; Quist, which has taken fast-growing technology companies like the Netscape Communications Corporation public, is preparing an initial public offering of its own shares, people familiar with the brokerage firm have said in recent days.</p>
        <p>Such an offering, which could still be postponed if market conditions change  or if its underwriters demur, would probably involve the sale of between 15 and 20 percent of Hambrecht's equity. The sale of those shares is likely to raise as much as $80 million, analysts said, assuming a current market value for Hambrecht, which is based in San Francisco, of between $400 million and $500 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hambrecht &amp; Quist, which has taken fast-growing technology companies like the Netscape Communications Corporation public, is preparing an initial public offering of its own shares, people familiar with the brokerage firm have said in recent days.</p>
        <p>Such an offering, which could still be postponed if market conditions change  or if its underwriters demur, would probably involve the sale of between 15 and 20 percent of Hambrecht's equity. The sale of those shares is likely to raise as much as $80 million, analysts said, assuming a current market value for Hambrecht, which is based in San Francisco, of between $400 million and $500 million.</p>
        <p>Daniel H. Case 3d, Hambrecht's president and chief executive, declined to comment yesterday on the plans of his firm for its capital structure.</p>
        <p>If it were successful, a Hambrecht offering could prompt other fast-growing brokerage firms to go public or to consider selling themselves to outside investors.</p>
        <p>Investors have recently shown considerable interest in the sorts of high-technology investment banking skills shown by Hambrecht and some other West Coast brokerage firms. Deutsche Bank A.G., for example, spent many millions of dollars a few weeks ago to persuade several of Morgan Stanley &amp; Company's technology-sector bankers, who were based in Menlo Park, Calif., to join its growing investment-banking effort in the United States.</p>
        <p>Robertson Stephens &amp; Company, another rapidly growing brokerage firm in San Francisco, recently denied rumors that it had plans to sell itself to outside investors or to go public.</p>
        <p>Brokerage firms have begun to show interest in public offerings as the current enthusiam for equity investments has gathered speed. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, which had previously been wholly owned by the Equitable Companies, the insurer that itself is a unit of the French insurance giant Axa S.A., sold 20 percent of its shares in an initial public offering late last year.</p>
        <p>Last month, Hambrecht's managing directors met for their annual strategic review in San Francisco and discussed the feasibility of a public issue. Since then, the firm has taken several further steps toward an equity offering of its  own shares.</p>
        <p>In planning to go public, Hambrecht is eager to have a much larger market for its shares, particularly because in recent years many s employees have received  much of their compensation in company shares. Companies generally seek a wider ownership of their shares because it tends to provide a more stable and reliable pricing.</p>
        <p>Hambrecht is now a limited liability company and does not publish detailed financial statements. But, according to people close to Hambrecht, it currently has equity capital of about $140 million.</p>
        <p>Hambrecht is owned by William R. Hambrecht, its co-founder, along with his partners and staff. George Quist, the other founder, died in 1982. Mr. Hambrecht has a longstanding friendship with Richard Fisher, the chairman and chief executive of Morgan Stanley &amp; Company, and the two firms have remained close, though rivals as well. Morgan Stanley and the Smith Barney unit of Travelers Group are expected to act as underwriters for the prospective offering for Hambrecht.</p>
        <p>The fortunes of Hambrecht have soared with the rising stock market. So far this year, it has raised $376 million in initial public offerings, ranking 11th  among brokerage firms that manage initial public offerings, according to the Securities Data Company.</p>
        <p>That compares with the $842.2 million that Hambrecht raised in such offerings last year. The Securities Data figures apportion full credit for an issue to the firm managing it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
