<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; It Looks Like an Abortion Clinic, but ...</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PRIME TIME LIVE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE1F31F932A05753C1A967958260" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; It Looks Like an Abortion Clinic, but ...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonight at 10 on Channel 7 , "Prime Time Live" takes its undercover cameras into what it calls fake abortion clinics. In a variation on the bait-and-switch advertising, these places, sponsored largely by religious groups, invite women in with lines like "Considering abortion? See us first!" Those who respond, says Chris Wallace, tonight's correspondent, "get a heavy dose of anti-abortion rhetoric and medical misinformation."</p>
        <p>The charge is backed up by scenes of clinic employees -- some of whom wear white lab coats, although they are not nurses or doctors -- passing along dubious descriptions and incorrect information plainly intended to frighten vulnerable young women. One former client calls such a counselor "the deceiving nurse."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tonight at 10 on Channel 7 , "Prime Time Live" takes its undercover cameras into what it calls fake abortion clinics. In a variation on the bait-and-switch advertising, these places, sponsored largely by religious groups, invite women in with lines like "Considering abortion? See us first!" Those who respond, says Chris Wallace, tonight's correspondent, "get a heavy dose of anti-abortion rhetoric and medical misinformation."</p>
        <p>The charge is backed up by scenes of clinic employees -- some of whom wear white lab coats, although they are not nurses or doctors -- passing along dubious descriptions and incorrect information plainly intended to frighten vulnerable young women. One former client calls such a counselor "the deceiving nurse."</p>
        <p>You can see and hear a counselor in St. Louis assert that a woman dies of an abortion every day or two. A counselor in Little Rock, Ark., declares that abortions cause cervical cancer. A counselor in Louisville hints there may be a link between abortion and breast cancer. Dr. Frank Chervenak, director of obstetrics at Cornell Medical Center, watches the tapes and gives the lie to such claims. He is not asked to comment on the revelation by a counselor in South Bend, Ind., that Satan is behind abortions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace quotes from a how-to manual put out by an anti-abortion group that has set up 200 clinics. It advises their operators: "Do not indicate you are pro-life." The reason: "Too much information may sometimes cause her not to come in." The manual also recommends that the anti-abortion office should be made to look like an abortion clinic. The program estimates that 2,000 such places are operating around the country.</p>
        <p>The otherwise careful program unfortunately passes along unconfirmed reports of women being shaken or locked in rooms by clinic staff members and relies a bit heavily on claims of emotional distress by Irene Lewis, a woman who is suing one of these centers: "Mentally they did something to me." One sympathizes, but the fact that she has a financial interest in the matter devalues her account. Much more damaging to the center are the statements by her counselor, which could give anybody nightmares. Speaking of the disposal of aborted fetuses, the counselor says: "Some may throw it out in the trash, some they put down the garbage disposal piece by piece."</p>
        <p>The scenes in the clinics, the strongest elements of the report, speak for themselves. A counselor in Missouri gives this account of an abortion to a "Prime Time" reporter who pretended to be eight and a half weeks' pregnant: "At your stage what they would have to do is they would have to go in there and cut the legs off and cut the arms off. And then they crush the head so that it fits through the mouth of the cervix." Even the clinic's director admits that is not accurate, never mind the choice of language. But the state Attorney General's Office says it can't crack down for deceptive advertising because "goods or services are not being sold."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
