<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Talks Deadlocked as Blame Flies</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="752895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAO, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D81739F937A35757C0A963958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Talks Deadlocked as Blame Flies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAO, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Negotiations over a new state budget remained deadlocked today as Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders spent the afternoon blaming each other for the impasse.</p>
        <p>The budget is now three days late, and Mr. Pataki along with his Republican colleague, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, charged that their Democratic opponent, Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, was secretly trying to increase spending on welfare and health-care programs by $1 billion or more. Mr. Silver, they added, has yet to explain where the state will find the money, even as New York faces a $5 billion shortfall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Negotiations over a new state budget remained deadlocked today as Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders spent the afternoon blaming each other for the impasse.</p>
        <p>The budget is now three days late, and Mr. Pataki along with his Republican colleague, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, charged that their Democratic opponent, Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, was secretly trying to increase spending on welfare and health-care programs by $1 billion or more. Mr. Silver, they added, has yet to explain where the state will find the money, even as New York faces a $5 billion shortfall.</p>
        <p>"He's unwilling to put out in public what he's fighting for in private because I think he knows that his positions are so outrageous that the public would react with shock if they heard the amount more he wants to spend on welfare and other areas," Mr. Pataki said after a short and unproductive negotiation session late this afternoon. "It's impossible to negotiate a budget when he refuses to even say what he wants to do."</p>
        <p>Mr. Silver has denied trying to restore money for welfare, saying his primary goal is to soften cuts to higher education and services for the elderly and middle class. He said Mr. Pataki had blocked his efforts to gain information about sources of additional revenue that might reduce those cuts.</p>
        <p>"You have not given us a good faith discussion of revenues available," Mr. Silver said he told Mr. Pataki during their session. "Just saying no is not the answer. You have to allow us access to information."</p>
        <p>With no end to the stalemate in sight, Mr. Pataki said the state was losing money each day that the budget was late because savings that would be won by planned reductions in state services were being delayed.</p>
        <p>Republican members of the Assembly estimate that the state adds $13.7 million to the deficit each day the budget is delayed -- a figure they reached by dividing the state's $5 billion projected deficit by 365 days. Mr. Pataki's aides said they are not sure that is a legitimate way to calculate the impact of the late budget. But the Governor did say he might have to make even deeper service reductions to offset the lost savings if the impasse continues much longer.</p>
        <p>Protests of the cuts already announced continue. In New York City, a collection of labor unions, church groups and social service organizations was calling hundreds, perhaps thousands, of their members to a march on Tuesday afternoon. The marchers plan to walk from City Hall Park to Wall Street. They say they are holding the protest in commemoration of the 27th anniversary of the death of Martin Luther King Jr.</p>
        <p>But even as the Governor and legislative leaders in Albany bickered, Mr. Silver and Mr. Pataki also couldn't agree on who should receive checks on the next pay day, Wednesday. Mr. Pataki has said that he would try to withhold pay checks for himself, about 100 of his aides, the 211 legislators and about 4,300 of their staff members until a budget is passed.</p>
        <p>Withholding those paychecks will require the Legislature to pass an emergency bill that provides pay for the roughly 95,000 state workers not in Mr. Pataki's targets this week. Mr. Bruno said today he would pass Mr. Pataki's emergency bill. But Mr. Silver said he might try to have the bill amended in the Assembly to give himself power to exempt certain legislative employees from having their pay docked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki and the legislative leaders have already agreed to exempt about 30 mentally disabled legislative messengers who would have otherwise lost their pay this week.</p>
        <p>"If the Legislature and the Governor had passed an on-time budget, no one would he worrying about how to buy groceries with a partial paycheck or how to pay the mortgage with no paycheck at all," said Comptroller H. Carl McCall, a Democrat. "State employees and state taxpayers deserve better than this."</p>
        <p>Several lawmakers in both parties said they were preparing to help aides who run into financial problems because their pay was being withheld</p>
        <p>State Senator Michael J. Hoblock, an Albany Republican, said he planned to give loans to hard-pressed aides from his campaign account, which grew last week after he held a $250 per head dinner attended by about 50 contributors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoblock, who said he generally supported Mr. Pataki's budget, said he thought the Governor was wrong to punish legislative aides for the delay. "I don't think we should put in the middle of this people who have nothing to do with the process," he said. "It's okay to withhold legislator's salaries."</p>
        <p>While the Senate has passed a version of the budget that Mr. Pataki supports, the Assembly has yet to finish passing its own variation. Mr. Silver criticized the Senate budget today as lacking details and for having what he described as a $1 billion shortfall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki responded, "I think his right to criticize is somewhat diminished by his failure to make any positive proposals."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
