<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>S.E.C. Chief Seeks Promotion; Chances Look Dim</title>
    <meta content="24PITT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/24/business/24PITT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1410668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pitt, Harvey L (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pitt, Harvey L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91238F937A15754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>S.E.C. Chief Seeks Promotion; Chances Look Dim</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">S.E.C. Chief Seeks Promotion; Chances Look Dim</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>SEC chairman Harvey L Pitt asks Congress for raise, to $166.700 from $138,200, and for cabinet-level status, even as critics call for him to step down because of way he is handling financial crisis; proposals, which would catapult SEC chief to higher rank than CIA and other top officials, is ridiculed by Democrats and disowned by White House; SEC is chronically pinched for money, but Pitt himself earned about $3 million as Wall Street lawyer in 17 months before joining government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harvey L. Pitt, who barely goes a week without new calls for him to step down as chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission because of his handling of the crisis in the markets, is asking Congress for a raise and more respect.</p>
        <p>Congressional aides and commission officials said today that in private discussions this week, Mr. Pitt had asked lawmakers to add a provision to the corporate and accounting bill moving swiftly through Congress that would elevate his office to the same rank as cabinet posts like secretary of state and attorney general.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harvey L. Pitt, who barely goes a week without new calls for him to step down as chairman of the S.E.C., is asking Congress for a raise and more respect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harvey L. Pitt, who barely goes a week without new calls for him to step down as chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission because of his handling of the crisis in the markets, is asking Congress for a raise and more respect.</p>
        <p>Congressional aides and commission officials said today that in private discussions this week, Mr. Pitt had asked lawmakers to add a provision to the corporate and accounting bill moving swiftly through Congress that would elevate his office to the same rank as cabinet posts like secretary of state and attorney general.</p>
        <p>The plan, which was ridiculed by Democrats and disowned this evening by the White House when asked about it, stands little chance of becoming law. It proposes to catapult Mr. Pitt above his counterparts at virtually every other independent agency. It would rank him higher than the director of the Central Intelligence Agency, the administrators of the Environmental Protection Agency and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, and all the civilian heads of the various branches of the armed services.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Pitt's agency is chronically pinched for cash, the change would increase his salary nearly 21 percent, to $166,700 from $138,200. Mr. Pitt, who for the last decade had been one of Wall Street's most successful lawyers as a senior partner at Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver &amp; Jacobson, earned about $3 million in the 17 months before becoming S.E.C. chairman last summer.</p>
        <p>Although he would have the same rank as all of the cabinet members, an elevated status would not change the independent nature of the commission or entitle Mr. Pitt automatically to attend cabinet meetings at the White House. Moreover, it is difficult to imagine that Mr. Pitt, who made millions of dollars a year in private practice representing many companies now facing inquiries, would have a better quality of life with the extra cash. Mr. Pitt likes to joke that even though he took a 99.9 percent pay cut to take the job, he would never want to do any other.</p>
        <p>But in a city driven by official status, the Level 1 designation being sought by Mr. Pitt is the brass ring. Officials with that designation tend to be showered with more invitations to state dinners and choice seats at other occasions. It makes it easier to qualify for burial at Arlington National Cemetery. Outside of members of the cabinet, only Alan Greenspan, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, and Jo Anne Barnhart, the commissioner of Social Security, have the designation.</p>
        <p>Brian Gross, the S.E.C.'s director of communications, said the rise in the agency's status had long been on Mr. Pitt's agenda, and the proposal was dusted off for the short wish list sent to Congress as the bill headed to a conference committee late last week.</p>
        <p>''I suggested this would be a good time for us to raise the profile of the agency,'' Mr. Gross said today. ''The markets are a little bit flustered. The agency has been in the news.''</p>
        <p>''And the chairman said, 'Yes, let's send that up there, this is good timing,' '' Mr. Gross said, adding that the proposal was important because investors are grasping for reasons to renew their confidence in the markets and this may be the most significant securities legislation to be adopted in many years.</p>
        <p>Asked if the proposal was met with criticism, given that it comes as Mr. Pitt is defending his stewardship, Mr. Gross said, ''No one has said, 'We think this is a bad idea or something we don't want to do for the S.E.C.' ''</p>
        <p>''No one to my face has rejected it,'' Mr. Gross added. He also said that the White House had not been consulted about the proposal.</p>
        <p>Claire Buchan, a spokeswoman for the White House, said Mr. Pitt's proposal ''could be a distraction from the real business of providing the S.E.C. with more people, better systems and additional resources.''</p>
        <p>Democrats and Republican critics of Mr. Pitt snickered at the proposal, which they said had no chance of passage and demonstrated Mr. Pitt's political tin ear.</p>
        <p>A small but influential group of lawmakers including the Senate majority leader, Tom Daschle, Democrat of South Dakota; Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut; and Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, have called on Mr. Pitt to step down. Aides to the three lawmakers said today that their bosses would be unavailable to comment on the proposal, with some suggesting that the proposal would do enough damage to Mr. Pitt's credibility without them piling it on.</p>
        <p>Senator Jon S. Corzine, the New Jersey Democrat who as a former top executive at Goldman Sachs has had more experience on Wall Street than any other member of Congress, said he thought the proposed pay increase was ''a diversion from the basic subject matter that needs to be dealt with.''</p>
        <p>Some critics said that even though it might be a good idea to elevate the agency's profile now that the markets are in turmoil, Mr. Pitt was the wrong person to be making the case given his political difficulties.</p>
        <p>The proposal first surfaced last Friday. In a memo to lawmakers, the agency asked for five items to be included in the legislation, like amendments to enable the commission to impose greater penalties on dishonest executives and a provision that would make it easier to coordinate its efforts with criminal investigators. The final item was a request to elevate the bureaucratic status of the agency, in governmentspeak, from Level 3 to Level 1, because of its importance to ''our nation's financial and capital markets.''</p>
        <p>The memo said the elevation of the agency's status ''would enhance our ability to attract qualified professionals at all levels.'' The proposed changes would elevate the pay and status of only the chairman and the four other commissioners who lead the agency. The pay of those four would rise from $130,000 to $150,000.</p>
        <p>Two years ago Congress passed legislation elevating the status of Mr. Greenspan, making him the only financial regulator other than the secretary of the Treasury in the top tier.</p>
        <p>The change was made at the urging of Representative Jim Leach, the Iowa Republican who was the chairman of the House Banking Committee, as a reward for Mr. Greenspan's service and recognition by lawmakers that he is among the most important officials in Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
