<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fastball Has Deserted Abbott, but Dignity Has Not</title>
    <meta content="06ABBO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="869914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Jim Abbott</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">California Angels</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friend, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abbott, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E7DF163EF935A3575BC0A960958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fastball Has Deserted Abbott, but Dignity Has Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM FRIEND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friend, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Aug. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Californ Angels pitcher Jim Abbott is losingest pitcher in major leagues with 1-14 record; Abbott, who was born with one hand, has lost his last 10 decisions, but his teammates say he has not lost his dignity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The baseball is helium in  Jim Abbott's left hand  it usually ends up in orbit. The former Yankee has his Olympic gold medal and his no-hitter, but his newest distinction is a dubious one: losing est pitcher in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>His record for the California Angels is 1-14, his earned run average is nearing 8.00 and that device cynically aimed his way is a speed gun. At Milwaukee in late June, Abbott maxed out at 79 miles per hour, and his manager sent him to a place just north of the minor leagues -- the bullpen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The baseball is helium in  Jim Abbott's left hand  it usually ends up in orbit. The former Yankee has his Olympic gold medal and his no-hitter, but his newest distinction is a dubious one: losing est pitcher in the major leagues.</p>
        <p>His record for the California Angels is 1-14, his earned run average is nearing 8.00 and that device cynically aimed his way is a speed gun. At Milwaukee in late June, Abbott maxed out at 79 miles per hour, and his manager sent him to a place just north of the minor leagues -- the bullpen.</p>
        <p>He spent his first two weeks as a reliever dodging the red phone and his last three weeks experimenting with everything but a knuckleball. Then a funny thing happened on his way to the waiver wire: he rejoined the rotation Sunday in Toronto. His first five innings were a throwback (two hits, no runs), but his sixth inning brought sirens. There were three singles, a walk, a hit batter and two misplayed balls behind him, and, six runs later, the Abbott resume was beginning to look like Anthony Young's.</p>
        <p>''Going 1-14 is comparable to a hitter going 0 for 60 or something,'' said an Angels teammate, Randy Velarde, who three years ago caught the last out of Abbott's hypnotic no-hitter at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>Born with one hand, but never one to use disabled parking, Jim Abbott -- for the first time in his 28 years -- is the victim. ''I've tried harder this year than any other time in my life,'' he said, his voice refusing to crack. ''Any other time.''</p>
        <p>He may have lost his last 10 decisions, but, somehow, he has not lost his dignity.</p>
        <p>''Not one guy in here feels sorry for him,'' said the Angels' utility man, Rex Hudler. ''Not one guy. Before, yeah. We took it personally. I dropped a ball for him in center field that cost him two runs. At the time I was thinking, 'I'll go through a wall for this guy,' and I'm running after this ball thinking, 'I've got to make this catch, got to, got to, got to,' and it hit me right in the glove and dropped out. I'd made it too big of a thing.</p>
        <p>''But we saw how he carried himself. We saw the same Jim Abbott every day, and we came to the point where we were just honored to play with this guy. At the ball park, he's the same. That smile, always something nice to say. The guy's been an inspiration to millions. Millions! That outweighs any kind of won-lost  record. He'll be remembered for so many more things than this record.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps he will be the next Young (who went 1-16 for the Mets in 1993) or the next Jack Nabors (who went 1-20 for the 1916 Philadelphia Athletics) or perhaps he will win a game by accident.</p>
        <p>''When I first went out to the bullpen a month ago, I'd hear the red phone and pray it wasn't for me,'' Abbott said. ''You get to the point where you say, 'I've tried everything. What's left?' ''</p>
        <p>It has confounded everyone from his dad to Disney. No one knows exactly why Abbott's pitches have traveled in slow motion or why his control has been on hiatus or why his e.r.a. is 7.31. But his teammates are attempting psychoanalysis anyhow.</p>
        <p>His manager, Marcel Lachemann, for one, is suspicious of Abbott's arm speed. In Abbott's halcyon days -- when he was 18-11 with a 2.89 e.r.a. for the Angels in 1991 or when he was a Yankee icon in 1993 -- he was mangling hitters with a 90-m.p.h. cut fastball.</p>
        <p>But either the speed gun needs new batteries or Abbott is slowing down. In the last two seasons, Lachemann said, Abbott has been stuck in the 80's, and this is a genuine mystery. It is rare for a pitcher to hit such a wall at 27 or 28.</p>
        <p>Langston suspects head games instead.</p>
        <p>''Listen, you lose a couple, and everything snowballs,'' Langston said. ''It's a lack of confidence with Jimmy, I tell you. I could definitely see it. You couldn't tell by talking to him, but by the way he pitched. I think he's over it now, but the ball wasn't coming free out of his hand. He was choking it. If you choke it, you're not going to have the same velocity, the same movement.</p>
        <p>''We'd be over on the bench screaming, 'Let it go! Let it go!' ''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Tim Mead, the Angels' assistant general manager, suspects the problem is Abbott's guilt. Guilt over the Angels' trading four players to the White Sox to reacquire him last season; guilt over the three-year, $7.8 million contract he signed in the off season; guilt over letting down his new bosses at the Walt Disney Company; guilt over his sour disposition at home while his wife Dana is expecting their first child.</p>
        <p>''His list of people he's trying to please is a lot longer than most players','' Mead said.</p>
        <p>But Abbott will not whine in public. A day after losing his 13th game, he was the one grinning at the news of his teammate Tim Salmon's newborn. On a team that is in last place in the American League West, he is the one cheering up teammates when it is supposed to be the other way around.</p>
        <p>''If I felt I was pitching as well as I could and wasn't getting people out, I'd have an easy time saying I've reached the end,'' Abbott said.</p>
        <p>''I've looked at that. I've said, 'Maybe this is it, maybe I can't get people out.' But I know I haven't pitched as well as I can. We'll just have to see. If the results aren't there, I'll look at my baseball mortality and tip my hat to the game.''</p>
        <p>In the interim, there is a surprising development at Anaheim Stadium: The losingest pitcher in baseball gets standing ovations.</p>
        <p>''Never seen a guy 1-13 with the crowd behind him,'' Lachemann said before Sunday's loss. ''Never.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
