<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Latvians Resent Russian Troops Who Stay On</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="677727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Latvia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDE153FF932A05750C0A962958260" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Latvians Resent Russian Troops Who Stay On</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Russia and Latvians Agree on Troop Pullout Deadline" (news article, March 17) illuminates how vestiges of Soviet imperialism influence ethnic relations in the region. Latvia accepts ethnic pluralism for its historical minorities and is struggling to find an equitable solution to the status of hundreds of thousands of economic settlers brought in under Soviet rule.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Russia and Latvians Agree on Troop Pullout Deadline" (news article, March 17) illuminates how vestiges of Soviet imperialism influence ethnic relations in the region. Latvia accepts ethnic pluralism for its historical minorities and is struggling to find an equitable solution to the status of hundreds of thousands of economic settlers brought in under Soviet rule.</p>
        <p>But it is another thing altogether to have Russia push for the legalization of the status of former Soviet military personnel as additional "minority" members. Paradoxically, Russia has had some success.</p>
        <p>As you report, Latvian negotiators have buckled under Russian pressure and have agreed that military pensioners of the former Soviet forces in Latvia will be allowed to stay, privatize their apartments and eventually claim citizenship. Miraculously, people experienced as occupiers by local inhabitants are transformed into compatriots, wealthy ones at that.</p>
        <p>This concession to Russian demands undermines ethnic conflict resolution because most Latvians perceive it as deeply unjust. It is dangerous to obfuscate truly ethnic issues with issues of Soviet and Russian expansionism. For years, the international community has demanded that Russia (and before that the Soviet Union) unconditionally withdraw its troops from the Baltic states.</p>
        <p>By linking troop withdrawal to demands about the status of demobilized soldiers, Russia reinforces the notion that Soviet-era settlers represent a Russian fifth column, rather than a minority to be integrated into the community of Latvia. It is international practice for states to extend citizenship rights based on loyalty to their constitution, not because a neighboring state demands it.</p>
        <p>Who is or is not given access to privatized apartments is another sensitive issue. During the Soviet era, access to state-owned apartments was one of the most sought after privileges bestowed by the Communist elite. In Latvia housing was assigned preferentially to former Soviet military and other new arrivals.</p>
        <p>Many Latvian families have never had the luxury of their own apartment and now battle the economic hardships of post-Communist transition. If the privatization of apartments perpetuates the privileges of old elites, this will reinforce popular bitterness about the persistence of ethnic and political injustice.</p>
        <p>Having recently returned from a trip to Latvia, I can say that the current "deal" with Russia is highly controversial and may fail to be ratified by Parliament. Even more so because Estonia has repudiated similar linkage between troop withdrawal and demands about privileges for retired Russian military officers wishing to avoid repatriation. If Estonia is coerced to sign, ethnopolitical strain will increase. RASMA KARKLINS  Assoc. Prof. of Political Science University of Illinois Chicago, March 23, 1994</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
