<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MANDELA SPEAKS OF RECONCILIATION</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="683888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE SOUTH AFRICAN VOTE: MANDELA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLER, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANDELA, NELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEED91530F933A05757C0A962958260" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MANDELA SPEAKS OF RECONCILIATION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KELLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the elections that will almost certainly elevate him to the presidency stuttered to a fitful conclusion today, Nelson Mandela laid out a vision of his government as a grand negotiating forum in which every party will have a voice, past crimes will be forgiven and the power of the majority will rarely be used.</p>
        <p>Rather than a dramatic break with the past, or a frantic first 100 days of presidential activism, Mr. Mandela said in interviews over two days, the first themes of his new presidency would be reconciliation and consensus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the elections that will almost certainly elevate him to the presidency stuttered to a fitful conclusion today, Nelson Mandela laid out a vision of his government as a grand negotiating forum in which every party will have a voice, past crimes will be forgiven and the power of the majority will rarely be used.</p>
        <p>Rather than a dramatic break with the past, or a frantic first 100 days of presidential activism, Mr. Mandela said in interviews over two days, the first themes of his new presidency would be reconciliation and consensus.</p>
        <p>Defenders of apartheid would be pardoned for crimes, he promised. Anxious ethnic minorities would retain their jobs and cultures. Big business would play an influential role in shaping economic policy. The departing President, F. W. de Klerk, and other holdovers from the white Government would not be a token presence but trusted partners in the Cabinet.</p>
        <p>Even the racist outlaws of the Afrikaner Resistance Movement, whose members have been accused by the police in a spate of pre-election bombings aimed at sabotaging the transition, would not be banned but invited to the bargaining table, Mr. Mandela said.</p>
        <p>"We must never forget that the National Party of Mr. de Klerk was once in exactly the same position as the right wing today," he said.</p>
        <p>He promised there would be no dismantling of monuments or symbols cherished by whites, no renaming of streets and cities that bear the names of apartheid founders, without "very intense, patient, serious discussion."</p>
        <p>And as for the yearning of some black nationalists to rechristen the country Azania, Mr. Mandela scoffed that this was "far-fetched."</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandela's concept of the new government sounded remarkably like a continuation of the negotiating partnership forged since Mr. de Klerk released him from prison four years ago. That process, involving more than 20 parties, produced an interim Constitution and the first elections open to all races. Moving Carefully</p>
        <p>"Even if we may emerge with a landslide victory, we have to be very careful and not create the fear that the majority is going to be used for the purpose of coercing minorities to accept the policy of a particular party which has emerged victorious," Mr. Mandela said.</p>
        <p>Outlining his program of reconciliation in interviews with The New York Times and other newspapers Thursday and today, Mr. Mandela made these points:</p>
        <p>*Most white police officers and others who killed or tortured in defense of apartheid would be given indemnity for their crimes and would not be publicly identified. Only those who committed the most recent crimes would be ineligible for such a pardon.</p>
        <p>*The new government would continue to subsidize schools run for ethnic minorities, including the white Afrikaners. Although the emphasis in education would be on upgrading black schools and promoting "nonracial" education, he said, "we believe that by recognizing diversity we will actually be uniting the people of South Africa."</p>
        <p>*He would support "a simple, low tax" because high taxes would scare off foreign investors. But if forced to choose between raising taxes and curtailing his party's promises, he would raise taxes. Setting a Minimum</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandela said the African National Congress's "reconstruction" program of housing, jobs and free education -- which the party estimates would cost $12 billion but which critics say could be twice as expensive -- was "the minimum policy."</p>
        <p>"It is inconceivable that at any time we will cut down on that policy," he said.</p>
        <p>Many whites mistrust Mr. Mandela's evocative talk of a consensus-oriented Camelot, and many of his own followers think it is a recipe for paralysis.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mandela was insistent that the same patient negotiations that produced the Constitution and elections could be used to balance the rival imperatives of his government -- the need to raise the hopes of impoverished blacks, and the need to prevent skilled whites from quitting or resisting. Five-Year Expedient</p>
        <p>He said he viewed the unity government as a five-year expedient, after which the country should revert to majority democracy in which defeated parties are consigned to the opposition.</p>
        <p>"I do not think that we need a government of national unity beyond five years, especially if we are able to build this environment of mutual trust," he said.</p>
        <p>Asked how his government would react if, as has happened in recent months, homeless blacks occupied houses built for others, Mr. Mandela said this white fear was unjustified because blacks will no longer feel unfairly excluded from state housing programs.</p>
        <p>In Durban and Cape Town, homeless people descended on new tract homes and refused to leave until they were promised alternative housing. The invasions generated alarm among whites, Indians and mixed-race voters about whether Mr. Mandela could control his followers. A New Perception</p>
        <p>"The situation will be totally different," he said today. "Because one of the reasons why people occupied these houses was the fact that the perception is now widespread that the Government has been concentrating on building houses for certain racial groups and not for Africans."</p>
        <p>"A democratic government will build houses for everybody," he said. Any occupation of property, he added, would be "a police matter."</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandela had effusive praise for some members of the outgoing Government, singling out four men with the hint that they might hold office in a new government.</p>
        <p>They were Roelof F. Botha, the longtime Foreign Minister, whom he lauded as "one of the most enlightened in the National Party"; Roelf Meyer, who was the Government's chief negotiator on the Constitution; Kobie Coetsee, the Justice Minister, who established a close rapport with Mr. Mandela as the Government's first intermediary to the liberation leader in prison, and Leon Wessels, the Minister of Local Government. Amnesty Categories</p>
        <p>On the question of an amnesty, Mr. Mandela has divided offenders into three categories.</p>
        <p>Under an agreement with the current Government, anyone who committed a crime with a political motive before October 1990 may obtain an automatic indemnity by applying to a commission.</p>
        <p>Those involved in political crimes up until last December must apply to the new Parliament case by case, but Mr. Mandela said he would personally favor absolving them.</p>
        <p>"Let us not open up wounds which would make it difficult for us as a government of national unity to promote this spirit of mutual confidence," he said.</p>
        <p>No one who continued illegally obstructing the transition this year, he said, should be eligible for indemnity.  THE SOUTH AFRICAN VOTE: MANDELA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
