<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting Erosion On Fire Island</title>
    <meta content="LTR233323" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fire Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MacWhinnie, Scott M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Fire Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D7113CF936A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting Erosion On Fire Island</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Letter by Scott M MacWhinnie on Feb 1 article on US agencies that are at odds on Fire Island, NY, coast erosion plan (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Regarding the article ''U.S. Agencies at Odds on Fire Island Erosion Plan,'' (Feb.1) it comes as no surprise to me that the Army Corp of Engineers did not acknowledge the Fire Island National Seashore in their public presentation for the Fire Island Interim Plan. This is typical of the arrogant way that this agency and its alarmingly low caliber of personnel conduct themselves in public. Emboldened, no doubt, by their overly cozy relationship with the Fire Island Association and Congressman Lazio.</p>
        <p>Hopefully, Interior Secretary Babbitt will be too busy with his fund-raising and Indian reservation scandals to be unduly influenced by Mr. Lazio. Then our system of checks and balances will work, and the National Seashore will have the clout to put a stop to this fiscal and environmental nightmare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Regarding the article ''U.S. Agencies at Odds on Fire Island Erosion Plan,'' (Feb.1) it comes as no surprise to me that the Army Corp of Engineers did not acknowledge the Fire Island National Seashore in their public presentation for the Fire Island Interim Plan. This is typical of the arrogant way that this agency and its alarmingly low caliber of personnel conduct themselves in public. Emboldened, no doubt, by their overly cozy relationship with the Fire Island Association and Congressman Lazio.</p>
        <p>Hopefully, Interior Secretary Babbitt will be too busy with his fund-raising and Indian reservation scandals to be unduly influenced by Mr. Lazio. Then our system of checks and balances will work, and the National Seashore will have the clout to put a stop to this fiscal and environmental nightmare.</p>
        <p>The article contends that the Fire Island Association represents all of Fire Island's 4,000 property owners. Nothing could be farther from the truth. My family, and many others who have lived on Fire Island for generations, will have nothing to do with them and their misguided projects.</p>
        <p>While some parts of the island have experienced erosion, other parts have enjoyed relative stability, and some, even significant accretion. This is simply the fluid nature of a barrier island. An eroded dune, overwash or even a naturally occurring breach, to anyone who knows local history, does not in itself threaten the mainland.</p>
        <p>The offshore sources are the very ones the interim plan will cannibalize. It is these offshore sand bars that absorb most wave energy, not the barrier island itself, as Mr. Lazio erroneously claims. The resulting stronger wave action at the shore will make fast work of any replenishment project as has been proven many times over on the East Coast of the United States. The incompatible grain size of offshore sand alone makes such projects not viable. As to certain fund-raising practices by the F.I.A., or its members individually, they are free to support Mr. Lazio if they choose. There is, however, a question in my mind if second homeowners on Fire Island are actually his constituents if they do not vote in his district.</p>
        <p>More troublesome is the appearance that Fire Island may get more attention than his constituency on the mainland, overriding, even working counter to their interests. Of course Mr. Lazio, the Fire Island Association and Army Corps will claim, as they always do, in the mainland press that this project is solely to protect the mainland. While in their newsletters and in the Fire Island press, the association claims they are ''owed one'' by the taxpayers and this project will restore lost oceanfront properties.</p>
        <p>My family has lived on the oceanfront of Fire Island for over 80 years, experiencing difficulty only in 1938. We built knowing the risks, never with any expectation of taxpayer bailouts.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, much of the oceanfront construction in recent decades has taken place in front of the primary dune line in order to take advantage of the light and breezes. For obvious reasons, these are the homes most imperiled or already lost, and these owners are screaming the loudest for taxpayer bailouts. Most of these homes would have been lost in the course of things even if the Moriches and Westhampton groins had never been built. That is simply a fact of life for owners of beach property. The fact that most of these homeowners have subsidized flood insurance makes this project all the more dubious.</p>
        <p>While Andrew Redant of the Department of the Interior raises questions on the vagaries of the duration of the project as presented by the Corps, Fire Island Association flacks have made it abundantly clear that they expect the taxpayers to guarantee the project for at least 30 years. Given the failure record of these ''soft'' replenishment projects, the final cost should be far more than the $60 million estimated, and future projects may end up taking the form of ''hard'' structures.</p>
        <p>The notion that without this project the barrier island will disintegrate and gravely threaten the mainland is, of course, absurd. The barrier islands off Long Island have been there for centuries, and will be there for many more, however they may shift. Public resources should be used to reverse the damage already done, remove all groins, give up on inlets that are not viable and let the islands take care of themselves. They will do this with or without the presence of homes.</p>
        <p>SCOTT M. MacWHINNIE  New York City</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
