<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Checking on Bugs To Test the Health Of the Quinnipiac</title>
    <meta content="RIVER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Quinnipiac River</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Quinnipiac River Watershed Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0DA143CF936A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="1348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Checking on Bugs To Test the Health Of the Quinnipiac</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Quinnipiac River Watershed Assn regularly checks on the health of the river and its tributaries, in part by monitoring insects that can only live in clean water; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLLUTION occurs throughout the year, not just during pleasant weather. So members of the Quinnipiac River Watershed Association's stream team check year-round on the health of the river's tributaries. The water quality there is intimately related to the health of the river, a 38-mile waterway that begins in Plainville and flows through New Haven into Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>On a cold, rainy day, several volunteers were hunkered down at Honeypot Brook off Creamery Road in Cheshire. They were collecting insects and water samples, looking for effects of what is called non-point source pollution, or pollution that cannot be traced to a specific source -- a factory, for example, or outlet pipe. Instead, it comes from the runoff of rain across streets and parking lots polluted with road salt, gasoline or oil, or from water that has seeped through lawns or fields sprayed with  pesticides and fertilizers anywhere in the watershed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLLUTION occurs throughout the year, not just during pleasant weather. So members of the Quinnipiac River Watershed Association's stream team check year-round on the health of the river's tributaries. The water quality there is intimately related to the health of the river, a 38-mile waterway that begins in Plainville and flows through New Haven into Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>On a cold, rainy day, several volunteers were hunkered down at Honeypot Brook off Creamery Road in Cheshire. They were collecting insects and water samples, looking for effects of what is called non-point source pollution, or pollution that cannot be traced to a specific source -- a factory, for example, or outlet pipe. Instead, it comes from the runoff of rain across streets and parking lots polluted with road salt, gasoline or oil, or from water that has seeped through lawns or fields sprayed with  pesticides and fertilizers anywhere in the watershed.</p>
        <p>''The long-term effects of non-point source pollution have often been determined through chemical monitoring,'' says George Logan of Manchester, an aquatic biologist and the group's scientific adviser.</p>
        <p>''But recently, research has pointed to the importance of biological monitoring,'' he said. ''Traditional water quality sampling methods have emphasized analyses of physical and chemical parameters such as dissolved oxygen, pH, temperature, nitrates and phosphates. We still do this, but a single chemical sample can only provide a snapshot of water quality on the day of sampling, and may provide no information on recent degraded conditions that have since cleared up.''</p>
        <p>So the river association has enlisted the help of a dozen volunteers for its team. Mr. Logan was one of four men in chest-high waders who were gathering insects, bare-handed, in the frigid stream. The association has since secured an impressive pair of neon orange insulated gloves, which cover the upper limbs from fingertips to armpit, and are attached to each other by means of elastic strips across the wearer's back.</p>
        <p>The Adopt-the-River program, of which the stream team is a part, began in 1994, with an emphasis on trash cleanup. When Sigrun Gadwa, the current executive director, was hired in 1995, she applied for money to do biological monitoring. ''In the summer of 1996,'' she says, ''a Yale graduate student got a grant to study biodiversity in the upper Quinnipiac River, the non-tidal northern section. That dovetailed with the Adopt-the-River program. He really knew his aquatic insects and stream surveys and could work with volunteers. He produced a report that he distributed to the planning agencies of all the towns adjacent to the river.''</p>
        <p>On a January evening, Ms. Gadwa, Mr. Logan and several volunteers analyzed their samples at a state Department of Environmental Protection lab in Bethany. The pungent odor of ethanol, used to preserve the insect samples, permeates the air in the lab. Volunteers sort insects into trays, hoping to find a moderate number of several different species, because that indicates a healthy stream. Large numbers of just a few species -- those that better tolerate pollution -- indicate a polluted stream.</p>
        <p>''I love identifying bugs to see what the health of the stream is,'' said Mr. Logan. ''And,'' he adds, as perhaps only an aquatic biologist could, ''they're pretty.'' The group found mayflies, stoneflies and caddisflies, all indicators of a healthy stream.</p>
        <p>The aquatic insect survey is one of several components of the Adopt-the-River program. The others are the turtle monitoring team, the breeding bird monitoring team and the team that measures the turbidity, or the amount of suspended sediments, of the river's tributaries. The group's turbidity sampling has revealed violations of the Federal Clean Water Act, according to Ms. Gadwa, and the group has notified the state's D.E.P.</p>
        <p>She and several others have identified wood turtles along the Ten Mile River, one of the tributaries of the Quinnipiac. The wood turtle is expected to be listed as a species of special concern under the state Endangered Species Act this spring, meaning the state is keeping an eye on it, and if the numbers keep decreasing, the turtle might be classified as threatened -- one step away from endangered. Threatened and endangered species are afforded government protection, while species of special concern are not. The association got a grant from the Quinnipiac Fund, administered by the Community Foundation for Greater New Haven, to monitor aquatic insects and wood turtles, which hibernate under water.</p>
        <p>The location of these turtles' habitat -- both aquatic and terrestrial -- puts them in conflict with a proposed expansion of Bloomingdale's By Mail in Cheshire, a major distribution center for the retailer. The association is seeking funds from the Nature Conservancy to subsidize a more costly alternative expansion plan for the retailer that would do less damage to the turtle habitat.</p>
        <p>''We're frustrated,'' says Ms. Gadwa, ''because we feel our concerns about the threat to the wood turtles were not taken seriously''  when presented to a local government commission. ''They are a treasure.''</p>
        <p>The Quinnipiac River, especially its southern part, is home to many industries and has suffered from repeated toxic discharges. In late January, a company in North Haven and its president were found guilty of having discharged oil and polluted wastewater into the river from July 1993 to October 1995. Both face the possibility of fines, while the president faces possible jail time as well.</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Gadwa says, ''It's important to have a balanced perspective on the human health risks and the risks to the aquatic environment. There are parts of the watershed that are in great shape and parts that are severely degraded. There are problems that are temporary, such as from construction sites, but there are longer term effects, too. Overall, the river has gotten a lot cleaner since the association was founded in 1979. Most of the credit goes to the Federal Clean Water Act and to enforcement by the D.E.P., but the association does serve a watchdog function. If there is not public pressure to enforce the regulations, they are not that likely to be enforced.''</p>
        <p>Other activities of the river adopters include vegetation management, which includes planting native species for wildlife food and cover, shading, soil stabilization or improvement of water quality, and the removal of aggressive alien species; habitat enhancement, which includes erecting nest boxes and bat boxes, adjusting drainage patterns and improving the substrate for fish; leading outings on educational field trips, and improving access to the river by removing tree blockages in the river and building trails, footbridges or  small docks. River adopters are encouraged, but not required, to be members of the association.</p>
        <p>A new level of citizen participation will be possible through the Quinnipiac River Initiative, a pilot program for a watershed-based approach to water management sponsored by the D.E.P. Rivers Program, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency's New England Region, the river association and the Center for Coastal and Watershed Systems at the Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies.</p>
        <p>The idea, Ms. Gadwa says, is to develop grass roots leadership to address specific river problems. Four meetings were held in November in towns in various parts of the watershed, to gauge citizens' concerns. They included issues such as pesticides, recreational access, stormwater runoff, illegal dumping and improving town zoning regulations to reduce urban sprawl and conserve open space. Organizational meetings are currently being held to determine the structure of the initiative.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
