<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Ask, 'Where's the Curry Powder?'</title>
    <meta content="16SIMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PLAIN AND SIMPLE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="883653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="PLAIN AND SIMPLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DC1431F935A25753C1A960958260" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Ask, 'Where's the Curry Powder?'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros Plain and Simple column suggests recipes for apple and chicken curry and brussel sprouts (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whenever I mention a dish with curry in the name, I receive a phone call or two asking where the curry powder is.</p>
        <p>There is no curry powder in Indian cooking: it is a combination of spices that makes a dish a curry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whenever I mention a dish with curry in the name, I receive a phone call or two asking where the curry powder is.</p>
        <p>There is no curry powder in Indian cooking: it is a combination of spices that makes a dish a curry.</p>
        <p>This chicken and apple curry has many of those spices, though in small amounts. I used ginger to season the accompanying Brussels sprouts -- it gives them the appropriate Indian accent.</p>
        <p>Apple and Chicken Curry</p>
        <p>1/2 cup long-grain rice  1 large clove garlic  8 ounces whole onion or 7 ounces chopped onion (ready-cut) (1 2/3 cups)  2 teaspoons olive oil  2 large tart apples, like Granny Smith  1 teaspoon ground cumin</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon ground coriander</p>
        <p>1/8 teaspoon turmeric</p>
        <p>1/8 teaspoon cinnamon</p>
        <p>Few dashes cloves</p>
        <p>Few dashes nutmeg</p>
        <p>Few dashes cardamom</p>
        <p>1/8 teaspoon salt</p>
        <p>Freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1/8 to  1/4 teaspoon hot-pepper flakes  8 ounces skinless, boneless chicken breast  1 cup no-salt-added chicken stock or broth  1 tablespoon cornstarch  1 teaspoon lime juice  1 cup nonfat plain yogurt.</p>
        <p>1. Combine rice and 1 cup water, and bring to boil in heavy-bottomed pot. Reduce heat to simmer, cover and cook a total of 17 minutes, until rice is cooked and water has been absorbed.  2. With food processor on, put garlic clove through feed tube and mince.  3. Cut the onion into eighths, and add to processor. Pulse to chop finely.  4. Heat the olive oil in large nonstick skillet, and saute garlic and onion in hot oil until onion begins to soften.  5. Wash, core, seed and cut apples into eighths, and add to skillet.  6. Season with all the spices and hot-pepper flakes, and stir well.  7. Wash, dry and cut chicken into  1/4-inch-wide strips. When onion is soft, push mixture to side of pan and add chicken. Saute on both sides until browned.  8. Mix a tablespoon of stock with cornstarch to make a smooth paste. When chicken is brown, add cornstarch mixture and remaining chicken stock.  9. Add lime juice to pan. Cook over medium heat, stirring occasionally, until mixture thickens. Serve over rice with yogurt.  Yield: 2 servings.  Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 595calories, 9 grams fat, 70 milligrams cholesterol, 345 milligrams sodium, 40 grams protein, 90 grams carbohydrate.</p>
        <p>Brussels Sprouts And Ginger Walnut Oil</p>
        <p>10 ounces brussels sprouts</p>
        <p>Enough fresh ginger to yield 1 tablespoon coarsely grated  1 teaspoon walnut oil.</p>
        <p>1. Wash and trim sprouts, and steam over hot water until they are tender, about 7 to 10 minutes.  2. Grate ginger. Drain sprouts, and mix with oil and ginger.  Yield: 2 servings.  Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 80 calories, 3 grams fat, 0 milligrams cholesterol, 35 milligrams sodium, 4 grams protein, 14 grams carbohydrate.</p>
        <p>Game Plan</p>
        <p>Prepare curry through step 4.  Prepare and cook brussels sprouts.  Continue with curry through step 7.  Finish sprouts  Finish chicken.</p>
        <p>PLAIN AND SIMPLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
