<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jet Offensive Line Desperate for First Aid</title>
    <meta content="16JETS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="883714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4D81431F935A25753C1A960958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jet Offensive Line Desperate for First Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problems besetting New York Jets offensive line discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before the start of this horror season for the Jets, the offensive line was a disaster waiting to happen. And a disaster of sorts did happen in Sunday's 21-17 loss to the Jacksonville Jaguars when center Dave Alexander, the team's most experienced lineman, suffered a torn anterior cruciate ligament in his left knee and was lost for the season.</p>
        <p>Now the Jets are searching for a remedy. The solution involves Roger Duffy, Harry Galbreath and maybe Siupeli Malamala.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before the start of this horror season for the Jets, the offensive line was a disaster waiting to happen. And a disaster of sorts did happen in Sunday's 21-17 loss to the Jacksonville Jaguars when center Dave Alexander, the team's most experienced lineman, suffered a torn anterior cruciate ligament in his left knee and was lost for the season.</p>
        <p>Now the Jets are searching for a remedy. The solution involves Roger Duffy, Harry Galbreath and maybe Siupeli Malamala.</p>
        <p>Duffy, the left guard, is the only returning starter from last year's 3-13 team. Of the other starters, Jumbo Elliott and David Williams were signed as unrestricted free agents, Matt O'Dwyer was a rookie backup last year and Alexander missed the 1995 season after tearing up his right knee on the first preseason play.</p>
        <p>Once Elliott's strained hamstring and Williams's bad back improved a month ago, the line started a slow growth process. Now it faces a new struggle because Alexander's injury has forced two changes. Duffy will move to center and Galbreath will leave the bench to replace Duffy at left guard.</p>
        <p>Coach Rich Kotite said Alexander's injury ''looks extremely serious,'' and the 10th-year pro has been placed on injured reserve. Malamala, on the physically-unable-to-perform list after reconstructive knee surgery in December, may be reactivated this week, but even then he may need weeks to be ready.</p>
        <p>The integration of new players is complex. ''Roger Duffy has been playing next to me, so now Harry Galbreath and I have to work out things,'' said Elliott, the left guard. ''It's a different feeling with different guards with combination blocks. You've got to get used to each other.''</p>
        <p>Duffy, a seventh-year pro, does have experience at center. At Penn State, Coach Joe Paterno called him ''the best center I ever coached.'' Duffy says he considers center his natural position.</p>
        <p>''I played a lot there my first two years with the Jets when Jim Sweeney was hurt a couple of times,'' Duffy said. ''In those years, I played all three spots in the middle.''</p>
        <p>A new center must coordinate the snap with the quarterback. That should not be a problem because Duffy and Frank Reich, starting at quarterback again for the injured Neil O'Donnell, have worked well together. And because Alexander was banged up the two weeks before his latest knee injury, Duffy had been taking repetitions at center.</p>
        <p>In July, two weeks into training camp, Galbreath joined the Jets as a free agent. In five seasons with the Miami Dolphins and three with the Green Bay Packers, he played in 129 games and started 126. He said he was grateful for his new opportunity.</p>
        <p>''It excites me to start,'' he said. ''I think I can do the job, but losing Dave is going to hurt us. In nine seasons, I've missed only two games because of an injury, and he has been knocked out twice in two years. My heart goes out to him.''</p>
        <p>For Duffy, the big difference between guard and center is that the center is the traffic-control officer for the offensive line. As Bill Muir, the Jets' offensive line coach, explained it, ''The center has to identify defensive fronts and make adjustments based on what the defense might do and communicate them up and down the line.''</p>
        <p>During the week, the linemen study the defense they will face. In the game, the center goes to the line of scrimmage, looks at the defense and identifies it to the other linemen by letters or by terms.</p>
        <p>When the crowd is especially noisy, the Jets may use a silent snap count, as they frequently did Sunday in Jacksonville in passing situations. In those cases, the center, with a visual signal, tells the other offensive linemen when the ball will be snapped.</p>
        <p>Muir is sure Duffy will be fine at center. He just hopes the problems that have beset the offensive line are over. ''Before we're done,'' Muir said, ''we may end up being an episode on 'The X-Files.' ''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
