<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Anger Artist</title>
    <meta content="02schillinger--.1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/02/books/review/02schillinger.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1751304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="'Doctors &amp; Nurses,' by Lucy Ellmann"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schillinger, Liesl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellman, Lucy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doctors &amp; Nurses (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Ellmann, Lucy</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Doctors &amp; Nurses (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1D71630F931A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Anger Artist</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Anger Artist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIESL SCHILLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schillinger, Liesl</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>T6</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DOCTORS &amp; NURSES</p>
        <p>By Lucy Ellmann.</p>
        <p>209 pp. Bloomsbury. Paper, $14.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lucy Ellmann writes a novel of scatological raillery and rollicking nihilism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DOCTORS &amp; NURSES</p>
        <p>By Lucy Ellmann.</p>
        <p>209 pp. Bloomsbury. Paper, $14.95.</p>
        <p>WHEN you put on a play and the actors strip naked, the play stops being chiefly about acting. When you write a novel and call attention to the physical form of the story's most irreducible elements -- the letters -- your book stops being chiefly about writing. It becomes performance art.</p>
        <p>The satiric novelist Lucy Ellmann likes capital letters. Her fifth novel, ''Doctors &amp; Nurses,'' which tells the story of an obese, murderous, sex-and-bodily-functions-obsessed nurse named Jen who has an affair with a homicidal doctor, is a violently worded rant in which Ellmann uses CAPITAL LETTERS to highlight random bits of text.</p>
        <p>This tactic is not unknown. It manifests itself benignly in British children's literature. (Ellmann, although born in America, moved to Britain decades ago.) Think, for example, of ''Mary Poppins,'' in which Significant Nouns, like Day Out or Laughing Gas, are capitalized to indicate their position in the hierarchy of Things That Matter -- above chimneys or a flagstaff and on a par with the Prime Minister and Poppins herself. In such kid lit, only one letter per word tends to be capped, but Ellmann accentuates EVERY LETTER. ''There's a lot of stuff we do WITHOUT thinking,'' she writes in ''Doctors &amp; Nurses.'' ''It's a sort of REFLEX ACTION.''</p>
        <p>This uppercase cluster-bomb approach was used successfully by John Irving in ''A Prayer for Owen Meany.'' But Irving had a good reason for his artifice. The title character, a tiny doll-like man, has a grating stentorian voice, and his speech is printed in capital letters so we never lose sight of the effect he produces on those who know him and those who taunt him, lifting him up in the air. ''PUT ME DOWN,'' he says ''in a strangled, emphatic falsetto. . . . CUT IT OUT! I DON'T WANT TO DO THIS ANYMORE.''</p>
        <p>In ''Doctors &amp; Nurses,'' however, this ploy serves mainly to distract the eye and clog the page, subjecting us to every jangling spike in the stream-of-consciousness narrative. It's like being held in a vise-grip by a glowing-eyed fanatic. ''We're ALL mass murderers anyway: we live with the ATOM BOMB. Our names should REFLECT this better.'' ''We should all be called ZIT, ZILCH, ZERO. We should all be called LOATHE SELF.'' Yet we are also reminded that ''it cannot be stated too emphatically how DANGEROUS self-hatred is. IT IS RESPONSIBLE FOR ALL TRAGEDY. It will bring the whole species to its KNEES.''</p>
        <p>''What if it's DISGUST, not love,'' Ellmann asks, ''that makes the world go round?'' If it is, would you really want to know?</p>
        <p>Many critics have embraced the saucy scatological raillery and rollicking nihilism in Ellmann's previous books, finding in them a bracing, if counterintuitive, humanism or feminism -- perhaps in the pattern of Annie Sprinkle, whose performance piece ''Post-Porn Modernism'' opened people's minds and her own cervix with the help of a speculum and a mirror. And in the right hands misanthropy can certainly be fun. Think of Voltaire's ''Candide'' or Céline's ''Journey to the End of the Night.'' Or Basil Fawlty.</p>
        <p>But Ellmann uses anger here in a cartoony way, reminiscent of David Lynch's comic strip, ''The Angriest Dog in the World,'' which ran for about a decade with little variation, always including the same first frame: ''The dog who is so angry he cannot move. He cannot eat. He cannot sleep. He can just barely growl. Bound so tightly with tension and anger, he approaches the state of rigor mortis.''</p>
        <p>Ellmann's anti-heroine is a caricature: ''Was she BORN angry? Nobody knows. What FEEDS her anger? MARS BARS? Maybe just having to proceed across the earth on THOSE LIMBS.'' ''Jen has become the embodiment of female RAGE, a real STINKER, the eau de cologne of female MURK.''</p>
        <p>This ''embodiment,'' as described by the author, amounts to a cross between the Venus of Willendorf and Josef Mengele -- grotesquely fat, dandruffy, sweaty and flatulent, and fond of making ''QUIPS'' with grieving parents about their dead children's ''final thrashings or the effect of projectile vomiting on her UNIFORM.''</p>
        <p>It's impossible to see in this succubus a pathbreaking Everywoman who can teach us that ''We've been trained to view the body as a HORROR -- not a lovable, ESSENTIAL egalitarian possession.'' And it's equally impossible to find liberation in Jen's crude trysts at carwashes with strangers -- or to believe that this ''pockmarked pustuled'' mountain of flesh manages not only to squeeze into an airplane bathroom but to have a torrid encounter there with a handsome doctor who, years later, coincidentally becomes her boss. It's no surprise, then, that we fail to feel any sympathy for Jen, despite her pitiful outcast status, ''never being loved, never GIVING love.''</p>
        <p>There's no reason an overweight, self-destructive female character can't beguile the reader. Anne Tyler's wonderful early novel ''A Slipping-Down Life'' achieved that small victory with the fat-girl character Evie Decker, married to a no-account rock musician who mistook her for a groupie. And Barbara Pym could transform a lonely nurse into someone recognizable, be she round or lean. But Ellmann's readers will have difficulty deciding whether the reaction she wants Jen to provoke is laughter, commiseration, guilt or the gag reflex.</p>
        <p>She does seem, however, to toy with the notion of Jen as a modern-day Jane Eyre. Complaining about Charlotte Brontë and her heroine, Ellmann asks: ''Couldn't she have made her a bit UGLIER? Jane doesn't hate herself ENOUGH.'' She subjects Jen to a botched Brontë-ish wedding in which it is revealed at the altar that the groom is already married to a lunatic. But there's one difference: Jen's fiancé is engaged to one too.</p>
        <p>In Brontë's novel, Mr. Rochester sought to stir Jane's pity by describing the miseries of his long, unwilling association with the depraved, demented Bertha. ''No professed harlot ever had a fouler vocabulary than she,'' he told Jane. ''Those are the sounds of the bottomless pit! I have a right to deliver myself from it if I can.''</p>
        <p>If Bertha wrote, she probably used a lot of capital letters.</p>
        <p>'Doctors &amp; Nurses,' by Lucy Ellmann Liesl Schillinger, a New York-based arts writer, is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Liesl Schillinger, a New York-based arts writer, is a regular contributor to the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
