<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Moscow to Leningrad, Russia's Timeless Heartland</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RURAL AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DE153CF934A25755C0A967958260" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Moscow to Leningrad, Russia's Timeless Heartland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To drive from Moscow to Leningrad in the springtime is to wander through the backroads of Russian history.</p>
        <p>The high-rise boxes of Moscow give way quickly to a panorama of whimsically painted wooden huts listing in the mud, to a vast horizon of birches, fields and swollen rivers punctuated by the onion dome of a village church. Grizzled men still wield razor-sharp axes to shape raw logs and grannies wrapped in thick shawls tend goats by the roadside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To drive from Moscow to Leningrad in the springtime is to wander through the backroads of Russian history.</p>
        <p>The high-rise boxes of Moscow give way quickly to a panorama of whimsically painted wooden huts listing in the mud, to a vast horizon of birches, fields and swollen rivers punctuated by the onion dome of a village church. Grizzled men still wield razor-sharp axes to shape raw logs and grannies wrapped in thick shawls tend goats by the roadside.</p>
        <p>This is timeless Russia, the delight of romantics, the despair of reformers and an abiding enigma for foreigners.</p>
        <p>Generations of Slavophiles have scoured this landscape for the sources of the storied "Russian soul," and generations of revolutionaries have cursed the backwardness, drunkenness and resistance to change, and generations of foreign travelers have been struck by the bewitching charm and hopeless squalor.</p>
        <p>Among the first villages out of Moscow, and once the first posting station on the road to St. Petersburg, is a village called Chornaya Gryaz, whose name literally translates as "Black Mud." It is a name that still leads the traveler to muse on the ambivalence of the land -- and on the real prospects for the great ambitions and plans that dominate the talk of the capital in the era of Mikhail Gorbachev and Boris Yeltsin.  The Road to Moscow</p>
        <p>It was in Chornaya Gryaz 200 years ago that a radical gentleman named Aleksandr N. Radishchev concluded the celebrated record of his "Journey from St. Petersburg to Moscow," with a literary gasp: "Moscow! Moscow!"</p>
        <p>Radishchev's journey was less a travelogue than a literary passage through the social injustices of his day, an effort that earned him several years in Siberia and a reputation as Russia's first literary revolutionary. But the contrasts he recorded have little changed, and travelers still echo his sigh of relief on completing the journey.</p>
        <p>In Chornaya Gryaz, moved by the grief of a serf couple compelled to marry by their lord, Radishchev exclaimed: "O grievous lot of many millions! Your end is hidden still, even from my grandsons!"</p>
        <p>An American reporter stops along the road near the Lenin's Bequest collective farm to photograph a family turning soil by a railroad crossing. "Quick Vera, call the police -- that's a foreigner, he's taking pictures," yells the man. "They'll take your film, that's sure," he snarls at the reporter as the crossing guard hastily twirls the phone dial. No police come.  Come Back and Fish</p>
        <p>Yet further on, at the village of Spas-Zaulok, a young man helping his father hew a new foundation for his log cabin openly identifies himself as a military officer. He shows no compunction in talking to the American, and invites him to come fishing next time.</p>
        <p>All along the road, whole families hack at fields, meadows and gardens with hoes and shovels -- bearded intellectuals, children in cloth caps, heavy-set old women called babushkas. Soviet city-dwellers have always yearned for a plot of land in the countryside, to be sure, but nobody can remember a time when people have taken to the land in such numbers.</p>
        <p>Muscovites by the thousands have roamed far from the capital to secure a quarter of an acre to put in some potatoes and carrots. Urban dailies have begun printing advice on how to store potatoes on city balconies, how to bake bread, how to can carrots.</p>
        <p>A private plot to plough and a "dacha" in the country have always been highly sought after in this land of short summers, but neither leisure nor status are at issue now that stores stand empty and prices soar.</p>
        <p>At Zelenograd, a massive mound of sculptured earth faced with a stone monument marks a common grave for thousands of Soviet soldiers who blocked the Nazi advance on Moscow here in December 1941. There are always fresh flowers and a clutch of visitors here.</p>
        <p>This is only one of scores of memorials that line the route of the fierce fighting here 50 years ago, and even now, in a time of violated taboos and shattered myths, the memory of that war retains a sacred place in the consciousness of the nation.</p>
        <p>On the radio, a Soviet tourist to Germany reports with some amazement that the war is a far lesser reality there. "They all know about it, of course, but it just doesn't seem as important to them as it does to us," he declares.</p>
        <p>The story of Torzhok, a picturesque town on the banks of the River Tvertsa some 130 miles north of Moscow, is somewhat typical for these parts. Recorded in annals as early as the 11th century, it was fought over by Russian princes, sacked by Mongols, Lithuanians and Poles, wrecked by Ivan the Terrible and bombed by the Germans.</p>
        <p>But the sad spectacle it presents today is largely a legacy of Soviet rule. Of 32 churches and monasteries that laced the 26 hills on which the town is set with a fairy-tale silhouette of onion domes and ramparts, only a handful still stand, ravaged and crumbling. The cathedral is a bakery, its yard a dump.</p>
        <p>The hotel where the poet Pushkin dined on the celebrated local dish, the chicken cutlets known as pozharskiye kotlety, is a seedy hangout of black marketeers. You'd better eat in your room, a visitor is told. And no, we're out of pozharskiye kotlety.  'Our Sacred Images'</p>
        <p>During the night, robbers broke into a house by the church and stole three icons. "They're being sold to foreigners by now," says the local priest. "Only I don't understand, why do foreigners need our sacred images?"</p>
        <p>"Freedom," sighs a local constable. "They always give it to the wrong ones."</p>
        <p>Yet restoration work has begun on the once-majestic Borisoglebsky Monastery, founded in 1038 and steeped in history. Crosses have appeared on some former churches. On the main highway, signs to neighboring Kalinin have been replaced by signs for Tver, its ancient name before it was renamed for the first Soviet President.</p>
        <p>In Torzhok, in Tver, as in Leningrad, Moscow, Georgia or Lithuania, people are seeking to reclaim interrupted histories, to fill the spiritual void left by the rapid disintegration of the Communist faith. The impulse is natural, but it leads in many directions. Fundamentalist religions, faith healing, nationalism, monarchism, racism, rumors all find fertile ground in a nation cast adrift.  'Leave Us Uncle Lenin'</p>
        <p>"What will they teach in school now?" worries the mother of a young girl looking at a cartoon spoofing Lenin, the demigod of the Soviet state whose bald and goateed visage still glares in all official buildings and town square. "Maybe they should leave us Uncle Lenin for a while longer, at least until we have something else."</p>
        <p>There was a time when the town of Vyshni-Volochek, about halfway between Moscow and Leningrad, stood at the juncture of East and West.</p>
        <p>Perched on the watershed between the Baltic and the Volga basins, Vyshni-Volochek was the point at which vessels were hauled overland from one side to the other. In 1703, Czar Peter the Great ordered a canal built to link the rivers Tvertsa and Msta as part of his grand scheme to link backward Russia with the modern West.</p>
        <p>For almost 200 years the canal played a major role in East-West commerce and even led Vyshni-Volochek to be styled the "Venice of Russia" -- probably by people who had never been to Venice. But then came the St. Petersburg-Moscow railway and by 1900 water traffic ceased entirely. In the Soviet era the city sank to provincial insignificance.</p>
        <p>Six years after Mr. Gorbachev launched the fateful process known as perestroika, there is a sense that the Soviet Union is again at the watershed, but no one can tell whether it will lurch "forward" toward Western-style democracy and a free market, or "backward" to isolation and authoritarian rule.</p>
        <p>It is a replay of a timeless conflict between reformer and reactionary, innovation and tradition, Westernizer and Slavophile, West and East -- except that for 75 years the debate stood frozen by the enforced orthodoxy of Communism. Now, as it slowly thaws, it seems at times dated and tinged with a new anxiety.</p>
        <p>"The West will never let us fail," declares a middle-aged accountant by the canal, in which rows of housewives are doing their washing. "I mean, this isn't Africa. Look at our resources, look at our size, our nuclear weapons, our European culture."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
