<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Victory Predicted By Time Warner</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="453315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TIME WARNER INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DF163CF934A25755C0A967958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Victory Predicted By Time Warner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geraldine Fabrikant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIME WARNER'S investment bankers told the company that its stock would trade at $100 to $105 a share after it announced its complex rights offering. But the shares plummeted on the initial news of the deal and continue to languish in the mid-90's; they dropped $1 on Friday to close at $94 in the face of a rising market.</p>
        <p>In the offering, made on June 6, the company gave stockholders the chance to buy 34.5 million new shares for $63 to $105 a share, depending on how many accept the deal. The offering could raise $2.1 billion to $3.5 billion to repay part of $11 billion in bank debt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIME WARNER'S investment bankers told the company that its stock would trade at $100 to $105 a share after it announced its complex rights offering. But the shares plummeted on the initial news of the deal and continue to languish in the mid-90's; they dropped $1 on Friday to close at $94 in the face of a rising market.</p>
        <p>In the offering, made on June 6, the company gave stockholders the chance to buy 34.5 million new shares for $63 to $105 a share, depending on how many accept the deal. The offering could raise $2.1 billion to $3.5 billion to repay part of $11 billion in bank debt.</p>
        <p>Despite the disappointing reaction in the market, Tod Hullin, Time Warner's newly appointed senior vice president for public relations, said on Friday that "this is a victory."</p>
        <p>"We're going to win this," he said, referring to the rights offering.</p>
        <p>And a number of portfolio managers believe the company will probably succeed in raising the money in the deal, which asks shareholders to put up more money to maintain their percentage ownership of the company.</p>
        <p>But would this be a victory for the shareholders? If they remain skeptical, it is because of the risk in a deal that asks them to bet heavily that the company's chairman, Steven J. Ross, can do precisely what he has failed to do twice: pull off a strategic alliance with an outside company in a related business to strengthen his balance sheet further. Theoretically, the investor would take a minority stake in one of Time Warner's core businesses, perhaps entertainment.</p>
        <p>After a year of trying, the company has failed to pull off a deal. "And the argument that they now need a rights offering to attract a strategic partner is badly undercut by the fact that in the original Time Warner merger, they argued that they needed each other as strategic partners and that it was a marriage made in corporate heaven," said one portfolio manager who has been assiduously courted by the company to buy stock and invest in the rights deal. "Now suddenly they need another partner," he added. "It's more like a menage a trois."</p>
        <p>One Time Warner executive, who spoke on condition of anonymity, implied that a deal could be easy. "Just wait six months and you'll see," he said enthusiastically. The concept is that such an investment would benefit the company, providing an infusion of money without loosening its control over its various operations.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Time Warner itself acknowledges that the rights deal does not make its various properties inherently more desirable. The company's chief counsel, James Schwab, said on Friday that "the deal would not make our properties more attractive to outside investors,"adding that "the point is that consciously or unconsciously we would have a better negotiating position."</p>
        <p>An investment banker who has worked with Japanese investors said, "Just because the balance sheet is better does not erase some of the basic problems that a Japanese company might feel about putting money into Warner Brothers films." He noted that an investor might well be skeptical of taking a minority stake in Warner Brothers when the film company sells its movies to Home Box Office, which is wholly owned by Time Warner. He wondered how much of an arm's-length negotiation there could really be.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ross may be able to pull a rabbit out of a hat. After all, he succeeded in selling his company to Time Inc., a sale that saw Warner shareholders profit handsomely. But Wall Street has a short memory. While 67 percent of Time Warner shareholders are large institutions that can afford to make the bet, it is harder for small shareholders, even though brokers can be expected to push the deal hard. The company has promised every broker a dollar for each right their clients exercise.</p>
        <p>J. Ezra Merkin of Ariel Capital Group, which itself owns preferred stock, believes that the small investor may not want to put up more money, particularly the former Time investor who has seen the stock drop so much.</p>
        <p>Some investors are further annoyed by the fact that the 15 million stock options held by management, including 1.8 million options with a strike price of $150 held by Mr. Ross, are to be adjusted downward. And while the company argues that it is legally required to do so and management is a passive beneficiary, presumably corporate officers could waive those rights, but there does not seem to be any indication that they plan to do so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
