<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Speaking the Language, and the Issues, Pataki Makes Inroads With Latino Voters</title>
    <meta content="16LATI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/16/nyregion/metrocampaigns/16LATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1432321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Navarro, Mireya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2D8163DF935A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Speaking the Language, and the Issues, Pataki Makes Inroads With Latino Voters</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Speaking the Language, and the Issues, Pataki Makes Inroads With Latino Voters</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIREYA NAVARRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Navarro, Mireya</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov George Pataki, seeking election to third term, appears to be gaining support in traditionally Democratic Hispanic community; has been aggressively courting Hispanic vote, speaking Spanish--albeit poorly--and taking up causes that appeal to Hispanic voters; Democrats view his efforts as too little, too late, but Republican tactics appear to be working if polling numbers are accurate; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed like another routine appearance for Gov. George E. Pataki last month when he showed up at a Manhattan restaurant to give a short speech in honor of Hispanic Heritage Month. But in a few minutes the well-heeled celebrators in the crowd were putting down their sangria glasses, shouting ''All right!'' and applauding wildly.</p>
        <p>''Nuestros barrios son mas fuertes, nuestro estado es mas fuerte,'' Mr. Pataki said. ''Porque tenemos una comunidad Latina muy fuerte.'' (Our neighborhoods are stronger, our state is stronger, because we have a very strong Latin community.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his bid for a third term, Gov. George E. Pataki has been engaged in an aggressive courtship of Latino New Yorkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed like another routine appearance for Gov. George E. Pataki last month when he showed up at a Manhattan restaurant to give a short speech in honor of Hispanic Heritage Month. But in a few minutes the well-heeled celebrators in the crowd were putting down their sangria glasses, shouting ''All right!'' and applauding wildly.</p>
        <p>''Nuestros barrios son mas fuertes, nuestro estado es mas fuerte,'' Mr. Pataki said. ''Porque tenemos una comunidad Latina muy fuerte.'' (Our neighborhoods are stronger, our state is stronger, because we have a very strong Latin community.)</p>
        <p>He said the words slowly, as if chewing, his accent more Peekskill, N.Y., than San Juan, Puerto Rico. Mr. Pataki acknowledges his Spanish is ''muy malo, still'' -- still very bad. But given the reaction he gets whenever he rolls his r's, this hardly seems to matter.</p>
        <p>In his bid for a third term, the governor has been engaged in an aggressive courtship of Latino New Yorkers that has him not only speaking Spanish but also advocating temporary asylum for Colombian immigrants, more trade between the United States and the Dominican Republic and an end to the United States Navy's target practice in the Puerto Rican island of Vieques.</p>
        <p>Latino voters say they are loving it. Despite their traditional loyalty to the Democratic Party, many are flirting back.</p>
        <p>''The biggest thing was for him to come up here and talk to people and say 'I'm your governor,' '' said Fernando Mateo, president of the New York State Federation of Taxi Drivers and a key Pataki supporter among Dominicans. ''No other Republican had ever done that before.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki is looking better and better to many Latinos, partly because of concrete steps he has taken to appeal to Hispanic constituencies -- like the financial aid he helped get for families of livery drivers who are injured or killed while on duty, a major issue for Mr. Mateo's group. Latinos also have given him credit for his handling of the World Trade Center tragedy. And like forlorn lovers ready for an affair, many Latino voters speak of disenchantment, if not outright anger, with their long-time partner, the Democratic Party, which many say has been taking them for granted.</p>
        <p>In New York, like elsewhere in the country, a shift within the Hispanic population is creating new opportunities for moderate Republican candidates like Mr. Pataki. Studies show that as the population has grown and become more diverse -- expanding beyond the Mexicans in the Southwest and the Puerto Ricans in the East, who have a history with the Democratic Party and its civil rights agenda -- Hispanic voters are increasingly harder to categorize.</p>
        <p>A survey released this month by the Pew Hispanic Center and the Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation indicated that while the majority of Latinos still start out as Democrats, they are not necessarily finding that a perfect ideological fit. The survey found that they tend to be more conservative than the average Democrat on social issues like divorce and abortion. At the same time, they also tend be more liberal than the average Republican on matters of taxes and government's role in providing social services.</p>
        <p>The ambivalence reflects differences within the population like nationality and whether they were born in or outside the United States, the survey showed. Immigrant Latinos, for instance, tend to be more socially conservative than those born here.</p>
        <p>But together they form an electorate that is essentially up for grabs, with significant numbers of voters willing to swing from one party to another.</p>
        <p>''At a time when the nation is very sharply and almost evenly divided politically, you have this fast-growing part of the electorate that straddles these differences,'' said Roberto Suro, director of the center. ''It has the potential to change the political equilibrium in big, important states.''</p>
        <p>The governor's race in New York, where three-quarters of Latino voters are registered Democrats, is a key test of their willingness to show more independence, some political analysts said. For the longest time, they have been noted as part of a black-Latino block that, while not automatic, has come together for many Democratic candidates.</p>
        <p>But Latinos are showing a greater interest in acting on their own -- it was a reason that Michael R. Bloomberg was able to edge out Mark Green in the mayoral election last year, after Mr. Green was criticized for campaigning unfairly against his Latino opponent in the Democratic primary, Fernando Ferrer, the former Bronx borough president.</p>
        <p>And though Latinos have a lower turnout rate than other groups of voters, they are seen as a powerful force if antagonized or inspired -- as in the mayor's race. Mr. Bloomberg, a Republican, got 43 percent of the Latino vote.</p>
        <p>The governor's race, political analysts note, is also a test of the progress the Republican Party has made in attracting a constituency vital to its own growth. There are 2.9 million Latinos in New York State alone.</p>
        <p>''Politics is about image, and from an image perspective this is very important,'' said Rodolfo de la Garza, a professor of political science at Columbia University and vice president of the Tomás Rivera Policy Institute in California. ''Republicans can't get black voters. They understand now that the nation is changing, and they don't want to be the white party.''</p>
        <p>So taking his cue from President Bush's success in tapping the Latino vote in states like Texas and Florida, and from 2000 census figures that underscored the population gains of Latino communities, there is Mr. Pataki struggling with Spanish on television advertisements and running with a Latina, Dora Irizarry, the Republican candidate for attorney general.</p>
        <p>Many are smitten. One survey, by the Hispanic Federation, shows Mr. Pataki's approval rating among Latinos at 75 percent this year.</p>
        <p>Pataki campaign aides say he is finding strong support among elderly Latinos and newer immigrants in Hispanic enclaves like Corona, Queens. Those areas now include large numbers of Colombians, Ecuadoreans and Mexicans.</p>
        <p>But any significant Latino support for Mr. Pataki has to come from the larger and more established Puerto Rican and Dominican communities, which together account for the majority of Latino registered voters in the state. Mr. Pataki seems to have plenty of converts in these groups, too -- people like Dennis Rivera, a national Democratic Party figure who heads the health care workers' union in New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rivera, who negotiated $1.8 billion for raises for hospital workers from Mr. Pataki, said he is still a Democrat and is campaigning for Democrats in Congress and the Legislature. But he said neither party should assume loyalty from a voting population suffering from ''a very difficult socioeconomic situation.''</p>
        <p>Support ''doesn't come automatically,'' Mr. Rivera said. ''It comes with deeds. If they help us, we help them.''</p>
        <p>Many Latino Democratic leaders, however, describe the Latino interest in Mr. Pataki as a flirtation -- not a full-fledged romance. Mr. Pataki's Democratic opponent, H. Carl McCall, the state comptroller, said he expects to capture ''a substantial portion'' of the Latino vote because of his record on issues of importance to Latinos. They include his promise to appoint Latinos to top positions in government, his push to raise the minimum wage and his call for revisions in the Rockefeller drug laws.</p>
        <p>''These are things that are important, and these are things he has not done,'' Mr. McCall said, referring to Mr. Pataki.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McCall also acknowledged Mr. Pataki's inroads into the Latino community. He said Mr. Pataki, as governor, can go around with ''a bag of goodies'' to win support and has advertised heavily on Spanish language television for over a year ''under the guise'' of promoting his administration's health insurance program for children.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall, hoping to avoid the perception that he is catering to any one group, has not pushed his candidacy with Latino voters, instead letting Latino leaders do most of the talking for him. One who has been vocal in his support is Mr. Ferrer, who mocked Mr. Pataki at a recent McCall fund-raiser in a Latin restaurant in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Much is made of George Pataki's midlife desire to speak Spanish,'' he told the gathering at Patria. ''That's all right. Better late than never. But bad policies are bad policies bilingually, in English and in Spanish.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who is leading in the polls, does not need huge support from the Latino community to win re-election, some political analysts noted. It is just enough for him to neutralize part of the Democratic vote in the big cities, they said. In New York City, Latino voters make up 18 percent of the overall electorate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki got about 25 percent of the Latino vote in 1998, said a campaign spokesman, Michael McKeon, adding that the governor expects to do ''a whole lot better than that'' this November.</p>
        <p>A better showing in New York for the Republican, said Angelo Falcon, senior policy executive for the Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, should give Democrats more than a few pangs of jealousy.</p>
        <p>''It would send a signal to the Democratic Party that they have to get their act together if they don't want to lose more and more elections,'' Mr. Falcon said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
