<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vehicle Sales Decline by 19.1% in Midmonth</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="412656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JUDGE, PAUL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD1638F930A35752C0A967958260" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vehicle Sales Decline by 19.1% in Midmonth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL C. JUDGE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JUDGE, PAUL C</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sales of cars and trucks made in the United States fell by 19.1 percent in mid-December, as demand for vehicles sank to the lowest level since 1982.</p>
        <p>"It takes two to three months for a collapse in real income to hit home in the auto sector, and that is what we are seeing," Scott Merlis, an automotive analyst with Morgan Stanley &amp; Company in New York, said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sales of cars and trucks made in the United States fell by 19.1 percent in mid-December, as demand for vehicles sank to the lowest level since 1982.</p>
        <p>"It takes two to three months for a collapse in real income to hit home in the auto sector, and that is what we are seeing," Scott Merlis, an automotive analyst with Morgan Stanley &amp; Company in New York, said today.</p>
        <p>Tom Webb, the chief economist for the National Automobile Dealers Association, a industry group in McLean, Va., said the sales plunge was "worse than I expected." He linked the drop in vehicle sales to the nation's depressed real estate markets, which he said have eroded personal wealth and caused consumers to postpone purchases of new vehicles.  More Factory Closings Seen</p>
        <p>If the slump in car sales persists into the spring, as many analysts believe, the result will be a depressing effect on the economy, "because it means more pressure to lower inventories by keeping factories closed," Mr. Merlis said.</p>
        <p>The major domestic automobile makers have resorted to widespread plant shutdowns to keep inventories from ballooning.</p>
        <p>The 10 manufacturers that produce vehicles in the United States said today that they sold 206,983 vehicles from Dec. 11-20, compared with 255,757 in the corresponding period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Car sales fell by 17.7 percent, to 127,933 cars in mid-December. Seasonally adjusted, cars sold at an annual rate of 5.1 million, representing the lowest level of demand since 1982, compared with an annual rate of 6.5 million during the same period in 1989. The annual rate for the last 30 days was 5.6 million. Through the middle of last year, cars have sold at an average annual rate of about 6.9 million.</p>
        <p>Sales of light trucks, which account for about a third of all vehicles sold, declined to 79,050 pickups, mini-vans and four-wheel-drive vehicles, a drop of 21.2 percent.  A Broad Decline</p>
        <p>The mid-December downturn in sales was broad, affecting American as well as foreign-based auto makers with plants in the United States. Sales of small models were just as depressed as those of large ones.</p>
        <p>The Big Three domestic auto makers reported a collective decline of 20.6 percent, with light trucks faring slightly worse than cars.</p>
        <p>The Japanese car companies with American plants showed overall sales declines of 9.9 percent for cars, while those of light trucks rose by 51.9 percent, reflecting increased production.</p>
        <p>The Toyota Motor Corporation, the only foreign auto maker to report sales of imported vehicles every 10 days, posted a decline of 8.5 percent in sales of its imported cars, and showed a drop of 2.7 percent in imported truck sales. Other foreign auto makers report such sales figures at the end of the month.</p>
        <p>Sales of cars made at Toyota's two American factories, in Georgetown, Ky., and in the venture with the General Motors Corporation in Fremont, Calif., fell by 10.6 percent, to 6,270 cars.  G.M. Sales Fall 18%</p>
        <p>General Motors sold 59,978 cars made in the United States and Canada, down by 18 percent from a year earlier. Among its stronger sellers were Chevrolet's Geo Metro, G.M.'s most fuel-efficient car; its full-size Park Avenue, intermediate Regal and compact Skylark, all sold by Buick, and the Pontiac Grand Prix.</p>
        <p>G.M. also posted weak sales of several models that have sold relatively well earlier in the year, including the Geo Prizm, Chevrolet Lumina and Cutlass Supreme.</p>
        <p>The luxury tax that took effect on Tuesday, imposing a 10 percent surcharge on the portion of retail prices exceeding $30,000 for cars, apparently did little to enhance sales of G.M.'s Cadillac cars. The division reported an overall sales decline of 23.7 percent for its five models. The Ford Motor Company reported higher sales of its Lincoln Town Car in mid-December, but analysts suggested the gain reflected higher fleet sales rather than private retail customers.</p>
        <p>Ford sold 32,364 cars in the 10-day period, a decline of 20.5 percent. The auto maker also posted sharp declines in sales of its Tempo and Festiva models, and sales of the Taurus and Mercury Sable also fell sharply.</p>
        <p>Ford's light-truck sales fell by 21.4 percent, to 25,582.  Chrysler Off 19.2%</p>
        <p>The Chrysler Corporation's car sales declined by 19.2 percent, to 16,278. The sales of Chrysler mini-vans, Jeeps and pickup trucks plunged by 36.9 percent, to 16,000.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, the No. 3 domestic auto maker said it planned to offer rebates on its 1991 model mini-vans for the first time, a move that some analysts regarded as a concession that sales of Chrysler's most important single vehicle were slipping.</p>
        <p>The Honda Motor Company sold 6,384 cars in mid-December, down by 43.2 percent. A Honda spokesman attributed the slump to "consumer uncertainties and concerns about the Middle East."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
