<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happy Ending for Ga. Tech</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="412719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOWL GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED PRESS INTERNATIONAL (UPI)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEBRASKA, UNIVERSITY OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARVIN, AL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowl Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB123CF930A35752C0A967958260" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happy Ending for Ga. Tech</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL HARVIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARVIN, AL</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were no bed checks and no curfews Tuesday night, so the Georgia Tech football players got a chance to stay up past midnight after their 45-21 Florida Citrus Bowl rout of Nebraska to see if their dream of winning a national championship might come true.</p>
        <p>And when Notre Dame's Raghib Ismail returned a punt 91 yards in the last minute of the Orange Bowl against Colorado a great roar went up in the large meeting room where the Yellow Jackets, their coaches and families were watching, as those dreams were apparently about to come true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were no bed checks and no curfews Tuesday night, so the Georgia Tech football players got a chance to stay up past midnight after their 45-21 Florida Citrus Bowl rout of Nebraska to see if their dream of winning a national championship might come true.</p>
        <p>And when Notre Dame's Raghib Ismail returned a punt 91 yards in the last minute of the Orange Bowl against Colorado a great roar went up in the large meeting room where the Yellow Jackets, their coaches and families were watching, as those dreams were apparently about to come true.</p>
        <p>That roar, however, was followed by a groan as the touchdown was nullified by a clipping penalty. Colorado held for a 10-9 victory that seemingly preserved its top ranking in the polls and dashed Tech's hopes.</p>
        <p>Coach Bobby Ross and his team knew that despite their record as the only undefeated major college team, they still needed a Notre Dame victory over Colorado to have any hope of going home with the school's first national title since the old International News Service voted the Yellow Jackets No. 1 in 1952.  Careful Planning</p>
        <p>"I thought the first and foremost thing we had to do was to beat Nebraska," said Ross. "I didn't want us to become absorbed with who's No. 1 and who's No. 2. There are a lot more important things. I know that if the No. 1 team wins its bowl game, it's a tradition that they never deny them the national championship."</p>
        <p>Some of the voters followed that tradition as The Associated Press poll of writers and broadasters gave its nod to Colorado early this afternoon, with Georgia Tech second. Then The New York Times's computer put Miami, which rocked Texas in the Cotton Bowl, on top with Tech again in second place.</p>
        <p>But United Press International took its time finding the members of its board of coaches, and when it did and had counted the votes, the Yellow Jackets had the No. 1 spot by the slim margin of a single point over Colorado. Questions Over Schedule</p>
        <p>All season long there had been questions about the strength of Georgia Tech's schedule and of its league, the Atlantic Coast Conference. Its lone blemish was a 13-13 late-season tie at North Carolina; otherwise, the 11-0-1 mark made Tech the only undefeated team in Division I-A, which encompasses more than 100 schools.</p>
        <p>After being informed of the top ranking by U.P.I. late this afternoon, Ross said he was pleased, and added:</p>
        <p>"Being perceived in this kind of light means a great deal to me personally and it's also very meaningful for our program.</p>
        <p>"After I heard about The Associated Press vote this morning, I was a little more disappointed than I thought I would be but this makes up for it. Over the past couple of weeks I've gotten a taste of what the national championship was really like and I was excited about the chance that we could win it."  Hard Work Pays Off</p>
        <p>So was Shawn Jones, Tech's sophomore quarterback who had a direct hand in three of the Yellow Jackets' touchdowns against Nebraska. He said he thought all the hard work had paid off.</p>
        <p>"I felt that even though Colorado won, we should have been No. 1 because of the way we beat Nebraska," he said. "I'm happy to see the coaches feel we should be No. 1 also. This erases the disappointment we had from the other polls."</p>
        <p>Jones, an early candidate for next season's Heisman Trophy, was outstanding for Georgia Tech, completing 16 of 23 passes for 277 yards, two touchdowns and a single interception. He also rushed for 65 yards on 11 carries.</p>
        <p>"I said after yesterday's game that this is the greatest team I've ever coached." Ross said. "I'm really happy for our players especially our seniors because they went through all of the tough times. This team would always have been a national champion to me regardless of where we finally ended in the polls. This makes it official."</p>
        <p>Would Ross like to see all this end of the season madness and mythical national championships end?</p>
        <p>"I think it would be good," said Ross. "I've been a supporter of that from day one. I think it should be done through the structure of the bowl games, because they've been good to us. A lot of coaches are against a playoff system. I'm for it, but I'm in the minority."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
