<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Charged With Sending Child Pornography on Internet</title>
    <meta content="06NET.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burke, Thomas (Deputy Warden)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roane, Kit R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E1D7153BF935A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Charged With Sending Child Pornography on Internet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIT R. ROANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roane, Kit R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Deputy Correction Warden Thomas Burke and teacher Anthony Wade are arrested on charges that they transmitted pornographic images of children over Internet in separate cases (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state deputy correction warden and a man who said he was a teacher were arrested yesterday on charges that they transmitted pornographic images of children over the Internet in separate cases, state and local prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>The deputy warden, Thomas Burke, 47, who works at Kings County Hospital in the prison ward, faces a four-count indictment on charges of possessing and transmitting two graphic photos of children engaged in sex acts with adults, said the State Attorney General, Dennis C. Vacco. The other suspect, Anthony Wade, 30, faces 20 counts of possessing and transmitting 10 such photos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state deputy correction warden and a man who said he was a teacher were arrested yesterday on charges that they transmitted pornographic images of children over the Internet in separate cases, state and local prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>The deputy warden, Thomas Burke, 47, who works at Kings County Hospital in the prison ward, faces a four-count indictment on charges of possessing and transmitting two graphic photos of children engaged in sex acts with adults, said the State Attorney General, Dennis C. Vacco. The other suspect, Anthony Wade, 30, faces 20 counts of possessing and transmitting 10 such photos.</p>
        <p>''The vile images allegedly transmitted by these defendants graphically depict young children who are being sexually abused by adults,'' Mr. Vacco said. He added that he had ''no tolerance for those engaged in the trafficking of child pornography and those who perpetuate the abuse and exploitation of young children.''</p>
        <p>Both suspects are from Staten Island. Prosecutors said that Mr. Wade claimed to be a teacher of disabled children at a local school, but he did not specify which one and city school officials said his name could not be found in their employee database.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burke has been a correction officer for 25 years, said Thomas Antenen, a spokesman for the Department of Correctional Services. Mr. Burke was suspended without pay, pending the ruling on the charges against him, Mr. Antenen said.</p>
        <p>If convicted, the suspects each face up to seven years in prison on each count and could be required to register with the local authorities as sex offenders under ''Megan's Law'' after their release, prosecutors said. Bail was set at $250,000 for both men.</p>
        <p>A message left on Mr. Wade's answering machine was not returned yesterday, and a woman who answered the telephone at Mr. Burke's home hung up when called for comment. Mr. Burke's lawyer was out of the country and could not be reached.</p>
        <p>The defendants live less than 20 blocks from each other on Staten Island but did not work in tandem, prosecutors said. Each was brought to the attention of investigators after customers of America Online, an Internet service provider, told the service that they had received pornographic images from the defendants while writing instant messages to other members in what are commonly referred to as chat rooms, the prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>According to the criminal complaints filed against the men, Mr. Wade transmitted the explicit images from February to May, both to members of the on-line service and later to undercover agents who logged into the chat rooms. Mr. Burke transmitted explicit images twice in January, the complaint said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
