<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Robbed the S.&amp;L.'s? Congress.</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONGRESSIONAL COMMITTEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEACH, JIM (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings and Loan Associations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE1731F931A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Robbed the S.&amp;L.'s? Congress.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jim Leach; Jim Leach, Republican of Iowa, is a member of the House Banking Committee.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEACH, JIM (REPR)</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The most captivating news story in my home state last year concerned an attempted robbery of tragicomic proportions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The most captivating news story in my home state last year concerned an attempted robbery of tragicomic proportions.</p>
        <p>The most captivating news story in my home state last year concerned an attempted robbery of tragicomic proportions.</p>
        <p>At the end of the basketball season, a star forward on the Iowa State University team walked into the campus Burger King, without a mask, carrying a rifle. He asked the high school sophomore at the counter to hand over the money in the cash register. The team's picture featuring this strapping athlete was on the wall. The teen-ager recognized him with a ''Hi, Sam.'' He looked up and responded, ''It's not me!''</p>
        <p>The savings and loan scandal is another kind of robbery, the biggest bank heist in history - one that goes beyond the bank vaults to pick the pocket of every American. And the picture of another pin-striped team is on the wall: It is the biannual official photograph of Congress.</p>
        <p>The savings and loan debacle symbolizes the breakdown in discipline in legislative bodies, especially at the committee level, where interest groups target their attention and dollars. Committees are designed to be delegated centers of legislative expertise. Too often they have become advocacy rather than oversight oriented, failing to provide stop signals for the inevitable train wrecks.</p>
        <p>In modern politics, legislative reputations are generally made by extremists, those who push the biggest programs or tax cuts, or who advocate the greatest new powers for Government or the private sector.</p>
        <p>With savings and loans, the committees of jurisdiction in Congress failed to rein in the powers that regulators had allowed the thrifts - to over-leverage capital, buy junk bonds and make speculative investments. They chose instead to encourage the continuation of patently imprudent practices.</p>
        <p>During the 1980's, the two costliest code words in the legislative lexicon became ''direct investments.'' Thrifts were released from their social contract to make home loans -the historical quid pro quo for receipt of Federal deposit insurance - and given license to speculate in commercial real estate and leveraged buyouts. Instead of following the Wall Street precept that ''first loss is best loss,'' gullible legislators bought the claim of Charles Keating and other industry insiders that inflation-ravaged thrifts could beat insolvency by gambling with other people's money.</p>
        <p>From a Sun Belt perspective the gamble worked: The wealth of the Midwest and Northeast was transferred on a one-shot basis to the Southwest and West. While graft was rampant, not all of the deposits were frittered away. A localized infrastructure of homes and modern offices was built that will stand for a generation as a government-induced incentive for migration to those states with the most lax regulation.</p>
        <p>This criminal transfer of wealth from one region to another, from middle-class taxpayers to lubricious high rollers, occurred because legislative bodies abandoned the national interest and represented regional and industry concerns. Once an innumerate Congress ceased to require prudent capital ratios and sanctioned phony accounting and capricious powers, the Government's gold could be stolen without breaking into Fort Knox.</p>
        <p>Ironically, it was the alleged defenders of the little guy in American politics who led the charge to transform an industry created under Franklin Roosevelt to serve small savers and average homeowners into a privileged preserve for the moneyed elite.</p>
        <p>The only honor that can be salvaged from this fiscal Vietnam - the chance to hold the ''ins'' accountable for privatizing profit and socializing loss - must be a demand for campaign reform, for fair rules, for competitive opportunity in American political as well as economic life. The $20 a month that the average American family must pay Uncle Sam for the next 30 years amounts to a Congressional Watergate, depriving Congress, particularly its majority party, of the moral authority to defend the political status quo.</p>
        <p>In Chinese history there is a theory of revolution based upon a ''mandate of heaven.'' A government may be overthrown when a catastrophe - a drought, flood or earthquake - signals the necessity. The question of the 1990's is whether the American people are concluding that the conflicts of interests that cost real people real money are of such earthquake proportions that the mandate of governance ought to be removed from the Democratic political establishment, which has controlled Congress and the majority of state legislatures during the past half-century.</p>
        <p>The challenge to Republicans is to stake out the position as the party of reform. The future belongs to the political party that puts the S.&amp; L. crooks in jail and removes America's legislative bodies from the control of moneyed influence peddlers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
