<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commander Sees at Least Another Year in Afghanistan</title>
    <meta content="Y19TROO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/19/international/asia/19TROO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1401776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Al Qaeda (Terrorist Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneill, Dan (Lt Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Al Qaeda</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McNeill, Dan K.</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6D9163FF93AA25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commander Sees at Least Another Year in Afghanistan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Commander Sees at Least Another Year in Afghanistan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>BAGRAM AIR BASE, Afghanistan, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lt Gen Dan K McNeill, United States commander in Afghanistan, says he expects to need at least one more year to crush remnants of Al Qaeda and Taliban and build foundations of Afghan nation, interview; sees US and its allies unlikely to significantly cut military presence until goals are met; sees nation gaining stability faster than expected; says partial withdrawal of US forces is possible starting next summer if trend continues; says he lacks authority to intervene in internal Afghan rivalries; many delegates to Afghan grand council currently meeting in Kabul say they welcome American troops, at least for now (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The commander of American troops in Afghanistan said today that he expected to need at least one more year to complete his mission here, namely to crush the remnants of Al Qaeda and the Taliban and to build the foundations of an Afghan national army.</p>
        <p>The commander, Lt. Gen. Dan K. McNeill, said that until those milestones were reached it was unlikely that the United States or its allies would significantly reduce their forces in Afghanistan, which currently number more than 12,000 soldiers, including 7,000 Americans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lt. Gen. Dan K. McNeill said on Tuesday that he expected to need at least one more year to crush the remnants of Al Qaeda and the Taliban and build an Afghan army.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The commander of American troops in Afghanistan said today that he expected to need at least one more year to complete his mission here, namely to crush the remnants of Al Qaeda and the Taliban and to build the foundations of an Afghan national army.</p>
        <p>The commander, Lt. Gen. Dan K. McNeill, said that until those milestones were reached it was unlikely that the United States or its allies would significantly reduce their forces in Afghanistan, which currently number more than 12,000 soldiers, including 7,000 Americans.</p>
        <p>General McNeill also asserted in an interview here, though, that Afghanistan seemed to be gaining stability faster than had been widely expected, and he suggested that a partial withdrawal of American forces was possible starting next summer if that trend continued.</p>
        <p>''Certainly you have to believe things are moving in a direction where the Afghans are clearly taking charge of their destiny,'' he said. ''That kind of narrows down the time the coalition will be here.''</p>
        <p>General McNeill's remarks are likely to be received warmly in Kabul, where many senior Afghan officials and Western diplomats take the position that American military power provides the surest short-term solution to Afghanistan's security problems. Those officials contend that American forces are capable not only of preventing Qaeda and Taliban forces from regrouping to destabilize the central government, but also of deterring powerful warlords from plunging the nation back into banditry and civil war.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some Western diplomats have urged the United States to keep a large military presence in Afghanistan during the two-year interim government of Hamid Karzai.</p>
        <p>''The decision the United States made to stand behind Karzai demands it remain at least through the transition phase,'' a senior Western diplomat said.</p>
        <p>But General McNeill said he had no authority to intervene in internal Afghan rivalries.</p>
        <p>An extended presence by American and coalition forces could also stir some resentment in the provinces, particular areas where the Taliban had strong support and where some local leaders have accused coalition troops of killing or detaining innocent civilians.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon is acutely aware of those potential resentments, and for that reason has consistently said that the United States has no intention of establishing permanent military bases in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Still, many delegates to the Afghan grand council currently meeting in Kabul said they welcomed the presence of American troops, at least for now. ''Al Qaeda soldiers and terrorists remain here, and we should search for them,'' said Hajji Abdul Qadir, governor of Nangarhar Province in eastern Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Looming behind American military operations in Afghanistan is preparation for a possible invasion of Iraq, which Pentagon planners have said could require as many as 250,000 soldiers drawn from bases scattered across the globe. It is possible that some troops in Afghanistan could be redeployed to the Persian Gulf if a major assault on Iraq were ordered.</p>
        <p>But General McNeill's comments suggest that the Pentagon continues to view the Afghan operation as a high priority and that it does not intend to allow plans for a possible invasion of Iraq to interfere with it.</p>
        <p>Asked if American forces could be withdrawn in fewer than 12 months, General McNeill said it was conceivable but unlikely. ''I'm not trying to rush out the door,'' he said. ''I'm a very patient man.''</p>
        <p>General McNeill, the three-star commander of the 18th Airborne Corps out of Fort Bragg, N.C., assumed control of all American and coalition forces -- which include troops from Britain, Australia, Canada, Germany, Italy, Poland and several other countries -- on May 31.</p>
        <p>In his time here, he said, he has concluded that while Qaeda forces and their Taliban allies have scattered, they remained a threat to Afghanistan. He estimated that possibly as many as 1,000 adversaries continued to operate in small bands on both sides of the Pakistan border.</p>
        <p>Many military analysts have described the current strategy for hunting Al Qaeda as counterinsurgency, similar to the American operation in Vietnam early in that conflict.</p>
        <p>While rejecting historical parallels, General McNeill agreed that the conflict here had evolved from conventional to unconventional warfare. ''We're in pursuit of a lot smaller forces than you typically see on the battlefield,'' he said. ''They are dependent on the countryside, and in some cases the local populace, to sustain themselves.''</p>
        <p>He mapped out a process for American military disengagement, saying that once his mission was completed, the Bush administration would have to consider replacing infantry troops and with civilians and other types of military units trained to do reconstruction work or peacekeeping operations.</p>
        <p>''If we continue into a transitional government that is a success, if the Afghans are taking control of their own destiny and we don't see the enemy for me to prosecute,'' General McNeill said, ''you then reach a point where you begin to have an argument over why we need to have this joint task force.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
