<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Weekend; Intrepid Report for The Daily Beast</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALONEY, MICHAEL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MASTERPIECE THEATER (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SCOOP (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE133DF93BA15751C1A966958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Weekend; Intrepid Report for The Daily Beast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Years ago "Masterpiece Theater" presented the lavish mini-series "Brideshead Revisited," based on one of Evelyn Waugh's serious novels. Sunday, on Channel 13 at 9 P.M., the public-television series is offering "Scoop," based on one of Waugh's satirical novels. This London Weekend Television production is a single two-hour presentation, which is quite adequate for its one-joke premise.</p>
        <p>Waugh, long a traveler to what the series' host, Alistair Cooke, describes as "obscure places," is here having a merry go at newspapers in general and foreign correspondents in particular. The novelist actually covered the 1935 Italy-Abyssinia war for London's Daily Mail. As Mr. Cooke notes, Waugh was "a traditionalist, a bellicose conservative lamenting the tumbling decay of European civilization."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Years ago "Masterpiece Theater" presented the lavish mini-series "Brideshead Revisited," based on one of Evelyn Waugh's serious novels. Sunday, on Channel 13 at 9 P.M., the public-television series is offering "Scoop," based on one of Waugh's satirical novels. This London Weekend Television production is a single two-hour presentation, which is quite adequate for its one-joke premise.</p>
        <p>Waugh, long a traveler to what the series' host, Alistair Cooke, describes as "obscure places," is here having a merry go at newspapers in general and foreign correspondents in particular. The novelist actually covered the 1935 Italy-Abyssinia war for London's Daily Mail. As Mr. Cooke notes, Waugh was "a traditionalist, a bellicose conservative lamenting the tumbling decay of European civilization."</p>
        <p>The hero of "Scoop," played with deft charm by Michael Maloney, is William Boot, a nature columnist for The Daily Beast, published by the tyrannical Lord Copper (Donald Pleasence ). Boot is quite content to file his copy from his rural ancestral home, where he lives with a family of eccentrics who include the exceptionally dotty Uncle Theodore (Sir Michael Hordern). But in a case of mistaken identity, Boot is suddenly assigned to the East African republic of Ishmaelia, which is supposedly on the verge of civil war. Ishmaelia is fictitious. Waugh's portraits of the news reporters are said to be fairly close to the truth, given an exaggeration here and there.</p>
        <p>Boot is advised that there are only two rules for the foreign correspondent: travel light and be prepared. As for who is supposedly fighting whom, Lord Copper explains that "it's, uh, the traitors against the patriots." Which is which? "The patriots are in the right, and they're going to win." Arriving in Ishmaelia, Boot finds little evidence of war, but there are curious brass bands that march to the tunes of "The Man I Love" or "Begin the Beguine." After a while the worried London editor (Denholm Elliott) demands some copy. Boot sends a wire: "No news. Stop. Weather improving."</p>
        <p>Boot's colleagues are a decidedly rum lot. One has a knowledge of foreign languages that stops at the phrase "beaucoup whisky, beaucoup soda." Sticking closely together, they warn Boot that "if a story breaks, you'll be out in the cold." All worry about one correspondent who always works on his own and clearly embodies the threat that the others might be scooped. Eventually Boot does stumble upon some sort of minor military coup, and his dispatches make him the toast of London, with instant rumors of a knighthood. Returning home, Boot meets a novice journalist who proudly says, "A great profession, isn't it?" "Up to a point," mutters Boot.</p>
        <p>"Scoop" is dated, not least in its arrogant colonialist attitude toward what are supposed to be the clearly "inferior" black populations. And, with the passing of more than 50 years, the novel's satire seems a bit thin. But this is a handsome production -- the African scenes were filmed in Morocco -- sprinkled with delicious performing turns. Mr. Pleasence's Lord Copper is delightfully mad, and a brief scene near the end between Mr. Holdern and Mr. Elliott is a comic gem. MASTERPIECE THEATER: Scoop  Directed by Gavin Millar; written by William Boyd, based on the book by Evelyn Waugh; Sue Birtwistle, producer; Nick Elliot and Patrick Garland, executive producers. At 9 P.M. Sunday on Channel 13. William Boot . . . Michael Maloney Uncle Theodore . . . Sir Michael Hordern Lord Copper . . . Donald Pleasence Salter . . . Denholm Elliott</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
