<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 BELL COMPANIES AGREE TO MERGER WORTH $17 BILLION</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="841012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES ANDTELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PACIFIC TELESIS GROUP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SBC COMMUNICATIONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANDLER, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED91239F931A35757C0A960958260" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 BELL COMPANIES AGREE TO MERGER WORTH $17 BILLION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LANDLER, MARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first marriage of two regional Bell telephone companies and one of the largest corporate mergers ever, SBC Communications announced yesterday that it would acquire the Pacific Telesis Group for $17 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal would create a communications colossus, providing service to more than 30 million residential and business telephone lines in seven states west of the Mississippi, including California and Texas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first marriage of two regional Bell telephone companies and one of the largest corporate mergers ever, SBC Communications announced yesterday that it would acquire the Pacific Telesis Group for $17 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal would create a communications colossus, providing service to more than 30 million residential and business telephone lines in seven states west of the Mississippi, including California and Texas.</p>
        <p>The combined company would also provide wireless service coast to coast, with cellular and other wireless franchises that reach a potential market of 80  million people from Boston to Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Coming just two months after Congress passed a sweeping telecommunications bill, the deal underscores how telephone and media companies are rushing to bulk up for the untrammeled competition of an open marketplace.</p>
        <p>Nynex and Bell Atlantic, the regional phone companies serving New England, New York and the other mid-Atlantic states, have been mulling a merger for months, and several analysts said yesterday's deal could goad them to consummate their courtship.</p>
        <p>Together, SBC and Pacific Telesis would be the nation's second-largest phone  company with more than $21 billion in annual revenues. Only AT&amp;T, the long-distance carrier, would be larger; both SBC (originally Southwestern Bell)  and Pacific Telesis were created in the 1984 breakup of the Bell System.</p>
        <p>Unlike AT&amp;T, which is in the process of cutting more than 30,000 jobs, SBC and Pacific Telesis said yesterday that they planned to hire 1,000 employees to  augment their combined work force of 100,000.</p>
        <p>The new company will be named SBC Communications and will be based at SBC's headquarters in San Antonio. Telephone service to customers in California and Nevada, however, will continue to be provided by companies named Pacific Bell and Nevada Bell.</p>
        <p>"We could have survived as an independent company," Philip J. Quigley, the chairman of Pacific Telesis, said yesterday. "But this is going to be an industry with a handful of strong global players."</p>
        <p>By negotiating quickly and mostly in one-on-one sessions, Mr. Quigley and his counterpart, Edward E. Whitacre Jr., the chairman and chief executive of SBC, were able to keep the deal almost completely under wraps until yesterday. Mr. Whitacre will become the chief executive of the combined company, while Mr. Quigley will become vice chairman.</p>
        <p>The deal is subject to approval from the Justice Department and the Federal Communications Commission. Despite the size and the first-of-its-kind nature of  the deal, legal experts predicted yesterday that the transaction would not run aground on antitrust or regulatory issues.</p>
        <p>"Like the Disney-ABC or Westinghouse-CBS deals, as long as there is robust competition, this should lead to economies of scale," said James H. Quello, an F.C.C. commissioner, "Success in these things is usually based on better service and more attractive prices for consumers."</p>
        <p>Wall Street's strong reaction also indicated that investors believed the deal would go through. The merger is intended to be a tax-free exchange of stock, with SBC giving 0.733 share of its stock for each Pacific Telesis share. That gives the deal a value of $39 a share, or $17 billion -- a 40 percent premium to Friday's closing share price of Pacific Telesis.</p>
        <p>The shares of Pacific Telesis rose $6 , to $33.75, on the New York Stock Exchange. But stock of the acquiring company, SBC, dropped $2.75, to $49.875. SBC is expected to have lower earnings per share for a couple of years, as it issues additional stock to finance the takeover.</p>
        <p>The secrecy and haste of the negotiations between SBC and Pacific Telesis stood in sharp contrast to the long-running talks between Nynex and Bell Atlantic. Neither of those companies have yet publicly acknowledged holding merger discussions, but the talks are such an ill-kept secret that speculating on their status has become a virtual parlor game on Wall Street and in the press.</p>
        <p>As a result, analysts and other experts were somewhat nonplused by the surprise deal, involving two companies on the other side of the country, serving geographic territories that do not even abut each other.</p>
        <p>"There are a lot of things that make sense about this, and a couple that are  tough to figure out," said William C. Bane, a communications consultant at Mercer Management Consulting in Washington.</p>
        <p>Like other analysts, Mr. Bane had been viewing Pacific Telesis as a possible  acquisition candidate. The company, which offers phone service in California and Nevada, has struggled under a double-whammy of intense external competition and  restrictive state regulations in its home market.</p>
        <p>Moreover, by spinning off its cellular properties two years ago into a separate public company, AirTouch Communications, Pacific Telesis unlocked the stock market value of that business but also gave up having a continuing stake in the fastest-growing segment of the industry.</p>
        <p>For its part, SBC Communications has been one of the top performers among the seven so-called Baby Bells. State regulators in its region -- Texas, Oklahoma, Arkansas, Kansas and Missouri -- have tended to be far more protective than California's utilities commissioners in shielding SBC from outside interlopers like AT&amp;T or MCI. As a result, SBC's franchises in local and toll calls have not been eroded nearly as much as those of Pacific Telesis.</p>
        <p>SBC has also aggressively acquired cellular properties in markets like Boston, Chicago and Washington. It has the most cellular subscribers -- 3.2 million -- of any Baby Bell.</p>
        <p>Then, too, SBC has bet heavily on its proximity to Mexico -- acquiring a 10 percent equity stake in the Mexican national phone company, Telefonos de Mexico, for $1 billion. It is this strategy, analysts said, that best explains why SBC wants to own Pacific Telesis. More than 50 percent of all international calls to Mexico originate in states served by Pacific Telesis and SBC -- namely, California and Texas.</p>
        <p>The fact that Pacific Telesis and SBC do not share any state borders is not seen as a major drawback. Although phone companies can cut some costs by consolidating contiguous operations, some analysts said that cost-cutting was not the prime motivation for this merger.</p>
        <p>One potential problem in the merger, however, is the difference in the nontelephone strategies of the two companies. Pacific Telesis has committed itself to an aggressive overhaul of its telephone network to enable it to carry  television programming. As an interim strategy, the company has even spent heavily to acquire wireless cable providers.</p>
        <p>Along with Bell Atlantic and Nynex, Pacific Telesis is a partner in Tele-TV,  a media company that has spent $120 million so far to develop interactive video  programming.</p>
        <p>SBC, by contrast, has been far more tentative about television, spending less to upgrade its network and eschewing wireless cable. SBC is a member of a video  consortium, Americast, which has spent a fraction of what Tele-TV is spending to get into the business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Whitacre sought to play down the importance of those differences yesterday, through a tepid endorsement of the video business. "In the scheme of  things, it's not that big a deal for us," he said.</p>
        <p>With the announcement of this deal, the industry's attention will now very likely swivel back to the East Coast and the Nynex-Bell Atlantic talks. Mark Bruneau, the president of Coba M.I.D., a consulting firm based in Boston, predicted at least one more big merger of telephone companies would occur in 1996.</p>
        <p>"Instead of seven Bell companies, plus three long-distance carriers," Mr. Bruneau said, "you're going to see four plus two."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
