<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="30TRNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1460766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DA1F39F933A05752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports transactions</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Agreed to terms with LHP B.J. Ryan on a one-year contract and INF Jeff Reboulet and INF John Valentin on minor league contracts.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Agreed to terms with RHP Billy Koch on a two-year contract.  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with INF Kevin Witt on a minor league contract.  TEXAS RANGERS--Agreed to terms with RHP Francisco Cordero on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Agreed to terms with LHP Ron Villone and RHP Mike Jackson on minor league contracts.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Agreed to terms with LHP Darren Oliver on a minor league contract.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Agreed to terms with RHP Mike Fyhrie on a minor league contract.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Agreed to terms with 1B Andres Galarraga on a minor league contract.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Agreed to terms with LHP B.J. Ryan on a one-year contract and INF Jeff Reboulet and INF John Valentin on minor league contracts.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Agreed to terms with RHP Billy Koch on a two-year contract.  DETROIT TIGERS--Agreed to terms with INF Kevin Witt on a minor league contract.  TEXAS RANGERS--Agreed to terms with RHP Francisco Cordero on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Agreed to terms with LHP Ron Villone and RHP Mike Jackson on minor league contracts.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Agreed to terms with LHP Darren Oliver on a minor league contract.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Agreed to terms with RHP Mike Fyhrie on a minor league contract.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Agreed to terms with 1B Andres Galarraga on a minor league contract.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  NBA--Suspended Utah coach Jerry Sloan seven games for shoving an official in a Jan. 28 game, and Indiana F Ron Artest four games for an altercation and flashing an obscene gesture during a Jan. 27 game.  CLEVELAND CAVALIERS--Activated F Tyrone Hill from the injured list.  SAN ANTONIO SPURS--Activated C David Robinson from the injured list.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS--Promoted Pete Mangurian to offensive coordinator and moved Mike Johnson to quarterbacks coach. Named George Stewart receivers coach.  CAROLINA PANTHERS--Named Mike Maser offensive line coach.  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS--Signed LB Paul Lacoste, WR Royd Williams and DB Kevin Jordan and allocated them to NFL Europe.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Signed FB Matt Stanley.  SEATTLE SEAHAWKS--Named Dwaine Board defensive line coach.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  FLORIDA PANTHERS--Recalled D Mathieu Biron from San Antonio of the AHL. Reassigned RW Denis Shvidki and D Kyle Rossiter to San Antonio.  LOS ANGELES KINGS--Placed G Felix Potvin on injured reserve. Recalled G Cristobal Huet from Manchester of the AHL.  MONTREAL CANADIENS--Traded F Eric Chouinard to Philadelphia for a 2003 second-round draft pick.  NASHVILLE PREDATORS--Assigned F Greg Classen to Milwaukee of the AHL.  NEW YORK ISLANDERS--Assigned D Ray Schultz to Bridgeport of the AHL.  NEW YORK RANGERS--Fired Bryan Trottier, coach.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Assigned Jeff Taffe to Springfield of the AHL.  ST. LOUIS BLUES--Recalled F Eric Nickulas from Worcester of the AHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS--Assigned D Bryan Helmer to Manitoba of the AHL.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
