<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEST SELLERS: March 3, 1996</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="833949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1DC1E39F930A35750C0A960958260" item-length="2033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEST SELLERS: March 3, 1996</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Weeks This Last</p>
        <p>On Week Week  List Fiction</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Weeks This Last</p>
        <p>On Week Week  List Fiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>PRIMARY COLORS, by Anonymous. (Random House, $24.) The</p>
        <p>progress of a certain Southern governor and his wife on</p>
        <p>their way to the White House.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>THAT CAMDEN SUMMER, by LaVyrle Spencer. (Putnam, $23.95.) In</p>
        <p>1916, a divorced woman, returning to her Maine hometown with</p>
        <p>her three daughters, finds scorn, harassment and romance.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>INTENSITY, by Dean Koontz. (Knopf, $25.) On a weekend visit to</p>
        <p>a Napa Valley farm, a young woman contends with a serial</p>
        <p>killer.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>ABSOLUTE POWER, by David Baldacci. (Warner, $22.95.) Political</p>
        <p>intrigue, sex and murder in Washington's high circles.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>4  24</p>
        <p>THE HORSE WHISPERER, by Nicholas Evans. (Delacorte, $23.95.) A</p>
        <p>troubled woman seeks solace for herself, her daughter and</p>
        <p>their horse from a wrangler in Montana.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>7  14</p>
        <p>FIVE DAYS IN PARIS, by Danielle Steel. (Delacorte, $15.95.) A</p>
        <p>chance encounter between two Americans at the Ritz changes</p>
        <p>their lives forever.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>CONTAGION, by Robin Cook. (Putnam, $24.95.) A physician seeks</p>
        <p>to learn why a deadly epidemic has struck a group of</p>
        <p>hospitals and clinics.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>8  105  THE CELESTINE PROPHECY, by James Redfield. (Warner, $17.95.)</p>
        <p>An ancient manuscript, found in Peru, provides insights into</p>
        <p>achieving a fulfilling life. (</p>
        <p>deadly bombing in an emporium.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>IN THE BEAUTY OF THE LILIES, by John Updike. (Knopf, $25.95.)</p>
        <p>Over four generations, a family shifts its allegiance from</p>
        <p>religious to cinematic illusions.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>THE WEB, by Jonathan Kellerman. (Bantam, $23.95.) On a</p>
        <p>research trip to a Pacific island, Alex Delaware encounters</p>
        <p>a series of macabre events.</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>BEHIND THE LINES, by W. E. B. Griffin. (Putnam, $23.95.) The</p>
        <p>Marine Corps must cope with a bogus general in the</p>
        <p>Philippines during World War II.</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>GUILTY AS SIN, by Tami Hoag. (Bantam, $21.95.) The ordeals of</p>
        <p>an assistant district attorney as she prosecutes a college</p>
        <p>professor for kidnapping his neighbor's child.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>14  10</p>
        <p>SHOCK WAVE, by Clive Cussler. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $25.) Dirk</p>
        <p>Pitt contends with a ruthless man whose diamond-mining</p>
        <p>operations in Antarctica threaten human life.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>15  22</p>
        <p>THE LOST WORLD, by Michael Crichton. (Knopf, $25.95.)</p>
        <p>Scientists visit a Costa Rican jungle that is the breeding</p>
        <p>ground of dinosaurs; a sequel to "Jurassic Park."</p>
        <p>Weeks This Last</p>
        <p>On Week Week  List Nonfiction</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>RUSH LIMBAUGH IS A BIG FAT IDIOT, by Al Franken. (Delacorte,</p>
        <p>$21.95.) A television comedian's comments on the current</p>
        <p>political scene.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>IT TAKES A VILLAGE, by Hillary Rodham Clinton. (Simon &amp;</p>
        <p>Schuster, $20.) The First Lady's quest for ways to help</p>
        <p>create a better society for children.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>HOW COULD YOU DO THAT?! by Laura Schlessinger. (HarperCollins,</p>
        <p>$22.) A condemnation of self-indulgent morality, and ways to</p>
        <p>overcome it. (</p>
        <p>Wohlmuth. (Running Press, $27.50.) The relationships of 36</p>
        <p>sets of sisters.</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>ENTER WHINING, by Fran Drescher. (Regan Books/HarperCollins,</p>
        <p>$22.) The memoirs of the star of "The Nanny."</p>
        <p>Weeks This Last</p>
        <p>On Week Week  List Advice, How-to and Miscellaneous</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>1  145  MEN ARE FROM MARS, WOMEN ARE FROM VENUS, by John Gray.</p>
        <p>(HarperCollins, $23.) Improving communication and</p>
        <p>relationships between the sexes. (</p>
        <p>Rankings reflect sales figures, for the week ending Feb. 17, at 3,985 bookstores plus wholesalers serving 50,000 other retailers (gift shops, department stores,  newsstands, supermarkets), statistically weighted to represent sales in all such outlets nationwide. An asterisk (*) indicates that a book's sales are barely distinguishable from those of the book above. A dagger ( ) indicates that some bookstores report receiving bulk orders for a book.</p>
        <p>And Bear in Mind  (Editors' choices of other recent books of particular interest)</p>
        <p>ATTICUS, by Ron Hansen. (HarperCollins, $22.) A rich, disturbing novel that explicitly favors simplicity, purity and intelligence; its title character forgives his prodigal son more than most readers would be inclined to forgive.</p>
        <p>AT THE STILL POINT: A Memoir, by Carol Buckley. (Simon &amp; Schuster, $23.) Deft, evocative, generous recollections by the youngest of William F. Buckley Jr.'s nine siblings; a lot of her life was hellish, but she seems to have emerged in health.</p>
        <p>BIRDSONG, by Sebastian Faulks. (Random House, $25.) A novel (the author's fourth) in which the "hell of the trenches" of World War I is played out in the literal underworld of mine and countermine, and the past recaptured through  the decoding of a sapper's diary in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>DANCING AFTER HOURS: Stories, by Andre Dubus. (Knopf, $23.) Gracious and graceful short fiction, chiefly about love, that addresses matters much closer to the province of poetry than of the novel; the author's eighth collection.</p>
        <p>FOUNDING FATHER: Rediscovering George Washington, by Richard Brookhiser. (Free Press, $25.) A noble and effective effort to comprehend a figure whose almost eerie political intelligence is hidden from us by the self-restraint and impersonality that were counted for virtues when he learned them.</p>
        <p>THE LOVE AFFAIR AS A WORK OF ART, by Dan Hofstadter. (Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, $24.) A rich and rewarding study of five 19th-century French literary couples and their frustrations as they tried to sustain both life and art in an era that was determined to separate the two realms.</p>
        <p>THE MIDDLE HEART, by Bette Bao Lord. (Knopf, $25.) This long-running (about 75 years) novel is a lightly disguised history of China itself; its characters are  compelled to renounce loved ones, political beliefs and personal morals to survive. NO INTERMISSIONS: The Life of Agnes de Mille, by Carol Easton. (Little, Brown, $29.95.) Even with de Mille's privileges of birth and talent, the price of her achievements as choreographer, author and lecturer, Ms. Easton tells us, was constant combat (she was skilled at that too).</p>
        <p>A STRUGGLE FOR POWER: The American Revolution, by Theodore Draper. (Times Books/Random House, $35.) A deep and original approach to the Revolution as a quarrel over sovereignty, beginning with the French and Indian War of 1763 and Britain's determination to make the Colonies pay for their own protection.</p>
        <p>TAKING ON THE WORLD: Joseph and Stewart Alsop -- Guardians of the American Century, by Robert W. Merry. (Viking, $34.95.) A dual biography of the smart, wellborn brothers whose programs and opinions dominated American journalism for  the generation after World War II.</p>
        <p>A TOUR OF THE CALCULUS, by David Berlinski. (Pantheon, $27.50.) An odd and tantalizing book by a writer who takes immense pleasure in this great mathematical tool, and tries to create it in others.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
