<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rivalry Turns A Board Game Into a Blood Sport; A Perpetual War Consumes Competing Chess Shop Owners</title>
    <meta content="23DECA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/23/nyregion/23DECA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="THOU SHALT NOT: Ninth of 10 articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="The Ten Commandments"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ten Commandments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chess Forum (NYC Store)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chess Shop (NYC Store)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDD143CF930A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rivalry Turns A Board Game Into a Blood Sport; A Perpetual War Consumes Competing Chess Shop Owners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chess Rivalry Becomes a Blood Sport</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hedges, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ninth article in series Thou Shalt Not, which tells stories of ordinary people and how their lives intersected with one of Ten Commandments; rivalry between owners of Chess Forum and Chess Shop, West Village stores specializing in chess, illustrates stricture not to bear false witness against neighbor and destructive power of perpetual war against competitor; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the Far East, where the game of chess was invented around 600 A.D., stones were supposed to be placed on each corner of the board to keep the evil of the match from spilling over into the world. But there are no stones on the boards in the rival chess shops on Thompson Street in Greenwich Village. And people here see evil all over the place.</p>
        <p>The owners of the Chess Shop, at 230 Thompson Street, and the Chess Forum, at 219 Thompson Street, along with the patrons who will go to one shop and not the other, are bitter rivals. The two owners, former partners, have filed lawsuits, had their customers take loyalty oaths and accused each other of spying and theft. They have engaged in name-calling and what each side considers character assassination. One shop briefly barred disloyal patrons. The shops unleashed price wars where each lost money. And all those involved, cursed with minds that often see life as an intricate battle between pieces on a board, have created whirlpools of intrigue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The owners of the Chess Shop, at 230 Thompson Street, and the Chess Forum, at 219 Thompson Street, are bitter rivals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the Far East, where the game of chess was invented around 600 A.D., stones were supposed to be placed on each corner of the board to keep the evil of the match from spilling over into the world. But there are no stones on the boards in the rival chess shops on Thompson Street in Greenwich Village. And people here see evil all over the place.</p>
        <p>The owners of the Chess Shop, at 230 Thompson Street, and the Chess Forum, at 219 Thompson Street, along with the patrons who will go to one shop and not the other, are bitter rivals. The two owners, former partners, have filed lawsuits, had their customers take loyalty oaths and accused each other of spying and theft. They have engaged in name-calling and what each side considers character assassination. One shop briefly barred disloyal patrons. The shops unleashed price wars where each lost money. And all those involved, cursed with minds that often see life as an intricate battle between pieces on a board, have created whirlpools of intrigue.</p>
        <p>The battle will probably not end until one of the shops goes into foreclosure.</p>
        <p>''It does not make very good business sense,'' said Imad Khachan, 37, who owns the Chess Forum. ''We would both make more money if we worked together.''</p>
        <p>The Bible warns, from the story of Cain and Abel to the commandment not to bear false witness against your neighbor, of the destructive power of perpetual war against a rival.</p>
        <p>Such rivalry usually ends not only with the destruction of the enemy but also in self-destruction. The hatred, eventually, consumes all who embrace it.</p>
        <p>''If I had to give him one book it would be 'King Lear,' '' said Mr. Khachan of his former partner, George Frohlinde, at the Chess Shop. ''He is the man who divided his kingdom. This did not need to happen.''</p>
        <p>But across the street, his long gray locks cascading down on the collar of a worn leather jacket, Mr. Frohlinde, a German immigrant who is in his 70's, dismissed the accusations.</p>
        <p>''He worked here,'' Mr. Frohlinde said of Mr. Khachan. ''He learned the business. He found out all my suppliers and my customers and went across the street to open another store.''</p>
        <p>The two shops are similar. They are dominated by tables where players sit, their heads bent over chess boards, for a dollar an hour. There is soft background music, with the Chess Shop preferring classical and the Chess Forum light pop. The players rarely speak, although many like to slam the wooden pieces on the board with an audible thump. The walls in each shop could use a coat of paint, the bathrooms are a bit grimy and the shelves are stacked with hundreds of chess sets, from the traditional to theme sets with pieces from ''The Simpsons'' and ''Star Trek.''</p>
        <p>Prices run from about $5 for a small magnetic set to $10,000 for a modern bronze set cast by the artist Mark Pilato.</p>
        <p>The commandment against bearing false witness calls on people not to defame and slander their neighbors. On Thompson Street, though, defamation and slander have divided the rival shops as neatly as two lines of pawns.</p>
        <p>The dispute began with an exiled Russian grandmaster, Nicholas Rossolimo, a cabdriver who ran a small chess shop on Sullivan Street in the 1950's. He hired Mr. Frohlinde to run it for him in 1963 and eventually left to live in Paris.</p>
        <p>The two eventually had a falling out and Mr. Frohlinde opened the Chess Shop in 1972. Mr. Rossolimo, an aristocratic exile from communist Russia, came back to try to save his shop but fell down a flight of stairs in 1975 and died; his shop perished not long after he did.</p>
        <p>Those who are set against Mr. Frohlinde seize on the story of how he began his life in America by betraying Mr. Rossolimo. The Russian grandmaster has assumed the role of the martyr in the narrative spun out by those seeking to demonize Mr. Frohlinde.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohlinde, however, said it was he who was betrayed. The Russian grandmaster had agreed to let him pay a monthly fee to run the shop and then began to demand more money when the profits rose, he claimed.</p>
        <p>Once he opened his own shop, he said he never spoke to his former employer again.</p>
        <p>Enter Mr. Khachan, a graduate student at New York University who was also fleeing war, in this case from Lebanon. He soon became the manager of the Chess Shop. He dropped out of graduate school because he was promised a partnership which, he said, was never delivered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohlinde, countering the charge, said Mr. Khachan never paid the required money to take over the business. Mr. Khachan walked out in 1995 and opened the Chess Forum.</p>
        <p>Some of the patrons walked out with him. The newest game began.</p>
        <p>When asked what happens when he bumps into his former manager on the street, Mr. Frohlinde answered, ''You don't see people you don't like.''</p>
        <p>He paused, seated under a fly strip with numerous dead bugs stuck to it and a bare neon light, and grimaced at the thought of his rival across the street.</p>
        <p>''I have not spoken to him since,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Those who defected to the Chess Forum began to refer to Mr. Frohlinde as ''the Nazi.'' Those in the Chess Shop began to call Mr. Khachan, a Muslim, ''Yasir Arafat.''</p>
        <p>The charges fly back and forth like swift-moving pieces in a clocked match. The Chess Shop, which says it does not allow gambling, insists that patrons in the Chess Forum often bet a dollar on games. Laurence Nash, 41, Mr. Frohlinde's nephew and the current manager and owner of the shop, said that ''the park crowd,'' the hustlers who sit in Washington Square Park and play people for $5 a game migrate to the Chess Forum late at night and continue to lure in their prey.</p>
        <p>''We try to keep our place pleasant with a family atmosphere,'' Mr. Nash said. ''The other place is a lot more rambunctious.''</p>
        <p>The vitriol does not surprise Mr. Khachan, who said that during the war in Beirut he noticed that the worst savagery was always between those of the same religious or ethnic group.</p>
        <p>''Former partners always tend to be worse than others when they go to war,'' he said. ''People are meaner to their own people. Maybe this is human nature. You become more self-righteous with your own family. You feel the violence is more justified. You are the big brother who will whip everyone into shape, even if you have to kill them all.''</p>
        <p>Ernie Rosenberg said that he and his son were barred from entering the Chess Shop after they defected to the Chess Forum. ''I printed up leaflets and told the owners of the Chess Shop I would distribute them on the sidewalk during the Christmas season unless they lifted the ban on my son,'' he said. ''Why did they ban my son? Because he was my son. My son did not really want to go there, but I got them to lift the ban. I used to go in and stand in the shop just to annoy them. They would try and throw me out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khachan threw in that when he worked in the Chess Shop, ''prices were inflated by 30 or 40 percent'' and ''the place was crawling with cockroaches.'' With all the goings-on in the Chess Shop, he said, ''it saves you from having to read Kafka.''</p>
        <p>''I can live with it,'' said Mr. Nash, sitting in the Chess Shop when asked about the hatred, ''although customers will go back and forth between the shops trying to lower the price on a set they want. We have had some bad price wars.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khachan stood one evening in front of the plate glass window that displayed his chess sets. He watched a young man in a black fatigue jacket and a black wool hat pulled down to his ears linger at the door. The man carried a folded chess board under his arm.</p>
        <p>''He is a spy,'' Mr. Khachan said in a whisper. ''He has been sent over to check the prices and count how many players are in my shop.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nash scoffed at the charge, calling Mr. Khachan paranoid.</p>
        <p>''I have caught people Imad sent over to stand in front of our shop and tell customers his shop is better,'' he said. ''He has been doing this for years. He doesn't let some customers into his shop because he says they are spies, but they are just players who like to play in both shops. It is all very weird.''</p>
        <p>Thou Shalt Not</p>
        <p>The Ten Commandments are among the oldest codes established to regulate ethical behavior. They deal with the fundamental quandaries of human life. The three great monotheist faiths latched onto them for moral guideposts, and they resonate in a season when many take time to carve out sacred space in their lives.</p>
        <p>While the commandments appear straightforward, their demands are often hard to fulfill. What does it mean, for example, for a professional soldier not to kill? What is idolatry in the 21st century? And how, as one rabbi asked, can the parents of a child who died accept the First Commandment, which is interpreted to mean that all is fated by God?</p>
        <p>This is the ninth of 10 articles that tell of personal struggles to comply with the directions of ancient laws in the modern world, reject them or simply cope with them. The articles and additional materials are also online at: nytimes.com/commandments.</p>
        <p>ONLINE: A FORUM ON THIS SERIES  Chris Hedges, the writer of these articles, discusses them with readers: nytimes.com/forums.</p>
        <p>The Ten Commandments</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
