<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistan's Bhutto Quandary</title>
    <meta content="08PAKI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bhutto, Benazir (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leghari, Farooq (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khalid, Malik Meraj</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7D61F38F93BA35752C1A960958260" item-length="1098" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistan's Bhutto Quandary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan, Nov. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of political future of Pakistan in light of ouster of Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto and proclamation issued by Pres Farooq Leghari, who set new elections for Feb 3, 1997; caretaker administration Leghari appointed is led by Prime Minister Malik Meraj Khalid; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Pakistan's new caretaker government settles down to its self-proclaimed task of providing ''good governance and clean administration,'' many Pakistanis are waiting to see what new steps, if any, will be taken to prevent a political comeback by Benazir Bhutto, the deposed Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>In the proclamation issued earlier this week dismissing Ms. Bhutto, President Farooq Leghari set new elections for Feb. 3, 1997. The caretaker administration he appointed, led by Prime Minister Malik Meraj Khalid, renewed the commitment after its first Cabinet meeting on Wednesday. ''Among the priorities listed by the Prime Minister, on top was preparation for free, fair and transparent general elections on Feb. 3 next year,'' a Cabinet statement said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Pakistan's new caretaker government settles down to its self-proclaimed task of providing ''good governance and clean administration,'' many Pakistanis are waiting to see what new steps, if any, will be taken to prevent a political comeback by Benazir Bhutto, the deposed Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>In the proclamation issued earlier this week dismissing Ms. Bhutto, President Farooq Leghari set new elections for Feb. 3, 1997. The caretaker administration he appointed, led by Prime Minister Malik Meraj Khalid, renewed the commitment after its first Cabinet meeting on Wednesday. ''Among the priorities listed by the Prime Minister, on top was preparation for free, fair and transparent general elections on Feb. 3 next year,'' a Cabinet statement said.</p>
        <p>But keeping the commitment may not be easy. One reason is that Ms. Bhutto has said that she will challenge her dismissal in Pakistan's Supreme Court, a process that could drag on for weeks or months and  provide grounds for delaying elections. Another is that Mr. Leghari, a former Bhutto loyalist who has been excoriated by Ms. Bhutto for betraying her, may be reluctant to allow elections if that means a contest between Ms. Bhutto's Pakistan People's Party and the opposition Pakistan Muslim League, which have alternated in government since civilian rule was restored in 1988.</p>
        <p>Many Pakistanis have said in recent days that dismissing Ms. Bhutto, on charges of corruption, nepotism and misrule will have achieved little, and may even have worsened the prospects for better government if she goes directly to the hustings to appeal for a new mandate. In a news conference on Wednesday, she vowed to return to power. ''I have been elected Prime Minister, and I'll be Prime Minister again,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Pakistanis who worry that Ms. Bhutto might return to power, possibly unleashing a new cycle of political bloodletting, are generally just as uneasy at the possibility of an election victory by Nawaz Sharif. Mr. Sharif, the main opposition leader, was Prime Minister from 1990 to 1993 until he, too, was dismissed because of accusations of corruption and misrule.</p>
        <p>As a senior Western diplomat put it today, ''We're told that Leghari did what he did to turn a new leaf, right? But if all he's achieved is a new runoff between Benazir Bhutto and Nawaz Sharif, what's the point?''</p>
        <p>Since dismissing Ms. Bhutto and going on television to explain his action, Mr. Leghari has gone to ground. The President, trained as an economist, has a reputation for cautiousness, and those who know him say they believe he would not have ousted Ms. Bhutto if he did not have a  plan to keep her from a quick return to power. Most of the speculation has focused on what has become the  buzzword of Pakistani politics in recents days, ''accountability.''</p>
        <p>By this, Pakistanis mean that some means must be found to make  officials, including judges, answerable for accusations of corruption and other misdeeds. It is almost an axiom these days that the ruling establishments, in both main parties, have acted for years as though no law could ever catch up to them. Pakistani newspapers and journals regularly chronicle cases of serious offenses by leading politicians, including murder, kidnapping, taking kickbacks and defaulting on millions of dollars in loans from state-owned banks. Almost the only prosecutions are ones that were started by politicians in power as part of a vendetta against those out of power.</p>
        <p>Before Ms. Bhutto was ousted, Mr. Leghari demanded the creation of an ''accountability commission.'' She responded with a draft statute that turned out to be a thinly-disguised attempt to empower the Prime Minister to dismiss public officials, including the President and senior judges, virtually at will. Many Pakistanis think the bill, which would have required a constitutional amendment, was the last straw for Mr. Leghari.</p>
        <p>Now people are waiting to see if Mr. Leghari has a plan to set up an accountability commission of his own. Some Western envoys here who have conveyed their backing for Mr. Leghari's dismissal of Ms. Bhutto have been urging the President, through his aides, to act quickly, so as to preserve the chance of obtaining convictions, or at least disqualifications from public office, before the new election campaign begins. ''He hasn't got a month,'' one envoy said. ''He's got 10 days.''</p>
        <p>A solution that has been widely discussed among Pakistanis is for Mr. Leghari to use his extensive executive powers to disqualify both Ms. Bhutto and Mr. Sharif from running in the election. But this would risk having both main parties take to the streets with their supporters in protest, which could throw the country into chaos. Ms. Bhutto has already said that ''taking to the streets'' is one option she has under consideration, although the reaction to her dismissal, with hardly any protests and widespread approval of the move, could deter her.</p>
        <p>An easier route for Mr. Leghari, and one most Pakistanis think virtually inevitable, is the prosecution of her husband, Asif Ali Zardari, whose business dealings and interference with Government agencies that handle contracts running into billions of dollars, is said to have been so widespread that he is known throughout Pakistan as ''Mr. 10 Percent.'' Mr. Zardari was arrested by army troops, apparently for questioning on possible corruption charges, in the early hours of Tuesday, as Ms. Bhutto was being informed of her dismissal. He was allowed to meet  his wife in an Islamabad detention center after midnight on Wednesday, but remains in custody.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zardari was held in jail for two years after Ms. Bhutto's first Government was dismissed in 1990, but he was freed without being convicted on any of a score of corruption charges, and became investment minister in Ms. Bhutto's second Government. Privately, officials of the caretaker government have said that the evidence against Mr. Zardari appears far stronger this time,  and that successful prosecutions may be possible. A trial of Mr. Zardari could discredit Ms. Bhutto to the point that she could be disqualified from the election without provoking public fury.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
