<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>D'Amato Declares His Pursuit Of Whitewater Inquiry Is Over</title>
    <meta content="08DAMA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="AFTER THE ELECTION: THE INVESTIGATIONS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="AFTER THE ELECTION: THE INVESTIGATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arkansas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Madison Guaranty Savings &amp; Loan Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Whitewater Development Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fritsch, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DA163BF93BA35752C1A960958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>D'Amato Declares His Pursuit Of Whitewater Inquiry Is Over</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE FRITSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fritsch, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Alfonse M D'Amato reiterates that he will not seek to reopen Senate hearings into Whitewater real-estate venture of Pres Clinton and his wife; D'Amato has seen his approval ratings slip since he began leading the hearings in 1994; he is up for re-election in 1998; exit polls in New York, where Pres Clinton won 59 percent of vote, suggest that D'Amato's dogged attacks on Clintons may have backfired in minds of others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato reiterated today that he would not seek to reopen Senate hearings into the Whitewater real-estate venture of President Clinton and his wife, Hillary.</p>
        <p>''It seems to me we've done our job,'' Mr. D'Amato said in an interview. ''Now it's time for us to let the special prosecutor do his. In my opinion, we should let the special prosecutor do his work and don't second-guess him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato reiterated today that he would not seek to reopen Senate hearings into the Whitewater real-estate venture of President Clinton and his wife, Hillary.</p>
        <p>''It seems to me we've done our job,'' Mr. D'Amato said in an interview. ''Now it's time for us to let the special prosecutor do his. In my opinion, we should let the special prosecutor do his work and don't second-guess him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato, who is up for re-election in 1998, has seen his approval ratings slip since he began leading the hearings in 1994. Exit polls on Tuesday showed that 59 percent of New York voters disapproved of how he does his job and 34 percent approved. At the same time, Mr. Clinton won New York with 59 percent of the vote. The numbers suggest that Mr. D'Amato's dogged attacks on Mr. Clinton, and particularly the First Lady, may have backfired in the minds of voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato said in the interview he had never had any intention of holding a new set of hearings, a fact that he said had been known for months. He said he repeated his position on Wednesday in response to a reporter's question at a news conference on other matters. He added that his position on Whitewater had nothing to do with the election results or with his approval rating.</p>
        <p>In fact, it would be nearly impossible for Mr. D'Amato to convene more hearings. His committees' authorization to investigate Whitewater expired last June. New hearings would require a new resolution from the Senate, but the atmosphere has changed sharply in the 18 months since the Senate voted 96 to 3 to investigate the Whitewater deal.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Republicans were barely able to win approval to extend the investigation. Now, Democrats would probably filibuster such a proposal to death. It takes 60 votes to end a filibuster, and the Republicans will have only 54 or 55 seats in the Senate, depending on the final election results.</p>
        <p>And the Republicans' zeal for investigating the Whitewater affair has waned, as there is little indication that their pursuit of the matter played well with voters.</p>
        <p>Still, Whitewater is not likely to fade from the headlines. The White House has repeatedly attacked the special prosecutor, Kenneth W. Starr, over the last few months as little more than a Republican political operative. In the coming months, Mr. Starr will be faced with decisions about whether to end his investigation or press on, possibly into the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato said today that it was time for him to move on to the pressing issues that face ordinary people, especially the impending crisis in Medicare. ''I'm going to concentrate on doing the things people want: smaller government, more efficient government and to be able to keep more of their money.''</p>
        <p>And he is not concerned, he said, about his approval rating.</p>
        <p>''Two years is a lifetime in politics,'' Mr. D'Amato said. ''You make a big mistake trying to pattern everything on the basis of a poll.''</p>
        <p>But an adviser close to Mr. D'Amato said aides believed his pursuit of the Clintons and Whitewater had hurt him significantly in New York and was largely responsible for his poor showing in polls.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato is now trying to recast himself in a new, softer image that will appeal to moderates in New York, the adviser said. One element of his new campaign was his support of the environmental bond act on Tuesday's ballot in New York, which he hoped would make him more appealing to environmentalists, the adviser said.</p>
        <p>The Republicans lost the race for the Presidency, Mr. D'Amato said, because they failed to bring home to people how the Dole economic plan would affect them. ''We could have done a better job of talking about the economic plan sooner,'' he said. ''People are hurting. We should have argued the case that the biggest part of the tax plan was the $500 tax credit for each child.''</p>
        <p>And the Republicans failed to counter the Democrats' ''chilling message'' that Republicans wanted to make large cuts in Medicare, he said.</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. D'Amato's relationship with his party and with former Senator Bob Dole has been somewhat strained over the last year.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dole telephoned Mr. D'Amato on Wednesday for what the Senator described as a ''personal'' conversation.</p>
        <p>''Here he was in all this pain and what-not,'' Mr. D'Amato said. ''He's a great person. We're good friends and I'm hurting for him.''</p>
        <p>AFTER THE ELECTION: THE INVESTIGATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
