<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Photorealism: Is That All There Is?</title>
    <meta content="30NJAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zimmerli Art Museum (New Brunswick, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDB173BF933A05752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Photorealism: Is That All There Is?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <dateline>New Brunswick</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews American Photorealism exhibit at Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum in New Brunswick, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SETTING aside the wow factor of photorealist painting  admittedly, a very big aside -- this insanely popular art genre holds precious little of enduring significance. That, at any rate, is the unhappy conclusion I reached after viewing ''American Photorealism'' at the Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum here.</p>
        <p>But that doesn't mean this is a bad exhibition. With 67 works by 27 artists, it offers a thoughtful, scholarly and comprehensive overview of photorealist painting in the United States over the past few decades. Exhibitors range from those who helped define the art movement, like Ralph Goings, Robert Bechtle, Robert Cottingham, Don Eddy, Richard Estes, Charles Bell and Audrey Flack, to a bunch of newcomers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SETTING aside the wow factor of photorealist painting  admittedly, a very big aside -- this insanely popular art genre holds precious little of enduring significance. That, at any rate, is the unhappy conclusion I reached after viewing ''American Photorealism'' at the Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum here.</p>
        <p>But that doesn't mean this is a bad exhibition. With 67 works by 27 artists, it offers a thoughtful, scholarly and comprehensive overview of photorealist painting in the United States over the past few decades. Exhibitors range from those who helped define the art movement, like Ralph Goings, Robert Bechtle, Robert Cottingham, Don Eddy, Richard Estes, Charles Bell and Audrey Flack, to a bunch of newcomers.</p>
        <p>Photorealism, a type of realist painting whose content is based on photographs or, better, a photographic way of seeing, took off in this country in the late 1960's. It was more of a style than a movement, for its practitioners tended to work independently, in a variety of media, with individual subject matter. Many, however, were concentrated around the gallery of Louis K. Meisel, a New York art dealer.</p>
        <p>It is a curious thing to say about such detailed paintings that they fail to hold much interest beyond the way they were painted. But photorealist art is, when you look closely, a kind of hyperformalism. It is all about form, technique and surface, a manic, unthinking empiricism -- every leaf, every blade of grass is carefully colored and defined.</p>
        <p>Yet to say this is to hit upon what many people admire about the genre, which is the skill of the artists to fashion such an accurate representation of reality. We admire their ability to do something we cannot, while marveling at the work's photographic detail. Trompe l'oeil painting tends to elicit a similar response.</p>
        <p>There isn't much in this exhibition that is going to have you reaching out in expectation of touching the real thing, but there are plenty of impressive paintings. Don Eddy's ''The Hesychia Tide'' (2002) deserves praise for its striking realism, as do Stephen Posen's untitled still lifes. My only complaint is the subject matter, which in neither case is terribly ambitious or engaging.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to an often-cited criticism of photorealism: the subject matter tends toward the corny and superficial. The present exhibition does little to dispel this, stocked as it is with gimmicky paintings of cars, airplanes, silver-service sets, window reflections, engines, street scenes and bling-bling. It is like a catalog of clichés, each more worn out than the next.</p>
        <p>It sounds like Pop Art, you say? Perhaps. But what's missing is the irony, the sense that the artists are knowingly working with clichés in a way that seeks to question or undermine them; or that there is some deeper thought behind the recycling of popular imagery. You never get this feeling looking at photorealist painting, which always feels like empty celebration or, when it dabbles with illusionism, a kind of cheap magic trick.</p>
        <p>What is also curious about photorealism is that while the subjects are usually man-made things located in urban environments, many of the paintings are strikingly devoid of signs of life: there is not a stray dog in sight. Why? I don't know, but the upshot is that they often strike you as cold, silent and sterile -- mere architectural models.</p>
        <p>Take, for instance, Richard Estes's ''Waverly Place'' (1980), a study of an intersection in Greenwich Village. The artist's technical command of fixed-point perspective is impressive, but denuded of people the painting feels icy, soulless and oppressive. It is like sitting alone in a massive, empty concert hall.</p>
        <p>All of this is not to say that there aren't great paintings here. Mr. Estes's ''Lee (Corner Window)'' (1974) is as masterly a work of photorealism as you are ever likely to see, while a newcomer, R.E. Penner, has a knack for imbuing unassuming suburban scenes with a mysterious intensity. ''House With Pickup Truck'' (2000), for instance, is a masterpiece of loving attention to prosaic detail.</p>
        <p>Yet detail, in the end, is what photorealism is all about -- acres of it, minutely rendered in mock imitation of the modern photograph. So look hard. What you see is what you get.</p>
        <p>''American Photorealism,'' Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum, 71 Hamilton Street, New Brunswick, through March 27. Information: (732)932-7237 or www.zimmerlimuseum.rutgers.edu.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
