<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happily a Target of Landlords and Tenants Alike</title>
    <meta content="30PROFILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/30/nyregion/30profile.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1593273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Marvin Markus</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rent Guidelines Board (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markus, Marvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rent Guidelines Board</org>
        <org class="online_producer">The Goldman Sachs Group Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1DB1238F933A05755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happily a Target of Landlords and Tenants Alike</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Happily a Target of Landlords and Tenants Alike</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives profile of Marvin Markus, longest-serving and arguably most dominant chairman in history of New York City's Rent Guidelines Board; every spring board determines rental increases for city's one million rent-stabilized apartments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>O.K., so Marvin Markus may not land on anyone's Top 10 List of Beloved Public Officials. Landlords don't care for him, and say that they have never been as unhappy as they are now. Tenants call him Marvin Markup, and accuse him of engineering cruel rent increases. And, who knows, maybe someone will someday resurrect the marionette that New York City renters made in his likeness more than two decades ago. ''They said that Ed Koch was pulling the strings,'' Mr. Markus says.</p>
        <p>But go ahead, hurl your nastiest insult at him. Pull out your cleverest poster. As the longest-serving and arguably most dominant chairman in the history of the city's Rent Guidelines Board, Mr. Markus is used to getting beat up by all comers. He may even kind of like it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marvin Markus is the longest-serving and arguably most dominant chairman in the history of the city's Rent Guidelines Board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>O.K., so Marvin Markus may not land on anyone's Top 10 List of Beloved Public Officials. Landlords don't care for him, and say that they have never been as unhappy as they are now. Tenants call him Marvin Markup, and accuse him of engineering cruel rent increases. And, who knows, maybe someone will someday resurrect the marionette that New York City renters made in his likeness more than two decades ago. ''They said that Ed Koch was pulling the strings,'' Mr. Markus says.</p>
        <p>But go ahead, hurl your nastiest insult at him. Pull out your cleverest poster. As the longest-serving and arguably most dominant chairman in the history of the city's Rent Guidelines Board, Mr. Markus is used to getting beat up by all comers. He may even kind of like it.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't trouble me,'' he says. ''It takes a thick skin to be involved in those kinds of things.''</p>
        <p>Every spring, Mr. Markus, 55, an affable and quick-witted investment banker, morphs into the bête noire of New York's polarized housing community. He leads a board that includes two people representing landlords, two representing tenants and four others appointed by the mayor. And boy, is that a great civic gig -- if, by great, you mean being squeezed by intense political pressures and qualifying for a measly $100 per diem that hasn't changed since the board's inception in the late 1960's. (The chairman is actually eligible for -- oooh -- $125, but Mr. Markus declines it.)</p>
        <p>But inherent in the job is tremendous power, for the board determines rental increases for the city's one million rent-stabilized apartments. And this spring, Mr. Markus drew exceptional ire -- first for proposing a range of increases rather than a specific percentage during a preliminary vote in May, then for successfully shepherding a proposal to raise rents by up to 6.5 percent through a raucous final vote two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Landlords say that the increase will do little to defray their rising costs. Tenants, convinced that Mr. Markus has an agenda to shrink the city's vast rent-regulation system, want Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg to fire him. A small group even protested outside his day job at Goldman Sachs, where he is a vice president specializing in municipal finance, and working on projects involving Hudson Yards and the United Nations Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>But to Mr. Markus, that kind of bipartisan sturm und drang is something that may be necessary to achieving what he says is the ultimate goal: helping to preserve the city's stock of apartments for low- and middle-income residents, through a complex rent-regulation system that could be conceivable only in New York.</p>
        <p>''Generally, the board has done a very fair and equitable job of balancing all the needs,'' says Mr. Markus, who calls himself a ''swing vote.''</p>
        <p>You can ask Mr. Markus, who was born in Germany in a refugee resettlement camp and grew up in Montreal and Brooklyn, a million ways why he has taken on so thankless a job, and he'll cite an enduring interest in housing policy. Ever since he became active in Brooklyn Democratic politics while attending Brooklyn College. Ever since he got a job as a research associate at the Citizens Housing and Planning Council (where he is now the president), while earning a master's degree in urban planning from New York University. Ever since he became a protégé of Roger Starr, an outspoken city housing official who later became an editorial writer for The New York Times.</p>
        <p>In 1979, at the age of 31, Mr. Markus was appointed by Mayor Edward I. Koch as the chairman of the rent board for the first time. The meetings were far more raucous then, he says, because the board had previously huddled in private. So when the board pushed through double-digit increases because of inflation and rising fuel costs, apoplectic tenants nicknamed him Marvin Markup.</p>
        <p>He stepped down in 1984, moving to Jericho, on Long Island, with his wife, Michelle, an interior decorator; their daughter, Adria, now 31, and their son, Bryce, 27. (Both children work for Goldman Sachs.)</p>
        <p>HIS civic instincts lay dormant in suburbia. But when Mr. Markus and his wife moved back to the city in 2001, buying an apartment near Lincoln Center, he asked Mr. Bloomberg to appoint him rent-board chairman again. That thick skin, again.</p>
        <p>In some ways, there aren't too many differences between Markus I and Markus II. The same posters appear, except that the name of the mayor has changed. The same faces show up to the same Kabuki-like meetings, if a bit fleshier and grayer. ''The season ticketholders,'' he calls them.</p>
        <p>He has also learned, he says, to let the audience stew for a while. Sometimes, he will arch his right eyebrow and right upper lip, then go into a good-natured snort of a laugh. ''There's energy in the room, and energy has a tendency to dissipate, so you need dissipation strategies,'' he says.</p>
        <p>To escape the pressures of work and public life, he has become an avid theatergoer, favoring musical revivals. He also signed up recently for a movie-appreciation course at New York University, and he gives big thumbs-ups to ''Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless Mind'' and ''Dogville.''</p>
        <p>But during one class, he spotted Jimmy Silber, a regular fixture at rent board meetings who is affiliated with the Small Property Owners of New York. Ah, the smallness of the world. ''You can't get away,'' Mr. Markus said, chuckling.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
