<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Tactic for Kosovo Rebels: Attacks on Isolated Serb Civilians</title>
    <meta content="24SERB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Movements and Secession</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Klina (Serbia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kosovo Liberation Army</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7D7103CF937A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Tactic for Kosovo Rebels: Attacks on Isolated Serb Civilians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hedges, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>KLINA, Serbia, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ethnic Albanian rebels change tactics in recent days and begin attacking and kidnapping Serbian civilians in apparent effort to drive them out of their villages in overwhelmingly Albanian province of Kosovo, Serbia; Kosovo Liberation Army previously avoided attacking civilians, despite deaths of scores of ethnic Albanian civilians in counterinsurgency sweeps by Serbs; take five Serbian villages and many small hamlets and farms around Klina after gun battles with residents; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The gong of church bells summoned the Serbs up to the weed-choked cemetery, with its ancient stone crosses, marble tombs etched with the faces of the departed, crooked iron gates and gnarled trees.</p>
        <p>During the tolling, the open coffin of Oliver Zaic, 17, his face waxy with the pallor of death, was carried through the dusty streets, lifted through a hole in the cemetery fence and borne up the steep hill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The gong of church bells summoned the Serbs up to the weed-choked cemetery, with its ancient stone crosses, marble tombs etched with the faces of the departed, crooked iron gates and gnarled trees.</p>
        <p>During the tolling, the open coffin of Oliver Zaic, 17, his face waxy with the pallor of death, was carried through the dusty streets, lifted through a hole in the cemetery fence and borne up the steep hill.</p>
        <p>The pallbearers were jostled by the densely packed crowd of 200 mourners, and the body, wrapped in a white sheet and strewn with flowers, bobbed toward its destination on a lake of black cloth.</p>
        <p>''Have we been abandoned?'' Milic Zaic, 42, the slain boy's uncle asked the crowd as he stood over the coffin. ''Are we doomed to face this terror alone? Are we strong enough to survive? You, Oliver, have shown us our destiny, the destiny of all who try to defend their homes. I apologize, my boy, that we cannot bury you in your own village.''</p>
        <p>Oliver Zaic was killed in his garden in Bica as he protected his widowed mother and 10-year-old sister, Marica, from ethnic Albanian rebels, his family said.</p>
        <p>In recent days the rebels have changed their strategy and begun to attack and kidnap Serbian civilians in an apparent effort to drive them out of their villages in the overwhelmingly Albanian province of Kosovo in southern Serbia.</p>
        <p>Until now the rebel group, the Kosovo Liberation Army, has avoided attacking civilians, despite the deaths of scores of ethnic Albanian civilians, including more than 20 children, in counterinsurgency sweeps the Serbs have mounted since March. But in the last few days, five Serbian villages and many small hamlets and farms around Klina have been seized by armed rebels after gun battles with residents.</p>
        <p>The Kosovo Liberation Army has cut most of the roads in this area, isolating it from the Yugoslav forces. In turn, these attacks have swiftly drawn in armed Serbian militias thirsting for revenge.</p>
        <p>Before, the war against Albanian separatists in Kosovo was waged by some 50,000 special police and army troops. But the new mixture of combatants threatens to usher into Kosovo the savagery inflicted on Bosnia during the war there, when battle was often waged by undisciplined paramilitary groups against civilians from opposing ethnic groups.</p>
        <p>In recent days armed ethnic Albanian groups have expelled Serbs from Jelovac and Kijevo, which were populated by Albanians and Serbs. There are now 900 Serbs, displaced from their homes in the last week, taking refuge in Klina, and several say male relatives detained by the rebels are still missing.</p>
        <p>''I have two brothers who were taken by the terrorists from their farm on Sunday,'' said Novica Vostic, 60, a farmer who fled to Klina. ''One is 70 and the other is 69 years old. The terrorists attacked my house yesterday in the village of Jelovac, four miles from here. We all fired back, and the Serbian families in 12 houses in Jelovac fled. We don't dare to go back. It's too dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Bodies have begun turning up near Serbian settlements. Zivojin Milic, shot six times in the head, was found last Wednesday on the outskirts of Pristina, apparently a victim of the ethnic Albanian militants.</p>
        <p>The village of Bica, three miles north of Klina, is one of the last Serbian villages staving off rebel bands in this corner of Kosovo, and like most it is trying to organize its men into an armed force.</p>
        <p>As nearby Serbian farms and hamlets have swiftly fallen to rebel bands, the 1,300 inhabitants of Bica have dug four trenches, built crude underground bunkers and established a home guard. The soccer field in the center of the village had a pile of new, white sacks filled with dirt destined for the barricades.</p>
        <p>Brief exchanges of fire with the rebels, who occupy a hill just a few hundred yards away, punctuate the shrill drone of the cicadas. And many people with jobs in Klina say they no longer go to work because of the danger.</p>
        <p>''The problems started in April when the Kosovo Liberation Army kidnapped three young men from the town,'' said Vojislav Doncic, 38, a local police officer who leads the militia, and whose extended clan has many members here. ''There were three Albanian men from the Hoti family near our village, and they agreed to be our mediators. They got the boys released after 10 days.</p>
        <p>''Then, two weeks ago, the terrorists began to take potshots at us. We sent the Hoti men over to mediate again, and they never came back.''</p>
        <p>To prove his point, Mr. Doncic walked up a road to a small hill that looked out over a valley. When he got to the top, shots rang out and he began to run, crablike, down the embankment.</p>
        <p>Serbian farmers, standing in a trench, let out a noisy volley from ancient bolt-action rifles, automatic rifles and an old World War II German machine gun.</p>
        <p>''See,'' Mr. Doncic said, bent nearly double, ''I told you. This is as far as I can go. Beyond here you get killed.''</p>
        <p>The Serbian farmers say the police, often hemmed down in sandbagged checkpoints along the main roads, are of little help. There is a growing feeling among Serbs in this isolated pocket that Belgrade has abandoned the Serbs, who number about 150,000 in a province with nearly two million ethnic Albanians.</p>
        <p>''The police come for a visit and leave,'' said Ljubisa Doncic, 38,a teacher who has not traveled out of the village for three days. ''We don't have proper weapons to fight back. The police do not protect us. We are getting pretty angry, especially since every day it gets worse.''</p>
        <p>Ljubisa Doncic walked toward his house as neighbors headed toward their guard posts, carrying their dinner and weapons.</p>
        <p>''I have my father's 1924 Belgian carbine,'' he said, ''and I get it out each night. My two children begin to cry. I tell them what you always tell children -- that everything is O.K., that I will not be far away. But they hear the shots at night. They know.''</p>
        <p>Two farmers, Zviko Doncic, 65, and Milenko Gorgevic, 47, stood next to 10 grazing sheep and four goats on the dirt road at the entrance to the village. They clutched Yugoslav carbines dating from World War II, which were of little use against the AK-47 assault rifles carried by the rebels. It is their job to wave down incoming cars and check those who enter the village.</p>
        <p>''See down there,'' said Mr. Gorgevic, pointing in a valley to a small settlement of white stucco houses. ''That little village was half Serb and half Albanian a week ago. Now there are no Serbs left.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
