<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Premier May Soon Dismiss Key Adviser</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOSOKAWA, MORIHIRO (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAKEMURA, MASAYOSHI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEED8153AF931A35750C0A962958260" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Premier May Soon Dismiss Key Adviser</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, March 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Morihiro Hosokawa was reported today to be ready to expel his chief Cabinet secretary from a crucial policy-making role, a step that is likely to encourage those who want faster changes in the economy and closer ties to the United States.</p>
        <p>After seven months of unstable government and several policy zigzags, Mr. Hosokawa was described as being on the verge of ending a longstanding battle within his Government by casting his lot with the conservative.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Morihiro Hosokawa was reported today to be ready to expel his chief Cabinet secretary from a crucial policy-making role, a step that is likely to encourage those who want faster changes in the economy and closer ties to the United States.</p>
        <p>After seven months of unstable government and several policy zigzags, Mr. Hosokawa was described as being on the verge of ending a longstanding battle within his Government by casting his lot with the conservative.</p>
        <p>He met today with the leaders of the seven parties and reportedly described the shuffling as an attempt to refocus on important economic issues -- resolving a trade dispute with the United States and jolting the economy out of recession. But few doubt that the real aim is to remove Masayoshi Takemura, the chief Cabinet secretary and once his closest ally.</p>
        <p>A Cabinet shuffle would be a major victory for the most conservative thinker in the Government, Ichiro Ozawa, who holds no official post but has been Mr. Hosokawa's key strategist. But the shake-up could drive deeper the wedge that has split the right and left wings, and could complicate the already painful decision-making process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Takemura and Mr. Ozawa share Mr. Hosokawa's commitment to cleaning up the electoral system and removing some of the layers of regulation that control the economy. But Mr. Takemura believes in consensus-building and gradual change. Mr. Ozawa, the strongman of the coalition's second-largest party, favors a faster pace and thus has long been seen as a closer ally of the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Takemura has hinted that the small party he heads might quit the coalition if he is dropped; the Socialists, the coalition's largest party, also oppose a Cabinet shuffle.</p>
        <p>Even if the disputed shuffle does not take place, it is clear that Mr. Takemura and his moderate policies have fallen out of favor.</p>
        <p>Up to now, the split between Mr. Takemura and Mr. Ozawa has left the Government careering on key issues, leaving all sides fuming.</p>
        <p>For instance, early this month Mr. Hosokawa announced a $140 billion stimulus package to lift the economy out of its recession. It included a three-year income-tax reduction and then a large increase in the sales tax to cover the loss in revenue.</p>
        <p>The tax proposal, which had been pushed by Mr. Ozawa, brought down a storm of protest and Mr. Hosokawa withdrew it the next day.</p>
        <p>Not long afterward, Mr. Hosokawa again took Mr. Ozawa's advice and backed a union of most of the parties in his coalition to create a counterweight to the Liberal Democratic Party, which the coalition ousted last summer after it had held power for 38 years.</p>
        <p>But the idea of a two-party system -- a central tenet of Mr. Ozawa's philosophy -- contradicted Mr. Hosokawa's pledge to maintain a multi-party system, which Mr. Takemura supports.</p>
        <p>If there has been a motif in Mr. Hosokawa's decisions, it has been to side with the conservative bureaucrats he had vowed to override. Whether the issue was taxes, trade negotiations or deregulation, Mr. Hosokawa has hewed to the demands of the ministries.</p>
        <p>"Hosokawa has been relying completely on the bureaucrats," said Takashi Inoguchi, a political scientist at Tokyo University. "It is doubtful that will change."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
