<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rates Climb on Report Of Inflation Pressures</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2DF123AF931A35750C0A962958260" item-length="571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rates Climb on Report Of Inflation Pressures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Interest rates climbed to their highest level in almost a year yesterday as investors sold on economic data that bore evidence of inflationary pressures building in the economy.</p>
        <p>The selloff came after the National Association of Purchasing Management reported that its price index climbed in February to its highest point since 1990. The report rekindled speculation that the Federal Reserve would move again on short-term interest rates as it did on Feb. 4.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Interest rates climbed to their highest level in almost a year yesterday as investors sold on economic data that bore evidence of inflationary pressures building in the economy.</p>
        <p>The selloff came after the National Association of Purchasing Management reported that its price index climbed in February to its highest point since 1990. The report rekindled speculation that the Federal Reserve would move again on short-term interest rates as it did on Feb. 4.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond fell 115/32 , to 935/16 . Its yield, which moves in the opposite direction from price, rose to 6.77 percent, from 6.65 percent on Monday, and was the highest since June 1993. For bondholders, that meant a loss of $12.31 for every $1,000 bond.</p>
        <p>Short maturities also came under pressure yesterday. The three-month Treasury bill rate rose 9 basis points, to 3.49 percent, the highest since July 1992. A basis point is one-hundredth of a percentage point.</p>
        <p>Although traders and analysts attributed the selloff to the purchasing management report, many thought the market's reaction was overdone.</p>
        <p>"The N.A.P.M. index shows only the market's direction of prices, not how far they are going," said Joseph Liro, chief economist at S. G. Warburg Securities in New York. "But the market is reacting to them as if they are hugely higher." Positions Examined</p>
        <p>Larry Daly, senior vice president and senior portfolio manager for the Global Investment Trust for Putnam Investments, said the market might be approaching an oversold position.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daly who saw just as much weakness in the overseas markets for Treasury bonds yesterday, said people were re-evaluating their positions in the markets after having misinterpreted the amount of tightening needed to ease market concern about inflation.</p>
        <p>"Not happy with the size of the Fed's last interest rate hike, the market is now wondering if instead the Fed shouldn't have made a larger move," he said. "Their concern is that small moves will only lag behind the market, instead of getting ahead of it."</p>
        <p>Joseph V. Battipaglia, managing director of Sterling Advisors, a division of Gruntal &amp; Company, said low interest rates were more of a crutch than market watchers had believed. "So when the reasons for low rates are removed, it creates enormous volatility and each bit of news raises concern," he said. Another Increase Seen</p>
        <p>Mr. Battipaglia said comments by Robert Parry, president of the San Francisco Federal Reserve Bank, left little doubt that there would be another increase in short-term rates. Mr. Parry said it was unlikely that one step was going to be enough, and "that added some fuel to the fire," Mr. Battipaglia said.</p>
        <p>The next closely watched economic report, February unemployment, is scheduled to be released on Friday.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that any tightening by the Fed will now be an admission that inflation is an immediate problem, and would prompt another selloff.</p>
        <p>But Donald Fine, chief market analyst at Chase Securities, does not see inflation as a threat yet. "The Fed's job is to prevent any potential overheating of the economy that will produce inflationary pressures in 1995 and 1996," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fine said that if the central bank continued to move in increments of a quarter-point, it might not be enough to curb inflation. He expects the Fed will increase the Federal funds rate to 3.50 percent from 3.25 in the near future.  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
