<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memorable Atlanta Debut for Manning</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BASKETBALL ASSN (NBA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE123AF931A35750C0A962958260" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memorable Atlanta Debut for Manning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hawks 102, Timberwolves 99</p>
        <p>Danny Manning, in his home debut for the Atlanta Hawks, hit a 12-foot jumper with 8 seconds left last night, salvaging a 102-99 victory over the Minnesota Timberwolves, who had mounted an impressive rally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hawks 102, Timberwolves 99</p>
        <p>Danny Manning, in his home debut for the Atlanta Hawks, hit a 12-foot jumper with 8 seconds left last night, salvaging a 102-99 victory over the Minnesota Timberwolves, who had mounted an impressive rally.</p>
        <p>The Hawks, who led by 28 points in the third period, still had a 94-69 advantage going into the final quarter, but Chuck Person's 3-pointer with 28 seconds left closed the Timberwolves to 100-99. The Hawks then worked the ball to Manning for the game-saving shot.</p>
        <p>"Kevin Willis swung the ball around and I was open," Manning said. "I just turned around and shot it.</p>
        <p>"It's a win, but it's a frustrating win," he continued. "You don't like to win like that. We should have beaten these guys by a big margin. Leads in this league slip away because we're dealing with the best group of basketball players in the world. We cannot afford to be passive with a big lead."</p>
        <p>Manning, traded from the Los Angeles Clippers last week for the popular Dominique Wilkins, received scattered boos when he was introduced to The Omni crowd Friday night, when he did not play. But there were no jeers last night as he made 8 of 13 shots and finished with 21 points. Pacers 106, Blazers 94</p>
        <p>The Portland Trail Blazers had a six-game winning streak snapped and lost their radio analyst in the process -- he was ejected by a referee.</p>
        <p>Rik Smits had 24 points and 13 rebounds, his fifth straight game with double figures in both, as the Indiana Pacers, playing in Indianapolis, topped the Blazers.</p>
        <p>Reggie Miller scored 20 points for the Pacers, who have won 3 straight games, 7 in a row at home and 13 of 15 over all.</p>
        <p>Indiana took control in a wild third quarter when the Blazers were called for two technical fouls and had their radio analyst, Mike Rice, ejected from press row by Referee Steve Javie.</p>
        <p>The Pacers wiped out Portland's last lead, 51-50, with a 10-0 run that included a technical on Cliff Robinson, who objected when a foul call on Dale Davis was changed to a blocked shot. Rice was then ejected after complaining to Javie.</p>
        <p>Rice is in his fourth season as a Blazers analyst and is a former coach at Duquesne and Youngstown State.</p>
        <p>The Pacers put together an 8-0 run late in the period, which ended with Indiana ahead 81-70. During that run, Portland Coach Rick Adelman complained about a foul on Clyde Drexler against Miller.</p>
        <p>Adelman was hit with a technical, and Miller made all three free throws.</p>
        <p>"It's a grand example of a guy losing control," Adelman said of Javie. "He has kicked out mascots, color men, fans. I guess they can do what they want, and we can't do anything." Rockets 97, Magic 85</p>
        <p>Hakeem Olajuwon scored 26 points and Sam Cassell had all of his 16 points in the second half as Houston held off visiting Orlando and snapped the Magic's seven-game winning streak. Cassell didn't score a basket until 1:19 remained in the third quarter but still equaled his season high. SuperSonics 112, Hornets 96</p>
        <p>Seattle's starting backcourt of Kendall Gill and Gary Payton broke loose in the second half and finished with 21 and 20 points, and the SuperSonics came on strong in the fourth quarter to defeat visiting Charlotte. The Sonics, who have the N.B.A.'s best record at 40-14, are 22-3 at home. Washington 109, Philadelphia 103</p>
        <p>Pervis Ellison posted season highs of 25 points and 12 rebounds as the Washington Bullets beat the 76ers in Philadelphia and snapped a six-game losing streak. Clarence Weatherspoon had 26 points and 14 rebounds for Philadelphia, which suffered its 10th straight loss. Heat 110, Bucks 102</p>
        <p>Glen Rice scored 25 points, including 16 in the first quarter, and Grant Long had a season-high 22 as the Miami Heat went five games over the .500 mark for the first time in franchise history with a victory at Milwaukee.  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
