<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nicaraguan Lawmakers Meet In Effort to Break Deadlock</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">NICARAGUA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DA1E30F935A15752C0A962958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nicaraguan Lawmakers Meet In Effort to Break Deadlock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MANAGUA, Nicaragua, Jan. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicaragua's rival political factions attended the National Assembly together for the first time in 16 months today as the country's leaders tried to end a bitter deadlock that has contributed to the country's political instability.</p>
        <p>Today, 90 of the 92 legislators discussed a measure to revise the national labor code. But for now the fact that the session was held at all may be far more important than any bill the Assembly approves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicaragua's rival political factions attended the National Assembly together for the first time in 16 months today as the country's leaders tried to end a bitter deadlock that has contributed to the country's political instability.</p>
        <p>Today, 90 of the 92 legislators discussed a measure to revise the national labor code. But for now the fact that the session was held at all may be far more important than any bill the Assembly approves.</p>
        <p>The country's political leaders have been unable to agree on many of the basics of how Nicaragua should remake itself after the 1990 elections, when the leftist Sandinista Government lost to a center-right coalition led by Violeta Barrios de Chamorro. Attacks From Right and Left</p>
        <p>The National Assembly stopped functioning in 1992, when leaders of the conservative parties that helped bring Mrs. Chamorro to power quarreled with her and then accused her aides of bribing legislators. The conservatives refused to attend legislative sessions unless the members they accused of having been bought off were removed from office. The Chamorro Government also came under attack from the left, which has retained control of the army and much of the Civil Service.</p>
        <p>For the last 16 months, as one group or another boycotted the Assembly, it seldom met, or met with only the barest quorum.</p>
        <p>While the politicians bickered, former soldiers of the Sandinista Government and former contras, members of the rebel army that fought against the Sandinistas in the 1980's, complained that Government promises of land and financial aid were not being met.</p>
        <p>Some took up arms again and seized control of many rural areas. Last July a group briefly seized Esteli, Nicaragua's fourth-largest city.  Officials Taken Hostage</p>
        <p>In August former contras took more than 80 officials and soldiers hostage to press demands for political changes. In response, former soldiers took the leadership of the conservative political parties hostage. Both incidents were resolved without bloodshed but only because the Government gave the groups amnesty, further undermining its authority.</p>
        <p>Diplomats say the country's political leaders have realized that the public will not tolerate further disorder. "These politicians looked back over the last year of chaos and realized they could look ahead to even worse if they didn't grow up and stop fighting among themselves," a diplomat said.</p>
        <p>"When the politicians squabble in Managua, that costs lives in the mountains," he said. "But when the politicians and the important social sectors try to find consensus, and another way to solve matters, that takes away the space for political violence all over the country."</p>
        <p>The President of the National Assembly, Luis Humberto Guzman, said that the legislature and President Chamorro could work together to make the country more attractive to business and that the first goal was to reduce unemployment and underemployment, now estimated to be about 50 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
