<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Schools Reopen, With Safety Lesson</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE EARTHQUAKE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTHQUAKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DA1E30F935A15752C0A962958260" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Schools Reopen, With Safety Lesson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON,</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shaken by earthquake destruction that has deepened chronic financial woes, the Los Angeles public school system limped back into session today, but many schools remained without water and scores of others were too damaged to open at all.</p>
        <p>Even where classes did resume, lessons on math, chemistry and language arts were displaced by a single subject: the Jan. 17 earthquake. Faculty and students conducted earthquake drills, crawling under desks at the sound of clanging bells, and psyhologists were dispatched to some schools to help students deal with the disaster. Many teachers urged pupils to describe the terrors of the past week as therapy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shaken by earthquake destruction that has deepened chronic financial woes, the Los Angeles public school system limped back into session today, but many schools remained without water and scores of others were too damaged to open at all.</p>
        <p>Even where classes did resume, lessons on math, chemistry and language arts were displaced by a single subject: the Jan. 17 earthquake. Faculty and students conducted earthquake drills, crawling under desks at the sound of clanging bells, and psyhologists were dispatched to some schools to help students deal with the disaster. Many teachers urged pupils to describe the terrors of the past week as therapy.</p>
        <p>"We saw them carrying people out of the wrecked houses and the people were all broken," said Terrell Hodge, a 5-year-old kindergarten student at Plummer Elementary School in the San Fernando Valley.</p>
        <p>At Birmingham High School in the Van Nuys section, Claudia Cespedes, a 17-year-old senior, was more bouyant. "We're back!" she told the school's principal as she and more than 2,500 other students streamed onto the schoolyard. "We lived through it."</p>
        <p>The resumption of classes after a six-day shutdown of the nation's second-largest system came as a Federal official said the damage to schools appeared higher than in any previous disaster in the country. The Board of Education has estimated structural damage to the city's 835 schools at $700 million.</p>
        <p>Dennis Kwaitkowski, Deputy Associate Director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, called that a "good working figure." In contrast, the Dade County school system in Florida suffered about $80 million in damages in Hurricane Andrew, Mr. Kwaitkowski said.</p>
        <p>Sidney A. Thompson, superintendent of the Los Angeles Unified School District, said classes resumed in 759 of the city's 835 schools, although attendance was well below normal. Many of the 65,000 students enrolled in the 76 schools that failed to open, which include six high schools, may return to classes later this week, Mr. Thompson said. The total enrollment in city schools is 641,000.</p>
        <p>At 17 junior and senior high schools, the reopening was complicated by the presence of Red Cross shelters on their campuses for 7,500 people made homeless by the quake.</p>
        <p>At Birmingham High School that meant cancellation of physical education classes because a Red Cross tent had been pitched in an athletic field and two gymnasiums were jammed with cots. And the school's 12-member kitchen staff, in addition to cooking for students, turned out breakfast, lunch and dinner for 700 homeless people. Damaged Schools in Valley</p>
        <p>The school system sprawls across more than 700 square miles and includes all or part of 28 cities. All but a handful of the most heavily damaged schools were scattered across the San Fernando Valley in the northern part of the city and suburbs. The epicenter of the quake was in the valley, where it ruined school boilers, cracked thousands of pipes, buckled hundreds of floors, and knocked scores of buildings off their foundations.</p>
        <p>Worried that tap water was contaminated, officials at some schools advised students to bring bottled water.</p>
        <p>The quake was a terrible blow to a system already reeling from overcrowding and cost-cutting measures, and educators expressed concern about how the recovery from the quake damage would be financed. The system's accounts are so shaky that teachers accepted a 10 percent pay cut last year to help close a $400 million gap in the $3.8 billion budget.</p>
        <p>Seeking to quiet the concerns of parents and teachers, the president of the Board of Education, Leticia Quezada, said later at a news conference that James Lee Witt, head of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, had committed his agency to pay for the full amount of the estimated $700 million in damages.</p>
        <p>Gov. Pete Wilson of California last week requested in a letter to President Clinton that the agency make an exception to its normal procedures of paying for 75 percent of disaster damage and pay for 100 percent of the damage to Los Angeles public buildings.</p>
        <p>In Washington today, however, the White House announced that it would pay for 90 percent of the damage to the school buildings.</p>
        <p>Helen F. Bernstein, the president of United Teachers, Los Angeles, the teachers' union, said Federal aid for the Los Angeles schools had already begun to arrive. The aid included a $10 million grant from the Department of Education that would be used, among other things, to maintain teaching staffs at pre-earthquake levels, even if school attendance dropped. Under California law that would normally result in immediate teacher layoffs. Some Students Camped Out</p>
        <p>Only about one-third of the 1,000 students at the Plummer Elementary School in the Sepulveda neighborhood showed up for classes, said Dolores J. Soll, the principal. Hundreds of other students, their homes destroyed, were camped out with their families in public shelters, Ms. Soll said.</p>
        <p>Many teachers themselves suffered losses in the earthquake, and some recounted harrowing stories today of crawling out of collapsed buildings the morning of the quake.</p>
        <p>"Many of us are earthquake victims ourselves, so we're dealing with a double whammy -- damage to our homes and damage to our schools," said Beverly Goldman, office manager at Lassen Elementary School in Sepulveda.</p>
        <p>One hour into classes at Plummer, as at most schools across the city, an earthquake siren shrieked.</p>
        <p>"Drop!" shouted Silvia Osorio, a first grade teacher, to her 12 students, and they dove beneath their desks for an emergency drill.</p>
        <p>Earlier, in a nearby classroom, Cheryl J. Feldman urged her kindergarten students to describe their experiences over the past week.</p>
        <p>But Elizabeth Gonzalez, a 7-year-old girl waiting in a line for classes to begin, wanted to talk about the future instead. "There'll be another earthquake," she said. "We're still waiting for the big one."</p>
        <p>THE EARTHQUAKE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
