<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pirro &amp; Pirro, a Partnership Of Love, Power and Distrust</title>
    <meta content="29marriage" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/29/nyregion/29marriage.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1793508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pirro, Jeanine</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DF1730F93AA1575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pirro &amp; Pirro, a Partnership Of Love, Power and Distrust</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pirro &amp; Pirro, a Partnership of Power and Distrust</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON and MIKE McINTIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To hear Jeanine F. Pirro's supporters tell it, she is a wronged woman leg-shackled to a loser, an ambitious and effective wife brought low by her badly behaved husband, Albert.</p>
        <p>Now her fears about his philandering have set off a federal investigation into possible eavesdropping and have threatened to derail her quest to become New York attorney general.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pirros are not only a couple, but political and financial partners with intertwined fates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To hear Jeanine F. Pirro's supporters tell it, she is a wronged woman leg-shackled to a loser, an ambitious and effective wife brought low by her badly behaved husband, Albert.</p>
        <p>Now her fears about his philandering have set off a federal investigation into possible eavesdropping and have threatened to derail her quest to become New York attorney general.</p>
        <p>But to many people who have been watching the couple for decades, the Pirros look a lot like an echo of that other Westchester power couple, the Clintons, who are also political and financial partners whose fates and fortunes are profoundly intertwined. The Pirros live in Rye, the Clintons in Chappaqua.</p>
        <p>When it comes to the Pirros, ''There's no question they are partners, there's no question it's a symbiotic relationship,'' said Murray Richman, a Bronx defense lawyer who knows both of the Pirros. ''There's no question Jeanine would never be where she is without Al.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pirro, 59, a lawyer and lobbyist, has provided money and political contacts for his wife's career and has financed their way of life: the fancy cars, the expensive houses, the pampered pot-bellied pigs. Her campaigns have been heavily financed by his business associates in Westchester, where he has a hand in many real estate projects. She, in turn, reflected her glamour and political power onto him.</p>
        <p>''Picture those two as the celebrities, the royalty, the power brokers in Westchester,'' said Bennett L. Gershman, a former prosecutor and professor of law at Pace University who has been a frequent critic of Ms. Pirro, 55.</p>
        <p>The Pirros' relationship has often come with a cost to Ms. Pirro, starting two decades ago when she dropped her bid for lieutenant governor in the face of questions about her husband's ties to a company in the garbage-hauling business, an activity that was often linked to the mob. (At the time, she said Mr. Pirro was not comfortable revealing his clients.)</p>
        <p>During Mr. Pirro's 2000 trial on charges of tax evasion, it became clear that she had benefited from his largess. But prosecutors said they were not accusing her of knowing that her husband improperly deducted as business expenses items ranging from her two-seater Mercedes to a $135 gold mirror. More recently, mobsters were caught on tape claiming that Mr. Pirro had tipped them off to an investigation conducted by the Westchester district attorney's office when Ms. Pirro ran it, a claim he denied.</p>
        <p>Ms. Pirro's loyalty to her husband has confounded those inside and outside the political world, and this week she hinted at why she stood by her man. At a news conference on Wednesday, she confirmed that she had talked to Bernard B. Kerik, the former New York police commissioner who is now a security consultant, about planting a listening device on her husband's boat. But she said no taping was done, and claimed that federal investigators looking into the matter were conducting a ''political witch hunt.''</p>
        <p>Then she said she was tired of having to justify her relationship with her husband. He is a ''great father'' to their children, she said -- a teenage son and a daughter in college. ''These are personal choices that I have made, and I shouldn't have to keep explaining them.''</p>
        <p>But earlier in her career, she was happy to talk about Mr. Pirro, whom she once described as ''the most exciting person I knew: quick, bright, always doing, very much an activist.''</p>
        <p>Jeanine and Albert Pirro met at Albany Law School, and were married in 1975, the year she graduated. She went to work in the Westchester district attorney's office, eventually becoming head of its domestic violence unit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pirro, meanwhile, became one of the leading real estate lawyers in Westchester, representing developers of offices, garages, malls and movie theaters. He represented Donald J. Trump in his effort to buy an island off New Rochelle in Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>Raising money for Republicans like George E. Pataki, Mr. Pirro became ''the consummate political insider,'' in the words of Michael R. Edelman, a lawyer and Republican political commentator who has been a friend of the Pirros for three decades.</p>
        <p>From her very first serious race -- for judge in 1990 -- Mr. Pirro used his connections to help his wife, according to a 1997 interview. That year, Mr. Pirro was under investigation for paying $5,000 to a Republican ward leader in Yonkers while he was seeking approvals for a theater complex there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pirro said the money was not a bribe but payment for a consulting arrangement that he initiated in order to gain inroads into the Republican establishment in Yonkers, where Ms. Pirro was largely unknown.</p>
        <p>''What occurs is that we start to build a relationship in Yonkers,'' Mr. Pirro said, ''which is not atypical in a political power move.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pirro was never charged in connection with the payment, which was investigated by the same federal prosecutor, Elliott B. Jacobson, who Ms. Pirro said is involved in the current investigation of her dealings with Mr. Kerik.</p>
        <p>Over the years, as Ms. Pirro's stature within the Republican Party grew, she developed a solid fund-raising base of her own and could reliably attract contributions from an array of companies and wealthy individuals, many of them her neighbors in Westchester.</p>
        <p>Still, some of her largest contributors continue to be her husband's clients and business associates, who collectively have contributed tens of thousands of dollars to her campaigns.</p>
        <p>Louis Cappelli, a longtime lobbying client and business partner of Mr. Pirro's, gave $25,000 to her campaign for attorney general in July and $4,200 to her Senate campaign last year. Mr. Cappelli is a developer who, most recently, retained Mr. Pirro to assist with a project to develop a Catskills resort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cappelli's wife, Kylie Travis, gave $33,900 to Ms. Pirro's main campaign committee in March, and an additional $10,800 to two other committees related to her endorsement by the Conservative and Independence Parties, state campaign finance records show.</p>
        <p>Another of Mr. Pirro's business associates, Louis L. Ceruzzi, a Connecticut developer, has given $33,900 to Ms. Pirro's attorney general campaign. Mr. Ceruzzi and people associated with his company gave $31,500 to her Senate race. Mr. Ceruzzi builds stores for Home Depot, a client of Mr. Pirro's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cappelli declined to comment, and Mr. Ceruzzi did not return a message left at his office.</p>
        <p>In 1993, Ms. Pirro was elected district attorney in Westchester, and her star continued to rise. Noted for her snappy suits and stiletto heels, she became a regular on television shows -- Geraldo Rivera, ''Nightline,'' Court TV -- commenting on cases from O. J. Simpson to Martha Stewart. In 1997, People magazine named her one of its ''50 Most Beautiful People.''</p>
        <p>In her personal life, there was trouble when DNA tests proved that Mr. Pirro had fathered a child with another woman while the Pirros were married.</p>
        <p>Yet in terms of bad publicity, probably nothing compared to Mr. Pirro's tax evasion case. In 1998, the Pirros paid close to $1 million in back taxes, but Mr. Pirro was indicted the following year, basically for billing personal expenses to his businesses and taking tax deductions on them.</p>
        <p>Among the purchases were a portrait of the Pirro children commissioned by Ms. Pirro, the set for her cable television show when she was a judge, furniture for their vacation home in West Palm Beach, Fla., and drivers and maids (in uniforms) to tend to the children, the wine cellar and the family's pet pot-bellied pigs.</p>
        <p>In June 2000, a jury convicted Mr. Pirro on 34 counts of conspiracy, tax evasion andfiling false returns. His brother, Anthony, an accountant, was also convicted. Albert Pirro served 11 months in federal prison.</p>
        <p>While some people suggest that Mr. Pirro remained a formidable force in Westchester even after he got out of jail, others are not so sure. Mr. Edelman, the Republican lawyer, said Mr. Pirro is ''out of the loop, not fund-raising, can't pull strings, doesn't have clout.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, he is mostly famous these days for accumulating speeding tickets. William O'Shaughnessy, who owns two radio stations in New Rochelle and is friendly with both of the Pirros, said: ''I think she loves him, and the feeling is mutual. These episodes are a cri de coeur. He's saying, 'Jeanine, don't forget me!' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
