<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>W's Mean Wins, Not Wow, For the Improving Giants</title>
    <meta content="17giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1797864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEFD91E30F934A25753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>W's Mean Wins, Not Wow, For the Improving Giants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN BRANCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Branch, John</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A victory adds one more tally under the column marked W. But not every victory is the same.</p>
        <p>Under Tom Coughlin, now in his third season coaching the Giants, the team have steadily improved, and for the second year in a row, it is included in conversations about the N.F.L.'s postseason possibilities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A victory adds one more tally under the column marked W. But not every victory is the same.</p>
        <p>Under Tom Coughlin, now in his third season coaching the Giants, the team have steadily improved, and for the second year in a row, it is included in conversations about the N.F.L.'s postseason possibilities.</p>
        <p>But one type of victory has eluded them, even during last season's 11-5 division-title march and during this season's 3-2 start: a defining game, a ''statement'' game, against a championship-caliber foe, particularly on the road. The Giants, for all their successes, have not had a result that forces others to take notice, or to say, ''Wow, the Giants beat those guys?''</p>
        <p>Beating the Falcons in Atlanta on Sunday might have been the biggest road victory for the rebuilt Giants of Coughlin's tenure.</p>
        <p>The Falcons had a 3-1 record and gaudy rushing and rush-defense statistics, the veneer of a contender. After the Giants won, 27-14, the Falcons suddenly seemed flawed -- one-dimensional on offense and not sturdy enough on defense.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think Atlanta was a very good football team,'' Giants receiver Plaxico Burress said. ''Out of all the teams that we've played, they were probably the worst team. I don't think any of us in there were surprised with us winning.''</p>
        <p>It is unlikely that any of the Giants would similarly downgrade the status of their next opponent. The Giants play the Cowboys (3-2) at Dallas on Monday night.</p>
        <p>It is the type of game that the Giants have not conquered. They have made a habit, particularly on the road, of beating the league's weaker teams and falling, sometimes admirably and in overtime, to the stronger ones.</p>
        <p>In 2005, the Giants were 4-4 on the road. The victories -- against San Francisco, Oakland, Philadelphia and New Orleans -- were against teams that did not finish better than 6-10. The game against the Saints, while officially an away game, was actually played at Giants Stadium, moved from the Superdome after Hurricane Katrina.</p>
        <p>Last season's road losses were against teams that finished 9-7 or better: San Diego, Dallas, Seattle and Washington.</p>
        <p>''Our philosophy is always, win all of them at home and try to steal some on the road,'' quarterback Eli Manning said. ''Because it's tough playing on the road, and when you're playing a tough team, it's even harder.''</p>
        <p>The question is not so much whether the Giants need to beat championship contenders in the regular season to boost themselves in the standings. Beating middling teams and losing to most of the top teams is often enough to make the playoffs, as the Giants demonstrated last season, when they lost to Carolina in the first round.</p>
        <p>The question, rather, is whether the Giants need to do it to prove to themselves, and others, that they are capable of such a trick.</p>
        <p>The Giants opened the season at home against the Indianapolis Colts, a perennial title contender and a worthy measuring stick. The Giants lost, 26-21.</p>
        <p>They then played miserably for three quarters in Philadelphia before scoring 23 points in the fourth quarter and overtime to beat the Eagles, a team that has since won three of four games, making the Giants' victory look better in hindsight than it did at the time.</p>
        <p>The Giants lost badly to the Seahawks in Seattle the next week. After a dominating home victory against the Washington Redskins, they beat the Falcons by overcoming another double-digit second-half deficit on the road, as they did against the Eagles.</p>
        <p>The Giants are carrying a feeling of confidence and a two-game winning streak that appeared improbable two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''Some games feel different,'' Manning said. ''You know you've done something -- you've kind of conquered a challenge, maybe a greater challenge playing on the road against a good team rather than some games. Everybody felt good after yesterday's game.''</p>
        <p>A victory against the Cowboys, a fierce division rival led by the former Giants coach Bill Parcells, would make the team feel even better. N.F.L. players often say that playing on a Monday night provides extra motivation, because it offers a chance to impress friends and family around the country.</p>
        <p>''You may say to some of the younger guys, 'All of your aunts and uncles, everybody, is watching,' and that may perk them up,'' Coughlin said.</p>
        <p>But among the millions watching are other N.F.L. players and coaches, taking a rare opportunity to watch another team's football game as it unfolds.</p>
        <p>The Giants want to win, of course; the standings matter most. Sending a message would be a side benefit, whether the message is delivered live on a Monday night or in a meeting room during the week.</p>
        <p>''You know what really is on that tape, that's what other people are watching,'' center Shaun O'Hara said. ''The tape doesn't lie. When people turn on that tape, you want them to see the type of play that you're playing, and the physical aspect of it -- that you're really bringing it to the other team. That's what you want to show them.''</p>
        <p>Against a top-level opponent, on a prime-time stage, the Giants have another chance to show themselves.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Linebacker Antonio Pierce took exception to a postgame comment by Falcons quarterback Michael Vick, who said the Giants used a ''vanilla'' defense to slow the league's top rushing team. ''We were vanilla -- vanilla with seven sacks and a win,'' Pierce said. ''It's good enough for us.''  The Giants' players have two days off; they will resume practicing Thursday.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
