<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Video Game Link Is Seen For Nintendo</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIDEO GAMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JOINT VENTURES AND CONSORTIUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTER CHIPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NINTENDO OF AMERICA INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SILICON GRAPHICS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD113EF932A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Video Game Link Is Seen For Nintendo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nintendo of America Inc. and Silicon Graphics Inc. will announce Monday that they are collaborating on a new generation of video game players, people close to the companies said today.</p>
        <p>Neither company would comment, but they have scheduled a joint news conference for Monday morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nintendo of America Inc. and Silicon Graphics Inc. will announce Monday that they are collaborating on a new generation of video game players, people close to the companies said today.</p>
        <p>Neither company would comment, but they have scheduled a joint news conference for Monday morning.</p>
        <p>The new-generation players would incorporate a version of the MIPS microprocessor used in Silicon Graphics work stations, which would allow photo-realistic images and high speed. Silicon Graphics machines are used to produce special effects in films, including the dinosaurs in Steven Spielberg's "Jurassic Park." Significantly Lower Cost</p>
        <p>A computer industry official said MIPS, a subsidiary of Silicon Graphics, had developed a version of its R4000 processor that operated on less than one-half watt and could be produced for about $40 each. This is a significant drop from previously announced versions of the chip, which have aimed at a target cost of $80 to $200 and power consumption of 1.5 to 2 watts. MIPS, which has no production capability of its own, is said to have decided that Toshiba will manufacture the chip.</p>
        <p>"The mere fact of a business relationship there is significant because of Nintendo's phenomenal ability to drive volume," said Michael Slater, publisher of The Microprocessor Report, an industry newsletter. "If it works at all, it could bring MIPS to levels of volume they never dreamed of," he said. He noted that the Sony Corporation had also discussed using the MIPS chip in consumer products.</p>
        <p>Mr. Slater emphasized that a game player using the MIPS chip would not offer the graphics performance of a Silicon Graphics work station.</p>
        <p>"There's a huge amount of expensive stuff in an S.G.I. machine that is not part of the processor," he said. "You are not going to get the performance of a $10,000 work station in a $700 video game." Competition for 3DO</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, a Nintendo machine incorporating Silicon Graphics technology would create formidable competition for the 3DO Corporation and its $700 Multiplayer, which is intended for video games and other forms of interactive multimedia. Corporate partners of 3DO include A.T.&amp; T. and Time Warner Inc. Shares of 3DO plunged today in Nasdaq trading, closing $4 lower at $26 after falling as much as $5 during the day.</p>
        <p>Shares of Silicon Graphics rose $1.875 each, to $38.50, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>The new machine could also be a way for Nintendo to catch up with its archrival, the Sega Corporation, which has captured the dominant market share in video game players using 16-bit microprocessors. The MIPS microprocessor is a 32-bit chip, meaning it processes data in chunks twice as large as those processed by the chip in Sega's Genesis machine, and four times that of earlier 8-bit video games. MIPS also incorporates RISC, or reduced-instruction set computing, which speeds operation.</p>
        <p>"It's about time Nintendo tried to play some leapfrog," said Mark Stahlman, president of New Media Associates, a multimedia consulting firm based in New York.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
