<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stun-Gun Reality, Magnificent In Its Artifice</title>
    <meta content="02KIMM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/02/arts/02KIMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1274697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Modern Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gursky, Andreas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Shanghai</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Germany</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Düsseldorf</location>
        <location class="online_producer">essen</location>
        <org class="online_producer">uses</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Church</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ruff, Thomas</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schmidt, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Adams, Robert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wall, Jeff</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDD163BF931A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stun-Gun Reality, Magnificent In Its Artifice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman reviews Andreas Gursky's photographs at Museum of Modern Art; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANDREAS GURSKY'S giant photographs are so eye-poppingly gorgeous that in this world, where no good turn goes unpunished, even admirers feel compelled to react with suspicion and reserve. Anything so seductive, so automatically appealing to collectors, so skillfully altered via computer, as some of Mr. Gursky's photographs are to enhance their cinematic irresistibility, must be at least untrustworthy.</p>
        <p>Have you ever seen -- and I don't mean in reproduction -- Mr. Gursky's photographs, say, of the trading floor of the Chicago Board of Trade? Or of hotel lobbies in Shanghai and Times Square? Or of a highway overpass in the Ruhr Valley with a solitary man wandering beneath it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANDREAS GURSKY'S giant photographs are so eye-poppingly gorgeous that in this world, where no good turn goes unpunished, even admirers feel compelled to react with suspicion and reserve. Anything so seductive, so automatically appealing to collectors, so skillfully altered via computer, as some of Mr. Gursky's photographs are to enhance their cinematic irresistibility, must be at least untrustworthy.</p>
        <p>Have you ever seen -- and I don't mean in reproduction -- Mr. Gursky's photographs, say, of the trading floor of the Chicago Board of Trade? Or of hotel lobbies in Shanghai and Times Square? Or of a highway overpass in the Ruhr Valley with a solitary man wandering beneath it?</p>
        <p>You would remember if you had. Knee-jerk resistance at the sight of these nondescript global emblems of new capitalist sprawl is instantly short-circuited by sheer awe at the incredible, sublimely weird, almost erotic glamour he imparts to them. The ultimate compliment to any exhibition is to say that the rest of the world looks different after you leave the show. That's certainly the case with Mr. Gursky's midcareer overview, which opens on Sunday at the Museum of Modern Art. The world suddenly becomes drab by comparison. Drab and tiny.</p>
        <p>Monumental size and stupendous saturated color are part, but only part, of the work's instant allure. Mr. Gursky is not just making fancy, digitally enhanced blowups of photographs you might see in annual reports, although he is, among other things, exploiting the formulas of those corporate advertisements at the same time that he intends us to think about Romantic painting and postwar American abstract art. We are meant to register illusion, then allusion.</p>
        <p>That said, even when the pictures are straight and unaltered, they look too good to be true. Their ambition and fetishized magnificence dispense with the concept that photographs need to tell the truth in the first place, as if truth were ever a thing as simple as whatever appeared in a viewfinder. Mr. Gursky steers photography toward his own private fiction, which, like all genuine art, needs to be true only to itself.</p>
        <p>Taken on such terms, the pictures expose a strangely persistent fallacy: that altered photographs are different from paintings or sculptures or drawings as objects of art. It's an idea that must finally be put to rest in the 21st century. All art involves manipulation, after all -- manipulations of color, perspective, scale, whatever -- which becomes the measure of its ingenuity and content. Mr. Gursky's art demands that we regard it likewise and not get hung up by the pyrotechnical mechanics, although the work eagerly exploits technology whenever necessary. That's a pretty good general definition for art in the digital age, by the way.</p>
        <p>Consider the hallucinatory curves of Mr. Gursky's towering photograph of the hotel in Shanghai, a computer-enhanced image that makes a seamless bending grid out of several shots of the same banal interior from different spots. What matters is not the process by which it was concocted but the glowing amber color and Minimalist perfection of the result: potent geometry supersedes the ostensible subject of the photograph, which is anonymous modern architecture.</p>
        <p>Anonymous architecture, not coincidentally, is also the subject of the work of Mr. Gursky's famous teachers, Bernd and Hilla Becher. The Bechers started taking their quasi-archaeological black-and-white photographs of gas tanks, cooling towers and other unpromising industrial sites in Germany about 40 years ago. Back then a few artists paid attention, but the work barely caused a stir in public. Then in the 70's it was adopted by advocates of the new Minimal and Conceptual Art.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the art world, like the rest of the world, works in the most peculiar ways. Having never particularly imagined themselves as Minimalists or Conceptualists, but more as documentarians, the Bechers became art stars, and aspiring cutting-edge photographers started to emulate their cool, deadpan, severely restricted, technically methodical aesthetic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gursky became their student in Düsseldorf in the 1980's. The art market was beginning to boom. Like his fellow Becher disciples Thomas Struth and Thomas Ruff, he profited almost immediately from the art world's fascination with whatever was coming out of the Bechers' studio and with new German art in general.</p>
        <p>One virtue of the present exhibition is to put this chapter of Mr. Gursky's development in context. Peter Galassi, the show's curator, has done the essential homework and in the catalog writes perceptively about the Bechers' influence on Mr. Gursky but also about other figures, too often ignored, who shaped German art and photography during the last quarter of the century.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gursky, he points out, was the son of a commercial photographer from whom he first learned to take pictures, and for a while during the 1970's he carried around a Leica, making snapshots on the street. Cartier-Bresson was an obvious model. But German and American photographers like Michael Schmidt, Robert Adams and Nicholas Nixon were at the same time putting aside their Leicas in favor of more cumbersome tripods to make deliberate, unembellished pictures of ordinary places. The Bechers were not alone in that respect.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gursky was alert to what was going on, the lessons of which he gradually assimilated.</p>
        <p>In the late 70's, before studying with the Bechers, he was also a student in Essen, where Otto Steinert had established the leading school of traditional art photography, the antithesis of the Bechers' style. By the early 80's he had absorbed the significance of the backlighted color panoramas of the Canadian photographer Jeff Wall, whose art frankly aspired to the status of old master painting, and he began to draw for inspiration on the color photographs of Americans like Stephen Shore and Joel Sternfeld.</p>
        <p>So he was looking at various things. And during the early 90's he became especially enamored of the work of Gerhard Richter, the painter, whose meditations on the conventions of Romanticism and Abstract Expressionism and also on photography set the gold standard for conceptual brilliance and icy elegance, the ultimate postmodern stance. Mr. Gursky's photographs of paintings by Pollock and Constable and a picture he took of an all-gray carpet clearly allude to Mr. Richter's work, a little too slavishly. A work like ''Aletsch Glacier,'' with its cold, moody grandeur, its metallic water and stormy sky, is a much more successful, less banal photograph but also pays homage to Mr. Richter unabashedly.</p>
        <p>''Gursky's world'' is the phrase Mr. Galassi uses to encapsulate the mix of ideas, sources and ambitions beneath the boffo surface of Mr. Gursky's varied extravaganzas. ''Documentary realism versus digital manipulation, modernist idealism versus postmodern skepticism, high art versus commerce, conceptual rigor versus spontaneous observation, photography versus painting,'' Mr. Galassi writes. ''These and other antagonisms have engendered some fierce battles, but for Gursky they are all givens -- not opponents but companions.''</p>
        <p>Simply put, the work wants to knock you off your feet, then tries to make you respect what hit you. But none of the intellectual pretense behind it matters except to help rationalize the art's elusive aura, which should speak for itself. To say that the picture of the overpass in the Ruhr brings to mind the work of Caspar David Friedrich, everyone's favorite art historical source for Mr. Gursky's work, is useful only to the extent that it describes how certain clichés of sublime nature are ironically adapted to an image of contemporary industry -- with predictably offbeat results. But cheap picture postcards are as much the source in that case, and add equally to the sense of oddness.</p>
        <p>It's worth noting that Mr. Gursky mostly avoids pictures of people alone, like the man beneath the overpass. He is not a psychologist of individuals. He prefers crowds, which become blurs of color and form, the forms sweeping across the photographs like brushed fur. They are interchangeable with piles of pastel cargo containers at a dock in Salerno, or the multicolored windows of a vast apartment complex at Montparnasse, or Nikes lined up like trophies on digitally enhanced shelves with a digitally invented reflection below them -- shoes that contrary to all reasoned thought look as desirable and otherworldly as anything you might imagine the second you see them. The images all draw you close in, the way you get drawn to the surface of an intricate painting, to take in the details and increase the ravishment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gursky's least successful work, like his brand new diptych of corporate executives from various companies at annual shareholder meetings, a hokey montage with flat-footed Minimalist pretense, ratchets up the technical gadgetry until it becomes the subject of the art, an uninteresting result. When there's magic it entails traditional formal satisfaction.</p>
        <p>Will these pictures seem as astonishing to a future generation accustomed to spiffier technologies? Paintings that looked magical to people a century ago -- by Bierstadt or Church or Moran -- look less magical now.</p>
        <p>But prognosticating is a fool's job. We only know that, to our eyes, Mr. Gursky's art is instantly attractive to the point of alarm, which is the feeling of falling in love. I suggest you give yourself over to it and worry about the consequences later.</p>
        <p>''Andreas Gursky'' opens on Sunday at the Museum of Modern Art, 11 West 53rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 708-9400, and runs through May 15.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
