<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tone It Down, He Urged Hemingway</title>
    <meta content="19KAKU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BOOKS OF THE TIMES" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="890684"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hemingway, Ernest (1899-1961)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perkins, Maxwell (1884-1947)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruccoli, Matthew J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Only Thing That Counts, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E3D9133AF93AA25752C1A960958260" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tone It Down, He Urged Hemingway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews book The Only Thing That Counts: The Ernest Hemingway-Maxwell Perkins Correspondence, edited by Matthew J Bruccoli; photo of Hemingway and Perkins in Key West in 1935 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ONLY THING THAT COUNTS  The Ernest Hemingway-Maxwell Perkins Correspondence  Edited by Matthew J. Bruccoli  Illustrated. 367 pages. Scribner. $35.</p>
        <p>Theirs was one of the most celebrated professional alliances in the history of publishing: one was America's most high-profile writer and purveyor of macho pursuits; the other was America's best-loved editor, the midwife to some of the most glittering achievements of a literary generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ONLY THING THAT COUNTS  The Ernest Hemingway-Maxwell Perkins Correspondence  Edited by Matthew J. Bruccoli  Illustrated. 367 pages. Scribner. $35.</p>
        <p>Theirs was one of the most celebrated professional alliances in the history of publishing: one was America's most high-profile writer and purveyor of macho pursuits; the other was America's best-loved editor, the midwife to some of the most glittering achievements of a literary generation.</p>
        <p>Although ''The Only Thing That Counts: The Ernest Hemingway-Maxwell Perkins Correspondence'' offers the reader a few new insights into their day-to-day relationship, the volume, for the most part, is a disappointment. The pair's most illuminating letters have already been quoted at length in A. Scott Berg's excellent 1978 biography of Perkins. The other letters gathered in this volume by the scholar Matthew J. Bruccoli tend to deal with mundane exchanges about money, advertising and editorial disputes -- the sort of forgettable exchanges that would routinely be dealt with today in a perfunctory telephone conversation.</p>
        <p>Perkins's letters are largely businesslike disquisitions on the problems of censorship and critics, or responses to Hemingway's complaints about money and the lack of ads for his books. Hemingway's letters, which often seem to have been dashed off at the end of the day, display little of the galvanic style that animated his early (and finest) fiction; they range from self-important pronouncements about the nature of writing to explosive diatribes against perceived enemies and rivals. There are very few discussions of his works in progress aside from progress reports on pages written and deadlines met.</p>
        <p>As expected, Perkins emerges as a patient, long-suffering editor serving as a sort of combination father figure, father confessor and cheerleader for his temperamental writer. Hemingway, on his part, comes across as the familiar self-dramatizing blowhard: alternately insecure and boastful, bullying and paranoid, a needy and demanding assignment for any editor, much less one also coping with the problems of Thomas Wolfe and F. Scott Fitzgerald.</p>
        <p>Perkins's relationship with Hemingway began in 1924, when Fitzgerald told him about a young American in Paris, a writer with a ''brilliant future'' -- ''the real thing.'' Although Hemingway's first book of stories, ''In Our Time,'' was already promised to another publishing house, he soon began a decades-long relationship with Perkins (and Perkins's employer, Charles Scribner's Sons) with his next two books, ''The Torrents of Spring'' and ''The Sun Also Rises.''</p>
        <p>This was exactly the sort of relationship Perkins cherished. As he wrote in a 1930 letter: ''The great interest in publishing is to take on an author at the start, or reasonably near it, and then to publish not this book and that, but the whole author.''</p>
        <p>Whereas Perkins's relationship with Wolfe was highly collaborative (helping him not only to cut but also  organize his books), his role with Hemingway was more advisory and supportive: he did not rewrite or revise, nor did he line edit. Judging from these letters, one of Perkins's chief duties seems to have been persuading Hemingway to tone down potentially offensive language. His argument, repeated again and again, is that it would be a shame if ''the very significance of so original a book should be disregarded because of the howls of a lot of cheap, prurient, moronic yappers.''</p>
        <p>Although Hemingway complains about this ''emasculation'' of his prose, he usually goes along with Perkins's suggestions; he does not succeed in spelling out the four-letter word for sexual intercourse until 1937 with ''To Have and Have Not.''</p>
        <p>Because this volume is very poorly annotated, because we see only Perkins's suggestions to Hemingway and not his arguments on behalf of the author to his editorial colleagues, he tends to come across as a far more cautious and conservative editor than he in fact was. The lack of useful footnotes and a more fully fleshed-out introduction also makes it difficult for the reader to put other relationships and developments into context. We get no sense of how Hemingway achieved his early chiseled style or why that style gradually devolved into a parody of itself; we also get no sense of why he grew increasingly belligerent and pugnacious or how Perkins felt about this development.</p>
        <p>What we do get are a lot of put-downs by Hemingway of other writers, friends and critics -- put-downs that comprise what are by far the liveliest passages in this volume. Of Edmund Wilson, he writes: ''His criticism is like reading second-rate gospels written by someone who is out on parole. He reads most interestingly on all the things one does not know about. On the things one knows about truly he is stupid, inaccurate, uninformative and pretentious.''</p>
        <p>And of Gertrude Stein: ''She lost all sense of taste when she had the menopause. Was really an extraordinary business. Suddenly she couldn't tell a good picture from a bad one, a good writer from a bad one, it all went phtt.''</p>
        <p>The writer who most fiercely engages Hemingway's attention -- and elicits the most sustained paternalism and scorn -- is Fitzgerald, whom he never seems to have forgiven for his early encouragement and help. ''He has taken a series of incidents,'' Hemingway writes, ''good incidents from his life and used them quite arbitrarily, made the story conform to the few wows he had saved up out of his life.'' And later in the same letter: ''The trouble is that he wouldn't learn his trade and he won't be honest. He is always the brilliant young gentleman writer, fallen gentleman writer, gent in the gutter, gent ruined, but never a man.''</p>
        <p>Fitzgerald's idea of literature, he adds, is nothing but a bunch of old ''worn Christmas tree ornaments.''</p>
        <p>As for Hemingway's own notions about writing, they are laid out, aphoristically, in passages that seem meant to be clipped and quoted. Among his apercus: ''Should always write as though you were going to die at the end of the book''; ''The first and final thing you have to do in this world is last in it and not be smashed by it and your work the same way''; ''there is a time in every man's life, if he is worth a damn, when he has to be unpopular,'' and ''writing is a hard business Max but nothing makes you feel better.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Hemingway seems to have been unable to believe in (or live by) his own homilies. He committed suicide on July 2, 1961. His ''most trusted friend'' and editor, Max Perkins, had died of pneumonia 14 years before.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
