<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Church Panel to Investigate Sexual Abuse Charges</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="558173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD ABUSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIESTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHICAGO (ILL)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERNARDIN, JOSEPH (CARDINAL)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DE153CF931A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Church Panel to Investigate Sexual Abuse Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph Cardinal Bernardin, the Archbishop of Chicago, named a nine-member board yesterday to investigate all future charges of sexual abuse of minors by priests in the nation's second-largest diocese.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Bernardin said the independent board, which will have a majority of lay members, was the main feature of new policies intended to rid the diocese of sexual misconduct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joseph Cardinal Bernardin, the Archbishop of Chicago, named a nine-member board yesterday to investigate all future charges of sexual abuse of minors by priests in the nation's second-largest diocese.</p>
        <p>Cardinal Bernardin said the independent board, which will have a majority of lay members, was the main feature of new policies intended to rid the diocese of sexual misconduct.</p>
        <p>"While I cannot change the past, I can do something about the future," the Cardinal said at a news conference in Chicago. "I accept the clinical data which suggest that once it has been demonstrated that a priest is an abuser, he should never again return to parish ministry or any ministry which might place a child at risk."</p>
        <p>The changes were recommended by a special commission that Cardinal Bernardin appointed a year ago to review the archdiocese's procedures for handling accusations of sexual abuse. The commission also reviewed the personnel files of 2,252 priests who had served in the Chicago archdiocese since 1963 and concluded that complaints of sexual abuse against 39 were well founded.  Where Accused Priest Went</p>
        <p>When Cardinal Bernardin made the commission's report public on June 15, all but eight of those priests had already resigned, retired or died. Cardinal Bernardin said yesterday that the remaining eight priests had either resigned or been reassigned to non-parish duties.</p>
        <p>In making the appointments, Cardinal Bernardin also named a "victim-abuse minister," who will head a team providing psychological and pastoral aid to abused minors, their families or others affected.</p>
        <p>Under the new policies, the archdiocese will publicize a 24-hour, toll-free telephone number to receive reports of sexual abuse by the clergy. Psychological screening of seminarians and courses in sexual development will be improved, the Cardinal said. Psychological profiles of new priests will be kept and periodically updated.</p>
        <p>The new board will hire a full-time administrator and support staff to conduct an immediate investigation quickly enough to allow the board to make a preliminary decision on removing a priest within 48 hours of receiving a complaint. The board will have the power to remove an accused priest until a complete report is made to the church authorities.</p>
        <p>As recommended by the special commission, none of the lay board members named today are church employees. Composition of the Board</p>
        <p>They include a social worker, a clinical psychologist, a psychiatrist and a computer programmer. Virginia Martinez, a lawyer named to the board, was identified as a "survivor of child sexual abuse." Three priests will also serve on the board.</p>
        <p>The Chicago commission's work has been closely watched by other church leaders. Cardinal Bernardin has called the new policies the most comprehensive in the United States.</p>
        <p>"There are other dioceses that have done some good things," he said in a telephone interview later. "But to my knowledge we are the only one with an independent board."</p>
        <p>Cardinal Bernardin appointed the special commission after fresh charges of sexual abuse were made against a Chicago priest reassigned to a parish despite previous such accusations. Many Catholic dioceses have been accused of being naive or lax in investigating such charges, allowing priests to continue their abusive behavior by simply reassigning them.</p>
        <p>Most cases now in the courts involve allegations that were made before the 1980's. But critics of church practices, led by several Catholic priests, have urged that to restore public credibility, investigations of complaints against priests and decisions about removing them from their posts should no longer be left in the hands of other priests and church officials.</p>
        <p>Recently Cardinal Bernardin clashed with the Cook County State's Attorney, Jack O'Malley, who said the church had not reported 14 of the cases it acknowledged in June. Mr. O'Malley, who is up for re-election, has himself been accused of laxness in pursuing complaints against priests.</p>
        <p>Turning over some but not all information on these cases, Cardinal Bernardin replied that complete reporting would would violate attorney-client privilege and the confidentiality of medical records and pastoral counseling. Yesterday he said that every allegation the new board considered worthy of investigation would be reported.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Ex-Priest Is Arrested</p>
        <p>NEW BEDFORD, Mass., Sept. 21 (AP) -- A former Roman Catholic priest accused of molesting scores of children more than 20 years ago was arrested today in Minnesota on Massachusetts charges of sexual assault, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The former priest, James R. Porter, was taken into custody in his hometown of Oakdale, Minn., said the Washington County sheriff's department in Minnesota. An extradition hearing is scheduled for Tuesday.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for some of Mr. Porter's accusers, Roderick MacLeish Jr., said prosecutors in Bristol County, which includes New Bedford, where Mr. Porter once served as a priest, indicted Mr. Porter on 46 sexual abuse counts involving 32 people. Although Mr. Porter is accused in incidents that occurred decades ago, experts say he can still be prosecuted in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter left the priesthood in the early 1970's and now is married and has four children. He said this summer that he had molested "a number of children" while he was a priest, but stopped after leaving the priesthood.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
