<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fischer So Far: Ups, Downs and Ups</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="558249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISCHER, BOBBY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPASSKY, BORIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA1F30F931A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="682" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fischer So Far: Ups, Downs and Ups</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT BYRNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BYRNE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the first half of Bobby Fischer's exhibition chess match with Boris Spassky in Sveti Stevan, Yugoslavia, there is still no definitive answer to the question that has been in the background from the start: Can the American genius play top-flight chess despite a 20-year layoff from public competition?</p>
        <p>Fischer is winning the $5 million series by 5-2, with 4 draws, which don't count; 10 victories are needed to win the match. But the quality of his play is not marvelous, as it was when he won the world championship in Iceland in the summer of 1972. Probably no one expected it to be. But how should it be assessed?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the first half of Bobby Fischer's exhibition chess match with Boris Spassky in Sveti Stevan, Yugoslavia, there is still no definitive answer to the question that has been in the background from the start: Can the American genius play top-flight chess despite a 20-year layoff from public competition?</p>
        <p>Fischer is winning the $5 million series by 5-2, with 4 draws, which don't count; 10 victories are needed to win the match. But the quality of his play is not marvelous, as it was when he won the world championship in Iceland in the summer of 1972. Probably no one expected it to be. But how should it be assessed?</p>
        <p>One is inclined to say up and down -- some of the legendary creativity alternating with almost a paralysis of thought -- but getting more and more up as the match goes on.</p>
        <p>Maxim Dlugy, an Englewood, N.J., grandmaster and president of the United States Chess Federation, has discussed the match with the world champion, Gary Kasparov. Yesterday, Dlugy gave this assessment: "Spassky is playing a lemon every game. Kasparov told me, 'Spassky's lack of strength is making the match a joke.' But Bobby is playing quite well, on a level to be included in the top 50 players in the world."</p>
        <p>Overall, nonetheless, Fischer's play has been spotty. As Dlugy added, "Off and on, Bobby shows a loss of perception of what to do."</p>
        <p>That was eminently true in Game 4, where Fischer could not organize a defense for his position and marched in circles to disaster. Game 5, which he also lost, was similar. But there are the other games, particularly the victories in Games 1, 7, 9 and 11, about which Dlugy said, "They are reminiscent of Bobby's straightforward logic of years ago."</p>
        <p>The best of them show the old pointed clarity, and Fischer still has the courage to believe in himself. One of his strongest talents was his capacity to produce innovations in tactics and strategy, and this can be glimpsed in the present contest.</p>
        <p>Yet the old merciless, clean-cut Fischer technique that made mincemeat of opponent after opponent is sometimes in evidence, as in Game 7, and sometimes not, as in Game 2, which he should have won routinely. Errors by Both Players</p>
        <p>He never used to let his alertness flag, but in the fourth game, Fischer got so wrapped up in planning his own strategy that he grievously discounted a potent sacrifice by which Spassky fired up a winning counterattack. Also in the fourth game, Fischer failed under pressure to work out the clever combinations that would have saved a draw. This would not have happened 20 years ago. Still, in the seventh game, when Spassky, who had been playing strongly, rushed his attack, Fischer sharply punched holes in it and won.</p>
        <p>In Game 8, both players misanalyzed a complex position, but Spassky made the last mistake and Fischer woke up to punish him for it and win.</p>
        <p>In Game 9, Fischer showed some of the profound inventiveness that distinguished his play years ago. In his favorite opening, he produced an incisive nuance that Spassky could not cope with and won all the more easily when his unnerved opponent offered little resistance in the endgame. This was vintage Fischer.</p>
        <p>In Game 11, Fischer innovated brilliantly with a new gambit to throw Spassky on the defensive. The game followed a scintillating course of slash and riposte until Spassky could stand the pace no longer and went down to defeat. An impressive battle.</p>
        <p>Thus, as the games go by and Fischer gets back into practice, he grows stronger. If he sustains the pattern and wins by a heavy margin, he might be ready to challenge a current hotshot like Anatoly Karpov of Russia, Nigel Short of England, Jan Timman of the Netherlands, Vasily Ivanchuk of Ukraine or Viswanathan Anand of India.</p>
        <p>And what about Kasparov? Ask again at the end of the match.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Play to Resume Next Week</p>
        <p>SVETI STEVAN, Yugoslavia, Sept. 21 (AP) -- Match organizers said today that the 12th game between Fischer and Spassky would start either Sept. 30 or Oct. 3. The exact date will be determined later, they said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
