<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Twin Is a Goal Scorer While the Other Twin Is Cut</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="666560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1994)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESKENAZI, GERALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERRARO, CHRIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERRARO, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D91139F937A35751C0A962958260" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Twin Is a Goal Scorer While the Other Twin Is Cut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ESKENAZI, GERALD</byline>
      <dateline>ROUEN, France, Feb. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Ferraro swiped at the puck and scored tonight, clinching a 5-3 Team USA exhibition victory over Norway. Not far away, as he had done a thousand times since the time they were practically toddlers on Long Island, his twin brother, Chris, cheered.</p>
        <p>But Chris was not on the ice or the bench tonight as Peter scored with 22 seconds remaining.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Ferraro swiped at the puck and scored tonight, clinching a 5-3 Team USA exhibition victory over Norway. Not far away, as he had done a thousand times since the time they were practically toddlers on Long Island, his twin brother, Chris, cheered.</p>
        <p>But Chris was not on the ice or the bench tonight as Peter scored with 22 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>For the first time in their lives, the 22-year-old Ferraro twins are not on the same team. Bumped by Drury</p>
        <p>Quietly, with no formal announcement, Coach Tim Taylor dropped Chris a few days ago, virtually on the eve of the Olympics. The Americans will start their Olympic odyssey on Feb. 13.</p>
        <p>"We talk about it," said Peter. "The fact he can't be with us and experience the whole Olympic thing."</p>
        <p>Chris is traveling with the club and could return if injuries strike. He became expendable when Ted Drury, who had been playing with Calgary until he injured his knee, was ready to join the Olympic squad.</p>
        <p>Chris would not say much about the situation, only a grunted "yeah" when asked whether he was upset.</p>
        <p>That was obviously the frame of mind back in Sound Beach, not far from Port Jefferson, L.I.</p>
        <p>Reached at the family sporting goods store, Plaza Surf and Sports, their father, Peter, said today: "I'm not making any comment. Call their agent." But he also said: "Sometimes, it's better to say nothing. I'm happy to have a son on the Olympic team. It would be nice to have two."</p>
        <p>According to Chris's twin brother, though, the boys telephoned their parents last weekend when they learned of the move.</p>
        <p>"It was an emotional and disappointing talk," Peter said.</p>
        <p>Since then, the pair have talked about what happened quite often.</p>
        <p>"I just told him not to get down, and to use what happened as motivation," said Peter, the Rangers' No. 1 draft pick of 1992. The Rangers chose Chris fourth.</p>
        <p>The forwards have played together in prep school hockey, junior hockey and in international junior competition, as well as last year at the University of Maine. Chris was tied for the Olympic team assist lead with his brother and Todd Marchant at 34. Peter is second in goals to Marchant with 27. Their mother, Diane, left the family business to follow them to school in Massachusetts and to junior hockey in Iowa, living near them to feed them meals and do their laundry. Illness Hurt</p>
        <p>The longest the brothers ever were separated was early on this tour, when Chris was sidelined with mononucleosis for three weeks. That, Peter suggested tonight, set back his progress on the team.</p>
        <p>"I talked to Peter after I made the cut," said Taylor. "It's probably very tough on him, but sooner or later, they're not going to go through life joined at the hip." SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The victory over Norway was produced with GARTH SNOW in goal. He yielded a quick two goals when the Americans were short-handed. But the comeback, even against the lightly regarded Norwegians, was important coming at the start of their final European exhibition schedule. They play the Swedish B team Friday and France -- against whom they open the Olympics -- on Saturday. MIKE DUNHAM will start Friday. But Coach TIM TAYLOR said he had not decided on the starter against France, and he may even split time between the two goalies on Saturday.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
