<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Struggling Wall St. Is Loath to Cut Jobs</title>
    <meta content="26WALL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/26/business/26WALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1328320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: WALL STREET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lehman Brothers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Wall Street (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moszkowski, Guy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDC133AF935A1575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Struggling Wall St. Is Loath to Cut Jobs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Struggling Wall St. Is Loath to Cut Jobs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysts and recruiters say another round of cost-cutting and layoffs on Wall Street is inevitable, but most firms are reluctant to make cuts immediately for fear of seeming heartless; some big investment banks insist that they will not dismiss people before end of year, choosing instead to dilute pain by paying employees significantly smaller year-end bonuses and making stock and options more important component of those shrunken pay packages; pattern on Wall Street is to start preparing senior investment bankers for their bonuses to be only 40 to 60 percent as big as they were last year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wall Street, the burning question is not if, but when.</p>
        <p>In an industry that was suffering through a long slump even before the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center, another round of cost-cutting and layoffs is inevitable, analysts and recruiters said. But most firms are holding off, reluctant to make the cuts immediately for fear of seeming heartless.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an industry that was suffering through a long slump even before the attack on the World Trade Center, another round of layoffs is inevitable, analysts and recruiters said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Wall Street, the burning question is not if, but when.</p>
        <p>In an industry that was suffering through a long slump even before the Sept. 11 attack on the World Trade Center, another round of cost-cutting and layoffs is inevitable, analysts and recruiters said. But most firms are holding off, reluctant to make the cuts immediately for fear of seeming heartless.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some big investment banks like Lehman Brothers are insisting that they will not dismiss people before the end of the year, choosing instead to dilute the pain by paying employees significantly smaller year-end bonuses and making stock and options a more important component of those shrunken pay packages. Something has to give because Lehman has increased its staff by 17 percent this year but has 10 percent less to pay them.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley -- where the staff has grown about 3 percent, to 62,000 workers -- faces a similar problem. So far this year, the amount the firm has paid its employees or set aside to pay them at year-end is $8 billion, down $1.2 billion, or about $20,000 per employee, from the first nine months of last year.</p>
        <p>A few firms, said Frank Fernandez, chief economist of the Securities Industry Association, might announce some job cuts as soon as this week. But the more common pattern on Wall Street is to start preparing senior investment bankers for their bonuses to be only 40 to 60 percent as big as they were last year.</p>
        <p>''The overwhelming majority of C.E.O.'s will cut bonuses rather than fire people at this point,'' Mr. Fernandez said. ''The last thing anybody wants to do right now is hand out pink slips.''</p>
        <p>But that does not mean that all layoffs have been postponed indefinitely. Several people inside or close to Wall Street firms said they had expected Bear, Stearns to announce job cuts in September as part of a yearlong cost-cutting campaign and that it was now weighing when it might be appropriate to proceed. A spokeswoman for Bear, Stearns, which is scheduled to report third-quarter earnings today, said yesterday that she could not confirm or deny those reports.</p>
        <p>J. P. Morgan Chase was another firm that delayed laying off people over the last two weeks, but was preparing to press ahead this week, according to a person close to the firm. The company said in the early summer that it would cut about 3,000 more jobs on top of the 5,000 that were lost in the merger of J. P. Morgan and the Chase Manhattan Corporation. A spokeswoman declined to comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>''Many of the cutbacks firms had intended to execute in September were put on hold,'' said Joan Zimmerman, a partner in the executive search firm G. Z. Stephens, ''not because they think market conditions will improve, but because there is such a heightened concern about employee morale. We are convinced, however, that they will occur before fiscal year-end.'' For most Wall Street firms, the fiscal year ends on Nov. 30.</p>
        <p>In New York City alone, employment in the financial industry peaked at about 200,000 jobs last year, according to the Securities Industry Association. That number had slipped to about 185,000 by April and Mr. Fernandez said securities firms had announced more than 12,000 layoffs before the attacks that still had not shown up in the figures.</p>
        <p>As those previously announced layoffs resume, they are likely to dilute some of the concerns about the inappropriateness of announcing new job cuts so soon after a catastrophe, recruiters said. So, employment in the industry is almost certain to trend downward into next year.</p>
        <p>''It's almost a game of cat-and-mouse or wait-and-see,'' said Amy Butte, an analyst at Bear, Stearns. ''Nobody wants to go first.''</p>
        <p>Before Sept. 11, Ms. Butte had expected firms to cut as much as 10 percent of their jobs in the last few months of the year. Now, she said, the timing is harder to predict because of what she called ''the sympathy effect.''</p>
        <p>Most big securities firms still need to shrink parts of their operations to adjust to a bleaker outlook for the financial markets that drive their businesses.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's got to reset for an environment that's less robust,'' said Peter Davis, a consultant with the Cambridge Group in Manhattan. ''This is a very difficult decision to make -- whether you cut people before the end of this year.''</p>
        <p>Nearly every Wall Street firm grew fat during the boom years of the late 1990's. They hired too many people, Mr. Davis said, paid them too much and promoted them too fast. ''Everything floated up and so everything's got to float down,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As cold as it may sound, he said, managers on Wall Street have an unusual opportunity to revamp their businesses after the disaster. In an industry where people have been trained to measure their contribution, and, to a large degree, their self-worth, by the size of their bonus checks, managers now must try to foster loyalty amid sacrifice.</p>
        <p>''People had already been preparing everyone for more stock, less cash and lower bonuses over all,'' Mr. Davis said. ''Does that engender a bit more team play? Maybe it does.''</p>
        <p>Team play had become a fading concept on Wall Street in the 1990's as most brokerage firms and investment banks evolved from partnerships into public companies and, in some cases, into global conglomerates. Executives and employees on Wall Street now own smaller stakes in their firms and often must answer to big shareholders and the financial analysts who represent them.</p>
        <p>''It would have been a sharing of the smaller meal at the table,'' said John Gutfreund, who in the 1980's ran Salomon Brothers, which is now part of Citigroup. In similar downturns in the past, he said, ''we would pay ourselves less, and less to our employees.''</p>
        <p>But today's Wall Street executives must consider eliminating jobs as soon as it is clear that revenue is not likely to rebound soon. Most firms have promised investors minimum returns and they have already fallen below them. For example, Morgan Stanley reported a 15 percent return on equity last quarter, down from 28 percent a year before.</p>
        <p>Stephen Crawford, Morgan Stanley's chief financial officer, said last week that ''the outlook for the short term has turned decidedly negative.'' Merger activity and stock underwriting, two engines of the firm's profits, remain subdued, he said.</p>
        <p>Still, he declined to discuss the need to cut jobs. Morgan Stanley had 3,500 employees working at the World Trade Center, and the firm had to find space for them in its backup center on Varick Street in SoHo and in other buildings in Manhattan. Mr. Crawford estimated the cost of the displacement at about $150 million.</p>
        <p>David Goldfarb, chief financial officer of Lehman Brothers, said unequivocally that his firm would not reduce employment this year.</p>
        <p>''People understand in our culture that they get paid based on performance,'' Mr. Goldfarb said. Lehman's profit fell 32 percent last quarter and the outlook is ''cautiously negative,'' he said. ''Just because of a potential couple of quarters of a slowdown, we're not going to retrench.''</p>
        <p>Guy Moszkowski, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said ''The environment is precarious enough that it's going to be very hard to avoid another round or two of downsizing over the next couple of months.'' But, he added, ''the only thing that's really clear is that overall amounts of compensation have to be much, much lower than they were last year.''</p>
        <p>One other thing is certain, said a high-ranking official at a major investment bank. ''After all we've been through this year,'' he said, ''nobody is going to have patience for anybody whining about their bonus.''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: WALL STREET</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
