<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Yale, Honors for an Acting Chief</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SETON HALL UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">YESHIVA UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDD1E3AF936A15756C0A965958260" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Yale, Honors for an Acting Chief</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Howard R. Lamar, who served as acting president of Yale University over the last year and was generally seen as a stabilizing force on campus, conferred degrees yesterday on 1,219 undergraduates and about 2,000 graduate and professional students at the university's 292d commencement exercises in New Haven. Mr. Lamar, who will hand over his powers on July 1 to Richard C. Levin, now dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, received an honorary degree of doctor of laws.</p>
        <p>A poignant moment in the proceedings came when an honorary degree of doctor of humane letters was announced for Arthur R. Ashe Jr., the tennis champion who died of AIDS. The degree was accepted by Alexandra Dell, a junior at Yale who was Mr. Ashe's goddaughter. The graduates stood in tribute to Mr. Ashe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Howard R. Lamar, who served as acting president of Yale University over the last year and was generally seen as a stabilizing force on campus, conferred degrees yesterday on 1,219 undergraduates and about 2,000 graduate and professional students at the university's 292d commencement exercises in New Haven. Mr. Lamar, who will hand over his powers on July 1 to Richard C. Levin, now dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, received an honorary degree of doctor of laws.</p>
        <p>A poignant moment in the proceedings came when an honorary degree of doctor of humane letters was announced for Arthur R. Ashe Jr., the tennis champion who died of AIDS. The degree was accepted by Alexandra Dell, a junior at Yale who was Mr. Ashe's goddaughter. The graduates stood in tribute to Mr. Ashe.</p>
        <p>Among others receiving honorary degrees were Elena G. Bonner, the Soviet dissident and widow of Andrei Sakharov, the human rights activist; Rembert G. Weakland, Roman Catholic Archbishop of Milwaukee and a prominent leader of the church's liberal wing, and Alistair Cooke, journalist, commentator and former host of "Masterpiece Theater."</p>
        <p>In keeping with a Yale tradition of protest, a plane circled the proceedings bearing the message, "Resign Loucks." Some students are upset at Vernon R. Loucks Jr., a Yale trustee who is also chairman and chief executive of Baxter International Inc., a medical products supplier which violated a Federal law against cooperating with the Arab economic boycott of Israel. Mr. Lamar has said he stands behind Mr. Loucks for his service to Yale.</p>
        <p>As is Yale's custom, there was no commencement day speaker. During Class Day ceremonies Sunday, the actress Jodie Foster, who graduated from the university magna cum laude in 1985, urged graduating seniors to "be advocates for people who don't have a voice" and to combat "racism, sexism and homophobia."  Seton Hall University</p>
        <p>Seton Hall University conferred degrees on 1,142 undergraduates and 500 graduates yesterday in ceremonies at Byrne Meadowlands Arena in East Rutherford, N.J.</p>
        <p>Mayor Raymond L. Flynn of Boston gave the main address for the 136th commencement. Mr. Flynn, who has recently been nominated as Ambassador to the Vatican, spoke of the need for a new civil rights movement in America and urged the graduates to get involved in changing society. Mr. Flynn received an honorary degree of doctor of humanitarian service. Yeshiva University</p>
        <p>Dr. Gershon Metzger, director general of Israel's Ministry of Science and Technology, delivered the main address yesterday at the 62d commencement of Yeshiva University. The commencement at Madison Square Garden, attended by 1,111 graduates, was the largest celebrated by the university this year.</p>
        <p>Dr. Metzger spoke of recent political, social, economic and demographic changes throughout the world and said, "There is cause for guarded optimism as you look forward to your future careers."</p>
        <p>Dr. Metzger, an alumnus of Yeshiva, received an honorary degree of doctor of science. Among the others receiving honorary degrees was Chief Judge Judith S. Kaye of the New York State Court of Appeals. Johns Hopkins University</p>
        <p>President Richard von Weizsacker of Germany delivered the main commencement address yesterday at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore. A total of 3,974 degrees were awarded at the school's 117th annual commencement.</p>
        <p>After the main ceremony many of the university's divisions held their own diploma-awarding ceremonies. In an address before graduating seniors, the director Barry Levinson, who was born in Baltimore, talked about the chasm between the unalloyed hope of his generation in the 1960's and the complex problems of today.</p>
        <p>"We were a promising generation," he said. "We had ideals and values. What went wrong is, it's easy to lose what's important today in this constantly cluttered world of media madness. We're told a thousand things we need, and we just get lost."</p>
        <p>Robert S. Strauss, the Ambassador to the Soviet Union under President George Bush, delivered the main address yesterday at commencement ceremonies for the Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies at Johns Hopkins University. The school awarded 259 degrees at its 50th annual commencement, which was held at the First Baptist Church in Washington.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
