<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Minks, Elegantly Simple Furs</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BERNADINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fur</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DE173CF936A15756C0A965958260" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Minks, Elegantly Simple Furs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNADINE MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BERNADINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fur fashion shows actually focus on a woman's second fur coat in tacit acceptance of the fact that the first one is usually a mink. There are plenty of lavish mink coats in most collections, but only a sampling is put on the runway for fear of boring the audience. The second styles in the fall fur showings last week were casual shearlings, sheared beaver or squirrel or luxurious fisher, sable, lynx or chinchilla, depending on whether the customer would be trading up or down.</p>
        <p>Still, there was considerable news in mink. Now that the enormous shoulder pads of the past decade have been relegated to fashion limbo and the structure of most coats has been softened by the elimination of most stiffening and inner construction, even the basic mink has changed its look. Often it is fitted, with just a suggestion of a higher waistline. Gold buttons marching double file down the front contribute to the military look also strong in cloth coats. Ranch-Bred Skins</p>
        <p>The favored skins this season are on the dark side, referred to in the programs as "wild-type mink." This is to reassure viewers and wearers that the furs are from ranch-bred animals, not trapped ones. Prices quoted by various companies for good-quality long coats range from $5,500 to $16,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fur fashion shows actually focus on a woman's second fur coat in tacit acceptance of the fact that the first one is usually a mink. There are plenty of lavish mink coats in most collections, but only a sampling is put on the runway for fear of boring the audience. The second styles in the fall fur showings last week were casual shearlings, sheared beaver or squirrel or luxurious fisher, sable, lynx or chinchilla, depending on whether the customer would be trading up or down.</p>
        <p>Still, there was considerable news in mink. Now that the enormous shoulder pads of the past decade have been relegated to fashion limbo and the structure of most coats has been softened by the elimination of most stiffening and inner construction, even the basic mink has changed its look. Often it is fitted, with just a suggestion of a higher waistline. Gold buttons marching double file down the front contribute to the military look also strong in cloth coats. Ranch-Bred Skins</p>
        <p>The favored skins this season are on the dark side, referred to in the programs as "wild-type mink." This is to reassure viewers and wearers that the furs are from ranch-bred animals, not trapped ones. Prices quoted by various companies for good-quality long coats range from $5,500 to $16,000.</p>
        <p>The lower figure was mentioned by Stuart Greenberg, who recently opened Corniche Furs with Michael Otto. The two, who had worked for other fur houses, believed this was an opportune time to start their own business. "The fur market hit rock bottom two years ago," Mr. Greenberg said, "and we felt we could grow as it came back." Both were delighted to sign up Bob Mackie as their designer. He had become available after HBA Furs, where he had worked, folded last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mackie contributed to the new company's prospects by eschewing decorated, showy, Hollywood-type styles and focusing on simple luxury in mink and sable. His wool coats with sheared nutria linings and his supple shearlings were fashionably correct. Mr. Mackie was also on target with his mink vests in blue, purple, green or red, tossed over white cotton shirts with the shirttails flying over black pants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mackie's show attracted the only demonstration of the week by animal-rights advocates. Protesting in front of 345 Seventh Avenue, in the heart of New York's fur district, the advocates drew a hostile audience of fur workers and did not interfere with the fashion show. Simplified Designs</p>
        <p>Other designers who usually favor more ornate styles turned to simpler designs this season. One of the best coats by Valentino at Alixandre Furs is a dark mink coat shaped like a bathrobe and held by a silk rope belt. The designer likes it best over a white silk blouse with ruffled cuffs and jabot and black pants with ruffled hems.</p>
        <p>Calvin Klein is, of course, fashion's leading minimalist. His sheared beaver coats for Alixandre in stone, putty and vicuna shades express his predilection for casual understatement. With soft shoulders, long hems and a wonderfully casual air, they bond comfortably with his knitted sweaters and pants. For understated luxury, Mr. Klein shows a fisher coat with deep side slits, opulent in a quiet way.</p>
        <p>Alixandre offers another fur collection by Vito Nacci of Italy that expresses the European preference for curvy seams in a mink coat with fitted waist and flaring skirt.</p>
        <p>Birger Christensen also shows a series of collections by different designers. Marc Jacobs attended the presentation of Perry Ellis furs, which reflected the young feeling Mr. Jacobs brought to ready to wear before he left Ellis last fall. The long and short shearlings, tie-dyed velvet jackets with fur collars and cuffs and fuzzy lamb coats were all cutting-edge fashion.</p>
        <p>The Christian Dior line at Christensen includes cashmere coats with sheared mink collars and cuffs, as well as mink and lynx coats. Under the Christensen label, there are shearling coats in three colors (brown, amber and green) and abstract styles patterned in checkerboards and squares. It's a lively way to extend the boundaries of fur fashion.</p>
        <p>The Altamoda collection by Maximilian goes even further, with patchwork effects on fur-trimmed velvet coats and designs suggesting Matisse paintings. The Louis Feraud collection for Maximilian uses a stylized cat face as a recurring motif. Karl Lagerfeld, the reigning king of fur design, makes his biggest impact at Maximilian with cashmere coats luxuriously collared in sable. "They are the greatest for any women in any part of the world," said Kalman Ruttenstein, Bloomingdale's fashion director, expressing the mood of the audience.</p>
        <p>The Anne Klein collection at Goldin Feldman tucked some snappy boleros among its mink and sable coats.</p>
        <p>Andre and Lisa Biseng opened their show for the Tepper collection with quilted cashmere short coats and ended it in a flurry of golden sable. In between, there were coats that reversed from smooth leather to Persian or broadtail lamb, a hooded white mink and a cashmere cape with a chinchilla tuxedo front.</p>
        <p>Jerry Sorbara's squirrel coats in rich shades of blue and purple, his red sheared mink styles and his burgundy beaver coats cast a colorful glow over a collection that included styles for both men and women. In more familiar fur shades like black and gray were Russian broadtail and chinchilla coats. The summer ermine and Russian lynx coats had an exotic look. The Giorgio Sant'Angelo furs designed for Robert Sidney by Jeff Mahshie focused on pale shades like powder blue and violet in mink and fox small fur pieces.</p>
        <p>Despite luxurious offerings, the fur showings were generally low-keyed, staged for retailers and the press rather than private clients. Dennis Basso was the exception, showing his styles to private clients at the Mark Hotel. Other furriers tried to keep a low profile so as not to attract fur protestors, but Mr. Basso believes the cloud is lifting. "People are becoming more rational," he said. Lisa Salomon, one of several hundred women at the show, agreed. "My friends are more relaxed about furs," she said as she settled into her seat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
