<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abandoning All Thoughts Of Heat Waves</title>
    <meta content="10BIG.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/10/nyregion/10BIG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="The Big City"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heat</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tierney, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/John Tierney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Inferno</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1D6153FF933A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abandoning All Thoughts Of Heat Waves</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Abandoning All Thoughts of Heat Waves</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tierney, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Tierney The Big City column finds way to look at New York's heat wave that makes it seem bearable by contrasting it with stories of survival in extraordinary circumstances (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the temperature hit 105 degrees yesterday afternoon inside the Fulton Street subway station, the only sign of rebellion was a discarded silk necktie lying on the platform. The people waiting for a train looked too weak to complain.</p>
        <p>They were resigned, like all who enter there in the summer, to a Dantean experience. The farther you descend, the worse it gets, and by the time you reach your level you are meditating on your sins. Are you being punished for a moral transgression, or is God just irritated at your stupidity in hanging around New York in August?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 105-degree temperature reached on Thursday can be compared to the heat described in Dante's "Inferno.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the temperature hit 105 degrees yesterday afternoon inside the Fulton Street subway station, the only sign of rebellion was a discarded silk necktie lying on the platform. The people waiting for a train looked too weak to complain.</p>
        <p>They were resigned, like all who enter there in the summer, to a Dantean experience. The farther you descend, the worse it gets, and by the time you reach your level you are meditating on your sins. Are you being punished for a moral transgression, or is God just irritated at your stupidity in hanging around New York in August?</p>
        <p>Ordinarily you can endure these moments by thinking of the air-conditioned subway cars, but yesterday's news of power blackouts provided a new complication. What if a blackout hit your train? Is there any torment in America or, for that matter, in Dante's ''Inferno,'' worse than a packed subway car without electricity stuck in a tunnel during a heat wave?</p>
        <p>Maybe, said Joshua Piven, a co-author with David Borgenicht of ''The Worst-Case Scenario Survival Handbook'' and its new sequel devoted to travel. If you drove to work, he said, you could be carjacked and wind up inside your trunk, where the temperature could reach 140 degrees. Still, while that might be hotter than a subway tunnel, at least you wouldn't be rubbing against any large hairy males in tank tops. And as Mr. Piven's book points out, you can escape from many cars' trunks by yanking the cable running from the trunk-release lever to the latch.</p>
        <p>It's physically possible to escape from many stalled subway cars, but it's illegal, as the Metropolitan Transportation Authority vehemently reminded me in 1995 when I wrote about my own flight to freedom. (In a fit of claustrophobia and Type A impatience, I got off and walked several hundred yards underground.) Mr. Piven doesn't recommend escaping either, although his book has a chapter (''How to Survive a Fall Onto Subway Tracks'') explaining how to walk through a tunnel without being run over or electrocuted. After reading the detailed advice, I was not surprised to learn that Mr. Piven is a fellow veteran of subway trekking.</p>
        <p>''I did a fair amount of exploring in the subway tunnels in Philadelphia when I was a teenager,'' Mr. Piven said. ''I wouldn't advise anyone to get off a stalled train, but it's not that hard to walk in a subway tunnel.''</p>
        <p>For an urban claustrophobe, he said, a stalled subway during a blackout wouldn't be as bad as a stalled elevator. ''We were going to have a chapter on escaping from an elevator,'' he said, ''but it seemed pointless once I talked to engineers. The escape hatches on most cars are locked from the outside, and even if you could get out into the hoistway -- that's what they call the elevator shaft -- it would be too dark and dangerous to try to escape.''</p>
        <p>SO what can you do if you're trapped in a sealed elevator during a power blackout in a heat wave? ''Look within yourself and find your happy place,''  Mr. Piven said. ''Think cool thoughts.''</p>
        <p>You might try contemplating Dante's ninth circle of hell, in which the worst sinners of all (traitors) are frozen in ice. For a more specific image, consider the icy problems of Peter Freuchen, a Danish explorer in the Canadian Arctic who faced what may well have been the all-time worst-case scenario.</p>
        <p>In 1923, Freuchen took refuge during a blizzard near Hudson Bay by digging a cave in the snow. He awoke to find the entrance blocked by a snowdrift. (He might have benefited from Mr. Piven's book, which advises building a snow cave at a right angle to the prevailing wind.) He was trapped in a dark space not much bigger than a coffin, with icy walls so hard that he couldn't dig out with his hands. After many desperate hours, he got an idea.</p>
        <p>''I had often seen dog dung in the sled track,'' he wrote, ''and had noticed that it would freeze as solid as a rock. Would not the cold have the same effect on human discharge? Repulsive as the thought was, I decided to try the experiment. I moved my bowels and from the excrement I managed to fashion a chisel-like instrument which I left to freeze.''</p>
        <p>Freuchen used the chisel to escape, but by then the toes on his left foot were frozen, and gangrene set in. Far from doctors and anesthetics, Freuchen used a hammer and pliers to amputate all five toes himself. ''I cannot attempt to describe the physical pain,'' he wrote. ''Perhaps one could get used to cutting off toes, but there were not enough of them to get sufficient practice.''</p>
        <p>Does the heat seem a little more bearable?</p>
        <p>The Big City</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
