<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hobbling Moss Returns to Ask About the Fuss</title>
    <meta content="10JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/10/sports/football/10JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316100"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moss, Santana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Miami (Florida)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">University of Miami</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Moss, Santana</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DE123FF933A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hobbling Moss Returns to Ask About the Fuss</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hobbling Moss Returns to Ask About the Fuss</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets Santana Moss is surprised to find himself at center of attention as he returns from knee surgery; will miss up to 12 weeks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Santana Moss was finishing his wobbly walk to the podium today, his left knee wrapped and in a brace, his metal crutches cast aside, when he wondered, as he eased himself into a chair, ''Why so many pictures?''</p>
        <p>Moss has been amused by the interest in him since he became the Jets' first-round draft pick, but never more so than now. On his first day back with the Jets since the knee surgery that will most likely keep him off the field for 12 weeks, Moss was once again the center of attention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On his first day back with the Jets since the knee surgery that will most likely keep him off the field for 12 weeks, Santana Moss was the center of attention, much to his own amusement</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Santana Moss was finishing his wobbly walk to the podium today, his left knee wrapped and in a brace, his metal crutches cast aside, when he wondered, as he eased himself into a chair, ''Why so many pictures?''</p>
        <p>Moss has been amused by the interest in him since he became the Jets' first-round draft pick, but never more so than now. On his first day back with the Jets since the knee surgery that will most likely keep him off the field for 12 weeks, Moss was once again the center of attention.</p>
        <p>''It caught me by surprise,'' Moss said of the interest in his injury. ''Athletes don't prepare for injuries. It shows your value a little bit.''</p>
        <p>Moss tore cartilage in his knee when he made a cut on a reverse during a practice on the artificial turf at Hofstra Stadium on Aug. 1. It happened so quickly, Moss said, that he did not know exactly when he had hurt his knee until he looked at the film afterward.</p>
        <p>When Moss was injured, the Jets at first thought he might miss only training camp. But after consulting with Moss and the Jets, Dr. John Uribe in Miami decided it was best to repair the cartilage in Moss's knee rather than simply remove it, ensuring better long-term results but also a much longer rehabilitation period.</p>
        <p>Moss decided to go to Uribe because he is the team doctor for the University of Miami, where Moss played college football. Moss said he had agreed with the doctor's decision, after a bit of persuading by Uribe and Moss's parents. Moss said he has since talked to other players who have had knees repaired and has been encouraged because they told him their careers continued for many years.</p>
        <p>''When it comes to careers, you have to think of your longevity first,'' Moss said. ''You think of your life after football. You don't want to come back to that knee later on. That was the best decision to me.</p>
        <p>''I feel like they invested in me to be here. I feel it's my duty to work for them. I'm always wanting to be on the field. I was just saying to myself, 'It's not that bad.' When I heard so many different things -- three to five weeks -- I thought, 'Let's do it.' When I heard later, I thought, 'I'm a rookie, let me go ahead and take care of it.' ''</p>
        <p>Moss has been philosophical about his injury, wondering if it happened at this time for a reason. He said it does not bother him to watch others play when he cannot. Moss has been encouraged by Coach Herman Edwards, who, he said, told him not to worry about the injury and to concentrate on his preparations for when he has recovered.</p>
        <p>Edwards said he was not concerned that Moss's injury could steal the receiver's greatest asset, his speed, or that missing the first half of the season could put him hopelessly behind.</p>
        <p>''We drafted him to be a punt-return guy,'' Edwards said. ''He can wake up at four in the morning and catch punts. He knows how to do that. What he has that others don't have, he can run fast. When guys have things like that, they come back even faster.''</p>
        <p>As Moss maneuvered through a crowd today to get to the players' cafeteria, he received pats on the back from some teammates. He smiled the whole time.</p>
        <p>When Moss arrived in Miami, where Uribe performed the arthroscopic surgery last Saturday, he found himself cheering up his family and friends, rather than the other way around.</p>
        <p>The relentless optimism does not stop there. Moss suspects that his hunger to get back will force him to work so hard in rehabilitation that his left leg will be even stronger than his right leg. He also hopes his layoff will leave him fresher than any other player on the field.</p>
        <p>''This isn't something to mope about,'' Moss said. ''I'm eager to learn. Now I have time to sit down and say, 'This is what I need to know.' The injury is going to be O.K. You have to say, 'This is what I have to get ready for.' I don't have to worry about it all coming to me at once.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets practiced in full pads for two hours Thursday morning, when a thermometer showed that the temperature on the field was 115 degrees in direct sunlight. The team held a 45-minute special-teams practice in the afternoon. . . . Looking to improve their depth at linebacker and shore up their special teams, the Jets re-signed linebacker DWAYNE GORDON, who spent the past four seasons as a reserve before being cut in a salary-cap purge at the start of the free-agency period in March. Gordon was sitting in the office of BILL POLIAN, the Indianapolis Colts' president, when the Jets called on Gordon's cell phone. He played in 15 games last season and started the final game  after BRYAN COX sustained a season-ending injury. Gordon was born in White Plains and raised in upstate New York, so he preferred to return to the Jets, even though he was being pursued by several other teams. ''This is my home,'' Gordon said. ''It's close to my family. It's important to have family and friends support me at games.'' Gordon will not play in the Jets' first preseason game against the Atlanta Falcons Saturday night in Giants Stadium. . . . Defensive tackle JASON FERGUSON saw the orthopedic specialist Dr. JAMES ANDREWS in Alabama on Thursday to get a second opinion on the torn rotator cuff in his right shoulder.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
