<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>One Park, Many Squabbles</title>
    <meta content="25FRON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BROOKLYN WATERFRONT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Piers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Heights (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DA143BF936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>One Park, Many Squabbles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brooklyn community groups squabble over plans for developing park along waterfront near Brooklyn Heights; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The vision is clear: a lush green park along the Brooklyn waterfront. The challenge, as recent developments indicate, is to prevent that goal from drowning in process.</p>
        <p>In December, Borough President Howard Golden and other elected officials proposed the formation of a Brooklyn Waterfront Local Development Corporation that would draft a plan and complete studies to advance the development of Piers 1-5, which lie beneath Brooklyn Heights like atrophied limbs, as a park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The vision is clear: a lush green park along the Brooklyn waterfront. The challenge, as recent developments indicate, is to prevent that goal from drowning in process.</p>
        <p>In December, Borough President Howard Golden and other elected officials proposed the formation of a Brooklyn Waterfront Local Development Corporation that would draft a plan and complete studies to advance the development of Piers 1-5, which lie beneath Brooklyn Heights like atrophied limbs, as a park.</p>
        <p>The corporation will have at its disposal $1 million that State Senator Martin Connor and Assemblywoman Joan Millman obtained in the State Legislature's last session. Eventually, it is to become a public benefit corporation that would obtain title to the piers.</p>
        <p>Contention quickly arose, primarily about the composition of the board. Local elected officials were each to appoint one or two representatives, as were Community Boards 2 and 6, the Brooklyn Heights Association, other neighborhood groups and the Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce. Excluded, however, was the Brooklyn Bridge Park Coalition, a volunteer advocacy group that has agitated nonstop for the development of the piers since 1989. Residents of the Dumbo area (down under the Manhattan Bridge overpass) also had no spot on the board.</p>
        <p>The exclusion of the coalition prompted concern in the Brooklyn Heights Association and elsewhere that elected officials were trying to limit public input. And the notion of a local development corporation had an alarming ring, critics said, since such corporations are usually used for job, not park, creation. Finally, there were limitations on the corporation's mandate: it cannot use its funding to plan for waterfront land between the Brooklyn and Manhattan Bridges that David Walentas, a Manhattan developer, wants to transform into a shopping and entertainment area.</p>
        <p>The coalition and other groups have said the land should be included in a park. When some 300 members of the powerful Brooklyn Heights Association and the Fulton Ferry Landing Association, along with many elected officials, crowded into a church on Jan. 13 to discuss whether the associations should participate in the corporation, the air was tense. Greg Brooks, Mr. Golden's chief of staff, defended the exclusion of the coalition, saying that the organizations that would be most closely affected by waterfront development had been included.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Fisher, the Councilman for Brooklyn Heights, urged the association to support the corporation. The prospect of a park, he said, was ''hanging by a thread.'' The coalition had been excluded, he said, because elected officials ''do not have confidence'' in it right now and because ''it is not accountable to anyone.''</p>
        <p>But by the end of the meeting, he had offered his appointment on the corporation to the coalition's chairman, John H. Watts. The Brooklyn Heights and Fulton Ferry Landing Associations subsequently decided to participate in the corporation, and Mr. Watts accepted Mr. Fisher's offer. The board is to meet in early February.</p>
        <p>AMY WALDMAN</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BROOKLYN WATERFRONT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
