<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Reckless Laws Team Up</title>
    <meta content="25ROSE$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosen, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Paula Corbin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DB123BF936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Reckless Laws Team Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeffrey Rosen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosen, Jeffrey</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeffrey Rosen Op-Ed article traces extraordinary spectacle of President investigated for alleged sexual relationship with White House intern; points to explosive collision of two novel and dangerously unrestrained areas of law: sexual harassment doctrine and Independent Counsel Act; says that, together, they have created constitutional crisis involving criminalization of sex and politics; traces how independent counsel Kenneth Starr, freed from political and financial accountability, has become unpaid investigator for Pres Clinton's accuser, Paula Jones; adds that counsels also have incentive to justify their existence by pinning a crime, any crime, on their targets; describes how Starr combed Arkansas for any evidence of Clinton's sexual activities, and has now concocted another 'cover-up' theory entirely (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So it comes to this. America finds itself in the extraordinary position of contemplating impeachment hearings, as an independent counsel investigates allegations that the President of the United States encouraged a 24-year-old woman to lie under oath about an adulterous affair.</p>
        <p>How did we find ourselves in this predicament? Part of the answer has to do with the explosive collision of two novel, illiberal and dangerously unrestrained areas of law: sexual harassment doctrine and the Independent Counsel Act. Together, they have created a constitutional crisis that confirms the worst fears of critics who have lamented the criminalization of sex and the criminalization of politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So it comes to this. America finds itself in the extraordinary position of contemplating impeachment hearings, as an independent counsel investigates allegations that the President of the United States encouraged a 24-year-old woman to lie under oath about an adulterous affair.</p>
        <p>How did we find ourselves in this predicament? Part of the answer has to do with the explosive collision of two novel, illiberal and dangerously unrestrained areas of law: sexual harassment doctrine and the Independent Counsel Act. Together, they have created a constitutional crisis that confirms the worst fears of critics who have lamented the criminalization of sex and the criminalization of politics.</p>
        <p>Let's start with sexual harassment. Last year, when the Supreme Court unanimously rejected the President's claim that Paula Jones's sexual harassment suit should be delayed until he left office, the justices dismissed concerns that a trial might paralyze the Presidency and generate unrelated litigation.</p>
        <p>The events of last week suggest that the Court's optimism was misplaced. Much of the problem stems from the ill-defined nature of sexual harassment litigation itself, which often spirals out of control because civil suits lack the procedural protections necessary to guard the privacy of the accused and all others with whom he comes into contact.</p>
        <p>Why, for example, were the lawyers for Paula Jones permitted to go on a fishing expedition into the President's sexual history, asking him and other women who crossed his path whether they had engaged in consensual affairs?</p>
        <p>In criminal trials involving serious sexual allegations, like rape, courts scrupulously limit inquiries into the sexual histories of both the accuser and the accused. But in civil lawsuits, Federal rules say that lawyers can ask about anything ''reasonably calculated to lead to the discovery of admissible evidence.''</p>
        <p>Because sexual harassment is vaguely defined to include ''unwanted'' advances, the lawyers for Ms. Jones have been permitted to rummage freely through the President's private life, on the dubious theory that he might have engaged in a pattern of unwanted advances in the workplace, rewarding subordinates who acquiesced to his advances and punishing those who did not.</p>
        <p>At trial, the President's answers might be excluded on the ground that they are more prejudicial than relevant. But merely by asking the questions, Ms. Jones's lawyers have forced the President to discuss his sex life under oath. In the process, they have violated not only his privacy but also that of Monica Lewinsky, an innocent bystander who has been forced to answer questions about her own private life.</p>
        <p>Confronted with questions about sexual relationships, it's not impossible to imagine that a man or a woman might be inclined to shade or to deny the truth. Of course, lying under oath is never a trivial matter. But the instinct to conceal sexual indiscretions is, at least, entirely human, and it's not the kind of sin that we ordinarily associate with thunderous legalisms like ''obstruction of justice.''</p>
        <p>Let's assume, for the sake of argument, that President Clinton and Ms. Lewinsky didn't tell the whole truth. What would be the appropriate remedy? In an ordinary sexual harassment suit, lawyers for Paula Jones would try to attack Mr. Clinton's credibility at trial, and the jury would ultimately decide whom to believe.</p>
        <p>But Jones v. Clinton isn't an ordinary civil suit because it has been shadowed at every turn by Kenneth Starr, the independent counsel investigating President Clinton. We shouldn't be surprised that Mr. Starr's investigation, originally set up to examine financial impropriety in Arkansas, should end up examining sexual impropriety in Washington.</p>
        <p>The relaxed requirements of the Independent Counsel Act authorize the investigation of ''other allegations . . . arising out of'' the original charges. This creates concentric circles of suspicion that often lead special prosecutors far from their starting point. And the result is to turn Mr. Starr into an unpaid investigator for Paula Jones.</p>
        <p>Freed from political and financial accountability, independent counsels have an incentive to justify their existence by pinning a crime -- any crime -- on their targets. As Justice Antonin Scalia warned in his dissent from the Court's decision to uphold the Independent Counsel Act, special prosecutors are appointed to investigate a particular person and then work their way backward to identifying a crime. Ordinary prosecutors begin by investigating a particular crime and then proceed to focus on particular individuals.</p>
        <p>In a political and legal culture in which the ''cover-up'' is always more damning than the underlying offense, it's no coincidence that the special prosecutor appointed to investigate Henry Cisneros, the President's Housing Secretary, also ended up investigating an alleged ''cover-up'' of sexual indiscretions. Mr. Cisneros was indicted last month on charges of misrepresenting the amount of hush money that he paid to his former mistress.</p>
        <p>Six months ago, Mr. Starr began a similar investigation, combing Arkansas for any evidence that the President might have had extramarital affairs, on the theory that Mr. Clinton might have talked to any paramours about his land deals. In the face of criticism, Mr. Starr backed away.</p>
        <p>But presented with evidence of a ''cover-up'' in the Paula Jones case, Mr. Starr was able to concoct another theory entirely. If Mr. Clinton had asked Vernon Jordan to secure a job for Monica Lewinsky to buy her silence, Mr. Starr is suggesting, he might have also asked Vernon Jordan to secure a job for Webster Hubbell, the former Deputy Attorney General, to buy his silence in the Whitewater affair. This theory was enough to persuade Attorney General Janet Reno to ask a three-judge panel to expand Mr. Starr's jurisdiction to include sexual indiscretions.</p>
        <p>So now there is talk of impeachment. In a sense, this talk is inevitable, too, because of another structural flaw in the independent counsel statute. Although the Supreme Court hasn't ruled definitively on the question, the Justice Department from the Nixon to the Clinton Administrations has held that a sitting President can't be criminally indicted before he is impeached.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, after having arranged a disgraceful sting operation to record Ms. Lewinsky surreptitiously, Mr. Starr is required by the statute to hand over any information he uncovers to the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>And now the House Judiciary Committee -- armed with the rough force of subpoena power and unconstrained even by the relaxed rules of evidence that apply in civil trials -- may comb through the President's sex life on the most public and humiliating stage imaginable.</p>
        <p>By lamenting the intersection of the criminalization of sex and the criminalization of politics, I don't mean to minimize the recklessness of the conduct the President is accused of engaging in. But under ordinary circumstances, citizens could disagree, in the course of political debate, about whether the betrayal of a spouse is qualitatively different from the betrayal of state.</p>
        <p>What makes the current scandal so poignant and so distressing is that, once allegations of perjury are in the air, the independent counsel and the impeachment process are poorly equipped to make the delicate moral and political judgments that the situation demands. Now that the brutal legal machinery has begun to grind into motion, there may be nothing anyone can do to stop it.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Rosen, the legal affairs editor of The New Republic, teaches constitutional law at the George Washington University Law School.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeffrey Rosen, the legal affairs editor of The New Republic, teaches constitutional law at the George Washington University Law School.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
