<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singletary and Munoz Lead Rush to the Hall</title>
    <meta content="25FAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SUPER BOWL XXXII"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DD133BF936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singletary and Munoz Lead Rush to the Hall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Jan. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Mike Singletary played college football at Baylor, he hit people so hard that he cracked nine of his own helmets. When he went to the Chicago Bears, he broke at least five more during a brilliant 12-year career as a linebacker.</p>
        <p>''And those are the ones I remember,'' said Singletary, the owner of that trademark stare, whose wife is expecting his seventh child in March. ''Kind of a scary thought, isn't it?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Mike Singletary played college football at Baylor, he hit people so hard that he cracked nine of his own helmets. When he went to the Chicago Bears, he broke at least five more during a brilliant 12-year career as a linebacker.</p>
        <p>''And those are the ones I remember,'' said Singletary, the owner of that trademark stare, whose wife is expecting his seventh child in March. ''Kind of a scary thought, isn't it?''</p>
        <p>Anthony Munoz played against the best defensive linemen and linebackers of his time -- Lawrence Taylor, Joe Klecko, Fred Dean, Bruce Smith. Few of them ever got the best of him, and what defined Munoz, who played 13 seasons with the Cincinnati Bengals -- 185 games in all -- was his size. Munoz was one of the first giant and skilled left tackles in football, standing 6 feet 6 inches and weighing almost 280 pounds.</p>
        <p>Singletary and Munoz, both in their first year of eligibility, were among the five players elected to the Pro Football Hall of Fame today by a 36-member board of electors. The three other members admitted: safety Paul Krause, who spent most of his 16-year career with the Minnesota Vikings and played in four Super Bowls; Dwight Stephenson, a smallish but tough center for eight years with the Miami Dolphins who became known for his great quickness, and Tommy McDonald, a wide receiver who was a third-round pick of the Philadelphia Eagles in 1957.</p>
        <p>McDonald, who was nominated by the seniors committee, also played with the Dallas Cowboys, Los Angeles Rams, Atlanta Falcons and Cleveland Browns. McDonald was a member of the 1960 N.F.L. champion  Eagles team that beat the Packers for the title and was a six-time Pro Bowl player who led the league in reception yardage (1,144) and touchdowns (13) in 1961. He retired after the 1968 season.</p>
        <p>The 1998 class will be officially inducted on Aug. 1 on the front steps of the Pro Football Hall of Fame in Canton, Ohio.</p>
        <p>There were some notable finalists who did not make it this year, and three were associated with the Pittsburgh Steelers. The owner Dan Rooney and wide receivers John Stallworth and Lynn Swann were not voted in. It is believed that Rooney will definitely make it soon, but it is looking more and more like Swann may not.</p>
        <p>Singletary and Munoz dominate this year's entrants because at times  they were bigger than the game when they played.</p>
        <p>Munoz was a physical specimen who spent years protecting the backside of quarterback Ken Anderson and later Boomer Esiason. His quick feet for someone his size made him the perfect offensive lineman.</p>
        <p>''This is an unbelievable experience for me,'' said Munoz, who broke down and cried this afternoon during the announcement here at the Marriott Marina.</p>
        <p>While Singletary was not all that big by pro football standards -- he was a shade under 6 feet and weighed just 230 pounds -- he was one of the toughest players ever.</p>
        <p>Asked what he wanted people to most remember about him, Singletary replied, ''More so than anything else I was a player who made the most of the ability he had.''</p>
        <p>The most joyful of the new Hall of Fame members seemed to be McDonald, who called in from his home in King of Prussia, Pa., and spoke to reporters in a conference call. While he was talking, his phone kept beeping, signaling he had a call on the other line. Presumably, the callers were people trying to congratulate him.</p>
        <p>''I've been waiting for this for 24 years,'' he said. ''I've been counting the days.''</p>
        <p>McDonald was asked why he didn't play with a face mask. He was the last in the N.F.L. not to wear one.</p>
        <p>''The reason is because I was so ugly I figured there was no room for improvement,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SUPER BOWL XXXII</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
