<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>But Will It Fly?</title>
    <meta content="25WILFORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shipman, Pat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dingus, Lowell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowe, Timothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chatterjee, Sankar</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Taking Wing (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mistaken Extinction, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rise of Birds, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDE1738F936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>But Will It Fly?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Noble Wilford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Noble Wilford reviews books Taking Wing: Archaeopteryx and the Evolution of Bird Flight by Pat Shipman, The Mistaken Extinction: Dinosaur Evolution and the Origin of Birds by Lowell Dingus and Timothy Rowe and The Rise of Birds: 225 Million Years of Evolution by Sankar Chatterjee; drawing (L)/</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TAKING WING</p>
        <p>Archaeopteryx and the Evolution</p>
        <p>of Bird Flight.</p>
        <p>By Pat Shipman.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 336 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
        <p>THE MISTAKEN</p>
        <p>EXTINCTION</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Evolution and</p>
        <p>the Origin of Birds.</p>
        <p>By Lowell Dingus and Timothy Rowe.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 332 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. H. Freeman &amp; Company. $34.95.</p>
        <p>THE RISE OF BIRDS</p>
        <p>225 Million Years of Evolution.</p>
        <p>By Sankar Chatterjee.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 312 pp. Baltimore:</p>
        <p>Johns Hopkins University Press. $39.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TAKING WING</p>
        <p>Archaeopteryx and the Evolution</p>
        <p>of Bird Flight.</p>
        <p>By Pat Shipman.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 336 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
        <p>THE MISTAKEN</p>
        <p>EXTINCTION</p>
        <p>Dinosaur Evolution and</p>
        <p>the Origin of Birds.</p>
        <p>By Lowell Dingus and Timothy Rowe.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 332 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>W. H. Freeman &amp; Company. $34.95.</p>
        <p>THE RISE OF BIRDS</p>
        <p>225 Million Years of Evolution.</p>
        <p>By Sankar Chatterjee.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 312 pp. Baltimore:</p>
        <p>Johns Hopkins University Press. $39.95.</p>
        <p>Some 150 million years ago, winged creatures the size of blue jays died and fell into a shallow lagoon in what is now Bavaria, where stonecutters found the first of their fossil remains in 1861. Here, pressed and preserved on slabs of limestone, in bas relief, was a creature that was half bird and half reptile. It was not only a beautiful piece of natural art but one of the most fascinating and famous paleontological discoveries of all time.</p>
        <p>Thomas Henry Huxley pounced on the find as the kind of transitional species that supported the theory of evolution recently published by his friend Darwin. Archaeopteryx, as the fossil specimen was named, provided strong evidence that birds evolved from reptiles. It had the teeth and sharp claws, long legs and tailbones of a reptile. And then there were wings and that impression of a single feather. Only birds, no other creatures, are known to have feathered wings. In time, Huxley went on to argue that the reptilian ancestors of Archaeopteryx were none other than dinosaurs, a theory that has had its ups and downs over the last 130 years but is now ascendant.</p>
        <p>Scientists agree that birds evolved from reptiles, and most of them also recognize Archaeopteryx (its fossil flock now numbers seven) as an early bird, though almost certainly not the earliest. New discoveries of other birdlike animals from Mongolia to Madagascar seem to fill in missing pieces of the evolutionary line connecting dinosaurs and birds.</p>
        <p>But the case for a dinosaurian ancestry of birds is by no means closed. Some scientists, particularly ornithologists, still have trouble conceiving of how two such distinct groups of animals could be directly related; they choose to think the bird line originated among pre-dinosaur reptiles. They also suspect advocates of the dinosaur-bird link of being influenced by the wish to believe that dinosaurs are alive, not extinct, that they are perched on the backyard feeder.</p>
        <p>Three new books take up the story of bird origins as it has been pieced together since the Archaeopteryx discovery. They differ in scope and style, although all the authors favor in various degrees the dinosaur-bird link. In ''Taking Wing,'' Pat Shipman, who seems to have started with an open mind, concludes that a group of predatory dinosaurs known as theropods is ''the most probable ancestor of birds.'' In ''The Mistaken Extinction,'' Lowell Dingus and Timothy Rowe express unqualified belief: ''Instead of dying out, dinosaurs were merely defined out of existence.'' Sankar Chatterjee writes in ''The Rise of Birds'': ''Birds are as much dinosaurs as bats are mammals.''</p>
        <p>Shipman brings to her excellent book the authority of a paleontologist and the talent of an accomplished writer on science for popular audiences. Her narrative is alive with stories of the many people, historical and living, who have puzzled and argued over the meaning of the fossil bird, with appropriate credit given to John Ostrom of Yale University for reviving and winning widespread support for the dinosaur-bird theory. Her reporting takes the reader into the minds of these scientists, especially as they ponder the question of how Archaeopteryx, or any other basically ground-dwelling reptile, took the fateful leap of flight. She seems to be on a journey of discovery herself, generously bringing us along.</p>
        <p>At one point, for example, she asks the question that must occur to most readers: Why so much contention over fine points of Archaeopteryx anatomy? ''At first,'' she writes, ''I suspected that the scientists were simply talking past each other, like small boys involved in an argument that has deteriorated to the 'Is too!' 'Is not!' stage.'' The more she investigated the matter, the more she realized there were good reasons for disagreement, because the morphology of the fossil bird ''is genuinely ambiguous.''</p>
        <p>With this, she plunges into an illuminating discussion of two ways of interpreting evolutionary anatomies: by homology and analogy. A human hand, a bird's wing and a whale's flipper are all homologous structures, she explains, in that each represents an evolutionary modification of the same ancestral limb structure. Analogy refers to a similarity of appearance due to similar function, not common descent, as in the wing of a bat, a bird and a butterfly. Much of the case for dinosaurian ancestry of birds rests on whether the wrist bones of certain dinosaurs, Archaeopteryx and modern birds are homologous structures, and some critics are unyielding in their opposition.</p>
        <p>Archaeopteryx has provoked another question that has long divided scientists: How did powered flight by birds originate -- from the ground up, or from the trees down? If, as it seems, Archaeopteryx's flight muscles were deficient, the bird must have had to get a fast running start, perhaps while chasing prey, and to flap its arms enough to gain altitude, however briefly. Or it glided out of the trees as ''a halfway step on the transition to flapping flight.'' A few scientists doubt that Archaeopteryx could fly at all.</p>
        <p>After assessing many reconstructions of the Archaeopteryx flight apparatus, Shipman writes, ''I am now convinced that Archaeopteryx was such a large-winged creature that it could take off from the ground, with either a reptilian or an avian physiology.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes one might wish she would move a little more briskly in her narrative, but the cumulative reward is an appreciation of how paleontologists think and extract meaning out of the barest scraps of evidence. In the end, the author wisely counsels scientists and the reader: ''Dinosaurs aren't birds -- at least, not birds as they are now -- and the first feathers weren't feathers as they are now, either. Even Archaeopteryx . . . isn't a bird as birds are now; it is only closer to them than it is to anything else we can lay our hands on.''</p>
        <p>The book by Dingus and Rowe, ''The Mistaken Extinction,'' makes their position clear by placing the subject of bird origins within a broader, almost encyclopedic review of dinosaurs. The first long section rehearses all the hypotheses about the extinction of great reptiles, which is a setup for their ultimate point about how, considering the ancestry of birds, reports of the demise of dinosaurs are greatly exaggerated.</p>
        <p>The authors, who are paleontologists, contend that the traditional Linnaean system of classifying organisms trapped most scientists into having to consign dinosaurs to the ranks of extinct life. In the Linnaean emphasis on classification by defining characteristics, they write, ''only birds could have feathers, and birds belonged to a class entirely separate from reptilian dinosaurs.'' A new method of determining evolutionary relationships, called cladistics, identifies unique anatomical features that the different lines shared. Under this system, as many paleontologists see it, birds retain several attributes that were inherited from their dinosaur ancestors.</p>
        <p>Scientific critics will no doubt pick at this argument. Even some paleontologists who accept a dinosaur-bird link may balk at classifying birds as latter-day dinosaurs. But Dingus and Rowe are spirited advocates. If their richly illustrated book is perhaps too comprehensive for cover-to-cover reading, it is well organized to be used for years as a reference work on all kinds of dinosaur and bird lore.</p>
        <p>The authors refer briefly and skeptically to a pheasant-sized creature named Protoavis, or primordial bird, that lived 75 million years before Archaeopteryx. They suspect the Protoavis fossils represent ''a death assemblage of different animals instead of associated parts of a single kind of animal.'' But Sankar Chatterjee, who found the fossils in West Texas in 1983, has claimed this may be the long-lost ancestor of birds.</p>
        <p>In ''The Rise of Birds,'' Chatterjee gives a more cautious account of Protoavis than he did at the time of its discovery. He enumerates the anatomical characteristics of Protoavis that are birdlike, including a chest that could have supported muscles for flapping flight and hand bones showing quill nodes for the attachment of feathers. The animal had a relatively large brain and carnivorous teeth. ''The most remarkable thing about Protoavis is that, although it predates Archaeopteryx by 75 million years,'' the author concludes, ''it is considerably more advanced than Archaeopteryx.''</p>
        <p>Such evidence, Chatterjee contends, indicates that Protoavis is more closely related to modern birds than is</p>
        <p>Archaeopteryx, which presumably would be relegated to a side branch of the main evolution of birds. The thought of toppling Archaeopteryx from its lofty evolutionary perch is probably enough to ruffle some scientific feathers.</p>
        <p>But ''The Rise of Birds,'' as the title promises, delivers more than an interpretation of a single bird, however ancient. Most of the book is devoted to a thoughtful analysis of bird evolution and anatomy aided by useful drawings. Chatterjee forcefully argues a minority view that bird flight originated from the ''trees down.''</p>
        <p>He also reminds us why we should be, as we are, fascinated by birds and their origins. ''Birds are the most successful terrestrial vertebrate,'' he writes. There are 300 billion of them -- 9,000 living species of birds, compared with 4,100 species of mammals. Thankfully, evolution has softened their monstrous image, leaving us with cardinals and chickadees instead of a yard full of</p>
        <p>Velociraptors.  John Noble Wilford is a senior science writer at The New York Times and the author of ''The Riddle of the Dinosaur.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Noble Wilford is a senior science writer at The New York Times and the author of ''The Riddle of the Dinosaur.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
