<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Younger Hevesi's Senate Bid Unites Comptroller and Rival</title>
    <meta content="25HEVE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Daniel R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manton, Thomas J (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Emanuel (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D7123BF936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Younger Hevesi's Senate Bid Unites Comptroller and Rival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Senate bid by Daniel R Hevesi, 27-year-old son of New York City Comptroller Alan G Hevesi, has united elder Hevesi and Congressman Thomas J Manton, Queens party leader, who has been rival of Alan G Hevesi; younger Hevesi is planning to run in district that includes Queens neighborhoods of Forest Hills, Rego Park and Bayside; seat is being vacated by Sen Emanuel R Gold (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a feud that cast a long shadow over Queens politics for the last four years.</p>
        <p>But to hear Democratic officials tell it, not only has the chill substantially thawed between Alan G. Hevesi, the City Comptroller, and Congressman Thomas J. Manton, the Queens party leader, but the two are also working together on a number of political goals, not least of which is getting Mr. Hevesi's son elected to  the State Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a feud that cast a long shadow over Queens politics for the last four years.</p>
        <p>But to hear Democratic officials tell it, not only has the chill substantially thawed between Alan G. Hevesi, the City Comptroller, and Congressman Thomas J. Manton, the Queens party leader, but the two are also working together on a number of political goals, not least of which is getting Mr. Hevesi's son elected to  the State Senate.</p>
        <p>Daniel R. Hevesi, the 27-year-old son of the Comptroller, is planning to run in a district that includes the Queens neighborhoods of Forest Hills, Rego Park and Bayside. The seat is being vacated by Senator Emanuel R. Gold, 62, the longest-serving Democrat in the State Senate, who announced recently that he would not seek re-election after 27 years in office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manton, in a recent interview, said that he was favorably disposed to supporting the younger Mr. Hevesi, who is now an aide to Claire Shulman, the Queens Borough President, and a former legislative intern to Mr. Gold. As for the relationship with Mr. Hevesi's father, Mr. Manton said: ''We are getting along just fine. We work very well together.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Comptroller Hevesi said: ''My relationship with Tom Manton is friendly and cooperative. He is an excellent political leader.''</p>
        <p>While both men insist that the tension between them has been exaggerated, such gushing camaraderie would scarcely have been imaginable just a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Their trouble began in 1993 when Mr. Hevesi was elected Comptroller, forcing him to resign his seat in the Assembly. Mr. Manton and the Queens Democratic Party endorsed Michael Cohen, a Democratic district leader, to fill the seat. Mr. Hevesi, on the other hand, supported Melinda Katz, a lawyer, who ran on the Liberal and Good Government Party lines.</p>
        <p>Ms. Katz won that race in 1994, providing Mr. Hevesi with additional political heft outside the Democratic organization.</p>
        <p>In the ensuing years, Mr. Hevesi and Mr. Manton found themselves on opposite sides of a number of races  in Queens, including two City Council races in 1997.</p>
        <p>Queens Democratic officials insist that the new-found harmony is a function of various political aspirations in Queens and the city. Mr. Hevesi is considered a leading candidate for mayor in 2001, a campaign in which the support of his borough's Democratic leader would be crucial.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ms. Katz, a political protege of the Comptroller, is planning to run for the Congressional seat that will be abandoned by Congressman Charles E. Schumer if he runs for United States Senate. That Congressional district is split between Queens and Brooklyn, and Ms. Katz is, at the moment, the only legislator from Queens in the race.</p>
        <p>And unlike the race in 1994, she now has the support of Mr. Manton. ''Because she is the only candidate from Queens, we look favorably upon her candidacy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Of course, by running for Congress, Ms. Katz would be forced to vacate her seat in the Assembly. And Mr. Manton suggested that a leading candidate for that Assembly seat will be Mr. Cohen, the Manton protege and Democratic district leader, who lost to Ms. Katz four years ago.</p>
        <p>''Tom Manton, Alan Hevesi and myself are looking forward to a very good working relationship,'' Ms. Katz said. ''Whatever fight that might have existed is over. I'm very happy that the Comptroller and the Congressman are at peace.''</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Hevesi's prospects are considered bright for the upcoming State Senate race. So far, no significant opposition has materialized, and Mr. Hevesi -- who is a Democratic district leader and a director in the Borough President's Office of Management and Budget -- is already considered a rising star in Queens politics.</p>
        <p>Several Queens Democrats suggest that Mr. Hevesi is in a strong  position. ''I happen to believe that the county organization will be strong in support of Dan in that race,'' said Walter L. McCaffrey, a City Councilman who is close to Mr. Manton. ''He is a bright young man. And, if he does have a primary, I think he'll get strong organizational support.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
