<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North Staff Not Taking A Victory As Assured</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="691160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIRGINIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORTH, OLIVER L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATEMAN, HERBERT (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, JAMES C 3D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DC1E3BF930A35755C0A962958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North Staff Not Taking A Victory As Assured</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>RICHMOND, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not that Oliver L. North's campaign staff is nervous. Certainly not. Aides responsible for tracking delegate votes at this weekend's Virginia Republican convention are saying the former Marine could win the Senate nomination over James C. Miller 3d with as much as 57 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>It's just that Mr. North's strategists know what can happen when almost 14,000 people get together in a carnival atmosphere to pick a candidate for high office. Many remember 13 years ago, when Herb Bateman came into the convention as the front-runner in a three-way race for attorney general. He finished third.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not that Oliver L. North's campaign staff is nervous. Certainly not. Aides responsible for tracking delegate votes at this weekend's Virginia Republican convention are saying the former Marine could win the Senate nomination over James C. Miller 3d with as much as 57 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>It's just that Mr. North's strategists know what can happen when almost 14,000 people get together in a carnival atmosphere to pick a candidate for high office. Many remember 13 years ago, when Herb Bateman came into the convention as the front-runner in a three-way race for attorney general. He finished third.</p>
        <p>"A convention takes on a life of its own, once it gets into the building," Dave Johnson, the party's executive director, said today as he prepared for the opening on Friday. "I would be surprised if North didn't win. But it would not be shocking. Anything's possible."</p>
        <p>Republican nominating conventions in Virginia, which have the final say on who will represent the party in the November election, have become ingrained in Republican politics here. Only three times since World War II have party leaders decided that Republican candidates for high office should be chosen by primary. Complicated Formula</p>
        <p>It is primarily the way that delegate votes are counted that makes the Virginia convention more volatile than the scripted national conventions of recent years. Here, anyone could have become a delegate this year for a $45 registration fee. But the party sets the overall delegate vote for each county, based on how many votes in the county were cast for George Bush for President in 1992 and George F. Allen for governor last year. The weight of each delegate's vote will be determined by how many other delegates from the same county show up on Saturday for the secret balloting in the Richmond Coliseum. For example, if a county had 50 votes and 100 voting delegates, then each of its delegate ballots would be worth half a vote.</p>
        <p>With that kind of system, and the two candidates for the Senate nomination remarkably similar in their conservative ideologies, both camps have developed sophisticated networks for monitoring delegates before and during the convention.</p>
        <p>Much of the work has involved telephone calls, mailings, wooing and schmoozing. Roger and Marie Hill, undecided delegates from Arvonia, a small town in the center of the state, say they have been inundated with flyers and mailings from both Mr. North and Mr. Miller and are still uncertain how they will vote. Staging Support</p>
        <p>Once the convention begins, however, the primary responsibility will fall to floor managers, who glue themselves to committed delegates to make sure they stay that way and who track undecided voters like the Hills. The camps also plant volunteers around the floor "to create spontaneous eruptions are that not really spontaneous," Mr. Johnson said.</p>
        <p>"Image is everything," he explained. "Bigger signs help. Brighter signs. Rallies around the Coliseum. Last year, the attorney general race was a dead heat going into the convention. Jim Gilmore blew it open because his campaign had better floor management and created the message and momentum that he was going to win."</p>
        <p>J. Kenneth Klinge, a consultant to the Miller campaign, said that even the perception of momentum could influence the outcome. He estimated that at least 5 percent of the delegates wanted to vote only for the winner and would make their decisions only after sensing which candidate had more supporters, wearing more buttons and making most noise.</p>
        <p>"Are we going to have shills out there?" he said. "Sure."</p>
        <p>In fact, he added, the campaign intends to have more than 1,200 people through the Coliseum, monitoring delegates, lobbying undecided voters like the Hills and making last-minute pitches to North delegates whom the Miller campaign has identified as wavering.</p>
        <p>Dan McLagan, a spokesman for the North campaign, said his camp had about half that many people to perform those same kinds of duties. Floor Strategy</p>
        <p>With many political analysts, not to mention Miller supporters, expressing doubt that Mr. North's lead remains as large as his staff describes, neither camp is taking any chances on losing delegate contact or support. Mr. North, for example, has circulated a three-page "campaign update" that offers guidelines for what his delegates may expect at the convention. Here are several excerpts:</p>
        <p>*On floor relations: "They will try to provoke North supporters into getting into scuffles with them. If you take the bait and retaliate, Miller's handlers will play that up with the press and make us look like the bad guys."</p>
        <p>*On press relations: "If they ask you what you think about all the bigwigs from Washington attacking Ollie, remind them that Ollie is going to shake up their little country club and they don't like it one bit."</p>
        <p>*On the possibility the Miller campaign would "come out with some story that they will claim blows Ollie out of the water": "It is important to remember that if there were a 'bombshell,' the Miller people would already have used it." 'Radio Free Ollie'</p>
        <p>In another recent letter, Mr. North urged supporters to bring portable radios to Richmond because the campaign had purchased eight hours of time on a local radio station on Saturday. Radio Free Ollie, his aides call it, and Mark Merritt, a campaign spokesman, said it would combat rumors, keep delegates abreast of convention proceedings and "shoot down all the mud we know they are going to throw at us."</p>
        <p>Mr. Klinge would not say what surprises the Miller camp might be planning.</p>
        <p>As for the reactions of the delegates, Mr. Hill, who runs an insurance agency, said that even with all the mail, the clamor of a convention and anything Mr. North and Mr. Miller might say to persuade them, he and his wife were not sure how they could be swayed.</p>
        <p>He said they felt uncomfortable with Mr. Miller, who was the budget director in the Reagan Administration, for his strong stand against abortion -- he would make exceptions only when the life of the pregnant woman was threatened -- and uncomfortable with Mr. North for his role in the Iran-contra affair.</p>
        <p>Then, with a reference to J. Marshall Coleman, a Republican who has indicated he may enter the fall campaign as an independent, Mr. Hill said: "I might come to the convention and not vote for either one. That would at least give me a clear conscience if I wanted to vote for someone else."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
