<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Executive Offers Plan With Alternatives to Abortion</title>
    <meta content="07suozzi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/07/nyregion/07suozzi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teenage Pregnancy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suozzi, Thomas R (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Teenage Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teenage Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFD8173EF934A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Executive Offers Plan With Alternatives to Abortion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nassau Executive Offers Plan With Alternatives to Abortion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Feb. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County Exec Thomas R Suozzi plans to announce proposal to reduce abortions with program intended to appeal to both sides of divisive issue; county would provide grants to groups that promote adoption, provide housing for single mothers, encourage abstinence and provide information on other birth control measures (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move with potential implications for the Democratic race for governor, Nassau County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi plans to announce on Tuesday a $3 million proposal to reduce abortions with a program intended to appeal to both sides of the divisive issue.</p>
        <p>The proposed county program would issue grants for the next three years to groups that promote adoption, provide housing for single mothers, encourage abstinence and provide information about other birth-control measures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The proposed county program would issue grants to groups that promote adoption, provide housing for single mothers, encourage abstinence and provide information about other birth-control measures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move with potential implications for the Democratic race for governor, Nassau County Executive Thomas R. Suozzi plans to announce on Tuesday a $3 million proposal to reduce abortions with a program intended to appeal to both sides of the divisive issue.</p>
        <p>The proposed county program would issue grants for the next three years to groups that promote adoption, provide housing for single mothers, encourage abstinence and provide information about other birth-control measures.</p>
        <p>In an effort to gain a consensus as he assembled his plan, Mr. Suozzi brought together groups that often battle over abortions laws, from Planned Parenthood on one side to Catholic Charities on the other.</p>
        <p>A Roman Catholic, Mr. Suozzi had argued that ''we must keep abortion legal and safe.''</p>
        <p>But he has tempered his position by advocating reducing those procedures and also by opposing late-term operations that opponents call partial-birth abortions.</p>
        <p>Similarly, he has steered a middle-road course on gay rights by opposing same-sex marriage but supporting domestic partnerships and civil unions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suozzi has been touring the state as he contemplates a run for the Democratic nomination for governor.</p>
        <p>The front-runner in that race, State Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer, opposes restrictions on late-term abortion and endorses gay marriage.</p>
        <p>The Suozzi administration says that its program to reduce abortions is one of the first, if not the first, in the nation for a local government.</p>
        <p>Some 60 people representing various public schools, universities and hospitals and social service, religious and other nonprofit organizations worked with Mr. Suozzi on the plan, holding about a dozen meetings in recent months to develop the details.</p>
        <p>Teenagers are the prime audience, and focus groups were used to plan the program.</p>
        <p>Participants expressed the wish to talk more about sex with their parents, according to those involved in the studies.</p>
        <p>Some youngsters said they were already sexually active, while others said they were trying to remain abstinent. Mr. Suozzi proposed his idea last May in a speech at Adelphi University called ''Common Sense for the Common Good.''</p>
        <p>The issue is not new to him. A decade ago, as mayor of the small city of Glen Cove, he helped find a site for Momma's House, which assists unwed mothers.</p>
        <p>The interim president of Planned Parenthood in Nassau, JoAnn D. Smith, hailed the program as ''very exciting'' and added, ''This is the first time that we will have received funding from the county.'' Her group's education efforts include abstinence as well as other birth control means, she said.</p>
        <p>The leader of another group proposed for a grant, Bishop Frank Otha White of the Zion Cathedral Church of God in Christ, in Freeport, said that its program will stress abstinence but also provide information about other choices.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Suozzi may have navigated through disparate groups on abortion issues, his program may face opposition in the Nassau County Legislature, which will vote on the proposed grant contracts.</p>
        <p>The Legislature's Republican minority leader, Peter Schmitt, who describes himself as ''pro-life,'' said: ''Leadership is not pandering to both sides of a contentious issue by using taxpayer dollars. I have pro-abortion people calling concerned that pro-life people are being funded, and pro-life people calling concerned that pro-abortion people are being funded. You can't be on both sides of this issue.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
