<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witness in Enron Trial Struggles With Emotions</title>
    <meta content="07enron" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/07/business/businessspecial3/07enron.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Enron Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Skilling, Jeffrey K</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lay, Kenneth L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7D8173EF934A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witness in Enron Trial Struggles With Emotions</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Witness in Enron Trial Struggles With Emotions</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXEI BARRIONUEVO and THAYER EVANS</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After nearly three days of calmly answering prosecutors' questions, the first witness in the Enron trial of Jeffrey K. Skilling and Kenneth L. Lay nearly broke down on the stand under questioning by a defense lawyer.</p>
        <p>The witness, Mark E. Koenig, 50, the former head of investor relations, became visibly distraught when asked by a defense lawyer, Daniel Petrocelli, about how old his three children were when he made the decision to plead guilty and cooperate with prosecutors in their investigation into Enron's spectacular implosion in December 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first witness in the Enron trial of Jeffrey K. Skilling and Kenneth L. Lay nearly broke down on the stand under questioning by a defense lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After nearly three days of calmly answering prosecutors' questions, the first witness in the Enron trial of Jeffrey K. Skilling and Kenneth L. Lay nearly broke down on the stand under questioning by a defense lawyer.</p>
        <p>The witness, Mark E. Koenig, 50, the former head of investor relations, became visibly distraught when asked by a defense lawyer, Daniel Petrocelli, about how old his three children were when he made the decision to plead guilty and cooperate with prosecutors in their investigation into Enron's spectacular implosion in December 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig appeared close to tears as his face reddened. As he struggled to contain his emotions, at least one juror appeared to shift in her seat, as if to get a better look at him.</p>
        <p>After several seconds of silence, Judge Simeon T. Lake III of Federal District Court ordered a break for jurors, even after Mr. Koenig said, ''I'm fine.''</p>
        <p>The emotional moment capped a tense day of questioning by Mr. Petrocelli, the lead lawyer for Mr. Skilling, a former Enron chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig, on the stand for his fourth day, is the first of several former Enron executives who have pleaded guilty to Enron-related crimes and are testifying for the government against their former bosses, Mr. Skilling and Mr. Lay, a former chief executive and a founder.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skilling is charged with 31 counts of fraud, conspiracy and insider trading in a case in which the government contends he manipulated the company's earnings and then lied about it while enriching himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lay is charged with seven counts of fraud and conspiracy for purportedly taking part in the conspiracy and then lying about Enron's true financial condition to analysts and investors. Both men, if convicted of all counts, could spend the rest of their lives behind bars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig's emotional moment underscored the tough decisions that were facing many of the 16 indicted Enron insiders the government is relying on, in large part, to persuade the jury that the former chief executives are guilty as charged.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig admitted in previous testimony that he lied to the Securities Exchange Commission and bank examiners. But by pleading guilty in August 2004 he agreed to help prosecutors in hopes of receiving less than the maximum of 10 years he faces for aiding and abetting securities fraud.</p>
        <p>Mr. Petrocelli, Mr. Skilling's lawyer, sought to show that Mr. Koenig was willing to say almost anything to avoid a long prison term and to protect the $5 million he has left in Enron-related earnings. Mr. Koenig, who was paid $1 million in salary and bonus in 2000, said he doubted he could protect the money, since he is named in 14 civil lawsuits related to Enron's collapse.</p>
        <p>Before the question about his children, he insisted he was being truthful this time around.</p>
        <p>''There was pressure from other people pleading guilty, there's no doubt,'' he said, ''but I was not pressured to say guilty when I was not guilty.''</p>
        <p>''Is it fair to say that your life is on the line?'' Mr. Petrocelli asked.</p>
        <p>''My life has been on the line since August 2004,'' Mr. Koenig replied.</p>
        <p>Cross-examination of Mr. Koenig will continue on Tuesday with more questions from Mr. Petrocelli and from Mr. Lay's lead lawyer, Michael Ramsey. As he was making his way from the courthouse on Monday, Mr. Ramsey gave a thumbs-up to reporters.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, under questioning by prosecutors, Mr. Koenig said he spoke to no avail to Mr. Lay and Mr. Skilling about investors' concerns about vague financial disclosures months before the company declared bankruptcy in late 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig said the misleading statements continued even as Enron disclosed huge quarterly losses in mid-October 2001, two months after Mr. Skilling had resigned and Mr. Lay had assumed the role of chief executive. That month Enron announced more than $600 million in quarterly losses in its broadband and water ventures as well as bad investments. The company also wrote down shareholder equity by $1.2 billion because of an accounting mistake that had gone unnoticed for months.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig said Mr. Lay was among those top executives who wanted to keep the detail about the $1.2 billion out of the company's earnings news release.</p>
        <p>''By not putting it in the earnings release, that was an attempt to minimize it,'' Mr. Koenig said. Instead, as a compromise, Mr. Lay mentioned the shareholder equity reduction in a conference call with analysts, Mr. Koenig said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koenig said Mr. Lay directed members of his communications team in an Oct. 21 meeting to do damage control about LJM, the entity controlled by the chief financial officer, Andrew S. Fastow, who was facing increased scrutiny from analysts and investors. Mr. Koenig said he fought for more disclosure to stem the tide of analysts' concerns and negative news stories. ''I was upset,'' he said. ''Saying that it was approved by the board and the accountants wasn't the way to go. But I was the lone wolf.''</p>
        <p>Two days later, on a special conference call, Mr. Lay diverted from a prepared script to express his support for Mr. Fastow. ''It was very shocking to me that that endorsement came at that time,'' Mr. Koenig said.</p>
        <p>Also Monday Mr. Koenig said that Mr. Skilling lied when he told analysts that Enron did not track the gains on sales of power plants. In a second-quarter 2001 conference call, Mr. Skilling lauded earnings in Enron's division that included its profitable trading unit, but did not tell investors that up to half of those earnings came from sales of power plants, so-called peaker plants. In the first half of 2001, the division recorded $1.5 billion in income in the first half of 2001, of which $670 million came from the asset sales.</p>
        <p>Still, while saying that Mr. Skilling lied, Mr. Koenig acknowledged that he was not certain whether Mr. Skilling knew the statement was untrue when he made it. ''There's absolutely no way I can know for a fact what he had in his head,'' Mr. Koenig said.</p>
        <p>Next up for the prosecution will be Kenneth D. Rice, the former chief executive of Enron's broadband division, who has pleaded guilty to securities fraud for purportedly conspiring with others to misrepresent Enron's network so that Enron stock would rise and he could profit from sales of inflated shares. He could take the stand as early as today, although Mr. Petrocelli indicated Monday that he expected to take at least another day to question Mr. Koenig. There is no testimony on Fridays.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
