<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Delays Rebuke In Copter Case</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="700065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HELICOPTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIDES AND EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEHL, DOUGLAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALDON, ALPHONSO JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATKINS, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Helicopters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DE1F3FF934A25754C0A962958260" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Delays Rebuke In Copter Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEHL, DOUGLAS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seven weeks after the White House said he would be reassigned for his role in the misuse of a Marine Corps helicopter, the head of the White House military office has not been disciplined and remains on the job, Administration officials said on Friday.</p>
        <p>They said that the White House had found it difficult to find a successor to the official, Alphonso Maldon Jr., and that some thought had been given to letting him stay in his post.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seven weeks after the White House said he would be reassigned for his role in the misuse of a Marine Corps helicopter, the head of the White House military office has not been disciplined and remains on the job, Administration officials said on Friday.</p>
        <p>They said that the White House had found it difficult to find a successor to the official, Alphonso Maldon Jr., and that some thought had been given to letting him stay in his post.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Maldon's fate remains unresolved adds another layer of embarrassment to the May 24 episode in which he and his superior, David Watkins, used a Presidential helicopter for a 55-mile excursion to the Holly Hills Country Club near Frederick, Md., for a round of golf.</p>
        <p>After details of the incident became public, Mr. Watkins was dismissed and ultimately agreed to reimburse the Government for the $13,000 cost of the helicopter flight; Thomas F. McLarty 3d, then the White House chief of staff, announced on May 26 that Mr. Maldon would be reassigned. Sensaitive About Military</p>
        <p>But the slow progress in settling the status of Mr. Maldon, a retired Army colonel, also appears to illustrate the continued sensitivities within the White House about relations with the military.</p>
        <p>Asked why Mr. Maldon remained on the job, White House officials on Friday praised him for having proved unusually effective as a liaison to the Army, Navy, Air Force and Marine Corps. They also said it had not been easy to find a successor with sufficient rank and talent.</p>
        <p>"He's someone who knows both the White House and the military," a senior White House official said, "and that's a pretty tough combination."</p>
        <p>Besides arranging for the use of Air Force One and other jets, Mr.  Maldon schedules the helicopters from the squadron maintained by the Marine Corps for Presidential use. It was Mr. Maldon, White House officials have said, who arranged for the helicopter that carried him, Mr. Watkins and a Navy officer to and from the Holly Hills course near Camp David, Md., for a Tuesday afternoon of golf. Simply Following Orders</p>
        <p>But the officials said Mr. Maldon did so at the behest of Mr. Watkins, who as the White House director of administration was Mr. Maldon's direct superior. Supporters of Mr. Maldon in the White House and on Capitol Hill now say they do not believe he should be punished for simply following orders.</p>
        <p>Before he joined the White House staff, Mr. Maldon was on active duty and was serving as an Army liaison to Capitol Hill. His first job at the White House was in the office of Congressional relations; he took over as director of the White House military office earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. McLarty, who is now the counselor to the President, did not respond to a telephone message asking for comment.</p>
        <p>A senior White House official involved in the discussions said Mr. McLarty's reassignment last month had compounded the delay in finding a successor to Mr. Maldon. They said the decision about whether to replace him and with whom would now be in the hands of Leon E. Panetta, the new White House chief of staff.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
