<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bissell Case Spurs Calls for Trenton to Rein In Officials</title>
    <meta content="08PROS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Somerset County (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verniero, Peter G (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bissell, Nicholas L Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5D6123FF93BA35751C1A960958260" item-length="1654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bissell Case Spurs Calls for Trenton to Rein In Officials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Atty Gen Peter Verniero has begun to review ways his office supervises state's 21 county prosecutors, in wake of conviction of Somerset County Prosecutor Nicholas L Bissell Jr on charges of abuse of power and embezzlement and of his suicide Nov 26 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1983, a year after Nicholas L. Bissell Jr. became Somerset County Prosecutor, he filed a lawsuit to remove Franklin Township's Mayor from office. His complaint? Misconduct in office, he said, because she had distributed fliers at a township Council meeting criticizing a police investigation of several rapes.</p>
        <p>In 1989, William B. Wahl, the director of Somerset County's governing body, the Board of Chosen Freeholders, apparently angered Mr. Bissell by questioning raises for his staff and demanding that the County Auditor audit the Prosecutor's office. Subsequently, Mr. Bissell accused Mr. Wahl of stealing a political campaign sign from a yard and then lying about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1983, a year after Nicholas L. Bissell Jr. became Somerset County Prosecutor, he filed a lawsuit to remove Franklin Township's Mayor from office. His complaint? Misconduct in office, he said, because she had distributed fliers at a township Council meeting criticizing a police investigation of several rapes.</p>
        <p>In 1989, William B. Wahl, the director of Somerset County's governing body, the Board of Chosen Freeholders, apparently angered Mr. Bissell by questioning raises for his staff and demanding that the County Auditor audit the Prosecutor's office. Subsequently, Mr. Bissell accused Mr. Wahl of stealing a political campaign sign from a yard and then lying about it.</p>
        <p>Complaints that Mr. Bissell had abused his power were made with the New Jersey Attorney General's office on behalf of both the Mayor and Mr. Wahl. No action was taken against Mr. Bissell in either case, the lawyers who made the complaints said.</p>
        <p>These stories and others told in interviews over the last week raise questions about how diligently the Attorney General's office monitored Mr. Bissell's performance or that of any of New Jersey's other 20 county prosecutors. They also raise questions about New Jersey's system of choosing and approving its prosecutors: they are nominated by the Governor and formally reviewed by the State Senate Judiciary Committee, which has no staff or money to investigate nominees.</p>
        <p>In the wake of Mr. Bissell's conviction last May on charges of abuse of power, embezzlement and tax and mail fraud, and of his suicide Nov. 26, the Attorney General, Peter Verniero, has begun to review the ways his office supervises New Jersey's 21 county prosecutors. For the moment, Mr. Verniero said, he is not certain how extensive any changes will be.</p>
        <p>''Reform might be too strong a word,'' he said. ''I don't want to indict the entire system because of one prosecutor gone astray.''</p>
        <p>But Edwin H. Stier, who was director of the Attorney General's Division of Criminal Justice -- the office that oversees the county prosecutors -- from 1977 to 1982, the year Mr. Bissell began his first term, said it was time for a major overhaul of the way New Jersey selects its county prosecutors and evaluates their performance in office. He said the ''terrible tragedy'' of the Bissell case should serve as ''a model to learn from'' and guide changes.</p>
        <p>''The potential for harm is so great that you can't say we have 20 good ones and one bad one,'' Mr. Stier said. ''You need 21 good ones.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stier, whose law offices are in Somerset County, said he had known Mr. Bissell for 15 years. ''Bissell was operating on or way over the edge,'' Mr. Stier said. ''That was clear if you look at how his office was run.''</p>
        <p>But he called Mr. Bissell shrewd and engaging and said he curried favor with his supervisors in the Attorney General's office by aligning himself with them against more independent-minded county prosecutors seeking greater latitude for their offices. County prosecutors, he said, exercise considerable law enforcement power and the state, in its obligation to insure their public accountability, should emphasize that prosecutors must always exercise their authority with restraint.</p>
        <p>He suggested two changes: requiring a specific minimum level of experience, preferably in criminal justice administration, and establishing, after a prosecutor takes office, a specific set of criteria to judge performance, especially the exercise of authority and discretion. The state law giving the Attorney General supervisory power over prosecutors makes evaluations optional. Mr. Stier suggested the process become mandatory and include well defined standards of conduct.</p>
        <p>Chuck Davis, a spokesman for the Attorney General's office, said Mr. Bissell's file in Trenton did not contain any formal written evaluations by superiors.</p>
        <p>He said there were 14 complaints in it, filed since he took office 14  years ago. Mr. Davis declined to disclose the nature of any of them, on grounds some contained confidential information and some were sent to the Attorney General anonymously. He also did not say how the complaints were dealt with.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Franklin Township Mayor, Nancy Henry, her lawyer, Henry Furst, said: ''Nobody did a thing. They never called me. They never asked me about it.'' It was not clear whether her case was among the 14. Mr. Stier, who made the complaint on behalf of Mr. Wahl, the director of the freeholders, said he was told afterward that the case had been investigated and that Mr. Bissell had done nothing wrong.</p>
        <p>Mr. Furst said he sent a booklet of documents, including a strong rebuke of Mr. Bissell by a Federal appeals court in Philadelphia, to the New Jersey Senate's Judiciary Committee in 1988. At the time, it was considering Gov. Thomas H. Kean's nomination of Mr. Bissell for a second five-year term. Mr. Furst said the committee sent him a thank-you note but nothing about its view of the Bissell-Henry fight.</p>
        <p>It apparently did little to tarnish the committee's view of Mr. Bissell. On May 26, 1988, it approved Mr. Bissell's reappointment by voice vote. A week later, the full Senate unanimously approved it.</p>
        <p>A State Senator on the committee at the time, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said he did not recall any criticism of the Bissell renomination. The committee, he said, has no staff or money to conduct its own investigations of nominees and routinely ''rubber stamps'' the Governor's recommendations unless strong objections are raised.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bissell's biggest booster in the Senate, John H. Ewing, a Republican from Somerset County, said he eagerly approved the Prosecutor's renomination. Under longstanding courtesy rules in the New Jersey Senate, all nominees for county prosecutor must have the backing of the senators in their county.</p>
        <p>Senator Ewing said he did not recall anyone from the Governor's office or the Judiciary Committee raising questions about Mr. Bissell.</p>
        <p>''He was tough on criminals,'' Mr. Ewing said. ''I O.K.'d him, the county chairman O.K.'d him. What he was doing was not brought to my attention as a reason to hold him up.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey is one of only a few states that choose their county prosecutors through nomination by the governor and confirmation by a legislative body; in most states, they are elected. Generally, appointed prosecutors undergo a greater degree of prenomination screening and background checks and tighter supervision by supervisors once in office, said James Polley, director of government affairs for the National District Attorneys Association in Alexandria, Va.</p>
        <p>At the time of his renomination and in the months afterward, Mr. Bissell was cultivating his image as a hard-nosed foe of drug dealers and endearing himself in Trenton with his seizures of drug suspects' money and property. In the 1990's, his office confiscated $3.7 million in cash alone. Since his conviction and suicide, the Attorney General's office has started poring over old spending records in an effort to insure that all the seized money was spent on law enforcement projects as required by state law, Mr. Davis, the Attorney General's spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>While in office, Mr. Bissell guarded these records closely and routinely rebuffed efforts by one Somerset County citizen, John Paff, to inspect them. Mr. Paff said he went to Trenton in 1992 and asked the Criminal Justice Division to compel Mr. Bissell to release documents on the seized money. The officials refused, Mr. Paff said.</p>
        <p>Two drug suspects who were targets of Mr. Bissell's office, Isaac Wright and Gregory Fuhs, took their grievances against him to court and prevailed this fall after years of legal fighting. Mr. Wright won a new trial on a drug kingpin charge after detectives testified that a 1989 cocaine seizure in the case was conducted without a search warrant and that Mr. Wright's accomplices gave perjured testimony against him in exchange for leniency. Mr. Fuhs's case dates to his arrest in 1988, after Mr. Bissell began his second term, on charges of growing marijuana plants at his home. Immediately afterward, Mr. Bissell's office seized $65,000 from Mr. Fuhs's bank account. In early October, a jury returned a $50,000 malpractice verdict against Mr. Fuhs's lawyer after finding that the money was confiscated without Mr. Fuhs's written consent.</p>
        <p>Throughout his second term, Mr. Bissell kept seized funds in his office or in a bank founded by a friend, in violation of state regulations requiring that seized drug money be turned over to the county treasurer. The funds were audited by his bookkeeper and friend, Thomas Wagner, who ultimately testified in Mr. Bissell's Federal trial last spring that he helped Mr. Bissell and his wife, Barbara, file false Federal income and corporate income tax returns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bissell was also convicted of skimming about $146,000 from two gasoline stations he owned in Somerset County, of threatening to plant cocaine in the car of an oil company official who complained the stations were dirty, and of operating the stations in violation of state ethics laws prohibiting county prosecutors from earning outside income.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors said the crimes occurred during the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Del Tufo, New Jersey's Attorney General from 1990 to 1994, said he and his top aides in the Criminal Justice Division had ''absolutely no knowledge'' that Mr. Bissell had committed any crimes. And he said he personally did not know of complaints against Mr. Bissell during his tenure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Del Tufo praised him for creating a training academy for police officers and firefighters, broadening drug education programs in schools, and helping with crackdowns on carjackings in adjacent counties. He described him as messianic and dynamic, as well as arrogant and abrasive.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes his judgment was flawed and he acted too precipitously,'' Mr. Del Tufo said. But he said he was unaware of any criminal wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>''I think hindsight is at play here and I think it's unfair,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
