<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unitarians Striking Chord of Spirituality</title>
    <meta content="08UNIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unitarian Universalist Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6DC123FF93BA35751C1A960958260" item-length="1402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unitarians Striking Chord of Spirituality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses shift under way within Unitarian-Universalist Assn, small movement long known as home for people who would put their faith in reason and social action rather than in God; lately Unitarian clergy members say that their congregations are increasingly exploring ritual, forms of prayer and meditation, candle lighting and music drawn from other religious sources; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Rev. Thomas J. S. Mikelson told his congregation one Sunday in April that he would end the worship with a healing service for anyone who felt physically or emotionally afflicted, he had no idea how church members would respond. With other ministers on the staff, he stood there, he said, ''waiting to see if anyone would come down the aisle.''</p>
        <p>Although healing services, with prayer and a laying on of hands, can be found in ritualized form among some Episcopalians and Roman Catholics, and in more free-flowing style among Pentecostals, Mr. Mikelson is the senior minister at First Unitarian Church, a congregation that belongs to a movement long known as a bastion of rationalism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Rev. Thomas J. S. Mikelson told his congregation one Sunday in April that he would end the worship with a healing service for anyone who felt physically or emotionally afflicted, he had no idea how church members would respond. With other ministers on the staff, he stood there, he said, ''waiting to see if anyone would come down the aisle.''</p>
        <p>Although healing services, with prayer and a laying on of hands, can be found in ritualized form among some Episcopalians and Roman Catholics, and in more free-flowing style among Pentecostals, Mr. Mikelson is the senior minister at First Unitarian Church, a congregation that belongs to a movement long known as a bastion of rationalism.</p>
        <p>So, when 30 people came forward that morning, one-fifth of his congregation, ''it just blew us away,'' Mr. Mikelson said. He repeated the healing service in October, and 40 people walked down the aisle.</p>
        <p>In a broad sense, the response he drew is a sign of the times, of the rising popular interest in spiritual experience, which has lifted books about the soul, angels and near-death experiences onto the best-seller lists.</p>
        <p>But the events at Mr. Mikelson's church also point to a shift under way within the Unitarian-Universalist Association, a small movement long known as a home for people who would put their faith in reason and social action, rather than in God. Lately, Unitarian clergy members say, their congregations are increasingly exploring ritual, forms of prayer and meditation, candle-lighting and music, drawn from Western, East Asian, American Indian and other religious sources.</p>
        <p>Some social scientists see in Unitarians a barometer of what is happening between organized religion and the larger society. Nancy Ammerman, a professor of sociology of religion at the Hartford Seminary in Connecticut, said that for decades, Unitarians had been known as no-nonsense humanists, believers in the human ability to tackle any problem, an approach that she said reflected the ''dominant motif'' of Western culture since the Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>But now, Professor Ammerman said, ''they are recognizing the degree to which we live in a very pluralistic society, and their incorporation of spirituality is very pluralistic.''</p>
        <p>Some Unitarian leaders suggest that the spiritual searching within the association is a rounding-out of their identity.</p>
        <p>''In Unitarian circles,'' said the Rev. Forrest Church, senior minister at All Souls Church in Manhattan, ''we're beginning to complement the work of the mind with the work of the heart and the work of the soul. I recognize in my own congregation a growing hunger for spirituality.''</p>
        <p>Numbering only 210,000 members (up about 10 percent over a decade ago), the Unitarians are a varied lot, ranging from people at the most liberal edges of Christianity to practitioners of Zen Buddhism and New Age rituals as well as humanists, agnostics and atheists.</p>
        <p>Shunning a creed, the association calls itself a liberal faith, whose members have tended to embrace political and social causes that reflected that orientation. These include the United Nations and the civil rights movement and, more recently, gay rights and abortion rights.</p>
        <p>But Unitarians have often described themselves in the negative, some saying that they were not Christian, others that they were not religious, and most everyone declaring that they were not fundamentalists. ''The last generation of Unitarian-Universalists were fleeing Methodism, Roman Catholicism, Judaism,'' said the Rev. Scott Alexander, a Boston Unitarian. ''What this generation is fleeing is the emptiness of the culture.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Alexander asked other ministers to contribute to a book on spiritual exercises, he heard from men and women whose practices range from the traditional to the offbeat. Some wrote about daily prayer, fasting or yoga; some said they tithed their incomes to charity; others reported discovering the transcendent in gardening or cooking.</p>
        <p>At Unity Church-Unitarian in St. Paul, the Rev. Roy Phillips's congregation has adopted an idea developed by local Catholics, by forming groups devoted to ''spiritual deepening,'' with discussion, reflection and readings, to build a basis for social action in behalf of the needy.</p>
        <p>Professor Ammerman said the many directions in which Unitarians seemed to be going posed a challenge of centrifugal proportions. ''You have a movement that has to deal with a lot of internal diversity, and has to build an identity around that,'' she said. ''And that's not easy.''</p>
        <p>Unitarian officials say they do not worry about spiritual eclecticism. ''We've never gathered on the basis of a common metaphysics,'' said the Rev. John Buehrens, the association's president, ''but rather a practical endeavor in spiritual growth and common commitment.''</p>
        <p>In his office at Unitarian-Universalist headquarters, a brick town house on Beacon Hill in Boston, Mr. Buehrens quoted the Rev. Theodore Parker, a famous 19th-century Unitarian, saying that the forms of religion are transitory, created for people, not the other way around.</p>
        <p>Denise Davidoff, the association's moderator, or highest-elected lay member, said Unitarians were drawn together by an increasing willingness to talk about their own beliefs and values, and also to work with other religious liberals -- for example, in coalitions like the Washington-based Interfaith Alliance, formed to counter politically active Christian conservatives.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people, myself included, who had grown up in a God-based family and culture, and who walked away from a theology of hierarchy and patriarchy, found ways to re-define a God,'' said Ms. Davidoff, who was raised in a conservative Jewish family.</p>
        <p>The growing ease that Unitarians now feel in talking about God, she said, ''has coincided with our willingness to go out and work with other people of faith.''</p>
        <p>For some Unitarian clergy members, the AIDS crisis fed the spiritual interest. Unitarian churches were among the first to openly welcome gay men and lesbians.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1980's, the Rev. Kim K. Crawford Harvie saw AIDS ravage the congregation she served in Provincetown, Mass. She came to realize that members needed rituals to honor the dying and give the living emotional release. ''One thing we needed to do was good memorial services,'' she said. ''The other thing we had to do well was celebrate, because you can't just grieve all the time.''</p>
        <p>The experience affected Ms. Crawford Harvie's theology. ''I've got to say, in a sound bite, suffering will do it to you,'' she said. ''Traditional Unitarians believed death was it. You're cold -- boom! -- it's over. I don't think I believe that any more.''</p>
        <p>She now serves as the pastor of Arlington Street Church, across from the Boston Public Garden, where she encourages people to light candles at Sunday services and to share their hopes and anxieties before the congregation.</p>
        <p>At First Unitarian Church in Cambridge, Mr. Mikelson spoke of his own pilgrimage. ''In the early '70's, I called myself a religious humanist,'' he said, sitting in an office whose windows faced Cambridge's old burying ground, where Harvard University's earliest presidents lie. ''I didn't talk about God.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mikelson now describes himself as a theist, a believer in the existence of the divine. ''It opens the door for me to feel a relationship with a personal God, to pray, to express my gratitude for my life and the world, and to have a deeper sense of vocation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As for the healing services, he displayed a stack of recent books by doctors exploring the relationship between faith and healing. Among them was ''Timeless Healing'' (Simon &amp; Schuster) by Dr. Herbert Benson, an associate professor at the Harvard Medical School.</p>
        <p>''If the doctors are out there on the frontier, exploring the power of spirituality,'' Mr. Mikelson said, ''shouldn't religious leaders be out there with them?''</p>
        <p>As for the broader interest in spirituality, he said, ''Our denomination really romanced with humanism'' for decades, a process he called ''very progressive and very daring'' for its time. ''Now,'' he added, ''there's a rich exploration of spiritual alternatives to humanism.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
