<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brown Hasn't Stopped Believing</title>
    <meta content="16rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/16/sports/basketball/16rhoden.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1740151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Raptors</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Toronto Raptors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Larry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4D8133EF935A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brown Hasn't Stopped Believing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Brown Hasn't Stopped Believing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William C. Rhoden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column discusses New York Knicks' win over Toronto Raptors, which could give Knicks coach Larry Brown momentum to turn 15-37 team around (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY favorite slogan from the 1960's is Adam Clayton Powell Jr.'s exhortation: ''Keep the faith, baby.''</p>
        <p>More than ''I have a dream'' or ''Power to the people,'' ''Keep the faith'' is hip, timeless wisdom that embraces perseverance, toughness and hope in a brighter tomorrow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The responsibility for victories and losses falls on Larry Brown's shoulders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY favorite slogan from the 1960's is Adam Clayton Powell Jr.'s exhortation: ''Keep the faith, baby.''</p>
        <p>More than ''I have a dream'' or ''Power to the people,'' ''Keep the faith'' is hip, timeless wisdom that embraces perseverance, toughness and hope in a brighter tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The Knicks family -- all you who have suffered since November and will continue to suffer until April -- should adopt this slogan as your mantra.</p>
        <p>You're going to have to keep the faith.</p>
        <p>The Knicks (15-37) are young, demoralized and, on many nights, disoriented. But nights like last night offer a glimmer of hope when the Knicks play well from start to finish and actually win.</p>
        <p>The blame game is played at no higher level than in New York: we climb over each other for credit and are quick to point fingers. Madison Square Garden is up to the rafters in accusations, but for now, let's just deal with the Knicks.</p>
        <p>Most of the blame for their woes has been aimed at Isiah Thomas, the team president. In fact, the responsibility for victories and losses falls on Larry Brown. From November to April, Brown is the maestro, the alchemist. He is the master teacher and Hall of Fame coach who can beat you with his players, then turn around and beat you with your own.</p>
        <p>We'll deal with Thomas's performance at the season's end.</p>
        <p>''We're 14-30-something and playing terribly, and nobody talks about people being out, nobody talks about how young this team is,'' Brown said yesterday. ''But it's my responsibility. I've said 100 times: I got to coach them better, and I believe that. You can look at my track record: I've been in a lot of situations like this but not in this environment. The reality is that there's enough blame to go around.''</p>
        <p>I'll give Brown and Thomas the benefit of the doubt. Thomas won an N.C.A.A. championship at Indiana and won two N.B.A. championships with the Detroit Pistons. He has run the Continental Basketball Association, had an ownership share with the Toronto Raptors and coached the Indiana Pacers. Brown won an N.C.A.A. championship at Kansas and an N.B.A. championship with the Pistons. Between them they have an idea of what it takes to win. These Knicks are part of an evolving picture.</p>
        <p>''I'm hopeful that this thing gets over, because it's never any fun to go through a period like this and read your names in the paper,'' Brown said.</p>
        <p>''You lack confidence. It's a hard thing to fight through, but that's the reality -- we've lost all these games and we just got to fight back.''</p>
        <p>Every losing season needs a face, and the face of the Knicks' free fall has become Eddy Curry, a 6-foot-11 center. Curry was the fourth pick of the 2001 draft. The Knicks obtained him from the Bulls for a 2006 first-round pick and a package of players and other picks.</p>
        <p>Thomas gambled that the 23-year-old Curry had an ocean of talent he hadn't begun to tap; Curry feels he has been letting the organization down, and to an extent he has. But there are nights like last night against Toronto when you can see a glimmer of potential. Curry was a beast inside, scoring 18 points, including a much-needed basket with 30.6 seconds left that gave the Knicks a 96-93 lead en route to a 98-96 victory.</p>
        <p>''I try to talk to him all the time,'' Brown said. ''Obviously, when we traded for him there was the talk that, 'Hey, you're getting a young center who's the future of your team.' I can see that he's taking a lot of this pretty hard, that he feels a responsibility for the problems we're having. And I tell him all the time, this is about 15 guys and a coaching staff, it's not about one guy, and he's just got to keep trying to get better. He's got to keep competing and not give in.''</p>
        <p>Brown said: ''The thing I got to make him understand -- he's 22 years old. I told him every day it's like his freshman year. He's in a market that they look at him and realize what we gave up and the expectations are pretty great.</p>
        <p>''It's tough, but I do believe there's a real chance here, and I like that, I like that the expectations are high. I like that they love this sport here and expect excellence. That's why you're so miserable. Not that you're not miserable in other places that you coach, but coming here I felt like if we ever played the right way, an appealing way, it would help our sport, because there is no better place to do it than in New York.''</p>
        <p>Before Brown left yesterday's shoot-around, he said he looked forward to the last two months of the season. The pattern for many of Brown's teams is that by midseason either everybody has bought in or been shipped out.</p>
        <p>It will be curious to see what happens to these Knicks. I'd be surprised if they continue to be terrible. Expect effort but not miracles.</p>
        <p>''As a player you got to keep believing that things are going change,'' Curry said after last night's game. ''If we give up, it's only going to get worse. We always got to believe that things are going to change.''</p>
        <p>Keep the faith, baby.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
