<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From: Port Chester;What About College? 'We'll Worry About It Later,' Father Says</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="835776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MULTIPLE BIRTHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">QUADRUPLETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARTIFICIAL INSEMINATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED HOSPITAL MEDICAL CENTER (PORT CHESTER, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">AMES, LYNNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEFKOWITZ, COCO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEFKOWITZ, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Infertility</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Artificial Insemination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reproduction (Biological)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D61F39F933A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1234" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From: Port Chester;What About College? 'We'll Worry About It Later,' Father Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AMES, LYNNE</byline>
      <dateline>PORT CHESTER</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYTHING is coming in fours these days for Coco and Bruce Lefkowitz of Rye. They have four cribs, four highchairs, four infant car seats, four swing sets, four rocking toys shaped like kangaroos. And they have four tiny babies conceived in a glass laboratory dish eight months ago and born at United Hospital Medical Center here between 2:55 and 2:57 P.M. on Feb. 21.</p>
        <p>The quadruplets came into being through in vitro fertilization. Mrs. Lefkowitz's eggs were fertilized by Mr. Lefkowitz's sperm in a petri dish; four  of the resulting embryos were implanted in her womb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYTHING is coming in fours these days for Coco and Bruce Lefkowitz of Rye. They have four cribs, four highchairs, four infant car seats, four swing sets, four rocking toys shaped like kangaroos. And they have four tiny babies conceived in a glass laboratory dish eight months ago and born at United Hospital Medical Center here between 2:55 and 2:57 P.M. on Feb. 21.</p>
        <p>The quadruplets came into being through in vitro fertilization. Mrs. Lefkowitz's eggs were fertilized by Mr. Lefkowitz's sperm in a petri dish; four  of the resulting embryos were implanted in her womb.</p>
        <p>Four embryos are considered optimal in such procedures because, statistically, it is likely that only one will take hold and develop into a fetus. For four of four to thrive and result in living, healthy quadruplets is "very, very rare," said Dr. Ronald Reiss, senior clinician at IVF America, an in vitro fertilization program at United Hospital.</p>
        <p>And here they were, on a recent night at the hospital, each in an Isolette, and though seven weeks premature, their features were well defined, chiseled looking; their bodies, although minuscule, looked graceful and well proportioned. They even have distinct facial expressions and, say their parents, personalities.</p>
        <p>Kyle Ann, with a birth weight of 2 pounds 8 ounces, is the tiniest and, Mr. and Mrs. Lefkowitz, the feistiest. The next smallest -- and the most vocal -- is Coby Tyde born at 2 pounds 14 ounces. (His name is a variation of Cody and a reference to the tides in Mrs. Lefkowitz's home town, Ocean City, N.J.) Jenna Lynne, 3 pounds 7 ounces at birth, is the serene type, as is her brother, Trent  James, whose birth weight of 3 pounds 15 ounces made him the giant of the group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lefkowitz, 30, vice president of sales for a marketing company, is a 6-foot-7 former college basketball player who can fit two babies in the crook of each arm. Mrs. Lefkowitz, marketing executive for a sports equipment company, is 32 and 5 foot 10 and can cuddle them all on her lap. She observed that her physique -- "long bones" -- made her particularly well suited to carry so many children during pregnancy. Both parents have posed for many pictures and answered an onslaught of questions from reporters.</p>
        <p>"People ask us, What about college, how will we pay for everything with quadruplets?" Mr. Lefkowitz said. "We tell them, 'We will worry about it later.' Jobs, careers, all of this pales in comparison to the joy of having a family."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lefkowitz, who has 10 brothers and sisters, said: "This is what it's all about. Instant family. People ask us, How long were we trying to get pregnant? We tell them we tried for seven years; the fact is, we've been married seven years, and we never not tried, so to speak. We never used birth control because  we've always wanted children as soon as possible."</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Lefkowitz did not get pregnant after several years, she and Mr. Lefkowitz consulted fertility specialists. After myriad tests and unsuccessful procedures, they went to IVF America.</p>
        <p>Dr. Reiss gave Mrs. Lefkowitz a drug to increase the production of eggs in her ovaries; she then underwent a retrieval in which eggs, still floating in fluid, were withdrawn. The 10 eggs retrieved were placed in a petri dish, mixed  with Mr. Lefkowitz's sperm and incubated for 24 hours in the hope that they would become fertilized.</p>
        <p>Doctors then picked "the four most viable looking" of the new embryos, Dr. Reiss said, and these were implanted in Mrs. Lefkowitz's uterus. Not long afterward, she had a positive pregnancy test. Then shortly after that she received another momentous piece of news: a sonogram showed four developing fetuses. Mr. Lefkowitz began carrying photo reproductions of his wife's sonograms in his wallet, showing friends and business associates his developing  family.</p>
        <p>When the babies had been gestating for seven and a half months, Mrs. Lefkowitz underwent a caesarean section to give birth to the quadruplets. (If such large multiple births are allowed to go full term, severe complications can result for the mother, Dr. Reiss explained.) Dr. Modestus Lee, director of neonatology at United Hospital, was there to take over their care immediately. No sooner were their first breaths drawn than the babies were started on treatments necessary to sustain their lives.</p>
        <p>Because premature babies' lungs are not fully developed, and they run a high  risk of respiratory problems, Trent, Jenna and Coby were given oxygen through their nostrils. Kyle breathed on her own; after three days, the others did too.</p>
        <p>The digestive systems of premature infants are also fragile. All four infants were fed an intravenous solution consisting largely of fats, carbohydrates and vitamins for a week. Coby, who developed gastrointestinal problems, is still being nourished intravenously.</p>
        <p>Jenna, Kyle and Trent are getting their mother's milk, which is pumped from her breasts and given to them through a naso-gastric tube. The most serious digestive complication to watch for, Dr. Lee said, is necrotizing enterocolitis, in which insufficient blood flow through vessels of the intestines can lead to overgrowth of potentially lethal bacteria.</p>
        <p>Other hurdles for premature infants may include impaired brain function and general susceptibility to massive infection because of the extreme immaturity of their immune systems. So far, the Lefkowitz babies show no signs of any of those devastating problems. "I expect them to grow up to be normal, healthy children," Dr. Lee said.</p>
        <p>For that -- and for their good fortune in giving birth at all after so many years of trying -- Coco and Bruce Lefkowitz are supremely grateful. They still cling, however, to the small superstitions common to many new parents, magnified perhaps by the potential precariousness of their infants' situations.</p>
        <p>During the pregnancy, Mr. Lefkowitz picked up the habit of fidgeting with whatever latex glove was nearby in whatever examining room he happened to be in; now for good luck he carries one around and blows it up like a five-fingered balloon when he is about to have a serious talk with a doctor.</p>
        <p>For the parents, the future is filled with hope, although they know that their babies will have to remain in the hospital at least a few more weeks. Looking beyond that, they said that as their children grew, they would try to cultivate a strong sense of individual identity in each one while also fostering the ties between such closely joined siblings.</p>
        <p>The children, who are not identical, should be as different as any four brothers and sisters.</p>
        <p>"We don't plan to dress them alike," Mrs. Lefkowitz said, "except maybe when  they are very small on holidays, just for a little fun."</p>
        <p>Some reporters asked the parents if they intended to try for more children. "We tell them we don't know," Mr. Lefkowitz said. "We also tell them that we still have three frozen embryos in storage. We tell them, You never know . . ."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
