<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Maturing Of an Investment In Ballet's Future</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="835783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOYNER, WILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FELD, ELIOT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5D61F39F933A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Maturing Of an Investment In Ballet's Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILL JOYNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOYNER, WILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEANING INTO THE FAINT GLOW from lamps on a monitor table at the back of the  Joyce Theater, Eliot Feld is displaying several of his many talents. One of these is, as he puts it, "dissatisfaction well addressed."</p>
        <p>It is two days before the premiere of his ballet "Meshugana Dance," and the choreographer is conducting a dress rehearsal. As he consults with his associates at the table, he uses adjectives like "gruesome" and "unpleasant" for certain tentative lighting adjustments but does so in a collegial sort of banter. Still, the tone is exacting; there's no letting up here. It doesn't matter that the dancers are children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEANING INTO THE FAINT GLOW from lamps on a monitor table at the back of the  Joyce Theater, Eliot Feld is displaying several of his many talents. One of these is, as he puts it, "dissatisfaction well addressed."</p>
        <p>It is two days before the premiere of his ballet "Meshugana Dance," and the choreographer is conducting a dress rehearsal. As he consults with his associates at the table, he uses adjectives like "gruesome" and "unpleasant" for certain tentative lighting adjustments but does so in a collegial sort of banter. Still, the tone is exacting; there's no letting up here. It doesn't matter that the dancers are children.</p>
        <p>On the bare stage, against a backdrop of sky blue and white, 14-year-old Armand Pretlow is doing an intricate solo to wailing klezmer music. Dressed in an elegantly ragtag costume that includes a shirt with only one sleeve, mismatched slippers (green and yellow) and a red headband, he stomps, flops, somersaults and mimes. Then, from a kneeling position, he launches into a series of rolling, sideways flips that are punctuated with a foot pointed skyward.</p>
        <p>"Lift the leg!" Mr. Feld yells after one flip. "Thattaboy!" he yells after two. "Yuck!" he yells after a weaker No. 3, but he laughs proudly.</p>
        <p>This is Kids Dance, a very serious business indeed.</p>
        <p>Kids Dance, a presentation for young audiences, features about 45 dancers from the New Ballet School, which Mr. Feld founded in 1977 as an affiliate to his company, Feld Ballets/NY. On Feb. 24, Kids Dance started its third season at the Joyce, and it will share the marquee with the company through March 31. It has grown from 3 to 5 to 12 performance dates, which says a lot about its popularity but perhaps even more about the evolution of the school, a now-venerable social experiment.</p>
        <p>These days, New York City arts institutions are ominously vocal about the need to bring more young people into concert halls and museums, and to take more performers into classrooms. In dance, the Joyce and City Center, in particular,  have broadened their programs for children and their effort to get the professional community to pay more attention to the public schools. Mr. Feld is  someone who can say he acted along these lines years ago, if for his own reasons.</p>
        <p>"I did it because I felt it was essential to the vitality of what I was engaged in," he explains. "I'm a choreographer, and I wanted to train young, gifted people to become dancers because that's my material for making dances."</p>
        <p>Befitting his slight build and whitish-gray hair, the 53-year-old Mr. Feld is both boyish and fatherly, and when he traces the life of the New Ballet School,  his idealism is evident but tempered by much experience.</p>
        <p>SOON AFTER HIS COMPANY moved into its extensive studio space at 890 Broadway, a building just north of Union Square that is also occupied by American Ballet Theater, Mr. Feld tried to start a traditional ballet school. But he couldn't find enough talented students.</p>
        <p>"Then one day I was coming down from the Upper West Side to the studio on the subway," he recalls. "There were some elementary-school children going on a field trip, and their excitement was palpable. They were beautiful with potential. I thought, there are hundreds of thousands of children in the city's  public schools, some of whom undoubtedly have a talent for dancing but almost none of whom have an opportunity to discover their gift."</p>
        <p>He and his associates at the Original Ballets Foundation, the corporate entity of which Feld Ballets/NY is a part, approached the Board of Education. Eventually an agreement was reached by which the New Ballet School would provide a tuition-free series of lessons to students selected through auditions at about 25 public schools. The students -- third, fourth and fifth graders -- would be brought to 890 Broadway by public-school buses, and students who showed sufficient potential and desire could continue indefinitely.</p>
        <p>"Over the years," Mr. Feld says, "what became clear was that the concept was  right: there were talented children. But the scale was wrong: there weren't enough of those children. There's a certain dynamic to a dance class that requires certain numbers."</p>
        <p>About six years ago, the audition teams expanded their pool of public schools. Now, auditions are held at 400 schools, 200 a year, with each school visited every other year. About 900 beginners are invited annually to attend ballet classes. And the New Ballet School now has about 300 continuing students, many of whom do their academic studies at P.S. Dance, a new occupant at 890 Broadway. The ethnic makeup of the 300 has ended up reflecting the makeup of the city's public schools, which means that the majority are black, Asian-American and Hispanic.</p>
        <p>The 40 performers in Kids Dance are children, ages 11 to 17, who have been at the school for at least three years and have learned various examples of Mr. Feld's repertory. As the students get older, they are progressively treated by their teachers as serious dancers, though most will not become professionals.</p>
        <p>Students who do have professional promise are invited to Feld Ballets/ NY classes and rehearsals as observers and then as apprentices. This season, 6 of the 19 performers in the company are former New Ballet School students and 2 are apprentices, a jump that indicates a new stage in Mr. Feld's experiment. He puts it this way: "What has changed is that now that many dancers from the school are joining the company, the children who come to the school see people like themselves and say, 'We can do that.' Their self-image is better."</p>
        <p>One former student who became a company member last summer is 18-year-old Ha-Chi Yu, a featured dancer in Mr. Feld's solemn "Gnossiennes." She remembers her two-year transition from school to company as a difficult time -- she had to put her academic studies on hold, for instance -- but one well worth it for someone like herself who had always wanted to be a dancer.</p>
        <p>"That's one attribute of the New Ballet School," she says. "If you want to dance, you're dancing. They're giving you the life style. At a certain point, you're dancing so much that you can't possibly be anything other than a dancer."</p>
        <p>Armand Pretlow, who was recruited from P.S. 110 on the Lower East Side six years ago, is clearly gifted, but now at the Joyce, he's not thinking about a career. He's thinking about "Meshugana Dance" -- a work that's true to its title, which uses a variation of the Yiddish word for crazy -- and how to get it right. "We've had some ups and downs about it," he says, "but we pulled together, and it has turned out well. It's an excellent ballet."</p>
        <p>AND THE DEMANDS OF ballet are what all of this is about. "Ballet is an old form," says Mr. Feld, a Brooklyn native who was accepted at the School of American Ballet when he was 11 years old. "But unless it is an evolving form, it's a dead form. There are ways I understand that conceptually, but the specifics I can't begin to understand. And I don't need to. They just need to be given soil in which to express their nature."</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
