<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How a Plane Crash Changed the Trip To Buy Groceries</title>
    <meta content="05PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="COMMUNITY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="899404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Port Norris (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DC1639F936A35752C0A961958260" item-length="1258" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How a Plane Crash Changed the Trip To Buy Groceries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <dateline>PORT NORRIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plane that crashed into only supermarket in Port Norris, NJ, in Dec has brought community together, with black and white churches jointly sponsoring bus to carry shoppers to supermarket 18 miles away; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are vast spaces between buildings along Main Street where houses and shops used to stand, ghosts of the prosperous past of this tiny Cumberland County town. So, what is most noticeable now is not what's here, but what isn't.</p>
        <p>Mostly gone is the oyster industry that boomed in the first half of the century and then was devastated by marine parasites. With it went the doctors, auto dealerships,  restaurants, clothing shops, ice cream parlors, the barbershop and the movie theater. The storefront pool hall, which somehow escaped demolition, is boarded up and covered with vines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are vast spaces between buildings along Main Street where houses and shops used to stand, ghosts of the prosperous past of this tiny Cumberland County town. So, what is most noticeable now is not what's here, but what isn't.</p>
        <p>Mostly gone is the oyster industry that boomed in the first half of the century and then was devastated by marine parasites. With it went the doctors, auto dealerships,  restaurants, clothing shops, ice cream parlors, the barbershop and the movie theater. The storefront pool hall, which somehow escaped demolition, is boarded up and covered with vines.</p>
        <p>And now the only food market for miles around is gone too, closed by a problem that literally fell from the sky on Dec. 8, when a single-engine plane crashed through the roof of Newcomb's Supermarket on Main Street.</p>
        <p>The accident -- which tore apart the only place that people with cars could buy a quart of milk or a loaf of bread -- has also served to bring the community together.</p>
        <p>Two Methodist congregations, one white and one black, have joined forces to produce a short-term solution, a bus to carry shoppers to a supermarket in Millville 18 miles away, and a long-term campaign to bring public transportation to the town of 2,000 people in the sparsely settled southern part of the state.</p>
        <p>SUSIE LOPEZ was working at the computer in the back of her store, writing up grocery orders for the coming week, when the small plane came through the roof.</p>
        <p>The building, a long hangar-like structure of concrete block that once housed a Chevrolet dealership, shook at the impact. Her two employees were safe, but the pilot, she later learned, was dead.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lopez, who bought the store seven years ago with her husband, Joe, has yet to hear from a contractor about what it will cost to repair damage to one of the trusses that support the store's roof. She cannot say when the store will reopen.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to delay anything,'' she said. ''This is my life; this is our income. Besides, a lot of people depend on us.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, five days after the crash, Chris Miller, the pastor of the First United Methodist Church on Main Street, got a call from Alice Reed, a former resident of Port Norris who had moved to Millville.</p>
        <p>''I think you should do something,'' she said. ''There are people in town who don't have transportation. And they don't have any food and no way of getting it.''</p>
        <p>The pastor was scheduled to speak the next morning to the men's group of the John Wesley United Methodist Church, an African-American congregation, several blocks away. He used the occasion to tell its pastor, the Rev. Joseph L. Scott, about the call.</p>
        <p>And the pastors, who had been looking for a project that could involve both congregations, come up with the bus plan.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, the two church's councils gave the plan their enthusiastic support and on Monday night about 10 members from the two churches met to work out details.</p>
        <p>Neither church has an office staff so David Ennis, assistant minister of Shiloh Baptist, another church in town, volunteered his.</p>
        <p>A few days later, Barney Hollinger, a township committeeman, heard about the plan.</p>
        <p>''When I went that night to the township committee meeting, I asked what the township could do,'' recalled Mr. Hollinger, a marina owner and part-time oysterman whose roots in Port Norris go back two generations.</p>
        <p>The commitee allocated emergency funding to cover the cost of bus rental: $30 a trip.</p>
        <p>SO far the turnout has been low. Since Dec. 20, only nine people have availed themselves of two trips; another was cancelled for lack of riders. The trips will continue until at least mid-January.</p>
        <p>''The need is greater than the response so far,'' said Mr. Miller. ''I'm a little disappointed but I don't think we made a mistake.''</p>
        <p>Neither does Roberta Horton, a woman on welfare who took advantage of the service twice.</p>
        <p>''It's really good to have,'' she said. ''If you run out of food or have no milk, there's no little store to run to. Unless you want to live on pizza '' she added referring to the lone pizzeria on Main Street.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Horton was interviewed on the bus returning from the Pathmark in Millville on Dec. 27. With her was her son, Mark, 21; her 19-year-old daughter, Laura, 19; Laura's 16-month-old son, Jeremy, and Mrs. Horton's friend, Daniel Evans.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of people around who need it,'' she said. ''A lot of people who can't walk and old people who can't shop for themselves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller, who has a commercial driver's license and was driving the schoolbus, said, ''Well, if you know of anyone like that, let us know and we'll shop for them.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Horton said a taxi to Millville costs about $20 to $25. Some people with cars make money ferrying people to shop, she said, and she pays one man $15 for a round trip.</p>
        <p>Mark Horton said he used to bicycle to work in Millville where he worked in a box factory until he was laid off. The trip took from half an hour to 45 minutes.</p>
        <p>''Casinos hire people,'' Mark Horton said. ''But you need a car to get to Millville to get the bus to Atlantic City.''</p>
        <p>CUMBERLAND COUNTY is economically depressed, compared to much of the rest of New Jersey. And Port Norris is poor, compared to the rest of the county.</p>
        <p>The county's unemployment rate is 8.7 percent compared with the state's 5.9, said Glenn Nickerson, public information officer for Cumberland County.</p>
        <p>Per capita income in Port Norris is only $10,401 annually, compared to $12,560 in the county as a whole.</p>
        <p>The county, which provides buses for seniors, would like to persuade NJ Transit to start a spur service for Port Norris.</p>
        <p>But Alan Maiman, NJ Transit's manager of bus service planning for the southern region of the state, said it's difficult to serve rural areas like Port Norris.</p>
        <p>''The mass in mass transit,'' Mr. Maiman said, ''means you need a concentration of people who are making similiar trips at similar times for similar purposes in significant numbers to justify a large vehicle like a bus to efficiently operate.''</p>
        <p>He said he and county officials are meeting early this month to brainstorm solutions, and on Thursday the two churches are holding a public meeting to see what can be done to bring public transportation to Port Norris.</p>
        <p>''My hope is that out of the tragedy of the loss of the pilot's life,'' said Pastor Scott, ''that some long-term change can be made.''</p>
        <p>As the Hortons got off the bus carrying three plastic bags of groceries, Roberta Horton called back cheerily to Pastor Miller, ''I'll see you next trip Friday then.''</p>
        <p>''All right,'' he replied. ''We'll be here.''</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
