<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congressional Roundup: Taxes; Legal Challenge To Voting Rule</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D7143CF93AA35751C0A963958260" item-length="440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congressional Roundup: Taxes; Legal Challenge To Voting Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using a century-old Supreme Court case as a model, lawyers for 15 Democratic Representatives and the League of Women Voters filed a lawsuit today challenging the constitutionality of a new rule in the House of Representatives that requires a three-fifths vote to approve any increase in the income tax rate.</p>
        <p>"It sets an extremely dangerous precedent that should not be allowed to stand," said Representative David E. Skaggs, a Colorado Democrat and the driving force behind the lawsuit. "While this year the supermajority requirement might apply just to taxes, next year it could be trade or civil rights or clean air legislation or even a declaration of war."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using a century-old Supreme Court case as a model, lawyers for 15 Democratic Representatives and the League of Women Voters filed a lawsuit today challenging the constitutionality of a new rule in the House of Representatives that requires a three-fifths vote to approve any increase in the income tax rate.</p>
        <p>"It sets an extremely dangerous precedent that should not be allowed to stand," said Representative David E. Skaggs, a Colorado Democrat and the driving force behind the lawsuit. "While this year the supermajority requirement might apply just to taxes, next year it could be trade or civil rights or clean air legislation or even a declaration of war."</p>
        <p>Two of the country's most respected constitutional lawyers are handling the complaint without compensation. They are Lloyd N. Cutler, a partner in the Washington-based law firm of Wilmer, Cutler and Pickering, and Bruce Ackerman, a professor at Yale Law School.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, filed in Federal District Court here, asks that the court toss out the three-fifths majority rule, first on the ground that it violates the constitutional principle of majority rule because it gives effective control to the minority during House debate on tax issues. Second, it says that the rule's prohibition on the consideration of any legislation containing a retroactive increase in Federal income taxes bars Congress from conducting its constitutionally mandated job of imposing and collecting taxes.</p>
        <p>The model for the lawsuit is an 1892 case, United States v. Ballin, in which the Supreme Court ruled that the House had an absolute and unchallenged right to make rules for its operations so long as it does "not ignore constitutional constraints or violate fundamental rights."</p>
        <p>The so-called supermajority rule -- House Rule XXI -- was one of the first changes imposed by Speaker Newt Gingrich when his Republican majority took control of the House on Jan. 4. With the majority Republicans and minority Democrats splitting along party lines, the measure was passed after a debate that was limited to 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>"The crucial question here is whether we can change the Constitution on the cheap," Mr. Ackerman said.</p>
        <p>Most votes in Congress are by simple majority: 50 percent of the voting members plus one. But the Constitution specifies seven instances in which a supermajority is required: for overriding a veto, ratifying a treaty, removing officials from office, expelling a representative or senator, proposing amendments to the Constitution, restoring certain rights of former rebels and determining whether a President is too disabled to continue to serve. JERRY GRAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
