<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Any Mayor, Politics Is Always Close to Home</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">STATEN ISLAND (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURNICK, JOYCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DD1030F93AA35751C0A963958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Any Mayor, Politics Is Always Close to Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joyce Purnick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURNICK, JOYCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI was going to Staten Island, the heartland in the city, the most Republican-voting borough of all five, the one known unofficially as Rudyland (even if it does still want to secede).</p>
        <p>Surely here, at a meeting in the auditorium of Susan B. Wagner High School, the Mayor would hear echoes of the national Republican cries for lower taxes and tougher anti-crime programs, complaints about government waste and affirmative action, welfare reform and Medicaid cuts. Wouldn't they denounce Mr. Giuliani's defection to the liberal Cuomo camp in last year's campaign for governor? Wouldn't they ask about the Republican revolution, or the new Governor's budget, or Newt Gingrich's book?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI was going to Staten Island, the heartland in the city, the most Republican-voting borough of all five, the one known unofficially as Rudyland (even if it does still want to secede).</p>
        <p>Surely here, at a meeting in the auditorium of Susan B. Wagner High School, the Mayor would hear echoes of the national Republican cries for lower taxes and tougher anti-crime programs, complaints about government waste and affirmative action, welfare reform and Medicaid cuts. Wouldn't they denounce Mr. Giuliani's defection to the liberal Cuomo camp in last year's campaign for governor? Wouldn't they ask about the Republican revolution, or the new Governor's budget, or Newt Gingrich's book?</p>
        <p>They didn't.</p>
        <p>In yet another reminder that "All politics is local," the savvy preachment of former Speaker of the House Thomas P. (Tip) O'Neill Jr., Staten Islanders at Mr. Giuliani's 14th town hall meeting asked about -- well, about Staten Island. For nearly an hour, mayoral aides raced up and down the aisles with cordless microphones, like young Oprahs and Donahues. And people asked about municipal meat and potatoes.</p>
        <p>Donald Gray and Fiorello Cicero asked about housing for the elderly planned by Seaview Hospital. Gabrielle Rozan worried about literacy services at the College of Staten Island. Lorraine Sorge asked about classroom overcrowding and whether school construction would keep up with residential development. One man even complained about a state regulation that, he said, forced him to get a commercial license plate for his private van. Several people said they were worried about rumors of a new homeless shelter in their neighborhood, and one young woman must have made Mr. Giuliani's evening by complaining about bureaucratic waste in the schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, who appears to have toned himself down since losing his temper at previous town hall meetings, was firm about reducing spending, but pleasant throughout. And, it is safe to assume, not only because he was among friends. The very fact that the Mayor continues to hold these local events -- a tradition Mayor Edward I. Koch began 17 years ago -- suggests he is thoroughly familiar with Mr. O'Neill's advice.</p>
        <p>PUNDITS make much of large national issues, and of Mr. Giuliani's alleged defection, and there is plenty to say about both. But the Mayor clearly realizes that at least at the local level, ideology is not what drives most voters. Their needs do. "They don't want to use this opportunity for a Harvard debate," recalled Mr. Koch, who says that the meetings, which sometimes influenced his policies, focused on quality-of-life issues.</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Fran Reiter, who oversees Mr. Giuliani's meetings, said it's the same today. "People don't want to debate homelessness as a problem," she said. "They want to talk about what touches them, like a shelter or a hotel on their corner. They don't want to debate the Board of Education. They want to talk about why their particular school isn't doing something right."</p>
        <p>The specifics change, but the nature of the questions are similar wherever the Mayor holds one of his town hall meetings, whether in Sunset Park, the South Bronx or Staten Island. Sometimes, the tone turns hostile, as it did in Brooklyn a few months ago when the Mayor berated critics of his spending cuts in schools and youth programs.</p>
        <p>But for the most part, the atmosphere is mutually respectful, for obvious reasons. These meetings are mutually beneficial: citizens get the ear of the man in charge, and the Mayor has the chance to talk to New Yorkers directly, without the filter of the pesky press. Mr. Giuliani makes the most of the opportunity. His staff even distributed a new, polished "Meet the Mayor" brochure on Tuesday: six pages prepared at taxpayer expense, filled with the words and images of Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>ON Tuesday night, Mr. Giuliani said over and over again that the city was not in a spending mode. Even when one questioner, Mr. Gray, argued that spending on housing for the aged now would save money in the long run, the Mayor said, "It's possible it would pay for itself in the long run, but when you have a $2.7 billion deficit, you need things that are going to pay for themselves in the short run."</p>
        <p>There were no guarantees, either, to Ms. Sorge, who said she was concerned about her grandchild's education, about reducing school overcrowding. But she understood. "I know the Mayor is trying as hard as he can to turn the city around," she said, before rushing off to get the Mayor's autograph.  METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
