<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baseball's Unreal World</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDC133CF93AA35751C0A963958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baseball's Unreal World</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At this point, either we have a baseball season with real players or we have a lot of championship bowling reruns. The guess here is that the longer the waltz between the baseball players and owners goes on, the less anyone will care.</p>
        <p>President Clinton whiffed on the first try. Knowing he had nothing to offer but the magic of the Oval Office, Mr. Clinton invited both sides to the White House and tried his level best to get them to submit their six-month-old dispute to binding arbitration. They rebuffed his efforts, at which point he spoke not just for himself but for increasingly disenchanted fans: "Both of you have a lot at stake, and I'm afraid you're both going to wind up losers."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At this point, either we have a baseball season with real players or we have a lot of championship bowling reruns. The guess here is that the longer the waltz between the baseball players and owners goes on, the less anyone will care.</p>
        <p>President Clinton whiffed on the first try. Knowing he had nothing to offer but the magic of the Oval Office, Mr. Clinton invited both sides to the White House and tried his level best to get them to submit their six-month-old dispute to binding arbitration. They rebuffed his efforts, at which point he spoke not just for himself but for increasingly disenchanted fans: "Both of you have a lot at stake, and I'm afraid you're both going to wind up losers."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, with other games to play, then called on Congress to impose arbitration. At which point the country was treated to a rare instance of congruity between House Speaker Newt Gingrich and the House minority leader, Richard Gephardt. Both said, quite rightly, that Congress was the wrong place to try to resolve the labor problems of the national pastime.</p>
        <p>There may be some merit in a broad Congressional redefinition of the rules under which baseball operates. Eliminating or narrowing the antitrust exemption, for example, would make it harder for the owners to operate as a cartel while enjoying immunity from lawsuits the players might file. In plain language, that would prevent the owners from unilaterally imposing a salary cap, as distinct from negotiating one. The threat of lawsuits has a way of encouraging negotiations.</p>
        <p>But eliminating or narrowing the antitrust exemption will not solve the economic problem that lies at the core of this dispute. That problem is to find ways to alleviate the effects of a bidding system, driven by the owners, that has inflated player payrolls and put one-fourth of the major league's 28 teams at risk. The solution is not, however, to destroy the players' right to sell their services on the free market.</p>
        <p>This complex economic issue has to be solved at the negotiating table. Unfortunately, neither the players nor owners seem to think the normal rules of collective bargaining apply to them. Everybody has so much money that serious negotiations can be deferred into the by-and-by.</p>
        <p>There is a limit, though, to the patience of those who subsidize all these talented athletes and driven owners. That is because ordinary folks, at some point in their lives, have had to solve their problems without invoking the majesty of the Presidency or running to Congress. Baseball people are living in a different and increasingly surreal world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
