<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. to Send 7,000 Peacekeepers to Monitor Accord in Angola</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANGOLA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D7163FF93AA35751C0A963958260" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. to Send 7,000 Peacekeepers to Monitor Accord in Angola</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Security Council voted unanimously today to send a 7,000-member peacekeeping force to Angola, the largest operation in Africa since troops went to Somalia in 1993.</p>
        <p>The Angola mission is a critical one for the United Nations because a previous international effort to monitor an Angolan peace accord and conduct elections after a long civil war was undone in 1992 when fighting resumed shortly after the voting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Security Council voted unanimously today to send a 7,000-member peacekeeping force to Angola, the largest operation in Africa since troops went to Somalia in 1993.</p>
        <p>The Angola mission is a critical one for the United Nations because a previous international effort to monitor an Angolan peace accord and conduct elections after a long civil war was undone in 1992 when fighting resumed shortly after the voting.</p>
        <p>Last November in Lusaka, Zambia, the Angolan Government of President Jose Eduardo dos Santos and the rebel army Unita, led by Jonas Savimbi, signed a new peace agreement.</p>
        <p>Today, Angola's Foreign Minister, Venancio de Moura, told the 15-member Council that the success of the cease-fire that prevailed since then "leads us to believe that this time peace has come to stay."</p>
        <p>The Angola peacekeeping operation will cost about $380 million a year, of which the United States would be assessed a third. Washington will not send troops, though the Clinton Administration will consider requests for logistical support.</p>
        <p>Republican leaders in Congress have already offered support for the mission. Senator Jesse Helms, chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and a strong anti-Communist, has been a supporter of Mr. Savimbi and his Unita movement in its fight against a leftist Government that had Soviet and Cuban support in its early phases. The last Cuban troops withdrew from Angola, a former Portuguese colony, in 1991.</p>
        <p>United Nations officials and diplomats hope that the new Angola mission will be as successful as a recent peacekeeping operation in Mozambique, another former Portuguese colony with a left-of-center Government caught in a civil war with a guerrilla force with outside support. In Mozambique, United Nations observers have overseen the demobilizing of troops on both sides and the organization of a peaceful election.</p>
        <p>The first peacekeepers to be deployed in Angola will come from Brazil, Uruguay, India, Pakistan, Romania and Zimbabwe. Under the resolution establishing the force, a limited number of observers will be sent initially to help set up quartering centers for rebel soldiers as long as the cease-fire holds. Infantry forces would follow, depending on regular assessments of progress made by Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali, a condition strongly backed by the United States.</p>
        <p>Several hundred non-military police officers serving as observers and advisers will also be sent to Angola, along with military observers, a civilian staff and a team of mine-clearing experts. Part of the costs of the operation will be paid by Angola, a country rich in oil and diamonds.</p>
        <p>Today Foreign Minister de Moura pledged $64 million plus some material assistance.</p>
        <p>Not all speakers in today's debate supported the idea that the Angolans should be required to defray the costs of peacekeeping or should be subject to other conditions. Portugal's United Nations delegate, Pedro Catarino, said calibrating the mission by linking it to developments on the ground could cause delays or derail the operation.</p>
        <p>The Angolan Government appears to be having some qualms about clauses in the resolution calling for human rights monitors, a ban on weapon purchases and the setting up by the United Nations of an independent radio station. A similar radio project proved to be useful and important in building confidence in Cambodia. Radio stations are also being established in Rwanda and Bosnia to provide impartial information and news.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
