<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revenge Is Motive in 7 Bronx Slayings, Police Say</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKS, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CASELLAS, LOURDES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CASELLAS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOPEZ, ELLIOT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ORTIZ, GILBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DC1031F935A15751C0A965958260" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revenge Is Motive in 7 Bronx Slayings, Police Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The shootings of six people in a Mott Haven apartment and a young woman at the entrance to the Bronx County Building were twin acts of revenge rooted in a simmering rivalry between two young women over a man, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>At the center of the case, the police said, were one of the young women, Lourdes Casellas, and her husband, Anthony. It was his rage at a teen-ager who had hit his wife that led him to plot retaliation, the police said. That plot came to fruition on St. Valentine's Day, they said, when three adults and three teen-agers were lined up on the living-room floor of a Bronx apartment and each shot in the head.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The shootings of six people in a Mott Haven apartment and a young woman at the entrance to the Bronx County Building were twin acts of revenge rooted in a simmering rivalry between two young women over a man, the police said yesterday.</p>
        <p>At the center of the case, the police said, were one of the young women, Lourdes Casellas, and her husband, Anthony. It was his rage at a teen-ager who had hit his wife that led him to plot retaliation, the police said. That plot came to fruition on St. Valentine's Day, they said, when three adults and three teen-agers were lined up on the living-room floor of a Bronx apartment and each shot in the head.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the revenge came full circle. Mrs. Casellas was slain at the courthouse in a shooting that was a payback for the Feb. 14 killings. A suspect was arrested in her slaying the same day, and another man was arrested in connection with the Mott Haven deaths. And yesterday, the police arrested four more men -- including Mr. Casellas -- in connection with the Feb. 14 slayings.</p>
        <p>"Revenge," said the New York City Chief of Detectives, Joseph R. Borrelli, "is the motive that's going through this whole thing."</p>
        <p>To those investigating the case, as well as to many people on the streets of the Bronx, the apparent motive for the violence -- and the fact that the feud played out on the steps of the borough's criminal court building -- showed how disputes that were once played out in private can escalate into shocking confrontations that command public attention.</p>
        <p>"It's the old story of a smack in the face, which 20 years ago may have resulted in somebody being stabbed, has now resulted in the death of seven people," said Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly.</p>
        <p>A police investigator said the suspects in the Mott Haven killings were believed to be members of a "loosely knit drug gang." But they said the murders appeared to be acts of simple revenge unrelated to drugs.</p>
        <p>The police say Mr. Casellas began plotting the killings sometime after August 1992, when he was being held on Rikers Island on a drug charge and his wife was injured in a fight with Edwin Santiago, 17, a student at South Bronx High School. The police said Mr. Santiago, one of the six victims in the apartment, was the intended target.</p>
        <p>The fight, according to police investigators and people who knew some of the victims and suspects, grew out of a long-simmering rivalry between Mrs. Casellas and Mr. Santiago's sister, Maria Santana. A police investigator, who asked not to be identified, said that Mr. Casellas had at one time dated Ms. Santana, and that he had broken off with her after he became involved with Lourdes Serrano, whom he later married and had a baby with.</p>
        <p>A woman who lives in the building at 645 Prospect Avenue, where the killings took place, said that Ms. Santana and Mrs. Casellas "hated each other," and at times exchanged heated words. She said that Mrs. Casellas had continued to view Ms. Santana as a romantic threat. "Lourdes was harassing her all the time," said the woman, who requested anonymity. "She was jealous."  Summer Confrontation</p>
        <p>The animosity between the women erupted on a Bronx street last summer. During the fight, the police said, Mr. Santiago came to the aid of his sister and slapped Mrs. Casellas. How severely injured she was is a matter of dispute -- Chief Borrelli said by some accounts she was "severely beaten." But other police officials and neighbors interviewed yesterday said that Mr. Santiago had slapped her and caused her to drop her baby.</p>
        <p>"Santiago gets involved, and he slaps her in the face and pushes her, causing her to drop the child," said one police official. "That, we feel, may have been the catalyst."</p>
        <p>Chief Borrelli, speaking at a news conference yesterday at the 40th Police Precinct station house in the Bronx, said Mrs. Casellas later visited her husband in jail and told him of the fight.</p>
        <p>"She visits him at Rikers and explains to him what happened," the chief said. "Subsequent to his release, he gets the cooperation of the other individuals. They arrange to commit and, we believe, they extract the revenge that he wants for his wife."</p>
        <p>Neighbors said that in the days before the Mott Haven killings, Ms. Santana had been telling people she was afraid of Mr. Casellas and what he might do to her, and that she had received a telephoned death threat.</p>
        <p>"She went around telling a lot of people that if anything happened to her, it had to be him," a neighbor said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Santana, 26 years old, was among the victims in the apartment, in which she lived. The others included her brother; her mother, Julia Santana, 40; Miguel Camacho Rivera, 23, who was dating Ms. Santana; Annette Medina, 17, who lived down the hall, and Christopher Hernandez, 15, an eighth-grade student at Public School 62.</p>
        <p>The men arrested with Mr. Casellas, who is 21 years old and lives at 1140 Burke Avenue in Baychester, the Bronx, were members with Mr. Casellas of what one police investigator described as "a loosely knit drug gang." A Correction Department spokesman, Officer Robert Montez, said Mr. Casellas also served six months in Rikers Island in 1988-89 on drug charges. Police records show he also has convictions for assault, robbery, theft with a deadly weapon and unlawful imprisonment.</p>
        <p>The others were identified as Elliot Lopez, 18, of 730 East 161st Street; Luis Romero, 19, of 845 Rev. James A. Polite Boulevard; Edgardo Rosado, 19, of 745 East 152d Street, and Luis Ramos, 17, of 2707 Sedgwick Avenue, all from the Bronx. Mr. Ramos was with the Casellases at the courthouse Wednesday and was shot in the thigh. Mr. Lopez was arrested that day when he appeared at a Bronx courthouse on an unrelated charge; the others were arrested early yesterday.</p>
        <p>Chief Borrelli said the police believe that all of the shooting was done by Mr. Casellas, who goes by the nickname "Ding Ding," and by Mr. Lopez, who is called "Tato."</p>
        <p>There was a "strong indication," he told reporters, "that Tato and Ding Ding were the shooters." Some of the others, sources said, may have been coming in and out of the apartment as the executions progressed.</p>
        <p>The sources said they had begun getting tips about a man called Ding Ding from neighborhood people and informants who called special police phone lines.</p>
        <p>The search for revenge did not end on St. Valentine's Day on Prospect Avenue. On Wednesday Mrs. Casellas herself was shot to death as she, pushing her 10-month-old son in a stroller, accompanied her husband to the courthouse for his scheduled appearance on the drug charges for which he had recently been held at Rikers. The baby was uninjured.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Kelly said the suspect in that shooting, Gilbert Ortiz, 23, of 960 Avenue St. John in the Bronx, told the police that he was a "brother" of Mr. Santiago, but that his precise relationship to the slain man remained unclear. It was also unclear whether Mrs. Casellas was the intended victim of the shooting; While Mr. Ramos, who accompanied the Casellas to court, was also injured, Mr. Casellas was not hurt.</p>
        <p>The police recovered a 9-millimeter semiautomatic pistol in the arrests of the suspects in the Mott Haven killings. But Chief Borrelli said the murder weapon had not been found.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
