<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Room for Bush's Civil Rights Appointee</title>
    <meta content="Y05CIVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/05/politics/05CIVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1365215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Civil Rights Commission (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center for New Black Leadership</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kessler, Gladys (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirsanow, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Victoria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Civil Rights Commission</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kessler, Gladys</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DA103DF936A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Room for Bush's Civil Rights Appointee</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Room for Bush's Civil Rights Appointee</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal District Court Judge Gladys Kessler deals sharp setback to Bush administration in what has become small but nasty dispute between administration and traditional civil rights activists over who gets to sit on United States Civil Rights Commission; Kessler rules that Pres Bush cannot appoint Peter N Kirsanow, labor lawyer and chairman of Center for New Black Leadership, to replace Victoria Wilson, who was appointed to commission in January 2000 by former Pres Bill Clinton; Bush administration has even held swearing-in ceremony for Kirksanow, who has criticized old-guard civil rights leadership as stale and committed to fostering 'loserhood' on blacks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge dealt a sharp setback to the Bush administration today in what has become a small but nasty dispute between the White House and traditional civil rights activists over who gets to sit on the United States Civil Rights Commission.</p>
        <p>The judge, Gladys Kessler of Federal District Court, ruled that President Bush could not appoint a Cleveland lawyer to the commission because there was no vacancy for him to fill. Mr. Bush had named Peter N. Kirsanow, a labor lawyer and chairman of the Center for New Black Leadership, to the commission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge ruled on Monday that President Bush could not appoint his choice to the United States Civil Rights Commission because there was no vacancy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge dealt a sharp setback to the Bush administration today in what has become a small but nasty dispute between the White House and traditional civil rights activists over who gets to sit on the United States Civil Rights Commission.</p>
        <p>The judge, Gladys Kessler of Federal District Court, ruled that President Bush could not appoint a Cleveland lawyer to the commission because there was no vacancy for him to fill. Mr. Bush had named Peter N. Kirsanow, a labor lawyer and chairman of the Center for New Black Leadership, to the commission.</p>
        <p>The White House even held a swearing-in ceremony for Mr. Kirsanow, who is black and has criticized the traditional civil rights leadership as stale and committed to fostering ''loserhood on blacks.''</p>
        <p>But Mary Frances Berry, the commission chairwoman and a fiery civil rights activist, resisted seating Mr. Kirsanow. Ms. Berry argued that Victoria Wilson, a woman appointed to the commission in January 2000 by President Bill Clinton to replace  Judge A. Leon Higginbotham Jr., has a six-year term under the law. The White House contends that Ms. Wilson's term expired on Nov. 29, when the term of Judge Higginbotham, who died in 1998, would have expired.</p>
        <p>Today, Judge Kessler said that the law clearly required that Ms. Wilson be allowed a full term and that there was no vacancy for Mr. Bush to fill.</p>
        <p>Barbara Comstock, a spokeswoman for the Justice Department, said this afternoon that the department would appeal the ruling as soon as possible to a three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit.</p>
        <p>''We respectfully disagree with the court's ruling,'' Ms. Comstock said.  ''The court's interpretation of the Civil Rights Commission's statute has the potential to allow political gamesmanship to occur on what should be a bipartisan, independent commission.''</p>
        <p>The appeal will certainly not come in time to have an impact on the next meeting of the commission, scheduled for Friday. Ms. Wilson is expected to take a seat at the table, and Mr. Kirsanow, if he shows up, will have to sit in the audience as he has at previous meetings, unrecognized by Ms. Berry.</p>
        <p>Ms. Berry told reporters outside the federal courthouse this afternoon, ''The court today upheld the independence of the commission, and for that I am grateful.''</p>
        <p>The dispute involves more than clashing views of civil rights issues like affirmative action; the appointment of Mr. Kirsanow would also affect the balance of power on the commission. Ms. Berry and her allies account for five of the eight seats on the commission, and the substitution of Mr. Kirsanow for Ms. Wilson would leave the commission deadlocked at four to four.</p>
        <p>Judge Kessler said the language of the law enacted in 1994 renewing the commission's charter made it clear that each commissioner was to serve for six years even if the appointment was to replace someone who had not completed a term. She dismissed the argument of Justice Department lawyers that the law required the terms to be staggered, which would have meant that Ms. Wilson had to leave office when Judge Higginbotham's term expired.</p>
        <p>Judge Kessler said Congress explicitly considered and rejected the inclusion of a section in the bill requiring staggered terms.</p>
        <p>The commission has no enforcement power but publicizes civil rights problems it perceives in government policy and agencies.</p>
        <p>Its last major project, a report on the 2000 presidential election, greatly irritated the Bush administration. Voting along traditional lines, the commission majority said Mr. Bush had won in Florida and gained the presidency through ''a pattern and practice of injustice, ineptitude and inefficiency'' by election officials that denied blacks the right to vote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
