<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 31, Steelers' Bettis Confronts Age</title>
    <meta content="17NFL.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/17/sports/football/17NFL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1512868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL: INSIDE THE N.F.L."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bettis, Jerome</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD61230F934A2575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 31, Steelers' Bettis Confronts Age</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bettis Confronts Age, Like Many Before Him</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every summer, the aging player in the National Football League walks onto another practice field and begins a conversation that only he can really understand.</p>
        <p>Can I still do this? Can my body take this? Is a Super Bowl title worth achy mornings and X-rays?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Pittsburgh Steelers' Jerome Bettis said that he was not committed to playing the 2004 season and that he was looking at his career only a year at a time now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every summer, the aging player in the National Football League walks onto another practice field and begins a conversation that only he can really understand.</p>
        <p>Can I still do this? Can my body take this? Is a Super Bowl title worth achy mornings and X-rays?</p>
        <p>Jerome Bettis, the Pittsburgh Steelers running back, remembers when others asked those questions. Now, in his 11th training camp, he is one of them.</p>
        <p>''You weigh everything,'' Bettis, 31, said while standing beneath a row of trees Wednesday at St. Vincent College in Latrobe, Pa., site of the Steelers' training camp. ''You say: 'Where am I physically? What will this year do to me physically?'</p>
        <p>''It's the daily grind of the same thing, not giving your body a chance to rest. It makes you wonder if you still want to do it. And then, at the end of the day, you come up with an answer.''</p>
        <p>And what is Bettis's answer?</p>
        <p>''I'm here,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For Bettis, like many elite athletes, a discussion about injuries is about as welcome as injuries themselves. The football player, in particular, needs his mind free of thoughts of pain and vulnerability.</p>
        <p>But in Pittsburgh, where Bettis has had injury setbacks in consecutive seasons, the questions must be posed, especially with Coach Bill Cowher expressing the view that the team's running back load will be shared among Bettis, Amos Zereoue, Chris Fuamatu-Ma'afala and others.</p>
        <p>Bettis has long been a workhorse back and a potential Hall of Fame player. The last two seasons, though, his load has dwindled.</p>
        <p>''We are going to use them all and try to keep everybody happy,'' Cowher said of his running backs. ''That onus will be on me. Those are nice problems to have and those are the egos that I am going to have to deal with.''</p>
        <p>Bettis, at 256 pounds, is a confrontational running back, a player whose style and size have made him susceptible to punishment. And as he has aged, his time in the Steelers' huddle has decreased.</p>
        <p>In 2001, he injured his groin, missed the final five games of the regular season and tried to grin through painkilling shots during the postseason. Last season, Bettis played on a bad left knee and turned in the least productive year of his career, rushing for 666 yards on 187 carries.</p>
        <p>Bettis, who had torn cartilage removed from the knee in February, says he feels healthy; it is a notion that his teammates echo as well.</p>
        <p>''I really think he's going to come out and put up a great year this year,'' receiver Hines Ward said. ''He's so enthused to come back.''</p>
        <p>Guard Alan Faneca said, ''He's looked the best that he's looked since I've been here, and I've been here six years.''</p>
        <p>In every way, Bettis has far exceeded his expectations for his career. He came out of Notre Dame as a fullback and did not expect to climb to 10th on the N.F.L.'s career rushing list (he is only 770 yards behind Jim Brown, who is sixth).</p>
        <p>But Bettis still has pride.</p>
        <p>''It's one of those situations where you're an older player so they automatically think you won't bounce back as good,'' he said. ''You hear it, see it in the papers, but you just deal with it. I don't read the paper and then ball it up and throw it at the television. You laugh and say, 'That's fine.' ''</p>
        <p>Bettis, who has not won a Super Bowl, said that he was not committed to playing the 2004 season and that he was looking at his career only a year at a time now. He will play this season and then, probably on another summer day, start a new conversation.</p>
        <p>''If you don't think you're running out of time, you're sadly mistaken,'' Bettis said. ''You only have so many years to play.''</p>
        <p>Staley's Holdout</p>
        <p>An awkward thing about having a name like Duce -- especially in Philadelphia -- is that it's hard to tell when the crowd is booing you or Duce-ing you. If and when Eagles running back Duce Staley ends his holdout, that mystery will undoubtedly continue.</p>
        <p>Staley has been a no-show at the Eagles' training camp in Bethlehem, Pa., because he wants to begin negotiations on a new contract. (He is scheduled to make $2.2 million in 2003, the final year of his deal.) The Eagles have responded by fining him $5,000 each day he misses camp.</p>
        <p>Including last night's preseason game against the Pittsburgh Steelers, Staley has missed 20 days of camp, or the equivalent of $100,000.</p>
        <p>Staley released a statement on DuceStaley.com, his Web site, saying that he only wants to know how he fits into the Eagles' plans after ''the best year of my career'' in 2002, when he scored 5 touchdowns and rushed for 1,029 yards on 269 carries, 3.8 yards a carry.</p>
        <p>(Staley actually had better rushing numbers in 1998, when he scored 5 touchdowns and rushed for 1,065 yards on 258 carries, a 4.1 average. Staley did have 541 receiving yards in 2002, however, compared with 432 in 1998.)</p>
        <p>''I've played my heart out for the Eagles the past six years,'' Staley said. ''There's no other team in the N.F.L. I would rather play for, this season and in the future, than the Eagles. I am heading into the final year of my contract with the team. I was just interested to know how I fit into the team's plans in the future.''</p>
        <p>Without Staley, who started every game last season, the Eagles have been leaning on Correll Buckhalter, a third-year pro out of Nebraska, and Brian Westbrook, who is in his second year out of Villanova. The team also has two rookies available, Reno Mahe from Brigham Young and Chris Downs from Maryland.</p>
        <p>The Making of a Legend</p>
        <p>Bill Cowher, the Pittsburgh Steelers' coach, recently nicknamed one of the team's new training camp practice fields at St. Vincent College the Field of Dreams because it sits next to a dense cornfield.</p>
        <p>In the movie of the same name, Kevin Costner builds a baseball field in Iowa, where past legends come to play before they disappear back into the corn.</p>
        <p>Cowher said of his players: ''I told them if you run and go into the cornstalks and you disappear, you must be a legend. They all keep coming back out, though.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL: INSIDE THE N.F.L.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
