<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Question in Messinger Camp: Where's the Party Support?</title>
    <meta content="23DEMS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971024T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1997 ELECTIONS: THE DEMOCRATS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messinger, Ruth W (Boro Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DA133EF930A15753C1A961958260" item-length="1571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Question in Messinger Camp: Where's the Party Support?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ruth W Messinger's campaign for New York City Mayor against incumbent Rudolph Giuluiani is encountering reality that there has been virtual collapse of support from leading Democrats across city and state and unwillingness of many of them to actively campaign with her (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Ruth W. Messinger wanted a Democrat of stature to campaign with her the other day, she reached out halfway across the country, enlisting Senator Paul Wellstone of Minnesota to fly in for a day of appearances at her side.</p>
        <p>The fact that Ms. Messinger turned for a campaign escort to a senator from Minnesota who is barely known in New York City reflects a reality the Messinger campaign is encountering in the final days of the mayoral race: the virtual collapse of support from leading Democrats across the city and state and the unwillingness of many of them to actively campaign with her as she tries to unseat a popular Republican mayor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Ruth W. Messinger wanted a Democrat of stature to campaign with her the other day, she reached out halfway across the country, enlisting Senator Paul Wellstone of Minnesota to fly in for a day of appearances at her side.</p>
        <p>The fact that Ms. Messinger turned for a campaign escort to a senator from Minnesota who is barely known in New York City reflects a reality the Messinger campaign is encountering in the final days of the mayoral race: the virtual collapse of support from leading Democrats across the city and state and the unwillingness of many of them to actively campaign with her as she tries to unseat a popular Republican mayor.</p>
        <p>''I've seen this happen in other places, but never on the scale I've seen here,'' Jim Andrews, Ms. Messinger's senior campaign consultant, said in an interview. ''The pressure is not from Rudy. It's from people she's known all her life, that she's fought with and helped and worked for, and who have turned on her now. For the fun of it.''</p>
        <p>''The true test of a party is when it's in a difficult situation -- not when it's not,'' continued Mr. Andrews, who is from Chicago and has been a consultant for 16 years.  ''If that is true, this party has failed miserably.'' He described the behavior of some Democrats as ''slimy.''</p>
        <p>The Wellstone visit, Ms. Messinger's aides said, was an unhappy reminder of what Mr. Andrews called a ''wholesale sell-out by Democrats,'' in which some Democrats have publicly endorsed Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. Mr. Andrews also expressed concern about Democrats who have endorsed Ms. Messinger and are now ''sitting in their foxholes somewhere.'' But, he said, he did not want to criticize any Democrat who had endorsed her, no matter how equivocally.</p>
        <p>The decision by Mr. Andrews and other senior Messinger advisers to discuss with a reporter their unhappiness with Democrats in New York suggests the depth of distress in Messinger quarters. It is also the latest evidence of disarray in the state Democratic Party: Mr. Andrews and others who are not involved with the campaign said that elected Democrats felt they had nothing to fear from bucking the party, a calculation that Mr. Andrews said would prove flawed in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>Democratic leaders in New York disputed the Messinger complaints, saying that while some defections were unfortunate, the party was, as a whole, strongly behind the Democratic standard-bearer.</p>
        <p>''It's important to focus on the positives and bring everyone together,'' said Judith Hope, the executive director of the state Democratic Party. ''I'm not going to indulge in a post-mortem two weeks before the election.''</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Hope said that she understood the anger expressed by Mr. Andrews and other Messinger aides. ''Look, I am not happy with the way things have developed here,'' Ms. Hope said. ''Clearly, the party has to do some very serious soul searching to prevent this kind of situation in 1998. Every Democratic elected official in this city ought to have been all-out for Ruth from Day One. That's a subject that will continue to generate some very serious discussion in the party after this election.''</p>
        <p>There have been almost daily reminders of the absence of support for Ms. Messinger in Democratic ranks. Mr. Giuliani was endorsed yesterday by the Central Labor Council, the umbrella group for the city's 1.5 million union members that almost always endorses Democrats. Mr. Giuliani's aides now keep a running list, which they update and distribute almost daily, of prominent Democrats who have publicly endorsed him.</p>
        <p>Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, New York's senior elected Democrat, posed for pictures with Mr. Giuliani last week at two appearances, batting away questions about the symbolism of the joint appearance with the Republican Mayor so close to an election. Ms. Messinger's aides said Mr. Moynihan's office never responded to two telephone calls asking him to find a moment for her during his day in New York. Mr. Moynihan, who is ideologically closer to Mr. Giuliani and is known as something of a maverick, endorsed Ms. Messinger last month by way of a late-afternoon fax to newspapers.</p>
        <p>''The Senator has been busy,'' said Mr. Moynihan's chief of staff, Tony  Bullock. ''That's the bottom line. We're very busy people in Washington right now.''</p>
        <p>Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, a Democrat who is also running on the Liberal Party line in his re-election bid, has been at Ms. Messinger's side so rarely that it has become a humorous topic among other Democrats, particularly because Mr. Hevesi has already started to organize his run for mayor in 2001. Councilman Sal F. Albanese, the Brooklyn Democrat, was marching alongside Ms. Messinger at the Columbus Day Parade last week and burst out laughing when asked if he knew why Mr. Hevesi was not at Ms. Messinger's side as well.</p>
        <p>''He's probably marching with Giuliani,'' Mr. Albanese said, though only half in jest.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Eric N. Vitaliano, the Democrat running for Congress in Staten Island, has repeatedly refused to come anywhere near the party's New York standard-bearer, much less endorse her. His press secretary, Sid Voorakkar, after first accepting an invitation for Mr. Vitaliano to discuss the mayoral race, called back to say that the candidate  was busy knocking on doors and did not have time to explain why he was not backing his fellow Democrat.</p>
        <p>Claire Shulman, the Queens Borough President and the most prominent Democrat to have endorsed Mr. Giuliani, was unavailable for comment yesterday because she was campaigning with Mr. Giuliani in Flushing and Forest Hills.</p>
        <p>Mario M. Cuomo, the three-term Democratic Governor who was endorsed by Mr. Giuliani in 1994, has not endorsed either candidate, but has been critical of Ms. Messinger in recent days. Representative Nita M. Lowey, Democrat of Westchester, whose district includes parts of the Bronx and Queens, said yesterday she would not endorse her fellow Democrat, because of what she said was Mr. Giuliani's convincing first term in office.</p>
        <p>The reluctance of Democrats to appear in a camera frame with Ms. Messinger extends beyond the borders of New York. Both Hillary Rodham Clinton and Tipper Gore, on trips to New York that included appearances with Ms. Messinger, severely limited their time with her, agreeing only to fleeting moments before photographers. Although President Clinton has now finally agreed to come in, it won't be until the Sunday before the election, and as part of a two- or three-state swing for a number of Democratic candidates.</p>
        <p>''Somebody made the strong recommendation that Betsy McCaughey Ross get a call from the President for switching parties,'' another of Ms. Messinger's senior aides said, describing Mr. Clinton's congratulatory call to the Lieutenant Governor for becoming a Democrat. ''We're still waiting for the call congratulating us for winning the primary,'' the aide said, speaking on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Several Democratic aides contended that at least some of the blame for the defections lies with Ms. Messinger and her campaign organization. From that perspective, Ms. Messinger is paying the price for years of being a fairly aloof figure in the city's Democratic Party, and for recruiting out-of-town figures, who do not have the political currency to press party members into duty, to run her campaign.</p>
        <p>But more than that, these very public signs of disrespect for Ms. Messinger point to the extent of the breakdown of the party structure in New York. Mr. Andrews argued that it would have long-term implications for the party, making it more difficult to build support for candidates in next year's Senate and gubernatorial races.</p>
        <p>''The self-defeating part of it is that in the process of doing whatever they can to protect themselves, or get whatever crumbs Giuliani's willing to sweep off the table, they are hurting themselves over the long haul because they are going to be out of power,'' Mr. Andrews said. ''And what's most important, they're hurting the people they represent.''</p>
        <p>''There's a kind of smarmy, rotten nature to this,'' Mr. Andrews said. ''It's not that it's just despicable, it's gratuitous: the constant bashing by Democrats of Ruth and her effort. While they are abandoning her in public, off the record they are trashing her to every reporter in town.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Andrews noted that there are some Democrats who have made a point of remaining close to Ms. Messinger: her three former rivals for the Democratic mayoral nomination in particular, Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx Borough President, Mr. Albanese, the Rev. Al Sharpton, as well as the city's Public Advocate, Mark Green.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green, who regularly appears with Ms. Messinger, said he was startled by the way some Democrats have treated her.</p>
        <p>''They are nowhere to be seen when the pressure is on,'' said Mr. Green. ''I don't want to sermonize to other people, but it's not the way I think her friends and colleagues and endorsers should operate. While people sometimes hide behind high rhetoric and high principles, so many politicians just follow the polls. And if they think a person may not or cannot win, they'll just look out for No. 1 and forget the friends that got them where they are.''</p>
        <p>THE 1997 ELECTIONS: THE DEMOCRATS  Correction:  October 24, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the absence of active support among some leading New York Democrats for Ruth W. Messinger, the Democratic mayoral candidate, misstated the title of Judith Hope. She is chairwoman, not executive director, of the state Democratic Party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 24, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the absence of active support among some leading New York Democrats for Ruth W. Messinger, the Democratic mayoral candidate, misstated the title of Judith Hope. She is chairwoman, not executive director, of the state Democratic Party.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
