<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.M.F. Loans to Rights Violators Are Attacked in Congress</title>
    <meta content="22INDO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Geither, Timothy F (Asst Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lissakers, Karin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED81F3CF931A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.M.F. Loans to Rights Violators Are Attacked in Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Asst Treas Sec Timothy F Geithner, urging House subcommittee to approve added $18 billion for International Monetary Fund, faces harsh questioning on United States support for IMF bailout of Indonesia in light of nation's human rights violations; he and Karin Lissakers, US representative to IMF, hold Clinton Administration uses its influence to spur human rights; human rights dispute is part of broader Congressional examination of IMF (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every year, the State Department's human rights report dwells at length on Indonesia's many forms of political repression, from its use of torture and killings to silence dissenters to its widespread military control of East Timor.</p>
        <p>So Indonesia's record might appear, at first glance, to require the use of a law compelling the United States to vote against lending billions of dollars through the International Monetary Fund to gross violators of human rights. But the United States favored a $40-billion I.M.F. bailout of Indonesia, and even offered to throw in $3 billion of back-up American financing if Indonesia needs more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every year, the State Department's human rights report dwells at length on Indonesia's many forms of political repression, from its use of torture and killings to silence dissenters to its widespread military control of East Timor.</p>
        <p>So Indonesia's record might appear, at first glance, to require the use of a law compelling the United States to vote against lending billions of dollars through the International Monetary Fund to gross violators of human rights. But the United States favored a $40-billion I.M.F. bailout of Indonesia, and even offered to throw in $3 billion of back-up American financing if Indonesia needs more.</p>
        <p>Today, defending that decision during two hours of hostile questioning by a Congressional committee, Treasury Department officials asserted that in the pantheon of human rights violators the Government of President Suharto did not rank among the worst of the worst.</p>
        <p>''The State Department makes these judgments, and Indonesia did not meet the standard to be on the list they send us,'' Timothy F. Geithner, an Assistant Secretary of the Treasury, said in testimony today, as he urged Congress to approve an additional $18 billion for the monetary fund.</p>
        <p>The debate over providing additional funding has turned into one of the hottest foreign policy issues on Capitol Hill this year. It has become a magnet for human rights activists, abortion opponents and critics of the monetary fund's role as the world's lender of last resort.</p>
        <p>The testimony today called into question whether the Administration, in its race to contain the Asian financial crisis, skirted a law that requires the United States to use its ''voice and vote'' to deny assistance to countries that ''engage in a pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.''</p>
        <p>The State Department insists that it keeps no official list of human rights violators that should be denied such loans. But, responding to questions today, Mr. Geithner said there were five countries that the United States would likely oppose for such aid: China, Sudan, Equatorial Guinea, Iran and Mauritania.</p>
        <p>''I concede,'' one senior Administration official said, ''that to the uninitiated it is a bit of a strange list.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, it has a number of gaping holes. For example, Nigeria, a country that has seen widespread violence and political repression since a 1993 coup, would not be automatically denied American support. Nor would Iraq, which is barred from borrowing money from the I.M.F. because it has not repaid loans for the last eight years.</p>
        <p>At the hearing before the House Banking subcommittee on general oversight and investigations, Representative Bernie Sanders, the Vermont independent who ranks among the fiercest critics of the monetary fund in the House, charged that the Administration violated the law. ''You are funding a vicious dictator who jails his opponents,'' he said. ''It seems to me you very clearly disobeyed the law.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Geithner and Karin Lissakers, the United States representative to the monetary fund, insisted that the Administration, working behind the scenes, has used its influence to promote both human rights and labor rights. It has blocked the I.M.F. from considering loans to Iran and the Sudan, they said, and held up money for Croatia while it was harboring war criminals.</p>
        <p>The human rights argument is part of a broader examination of the workings of the fund that has never before taken place in Congress. The fund is known for its secretiveness, in large part because it offers confidential advice to its 182 member countries, many of which turn over sensitive economic data to the fund.</p>
        <p>But that secretiveness has also made it difficult for the United States to defend its support of the fund, or discuss specific decisions. Now, increasingly fearful that the funding it seeks could be denied, Washington has begun to turn over thousands of pages of data about its interactions with the fund.</p>
        <p>Each disclosure, though, has raised new objections. Some Republicans argue that the I.M.F. should not provide below-market-rate loans to recipient countries; Mr. Sanders argued the opposite today, maintaining that the fund has turned into a ''loan shark'' burdening deeply indebted countries with even more interest payments.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
