<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Media Debtors Barred From Traveling With Clinton</title>
    <meta content="Y22BIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1193682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White House Correspondents Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lacey, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lelyveld, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5D91630F931A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Media Debtors Barred From Traveling With Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC LACEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lacey, Marc</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House travel office bars dozens of journalists, mostly from foreign media outlets, from traveling with Pres Clinton because of their outstanding debts from previous trips; travel office wants news organizations that are not in arrears to pay the nearly $74,000 in bad debt from delinquent news organizations; that plan was endorsed by White House Correspondents' Assn, but several media outlets, including The New York Times, are balking at paying bills of others; White House threatens to bar The Times from future travel if it does not pay $5,777.52, which White House says is its share of other organizations' bad debt; Joseph Lelyveld, Times's executive editor, calls threat 'crude and almost childish' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton has been hopscotching the nation and the world in the final year of his presidency, following a frenetic schedule that shows no signs of letting up. But dozens of news organizations have been barred from traveling along because of outstanding debts, and the list may be growing.</p>
        <p>The White House travel office has restricted organizations like The Weekly Standard and Esquire magazines and the national television network of Chile from participating in official White House trips. The debts range from $2.94 to $10,131.71, the White House said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton has been hopscotching the nation and the world in the final year of his presidency, following a frenetic schedule that shows no signs of letting up. But dozens of news organizations have been barred from traveling along because of outstanding debts, and the list may be growing.</p>
        <p>The White House travel office has restricted organizations like The Weekly Standard and Esquire magazines and the national television network of Chile from participating in official White House trips. The debts range from $2.94 to $10,131.71, the White House said.</p>
        <p>After failing to recover the nearly $74,000 in bad debt from the delinquent news organizations, the travel office recently began trying to collect the money from other organizations that are not in arrears but regularly travel with the president. The plan was endorsed by the White House Correspondents' Association, which represents news organizations, but some media outlets, including The Washington Post and The New York Times, are balking at paying bills of others.</p>
        <p>The New York Times has refused to pay $5,777.52, which the White House says is its share of the other organizations' bad debt. The White House has said that failure to pay the March 13 bill within 90 days may result in The Times being barred from future travel.</p>
        <p>''They're not our debts, and no one has explained to me why we're responsible for the debts of other people,'' said Joseph Lelyveld, the executive editor of The Times. He called the threat to cut off The Times from presidential travel ''crude and almost childish.''</p>
        <p>Others, including The Los Angeles Times and USA Today, have opted to pay the debts. Susan Page of USA Today, the departing president of the correspondents' association, defended the plan in a letter to news organizations last month. ''We believe that this reallocation method represents an accurate and fair tool to balance our books,'' she wrote.</p>
        <p>Journalists pay their own way while trailing Mr. Clinton. A small pool of reporters travels on Air Force One while the rest of the press corps flies on a separate plane. The travel office, which works with White House staff as well as the press, arranges charter flights, hotel accommodations and other matters.</p>
        <p>Some organizations on the bad debt list contend that the travel office billed them improperly. But a White House spokesman, Jim Kennedy, said officials had been diligent in trying to collect from ''some deadbeats who aren't paying.''</p>
        <p>William Kristol, publisher of The Weekly Standard, said his magazine had been challenging a White House charge of $504.97 since 1996, when a reporter traveled with the president to Jerusalem for the funeral of Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kristol said the reporter, David Brooks, told the White House that he merely wanted to fly to and from Jerusalem on the press plane but did not require any space in the press center that the White House typically sets up at presidential events, or any food or ground transportation. But Mr. Brooks did hop on the press bus at the airport, Mr. Kristol said, prompting the White House to bill him for all the ground services.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kristol said he had no idea his organization had been barred from White House travel and was also unaware that the debts were being passed along to other organizations. ''I'm totally stunned,'' he said.</p>
        <p>To prevent future bad debts, the travel office has instituted a policy that requires organizations on costly foreign trips that have never traveled before to pay up front. Most of the organizations that owe money are foreign media outlets.</p>
        <p>Paying up front is the way White House travel was handled in previous presidencies. But early in the Clinton administration, aides fired the seven-member travel office staff, accusing them of financial mismanagement in their handling of press trips and ordering an F.B.I. investigation. The new office began billing media organizations, which has proven to be a cumbersome process.</p>
        <p>None of the fired workers were ever found guilty of any violations, and the way the White House handled the matter was eventually investigated by the independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr. Mr. Starr's replacement, Robert W. Ray, is expected to issue a report on the matter in the coming months.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
