<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gay Rights Advocates Brace for Ballot Fights</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="661504"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DB1231F931A25752C0A962958260" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gay Rights Advocates Brace for Ballot Fights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gay rights advocates are facing a record number of state ballot initiatives this year that would forbid laws specifically protecting homosexuals from discrimination.</p>
        <p>And to fight the measures the advocates are intending to focus on the discrimination they say they suffer rather than devote their energies to countering the notion that they are seeking special protections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gay rights advocates are facing a record number of state ballot initiatives this year that would forbid laws specifically protecting homosexuals from discrimination.</p>
        <p>And to fight the measures the advocates are intending to focus on the discrimination they say they suffer rather than devote their energies to countering the notion that they are seeking special protections.</p>
        <p>Officials with the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force said on Monday that anti-gay rights initiatives could be placed on the ballots in eight states this year. That would be by far the largest number of such statewide voter initiatives held in any one year. Opponents of gay rights have been emboldened since voters in Colorado passed an anti-gay rights measure in 1992.</p>
        <p>Last year, the number of such initiatives rose to 19, all at the local level, and all were approved.</p>
        <p>With virtually no prospects that Congress will pass Federal legislation outlawing discrimination against homosexuals, and with mixed results in the Federal courts on the issue, gay rights advocates say they are forced to focus on fighting these voter initiatives at the state and local level.</p>
        <p>"We're taking our focus off Washington and bringing it back to the grass roots," said David M. Smith, director of public information for the task force. Assailing Anti-Gay Motives</p>
        <p>Gay rights leaders say they will try to portray organizers of the anti-gay rights initiatives as ultraconservatives who are seeking to attract adherents and political contributions to other causes, like restricting abortions and state support of religious schools.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the gay rights movement in Oregon said such a counteroffensive was successful in 1992, when voters defeated a measure that would have repealed existing gay rights measures, prohibited enactment of future ones and required the state to discourage homosexuality.</p>
        <p>Supporters of anti-gay rights measures, primarily fundamentalist Christians, hope to place initiatives on the ballot in November in Arizona, Idaho, Florida, Maine, Michigan, Missouri, Oregon and Washington. The most anti-gay rights initiatives on the ballot in any one year was two, in 1992, in Oregon and Colorado.</p>
        <p>"As the level of awareness is raised in America about what the homosexual agenda is, it's important that people feel that the homosexual agenda can be turned back by grass-roots involvement," said the Rev. Lou Sheldon, chairman of the Traditional Values Coalition, a conservative religious organization in Anaheim, Calif. The group is sponsoring the Arizona measure and helping to organize the initiatives in Oregon, Washington and Missouri.</p>
        <p>In some cases the measures would repeal existing local gay rights ordinances, and prohibit the enactment of such new laws. In others, the initiatives would replace state antidiscrimination statutes with statutes omitting specific protections for homosexuals.</p>
        <p>One local initiative seeks to repeal an ordinance in Austin, Tex., that allows benefits to be paid to the domestic partners of city workers, regardless of sex.</p>
        <p>"What we're seeing is a national assault against the rights of gays and lesbians," said Scot Nakagawa, who will help coordinate the coalition's campaigns in some states, including Oregon, Washington and Idaho.</p>
        <p>In most states, proponents of the anti-gay rights initiatives are still gathering signatures. But both supporters and opponents say they have little doubt that enough signatures will be obtained to qualify the initiatives for the ballots in most of the eight states if not all of them.  New Group: 'Fight the Right'</p>
        <p>Mr. Nakagawa and other members of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force say gay rights advocates are forming a new coalition, Fight the Right, to defeat the initiatives. Leaders of the task force say they, too, will be involved in grass-roots organizing and fund raising. In addition, they will soon be conducting polls and setting up focus groups to determine the most effective way to make their case.</p>
        <p>"We need to find out what message will resonate with voters and speak the truth about our experience," Mr. Smith said, "as well as make the case that these initiatives are the product of the far right and indicative of a broader political agenda that will affect all Americans."</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith and leaders of other gay rights organizations say they need to make sure that the debate is about discrimination and not, as their opponents contend, efforts by homosexuals to seek special status or preference programs.</p>
        <p>"There's a tremendous insecurity among voters," said Robert Bray, a task force official who will help run the campaign in Florida and Arizona. "They're concerned about jobs and schools. What they're being told is that we will set quotas. The right wing comes along and says these people are going to take your jobs away." Challenges Under Way</p>
        <p>Last month, a state judge in Colorado ruled that the anti-gay rights measures approved by voters in 1992 violated the Constitution's equal protection clause.</p>
        <p>Lawyers from the American Civil Liberties Union and the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, a gay rights organization, have challenged the validity of a number of the pending initiatives, either on constitutional grounds of equal protection or on the ground that they are in technical violation of state laws on voter initiatives. The groups have also gone to court to try, on constitutional grounds, to overturn the initiative in Cincinnati that repealed the city's ordinance banning discrimination against homosexuals.</p>
        <p>Polling data suggest that when the issue is framed as one dealing with discrimination, the public tends to be more sympathetic to gay rights.</p>
        <p>More than three-quarters of the respondents to a New York Times/CBS News poll conducted last February said they believed that homosexuals should have equal rights with heterosexuals on job opportunities, while 15 percent said they disagreed and 6 percent said they had no opinion. In the same poll, however, 50 percent said special laws were not necessary to insure the equal rights of gay men and lesbians; 42 percent said they were.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
