<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="02TRANSTF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3D7163DF931A35753C1A961958260" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  COLORADO ROCKIES--Named Jay Alves public relations director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  COLORADO ROCKIES--Named Jay Alves public relations director.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  CHICAGO BULLS--Signed G Dante Calabria, F Boris Gorene, G Rusty LaRue, F Kornel David, F Dwayne Whitfield and C Eric Gingold to one-year contracts.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Named Jay Alves director of public relations.  DENVER NUGGETS--Traded F Antonio McDyess to the Phoenix Suns for a minimum of three first-round and two second-round draft picks.  DETROIT PISTONS--Signed F-C Don Reid to a multiyear contract and F Scot Pollard and F Charles O'Bannon.  MIAMI HEAT--Signed F Ben Davis and G Malcolm Huckaby.  MINNEASOTA TIMBERWOLVES--Agreed to terms with F Kevin Garnett on a six-year contract.  NEW YORK KNICKS--Signed G Pete Myers.  PHOENIX SUNS--Traded G Wesley Person and G Tony Dumas to the Cleveland Cavaliers for a first-round pick no earlier than 2000.  VANCOUVER GRIZZLIES--Signed F Mark Hendrickson and F David Booth, C Alan Ogg and G Litterial Green.</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  WNBA--Awarded franchises to Detroit and Washington to begin play next season.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Signed LB Mike Crawford and FB Jim Kitts. Signed OT Ron Collins to the practice squad.  NEW ORLEANS SAINTS--Signed S Chris Hewitt to a one-year contract. Signed DE Duane Ashman, DB Earl Little and WR Gunnard Twyner to the practice squad.  NEW YORK JETS--Agreed to terms with CB Aaron Glenn on a five-year contract extension.  OAKLAND RAIDERS--Signed DE Aundray Bruce.  TENNESSEE OILERS--Signed TE James McKeehan and WR Nate Singleton.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  CAROLINA HURRICANES--Signed RW Kevin Dineen to a one-year contract extension, through the 1998-99 season and F Kevin Brown to a one-year contract.  NEW JERSEY DEVILS--Assigned G Richard Shulmistra to Fort Wayne of the IHL. Placed D Sheldon Souray and C Sergei Brylin on injured reserve.  NEW YORK RANGERS--Assigned C Christian Dube and D Geoff Smith to Hartford of the AHL.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Claimed F Peter Ferraro and F Chris Ferraro off waivers from the New York Rangers. Signed RW Rob Brown. Announced Joe Mullen has rejoined the team to work in the community and alumni relations departments.</p>
        <p>American Hockey League  BEAST OF NEW HAVEN--Released G Tripp Tracy and LW Andrew Taylor.</p>
        <p>International Hockey League  FORT WAYNE KOMETS--Released G Rob Laurie and G Jon Hillebrandt. Assigned C Eric Boguniecki and D Dave Froh to Dayton of the ECHL.  HOUSTON AEROS--Announced Austin of the WPHL will serve as their developmental team.  KANSAS CITY BLADES--Assigned F David Beauregard and D Dan Delisle to Wichita of the CHL.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>METROPOLITAN INTERCOLLEGIATE BASKETBALL ASSOCIATION--Named Robert J. Byrnes president.  BOWLING GREEN--Named Kurt Thomas golf coach-golf course director.  CINCINNATI--Named Bob Goin athletic director.  DREXEL--Named Dan Baker director of broadcast relations and corporate sales.  FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON--Named Neal Biscaldi and Harry Moumdjian men's assistant basketball coaches.  FLORIDA ATLANTIC--Named Doni O'Bryan and Keith Klahold graduate assistant trainers.  FLORIDA TECH--Named Jennifer Mitchell assistant softball coach.  KEAN--Announced the resignation of Jim Casalino, men's baseball coach. Named John Stallings sports information director.  MAINE--Named Rick Filighera women's ice hockey coach.  MARQUETTE--Named Brian Bidlingmyer men's assistant basketball coach.  PITTSBURGH-JOHNSTOWN--Named Todd Williams baseball coach.  RADFORD--Named Donnie Tickle assistant athletic director.  RHODE ISLAND COLLEGE--Named Scott Gibbons assistant athletic director for media relations.  SAINT JOHN FISHER--Named John Lonez men's and women's cross country coach.  TEMPLE--Named Valerie Abbott assistant athletic director for advertising, promotions and ticket sales-women's interim senior administrator.  TENNESSEE STATE--Named Vivian Fuller athletic director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
