<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inman's Careful Career Of the Unexpected Move</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">INMAN, BOBBY RAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASPIN, LES (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">INMAN, BOBBY RAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASPIN, LES (SEC)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D7123BF932A15751C1A965958260" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inman's Careful Career Of the Unexpected Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Truly voluntary resignations in Washington are as rare as camera-shy lawmakers, but Bobby Ray Inman, chosen by President Clinton last week to be Secretary of Defense, once racked up two in a year.</p>
        <p>Those departures, in 1982, were bipartisan. Mr. Inman quit as the Reagan Administration's Deputy Director of Central Intelligence after clashes with William J. Casey, the Director. Shortly afterward, he accepted and then resigned from a post as consultant to the House Intelligence Committee, charging that the panel, which was controlled by Democrats, had issued a partisan staff report on El Salvador.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Truly voluntary resignations in Washington are as rare as camera-shy lawmakers, but Bobby Ray Inman, chosen by President Clinton last week to be Secretary of Defense, once racked up two in a year.</p>
        <p>Those departures, in 1982, were bipartisan. Mr. Inman quit as the Reagan Administration's Deputy Director of Central Intelligence after clashes with William J. Casey, the Director. Shortly afterward, he accepted and then resigned from a post as consultant to the House Intelligence Committee, charging that the panel, which was controlled by Democrats, had issued a partisan staff report on El Salvador.</p>
        <p>Resignation, or threat of it, is just one of the ways in which Mr. Inman, throughout a long career as an intelligence officer, managed to build a reputation as a man of principle and made himself popular with the Washington establishment.</p>
        <p>From interviews with an array of colleagues, a picture emerges of a "player" who has nurtured relationships of trust with the press and Congress by exhibiting unusual candor about the Government's shortcomings. And over the years his proteges -- some call them the "Inman mafia" -- have risen to leading intelligence positions, giving Mr. Inman the means, as one Clinton Administration official put it, "to take on the bureaucracy frontally or through the backdoor." Some Unappreciated Risks</p>
        <p>The President's nomination of Mr. Inman has been greeted by an outpouring of praise and outright adulation with few recent parallels in Washington. But as Mr. Inman prepares for the confirmation process, some officials who have worked with the self-assured insider see greater risks in the appointment than have yet been appreciated.</p>
        <p>It is not clear, they say, what kind of chemistry will develop between Mr. Inman and the other members of Mr.  Clinton's national security team. Last Thursday, at the White House ceremony where his nomination was announced, Mr. Inman startled even his admirers by the alacrity and bluntness with which he declared his independence. As the President looked on, he said that before deciding to accept the nomination, he had felt it necessary to reach "a level of comfort" in Mr. Clinton's skills as Commander in Chief.</p>
        <p>"He's very principled but hard-headed," a senior national security official in the Reagan Administration said of Mr. Inman. "There's not a lot of room for compromise there. I imagine that President Clinton will go to sleep at night with one eye open."</p>
        <p>The circumstances of Mr. Inman's appointment further strengthen his hand in an Administration whose credentials on national security have been questioned from its first days. One Government official with decades of experience in Washington suggested that Les Aspin's resignation as Defense Secretary after only 11 months in office would give Mr. Inman extraordinary leverage in his new post.</p>
        <p>"If one Secretary resigns, that's a failure of the Secretary," this official said. "If a second one resigns, that's a failure of the Administration."</p>
        <p>Mr. Inman, who spent his intelligence career confronting the Soviet threat, left the Government in 1982 after helping set in motion the most expensive intelligence buildup in the nation's history. He returns with an imperative to cut budgets in a post-cold-war environment where certainties are few.  Courting Press and Congress</p>
        <p>Mr. Inman has always been an anomaly among intelligence officials. While many in his profession suspect the press and distrust members of Congress, he chose long ago to forge close ties to both groups.</p>
        <p>A Navy officer who rose rapidly through the intelligence ranks, he was named in 1977 to head the National Security Agency. Responsible for code-breaking, eavesdropping and protecting American messages from prying ears, the agency had a well-earned reputation for not only secretiveness but also a cavalier approach to civil liberties.</p>
        <p>A year before Mr. Inman took over, an ad hoc Senate committee's report on the nation's intelligence agencies had made public a litany of dubious activities, including the National Security Agency's routine monitoring of private communications sent overseas by Americans. The findings spurred creation of the House and Senate intelligence committees.</p>
        <p>It was a new day, and the instinct among many in the intelligence world was to retreat. William E. Colby, President Gerald R. Ford's Director of Central Intelligence, was reviled by longtime intelligence officers who thought he was too open with Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>Anyone heading any intelligence agency in that period had to walk a fine line between building bridges to the Congress and maintaining credentials within an intelligence world that felt it had been unfairly pilloried.</p>
        <p>Former associates say Mr. Inman succeeded. Indeed, they say, he was one of the first to grasp that Congressional scrutiny was actually a chance for the intelligence agencies to improve their standing -- and increase their budgets. Initiated into the world of high-technology satellites and secrets gleaned from abroad, the lawmakers could be turned from skeptics to advocates for the agencies they were overseeing.</p>
        <p>The process of winning over the Congressional panels began soon after Mr. Inman was picked by President Jimmy Carter to head the security agency. Former members of the House Intelligence Committee vividly recall Mr. Inman's first briefings. He would confidently stride into a windowless room in the Capitol, and, unlike most other senior officials, who testify before Congress with the help of a retinue of aides, he came alone, without briefing papers or props.</p>
        <p>One of the congressmen would pose a question about one problem or another, and Mr. Inman would detail how the various agencies saw it. Then, according to several former members of the committee, he would pause, lean forward and say, "Now, the Inman view is. . . ."</p>
        <p>Representative Norman Y. Mineta, a California Democrat who served on the House Intelligence Committee when it was first created, says he was so impressed by Mr. Inman's account of the security agency's capabilities that he insisted the members visit the agency's headquarters for more detailed briefings.</p>
        <p>"At first they were a little goosey in terms of what they would tell us," Mr. Mineta said of the agency's officers.  "It was Admiral Inman who really broke down that stilted atmosphere. Within his agency, dealing with Congress, it was going to be straightforward. No mousing around."</p>
        <p>Members of the House and Senate committees say in retrospect that Mr. Inman built trust on Capitol Hill by squarely acknowledging blunders.</p>
        <p>"One of the things that's always helped him is his willingness to admit things that may go against his department's interests," said Senator Patrick J. Leahy, the Vermont Democrat who served as vice chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee. "I would get all sweetness and light from the Administration, and then I would call him and he'd be honest in admitting mistakes.</p>
        <p>That was important. When he would disagree with me -- and he'd make his case -- I felt I could believe what he was saying." An Image Repaired</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Inman left the security agency in 1981, the agency was widely perceived by members of Congress as law-abiding and, most important, under control.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Inman was working on his own legacy. Beginning in the 1970's, he promoted the careers of a cadre of capable young Navy intelligence officers, many of whom have since risen to positions of even greater prominence.</p>
        <p>They include William O. Studeman, former head of the security agency, who is now Deputy Director of Central Intelligence; Richard L. Haver, who runs the Administration staff that coordinates the activities and budget requests of all intelligence agencies, and Adm. John M. McConnell, current head of the security agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inman also cultivated members of the Congressional intelligence committee staffs, telling leading aides to call him at home if necessary.</p>
        <p>When the Reagan Administration prepared to take office, Mr. Inman's popularity in Congress prompted several leading Republicans to recommend him as Director of Central Intelligence. Instead, Mr. Reagan chose his campaign chairman, Mr. Casey, and Mr. Inman settled in for what would be 16 uneasy months as Deputy Director.</p>
        <p>Shortly after taking the job, Mr. Inman publicly drew the line against conservative forces in the Administration. An executive order had been drafted that, among other things, would have given the Central Intelligence Agency some latitude for intelligence gathering within the United States, and it leaked into print. The next day, Mr. Inman repudiated the draft at a news conference and told a reporter afterward that he was personally trying to avert "a series of repugnant changes for which I would not stay in this Administration." The offending provisions were dropped. Disputes With Casey</p>
        <p>Mr. Inman, who had said at the outset that he would not stay longer than two years, resigned a year later, in the spring of 1982. In an interview at the time, he spoke of his "steadily diminishing tolerance for petty bureaucratic intrigue." The report by the Congressional committees that investigated the Iran-contra affair said that shortly before he quit, he had disagreed with Mr. Casey's belief in the legality of expanding covert assistance to one of the rebel leaders in Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>His major accomplishment, former officials agree, was his role in creating a blueprint for the nation's multibillion-dollar investments in surveillance and eavesdropping satellites, although some of the projects were subsequently canceled, when budgets tightened in the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>After leaving the C.I.A., Mr. Inman entered private business, but he kept a toe in the world of intelligence, working as a consultant to the House Intelligence Committee.</p>
        <p>That role did not last long. Mr. Inman left shortly after the committee, in September 1982, issued a staff report that claimed there was bias in El Salvador analyses by intelligence agencies and the State Department.</p>
        <p>One of the report's central assertions was that the State Department had inadequately examined claims that American-trained El Salvadoran troops had massacred civilians in the village of El Mozote. Those claims of a massacre have since been confirmed by evidence gathered by a United Nations commission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inman announced his resignation from the House panel to a group of retired intelligence officers, saying he had not been consulted about the contents of what he felt was a "deeply flawed" document.</p>
        <p>Characteristically, this criticism did not leave any hard feelings among members of the House committee, and Mr. Inman was still consulted on many issues.</p>
        <p>"We said, 'He has a right to his opinion,' and we wrote it off," Mr. Mineta recalled.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
