<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islamists Take Office In Province Of Pakistan</title>
    <meta content="Y26STA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/26/international/asia/26STAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1443842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THREATS AND RESPONSES: TALIBAN BACKERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DB1F39F935A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islamists Take Office In Province Of Pakistan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Islamists Take Office in Province of Pakistan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>PESHAWAR, Pakistan, Nov. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pro-Taliban clerics and politicians fill old colonial hall of provincial assembly in Peshawar, Pakistan, to take their oath of office, vowing to introduce strict Islamic law and to end American military presence in province; Islamic radicals now dominate Pakistan's Northwest Frontier Province; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pro-Taliban clerics and politicians filled the old colonial hall of the provincial assembly here to take their oath of office today, vowing to introduce strict Islamic law and to end the American military presence in the province.</p>
        <p>In Pakistan's recent elections, the alliance of militant Islamic parties, the Muttahida Majlis-e-Amal, won a majority in the local assembly in the North West Frontier Province, which borders Afghanistan. Their success at the polls was an unwelcome surprise to the government of President Pervez Musharraf and to the United States, since the province has been a focus in the search for Al Qaeda and Taliban members who were thought to have escaped to the area from Afghanistan this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pro-Taliban clerics and politicians vowed to introduce strict Islamic law and to end the American military presence in Peshawar, Pakistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pro-Taliban clerics and politicians filled the old colonial hall of the provincial assembly here to take their oath of office today, vowing to introduce strict Islamic law and to end the American military presence in the province.</p>
        <p>In Pakistan's recent elections, the alliance of militant Islamic parties, the Muttahida Majlis-e-Amal, won a majority in the local assembly in the North West Frontier Province, which borders Afghanistan. Their success at the polls was an unwelcome surprise to the government of President Pervez Musharraf and to the United States, since the province has been a focus in the search for Al Qaeda and Taliban members who were thought to have escaped to the area from Afghanistan this year.</p>
        <p>The religious alliance won great popularity in the border areas with a strongly anti-American campaign. Its politicians opposed the American military presence in Afghanistan and called for an end to America's use of Pakistan's air bases and to the presence of F.B.I. agents, who have taken part in police raids in the province. Legislators continued to emphasize that agenda today as the local assembly convened.</p>
        <p>''There is no need for help from American forces or F.B.I. agents or other U.S. agencies,'' Liaquat Baluch, deputy leader of the Jamaat-e-Islami party, one of the dominant parties in the alliance, told Reuters in Islamabad.</p>
        <p>''If there is a need to control terrorism, then Pakistani forces are in a position to control these people, and there is no need for support from outside,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The provincial assembly and its chief minister may in fact not have the power to end the American presence. The nation's prime minister, Zafarullah Khan Jamali, who was sworn in on Saturday together with most of his cabinet, has said foreign policy would continue unchanged.</p>
        <p>The provincial assembly will have nominal control over the local police force, but not over army forces in the province. Under a law passed last week, the federal government will be able to override provincial orders in the interests of national security.</p>
        <p>Yet the provincial legislators who took office today, many of them for the first time, expressed their determination to bring change.</p>
        <p>Akram Durrani, 48, a conservative politician from the tribal areas bordering Afghanistan who is likely to be elected the province's chief minister by legislators this week, described his agenda. ''Enforcement of an Islamic system is our top priority,'' he said after taking his oath of office. ''We will make laws according to Islam.''</p>
        <p>Legislators set the tone for future debates, pausing to offer prayers for Mir Aimal Kasi, the Pakistani who was executed in Virginia last week for killing two C.I.A. employees in 1993. In speeches made before taking their oath several said they refused to recognize constitutional amendments introduced by General Musharraf in the three years since he seized power in a coup.</p>
        <p>One legislator asked that members be allowed to take the oath in Arabic, alongside the three national languages -- Pashto, Urdu and English -- saying that Pakistan was an Islamic state and that Arabic was God's language.</p>
        <p>THREATS AND RESPONSES: TALIBAN BACKERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
