<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bid for Retrial Cites Claim That Judge Had Affair</title>
    <meta content="17judge" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/17/nyregion/17judge.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1718314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DB113EF934A25752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bid for Retrial Cites Claim That Judge Had Affair</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bid for Retrial Cites Claim That Judge Had Affair</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens man in prison for murder has filed a motion for a new trial, based on accusations that the judge unfairly helped Queens prosecutors and had an affair with one of them, which tainted his judgment.</p>
        <p>The accusations came from the judge's former law clerk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Queens man in prison for murder has filed a motion for a new trial, based on accusations that the judge unfairly helped Queens prosecutors and had an affair with one of them, which tainted his judgment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Queens man in prison for murder has filed a motion for a new trial, based on accusations that the judge unfairly helped Queens prosecutors and had an affair with one of them, which tainted his judgment.</p>
        <p>The accusations came from the judge's former law clerk.</p>
        <p>The man, Tyrone Johnson, was initially convicted in 2002 in the fatal shooting of a nightclub owner in 2000, but that decision was thrown out after a prosecutor was found to have lied to the judge about a witness. In 2003 Mr. Johnson was retried in front of the judge, Justice Jaime A. Rios, in State Supreme Court and was convicted by a jury. Justice Rios, 59, sentenced Mr. Johnson, 28, of Jamaica, Queens, to 20 years to life. He is now in Sing Sing Correctional Facility in Westchester.</p>
        <p>But he recently retained the defense lawyer Ronald L. Kuby and seized on a complaint against Justice Rios made by the law clerk, Judith B. Memblatt, whom Justice Rios dismissed last year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Memblatt, 47, in a complaint to the State Commission on Judicial Conduct, claimed that Justice Rios began a sexual relationship in 1996 with a Queens prosecutor, Meryl A. Lutsky.</p>
        <p>Although Ms. Lutsky left the Queens district attorney's office in 2000, before Mr. Johnson's case came before Justice Rios, Ms. Memblatt claims that his affair was ''an open secret'' in the district attorney's office and that Justice Rios regularly curried favor with prosecutors to keep them from exposing him. Ms. Memblatt, who is suing Justice Rios for wrongful termination, also said that the judge suggested improvements in the prosecution's case during Mr. Johnson's trial.</p>
        <p>Ms. Memblatt charged that Justice Rios openly flirted with Ms. Lutsky in court and made humorous hints of their affair. In an interview yesterday, she said she became concerned about the relationship for fear that it might adversely affect some defendants' cases. Her complaints to the commission were included in Mr. Johnson's motion, which was filed Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Kuby said that Ms. Memblatt's complaint indicated that Justice Rios gave the prosecutor in the case ''a secret tutorial'' on how to convict Mr. Johnson.</p>
        <p>''Is it too much to ask that my client get one fair trial without sex or secret coaching?'' he said. ''If the D.A.'s office knew Justice Rios had an ongoing sexual relationship with one of their prosecutors, the judge had a real motive to maintain good relations with other Queens prosecutors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuby said that he was confident Mr. Johnson would get a new trial and that it would certainly include ''lots of lurid testimony about sex and corruption in the Queens courthouse.''</p>
        <p>''I'm certainly going to have all of them testify -- Justice Rios, Ms. Lutsky -- it's gonna be ugly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a statement, a spokesman for the Queens district attorney, Richard A. Brown, called Mr. Johnson's motion ''a rehash of allegations'' by ''a disgruntled former court system employee.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the State Office of Court Administration, David Bookstaver, said yesterday that Justice Rios had chosen not to comment.</p>
        <p>''It's crucial to remember though that these allegations are from a disgruntled former employee,'' Mr. Bookstaver said.</p>
        <p>Robert H. Tembeckjian, the administrator for the Commission on Judicial Conduct, said he could not comment specifically on the investigations into Ms. Memblatt's complaints because investigations are kept confidential.</p>
        <p>''But I can say that when we find that a judge is having a sexual relationship with someone appearing before that judge, we discipline them publicly,'' he said. ''Judge Rios has never been disciplined for that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lutsky, 38, who now works for the state attorney general's office, did not respond to messages left at her home and office yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
