<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="27POP.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D71539F934A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="3253" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>BLUES TRAVELER, Roseland, 239 West 52d Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800. Ten years into its career, Blues Traveler gives its fans an occasion to twirl in their tie-dyed T-shirts while the band stretches whiny songs into interminable jams. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8; tickets are $22.50 (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>* RAY BROWN, Blue Note, 131 West Third Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 475-8592. It can be heard immediately: the precision of his time, his thick sound and his faultless intonation. Mr. Brown, a bassist and a major figure in be-bop, is simply apart from the rest of the competition. And he's a fine band leader; his tunes and arrangements are detailed and make trio performances more than improvisations on a theme. He'll be joined by Geoff Keezer on piano and Karriem Riggins on drums. Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday, sets are at 9 and 11:30 P.M.; the cover is $35 and the minimum is $5 (Peter Watrous).</p>
        <p>COMBUSTIBLE EDISON, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, at the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111. In Combustible Edison's neo-lounge music, easy-listening tempos and cheesy keyboard tones enfold angular jazz harmonies and oddball structures. The music suggests that martinis were the hallucinogens of the 1950's, plunging their users into realms of exotica and uncharted strangeness. Tomorrow night at 9:30 and 11; admission is $12 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* MARSHALL CRENSHAW, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 798-0406. He's a scholar of rock-and-roll dreams, a man who knows how to shape a melody and a trusty live wire in concert. In short, Marshall Crenshaw is a local treasure, and he deserves devotion. Currently preparing for the birth of a baby and the recording of a new album that he promises will emanate vintage cool, he will probably break out some fine new material for these gigs and stretch out on some classics. Tonight, Michael Shelley opens the show; tomorrow, the Moonlighters share the bill. Tonight and tomorrow night at 10; tickets are $12 (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>ELVIS CRESPO, Copacabana, 617 West 57th Street, Manhattan, (212) 582-2672. He's the king of the radio with his hit ''Suavemente.'' It's merengue, and as usual, it comes in one flavor. But Mr. Crespo can move and entertain, and he'll be joined by the salsa singer Jerry Rivera. The show tomorrow night starts at 11; the cover is $30 (Watrous).</p>
        <p>* DAVE DOUGLAS'S TINY BELL TRIO, Knitting Factory, Old Office, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. With this band Mr. Douglas runs Eastern European music through the post-Ornette Coleman wringer. Given all of the band members' other diversions (they might be in 20 groups among the three of them), the band hasn't performed in quite a while. Gearing up for its next recording, it will be playing new material through the weekend. Sets, tonight through Sunday night, are at 8 and 9:30; admission is $10, and there is a one-drink minimum (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>CANO ESTREMERA, Copacabana, 617 West 57th Street, Manhattan, (212) 582-2672. A night of five bands, including Mr. Estremera and his group; he's considered one of Puerto Rico's finest improvisers. He'll have some heavy company tonight, including the singers Hector Tricoche, Sammy Gonzalez and Luisito Carrion. The show starts at 9; the cover is $10 for women and $15 for men (Watrous).</p>
        <p>CARLOS GARNETT QUARTET, Lenox Lounge, 288 Lenox Avenue, at 125th Street, Harlem, (212) 427-0253. Once a satellite in Miles Davis's orbit (he played on ''Get Up With It'' and ''On the Corner''), the saxophonist Carlos Garnett has been playing more traditional fare in recent years. He appears here with a rhythm section including the extraordinary young pianist James Hurt. Sets tonight and tomorrow night are at 9, 10:30 and midnight; there is an $8 cover charge and a two-drink minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* EL GRAN COMBO, Latin Quarter, 2551 Broadway, at 96th Street, (212) 864-7600. One of the Caribbean's great bands, El Gran Combo has been playing around town fairly often recently, and that's a good thing. Puerto Rico's swing machine -- it developed out of the percussionist Cortijo's band -- led by Rafael Ithier, is still powerful. It's elegant and reaches its ecstasy carefully, step by step. And there's always the choreography, which is controlled yet extravagant. The band's an experience. It will be joined by Tony Vega, a good salsa singer. The show tomorrow night starts at 11:30; the cover is $20 (Watrous).</p>
        <p>ARLO GUTHRIE AND PETE SEEGER, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Every Thanksgiving weekend brings this annual celebration of two cantankerous American traditions: the tall tale, as spun by Mr. Guthrie in songs and between them, and the determination to crusade through song, as Mr. Seeger has through his long career. The audience will be there to sing along. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 P.M.; tickets are $20.50 to $32.50 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>HOT TUNA, Tramps, 51 West 21st Street , Chelsea, (212) 727-7788. The guitarist Jorma Kaukonen and the bassist Jack Casady started Hot Tuna as a side project from the Jefferson Airplane, but it has now outlasted the original band. Mr. Kaukonen plays spiky, fingerpicked blues that calmly contemplate death and loss, still harking back to the Rev. Gary Davis; with Hot Tuna's electric lineup, he also unleashes one of the most distinctive solo styles of the psychedelic era, burning with cold like liquid nitrogen. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9; tickets are $30 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>KISS, Nassau Coliseum, Uniondale, N.Y., (516) 794-9300. All Kiss had to do was reconvene its original lineup, put the makeup back on, hook up the fireworks and stage blood, and voila! -- nostalgic old fans raced younger thrill-seekers for tickets. The heavy-breathing songs are workmanlike; the spectacle is its own reward. Tonight at 8 P.M.; tickets are $30 to $85 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>VICTOR LEWIS QUINTET, Sweet Basil, 88 Seventh Avenue South, Greenwich Village, (212) 242-1785. Mr. Lewis is a marvelous drummer, known in the 80's for his associations with Stan Getz and Bobby Watson, and in the 90's for freelancing and playing with his own band, which constitutes the menu for this weekend. The band includes the saxophonist Seamus Blake, whose John Wayne style of delivery challenges the theory that fast playing equals good playing, as well as the pianist Stephen Scott and trumpeter Terell Stafford, important contributors to the current scene. Sets through Sunday night are at 9 and 11, with 12:30 sets tonight and tomorrow night; admission is $20 tonight and tomorrow, $17.50 on Sunday, with a $10 minimum at all shows (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>STEPHIN MERRITT, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street between Delancey and Rivington Streets, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503. Stephin Merritt, the abashed creative genius leading Magnetic Fields and several other underground combos, writes standards for individualists that evoke Cole Porter with a cold while never abandoning their roots in moony 1980's New Wave pop. Here, he does the solo thing as part of this Lower East Side club's singer-songwriter series, although he'll probably bring along a few interesting friends for occasional support. Sunday night at 9 and 10:30; tickets are $8 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* PINETOP PERKINS, Chicago Blues, 73 Eighth Avenue, below 14th Street, West Village, (212) 924-9755. Pinetop Perkins, 85, was the longtime pianist in Muddy Waters' Chicago blues band. He has the entire blues vocabulary in his fingers, from boogie and shuffle bass lines to florid barrelhouse trills and filigrees. But he plays his solos like a cardsharp who only shows what he needs to, and his ruthless economy translates into pithy, ornery blues. Tonight and tomorrow night, with sets at 9:30, 11 and 12:30. Admission is $15 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* ERIC REED TRIO, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan (212) 576-2232. The pianist Eric Reed plays in a sweet style, radiant with gospel and the blues. He's a sentimentalist, but that's only one card in a packed hand. He's increasingly inventive with song structure and arrangement; he can also set fire to a band. And the accompanists -- the bassist Buster Williams and the drummer Rodney Green -- are probably enough to insure that this gig is worth hearing. Sets tonight and tomorrow night are at 8, 10:30 and midnight, with a $20 cover ($15 at midnight) and $10 minimum; on Sunday night, there is one set, at 7, and the cover is $15 with a $10 minimum. A new practice begins at the club on Sunday: half price (Sunday only) for anyone under 18 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>SASHA AND DIGWEED, at Twilo, 530 West 27th Street, Chelsea (212) 462-9422 or (212) 268-1600. A longing for rapture and transcendence is never far from the surface of dance music, particularly in the utopian pulsations set out by the English disk jockey team of John Digweed and Sasha. On their album ''Northern Exposure,'' steady repetition holds time at bay and floating, whooshing sounds and voices suggest freedom from the rigors of form. Tonight; doors open at 11, with John Digweed and Sasha starting at 12:30 and continuing well past dawn. Admission is $25 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>CLARK TERRY, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, West Village, (212) 255-4037. The trumpeter and fluegelhornist developed one of the great distinct styles of the 1950's and 60's, and his solos with Duke Ellington are marvels of rhythmic and melodic development. Like the better, younger members of the orchestra, Mr. Terry assimilated and used both swing and be-bop ideas and turned it all into something important. His approach is, like Thelonious Monk's, above copying; it's simply too personal. Mr. Terry's band includes Don Friedman on piano, David Glasser on saxophone, Marcus McLaurine on bass and Sylvia Cuenca on drums. Sets are 9:30 and 11:30 tonight through Sunday. The cover is $20 on Friday and Saturday; $15 on Sunday with a $10 minimum at all shows (Watrous).</p>
        <p>THE TRAGICALLY HIP, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 564-4882. New York's usually invisible Canadian contingent should turn out in force for the Tragically Hip, a band that's hugely popular up north. Long before the Dave Matthews Band or the Wallflowers, the Tragically Hip was matching disillusioned lyrics to 60's-flavored folk-rock, turning riff songs into chipper, extended jams that throw off their frustration in brash guitar workouts. Tomorrow night at 8; admission is $22.50 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>RANDY WESTON, Iridium, 48 West 63d Street, Manhattan (212) 582-2121. The pianist Randy Weston has been essential in the process of bringing African elements into jazz; he's traveled all over the continent and is tireless as its exponent. Before he took that route, though, he was a student of Thelonious Monk and Duke Ellington, and no other pianist in jazz has the Ellington touch that he does: ringing, big and percussive. The band includes Benny Powell on trombone, Talib Kibwe on saxophone, Alex Blake on bass and Neil Clark on percussion. The sets are at 8:30 and 10:30 P.M. and midnight with no third set on Sunday. The cover is $25 and the minimum is $10 (Watrous).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
