<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIME</title>
    <meta content="27KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D91539F934A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="2862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIME</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''GRIMM TALES,'' a production by the Young Vic Theater Company of London, uses simple props and live music on a range of instruments, including mbira, hurdy-gurdy and dulcimer, to conjure up familiar (''Rumpelstiltskin, ''Little Riding Hood,'' ''Cinderella'') and not so familiar (''The Golden Goose,'' ''The Hare and the Hedgehog,'' ''Brother Scamp'') Grimm fairy tales. Directed by Tim Supple. Victory Theater, 209 West 42d Street, Manhattan. Today through Sunday at 1 and 7 P.M.; Wednesday at 8 P.M.; Thursday and next Friday at 7 P.M. Through Jan. 3. Tickets: $10 to $35. Reservations: (212) 239-6200.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR CHILDREN</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''GRIMM TALES,'' a production by the Young Vic Theater Company of London, uses simple props and live music on a range of instruments, including mbira, hurdy-gurdy and dulcimer, to conjure up familiar (''Rumpelstiltskin, ''Little Riding Hood,'' ''Cinderella'') and not so familiar (''The Golden Goose,'' ''The Hare and the Hedgehog,'' ''Brother Scamp'') Grimm fairy tales. Directed by Tim Supple. Victory Theater, 209 West 42d Street, Manhattan. Today through Sunday at 1 and 7 P.M.; Wednesday at 8 P.M.; Thursday and next Friday at 7 P.M. Through Jan. 3. Tickets: $10 to $35. Reservations: (212) 239-6200.</p>
        <p>''PUPPETS AND PROKOFIEV'' and ''PETER AND THE WOLF,'' presented by Susan Delery Whedon, who uses hand and rod puppets in both productions. ''Puppets and Prokofiev'' (at noon) and ''Peter and the Wolf'' (at 1:30 P.M.) run Fridays through Sundays through Dec. 20. Papageno Puppet Theater, 462 Columbus Avenue, near 82d Street. Tickets: $5. Reservations: (212) 874-3297.</p>
        <p>''THE ROSE SLIPPERS.'' Set on a Caribbean island, this musical involves a young girl's quest, a fearsome forest, some nonhuman companions and witches. The Latin-flavored one-hour show, based on a poem by the Cuban national hero Jose Marti, is directed by Katrina Market. The author is Rosa Soy and the composer is Sue Hadjopoulos. Saturdays and Sundays at 2 P.M. through Dec. 20 at the Looking Glass Theater, 422 West 57th Street, Clinton. Tickets: $10; $8 for children. Information: (212) 307-9467.</p>
        <p>''THE SORCERER'S APPRENTICE,'' a story adapted by Nicolas Coppola, featuring a mischievous apprentice, a baby dragon and a witch, is brought to life with puppets, music and magic. Every Sunday at 2 and 4 P.M. through Dec. 13 at the Children's Aid Society, Greenwich Village Center Theater, 219 Sullivan Street. Tickets: $8; $5 for children. Reservations required: (718) 965-3391.</p>
        <p>''LA PLENOPERA DEL EMPACHE,'' a children's theater classic from Puerto Rico about a little boy who eats too much and gets severe indigestion. That requires a doctor, who solves the problem by playing a joke on the boy and his mother. Performed in Spanish with English titles. Tomorrow at 2 P.M. At La Tea Theater at the Clemente Soto Velez Cultural Center, 107 Suffolk Street, second floor, Lower East Side. Tickets: $10. Reservations: (718) 956-1587 or (212) 529-1948.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>BIG APPLE CIRCUS. New York's own one-ring circus returns to Damrosch Park at Lincoln Center through Jan. 10. No seat is more than 50 feet from the action. The year's theme is ''Happy On!,'' inspired by vaudeville and French music-hall revues. There will be plenty of acrobatics, clowning, jugglers and canine capers. Tickets from $12 to $58. Information, including days and times: (212) 268-2500 or (212) 721-6500.</p>
        <p>''HARVEST CEREMONY: BEYOND THE THANKSGIVING MYTH,'' an interactive theater production about the story of the first Thanksgiving, by Marty Kreipe de Montano, with Jennifer Fell Hayes. Today, tomorrow and Sunday at noon, 1:30 and 3 P.M. at the National Museum of the American Indian, Alexander Hamilton United States Custom House, 1 Bowling Green, lower Manhattan.Free. Information: (212) 514-3700.</p>
        <p>''FAT CATS.'' Stuff paper and glue together to create roly-poly felines. Learn how to make cheery holiday table centerpieces at a workshop tomorrow and Sunday at 1, 2 and 3 P.M., at the Staten Island Children's Museum, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston. Free with museum admission. Admission: $4; children under 2, free. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>HOLIDAY BOOK KICKOFF. The children's bookstore Books of Wonder will introduce four authors and artists with their works: James Gurney of the ''Dinotopia'' series; Leo and Diane Dillon, illustrators of ''To Every Thing There Is a Season,'' and Robert Sabuda, the creator of ''Disney ABC Pop-Up.'' Free tomorrow from noon to 2 P.M. at the bookstore, 16 West 18th Street, Chelsea. Information: (212) 989-3270.</p>
        <p>''THE NUTCRACKER'' ON ICE. The St. Petersburg State Ice Ballet will present the Tchaikovsky ballet, Sunday at 1 and 4:30 P.M. at the Brooklyn Center for the Performing arts at Brooklyn College, one block from the junction of Flatbush and Nostrand Avenues, Brooklyn. Bring canned foods, toys, bottled water and other donations for the victims of Hurricane Mitch in Honduras. Tickets: $15. Reservations: (718) 951-4500.</p>
        <p>QUILT DESIGN WORKSHOPS will be offered through Sunday at 2 and 3 P.M. at the Lefferts Homestead Children's Museum, off Flatbush Avenue near Empire Boulevard, Prospect Heights, Brooklyn. Learn the basics of creating and designing a quilt. Free. Information: (718) 965-6505.</p>
        <p>''REEL TO REAL FOR KIDS,'' a series combining films with live performances, will present ''The Blacksmith'' and ''Cops,'' two 1922 Buster Keaton capers, tomorrow at 11:30 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. The films will be shown with their original scores recreated by Rick Benjamin and his Paragon Ragtime Orchestra. Walter Reade Theater, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $10; $6 for children 16 and under. Information: (212) 875-5370.</p>
        <p>THE STATION AT CITICORP CENTER. Visitors to the Atrium at Citicorp Center, 153 East 53d Street, Manhattan, will find a miniature train exhibition made of more than 25 trains and trolley cars, 20 automated signals, 70 train controls, nearly 1,000 feet of track and more than 1,000 miniature people, animals and other figures. Free. Through Jan. 2. Mondays through Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Sundays, noon to 5 P.M. Closed Thanksgiving, Christmas and New Year's Day.</p>
        <p>THANKSGIVING WEEKEND. Recycle and remake storybook tales into television fantasies, Friday through Sunday at the Children's Museum of Manhattan, Tisch Building, 212 West 83d Street. Admission: $5; the elderly, $2.50; under 1, free. Information: (212) 721-1234.</p>
        <p>''STORY CORNER: STORIES UNDER THE MOON,'' a continuing series at the Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. Traditional stories from around the world will take you to the moon and back. Catherine Fukushima will tell stories about the moon, including why it was created and why its colors and shadows look the way they do, tomorrow at 4 P.M. in the Hall of the Americas, on the first floor. Free with museum admission. Admission: $4; students, $2; the elderly, $1.50. Information: (718) 638-5000, extension 327.</p>
        <p>SEVENTH ANNUAL INTERNATIONAL CHILDREN'S FESTIVAL. The Museum of Television and Radio, 25 West 52d Street, Manhattan, continues this event with ''Making Mischief,'' screenings of six international children's programs about characters who can't stay out of trouble. Saturdays and Sundays from noon to 6 P.M. through Dec. 13. Also, Stephanie D'Abruzzo, one of the Jim Henson Company's Muppet performers, will conduct a puppetry demonstration, tomorrow and Sunday at 12:15 and 2:45 P.M. Free, with suggested admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; children under 13, $3. Information: (212) 621-6600.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''BEAKMAN'S WORLD ON TOUR.'' The wacky science wizard is taking his world to the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens, through Jan. 3. Visitors can take a journey into the Philippine rain forest, find out what they weigh on the moon and discover Mount Beakmore in the 4,000-square-foot traveling show based on the ''Beakman's World'' television series. Museum hours: Mondays through Wednesdays, 9:30 A.M. to 2 P.M.; Thursdays through Sundays, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $6; $4 for children 4 to 15 and the elderly. Information: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>''BEHIND THE SCREEN,'' an exhibition at the Liberty Street Gallery, 225 Liberty Street, lower Manhattan, is a traveling version of the permanent exhibition at the American Museum of the Moving Image in Astoria, Queens, with an important difference: new software. Using computer work stations, visitors can play director, actor, animator, special-effects designer, music supervisor and sound-effects editor. On view through Dec. 6, Mondays through Fridays, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 6 P.M. Suggested admission: $5; $3 for children. Information: (718) 784-4520.</p>
        <p>''WORLD CIRCUS,'' a 1,200-square-foot exhibition at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights, on view through Jan. 3, focuses on the circuses of various cultures. It is more like a road show than a static museum display. Build your own stilts for a ''Walking Tall Workshop,'' today from 11 A.M. to noon and 2 to 4 P.M.; tomorrow and Sunday at 1 P.M. Museum hours: Wednesdays through Fridays, 2 to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Events are free with suggested admission: $3. Information: (718) 735-4402.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>BRONX ZOO, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham. Until Dec. 31, the zoo illuminates more than 50 animal sculptures covered in thousands of lights. Holiday Lights hours: Monday through Thursday, 5:30 to 9 P.M.; Friday and Saturday until 9:30 P.M. Zoo hours through March: daily, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.. Holiday Lights admission: $6; for children and the elderly, $3. Zoo admission through Jan. 3: $6; the elderly and ages 2 to 12, $3; under 2, free; free for everyone on Wednesdays, except for Holiday Lights. Parking, $6. Information: (718) 367-1010.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
