<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Pop Music For Middle Age</title>
    <meta content="XX27AD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="RECORD REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgarrigle, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdonald, Audra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgarrigle, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D61539F934A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Pop Music For Middle Age</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden comment laments dearth of unpretentious, nondisposable pop music in age of MTV; recommends some notable exceptions, including debut recording of Audra McDonald and The McGarrigle Hour, collection by North America's leading folk music dynasty; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attention fellow dinosaurs, old fogies and senescent Beatlemaniacs. If you can hardly find any music on the radio to listen to nowadays, and the bouncy toy sounds of Brandy and Monica fighting over a boy don't speak to your soul the way Joni Mitchell's or Bob Dylan's records once did, there is still pop music being made that is worth caring about. Some of it is even made by musicians in their 20's. And some of it (although not much) is even very popular.</p>
        <p>That music is not the weepy bombast of Celine Dion or the generic country-pop of Shania Twain, two talented mass-appeal singers whose songs and productions reflect a glitzy late-90's, corporate impersonality. Nor is it the Three Tenors peddling ersatz high culture to stadium-size audiences. It is certainly not Barry Manilow delivering a shallow, emotionally vapid tribute to Frank Sinatra on his newest album, ''Manilow Sings Sinatra'' (Arista), or Neil Diamond pompously trampling over classic movie songs on his new two-disk recording, ''The Movie Album: As Time Goes By'' (Columbia).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attention fellow dinosaurs, old fogies and senescent Beatlemaniacs. If you can hardly find any music on the radio to listen to nowadays, and the bouncy toy sounds of Brandy and Monica fighting over a boy don't speak to your soul the way Joni Mitchell's or Bob Dylan's records once did, there is still pop music being made that is worth caring about. Some of it is even made by musicians in their 20's. And some of it (although not much) is even very popular.</p>
        <p>That music is not the weepy bombast of Celine Dion or the generic country-pop of Shania Twain, two talented mass-appeal singers whose songs and productions reflect a glitzy late-90's, corporate impersonality. Nor is it the Three Tenors peddling ersatz high culture to stadium-size audiences. It is certainly not Barry Manilow delivering a shallow, emotionally vapid tribute to Frank Sinatra on his newest album, ''Manilow Sings Sinatra'' (Arista), or Neil Diamond pompously trampling over classic movie songs on his new two-disk recording, ''The Movie Album: As Time Goes By'' (Columbia).</p>
        <p>Unpretentious, nondisposable pop has always been hard to find, but it's a little harder to come by nowadays than it used to be. Eons ago, it seems, pop music was the medium adopted by baby boomers for sharing their feelings about sex, politics, relationships and society. Pop music mattered. With the rise of MTV, television swallowed up pop and regurgitated it as passive couch entertainment. Now computers are supplanting television as the hot center of youth culture. The world is a chat room in which you can download fragments of the new Jewel and Alanis Morisette albums and sample them like dabs of cologne.</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago, it seemed possible that the American songwriters who came of age in the 1960's and 70's would develop into grand old sages of rock-and-roll and that their audiences would grow old with them, continuing a shared conversation about growing up, learning hard lessons and facing mortality. That expectation proved wrong. Once it had grown up, the rock-and-roll generation didn't need its pop stars to be role models anymore. It was too busy making money and creating babies to keep up with heroes who themselves seemed less heroic as they aged and sobered up.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the performers who were supposed to remain beacons of wisdom and enlightenment in an extended rock-and-roll community (with a few scattered exceptions) lost courage. Fame tends to be addictive and toxic. Once it's attained, holding onto it becomes an end in itself. In a youth-obsessed culture, pop stars are the last people in the world who want to be viewed as middle-aged. Most feel compelled to eke out the last drop of youth-culture adoration before their fan bases evaporate.</p>
        <p>Even pop stars who are now in their 30's are busy cultivating ''younger'' sounds. On much of Whitney Houston's new album, ''My Love Is Your Love'' (Arista), one of pop's most powerful balladeers has suddenly turned girlish, reining in her majestic gospel power to pose as Brandy and Monica's sassy peer.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the old dinosaurs roll on. Joni Mitchell's hugely disappointing new album, ''Taming the Tiger'' (Reprise), may not have a fraction of the immediacy, depth and melodicism of her best 1970's work, but the music has some texture, and the voice sounds lived in. Probably this year's best ''new'' album of adult pop music was recorded 32 years ago: ''Bob Dylan Live 1966'' (Columbia), a two-disk ''authorized bootleg.''</p>
        <p>So here follows one veteran critic's annotated personal roundup of favorite adult pop albums of 1998. Omitted is Mr. Dylan's album because it consists of old material. Except for the top two -- Audra McDonald's ''Way Back to Paradise'' and ''The McGarrigle Hour'' -- the rest are listed alphabetically. (CD's are $17 to $18 for a single disk to $25 for a two-CD set.)</p>
        <p>AUDRA McDONALD: ''WAY BACK TO PARADISE''  (Nonesuch). The debut recording of the 28-year-old vocal phenomenon who has won three Tony Awards just barely qualifies as a pop album, since most of the material hovers on the thin line between Broadway and opera. Instead of making a conventional debut by singing Broadway standards, Ms. McDonald boldly introduces recent work by six rising young composers who represent musical theater's best hope of transcending the schlock of Andrew Lloyd Webber, Frank Wildhorn and Disney's second-string songwriting teams. Whether any of these composers make it on Broadway, however, depends on whether their work strikes a populist chord.</p>
        <p>The group includes one genius, Adam Guettel (the grandson of Richard Rodgers), whose deeply romantic pop music roams all over the landscape, from Samuel Barber to gospel, and several others who over time might prove to be equally important. Ricky Ian Gordon's settings of texts by Langston Hughes and James Agee, like Mr. Guettel's three contributions, are accessible, moving art songs. The chattiest numbers are by Michael John LaChuisa, who is composing a musical, ''Marie Christine,'' specifically for Ms. McDonald.</p>
        <p>Ms. McDonald's singing is magnificent: highly dramatic, tasteful, psychologically acute, heart-rending. Although operatically trained, this mezzo-soprano thinks nothing of slipping into gospel or into speech-song or into hard belting when the song demands.</p>
        <p>Her casual breaking down of musical categories, both vocally and in her choice of material, indicates the affinity a new generation of formally trained singers has for nonclassical music. Everything about the record is extremely encouraging.</p>
        <p>''THE McGARRIGLE HOUR''  (Hannibal/Rykodisc). This wonderful 21-song collection is a kind of summary statement by North America's leading folk music dynasty, whose senior members are now in their 50's. They include the French-Canadian sisters Kate and Anna McGarrigle; Kate's former husband, Loudon Wainwright 3d; their two children, Rufus and Martha Wainwright, and assorted other relatives and friends. The album is a kind of marathon home musicale in which they sing one another's songs as well as personal favorites by others, from Irving Berlin's ''What'll I Do?'' to Cole Porter's ''Allez-Vous-En.'' Even the vintage Broadway tunes shed their urban glamour to become bare-bones reflections on life, love and loss, sung plainly without a trace of self-pity by the McGarrigles' lovely homespun voices.</p>
        <p>''The McGarrigle Hour'' conveys a powerful sense of the extended family as a vital, complicated organism nurturing itself through music, the young and the middle-aged singing side by side, all allowing their blemishes and quirks to show. The folksy purity of the music along with a sense of these intertwining creative lives offers a realism rarely found in pop. (Loudon and Rufus Wainwright each have fine solo albums in this roundup.)</p>
        <p>Here are the other recommended albums:</p>
        <p>ANDY BEY: ''SHADES OF BEY''  (Evidence). The little-known jazz baritone has a voice so cool and mellow you want to take a dip in it. Dorival Caymmi's ''Like a Lover'' (with lyrics by Alan and Marilyn Bergman), crooned to a softly strummed guitar, sets the dreamy mood.</p>
        <p>ERIC CLAPTON: ''PILGRIM''  (Reprise). The best songs on this bleakly eloquent album of orchestrated blues meditations express a choked-up grief and despair that slices to the bone. The year's most underrated album. Killer cuts: ''Pilgrim'' and ''Inside of Me.''</p>
        <p>''ADAM COHEN''  (Columbia). The debut album of Leonard Cohen's son Adam reveals him to be a chip off the old block in his grimly perceptive evisceration of troubled sexual relationships and rivalries. A promising beginning.</p>
        <p>ELVIS COSTELLO WITH BURT BACHARACH: ''PAINTED FROM MEMORY''  (Mercury). The collaboration on a suite of lovelorn ballads with music (lavishly arranged) by Mr. Bacharach and lyrics by Mr. Costello, who sings them in an anguished geeky voice, powerfully weds an airy 60's pop romanticism with a lingering post-punk orneriness. Killer cut: ''God Give Me Strength.''</p>
        <p>SHERYL CROW: ''THE GLOBE SESSIONS''  (A&amp;M). These tough, knotty well-made observational songs sung with sinewy bravado (tinged with tenderness) find a bracing balance between vocal spontaneity and solid song craft.</p>
        <p>ARETHA FRANKLIN: ''A ROSE IS STILL A ROSE''  (Arista). In songs written and produced by such hip-hop luminaries as Lauryn Hill and Sean (Puffy) Combs, soul, hip-hop and funk collide happily. If the material is uneven, the queen of soul is in great voice, not having sounded this good since the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>HERBIE HANCOCK: ''GERSHWIN'S WORLD''  (Verve). Mr. Hancock's triumphantly sweeping overview of George Gershwin and his influences features an all-star cast that ranges from Stevie Wonder (''St. Louis Blues'') to a craggy-voiced Joni Mitchell (''The Man I Love''). Mr. Hancock plays a movement from Ravel's Piano Concerto in G. Comprehensive and deep.</p>
        <p>LYLE LOVETT: ''STEP INSIDE THIS HOUSE''  (Curb/MCA). The two-disk anthology of Mr. Lovett's favorite Texas songwriters (including Townes Van Zandt, Vince Bell, Guy Clark and Willis Allan Ramsey, among many others) is a labor of love that is beautifully sung, if a trifle bland.</p>
        <p>MADONNA: ''RAY OF LIGHT''  (Maverick/Warner Brothers) This transcendent semi-electronic disco album matches the best Donna Summer in atmospheric intensity. Madonna's explorations of spirituality feel sincere if a little awkward. But the spectacle of the 40-year-old pop star still refusing to play it safe is heartening.</p>
        <p>BETTE MIDLER: ''BATHHOUSE BETTY''  (Warner Brothers) Ms. Midler's best and most varied album since her 1972 debut, ''The Divine Miss M,'' captures its prototype's exuberance but in a more restrained, grown-up 90's way.</p>
        <p>WILLIE NELSON: ''TEATRO''  (Island). The producer Daniel Lanois, the master of evocative rustic sound effects, helps enhance Mr. Nelson's well-earned aura of Texas sage on a collection of old and recent Nelson true-grit ballads. Emmylou Harris provides haunting rough-edged backup vocals.</p>
        <p>BONNIE RAITT: ''FUNDAMENTAL''  (Capitol). Ms. Raitt, teamed with the producer Mitchell Froom, draws back into a spare bluesy groove. The singing is tough and convincing. Killer cut: John Hiatt's devastating ''Lovers Will.''</p>
        <p>SEAL: ''HUMAN BEING''  (Warner Brothers). Multi-layered, impassioned, almost symphonic in places, Seal's third album broods about the end of a relationship and its cosmic implications. Trevor Horn's astonishingly rich production makes up for the vagueness of some of the lyrics. Killer cut: ''No Easy Way.''</p>
        <p>DUNCAN SHEIK: ''HUMMING''  (Atlantic). Mr. Sheik's Buddhist-influenced reflections are gently sung and exquisitely arranged in an orchestral style that recalls Nick Drake's early records inflected with George Harrison-style psychedelia. Luscious.</p>
        <p>ELLIOTT SMITH: ''XO''  (Dreamworks). While the bright, lush production of the first major-label album for a rising singer-songwriter recalls the heyday of the Beatles and the Beach Boys, Mr. Smith's introspective songs and low-key delivery pull intriguingly against the arrangements.</p>
        <p>LOUDON WAINWRIGHT 3D: ''LITTLE SHIP''  (Charisma). Just because the songs' middle-aged growing pains are expressed comically doesn't mean they don't hurt. Mr. Wainwright imparts bitter truths and makes you laugh at them.</p>
        <p>''RUFUS WAINWRIGHT''  (Dreamworks). Once you get used to his marble-mouthed diction, you find delight in the lavishly arranged folk-pop songs by Loudon Wainwright's gay son. These elliptical, anguished, funny, ornate reflections on family ties and the painful comedy of (usually) unrequited love are well worth studying.</p>
        <p>LUCINDA WILLIAMS: ''CAR WHEELS ON A GRAVEL ROAD''  (Mercury). Southern country-rock realism constructed so artfully it sounds artless. These timeless vignettes evoke people and places with the same pungency as great short stories. Ms. Williams embodies a literary and musical esthetic that might be called essentialist in its leanness and precision of inflection.</p>
        <p>RECORD REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
