<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agent 007, Your Armored Car Is In</title>
    <meta content="27CARS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevrolet Division of General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1DA1439F934A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agent 007, Your Armored Car Is In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Autos column on vehicles that have been fortified to protect occupants from attack; armored-car specialists and companies like BMW see increased demand for such models; photos; diagram of armored Chevy Suburban, which is said to be able to withstand hits from military assault rifles (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT looks like any other brand-new BMW 540i. But try firing a .44 Magnum at the ''540i Protection'' -- it handles bullets as blithely as Superman does. Still, no car can do everything that the Man of Steel can; the 540i Protection still has to be driven around tall buildings.</p>
        <p>We are talking armored cars here, automobiles that have been fortified to withstand attacks by shady characters with guns or crowbars in their hands and larceny, or worse, on their minds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT looks like any other brand-new BMW 540i. But try firing a .44 Magnum at the ''540i Protection'' -- it handles bullets as blithely as Superman does. Still, no car can do everything that the Man of Steel can; the 540i Protection still has to be driven around tall buildings.</p>
        <p>We are talking armored cars here, automobiles that have been fortified to withstand attacks by shady characters with guns or crowbars in their hands and larceny, or worse, on their minds.</p>
        <p>Turning out these cars, customized to keep the enemy out, is a growing business: O'Gara-Hess &amp; Eisenhardt, the armored-car division of the far-flung Kroll-O'Gara security company, has opened factories in four countries in the last five years. Until 1993, it did all its work at its Cincinnati headquarters.</p>
        <p>BMW, too, sees demand for armored cars that do not look like armored cars. The bottom line, BMW says, is the bottom line: installing security equipment at the factory is less expensive than having the materials added after a car has left the assembly line.</p>
        <p>BMW maintains that these after-market alterations weaken the cars they are meant to strengthen. ''It is a fact that work of this kind often means a loss of quality,'' said Edward T. Hightower, manager of 5- and 7-Series cars for BMW of North America. ''And you don't have the body panels being disassembled, as by an after-market supplier, which in most cases voids the manufacturer's responsibility.'' Or, by another name, the warranty.</p>
        <p>O'Gara-Hess disputes the idea that a specialty coach builder cannot do the job. ''To answer the idea that we're going to mess up the car, we've never, ever had that complaint, not even once,'' said Dan Heimbrock, O'Gara-Hess's marketing manager. ''You're only adding a couple hundred pounds, the majority of it glass. The competency has to be that you put the glass in right and put the trim back. It's not tremendously complicated. The hard part is how do you make sure that the armor is integrated into the body of the car so that the bullets don't go through -- ever.''</p>
        <p>To keep that from happening, O'Gara-Hess's Lincoln Town Car has reinforced body panels and an armored roof. BMW's 540i Protection (yes, the ''P'' word is part of the name) comes factory-equipped with everything needed to outgun and outrun the average armed assailant, from a bullet-resistant body and windows to run-flat tires.</p>
        <p>That is also everything that Bonnie and Clyde could have wished for in a getaway car, though BMW's marketing pitch is aimed at potential victims -- high-profile types whose names are more likely to appear in the gossip columns than on most-wanted posters.</p>
        <p>BMW insists that the 540i Protection was not designed with drug lords in mind. ''That's certainly not something we're promoting,'' Mr. Hightower said. ''We're not promoting or targeting any illegal type of activity.''</p>
        <p>O'Gara-Hess goes a step further, running background checks on customers. ''There are enough lower-end companies that don't care who they serve, particularly in places like Colombia,'' Mr. Heimbrock said. ''If someone shows up on our doorstep with a suitcase full of money, we don't just hand them the keys.''</p>
        <p>Hess &amp; Eisenhardt, predecessor of O'Gara-Hess, began as a maker of ambulances and hearses and got into the armored-car business at the request of the Secret Service in the 1940's. Mr. Heimbrock said today's customers were ''people who are afraid of rape, abduction, kidnapping or armed assault.'' All are high-profile people, he said, and most fall into one of three categories: celebrities, politicians or captains of industry. ''Outside the United States, the market is much broader,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The BMW 540i Protection has mats of a plastic tissuelike material called aramide fiber -- which BMW says is lighter and stronger than bulletproof vests -- tucked like insulation behind the body panels and the back seat. If a hapless attacker tries to drill his way in, BMW says the material will wrap itself around the drill bit, rendering it useless.</p>
        <p>BMW also replaces the conventional windows with reinforced glass made with nearly invisible steel fibers. Don't try to roll down the rear windows to wave at crowds: As a precaution against would-be assassins, the windows do not move. Also, hope that sledgehammer-wielding attackers miss the mark. At least one auto writer -- a latter-day Clark Kent -- managed to crack the glass with a forceful heave at a demonstration arranged by BMW.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hightower said the changes added only 255 pounds of weight, raising the car's 0-to-60 acceleration time to 6.7 seconds, only a half-second slower than an unarmored 540i. And while the car may be intended for people who like to shift for themselves in the real world, they must accept an automatic: The 540i Protection is not available with a stick shift. It goes 21.4 miles on a gallon of premium, the same as an ordinary, thin-skinned 540i. Mr. Hightower said the price had not been set; the 540i Protection will cost more than the $51,670 sticker of an ordinary 540i with an automatic transmission.</p>
        <p>O'Gara-Hess offers modifications on 20 brands of cars. It charges $45,000 to convert a Lincoln Town Car, not including the car. It is, Mr. Heimbrock said, ''a logical, affordable, practical piece of personal security equipment'' -- one that is designed to be driven away from danger. That means the car has to keep running. So the battery is encased in bullet-resistant materal. (''It can take multiple ballistic impacts or even penetrations from bullets,'' he said.)</p>
        <p>The O'Gara-Hess Lincoln has armor on the roof and sides, but not the floor (that is an option). The idea is to provide what Mr. Heimbrock called ''protection against what the common criminal uses, which is typically easy-to-conceal handguns and submachine-gun types of threats.''</p>
        <p>''Not too often will you see a street thug with an M-16,'' he said. ''The rebels up in the mountains have those, but the guy who's going to rip off your watch, he's going to come up with a 9-millimeter handgun.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
