<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Is the Garbage State No More; Once Known for Its Pollution, It Is Now Known for Getting Tough on the Polluters</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="553175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PETERSON, IVER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC1330F93AA1575BC0A964958260" item-length="1477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Is the Garbage State No More; Once Known for Its Pollution, It Is Now Known for Getting Tough on the Polluters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IVER PETERSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PETERSON, IVER</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J. Aug. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In July, three demolition contractors were indicted here on charges of dumping building debris on city property. In Jersey City, two brothers were just released from jail after serving nearly a year for allowing oil leaks at their auto salvage yard. And in Newark, a 67-year-old chemical company president spent about two weeks in jail recently after being convicted of illegally storing and releasing hazardous waste.</p>
        <p>The three cases are among dozens that have been pursued by a new breed of pollution fighters in New Jersey, environmental cops who are carrying out one of the nation's toughest environmental laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In July, three demolition contractors were indicted here on charges of dumping building debris on city property. In Jersey City, two brothers were just released from jail after serving nearly a year for allowing oil leaks at their auto salvage yard. And in Newark, a 67-year-old chemical company president spent about two weeks in jail recently after being convicted of illegally storing and releasing hazardous waste.</p>
        <p>The three cases are among dozens that have been pursued by a new breed of pollution fighters in New Jersey, environmental cops who are carrying out one of the nation's toughest environmental laws.</p>
        <p>Using a network of environmental detectives and criminal prosecutors, New Jersey's program has resulted in jail sentences for 20 people since it was instituted in 1990 as a way of fighting the growing and ever more ingenious efforts of illegal dumpers to avoid the rising costs of disposal.</p>
        <p>Moreover, as the ingenuity of environmental offenders has increased, so has the determination of state agencies to see that the Garden State does not regain its grim reputation as the Garbage State of a decade ago, when waste dumps smoked and smoldered, waterways were glazed with gunk and Federal officials identified more toxic cleanup sites per square mile than in any other state.</p>
        <p>"In those days you had landfills that were burning, drums of chemicals were exploding; it was a mess," said Robert T. Winter, director of the Division of Criminal Justice in the State Department of Law and Public Safety. "Polluting was treated under the public nuisance law, a misdemeanor, and if inspectors tried to look over a landfill, they'd just be threatened until they went away. So we had to do something to get people's attention -- we had to go after them criminally."</p>
        <p>The approach caught Frank Imbriaco and his brother Stanley by surprise.</p>
        <p>"I didn't do nothing wrong," said Frank Imbriaco, who with his brother recently finished serving 260 days in the Hudson County Jail for allowing oil from a tanker truck they were dismantling at their Jersey City salvage yard to leak into the ground.</p>
        <p>"If I had done something intentionally it would have been wrong," said Mr. Imbriaco, who is 48 years old.  "If I had held up a bank, O.K., I held up a bank. But this is something that's been going on in New Jersey for 30 years, and now they want me to pay for everybody else's mistakes."</p>
        <p>Mr. Imbriaco was rueful. "My mistake was I hired a criminal lawyer," he said. "I should have hired an environmental lawyer."</p>
        <p>Since Gov. Jim Florio created the office of Environmental Prosecutor in 1990, the Imbriaco brothers and 18 other environmental offenders have been sentenced to a cumulative 27 years in prison. Some of the offenders were local officials who were bribed to look the other way.</p>
        <p>"New Jersey, along with California, is in the forefront of the country in the trend toward criminalizing environmental offenses," said Richard T. Nixon, executive vice president of the newly formed National Environmental Crimes Prosecution Center in Alexandria, Va., an information clearinghouse financed by the Justice Department and the National District Attorneys' Association. Trend Toward Toward Criminal Cases</p>
        <p>"The environmental regulation approach that has been used in the past has been unsuccessful in enforcing violations," Mr. Nixon said, "and now the trend that has continued to grow over the past several years is environmental criminal enforcement."</p>
        <p>Among those who were caught was James W. White, the 67-year-old president of the White Chemical Company of Newark, who was sentenced to a year in the Essex County Jail for illegally storing and discharging hazardous waste at his plant. Because of his age and health, he was released from jail after two weeks and is now finishing his sentence in a supervised program at his house.</p>
        <p>Federal officials are now cleaning up the scores of chemical-filled drums that litter the grounds of White Chemical Company's Frelinghuysen Avenue site. The drums contain toxic compounds that were byproducts from Mr. White's plant, which made plastic components and flame-retarding chemicals.</p>
        <p>Mr. White declined to be interviewed, but his lawyer, Joseph A. Hayden, said the "case really frames the dilemma we have as an industrial society."</p>
        <p>"White in no way was involved in off-site dumping, he was in no way involved in midnight dumping," Mr. Hayden said. "He was a businessman whose company had lost contracts, and he faced a decision between cutting his costs and laying his workers off, and he decided one way to cut was to delay disposing of the byproducts from some of his processes."</p>
        <p>State law requires that factories dispose of unwanted chemicals within 90 days. Instead, according to the state, Mr. White stored some 8,000 rusting drums of chemicals at the plant for more than a year.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Jack and Charles Colbert, two brothers who owned the Signo International Trading Company., in New York City, are serving three-year sentences in state prison for illegally storing hazardous wastes in a Newark warehouse, according to Mr. Winter's office. Not Just Environmental Laws</p>
        <p>In the dumping case here, Robert Hargrove, owner of Hargrove Brothers Inc., a demolition company, and Willie Walker and Willie Peterson were indicted in a conspiracy to bribe city officials to allow the company to dump debris on city property.</p>
        <p>Also indicted were seven officials in the Camden Public Works Department, including the street superintendent, on charges of accepting bribes to allow the illegal dumping. No trial date has been set; the defendants could be sentenced to 5 to 10 years, with more severe penalties for the senior public employees.</p>
        <p>Although other states, including New York, have special environmental-offense units within the offices of the attorney general, New Jersey has gone a step further than every other state -- save California -- by creating trained environmental-crimes squads in each of the state's 21 counties. These task forces, made up of local police officers, sheriffs and environmental protection officials, are often the first to spot an environmental crime, and they do much of the investigating.</p>
        <p>Environmental crimes are investigated much like other felonies. Informers are used in about half of the cases, officials said, and environmental forensics can play as big a role in tracking the source of a pollutant as undercover observations of factories, wrecking yards and haulers.</p>
        <p>In one case last year, Steven J. Madonna, the state environmental prosecutor, and the New Jersey State Police Marine Bureau traced a bag of garbage found floating in Delaware Bay to a Saudi Arabian ship, the Saudi Diriyah. Using the United States Coast Guard and an international convention against ship pollution, the shipping line was fined $20,000 and a warning placed in the ship captain's file. No Pain, No Effect</p>
        <p>Mr. Winter said that until environmental offenses were upgraded to felonies beginning in the mid-1980's, penalties for violations of dumping or landfill laws were so paltry that inspectors from the Bureau of Public Utilities, the office that regulated waste handling, were simply defied by hard-bitten garbage operators.</p>
        <p>In other cases, daily fines against the company and against company officers were so small that it was cheaper to pay the penalties than to properly dispose of the noisome cargo. Because the penalties involved were civil ones and because the violations tended to be regulatory or administrative -- a matter of licenses and permits -- companies often avoided having to correct a pollution problem for years.</p>
        <p>"Our position is that regulation itself doesn't work," said John Kaye, the Ocean County Prosecutor, echoing the sentiment that earlier attempts to enforce good environmental behavior have been unavailing.</p>
        <p>"Regulation has been going on for 30 years and people don't comply, because there are always ways around regulation," he said. "Regulators are not prosecutors, they're mediators. But if you want to get someone's attention, there's nothing like jail. It sure gets their attention."</p>
        <p>Not all environmental offenses are treated as crimes, officials said. New Jersey state and county prosecutors have considerable leeway in deciding when the offense is a civil infraction, such as the common case of a backyard mechanic who dumps motor oil in a storm sewer, and when it becomes a crime.</p>
        <p>The way to be treated as a criminal polluter in New Jersey, said Edward Borden, the Camden County Prosecutor, is to do it often, on a large scale and with intent to evade the law.</p>
        <p>"If you have intentional violation of environmental law, bribery, serious health issues, an ongoing crime, lots of dollars involved," Mr. Borden said, "then you're a criminal in New Jersey."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
