<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JUDGE HAYDEN'S FAMILY VALUES</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="797938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JUDGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FAMILY COURTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ESSEX COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYDEN, KATHARINE SWEENEY (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYDEN, KATHARINE SWEENEY (JUDGE)(BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFFMAN, JAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DF1039F936A25753C1A963958260" item-length="8333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JUDGE HAYDEN'S FAMILY VALUES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Jan Hoffman is the metropolitan legal affairs reporter for The New YorkTimes.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOFFMAN, JAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT HAS TAKEN ALMOST FOUR YEARS TO GET to this afternoon in a muggy Newark courtroom. That's how long the parents have been duking it out over their son, each trying to win the judge over, each saying, Your Honor, you decide because we can't. Just let me be the one to keep the child. Yet no matter how she calls the custody fight, Judge Katharine Sweeney Hayden knows that one parent will bless her and the other will curse her. She shrugs. It's not my job to make happy endings, she thinks. If a couple is so anger-locked that they have to ask  a stranger to make their most intimate decisions, well, too bad: I'm it, I'm what you've got.</p>
        <p>Then she relents a little. She reminds herself that people so desperate that  they must turn to an Essex County family court judge have no choice but to trust her. And that is why she often feels protective of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT HAS TAKEN ALMOST FOUR YEARS TO GET to this afternoon in a muggy Newark courtroom. That's how long the parents have been duking it out over their son, each trying to win the judge over, each saying, Your Honor, you decide because we can't. Just let me be the one to keep the child. Yet no matter how she calls the custody fight, Judge Katharine Sweeney Hayden knows that one parent will bless her and the other will curse her. She shrugs. It's not my job to make happy endings, she thinks. If a couple is so anger-locked that they have to ask  a stranger to make their most intimate decisions, well, too bad: I'm it, I'm what you've got.</p>
        <p>Then she relents a little. She reminds herself that people so desperate that  they must turn to an Essex County family court judge have no choice but to trust her. And that is why she often feels protective of them.</p>
        <p>But today she's unusually edgy: she still has no idea how she is going to rule. It's already June and the case has a firm deadline, two months away.</p>
        <p>During the years the parents have come before her, they have treated the boy  like a shuttlecock -- one month with the mother, first in Cleveland, more recently in Wilmington, Del.; the next month with the father in a New Jersey suburb. But now their son is 6. In September, he must start first grade in one state or another -- and stay there.</p>
        <p>The husband's lawyer is summing up. He makes a powerful claim for the father, Carl H., a 30-year-old airline supervisor. The court-appointed psychologist has favored the father -- important, thinks the judge, but not a deal maker. A tall, quiet man with two years of college, Carl offers the boy not only his own  love but also the love and caretaking of Carl's parents, with whom he lives, as  well as the boisterous affection of an extended family.</p>
        <p>Hayden, a slim, handsome woman of 53 with a passing resemblance to Sigourney  Weaver, listens fixedly, chin cradled in her right palm, unconsciously inching an elbow forward across her desk until the upper half of her body is all but horizontal.</p>
        <p>Carl's lawyer now turns on the mother, Amber H. It was she who had an affair  and moved out, leaving her husband and son behind in 1991. She changed addresses half a dozen times in four years, landing briefly in a violent relationship.</p>
        <p>The judge pauses from her note taking to flex a sore wrist. But why, she wonders, has Carl been driving with a revoked license for two years? And why is  a 30-year-old man living with his parents?</p>
        <p>Now Amber's lawyer gets to her feet. Sure, her 26-year-old client, an airline ticket agent, made some mistakes. But she's matured since she walked away from a marriage that left her emotionally and, she says, physically bruised. Amber has settled down. In Delaware she has a home, a school, a church ready for her boy.</p>
        <p>But how, the judge worries, can Amber justify taking the boy to another state, away from his father and grandparents? This bothers her. A lot.</p>
        <p>Finally the lawyer offers Amber's most provocative claim -- biology is indeed destiny. Amber was adopted. Her only known blood relation is her son. That argument, thinks the judge, has an emotional pull but not a legal one. But the next point will send her to the law library: paternity tests have proved that Carl is not the boy's biological father.</p>
        <p>The baby was born less than a year after they started dating. Carl says he always assumed the child was his. Amber says she told him the truth right away.  The judge has to decide who's lying.</p>
        <p>Hayden announces she will rule in a few weeks. Then she escapes to her chambers, where she tosses off her black robe and nervously runs her long fingers through her close-cropped hair.</p>
        <p>This case is driving her nuts.</p>
        <p>ON MOST WEEKDAYS, THE JUDGE GETS up at 5:30 A.M., pushes herself through three miles of race walking and makes a good-faith effort to pull into the court's parking lot by 8:26 A.M. She heads over to the Hall of Records, a gloomy, turn-of-the-century building in a downtown Newark neighborhood that empties out when darkness falls.</p>
        <p>Today begins promisingly: one of the main entrance's six elevators is actually working. As she strides down a dimly lighted hallway to her chambers, she sees people of all races waiting for her. Aunts and grandmothers dandling babies. A skinny man with oozing scratches from ear to collarbone. An elderly couple. A couple looking prosperous and deeply annoyed, separated by lawyers. They are residents of Essex County, which includes Newark, one of the country's  most ravaged cities, as well as the plush, Manhattan-commuter suburbs of South Orange, Livingston and Short Hills.</p>
        <p>Hayden is acutely aware that the people who come before her have no buffer to protect them from how she, a white, affluent, divorced and remarried mother of two, views their case. She is their sole juror -- there are no jury trials in family court. Many couples come before her without lawyers and cannot afford to challenge her rulings. A scant fistful of her cases have ever been appealed.  So although she doesn't share the glamorous status of those who preside over lurid criminal cases or big-ticket lawsuits, the impact she has on litigants can often be more profound and longer lasting.</p>
        <p>But her job, like that of her colleagues, is getting harder, at times seemingly impossible, as the definition of family keeps mutating. When Katharine Hayden was starting law school almost a quarter-century ago, in-vitro fertilization was still half a dozen years away, and the landmark New Jersey family court case about Baby M. and Mary Beth Whitehead, the child's surrogate mother, nearly 15. A father like Carl would almost never have challenged his wife over custody, regardless of blood ties. That gay and lesbian couples might  adopt children was virtually unimaginable.</p>
        <p>Bewildered and sometimes genuinely stumped by family dilemmas, she and her fellow judges have become society's gatekeepers, making decisions based on an uneasy mixture of inadequate laws and their own private values. The longer she sits on the bench, the more she realizes she's the interpreter of what society views as right and wrong.</p>
        <p>Unlike those in many states, where different types of domestic cases are dispersed throughout the system, New Jersey's family court is a self-contained mini-mall of household horrors. Eventually, almost every modern family problem lands in Hayden's court. Her caseload includes child abuse, spousal violence, divorce, custody disputes among unmarried couples, deadbeat dads and termination of parental rights. (Adoptions and juvenile-delinquency cases are assigned to other judges.) She hears about 75 cases a week.</p>
        <p>But in contrast to most of her colleagues around the country, who come to the despised, entry-level "kiddie court" with no background in family law, Hayden was a widely respected matrimonial lawyer.  Even though she is to be rotated to  the more high-profile criminal bench next year, when that stint is up she wants  to return to family court. In a 1993 New Jersey Law Journal survey, for which lawyers rated Essex County's 56 family, equity, criminal and civil Superior Court trial judges on efficiency, knowledge and fairness, she was first overall.</p>
        <p>While family court judges tend to cling tightly to confidentiality, Hayden spoke candidly about many of her cases to a reporter, whom she permitted to sit  in on her court proceedings and chambers conferences for a month. (For privacy reasons, the parents have been identified in this article by first names or initials; the children's names have been omitted.) So it became possible to see how a family court judge, by questioning, scolding and listening to people for whom love has long since turned rancid and dull-eyed, performs a role that is far more complex than administrator of the law. From Hayden's wooden perch in her dingy four-row courtroom, she is mother, psychologist, preacher.</p>
        <p>And to the families whose intimate lives she will reshape for years to come,  she can seem like the hand of God. Or, occasionally, the Devil's.</p>
        <p>THIS AFTERNOON, THE JUDGE TAKES HER FIRST measure of a difficult domestic violence case. The husband presents his story and the judge hears his rough voice breaking; she particularly notices that as he leans toward his daughter and wife, they stiffen. Contact lenses corrected her poor eyesight years ago, but she noses around new cases like a mole, sensing shapes and body language.</p>
        <p>Mr. and Mrs. B. have each filed a domestic violence complaint against the other. Each wants to evict the other from their home. Neither spouse has a lawyer. But Mr. B. has brought a witness -- their shy, gangling 12-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>Smiling graciously, the judge immediately tells a court officer to escort the daughter outside. A child shouldn't have to hear her parents' ragged, recriminating tales of a 15-year marriage collapsing in infidelity and shattered pride.</p>
        <p>At first, the father seems the more sympathetic figure of the two. Mr. B., a  49-year-old truck driver, says in a tear-soaked voice: "I love my wife. I've tried to do everything to keep our family together."</p>
        <p>His story is ancient: he caught his wife with another man. At 2 A.M. their escalating fight culminated with Mrs. B.'s pulling a knife on her husband and locking him out of the house, barefoot. The daughter let him in and later confirmed his story to the police.</p>
        <p>The judge squints at him. Something doesn't ring true here. Why didn't he kick her out or pack his things? He's a big guy -- he can't possibly be physically afraid of her. So what does he want? To get me to evict her so he can get the house?</p>
        <p>Mrs. B., a medical secretary, doesn't exactly deny what happened. But in a voice at once defiant and defensive, she explains that her husband, a recovering alcoholic, is insecure because the two have not had "an intimate relationship" in some time.</p>
        <p>She locks eyes with the judge, scrupulously avoiding her husband. "He said he wanted to purchase a gun and blow my head off. He got my mink coat, along with my cellular phone."</p>
        <p>The judge throws her arms in the air. Who's to blame? She will have to call the young witness. But first she cautions the parents: "The one who loses will think it's because your daughter pointed the finger one way or the other. I'm telling you on the record I've made up my mind, but I want to explain it to her  first. You have to have faith in this judge that I'm not lying to you."</p>
        <p>Warily, the daughter enters the courtroom, craning her neck to watch her parents leave, abandoning her to this stranger in a black robe. After they have  gone, the judge speaks gently to the girl. "I want to ask your mom to leave the  house because your dad's case fits the law better than hers. But how do you feel about living with him at home?"</p>
        <p>The girl stares at her, dumbfounded. Then, to the judge's dismay, the child bursts into tears.</p>
        <p>"I want to go with my mother," she says.</p>
        <p>The judge pauses. Stay calm, she tells herself. "I could say I want you with  your mother and I want you in the house. Do you mind if I tell your dad?"</p>
        <p>The girl shakes her head. "He'll be real mad at me," she sobs. "When I was little, he used to beat me. My older sister told me that when they fought, to go to my room and turn the music up loud."</p>
        <p>The judge's face is a mask of sympathetic anguish. "That must be a terrible thing for you."</p>
        <p>The girl is warming up. "My sister said he used to hit my mother."</p>
        <p>The judge scribbles notes and carefully asks, "When did he start up his drinking again?"</p>
        <p>"Oct. 1, 1994," the child promptly replies.</p>
        <p>"How do you know that date so well?"</p>
        <p>"Because it was my birthday," says the girl. "He said he was happy I was turning 12, but I don't believe it, because he started drinking that day."</p>
        <p>The judge massages her aching temples. So the family is in a far more precarious state than she had realized. Why did the father resume drinking? Given that his wife isn't sleeping with him, was he unnerved by his daughter's budding puberty?</p>
        <p>The judge sighs and tells the girl that she will let her remain with her mother. "But I'm in a pickle," she adds. "I told your parents I wouldn't let you change my mind, but now you've gone and done it."</p>
        <p>Then the judge telephones a lawyer who has a gift with child clients and asks her to represent the daughter. According to the law, Mrs. B. should have to leave because she threatened her husband with a dangerous weapon. But now that the daughter has raised new issues, the judge must consider which outcome will be in the child's best interest.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the girl waits in the judge's chambers, looking almost chipper. Then she goes into the courtroom to whisper in the judge's ear: can Hayden now help the mother, who fears the father may damage their car, down in the court parking lot?</p>
        <p>Damn it, the judge thinks irritably, I extended myself, and now she's taking  advantage of me. I'm not going to micromanage their squabbles. Politely but firmly, she dusts the girl off.</p>
        <p>The hearing resumes. The girl keeps her eyes on the table as her lawyer speaks. "She loves her dad and doesn't want to hurt him," says the lawyer, "but  she would be happier if her dad moved and she could see him as much as possible."</p>
        <p>The judge issues no-contact orders against both parents: "You are pushing each other's buttons. But if I say Mrs. B. leaves, then your daughter has to leave the house, too. So I'm asking Mr. B. to leave for two weeks."</p>
        <p>The family walks tiredly, even peacefully out of court, wife smiling at husband, father wrapping his arm around his daughter. Hayden steps down from the bench. Good job, Katharine, she thinks.</p>
        <p>Fifteen minutes later, Mrs. B. and her daughter race back into court, banging on the door of the judge's chambers. They say that in the elevator, Mr. B. swore he would mess up the house and his wife as well. Then he ran off. Mrs. B. speaks in gasps; her daughter looks crushed. When they got to the parking lot, Mrs. B. saw that her right front tire had been slashed and her antenna snapped. He had apparently attacked the car before he returned to court.</p>
        <p>The judge's face goes taut with rage. She orders a sheriff's officer to accompany Mrs. B. and her daughter to a service station. Then, tremulously wishing the two of them the best of luck, the judge has another officer tell the local precinct to send a squad car to meet Mrs. B. at the house.</p>
        <p>That night, Hayden sleeps fitfully. One of a family judge's worst nightmares  is to make a wrong call on a domestic violence case. At 4 A.M. she wakes herself, scolding: letting the daughter live with her father would have been a stupid, dead-wrong decision.</p>
        <p>She shouldn't have dismissed the girl when she asked for help. And she had absolutely misread the couple's smiles. She had thought that the wife was smiling in triumph for having got the house and that the husband was smiling because he had just heard his daughter say she loved him.</p>
        <p>But she now sees that Mrs. B. had the nervous smile of a very frightened woman and that Mr. B. had been smiling because he knew what was waiting for his  wife in the parking lot. All the while, the judge had had the arrogance to think that she had fixed everything.</p>
        <p>She can't go back to sleep. She has a strict rule about post-mortem lashing.  One good stinging self-beratement session, but that's it. As dawn breaks, she forces herself out of bed and into her running clothes. She cannot afford to let Mr. and Mrs. B. haunt her. Time to cauterize the case, and move on.</p>
        <p>FRIDAY IS DIVORCE DAY. YOU CAN SNIFF THE tension and the money in the air. Not coincidentally, Friday is also the Day of the Lawyers.</p>
        <p>Today Hayden wears her favorite earrings, dangling portraits of moon-eyed cows. Too bad if people think they're completely silly. To keep herself happy, a judge has to do what a judge has to do.</p>
        <p>She takes the bench, sparring deftly with pin stripe after pin stripe as they bring divorce motions before her, flexing her judicial muscle, earrings swaying. She's almost having too much fun. Bearing down on a battalion of lawyers, her face alight with the slyest of grins, she says: "I don't know how you'll be ready for trial in two weeks either. You'll have to cram and it will be horrible."</p>
        <p>Who's next? One couple, unencumbered by counsel, raise their hands. Like most family court judges, she hates to be the one to divide up the spoils. "You've settled?" she sings out. "Be still, my heart!"</p>
        <p>But while 90 percent of divorce cases do settle, often the judge has to bang  heads in her chambers to get there. When tempers get too short, she'll wind up the yellow Power Ranger she keeps on her desk and let it stalk noisily across the floor before the embarrassed lawyers.</p>
        <p>One day she keeps stepping off the bench for updates from Howard Danzig and Cary Cheifetz, who represent a suburban couple in their mid-40's. The wife is a  Wall Street lawyer who earns $165,000 a year; the husband quit his job with the  Internal Revenue Service 15 years ago and has since stayed home to raise their five children.</p>
        <p>"We don't know what's happening, judge," says Danzig, looking hapless. "They  sent us away and they're sitting in the cafeteria with their laptops."</p>
        <p>BY DAY'S END, HAYDEN SETS THE TRIAL FOR THE following week. When they return  on that date, Danzig, who represents the husband, announces that negotiations have broken down over alimony his client wants the wife to pay.</p>
        <p>The judge is both indignant and trying not to laugh. The couple's youngest child is already in high school; the eldest is already out of the house. "Really, Howard! Your client has to go to work. He can't stay at home anymore!"</p>
        <p>Danzig looks nearly apoplectic. "Reverse the sexes, Judge! Imagine he earns $165,000 and she stays home with the kids."</p>
        <p>"But he's more employable than his analogue," says Hayden. "And I don't want  to barter her future for his alimony."</p>
        <p>Cheifetz points out that the wife has already offered to pay not only all child support but also all five college tuitions.</p>
        <p>Hayden looks quizzical. "I smell a rat," she says. "Is the wife taking on extra responsibility for the children so she won't have to give him money?"</p>
        <p>This piece of information is enough to turn her head around about the case. Ushering the two lawyers to the door, she says: "You're right, Howard. Tell them the judge agrees it's definitely an alimony case. I finally saw what a sexist pig I am."</p>
        <p>The next week, the couple settle.</p>
        <p>When the judge does have to hand out marital booty, she holds her nose. "Financial decisions are intrusive and awkward forays into how people spend their money," she sputters one Friday morning. She stares at a list of items. "I hate TV's!" she shouts. "Why can't people divide up their own toys?"</p>
        <p>The judge's first marriage, to a professor of medieval literature, fell apart after nearly 20 years. The dissolution was slow, sad but civilized. Even so, she will never forget the one blowup in their Maplewood kitchen, when he shouted, "I'll get a lawyer!" She was by then a major league divorce lawyer, and yet she  still felt as if an earthquake had shaken their home. Lawyers? Judges? Combing through her life?</p>
        <p>All the trust between her and her husband, the father of her two sons, would  have been ripped away by the legal system. Luckily, the two of them worked out an amicable settlement. But the memory of those 10 seconds of panic in a suburban kitchen stays with her still, and she recalls it every time she has to  reach into a divorcing couple's private cupboard.</p>
        <p>The next hearing is to give a couple in divorce litigation a temporary budget until a final ruling. In addition to the divorce case, the husband and wife have filed domestic violence charges against each other. Both matters are before Hayden. Suzanne Spina, 30, is a Verona homemaker with two little children; Robert Spina, 40, is Police Chief of West Orange, appointed last year by his father, the Mayor. In a few weeks, Hayden's finding that Robert Spina abused his wife will be local front-page news. But right now there are bills to be paid. And Suzanne wants Robert to keep right on paying them.</p>
        <p>Like Suzanne's car phone.</p>
        <p>"Go on the low monthly end -- $50," Hayden says. "You can rob from the food bill if you talk too much. How about $55 for your home phone?"</p>
        <p>Ellen Marshall, Suzanne's lawyer, leaps up. "Ma'am," she cries out, "this is  a devastated lady! She needs the support of her family," who reside in long-distance area codes and whom Suzanne needs to telephone regularly. A piddling $105 a month?</p>
        <p>The judge fixes the lawyer with a deadpan stare. "So put it on her family's dime," she says.</p>
        <p>Propping her reading glasses on her nose, the judge marches down the list of  operations at the Spina manse, revising expenses for lawn care, utilities, repairs on the Mercedes, the burglar alarm, karate and tennis lessons for the 4-year-old, cleaning woman, birthday parties. She informs the Spinas that she doesn't do TV's and VCR's. The couple snipe at each other but eventually strike  an accord. Then the judge makes a ruling on the treadmill. She gives it to Robert.</p>
        <p>She knows that every divorcing party, consciously or not, draws a line that cannot be crossed. Robert has testified extensively about his exercise routine,  and she has a hunch that losing the treadmill would have been the deal killer for him.</p>
        <p>Besides, she thinks, the Spinas' health club is a good spot for Suzanne to meet people. Many hard bodies, many fancy treadmills -- she laughs, shaking her  head -- and a regular Peyton Place.</p>
        <p>HAYDEN HEARS HUNDREDS OF CASES through June and July. But each dawn as she sets out to race walk through her riverfront town, the battle over Amber and Carl's boy hovers in her head. One morning, Amber wins. Carl, the next. While blocks of brownstones go by, details from the case pluck at her. Why hasn't Carl made getting back his driver's license a priority? What about Amber's overbearing mother back in Washington State? She had heedlessly told her grandson that his daddy wasn't his real father. Amber merely said in court that  she couldn't control her. Worrisome?</p>
        <p>The truth is, Hayden realizes, that even though state family law seems specific, in close cases she can stack the facts and find legal backing for her  decision no matter which way she goes.</p>
        <p>A week later, during lunch hour in chambers, she is thinking aloud between bites on a chicken sandwich from the corner truck. Amber's insistence on the paternity test is irking her. By saying to her son, "You're mine but not his," Amber is seeking to remove him from his grandparents and his father, as well as  an uncle, aunts and cousins -- all the family he grew up with. The judge can't buy that.</p>
        <p>Yet today, she is starting to think that Carl should lose. The psychologist said Carl played beautifully with his son, but what does that mean? How much time does Carl spend with him, anyway, compared with the grandparents? By contrast, it is Amber who deals with doctors, sets up play dates, gets calls from school and, in the judge's view, edges out Carl because she does it on her own.</p>
        <p>Still, is Amber getting her life together? No. During part of the litigation, Amber made some foolhardy choices that worry the judge: for one, she moved in briefly with a Cleveland boyfriend who beat her.</p>
        <p>Hayden nibbles some potato chips. She remains unsure about the violence in Amber and Carl's marriage, a factor she must consider in a custody dispute. The  testimony from witnesses was inconclusive. She thinks Carl is soft-pedaling the  violence and Amber is overdescribing. If Amber was so afraid of her husband, why did she leave their son with him for six months when she walked out?</p>
        <p>All month long, the bulging Amber-and-Carl file sits, unexamined and accusing, on the judge's dining-room table at home, amid half a dozen glowering  unpaid bills. The more she worries about a case, the longer she avoids it. She knows herself: she's Queen of the Last Minute and so must give herself a deadline.</p>
        <p>Even so, the judge dithers away another week, obsessing now about geography.  If only Amber had relocated within New Jersey, this case would be a no-brainer.  Amber would win residential custody and Carl would get liberal visitation; the boy would not lose access to his extended family.</p>
        <p>She asks her law clerk to search case law to see if she can give Amber custody on the condition that she move back to New Jersey. Or construct a ruling that says Carl gets custody unless Amber returns.</p>
        <p>But she's clutching at legal straws. A wasted week. And so another morning, another fast wobble-walk through the streets of her humid, somnolent town. It is now the third week of July. The first day of school is fast approaching and she  has to make a decision.</p>
        <p>AT THE END OF THE DAY -- sometimes 6 P.M., occasionally 7 -- the judge droops out of the courthouse. The roughest days are those when she ignores her own rule: don't go out on a limb for people. Because every time you say, Follow  me into the wilderness for I am the judge. . . . Yeah, right.</p>
        <p>Sometimes a day closes just when she's in the exasperating middle of trying to solve someone's insoluble problem. Or just after somebody has yelled back and embarrassed her on the bench. Her face gets hot, her neck splotchy, her breathing choppy. She hates that. She hates for people in the courtroom to think she's vulnerable. She wants them to see Olympian perfection in a black robe.</p>
        <p>She couldn't have done this job when her kids were small because once she got home, they made demands on her. In court, she lavishes all her maternal instincts on people. She is Judge Big Sister Katharine, eldest of three, who learned to take charge after her adored Wall Street lawyer father died when she  was 17. But by the end of the court day, she has nothing left to give.</p>
        <p>Her friends ask how she can stand it that her husband, Joe Hayden, a criminal lawyer, doesn't get home sometimes until 10:30 at night, but she thinks, thank God, that's the beauty of her marriage: no demands, the solitude at dusk, the freedom just to be quiet and rebuild herself. She returns to her lemon-yellow 19th-century brick behemoth with the twisting staircases and stained-glass windows, feeds the cats, settles back into her armchair and stares at the wall.</p>
        <p>Once in a while her thoughts may stray over the cases she has heard in the last few days -- in one July week, she terminated the parental rights of a formerly drug-addicted mother and sent a commodities broker to jail until he paid $15,000 in overdue support for his young son and wife. But mostly she tries to make her mind blank. Then she may read. Hardly the stuff of someone with a graduate degree in English literature: detective fiction and serial-murder mysteries.</p>
        <p>In her first months on the bench, she'd sometimes nod off at the dinner table to stave off attacks of panic. She'd rip her cuticles, curl up in bed in a fetal position, then lie awake for hours, obsessing. This is fun? she would think.</p>
        <p>Gradually the terror slid back into the corner and she took command of her court, her self. And she knows she couldn't do her job if this marriage weren't  solid. When you're trying to salvage people from their emotional messes, you have to be in decent shape yourself. The Haydens are well known in a circle of New Jersey lawyers and Federal and state judges.  A typical vacation for the couple begins in the car ride to a judicial conference, six hours together, the  simple pleasures of talk.</p>
        <p>To recharge herself, she goes to Mass every Sunday. She's a modern Catholic -- she divorced and signs off on hundreds of divorces a year -- but she's not entirely certain that God won't strike her dead if she misses a week at Mass. Sure, half the time she's sitting in church she's thinking up recipes. But she says that if she puts herself in the presence of God, when she needs to call upon Him, either shaking her fist or negotiating hard, she will already have paid her respects.</p>
        <p>And it's usually on Sundays that she enters races. Her not-so-well-kept secret is that she is a lousy race walker. For a woman whose puckish sense of humor includes herself as fair game, she is unexpectedly earnest on the topic of her little races, as she calls them. She keeps at them to maintain her mental equilibrium. She is moved and bothered by the power she has over people as a judge. But every time she goes out for a race, she feels terror, the potential for humiliation, which may be something close to how the people who come before  her feel.</p>
        <p>Although the days wring her out, there has not been a morning yet when she hasn't looked forward to sitting in family court, which is still so much better  than being a divorce lawyer. It was wrenching when your clients were so unhappy  and all you could do was try to pave the way for less anarchy in their lives.</p>
        <p>But as a judge, she can make things happen, in a glacial-pace sort of way. That's the thought that keeps her going, the optimism of being a Catholic: a judge can hold out legal absolution, the promise of a redeemed life.</p>
        <p>COMING OFF THE BENCH after a hearing one day, Hayden wants a reality check. "Miss Bert, what did you think of that methadone mother?" she asks Alberta Gregory, her court clerk.</p>
        <p>Gregory, who has lived many of her 61 years in Newark, arches her brows. "Boss, she lies like a rug!"</p>
        <p>Hayden looks taken aback but braces herself to hear more; she's quite aware that she's a white woman who was raised on Manhattan's Upper East Side and educated through college by nuns. She depends on Gregory, who is black, to clue  her in about life in Newark's poor neighborhoods. "Judge," says Gregory with a sigh, "let me tell you how methadone goes down in this town."</p>
        <p>Hayden's rulings are her own, but in addition to voraciously consulting legal, psychological and social tracts, she turns to a select few people to be her sounding board.</p>
        <p>So today, she puts up her long legs and considers questions of great moment with Gregory and Patti Cassidy, her secretary: even though that couple have filed for divorce, are they still sleeping together? Is that why they are taking their sweet time to push the case? "Forbidden sex can be pretty hot," muses the  judge.</p>
        <p>She often speculates about the sexual dynamics of the couples who come before her. On another day, a suburban wife testified that as part of her husband's continuing emotional abuse, he made love to her one spring morning, then got out of bed and, without a word, packed and walked out. The judge, Cassidy and Gregory shriek, collectively appalled. "That's psychological rape!" says the judge.</p>
        <p>"But you know the final insult? When he was asked on the stand about whether  he had sex with her that morning, he said, 'I don't recall.' "</p>
        <p>And Hayden regularly consults with the other "Cardinals," as the four judges  in Essex County family court who hear divorce cases have been anointed by their  sardonic boss, Judge Philip M. Freedman. ("More like the four Mouseketeers," mutters Gregory.) The Cardinals -- Thomas P. Zampino, Richard C. Camp, Herbert S. Glickman and Hayden -- sometimes handle multimillion-dollar divorces. Central to why so many matrimonial lawyers kiss their rings is that the Cardinals can order legal fees paid by the wealthier spouse.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals often confer in Hayden's whimsical, who's-in-charge-here? chambers. Cat and cow memorabilia clutter the shelves, as do plastic monsters from the movie "Alien." A poster of her son's fledgling rock band hangs under her law diploma. As the Power Ranger looks on, the Cardinals frequently trade tales about litigants and lawyers. Their gallows humor may be indiscreet, but they say that because they preside daily over fraying lives, they need to blow off steam.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the judges talk about how their own marriages affect their decision making. Hayden has her ear cocked for problems that face mothers struggling to re-enter the work force. Her own boys were toddlers and she was 30 when she entered Seton Hall University Law School. She would go on to become a Federal prosecutor, a formidable matrimonial lawyer and a county bar association president, dramatically outearning her first husband, the professor. To this day she credits his flexible schedule and willingness to share child care as critical to her success.</p>
        <p>And she'll be sitting on the bench, trying to decide whether custody of a prison mother's newborn should be given to an aunt or to the state, when her own family comes knocking. One morning it's her 82-year-old mother, who is living with her this summer, phoning in a report on how the cats are handling the heat. Then her would-be-rock-star son calls. Then from Los Angeles, a call from the other musician son. Later it's her husband: dinner and a movie tonight? Now Patti Cassidy runs in with another scrawled message: does the judge remember where her mother put the house keys this morning?</p>
        <p>ON THURSDAYS, THE JUDGE wakes at 4 A.M., pads out to the big armchair in the  living room and settles in with the two cats to read two dozen files of child abuse and neglect cases -- the basic work of virtually every American family court. She pores over them like paperback mysteries, sometimes anxiously skipping to the end to find out what happened. Almost all the parties are Hispanic or black, yet what distinguishes them in her mind from other litigants  is not their color but their poverty. Their life experiences couldn't be more different than hers; even so, she must decide which children must be saved from  their parents, which struggling families should be saved from the intrusion of the state.</p>
        <p>One morning in early July she opens a thick folder and smiles wearily. A mother known in court papers as M. W. is back: my all-star, thinks the judge, obdurate and durable, my Darryl Strawberry of the lot.</p>
        <p>M. W., in her mid-20's, has been before Hayden many times over the past 18 months. She has a bad cocaine habit, four children under 6 in foster care and a  13-year-old son who until now has been staying with an uncle. She recently moved to a Southern state to live with a new boyfriend.</p>
        <p>The latest issue involves the teen-ager. His uncle refuses to board him any longer. The Division for Youth and Family Services in New Jersey knows that placing the boy in a foster home is futile, because he will run away to find his mother. But M. W. refuses to undergo regular drug screens and enter treatment. The agency does not want to return the boy to her. But it feels it has no choice.</p>
        <p>At the hearing later that morning, the judge's patience is sorely tried. (These proceedings are closed to observers. Hayden allowed a reporter to hear a  tape of the case.) M. W. assumes that if she gets clean, all her children will be returned by September, a fantasy the judge struggles to dispel. Finally, the  judge tells M. W. the unsweetened truth about the state's promises: "Let me make this clear. You will never, never, never get your kids back unless you kick your drug habit. If you kick your drug habit, you may still not get your kids back."</p>
        <p>Hayden tells M. W. that she also has to set up a stable home for the children. "Does your fiance know about the drug problem? Probably not, because I think one of the reasons you're not going to a program is because you're scared  he'll find out."</p>
        <p>The judge tells the agency's lawyers that she is inclined to deny the return  of the son to his mother. Panicky, M. W. vows to enter a program, immediately go for drug screens, tell her boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Hayden is dubious; she tries speaking mother to mother. She is about to make  a risky decision, so she explains carefully for the record: "Anyone looking at this case will think I'm insane to send your boy to you. The division is telling me to do it anyway. But your son believes in you and he will walk all the way down South to be with you. If my firstborn felt that close to me, that would be  an awfully good reason to try to clean up."</p>
        <p>Then the judge talks to M. W.'s son. "I'm very concerned that your mom will have a problem licking her drug problem," she says. "In order to keep you with her, she's got to go into a program. I don't think it's right for me to lay on a kid the responsibility for his mother, but in a way, you've done it many times before." She tells him that his main job is to stay in school, that his mother has to come back to court with his attendance records.</p>
        <p>"I think you and your mom are a good team," says the judge. "But I also want  you to have a good life and be a kid and play sports and have fun."</p>
        <p>But later that day, M. W. flunks her drug test: she is caught trying to dilute her urine sample by pouring toilet water into the cup. In the next two weeks, she doesn't head back to the South and doesn't begin treatment. The son briefly disappears.</p>
        <p>At another Thursday hearing, the judge tells the boy that because M. W. has failed him, she is sending him to foster care; she tries to rile him so he will  distance himself from his beautiful junkie mother. Hayden wants the boy to know  that if he feels his mother is using him, she agrees. She says: if you run away, you run. It's up to you.</p>
        <p>The system is powerless now, she thinks. What more can a judge do?</p>
        <p>ONE THURSDAY, SHE GIVES herself a final deadline for Amber and Carl's case: next Wednesday, the last in July, 9 A.M., she tells the lawyers.</p>
        <p>That Saturday, she opens the file on her dining-room table and puts in order  nearly four years of narrative -- events, motions, cross-motions, trial testimony, expert reports. On the Sunday afternoon before the decision is due, she dives into the file.</p>
        <p>Who lied? Did Amber tell Carl during her pregnancy that the baby wasn't his,  as she maintained, or didn't she? Did Carl beat her regularly or didn't he?</p>
        <p>Late Sunday night the judge begins dictating notes for her secretary, Patti Cassidy. She's in court all day Monday; that night she continues scribbling thoughts. As a pattern emerges from the file, so does the decision. Tuesday she's back on the bench, and that night she works until 1 A.M., crashes and starts up again at 4 A.M. She sprawls on the living-room carpet, piles of legal  pads around her.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday morning she drives to work like an automaton, radio off. She silently chants, I just have to do this. She isn't dreading making the announcement, exactly; she's steeling herself.</p>
        <p>When she takes the bench, she deliberately avoids eye contact with Amber and  Carl, instead fixing her squint on the comfortable blur of the parking lot out the window. Then, walking them through her logic, she speaks for two and a half  hours.</p>
        <p>First she addresses Amber's claim that biology should trump in a custody dispute. She cites a 1984 New Jersey Supreme Court case, Miller v. Miller, which says that once you put something out there, you can't take it back if the  repudiation helps you and hurts others. And that is Amber's problem. She had presented Carl as her boy's father for nearly six years and is now withdrawing the claim: it favors her and harms Carl and the boy.</p>
        <p>Amber's lawyer glares at the judge. Amber flinches.</p>
        <p>The judge plows on, now turning to the paternity question. State law permits  a paternity test to establish a child's inheritance rights. But Amber, says the  judge, has refused to contact the boy's biological father and so did not use the test for that purpose. Instead, she has stripped her son of one father, Carl; by not bringing in the unnamed one, she is eviscerating the boy's inheritance and rendering him fatherless.</p>
        <p>And the judge concludes that because Carl helped raise the boy and held him out as his own, he stands in the shoes of a father. "How can Carl not be taken seriously as an equal parent?" she says.</p>
        <p>So far, Carl has been sitting motionless, as if afraid to breathe. His father, whom the judge praises as a wise and loving grandparent, is in the row behind him, listening just as hard, taking notes, occasionally wiping a tear from under his bifocals.</p>
        <p>The judge reviews the experts' evaluations. A psychologist said Carl offered  a more secure environment and that Amber tended to confuse her own needs with her son's. But both parents have strengths and weaknesses.</p>
        <p>Finally she examines the question that propelled her hunt through the file: credibility. Amber, she concludes, has lied.</p>
        <p>At one point Amber had testified that when she learned she was pregnant, she  told Carl he wasn't the father. Another time she testified that she broke the news to him three months later after a sonogram showed a fetus too large to have been conceived when the couple starting having sex. Her early court papers, filed before she asked for the paternity tests, are evasive: instead of referring to the boy as "our child," she calls him "the child."</p>
        <p>The judge concludes that Carl most likely did not know early on that he was not the father. "Why would he acquiesce only five months into their relationship to take on the public role of Dad?" Hayden says. "Probably because she kept it a secret."</p>
        <p>Carl's shoulders lower a good inch; Amber is starting to weep.</p>
        <p>From there the judge extrapolates about domestic violence, weighing the weak, contradictory testimony. She decides that Amber will say nearly anything to regain her child, her biological connection to the world, whom she believes to be her property right. Therefore, says the judge, "I do not believe that she was regularly abused by Carl."</p>
        <p>Amber's lawyer looks fit to spit.</p>
        <p>Finally, Hayden lists the 15 factors the state says she must consider to determine what is in the best interest of the child. Domestic violence, safety of the child, quality of education, fitness of the parent and so forth. The case is a close call, she says, but she has to decide whether it is better for the boy to stay with Carl and the grandparents in the home and the town with the friends, church and schools he has known from birth or to move in withhis biological mother, who loves him dearly but whose life is still shaky.</p>
        <p>Amber, she says, is a young woman still finding her way. She made choices that were in her best interest but not her son's. Carl, by contrast, put his son first, making the decision to move back in with his parents, who could help raise the child.</p>
        <p>And although she says she believes Amber loves her son and so should spend substantial time with him, Hayden awards Carl residential custody. Then she stands and walks out.</p>
        <p>Carl and his father rush from the courtroom, looking stunned. Amber's lawyer  starts cursing furiously. Amber slumps, sobbing, saying over and over: "What trial was she at? What trial was she at?"</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Hayden is back in her chambers. She has taken off her black robe and is seated behind her desk, staring at her hands. It was her decision to place the boy, who is his mother's only known blood relative, with a man to whom the child has no biological connection. The judge looks completely drained.</p>
        <p>Will Amber figure out that if she moves back to New Jersey, the custody issue could be reopened, perhaps with a different outcome? she wonders. The judge has  a queasy feeling that Amber's loss is greater to her than Carl's win is to him.  Amber, after all, is a reasonably good mother, she muses. Did she make a wrong ruling?</p>
        <p>A poisonously seductive question, for that way lies judicial paralysis. No, the judge tells herself, she decided correctly; her responsibility was not to a  sorrowful, desperate mother but to the son.</p>
        <p>Patti Cassidy sticks her head in. Would the judge like her usual chicken sandwich? Ah, yes, the best way to put the case behind her: protein on rye, mayo on both slices.</p>
        <p>But as Amber and Carl start to recede from her mind, she realizes that her impact on them is only beginning. In the years to come, they will have to struggle with the fallout from her decision, the very thing that they had wanted so badly from her. Hayden sighs. Doubt flickering across her face, the judge picks up the stack of papers her secretary has just dropped on her desk. On top  is her calendar of cases. Looks like another busy afternoon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
