<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Riverboat Gambler Was Also a Giver of Gifts</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="797951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY OPERA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLLAND, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEENE, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DF1039F936A25753C1A963958260" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Riverboat Gambler Was Also a Giver of Gifts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Holland</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLLAND, BERNARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher Keene took a lot of the New York City Opera with him when he died last Sunday. Anyone who wanted to know what was right about this company, and why a lot of what it did didn't work, had only to follow him around for a while. Mr. Keene had a way of staking his opera house on ventures that never had much chance of succeeding in the first place, but ones that had to be tried just the  same. The cards dealt him when he took over the job of general director in 1989  were for the most part losing ones, but how cheerfully and gracefully he bluffed and sometimes won.</p>
        <p>His epitaph is already written on the current performance calendar, in the titles of works like "Mathis der Maler" and "Kinkakuji," which opens on Thursday evening. The first is known for Hindemith's music, but how many avid operagoers  had ever seen the opera itself? The second is 20 years old, and not many people  know much about it at all. Indeed, the most famous thing about "Kinkakuji" is not its Japanese composer (Toshiro Mayuzumi) or its German librettist (Claus Henneberg) but their literary source, the great writer Yukio Mishima. The public did not clamor for these pieces, and I doubt that City Opera board members pounded their fists in enthusiastic insistence that they be done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christopher Keene took a lot of the New York City Opera with him when he died last Sunday. Anyone who wanted to know what was right about this company, and why a lot of what it did didn't work, had only to follow him around for a while. Mr. Keene had a way of staking his opera house on ventures that never had much chance of succeeding in the first place, but ones that had to be tried just the  same. The cards dealt him when he took over the job of general director in 1989  were for the most part losing ones, but how cheerfully and gracefully he bluffed and sometimes won.</p>
        <p>His epitaph is already written on the current performance calendar, in the titles of works like "Mathis der Maler" and "Kinkakuji," which opens on Thursday evening. The first is known for Hindemith's music, but how many avid operagoers  had ever seen the opera itself? The second is 20 years old, and not many people  know much about it at all. Indeed, the most famous thing about "Kinkakuji" is not its Japanese composer (Toshiro Mayuzumi) or its German librettist (Claus Henneberg) but their literary source, the great writer Yukio Mishima. The public did not clamor for these pieces, and I doubt that City Opera board members pounded their fists in enthusiastic insistence that they be done.</p>
        <p>As to "Kinkakuji," we shall have to see, but no right-minded music lover will complain about the substance of Hindemith's opera or its right to be acknowledged. And despite the less than brilliant production Mr. Keene's forces  were able to muster, no one can deny that New York received a gift others in this city were unwilling or unable to give it. The stage was too small, the production somewhat cheesy. The chorus did not sing well, nor was the orchestra terribly brilliant. Plagued by illness, the cast sang valiantly. It took a lot of faith to get through this "Mathis der Maler," but a lot of us are  glad we had enough.</p>
        <p>Frail and shorn yet filled with high humor, Mr. Keene conducted the opening night of "Mathis." Not very well, I'm afraid. One of the cards dealt him was a pit orchestra of intractable mediocrity; and despite all his energy and musical  intelligence, he never quite had the conductorial skill to make it play much better than it always had. One accepted Mr. Keene's conducting for much the same reason audiences struggle through John Crosby's Strauss performances at the Santa Fe Opera and Placido Domingo's on-the-job training exercises in the pit at the Metropolitan Opera. All three men have given largely of themselves to the institutions in question. Let them conduct, we have thought to ourselves, and bless them.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Keene inherited at the City Opera was a company set down in the wrong place and pulled in different directions by conflicting mandates. The New  York State Theater has neither the shape nor the facilities for opera, and it is disastrously situated only a few feet from the Met, which dwarfs it in every conceivable way. The fair-minded can fight back the comparisons, but geography makes it difficult to avoid them. How happy this company would be in more modest surroundings, a mile or so away, in a theater that reflected its limited  resources and its occasional flights of fancy.</p>
        <p>One of the City Opera's traditional duties has been to provide tidy, affordable versions of the standard repertory. In the years before Mr. Keene's accession, Verdi, Puccini and Bizet had come to look shabby indeed, but he began a systematic sprucing up: a series of new productions of old favorites that have largely been successful. The policy of casting young American singers has continued, but so unfriendly is the New York State Theater to developing voices  that many singers have been advised to avoid a space so large and unforgiving.</p>
        <p>Adventure has been the other side of this company and one that Mr. Keene leapt into enthusiastically. A lot of the new operas were bad ("Marilyn," "Harvey Milk"), but at least we were given a sense of expectancy and a chance to hope. Although "Carmen" is nice, it is hard to feel much expectancy when it is on the bill. But these new operas freed us, for a moment at least, from the masterpiece syndrome, the rather addled modern expectation of genius every time  out. How many operagoers in 1840 awaited eternal verities, or even competence, with every premiere? Operas came and went much as musicals do now on Broadway.</p>
        <p>The City Opera is a company in precarious straits, and whom it can find and persuade to be the new Christopher Keene may influence its fate to a high degree. What a job awaits the newest happy warrior: finding a program so plausible that generous benefactors on the board of directors will be moved to deepen their pockets once again; continuing the refurbishment of familiar repertory; summoning the requisite imagination and guts to strike out boldly even when failure threatens.</p>
        <p>This company may never be able to move to a new home despite its recent dreams of doing so. Lincoln Center needs its presence and its audiences, and the pressures to stay must be strong. The cost of resettling a company with such a shaky future would be dauntingly risky in any case. A lot of deep thinking will  be going on during the next months. Christopher Keene has just left us, but one  can already hear the cry from the southern end of Lincoln Center: "Where are you when we need you?"</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
