<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maverick Among Block Patrols</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="798787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BEDFORD-STUYVESANT/FORT GREENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BEDFORD-STUYVESANT (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERSON, LEONARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KILGANNON, COREY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDD1030F936A25753C1A963958260" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maverick Among Block Patrols</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KILGANNON, COREY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along Tompkins Boulevard in Bedford-Stuyvesant, the series of once-majestic old brownstones, pockmarked with burned-out windows or boarded-up doors, is suddenly broken by an oasis of kempt storefronts with banners on the walls and benches on the sidewalk. A large mural proclaims, "Bed-Stuy Block Patrol, It's time for a change."</p>
        <p>The block patrol, headquartered in a pop-up camper, is much like other neighborhood policing efforts that have sprung up around the city. It was founded by one determined man, Leonard Person, 41, a general contractor who has reached into his own pocket for equipment. The 40 men who make it up are neighborhood residents who carry walkie-talkies and are told to call 911 if trouble arises.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Along Tompkins Boulevard in Bedford-Stuyvesant, the series of once-majestic old brownstones, pockmarked with burned-out windows or boarded-up doors, is suddenly broken by an oasis of kempt storefronts with banners on the walls and benches on the sidewalk. A large mural proclaims, "Bed-Stuy Block Patrol, It's time for a change."</p>
        <p>The block patrol, headquartered in a pop-up camper, is much like other neighborhood policing efforts that have sprung up around the city. It was founded by one determined man, Leonard Person, 41, a general contractor who has reached into his own pocket for equipment. The 40 men who make it up are neighborhood residents who carry walkie-talkies and are told to call 911 if trouble arises.</p>
        <p>But the patrol is also different. It is not particularly rare for members to have lost friends or relatives to street violence. And, in a neighborhood where a common complaint is that the police just do not come, there is an aversion to the authorities that borders on hostility.</p>
        <p>"No one will trust you when you deal with the police," Mr. Person said. "We don't mess with the drug dealers, but we let them know we're there. If they see us talking to a cop on the street, they'll think we're informers."</p>
        <p>While some clergy members and residents say the patrol has made the area safer, the police are not enthusiastic. "They don't patrol anything," said Officer Robert Barnes at the 79th Precinct. "We drive by there all the time, but we don't have anything to do with him."</p>
        <p>The Bed-Stuy Patrol goes into action at 6 A.M., when Mr. Person begins deploying his troops, on bike or foot. One patroller is Tony Snowden, whose 6-year-old daughter, Shamone Johnson, was fatally shot in August, when she rollerskated into drug-dealer crossfire at the Prospect Plaza Houses. Mr. Person, whose father was shot four times by dealers and whose crack-addicted brother died of AIDS, heads to work around 9 A.M. A volunteer, Gilbert Mitch, takes over, keeping in radio contact with the patrols and Mr. Person. Mr. Person pointed out that although he instructs his staff to keep out of drug-related incidents, when other incidents like muggings do occur, the patrol will do "whatever is necessary" to break them up.</p>
        <p>But, he added: "We're basically just watching. We're not vigilantes or the Guardian Angels, but we are streetwise -- you got to be to decide what actions to take. But we're not cops and we do not carry weapons."</p>
        <p>Somebody does. On Wednesday night, a man was shot and killed in front of 413 Putnam Avenue. "He was a known mugger and thief," said Mr. Person, who believes a vigilante pulled the trigger. "Everyone knew he had it coming to him."</p>
        <p>The Rev. Gary Simpson at the nearby Concorde Baptist Church praised Mr. Person's efforts. "A lot of people get cold and callous and turn their backs on the community," he said. "Lenny has the kind of spirit that needs to be resurrected in this neighborhood."</p>
        <p>A 14-year-old, Kim Wheeler, said: "There are still shootouts, but not as many." As for the drug dealers? "It's a little better," nodded her friend Danesha Payadue. "But they're still passing drugs all the time right in front of me and my little sister."  COREY KILGANNON  NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BEDFORD-STUYVESANT/FORT GREENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
