<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="798098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DD1039F936A25753C1A963958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSHUA MILLS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OMERTA, JAPANESE STYLE</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OMERTA, JAPANESE STYLE</p>
        <p>Who Knew What When?  The Daiwa Bank's loss of $1.1 billion because of one employee's unauthorized trading in U.S. Treasuries left egg all over the bank's top executives. Now the  stain has spread: six weeks weeks before Daiwa notified American regulators of its problem, it told the Japanese Government -- which decided this was not information it had to share with Washington. At best, Tokyo's secrecy was a serious breach of protocol at a time when the two Governments were trying to sort out various financial issues -- and when concerns about the shaky underpinnings of some Japanese banks had reached the point that American institutions were charging a premium for lines of credit extended to Japan. A phone call between Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin and Japan's Finance Minister, Masayoshia Takemura, seemed to do little to mend the fence: Treasury officials said the Japanese had expressed regret; the Japanese insisted that they had not apologized and that American regulators were upset because of "cultural differences." In any event, said the Vice Minister of Finance, Kyosuke Shinozawa, it was Daiwa's responsibility to inform the United States, not the ministry's.</p>
        <p>THE HIGH-TECH YO-YO</p>
        <p>Which Way to Jump? In the latest pang for all those heavily invested in high technology, the sector took a nose dive on Monday, with the Nasdaq composite down 2.7 percent, precipitated by Novell's announcement of anticipated lower earnings, followed by Motorola profits that disappointed some investors.  By Tuesday's opening, the Dow had been dragged down 65 points. But then investors dived back in, and yet again The Selloff had become The Buying Opportunity. By week's end the markets were setting or flirting with records.</p>
        <p>LABOR</p>
        <p>Flight Attendants Win a Round In a rare success for organized labor, arbitrators awarded the flight attendants union at American Airlines a 17 percent salary increase over four years and maintained vacation time at current levels. The 20,000 flight attendants at American struck just before Thanksgiving 1993; they returned to work five days later after President Clinton twisted the arm of Robert L. Crandall, the chairman of AMR, which owns the airline, until he agreed to arbitration. The arbitrators did grant American the right to reduce staffing on some flights.</p>
        <p>GOODBYE</p>
        <p>Manzi Bails Out at I.B.M. In the credit markets, three months is short term. But that's not how Jim P. Manzi, chief executive of Lotus Development, sees things. After quickly giving in to I.B.M.'s takeover offer last summer, Mr. Manzi pledged to stay with Big Blue for "the long haul." Ninety-nine days later, he has walked away, saying he  was not "the right person" to run a division at I.B.M., where no one seemed to be crying at the news. If Lotus's software geniuses were to follow Mr. Manzi out the door, that could change quickly.</p>
        <p>CYBERSPACE</p>
        <p>Roadworks Ahead Weaknesses in the structural integrity of the Internet could allow a criminal to divert documents or transactions transmitted over computer networks, researchers at the University of California warned. The problem requires more than a hot patch on the information superhighway, the experts say, urging businesses to contain their enthusiasm for digital commerce until adequate safeguards are in place.</p>
        <p>BANKING</p>
        <p>New Week, New Merger Forging a combination that would dominate banking in metropolitan Philadelphia,  Core states Financial agreed to acquire Meridian Bancorp for $3.2 billion in stock. As banking mergers grew to fever pitch earlier this year, Meridian held out. But Corestates turned up the heat after an unsuccessful pass at the Bank of Boston. Corestates said the combined company would close or sell 115 branches and trim nearly 2,000 jobs, about 10 percent of its staff.</p>
        <p>BORDER WAR</p>
        <p>Coffee Exchange to Stay Put Grabbing the gold ring offered by New York city and state officials, the Coffee, Sugar and Cocoa Exchange said it would remain in Manhattan and build a new home, rather than move to Jersey City as it had planned. New York officials hoped the  Cotton Exchange would similarly reverse course. By agreeing to put up $91 million in subsidies, the officials said, they were saving 5,000 New York jobs.</p>
        <p>WAR CHEST</p>
        <p>A Reserve Against Speculators Finance ministers from the world's richest nations agreed to set up a $50 billion fund to combat currency crises. The money would be available to the International Monetary Fund to make loans to countries suffering from capital flight. Even as the pool was established, brush fires flared in Europe, where speculators pressured the French franc and the lira. NOBEL PRIZE</p>
        <p>A Rite of Fall It's a harbinger of the season, like leaves turning colors: Each year -- five of the last six, anyway -- the Nobel jurors look to the University of Chicago to award the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economics. This time around the winner was Robert E. Lucas Jr., whose influential research in macroeconomics encouraged skepticism about the ability of Government policy makers to fine-tune the economy. A man for the times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
