<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA173FF934A15751C1A964958260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Law on Mobile Homes Question: I currently rent a small lot (25 by 100 feet) in a heavily industrialized and badly deteriorated neighborhood on the Brooklyn waterfront. Although the lot is zoned residential, I use it for parking and Sunday storage. I would like to know what obstacles -- if any -- preclude my having a mobile home or trailer home sited on this lot. I have noted a complete absence of mobile homes in the five boroughs and I am curious if there is some citywide statute banning their use. . . . Thomas O' Reilly, Seaford, L.I. Answer: Yes, there is. With one exception, mobile homes are not allowed in any of the five boroughs in New York City, regardless of how an area is zoned, said Vahe A. Tiryakian, spokesman for the city's Department of Buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Law on Mobile Homes Question: I currently rent a small lot (25 by 100 feet) in a heavily industrialized and badly deteriorated neighborhood on the Brooklyn waterfront. Although the lot is zoned residential, I use it for parking and Sunday storage. I would like to know what obstacles -- if any -- preclude my having a mobile home or trailer home sited on this lot. I have noted a complete absence of mobile homes in the five boroughs and I am curious if there is some citywide statute banning their use. . . . Thomas O' Reilly, Seaford, L.I. Answer: Yes, there is. With one exception, mobile homes are not allowed in any of the five boroughs in New York City, regardless of how an area is zoned, said Vahe A. Tiryakian, spokesman for the city's Department of Buildings.</p>
        <p>If someone wanted to establish a mobile home on a particular lot despite the ban, he or she would file a plan with the city's Department of Buildings, which would file an objection. The matter then would be decided by the city's Board Standards and Appeals.</p>
        <p>"We have never heard of that happening -- it's a far-out possibility," said Mr. Tiryakian. "The bottom line is that they are not allowed."</p>
        <p>There is, though, a trailer park on Goethals Road North in the Port Ivory section of Staten Island, said Mr. Tiryakian. While trailers and mobile homes were outlawed in the city's zoning resolution of 1961, he explained, the courts decided that this one park, which had already been substantially built, could remain.</p>
        <p>"That's the only exception," Mr. Tiryakian said. Right to a Spare Key Question: A year ago I rented a room in my apartment to a subtenant. In order for him to obtain renter's insurance, I put a lock on his door, with the understanding that I would have a copy of the key and that my cleaning lady would enter to clean the room on a weekly basis. Recently he changed the lock, did not give me a key and forbade my cleaning lady to enter. There were no complaints of missing property or explanation for this.</p>
        <p>Am I entitled to have a copy of this key and have his room cleaned as per our agreement? . . . Fiona Graham, Manhattan Answer: Yes. Legally, you are entitled to a key and a restoration of the agreement to allow a cleaning lady in the apartment once a week. Practically, though, if your agreement with the tenant was verbal, enforcement can be difficult.</p>
        <p>According to Michael R. Finder, a Manhattan real estate lawyer, the matter would likely have to be decided in court as a breach of rental agreement. He cautioned that this is a lengthy and costly process with no certain outcome, particularly if you have neither witnesses nor a written proof of an agreement. Damages for a Leak Question: Shortly after completing the renovation of my prewar condominium, a water leak occurred from the apartment above me. The leak happened over a weekend while I was not at home. The water stained and cracked the paint on the wall and molding in the doorway between the dining room and living room. It also damaged a newly installed wood floor, causing numerous small cracks and raising the grain in several areas.</p>
        <p>The damage is not noticeable unless you look closely, so the other tenant is refusing the pay for replacing the damaged boards. I do not want to have the cracks sanded out because it will leave an obvious imperfection in an otherwise new floor. I am also concerned about how the floor will wear if it is left as is. What level of repair am I entitled to? Also, the other tenant will only provide for repairs if I use her repairman. Can I use the contractor, who did the original work? . . . A. Jones, Manhattan Answer: Yes. You are entitled to select the contractor within the confines of reasonable costs, said Mr. Finder. As to the level of repair, you are entitled to have the floor repaired to what it had been before the accident.</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Finder added, "if it takes a magnifying glass to catch the imperfections it's not going to fly with an insurance company or a judge."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
