<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nets Win Going Away, This Time at Cleveland</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CLEVELAND CAVALIERS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D61530F934A15751C1A964958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nets Win Going Away, This Time at Cleveland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <dateline>RICHFIELD, OHIO, Dec. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey Nets. Go figure. No one can. When they're in New Jersey, they play like they can't wait to get the game over so they can go play Nintendo. When they're on the road, they play like champions. This is the road, so you can guess which Nets team showed up today.</p>
        <p>With forward Derrick Coleman playing some of his best basketball of the season (he tied his season high with 30 points), Kenny Anderson constantly finding the open man and Chris Morris hitting some key shots in the final minutes, New Jersey overwhelmed the Cleveland Cavaliers, 119-114, ending Cleveland's seven-game winning streak. It was New Jersey's first victory here since 1986, and the Nets' 68 points in the second half is a season high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Jersey Nets. Go figure. No one can. When they're in New Jersey, they play like they can't wait to get the game over so they can go play Nintendo. When they're on the road, they play like champions. This is the road, so you can guess which Nets team showed up today.</p>
        <p>With forward Derrick Coleman playing some of his best basketball of the season (he tied his season high with 30 points), Kenny Anderson constantly finding the open man and Chris Morris hitting some key shots in the final minutes, New Jersey overwhelmed the Cleveland Cavaliers, 119-114, ending Cleveland's seven-game winning streak. It was New Jersey's first victory here since 1986, and the Nets' 68 points in the second half is a season high.</p>
        <p>"I haven't been able to figure it out, and I don't know if I ever will," said Coach Chuck Daly about the Nets' strange behavior. He has watched the Nets go 8-5 on the road but only 6-7 at home. A Show by the Starting Five</p>
        <p>"It's a strange situation," said center Sam Bowie. "But we just seem to pick it up when we're on the road. We need to do that at home. I don't understand it."</p>
        <p>The Nets have been concerned about the effect Coleman has on the team. The fact is when Coleman missed a series of games because of injuries, the team played better without him and the Nets even went on a six-game winning streak. But this game represents a demonstration of how well the starting five of Coleman, Anderson, Morris, Drazen Petrovic and Bowie can play together. They played so well, in fact, that it was hard for Daly to take them all out as each logged at least 33 minutes. And Petrovic (44), Anderson (43) and Coleman (41) each had over 40.</p>
        <p>Indeed, whatever happens to New Jersey (14-12) from here, this victory will be looked upon as one of the team's finer moments. The Nets haven't won here in 14 regular-season games (16 including playoffs) and the Coliseum is as imposing a building as there is in the National Basketball Association. Yet there were the Nets, ignoring the 19,532 screaming fans by going on a 14-2 run for a 77-75 lead midway through the third period after trailing by 12 points at halftime. There were the Nets, playing great defense of all things, holding the All-Star forward Larry Nance to 12 points. In fact, Nance scored all of his points in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Center Brad Daugherty led the Cavaliers in scoring with 28 points and added 10 rebounds. But he was the lone force for Cleveland late in the game. The Cavaliers opened the game with some incredible shooting, 58 percent in the first half to the Nets' 50. But New Jersey responded in the third period by shooting 68 percent and holding the Cavaliers to 42.</p>
        <p>"We were hoping they would cool off," said Coleman. But the Cavaliers didn't just cool off, they iced over on defense by the Nets. Coleman added: "Execution, buckling down, trying to play some defense, rebounding. It was all of those things."</p>
        <p>The Cavaliers' Gerald Wilkins, who came off the bench for 18 points, said: "I don't think we came out with the kind of intensity we needed to put them away. They just took over the game."</p>
        <p>They did so by playing some of their best team basketball in a long time. Anderson (26 points, 10 assists) kept threading the ball to the open man in the middle and his passes often led to foul shots for the Nets (they made 20 of 21 free throws). Coleman and Petrovic (21 points) were also passing well. The Nets played a completely unselfish game.</p>
        <p>But it was Coleman who led the Nets. His 30 points on 12-of-18 shooting led all scorers. He snagged 13 rebounds, had 7 assists and made all 6 of his free throws. Coleman's 16 points in that hot third quarter tied the most any player has scored against Cleveland in the third quarter. Coleman also had 13 rebounds, a team high, as he has averaged 16.7 rebounds in his last three games.</p>
        <p>Coleman not only drove inside on the Cleveland defense, he sometimes took the soft jumper from 12 feet and a couple of times was the point guard on the fast break. He did it all.</p>
        <p>One of the many crucial points in the game came with the Nets holding a tentative lead, 101-99. Mark Price had just made a jumper to pull closer and the Nets needed a basket. When a shot by Anderson rolled off the rim, Coleman was there to tip it in, doing so just as the shot clocked ticked to zero.</p>
        <p>"Once the jump shot gets going it opens up everything else for me," said Coleman. And once Coleman gets going it opens up everything for the Nets.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
