<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killing of 5 in Boston's Chinatown Raises Fears of Asian Gang Wars</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="415329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHINESE-AMERICANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSTON (MASS)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINATOWN (BOSTON)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MYANMAR</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D91139F936A25752C0A967958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killing of 5 in Boston's Chinatown Raises Fears of Asian Gang Wars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BUTTERFIELD, FOX</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Jan. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The killing of five men in a Chinatown social club on Saturday has raised fears that new and more violent Asian gangs are struggling for control in Boston and underscores how a recent wave of immigrants from Asia has transformed this city's small Chinatown, the police and community leaders say.</p>
        <p>The five men, who were playing cards when they were killed, were shot numerous times, each at least once in the head, Police Superintendent Joseph V. Saia Jr., said. A sixth victim was critically wounded and is being kept under police protection at a hospital whose name the police have refused to disclose for his protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The killing of five men in a Chinatown social club on Saturday has raised fears that new and more violent Asian gangs are struggling for control in Boston and underscores how a recent wave of immigrants from Asia has transformed this city's small Chinatown, the police and community leaders say.</p>
        <p>The five men, who were playing cards when they were killed, were shot numerous times, each at least once in the head, Police Superintendent Joseph V. Saia Jr., said. A sixth victim was critically wounded and is being kept under police protection at a hospital whose name the police have refused to disclose for his protection.</p>
        <p>Neighborhood residents said the social club was frequented by ethnic Chinese from Myanmar, many of whom worked as waiters in nearby restaurants and stopped off to play cards after work. Today the police released the names of the first two victims: Kwang Luu, 26 years old, and Man Cheung, 56 years old. Their occupations and ethnic backgrounds were not disclosed.</p>
        <p>The killings came after the shooting death last Tuesday of Steve Huy Tan, 30, a part-time waiter who was shot in the lobby of his apartment a few blocks from the site of Saturday's slayings. Breakup of Traditional Gang</p>
        <p>Mr. Saia said that "there has been no real organization of the criminal element in the Chinatown section of Boston" since the mid- to late-1980's, when the leader of the Ping On, the once-dominant gang here, fled to Hong Kong and his second in command was slain in his suburban restaurant.</p>
        <p>With the breakup of the Ping On, which had a base in the traditional Chinese underworld of the triads and tongs, or secret societies and mutual aid groups, a new generation of smaller, less formally organized but more violent gangs have emerged, a law-enforcement officer familiar with Asian gangs here said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saia acknowledged that there were "a lot of gangs and criminal elements that are vying for power" in Chinatown, and he said the police "will investigate all aspects of that."</p>
        <p>The change in criminal activity in Boston's Chinatown is similar to changes that have taken place in Chinatowns in New York, San Francisco, Toronto and Vancouver, said Ko-Lin Chin, a senior research analyst for the New York City Criminal Justice Agency. "This new group of Chinese criminals has nothing to do with the traditional Chinese criminal organization in Chinatown of triads, tongs and street gangs," he said. No Loyalties and No Pity</p>
        <p>The new groups are involved in heroin smuggling, prostitution and the smuggling of Chinese aliens into the United States, he added. Because they lack ties to the traditional organizations, "they have no loyalties and are much more ruthless," said Mr. Chin, the author of "Chinese Subculture and Criminality: Nontraditional Crime Groups in America," a book published recently by the Greenwood Press.</p>
        <p>These new groups also present a difficult problem for the police, Mr. Chin said, "because they don't have a headquarters or permanent organization and are constantly changing their composition."</p>
        <p>The changes in Chinatowns across the country began with the change in the immigration law of 1965, which removed barriers to Asian immigrants. In the last decade the number of Asians in the Boston metropolitan area has doubled, to 100,000 people, said Michael Liu, director of the Asian American Resource Workshop. But only about 8,000 live in Boston's Chinatown, an area of only a few square blocks.</p>
        <p>Some of the most violent new gang members are believed to be Vietnamese or ethnic Chinese from Vietnam, similar to those blamed for some recent shootings in New York's Chinatown, a law-enforcement specialist here said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
