<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bradley Is Rested and Raring for Biggest of Games: Presidential Race</title>
    <meta content="06BRAD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE3D61F3BF935A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bradley Is Rested and Raring for Biggest of Games: Presidential Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Dec. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill Bradley talks enthusiastically about running for President in 2000, apparently having banished the self-doubts that some said marked him as Senator; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''It's a good time to be out of Washington,'' Bill Bradley was saying two hours after he held a news conference to announce his yearning to return there as President in the year 2001.</p>
        <p>The former New Jersey Senator was referring to the excruciating year that has put President Clinton on the brink of impeachment, forcing Mr. Bradley and any other candidate to wonder whether a Presidential run is worth the trouble. As if offering the first chicken-in-every-pot enticement of a fresh political season, he suggested a way for the next field of candidates to deal with the Clinton scandal that many Americans might find refreshing, if the polls are to be believed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''It's a good time to be out of Washington,'' Bill Bradley was saying two hours after he held a news conference to announce his yearning to return there as President in the year 2001.</p>
        <p>The former New Jersey Senator was referring to the excruciating year that has put President Clinton on the brink of impeachment, forcing Mr. Bradley and any other candidate to wonder whether a Presidential run is worth the trouble. As if offering the first chicken-in-every-pot enticement of a fresh political season, he suggested a way for the next field of candidates to deal with the Clinton scandal that many Americans might find refreshing, if the polls are to be believed.</p>
        <p>''You don't,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''You turn the page. You move on. This is not about the past; it's about the future.'' And, with a slight, confident smile, the candidate moved on to the issues that intrigue him: impoverished children, racial divisions, health care, the working family's life.</p>
        <p>For a politician once tagged as a waffler on the subject of running for President, Mr. Bradley seems brimming with certainty this time, describing his new exploratory committee as the necessary ''training camp'' for the full political season that he firmly predicts will include him. He has been considering all the factors, he says, from catching Vice President Al Gore, who has a head start for the Democratic nomination, to raising the $20 million or so it takes to make a serious challenge.</p>
        <p>He would entertain no doubts as he leaned back in his office, already kinetic with campaign advisers and clutter, and talked enthusiastically of forming his team, running his plays, barnstorming the country.</p>
        <p>''I'm at the top of my game,'' said Mr. Bradley, 55, a former New York Knick basketball star, his campaign mantra already clear as he repeats this assertion for one and all, as if answering a skeptical newspaper headline taped outside: ''He Got Game?'' The scholar-athlete tensions and self-doubts that some said marked Mr. Bradley as Senator seemed determinedly banished; candidate Bradley talks of running all out, enthusiastic as a gym rat, not a jot of equivocation in sight.</p>
        <p>''Look, you go out and tell the people what you believe,'' he said, summarizing his uphill task as if  diagraming a play. ''You know why you're doing it. You're at peace with yourself. You respect the wisdom of the American people. That's the sequence of the things that you do.''</p>
        <p>When he left in 1996 after 18 years in the Senate, the New Jersey Democrat sourly pronounced the political system ''broken.'' But he talked, too, of personal burnout after a career in which he twice openly mused about a Presidential run but turned away. In the interlude, he has taught, written, campaigned for other candidates and, he said, regained his competitor's edge.</p>
        <p>''I always believe you listen to that inner voice,'' said Mr. Bradley, a former Rhodes scholar. ''Now I'm back and it says, 'Go.' So I'm going.''</p>
        <p>He still harbors some of the old anxieties about the nastiness and invasiveness of a Presidential run that put him off in 1988 and 1992, he acknowledged. In his political memoir, ''Time Present, Time Past,'' he wrote, ''Sometimes I feel that I'm living during a political era in which what I value most, character, is endangered; what I admire most, humanity, is devalued; and what I feel most sensitive about, privacy, is denied.''</p>
        <p>But as he talked, Mr. Bradley's wariness about the bear-pit nature of politics seemed no match for his appetite to finally run plain and straight for the White House.</p>
        <p>''That's either a fever that's going to break,'' he said of the character vetting and attacking that seem to dominate modern campaigning, ''or it's an unfortunate continuing aspect of the environment.'' He seemed to be treating it as a bruising dynamic of the game that he could handle. ''The way you deal with that is to be yourself,'' said the man once known for setting stinging body blocks.</p>
        <p>In today's announcement speech, which campaign aides say Mr. Bradley painstakingly composed himself over the last two months, the candidate promised ''a type of leadership that doesn't stand in the spotlight as much as call attention to millions of Americans who shine.'' The ''spotlight'' allusion touched on the marketing challenge for Mr. Bradley's campaign team: how to artfully contrast the sensational celebrity-cum-notoriety of Mr. Clinton with Mr. Bradley's quieter political professionalism.</p>
        <p>''We think he offers authenticity,'' said one Bradley strategist, hoping voters sense this as a welcome relief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley shrugs off any shortcoming in celebrity flash. He promises nothing more than himself and a considerable assortment of ideas. ''I have a clear sense of what I want to do,'' he said, ''and in a very fundamental sense, it's the right time for me to run.''</p>
        <p>Even as he plunges back in, he flatly states what is wrong with politics. ''There's too much money,'' he said, ''the media is often too superficial and sensational, and not enough politicians speak from their core convictions.''</p>
        <p>On his first day of running, Mr. Bradley emphasized that his ''exploratory'' status was merely the initial requisite of what he expects will be a full campaign. ''Been to New Hampshire, been to Iowa,'' he noted, smiling at the inevitable nuts-and-bolts questions. He has no operation yet in either place, but his strategists promise to be ready in time for the front-loaded primary calendar of the 2000 campaign.</p>
        <p>''There's no kind of magic that you use,'' Mr. Bradley said, insisting that he was undaunted at the task of rapidly creating a credible campaign machine. ''You just go out there and tell the country what you believe.''</p>
        <p>There is far more to it than that, and Mr. Bradley has been seeing to the details for months, with names of more than 300 friends and operatives, for example, on one special announcement list he personally attended to, aides said.</p>
        <p>The campaign manager is Gina Glantz, whose experience goes back to the Walter Mondale campaign of 1984. Douglas Berman, former New Jersey state treasurer, is campaign chairman. The deputy manager is the former chief of staff to Gov. Jim Hunt of North Carolina, Ed Turlington, who has been scouting the trail on behalf of Mr. Bradley's Presidential bid since he left the Senate. The treasurer is Ted Wells, a criminal lawyer and longtime Bradley adviser. Already at the candidate's side is Anita Dunn, who was the Senator's chief of staff, and Eric Hauser, another former staff member.</p>
        <p>When asked about Iowa, the early caucus stop in the campaign, Mr. Bradley tells of being an 11-year-old Little Leaguer in the regional championship game in Keokuk. ''I'm on first and we're trailing by a run,'' he recalled. ''I take a step off the base, the guy does the hidden-ball trick and, bang, we lose.''</p>
        <p>Bill Bradley, the legendary unsmiling competitor, beamed for perhaps the only time at the memory of losing. ''Ever since, I've dreamed of going back to Iowa and winning one,'' he said, his hustings act obviously ready. ''So here we are.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
