<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York -- A warm Irish welcome just a stroll from Grand Central</title>
    <meta content="NYC.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HOTEL CHECK-IN: ROOMS WITH A PERSONAL MAGNETISM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fitzpatrick Grand Central Hotel (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD1E38F935A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York -- A warm Irish welcome just a stroll from Grand Central</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates report on Fitzpatrick Grand Central, Manhattan hotel that offers warm Irish welcome; photo; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was something festive about the Fitzpatrick Grand Central in New York when I arrived on a recent Tuesday night. The guests chatting in the lobby looked so pretty, dressed in party-quality black, surrounded by gleaming mahogany and brass. They sounded pretty, too, in a blend of British and Irish voices.</p>
        <p>The 155-room Fitzpatrick is -- there's no other way to say it -- a little bit of Ireland on East 44th Street, exactly 90 steps from the Lexington Avenue entrance to Grand Central Terminal. It's a new sister property to the Fitzpatrick Manhattan 12 blocks north and to hotels in Dublin, Cork and Bunratty. My stay there was lovely (with the exception of one room-service debacle).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was something festive about the Fitzpatrick Grand Central in New York when I arrived on a recent Tuesday night. The guests chatting in the lobby looked so pretty, dressed in party-quality black, surrounded by gleaming mahogany and brass. They sounded pretty, too, in a blend of British and Irish voices.</p>
        <p>The 155-room Fitzpatrick is -- there's no other way to say it -- a little bit of Ireland on East 44th Street, exactly 90 steps from the Lexington Avenue entrance to Grand Central Terminal. It's a new sister property to the Fitzpatrick Manhattan 12 blocks north and to hotels in Dublin, Cork and Bunratty. My stay there was lovely (with the exception of one room-service debacle).</p>
        <p>My room, No. 814, was spacious for a single and very pleasant. The bed had a gold brocade-print spread and a faux canopy of gold and blue print fabric against the wall (a little too wannabe-grand for my taste, but attractive enough). An armoire contained the television and a mini-fridge (stocked, sad to say, only with a couple of bottles of water). An electric trouser press stood, a little inelegantly, beside the desk. The carpet was royal blue and the walls a very elegant ivory-on-ivory stripe, but they were mostly bare, giving the room a somewhat unfinished feeling. But let's be fair: The hotel is barely three months old. There were still ''Wet Paint'' signs in the hallways, and a white teddy bear the size of an 8-year-old child sat in the lobby with a sign imploring guests to ''bear with us.''</p>
        <p>The Fitzpatrick wants to be a business traveler's hotel, so there were a two-line telephone with voice mail, a personal fax machine (which worked) and a data port (which didn't seem to, but the telephone jack underneath the desk did just fine). My view of the air shaft was nicely disguised by white sheers and blue-print draperies that matched the bed canopy.</p>
        <p>The bath was small but gleaming, with midnight-blue faux-marbre tile on the walls, chrome fixtures and a pretty white-eyelet shower curtain. It's too bad that much of the counter space was taken up by a tray with a coffeemaker and the fixings, but there seemed to be no other place to put it. The white terry robe promised in the brochure was nowhere to be seen, but there was a good built-in three-speed hair dryer. I had some trouble with the shower's water-temperature controls. Maybe that's what the two workmen who arrived unbidden were there to fix. The evening was getaway heaven: room-service dinner in front of the television with a bottle of wine and the final Jimmy Smits episode of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.'' The dinner menu is extensive, with sandwiches and entrees (including bangers and mash) from $12.50 to $20 and a very affordable wine list. It did seem unnecessary to give the food cute Irish names like Molly Malone's Mussels and the Crock of Gold (Irish cocktail sausages).</p>
        <p>Dinner arrived in the promised 25 minutes, brought by a friendly, courteous waitress, and couldn't have been better -- for Irish cuisine, which often errs on the bland side. I had Salmon Chu Culainn (''honey-mustard encrusted'') atop rice pilaf with the vegetables du jour, which turned out to be broccoli and cauliflower, accompanied by an Italian cabernet and a basket of good, chewy bread. (Downstairs there's a casual pub-style restaurant, which looks inviting.)</p>
        <p>If only breakfast had worked out as well. I ordered the full Irish breakfast for 6:30 A.M. because I had work to do on the laptop before going to the office. At 7:10 A.M., I was still waiting. That was when the room-service people telephoned to apologize for having misplaced the order and to ask if I still wanted it. Yes. After another 30 minutes, I called, a little annoyed, and my meal was at my door within five minutes. Again, there were profuse apologies, and it was a meal worth waiting for: a salute to calories and cholesterol, with scrambled eggs, sausage links, thick Irish bacon, black and white pudding, a couple of tomato wedges on the side, orange juice and coffee.</p>
        <p>Singles normally start at $265 and doubles at $295, but I paid $189, a Thanksgiving-week rate, I was told. The Fitzpatrick is still getting its footing, I imagine, but it already has a welcoming lilt -- a nice thing to find in midtown.</p>
        <p>Fitzpatrick Grand Central, 141 East 44th Street, New York, N.Y. 10017; (800) 367-7701, fax (212) 818-1747.</p>
        <p>HOTEL CHECK-IN: ROOMS WITH A PERSONAL MAGNETISM ANITA GATES is an editor for the Arts and Leisure section of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ANITA GATES is an editor for the Arts and Leisure section of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
