<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flying Reptiles Pose Evolutionary Puzzle</title>
    <meta content="22FLY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="884891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pterosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fossils</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Society of Vertebrate Paleontology</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Padian, Kevin (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruben, John A (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DB1730F931A15753C1A960958260" item-length="1666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flying Reptiles Pose Evolutionary Puzzle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Flying reptiles known as pterosaurs, which thrived for 135 million years, remain evolutionary mystery, even though more than 3,000 specimens have been collected from around the world since 1784; pterosaurs diversified into some 85 species, from size of sparrows to size of airplanes; drawings; Society of Vertebrate Paleontology takes up mystery of flying reptiles' origin in heated discussion at New York meeting; some of missing link between reptiles and birds is discussed by American and Chinese experts who describe recently discovered dinosaur fossil with traces of feathery, but no such intermediate animal has been found to link reptiles and pterosaurs; contesting views of Dr Kevin Padian, Dr John A Ruben and others noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the most successful orders of animals, the flying reptiles known as pterosaurs, thrived for 135 million years and diversified into some 85 species, some as small as sparrows, some the size of airplanes.</p>
        <p>Although more than 3,000 specimens of pterosaurs have been collected from every continent except Antarctica, and although scientists have been studying them since 1784, when Cosimo Collini, a former secretary of Voltaire, found the first one, pterosaurs remain an evolutionary mystery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the most successful orders of animals, the flying reptiles known as pterosaurs, thrived for 135 million years and diversified into some 85 species, some as small as sparrows, some the size of airplanes.</p>
        <p>Although more than 3,000 specimens of pterosaurs have been collected from every continent except Antarctica, and although scientists have been studying them since 1784, when Cosimo Collini, a former secretary of Voltaire, found the first one, pterosaurs remain an evolutionary mystery.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid the only thing on which all paleontologists can agree,'' said Dr. Peter Wellnhofer of the Bavarian State Collection for Paleontology in Munich, ''is that the pterosaur was a creature that could fly. Beyond that, we don't agree on much.''</p>
        <p>This was the thrust of discussions by scientists who attended a meeting of the Society of Vertebrate Paleontology in New York last week.</p>
        <p>Although the sessions covered fishes, turtles and early mammals, among other vertebrates, a feature of the meeting was a special symposium on pterosaurs, at which many of the world's leading experts presented papers, specimens and heated commentary.</p>
        <p>The biggest mystery of the pterosaurs is their origin. No fossil has been found that can be identified as an immediate ancestor of the pterosaurs.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the evolution of birds from dinosaurs is marked by several intermediate creatures that paleontologists have found, including a primitive bird called archaeopterix -- with a skeleton almost identical to that of certain dinosaurs but covered with feathers of advanced design that clearly enabled it to fly.</p>
        <p>Another kind of missing link between reptiles and birds came to light last week at the paleontology meeting, where American and Chinese paleontologists displayed photographs of a recently discovered dinosaur fossil that has traces of feathery down along its backbone, tail and sides. It is clearly a dinosaur of the compsognathus type, but the down looks like primitive feathers.</p>
        <p>No such intermediate animal has ever been found bridging the evolutionary gap between reptiles and pterosaurs, however.</p>
        <p>''It's as if pterosaurs sprang full blown from the head of Zeus,'' said Dr. Robert Bakker of the Tate Museum at Casper College in Casper, Wyo.</p>
        <p>The pterosaurs eventually went into a decline that lasted several million years, according to Dr. Wann Langston Jr. of the Texas Memorial Museum in Austin, and then died out about the same time as their reptile cousins, the dinosaurs, 65 million years ago. There is little agreement as to why.</p>
        <p>''We are all friends despite our disagreements over almost everything,'' said Dr. Kevin Padian of the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Among the many subjects of disagreement is the question of whether pterosaurs walked with an erect stance, like that of birds, or alternatively, dragged themselves along the ground like bats. Large issues are related to this question, including the origin of flight. If early pterosaurs were able to run like modern birds they might have developed the ability to leap into the air and make short flights, eventually achieving true flight. But if they sprawled in the manner of bats, they are more likely to have begun flying by gliding between trees, or parachuting to the ground.</p>
        <p>The wings of pterosaurs were unlike those of either birds or bats. A bird wing consists mainly of fairly rigid feathers attached to the animal's forearm and second finger, while a bat wing is a thin membrane supported by its equivalent of the second through fifth fingers. The pterosaur wing was a membrane stretched between a very elongated fourth finger and the animal's trunk.</p>
        <p>But how the membrane was attached is a point of disagreement. Some paleontologists argued that the main part of the membrane, the brachiopatagium, extended all the way to the hind feet, thereby making the hind feet very clumsy on the ground and necessitating a crawling stance. This drawback might have been made still more troublesome if another membrane, called the uropatagium, spanned the space between the hind legs, adding lifting surface to the pterosaur's wing. The fossil record on this point is somewhat ambiguous; the apparent presence of a uropatagium in some specimens has been interpreted by skeptics as ''Jurassic road kill,'' in which impressions of body skin have been squashed and distorted by geological processes to look as if they were attached to the hind legs.</p>
        <p>One way to examiniethis issue depends on the analysis of fossil tracks left on wet sand, but the interpretation of possible pterosaur trackways spurred many disagreements at the meeting.</p>
        <p>Dr. Martin G. Lockley of the University of Colorado at Denver and Dr. David Unwin of the University of Bristol in England presented images of footprints they identified as those of pterosaurs, in which two separate types of marks could be discerned: those that might have been left by a ''pes'' or hind foot, and those left by a ''manus'' or the equivalent of a hand at the front edge of a pterosaur wing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lockley acknowledged that some of the tracks found in the western United States were not those of pterosaurs, but that other trackways discovered recently in England, France, Spain and Utah were almost certainly those of pterosaurs. Moreover, the impressions of the animal's ''hand'' are deeper than those of its hind feet, perhaps implying that it threw more of its weight on its forearms than its hind feet as it crawled. Some tracks appeared as parallel scratches that might have been made by pterosaurs swimming in very shallow water, with their feet sometimes scratching along the underlying mud.</p>
        <p>This view was contested by Dr. Padian, who said that he and others had interpreted the same tracks as those of crocodiles. He said the evidence favored a two-legged stance for pterosaurs, much like that of modern birds, although pterosaurs might sometimes have moved on all four limbs.</p>
        <p>''But it's healthy to debate these questions,'' he said, ''because it helps us to consolidate what we agree on.''</p>
        <p>Agreement was mainly apparent in its absence, however.</p>
        <p>A particularly divisive question was the subject of warm-  versus cold-bloodedness among the pterosaurs as well as dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>Since the 1970's, several leading paleontologists, including Dr. John H. Ostrom of Yale University and Dr.  Bakker in Wyoming, have argued that many, if not most, dinosaurs and pterosaurs were endothermic, capable of maintaining a warm body temperature.</p>
        <p>A contrasting view was presented last week by Dr. John A. Ruben of Oregon State University at Corvallis, who argued that pterosaurs need not have been warmblooded to sustain flight.</p>
        <p>''Ectothermic, or coldblooded, reptiles can produce bursts of high power for locomotion, although their endurance is limited,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''There is no compelling physical evidence for pterosaur endothermy and it is becoming increasingly apparent that many early birds, although fully capable of powered flight, may well have been ectotherms.''</p>
        <p>The body skeletons of pterosaurs more closely resemble those of coldblooded lizards and alligators than they do the bodies of warmblooded birds, which contain abdominal air sacks that are used for respiration, he said: another indication that pterosaurs were coldblooded.</p>
        <p>Two leading pterosaur experts, Dr. Thomas M. Lehman of Texas Technical University at Lubbock and Dr. Langston of the Texas Memorial Museum, presented new evidence of the domestic habits of one of the most enigmatic of the pterosaurs, the gigantic Quetzalcoatlus, which is widely regarded as the largest animal ever to have taken to the air.</p>
        <p>Quetzalcoatlus, named after an Aztec god, lived at the very end of the age of dinosaurs, and grew to enormous size; one wing specimen indicates that the larger specimens were more than 30 feet across from wingtip to wingtip.</p>
        <p>But while most fossil pterosaurs are found in sediments left by shallow coastal lagoons and lived by catching fish, Quetzalcoatlus apparently lived hundreds of miles from the nearest sea coast, in parts of the present-day American Southwest that were warm, dry, and nonseasonal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lehman and Dr. Langston concluded from the study of some nine individuals and other evidence found in southwestern Texas that Quetzalcoatlus lived mainly along shallow lake shores, perhaps using its long beak to dig into coastal mud for clams, arthropods and other invertebrate animals known to have burrowed in the region 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>The huge pterosaurs, although presumed to have been expert at long-endurance soaring, must have been very awkward on the ground, and could only have lived by digging for crayfish and similar prey in the absence of large enemies. In fact, fossils found in the area do not include any animals that might have presented a danger to Quetzalcoatlus.</p>
        <p>The ambiguities that the study of the pterosaurs always turn up result from several factors, paleontologists agree. For one thing, pterosaurs lived so long ago that their fossils have largely weathered away. Their bones were small and easily scattered, and scientists are not sure which bones were connected to each other or how they were connected.</p>
        <p>The result of such sketchy information is that occasionally discoveries that fill in a gap in the fossil record compel scientists to completely revise their views. For example, most paleontologists assumed that pterosaurs had smooth reptilian skin until 1970, when a Russian scientist, A. G. Sharov, discovered one with a dense coat of long hairy scales. The discovery implied the possibility that the pterosaur was fundamentally coldblooded, but that it could generate and conserve body heat by vigorous activity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
