<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Yankees, Time for Plan B</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="194948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BEDROSIAN, STEVE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D8153CF936A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Yankees, Time for Plan B</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Yankees' effort to pursue a first-class relief pitcher was stalled yesterday, hours before the midnight deadline for declaring free agency, when Steve Bedrosian, the relief pitcher they coveted most, reached agreement on a three-year contract with the Philadelphia Phillies. The contract is worth $4.35 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Yankees' effort to pursue a first-class relief pitcher was stalled yesterday, hours before the midnight deadline for declaring free agency, when Steve Bedrosian, the relief pitcher they coveted most, reached agreement on a three-year contract with the Philadelphia Phillies. The contract is worth $4.35 million.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' effort to pursue a first-class relief pitcher was stalled yesterday, hours before the midnight deadline for declaring free agency, when Steve Bedrosian, the relief pitcher they coveted most, reached agreement on a three-year contract with the Philadelphia Phillies. The contract is worth $4.35 million.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were hoping to acquire Bedrosian, the 1987 Cy Young Award winner in the National League, and possibly return Dave Righetti to the starting rotation after five years in the bullpen.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, a high-quality starting pitcher, Bruce Hurst of the Boston Red Sox, filed for free agency, but a Yankee source said the Yankees would not become involved in the bidding for the left-hander, who won 18 games last season. Hurst has expressed an interest in returning to the Red Sox, although the St. Louis Cardinals are expected to make a bid at acquiring him. Slaught Gets Two-Year Pact</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Yankees announced the signing of the catcher Don Slaught to a two-year contract. Slaught, who hit .283 last season but threw out only 12 of 72 base stealers, will earn $650,000 for each of the next two seasons. He had been eligible to file for free agency.</p>
        <p>Filing yesterday were Rick Honeycutt, the Oakland Athletics relief pitcher, and Dennis Lamp, the Boston reliever.</p>
        <p>The Yankee chances of landing a late-inning reliever are slim, unless they make a trade. They had intended to use Bedrosian in the role occupied since 1984 by Righetti, who failed in 9 of 34 save opportunities last season.</p>
        <p>Righetti, who will turn 30 years old this month, has not started since the 1983 season, when he went 14-8 and threw a no-hitter against Boston. He was moved to the bullpen the next season and has saved 31, 29, 46, 31 and 25 games in the last five seasons.</p>
        <p>The only relievers of note in this winter's free-agent market are Tom Niedenfuer, who pitched last season with Baltimore, and the well-traveled Ted Power of Detroit.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will continue to seek starting pitching help through free agency, and the source, who requested anonymity, said they would express interest in Bob Walk, a right-hander, and Dave LaPoint, a left-hander. They may also pursue Scott Fletcher, the Texas Rangers' shortstop.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
