<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. LAWMAKERS SCRAMBLE TO PASS A MEDICARE PLAN</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL DEBT (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLYMER, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (SPEAKER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIVLIN, ALICE M (DIR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Debt (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D7153EF93AA25753C1A963958260" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. LAWMAKERS SCRAMBLE TO PASS A MEDICARE PLAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLYMER, ADAM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the eve of a crucially important Medicare vote, House Republicans today opened a vote-trading bazaar to line up a majority and joined their Senate allies in accusing the Clinton Administration of playing political games with the national debt.</p>
        <p>After tinkering with Medicare allowances for rural areas and dealing with complaints about other measures, from lobbying to nursing-home payments, the Republicans expressed confidence that they had persuaded enough doubters to pass their Medicare proposal on Thursday.  [ Page B12. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the eve of a crucially important Medicare vote, House Republicans today opened a vote-trading bazaar to line up a majority and joined their Senate allies in accusing the Clinton Administration of playing political games with the national debt.</p>
        <p>After tinkering with Medicare allowances for rural areas and dealing with complaints about other measures, from lobbying to nursing-home payments, the Republicans expressed confidence that they had persuaded enough doubters to pass their Medicare proposal on Thursday.  [ Page B12. ]</p>
        <p>Although Speaker Newt Gingrich cheerfully described the bargaining as "a little bit like Christmas shopping," his closed-door efforts were the most serious business of the day.  Medicare is the bloodiest political battlefield of this fall's budget wars, and the first test of the Republican effort to balance the budget by the year 2002.</p>
        <p>Even so, there was plenty of time for intense posturing over the national debt, as each side demanded that the other abandon political advantage for the sake of the national interest. All day long the White House and Mr. Gingrich traded offers and non-offers, and then charges and countercharges, on a temporary increase in the debt limit.</p>
        <p>The Treasury Department calculates that an increase must be enacted by early November, when, it says, the Government will reach its current, $4.9 trillion ceiling on public borrowing.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gingrich, after suggesting a temporary debt-limit increase that would allow Congress and the White House time to try to resolve their differences over the 1996 budget, backed off and complained that the Administration was playing political games.</p>
        <p>"We have no belief the Treasury has accurate figures," he said. "I want to look at the facts. Who knows what the truth is? I don't have a clue."</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Bob Dole of Kansas, agreed, although a little less forcefully. He said he was not "trying to cause any calamity in the Government," but insisted that the Administration "stop playing games."</p>
        <p>The Administration responded with confused disappointment from Michael D. McCurry, White House press secretary, who said of the Republicans, "It's impossible to predict where they're going to be from one moment to the next, you know." The White House chief of staff, Leon E. Panetta, offered regretful exasperation, saying, "I don't think the game-playing on the debt ceiling is a responsible thing to do."</p>
        <p>The Republicans had an easier time with a gleeful celebration of a remark, delivered on Tuesday night at a Houston fund raiser, in which President Clinton said he thought he had raised taxes too much.</p>
        <p>The Republicans interrupted a session of the Senate Finance Committee, which was trying to pass a $245 billion tax-cut measure, to offer unusual congratulations to the President. "I have to say maybe I agree with President Clinton this time," said the chairman, Senator William V. Roth Jr. of Delaware.</p>
        <p>The committee, delayed by Democratic objections, worked into the night on the tax cut before deciding to recess for the evening and reconvene on Thursday. The measure, whose main element would give a $500-a-child tax credit to most families, has the support of all the Republicans on the committee and will probably go to the full Senate for a vote later this month. It will be part of the budget reconciliation bill, which will also include reductions in the growth of entitlements like Medicare and Medicaid.</p>
        <p>"We're here to reduce taxes," Mr. Roth declared, "for the purpose of creating growth."</p>
        <p>But Democrats held that cutting taxes was bad policy, especially when it was being done in conjunction with lower spending for Medicare, Medicaid, education and other Government programs.</p>
        <p>The Senate measure follows the general path of even deeper tax reductions approved by the House last April. But the Senate proposal differs from the House bill in several important respects, which will have to be resolved in a House-Senate conference before the budget reconciliation bill can go to Mr. Clinton. These are the major differences:</p>
        <p>The Senate bill would give the $500-a-child tax credit to single parents with annual taxable incomes up to $75,000 and to couples with incomes up to $110,000. The House bill would allow parents with adjusted gross incomes up to $200,000 to claim the credit.</p>
        <p>Like the House bill, the Senate bill would reduce the top tax rate on capital gains, the profits from the sale of investments, to 19.8 percent for individuals, from the current 28 percent. But the senators did not accept a House provision that wouldallow the value of investments to be adjusted annually for inflation.</p>
        <p>The Senate measure would not lift the maximum income a retiree could earn without forfeiting some Social Security benefits; nor would it repeal a provision, enacted in 1993, that increased the portion of middle- and upper-income retirees' Social Security benefits that is subject to taxation. The House bill would take both these steps.</p>
        <p>The senators did not go along with House-passed provisions that would repeal the alternative minimum tax, for wealthy taxpayers with large write-offs. Nor did they agree with the House plan to give businesses a more favorable schedule for depreciating their investments in plants and machinery.</p>
        <p>Like the tax cut, the Republicans' Medicare proposal drew heavy fire from the Administration again today. In renewing a threat by Mr. Clinton to veto the entire budget reconciliation bill, Alice M. Rivlin, director of the White House Office of Management and Budget, attacked its "deep, unwarranted cuts in Medicare that would raise costs for beneficiaries and sharply cut payments to providers, jeopardizing access to, and the quality of, care."</p>
        <p>In a letter to Representative Gerald B. H. Solomon, the New York Republican who heads the House Rules Committee, Ms. Rivlin said, "The President has made it clear that he will veto any reconciliation bill that includes Medicare" cuts of that size.</p>
        <p>Undaunted, Republicans went ahead with intense tinkering on the Medicare bill today. As Mr. Gingrich observed, "Any time you are in the last 48 hours before a major vote, 17 people show up who suddenly figure out you need their vote and they have this one thing they haven't gotten yet."</p>
        <p>Seventeen is indeed a crucial figure. If 17 Republicans defect on Thursday, and if no Democrat crosses party lines to vote for the bill, it will be defeated.</p>
        <p>Responding to complaints by Representatives from rural areas, for example, Mr. Gingrich engineered an increase in the amount that health plans in less populated counties would be guaranteed when they enlist elderly Americans in managed care, a major goal of the bill. Such plans had been promised no more than $200 a month, but the bill was changed to guarantee them at least $250. Even so, rural lawmakers said that was still not enough, and some were saying they would oppose the bill.</p>
        <p>Another major change was made to that part of the reconciliation bill that deals with Medicaid, the Federal-state program that pays medical costs for the poor, the disabled and thousands of elderly nursing home residents.</p>
        <p>As originally drafted, the bill would have allowed states to seize money and property from the spouses and adult children of nursing home patients to pay for their care before any Medicaid money would have gone to help them. Current law prohibits tapping the resources of spouses and adult children, and the latest revision would continue that practice.</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas S. Bliley, the Virginia Republican who heads the House Commerce Committee, announced this reversal from the bitterly protested provision in the bill that his committee had approved.</p>
        <p>"In the Commerce Committee, we pride ourselves on our ability to listen and to make improvements in legislation when called for," he said in a statement. "We should not risk a single American going to the poorhouse just because a spouse or parent had to enter a nursing home."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
