<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Million Man March Puzzles a Houston Suburb</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHANNELVIEW (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D9103EF93AA25753C1A963958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Million Man March Puzzles a Houston Suburb</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
      <dateline>CHANNELVIEW, Tex., Oct. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Get out, get a job, take care of your family, and don't kill people," said Tracie Bratton, offering her own distillation of the theme from the Million Man March in Washington.</p>
        <p>"Now that's a good message," added Mrs. Bratton, who caught grainy glimpses of Monday's huge rally on the small black-and-white television here at Hauck's Hair Haven, a beauty salon where she works. "Who in the world is going to disagree with a message like that? But what I don't understand is, why did they direct it only at black men? I mean, they should have opened it to all men."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Get out, get a job, take care of your family, and don't kill people," said Tracie Bratton, offering her own distillation of the theme from the Million Man March in Washington.</p>
        <p>"Now that's a good message," added Mrs. Bratton, who caught grainy glimpses of Monday's huge rally on the small black-and-white television here at Hauck's Hair Haven, a beauty salon where she works. "Who in the world is going to disagree with a message like that? But what I don't understand is, why did they direct it only at black men? I mean, they should have opened it to all men."</p>
        <p>Like a lot of white people here in this largely white, working-class outpost of the Houston area, the 30-year-old Mrs. Bratton freely admits that there are a lot of things about race relations these days that she just does not understand.</p>
        <p>Not the appeal of Louis Farrakhan, the leader of both the march and the Nation of Islam. Nor the jubilation so many black people seemed to feel at the acquittal of O. J. Simpson. Nor the reason for all those black men to get together and express black pride or black anger or "what, exactly, this rally was supposed to be all about" in Mrs. Bratton's words.</p>
        <p>"It's unnecessary, really," added one of her customers, Anna Baize, 24, a bartender whose hair was wrapped in tight curls for a perm. "I thought all that was over in the 1960's. It's like, get a life."</p>
        <p>No place in America can offer a perfect snapshot of white attitudes about race relations. But this blue-collar town, home to chemical refineries, polyethylene plants and an infamous woman accused of trying to murder the mother of her daughter's chief cheerleading rival a few years back, does offer a look at the gulf suggested in many polls between how many white Americans and black Americans view everything from Mr. Simpson's trial to the need for affirmative action.</p>
        <p>Many white people here, for instance, present it as a matter of indisputable fact that black people can get jobs more easily than whites these days. And while many white residents here went out of their way to express benign sentiments about Monday's rally and its aftermath, many of their comments could be construed as doubled-edged -- patronizing, or worse -- and may thus illustrate the very racial divide that they say should be erased.</p>
        <p>"There could have been a riot," said 36-year-old Julius Honeycutt, a ponytailed man who works as a machine operator at a plastic bottle plant here. "It was a success because nobody got hurt. That's the way I look at it."</p>
        <p>At the lunch break at the construction site for a new high school, a group of white electricians, all from Channelview or nearby towns, found themselves in disagreement over what the march and its message might accomplish.</p>
        <p>"I think it was good," said Tim Savell, 38, an expressive man wearing jeans and work boots, who said he had "no problems" with a blacks-only rally. "The point was, blacks should be more responsible. If they get off welfare, that's going to help all of us out. And let's face it, many of the problems are in black neighborhoods. There are kids in the ghettoes who don't have any fathers. There are high death rates for youths. Drugs. The prisons are full of blacks."</p>
        <p>But Wayne Garrett, 49, said the march was little more than an empty publicity stunt.</p>
        <p>"I'm not sure it's going to change black people at all," he said, shaking his head. "The point was to see how many people they could get together, show how many votes they have.</p>
        <p>"But as soon as they get back home," he continued, "they're going to be back on food stamps, back on welfare. Blacks are always talking about discrimination -- the white man is doing this, the white man is doing that. It's everybody's fault but theirs. I don't think that's going to change."</p>
        <p>Dwayne Phillips, 24, another electrician at the construction site, said he liked the message but was appalled at the chief messenger, Mr. Farrakhan.</p>
        <p>"He's as prejudicial as they come, trashing the Jews and everything," Mr. Phillips said. "They picked the wrong guy. It's like Pee Wee Herman selling Nike shoes or something. That's not going to work. You need a Michael Jordan."</p>
        <p>The other white workers nodded in agreement but quickly fell into dispute over who the best black preacher for black self-reliance would be.  Mr. Phillips suggested the Rev. Jesse Jackson, a choice met with several side-to-side "no" headshakes from colleagues. Gen. Colin L. Powell got a few "yes" nods.</p>
        <p>"Martin Luther King was probably the best man for the job," offered Mr. Savell. "But he's dead."</p>
        <p>Even as speakers and marchers at Monday's rally talked about the lack of economic opportunity for black men, many of the whites here seemed to have a startlingly different view.</p>
        <p>"What makes any of this a black issue?" said Mrs. Bratton, the hairdresser. "There are whites, Chinese, Mexicans that are poor.</p>
        <p>"It's an issue for them -- yes, if not more so than blacks," she said. "If you have three men applying for a job -- a black man, a Hispanic man and a white man -- it's pretty much always going to be the black man gets the job because he's black. Don't ask me who made the rules. That just seems to be the way it is these days."</p>
        <p>Miss Baize, her customer, also said she detected a racially tinged double standard in the fact that the blacks-only rally even took place on public property.</p>
        <p>"If a white man had led a rally like this, people would have had a fit," she said. "In fact, it wouldn't have been allowed. Black men have a rally, and it's all about black pride. But if whites had a rally, it'd be, 'Uh-oh, it's the Ku Klux Klan.' "</p>
        <p>Although only 15 miles from Houston, which is a racially mixed city and the country's fourth largest, Channelview is an insular world of tidy ranch houses and mobile homes.</p>
        <p>It has been the scene of calamities -- a compressor explosion at a chemical plant that killed 17 people in 1990, and the floods and fires that seemed to bring literal hell and high water to the town a year ago -- that have served, people here say with a touch of pride, to make the community all the more tight-knit.</p>
        <p>But in some ways, the sense of detachment here made Monday's march of hundreds of thousands of black men seem all the more remote, a bit like watching a lunar landing on television.</p>
        <p>Many here said they did not quite "get it" when asked what the rally was all about, and others watched the rally or news accounts of it with suspicion, amusement or total disinterest. Some said they knew absolutely nothing about the rally until asked about it by a reporter.</p>
        <p>"I've been working 12-hour shifts," said Mike Meek, an electrician. "I haven't heard a thing about it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
