<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apple's Income For Quarter Falls 47.6%</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">APPLE COMPUTER INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLYNN, LAURIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DE1139F93AA25753C1A963958260" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple's Income For Quarter Falls 47.6%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FLYNN, LAURIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Capping a strenuous year of slipping market share and an inability to meet demand for its most popular products, Apple Computer Inc. reported yesterday that its earnings fell 47.6 percent in its fiscal fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The results were below Wall Street's expectations for a quarter that Apple's  chief executive, Michael H. Spindler, had called the company's most difficult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Capping a strenuous year of slipping market share and an inability to meet demand for its most popular products, Apple Computer Inc. reported yesterday that its earnings fell 47.6 percent in its fiscal fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>The results were below Wall Street's expectations for a quarter that Apple's  chief executive, Michael H. Spindler, had called the company's most difficult.</p>
        <p>But there were some positive signs in the financial results of Apple, which  has been undergoing a well-publicized and painful transition the last few months. The company impressed analysts with a 20 percent increase in revenues during the quarter. And it said demand for its products was higher than ever, with shipments rising more than 25 percent from a year earlier, to more than 1.25 million units.</p>
        <p>"I guess I'm a little surprised," said John T. Rossi, an analyst at Robertson, Stephens in San Francisco. "But it appears there's an organizational  awareness about what they need to do next."</p>
        <p>Still, Wall Street's initial reaction was negative. Apple's earnings were released after the stock market closed, and its stock ended regular Nasdaq trading at $37.375, up 75 cents. But in after-hours trading, Apple's shares fell about $2.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended Sept. 29, Apple's net income totaled $60.1 million, or  48 cents a share, compared with $114.7 million, or 95 cents a share, a year ago. Wall Street had been expecting about 52 cents a share in the latest quarter, according to a survey of 25 analysts by IBES International Inc.</p>
        <p>Revenue rose to $3 billion, from $2.5 billion.</p>
        <p>For fiscal 1995, Apple reported net income rose 36.8 percent, to $424.2 million, or $3.45 a share. Revenues rose 20.4 percent, to $11.1 billion.</p>
        <p>The company attributed a decline in operating income to lower gross margins as a percentage of sales. In the fourth quarter, gross margins were only 20.7 percent of net sales, compared with 27.2 percent a year ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spindler told computer industry analysts in a conference call yesterday that the company would continue its strategy of lowering prices to compete better with PC's from rivals like the Compaq Computer Corporation. Apple continues to battle a long-standing reputation for having higher prices, Mr. Rossi said.</p>
        <p>"They're going to do a balancing act," Mr. Rossi said. "They've got to change the business model while not throwing things topsy-turvy."</p>
        <p>Apple's stock has been under pressure for months after reaching a 52-week high of $50.125 in June. Over the summer, the stock lost nearly 30 percent of its value on news that the company continued to face shortages of key parts, like custom ASIC chips used in many of its more powerful PowerMac models aimed at businesses.</p>
        <p>Because its computers do not conform to the industry standards, Apple feels the effect of component shortages more severely than other computer makers do. In June, Apple's unfilled orders reached a staggering $1 billion.</p>
        <p>Apple is also facing renewed competition in the PC market after Microsoft's $200 million advertising campaign to promote its Windows 95 software, which functions as the brains of computers from Apple's competitors.</p>
        <p>The earnings report yesterday came just two weeks after Apple announced the resignation of Joseph A. Graziano, who as executive vice president and chief financial officer was considered Apple's No. 2 executive. Mr. Graziano lost in an apparent power struggle with Mr. Spindler, in which Mr. Spindler got a vote of confidence from Apple's board for his efforts to turn the company around.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graziano was reportedly urging the board to find a buyer for Apple, arguing that the company could no longer survive independently and that its market share would continue to decline. According to Infocorp, a market research firm, Apple's share of the personal computer market has already fallen to a projected 7.2 percent in 1995 from 8.2 percent in 1993. For his part, Mr. Spindler has said he is not interested in seeking a buyer and that the worst is  over.</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
