<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton to Name Republican To Aid in Selling Trade Pact</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="632237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KANTOR, MICKEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENZEL, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DB1F39F930A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton to Name Republican To Aid in Selling Trade Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration plans to announce on Friday that William Frenzel, a former 10-term Republican Representative from Minnesota, will join the White House campaign for Congressional approval of the North American Free Trade Agreement, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>Mickey Kantor, the United States Trade Representative, said at a news conference today that the long-expected announcement of a Republican advocate for the agreement would be made on Friday. Other White House officials said the Administration had selected Mr. Frenzel, who served in the House from 1971 to 1991, including 15 years on the Ways and Means Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration plans to announce on Friday that William Frenzel, a former 10-term Republican Representative from Minnesota, will join the White House campaign for Congressional approval of the North American Free Trade Agreement, White House officials said today.</p>
        <p>Mickey Kantor, the United States Trade Representative, said at a news conference today that the long-expected announcement of a Republican advocate for the agreement would be made on Friday. Other White House officials said the Administration had selected Mr. Frenzel, who served in the House from 1971 to 1991, including 15 years on the Ways and Means Committee.</p>
        <p>If approved by the House and Senate, the agreement would gradually eliminate trade and investment barriers among Canada, Mexico and the United States over the next 15 years. Ad Campaign Against Pact</p>
        <p>On the other side of the issue, a coalition of labor, environmental and consumer groups, announced that it would begin broadcasting radio advertisements against the trade agreement in 13 states on Labor Day weekend.</p>
        <p>According to a script made public this evening by the coalition, the Citizens Trade Campaign, the advertisements begin with the sound of a busy factory slowing to a halt. "This is the sound of factories across America if the NAFTA trade deal becomes law," says an announcer.</p>
        <p>The background sound track for the advertisement then changes, according to the script, to "Industrial sounds, voices shouting to one another in Spanish -- subtle level."</p>
        <p>The announcer then warns, "And this is the sound of new factories in Mexico -- dirty, often toxic work sites that pay $5 a day." The announcer urges listeners to call their representatives to criticize the trade pact.</p>
        <p>Representative Robert T. Matsui, the California Democrat who is leading advocates of the agreement, said, "These radio ads are full of distortions -- this agreement is going to produce jobs."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frenzel, 65, specialized in trade issues during his years on the Ways and Means Committee, and espoused free trade. He is now a guest scholar in governmental studies at the Brookings Institution. Kantor Criticizes Perot Book</p>
        <p>President Clinton announced on Aug. 19 that William M. Daley, a Chicago banker and brother of the city's Mayor, Richard M. Daley, would head an interagency task force to seek House and Senate approval of the agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kantor held a news conference today to criticize a new book, "Save Your Job, Save Our Country" (Hyperion). The book, by Ross Perot and Pat Choate, a Washington author and economist, contends that the trade pact would send thousands of American jobs to Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kantor said the book included at least 193 statements that were misleading or inaccurate. Mr. Choate said in a telephone interview today that while a few dates might be wrong and would be corrected in later editions, most of the statements reflected a disagreement with the Administration over interpretation of the complex agreement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
