<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB133DF937A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="362" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: * A&amp;B Hawaii Inc., a subsidiary of Alexander &amp; Baldwin Inc., Honolulu, an ocean transportation company, closed the purchases last week of four commercial properties for a total of almost $55.9 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: * A&amp;B Hawaii Inc., a subsidiary of Alexander &amp; Baldwin Inc., Honolulu, an ocean transportation company, closed the purchases last week of four commercial properties for a total of almost $55.9 million.</p>
        <p>* A&amp;B Hawaii Inc., a subsidiary of Alexander &amp; Baldwin Inc., Honolulu, an ocean transportation company, closed the purchases last week of four commercial properties for a total of almost $55.9 million.</p>
        <p>* ADT Ltd., Hamilton, Bermuda, a security company, said Laidlaw Inc. had raised its stake in ADT to 28.8 percent, or 284.6 million common shares, from 27.7 percent previously.</p>
        <p>* Avalon Corp., New York, a developer of oil and gas reserves, said it had sold 70 percent of its U.S. oil and natural gas assets to J.N. Exploration and Production L.P., Billings, Mont., for $13.6 million plus future payments contingent on the cash flow generated by the properties.</p>
        <p>* Cincinnati Bell Inc., Cincinnati, a holding company, said its marketing services subsidiary, Matrixx Marketing Inc., had acquired majority ownership of two telemarketing agencies in Paris for about $39 million.</p>
        <p>* Ivax Corp., Miami, Fla., a pharmaceutical company, said it would acquire all of the outstanding shares of Harris Pharmaceuticals Ltd., of London and Waterford, Ireland, a manufacturer and marketer of generic pharmaceutical products, in exchange for 6,250,000 shares of its common stock.</p>
        <p>* Lone Star Technologies Inc., Dallas, a holding company, said its Lone Star Steel Company had filed a reorganization plan in the U.S. Bankruptcy Court.</p>
        <p>* Meredith Corp., Des Moines, a publishing company, said its directors had authorized the repurchase of one million of its 18.5 million shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>* Pool Energy Services Co., Houston, an oil field equipment rental company, said it had entered into a non-binding agreement in principle to sell its oil tools operations to a foreign company controlled by investors in Malaysia and Indonesia, for about $24.5 million.</p>
        <p>* S. E. Nichols Inc., New York, an operator of discount stores in the Northeast, said it had filed for Chapter 11 protection in Federal Bankruptcy Court in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>* Tyco Laboratories, Exeter, N.H., a fire-protection company, said it had completed the previously announced acquisition of all the operating assets of Wormald International Ltd., Australia, in a transaction valued in excess of $600 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
