<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Roll-Call on Rights Bill</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">QUOTAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HIRING AND PROMOTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AFFIRMATIVE ACTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D7153DF937A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1306" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Roll-Call on Rights Bill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Following is the roll-call vote of 272 to 154 by which the House of Representatives today approved a civil rights bill to combat job discrimination. A yes vote was a vote to pass the bill. Voting yes were 240 Democrats and 32 Republicans. Voting no were 12 Democrats and 142 Republicans. X denotes those not voting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Following is the roll-call vote of 272 to 154 by which the House of Representatives today approved a civil rights bill to combat job discrimination. A yes vote was a vote to pass the bill. Voting yes were 240 Democrats and 32 Republicans. Voting no were 12 Democrats and 142 Republicans. X denotes those not voting.</p>
        <p>Following is the roll-call vote of 272 to 154 by which the House of Representatives today approved a civil rights bill to combat job discrimination. A yes vote was a vote to pass the bill. Voting yes were 240 Democrats and 32 Republicans. Voting no were 12 Democrats and 142 Republicans. X denotes those not voting. There are two vacancies in the 435-member House.</p>
        <p>ALABAMA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Bevill, Y; Browder, Y; Erdreich, Y; Flippo, Y; Harris, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Callahan, N; Dickinson, N.</p>
        <p>ALASKA</p>
        <p>Republican - Young, N.</p>
        <p>ARIZONA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Udall, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Kolbe, N; Kyl, N; Rhodes, N; Stump, N.</p>
        <p>ARKANSAS</p>
        <p>Democrats - Alexander, Y; Anthony, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Robinson, X; Hammerschmidt, N.</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Anderson, Y; Bates, Y; Beilenson, Y; Berman, Y; Bosco, Y; Boxer, Y; Brown, Y; Condit, Y; Dellums, Y; Dixon, Y; Dymally, Y; Edwards, Y; Fazio, Y; Hawkins, Y; Lantos, Y; Lehman, Y; Levine, Y; Martinez, Y; Matsui, Y; Miller, Y; Mineta, Y; Panetta, Y; Pelosi, Y; Roybal, Y; Stark, Y; Torres, Y; Waxman, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Campbell, Y; Cox, N; Dannemeyer, N; Dornan, N; Dreier, N; Gallegly, N; Herger, N; Hunter, N; Lagomarsino, N; Lewis, N; Lowery, N; McCandless, N; Moorhead, N; Packard, N; Pashayan, N; Rohrabacher, N; Shumway, N; Thomas, N.</p>
        <p>COLORADO</p>
        <p>Democrats - Campbell, Y; Schroeder, Y; Skaggs, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Brown, N; Hefley, N; Schaefer, N.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>Democrats - Gejdenson, Y; Kennelly, Y; Morrison, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Johnson, Y; Rowland, Y; Shays, Y.</p>
        <p>DELAWARE</p>
        <p>Democrat - Carper, Y.</p>
        <p>FLORIDA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Bennett, Y; Fascell, Y; Gibbons, Y; Hutto, N; Johnston, Y; Lehman, Y; Nelson, X; Smith, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Bilirakis, X; Goss, N; Grant, Y; Ireland, N; James, Y; Lewis, N; McCollum, N; Ros-Lehtinen, Y; Shaw, N; Stearns, N; Young, N.</p>
        <p>GEORGIA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Barnard, N; Darden, N; Hatcher, Y; Jenkins, N; Jones, Y; Lewis, Y; Ray, Y; Rowland, Y; Thomas, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Gingrich, N.</p>
        <p>HAWAII</p>
        <p>Republican - Saiki, Y.</p>
        <p>IDAHO</p>
        <p>Democrat - Stallings, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Craig, N.</p>
        <p>ILLINOIS</p>
        <p>Democrats - Annunzio, N; Bruce, Y; Collins, Y; Costello, Y; Durbin, Y; Evans, Y; Hayes, Y; Lipinski, N; Poshard, Y; Rostenkowski, Y; Russo, Y; Sangmeister, Y; Savage, Y; Yates, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Crane, N; Fawell, N; Hastert, N; Hyde, N; Madigan, N; Martin, Y; Michel, N; Porter, N.</p>
        <p>INDIANA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Hamilton, Y; Jacobs, Y; Jontz, Y; Long, Y; McCloskey, Y; Sharp, Y; Visclosky, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Burton, N; Hiler, N; Myers, N.</p>
        <p>IOWA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Nagle, Y; Smith, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Grandy, N; Leach, Y; Lightfoot, N; Tauke, N.</p>
        <p>KANSAS</p>
        <p>Democrats - Glickman, Y; Slattery, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Meyers, Y; Roberts, N; Whittaker, N.</p>
        <p>KENTUCKY</p>
        <p>Democrats - Hubbard, Y; Mazzoli, Y; Natcher, Y; Perkins, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Bunning, N; Hopkins, N; Rogers, N.</p>
        <p>LOUISIANA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Boggs, Y; Hayes, Y; Huckaby, N; Tauzin, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Baker, N; Holloway, N; Livingston, N; McCrery, N.</p>
        <p>MAINE</p>
        <p>Democrat - Brennan, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Snowe, Y.</p>
        <p>MARYLAND</p>
        <p>Democrats - Byron, Y; Cardin, Y; Dyson, Y; Hoyer, Y; McMillen, Y; Mfume, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Bentley, N; Morella, Y.</p>
        <p>MASSACHUSETTS</p>
        <p>Democrats - Atkins, Y; Donnelly, Y; Early, Y; Frank, Y; Kennedy, Y; Markey, Y; Mavroules, Y; Moakley, Y; Neal, Y; Studds, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Conte, Y. MICHIGAN</p>
        <p>Democrats - Bonior, Y; Carr, Y; Conyers, Y; Crockett, Y; Dingell, Y; Ford, X; Hertel, Y; Kildee, Y; Levin, Y; Traxler, Y; Wolpe, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Broomfield, N; Davis, Y; Henry, N; Pursell, N; Schuette, N; Upton, N; Vander Jagt, N.</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Oberstar, Y; Penny, Y; Sabo, Y; Sikorski, Y; Vento, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Frenzel, N; Stangeland, N; Weber, N.</p>
        <p>MISSISSIPPI</p>
        <p>Democrats - Espy, Y; Montgomery, N; Parker, N; Taylor, N; Whitten, Y.</p>
        <p>MISSOURI</p>
        <p>Democrats - Clay, Y; Gephardt, Y; Skelton, Y; Volkmer, Y; Wheat, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Buechner, N; Coleman, N; Emerson, N; Hancock, N.</p>
        <p>MONTANA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Williams, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Marlenee, N.</p>
        <p>NEBRASKA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Hoagland, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Bereuter, N; Smith, N.</p>
        <p>NEVADA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Bilbray, Y.</p>
        <p>Republican - Vucanovich, N.</p>
        <p>NEW HAMPSHIRE</p>
        <p>Republicans - Douglas, N; Smith, N.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>Democrats - Dwyer, Y; Guarini, Y; Hughes, Y; Pallone, Y; Payne, Y; Roe, Y; Torricelli, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Courter, N; Gallo, N; Rinaldo, Y; Roukema, Y; Saxton, N; Smith, N.</p>
        <p>NEW MEXICO</p>
        <p>Democrat - Richardson, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Schiff, Y; Skeen, N.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Democrats - Ackerman, Y; Downey, Y; Engel, Y; Flake, Y; Hochbrueckner, Y; LaFalce, Y; Lowey, Y; Manton, Y; McHugh, Y; McNulty, Y; Mrazek, Y; Nowak, Y; Owens, Y; Rangel, Y; Scheuer, Y; Schume, Y; Serrano, Y; Slaughter, Y; Solarz, Y; Towns, Y; Weiss, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Boehlert, Y; Fish, Y; Gilman, Y; Green, Y; Horton, Y; Houghton, N; Lent, N; Martin, N; McGrath, N; Molinari, N; Paxon, N; Solomon, N; Walsh, Y.</p>
        <p>ORTH CAROLINA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Clarke, Y; Hefner, Y; Jones, Y; Lancaster, Y; Neal, Y; Price, Y; Rose, Y; Valentine, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Ballenger, N; Coble, N; McMillan, N.</p>
        <p>NORTH DAKOTA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Dorgan, Y.</p>
        <p>OHIO</p>
        <p>Democrats - Applegate, Y; Eckart, Y; Feighan, Y; Hall, Y; Kaptur, Y; Luken, Y; Oakar, Y; Pease, Y; Sawyer, Y; Stokes, Y; Traficant, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - DeWine, N; Gillmor, N; Gradison, N; Kasich, N; Lukens, N; McEwen, N; Miller, N; Oxley, N; Regula, Y; Wylie, N.</p>
        <p>OKLAHOMA</p>
        <p>Democrats - English, Y; McCurdy, Y; Synar, Y; Watkins, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Edwards, N; Inhofe, N.</p>
        <p>OREGON</p>
        <p>Democrats - AuCoin, Y; DeFazio, Y; Wyden, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - D. Smith, N; R. Smith, N.</p>
        <p>PENNSYLVANIA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Borski, Y; Coyne, Y; Foglietta, Y; Gaydos, Y; Gray, Y; Kanjorski, Y; Kolter, Y; Kostmayer, Y; Murphy, Y; Murtha, Y; Walgren, Y; Yatron, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Clinger, N; Coughlin, Y; Gekas, N; Goodling, N; McDade, N; Ridge, N; Ritter, N; Schulze, Y; Shuster, N; Walker, N; Weldon, Y.</p>
        <p>RHODE ISLAND</p>
        <p>Republicans - Machtley, Y; Schneider, Y.</p>
        <p>SOUTH CAROLINA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Derrick, Y; Patterson, Y; Spratt, Y; Tallon, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Ravenel, N; Spence, N.</p>
        <p>SOUTH DAKOTA</p>
        <p>Democrat - Johnson, Y.</p>
        <p>TENNESSEE</p>
        <p>Democrats - Clement, Y; Cooper, Y; Ford, Y; Gordon, Y; Lloyd, Y; Tanner, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Duncan, N; Quillen, N; Sundquist, N.</p>
        <p>TEXAS</p>
        <p>Democrats - Andrews, Y; Brooks, Y; Bryant, Y; Bustamante, Y; Chapman, Y; Coleman, Y; de la Garza, Y; Frost, Y; Geren, Y; Gonzalez, Y; Hall, X; Laughlin, Y; Leath, X; Ortiz, Y; Pickle, Y; Sarpalius, N; Stenholm, N; Washington, Y; Wilson, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Archer, N; Armey, N; Bartlett, N; Barton, Y; Combest, N; DeLay, N; Fields, N; Smith, N.</p>
        <p>UTAH</p>
        <p>Democrat - Owens, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Hansen, N; Nielson, N.</p>
        <p>VERMONT</p>
        <p>Republican - Smith, Y.</p>
        <p>VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Boucher, Y; Olin, Y; Payne, Y; Pickett, Y; Sisisky, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Bateman, N; Bliley, N; Parris, N; Slaughter, N; Wolf, N.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Democrats - Dicks, Y; Foley, X (by tradition, the Speaker seldom votes); McDermott, Y; Swift, Y; Unsoeld, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Chandler, N; Miller, N; Morrison, N.</p>
        <p>WEST VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Democrats - Mollohan, Y; Rahall, Y; Staggers, Y; Wise, Y.</p>
        <p>WISCONSIN</p>
        <p>Democrats - Aspin, Y; Kastenmeier, Y; Kleczka, Y; Moody, Y; Obey, Y.</p>
        <p>Republicans - Gunderson, N; Petri, N; Roth, N; Sensenbrenner, N.</p>
        <p>WYOMING</p>
        <p>Republican - Thomas, N.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
