<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="373617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD173CF937A3575BC0A966958260" item-length="1326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-7</p>
        <p>Iraqi forces wheeled into position for a possible attack on Saudi Arabia, while the U.S. and its allies continued to search without success for a way to force Iraq to pull back from its rapid conquest of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Iraq has deployed armored brigades close to the Saudi border and poured reinforcements into occupied Kuwait, Pentagon officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-7</p>
        <p>Iraqi forces wheeled into position for a possible attack on Saudi Arabia, while the U.S. and its allies continued to search without success for a way to force Iraq to pull back from its rapid conquest of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Iraq has deployed armored brigades close to the Saudi border and poured reinforcements into occupied Kuwait, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-7</p>
        <p>Iraqi forces wheeled into position for a possible attack on Saudi Arabia, while the U.S. and its allies continued to search without success for a way to force Iraq to pull back from its rapid conquest of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>Iraq has deployed armored brigades close to the Saudi border and poured reinforcements into occupied Kuwait, Pentagon officials said. The deployments heightened concern that the Iraqi President might be contemplating an attack on Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Americans in the capital of Kuwait told of a modern city transformed overnight into a war zone by Iraqi invaders who seized Government buildings, commandeered police cars and chatted on street corners as residents cowered behind locked doors.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>U.S. oil workers missing; some believed to be in Iraqi hands</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>News analysis: The crisis in the Persian Gulf appears to be turning into a struggle between the United States and Iraq for influence over Saudi Arabia and its oil reserves.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A summit meeting in Saudi Arabia this weekend was arranged to deal with Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and King Hussein of Jordan, along with King Fahd of Saudi Arabia, played leading roles in the agreement.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>The United Nations Security Council was asked by Washington to endorse its proposal for a worldwide economic boycott of Iraq until Baghdad agrees to withdraw its military forces from Kuwait.</p>
        <p>6 The Soviet Union and the U.S. joined in urging a worldwide halt in arms deliveries to Iraq after what they called ''the brutal and illegal invasion of Kuwait.''</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>The stock market fell sharply in unusually volatile trading as investors feared that higher energy prices brought on by the turmoil in the Middle East could push an American economy that is already weak into recession. Oil prices rose again.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Uncertainties are intensified for U.S. policy makers</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>National elections in the Germanys will be held on Oct. 14, seven weeks earlier than previously proposed. Leaders in Bonn and East Berlin changed the date to speed up the formal unification of Germany.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Hungary affirms a new president</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Talks between Tokyo and Moscow this week failed to narrow the countries' differences on a 45-year territorial dispute that has stood in the way of their improving relations.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Bhutto must now confront foes on volatile issue of religion</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Iran sees time nearing for new ties to Britain</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Bombs in South Lebanon kill 11 and wound 80</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Fighting worsens in Liberia capital</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>As India opens its economy, some cling to socialist ideals</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Subic Bay Journal: American might is a bit high and mighty</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>8-12, 24</p>
        <p>The nation's unemployment rate climbed three-tenths of a point in July, to 5.5 percent, as the ranks of employed Americans thinned substantially, the Labor Department reported. It was the biggest increase since early 1986.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A civil rights bill was approved by the House, despite threats by President Bush to veto the measure, which he contends would lead to job quotas for women and minorities.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>An AIDS bill was approved by House and Senate negotiators. The measure permits the spending of $875 million next year to provide health care to people with AIDS in cities and states hardest hit by the epidemic.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The rising costs of campaigns for Congress would be slowed under a bill passed by the House after a rancorous debate. Lawmakers rejected pleas from colleagues in both parties that they not move so fast on legislation that would affect their re-election drives.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>G.O.P. candidates in close race to face Gore for Senate seat</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>A policy banning most abortions at American military hospitals overseas was upheld by the Senate. Lawmakers, pushing to complete action on a military programs bill, rejected an amendment that would have overturned the policy.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Rep. Pete Stark apologized for calling the Secretary of Health and Human Services ''a disgrace to his race'' when he criticized the Secretary's policies on Thursday.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Jury in Barry trial meets; reaches no verdict</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Ex-civic leader is jailed in drug smuggling</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Newly arrived illegal immigrants in the U.S. have no trouble buying fake documents and using them to find jobs. That has become one of the most pressing problems Government officials face as they try to enforce the nation's 1986 immigration law.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>A candidate for governor of Texas, Clayton Williams, a Republican, has launched a series of pre-emptive strikes against his Democratic rival, Ann Richards.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>25-28</p>
        <p>New York City transit police officers will be allowed to carry a more powerful handgun that has long been resisted in the city because of its possible danger to the public, transit police officials announced.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Memorials have been springing up across New York City where people have been taken suddenly - but all too routinely - in violent death. They silently counter the notion that life means little in neighborhoods where crime is a constant.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Violence, Irish and American style</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Inquiry in L.I. bomb killing still centers on officer</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>To village's disbelief, farmer is indicted in brother's death</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Covenant House released a report saying complaints about sexual contacts between the Rev. Bruce Ritter and residents at Covenant House were circulating for close to 20 years and were referred to senior staff members at least twice.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Harry Macklowe has opened a hotel near Times Square. He hopes his stature will soar with the elegant, 38-story building. In an industry that many people love to hate, no developer's reputation has needed more rehabilitation in recent years than Mr. Macklowe's.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Borough chief dooms Audubon Ballroom project</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Pierre Rinfret reneged on a promise to release eight years of tax returns, releasing instead only his returns for 1989. Among the deductions taken by Mr. Rinfret, the Republican candidate for governor of New York, was for interest paid on a yacht.</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>Fuel emergency for Avianca jet said to be premature</p>
        <p>26 Business Digest</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Prosecutor asked Dowd to wait</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Mets top Cardinals</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Yanks foil another no-hitter</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Tax questions raised on Steinbrenner</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Rose and Hall of Fame</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Golf: PGA Tour tightens site policy</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Football: Giants have contingency for Bavaro</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Horse Racing: To Freedom wins</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Thomas M. Macioce, lawyer</p>
        <p>Lucy Goldschmidt Moses, philanthropist</p>
        <p>Consumer's World</p>
        <p>48</p>
        <p>F.D.A. and a dangerous diet pill</p>
        <p>Preventing mortgage foreclosures</p>
        <p>Coping with household products</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Arts advisers oppose pledge</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Music: Santa Fe ''Boheme</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>City Opera's ''Butterfly''</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Lee Konitz improvises</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Dance: Serious Fun ends</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Books: Kapek centenary</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Covering Iraq's invasion</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Sense and senseless crime</p>
        <p>America's English disease</p>
        <p>Workers' Compensation</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: Fruit of appeasement</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Huzzahs for George</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Kemp: Why Iraq's move may backfire</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Peter M. Herford: In news, public choice is a disaster</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>David Ortiz: Let islanders decide Puerto Rico's fate</p>
        <p>23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
