<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leetch Studies His Role In the Rangers' Decline</title>
    <meta content="Y03RANG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1189039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leetch, Brian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDE1F3CF930A35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leetch Studies His Role In the Rangers' Decline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers captain Brian Leetch discusses team's disappointing season and failure to qualify for playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brian Leetch is three games removed from some much-needed closure to one of the most frustrating seasons of his career. Few would question his credentials as the Rangers' best player. After 13 seasons, Leetch is still a member of the National Hockey League's defensive elite.</p>
        <p>But this has been Leetch's roughest season since 1992-93, when he played just 36 games because of a neck injury and then a broken right ankle, which ended both his season and any fleeting playoff hopes the Rangers had.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brian Leetch is three games removed from some much-needed closure to one of the most frustrating seasons of his career. Few would question his credentials as the Rangers' best player. After 13 seasons, Leetch is still a member of the National Hockey League's defensive elite.</p>
        <p>But this has been Leetch's roughest season since 1992-93, when he played just 36 games because of a neck injury and then a broken right ankle, which ended both his season and any fleeting playoff hopes the Rangers had.</p>
        <p>This season, Leetch missed 32 games because of a broken right forearm. His seven goals are the fewest he has scored since 1992-93, and his 25 points are the fewest of any full season of his career. And the Rangers, who play their final road game of the season against the Washington Capitals on Monday night, were officially eliminated from playoff contention with their 2-2 tie in Boston on Saturday afternoon.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers played some of their best hockey this season with Leetch out of the lineup, which was not the case in 1992-93. Leetch had to watch the Rangers turn their season around without him, and then they slipped back to their early-season level of play after his return.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' disintegration can be traced to Mike Richter's torn anterior cruciate ligament in his left knee, sustained during the All-Star Game activities, rather than to Leetch's return to the lineup two games later. The Rangers were 16-11-5 without Leetch this season, though, and 13-27-7 with him.</p>
        <p>When asked why he has been so hard on himself, Leetch's reply was to the point.</p>
        <p>''Because it's been a long year with me being in the lineup for only 13 wins,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Rangers have not qualified for the playoffs in Leetch's three seasons as captain. Some believe that is a coincidence. And it is hard to blame him for the Rangers' inability to find him a steady defensive partner this season.</p>
        <p>But the captaincy that Leetch inherited from his close friend and mentor, Mark Messier, who left the Rangers after the 1996-97 season, may weigh heavily upon Leetch.</p>
        <p>One theory is that by going back to his role as an alternate captain, Leetch could concentrate solely on the game at hand and lead by example with his play.</p>
        <p>Leetch, who chooses his words carefully, will have none of the speculation that he might be better off leaving the captaincy to someone else, however.</p>
        <p>''When we win, everything will be fine,'' Leetch said after a brief practice session this afternoon. ''That's the bottom line. There's no use coming in and talking about it. It does no good.''</p>
        <p>A little time off to rid the taste of this season may do Leetch some good, however. His wife, Mary Beth, is expecting their first child at the end of this month. and he will experience a new beginning of sorts.</p>
        <p>That is something he could use after what has transpired this season.</p>
        <p>''When I got hurt, it was no fun watching,'' Leetch said. ''And then it was sort of exciting, working out, knowing that I was coming back to a positive situation.''</p>
        <p>That situation quickly unraveled once Richter hurt his knee. More times than ever before, Leetch -- whose plus-minus rating is a minus-13, has had to come out after a loss and answer the same questions about what went wrong.</p>
        <p>This season has worn on Leetch, who holds himself personally responsible for every loss.</p>
        <p>''I should hope that's how everyone feels about themselves,'' Leetch said. ''And about what could be done differently to make the situation better.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
