<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hunt Oil Is Thwarted in a Canadian Hostile-Takeover Attempt</title>
    <meta content="Y18OIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000419T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ulster Petroleums Ltd</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hunt Oil Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anderson Exploration Ltd</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pritchard, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEEDB1531F93BA25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hunt Oil Is Thwarted in a Canadian Hostile-Takeover Attempt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY PRITCHARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pritchard, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ulster Petroleums Ltd of Calgary foils hostile takeover attempt by Hunt Oil Co of Dallas, agreeing to richer offer from Anderson Exploration; Ulster accepts $45 million offer in cash and stock from Anderson, one of Canada's largest and most profitable independent oil-exploration companies; price is 19 percent higher than $350 million in cash that privately owned Hunt had offered on April 5 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ulster Petroleums Ltd. of Calgary foiled a hostile takeover attempt by the Hunt Oil Company of Dallas today, agreeing to a richer offer from a crosstown rival, Anderson Exploration.</p>
        <p>In the latest of a spree of takeover deals to have swept through Canada's energy industry, Ulster accepted a $45 million offer in cash and stock from Anderson, one of the country's largest and most profitable independent oil-exploration companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ulster Petroleums Ltd. of Calgary foiled a hostile takeover attempt by the Hunt Oil Company of Dallas today, agreeing to a richer offer from a crosstown rival, Anderson Exploration.</p>
        <p>In the latest of a spree of takeover deals to have swept through Canada's energy industry, Ulster accepted a $45 million offer in cash and stock from Anderson, one of the country's largest and most profitable independent oil-exploration companies.</p>
        <p>The price is 19 percent higher than the $350 million in cash that the privately owned Hunt had offered on April 5. Anderson will match the 11 Canadian dollars in cash that Hunt bid for each Ulster share, plus one-tenth of an Anderson share, for a total of 13.10 Canadian dollars, or $8.81, a share. Ulster stock rose nearly 12 percent on the news today, to 12.70 Canadian dollars. Anderson fell 8 percent, to 20 Canadian dollars.</p>
        <p>Ulster has been on the block since the beginning of the year. Anderson began its evaluation in mid-February and was about to negotiate a friendly takeover when Hunt made a surprise bid. Ulster shares were trading for less than 8 Canadian dollars at the time.</p>
        <p>Under terms of the agreement announced today, Anderson has the right to offer a higher price if any other bids are made. It will also collect 30 million Canadian dollars if the purchase does not go through.</p>
        <p>The acquisition of Ulster is expected to increase Anderson's production volume 28 percent. Last year, it reported a profit of 71 million Canadian dollars on revenue of 800 million Canadian dollars. Revenue grew 17 percent and profit almost tripled.</p>
        <p>Although Anderson will have to tap into a new $620 million line of credit for the acquisition, Ulster is a good strategic fit, company officials and analysts said. Not only is it primarily a gas producer, like Anderson, but most of its output comes from properties that are adjacent to Anderson's.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS  Correction:  April 19, 2000, Wednesday  Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about an agreement by Anderson Exploration Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, to buy Ulster Petroleums Ltd., also of Calgary, misstated the price. It is $445 million, not $45 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 19, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day yesterday about an agreement by Anderson Exploration Ltd. of Calgary, Alberta, to buy Ulster Petroleums Ltd., also of Calgary, misstated the price. It is $445 million, not $45 million.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
