<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Savings Bailout Irks State Officials</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings and Loan Associations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC1E30F932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Savings Bailout Irks State Officials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: REPORTS that the Federal cleanup of the savings and loan disaster will result in Connecticut residents paying $1,237 a person more to rescue the failed thrifts than they will receive in bailout benefits has angered state lawmakers and banking officials, and last week several were looking for ways to offset the situation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: REPORTS that the Federal cleanup of the savings and loan disaster will result in Connecticut residents paying $1,237 a person more to rescue the failed thrifts than they will receive in bailout benefits has angered state lawmakers and banking officials, and last week several were looking for ways to offset the situation.</p>
        <p>REPORTS that the Federal cleanup of the savings and loan disaster will result in Connecticut residents paying $1,237 a person more to rescue the failed thrifts than they will receive in bailout benefits has angered state lawmakers and banking officials, and last week several were looking for ways to offset the situation.</p>
        <p>''We seem to be getting a double whammy,'' said the State Banking Commissioner, Howard B. Brown. Federal regulators have already put severe restrictions on still-solvent Connecticut institutions, he said, resulting in a credit crunch, and now the Federal bailout program will require Connecticut residents to rescue savings and loans in other states.</p>
        <p>''There must be a more equitable manner of dealing with this,'' Mr. Brown said. He said he had already contacted Federal officials about the situation and planned to talk with the Governor's staff to determine what steps the state could take to offset it.</p>
        <p>United States Senators Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of New Haven, and Christopher J. Dodd, Democrat of East Haddam, said they would press for investigations of the savings and loan industry. ''The only way to ameliorate the anger and frustration people in states like Connecticut are feeling,'' said Mr. Dodd, ''is to go after - hammer and tongs - the people who are responsible.''</p>
        <p>Both Senators said they might seek to use the fact that Connecticut will be a big loser under the bailout program as leverage in getting other Federal aid for Connecticut, for housing or transportation or a program to save defense jobs. ''After this, I think they owe us a big one,'' Mr. Lieberman said.  ''There's the matter of equity here,'' he continued. ''There's a transfer of money going on here that is enormous, and one that we cannot afford, because our own economy is vulnerable right now.''</p>
        <p>All taxpayers will pay the same amount under the Government's $203 billion bailout of the savings and loan industry, but many economists and politicians have concluded that it will result in a significant transfer of wealth from the Northeast and Middle West to Texas and other states in the Southwest, where the savings and loan failures are concentrated. This shift, they say, will result in a stronger economy in the Southwest in the years ahead and a weaker economy for most other states.</p>
        <p>But one financial expert said Connecticut should not complain too loudly, because the financial troubles being faced by the state's own savings institutions could result in a number of bailouts here. ''We may end up very happy there is this kind of a rule on the books,'' said Lewis Mandell, a professor of finance at the University of Connecticut who is a consultant for the United States Comptroller of the Currency and is writing an article for Grolier's Encyclopedia on the savings and loan problems. ''All the bailouts aren't over yet, and Connecticut may be in for its share.''</p>
        <p>He noted that the state-chartered Savings Bank of Brooklyn is in serious trouble, and the Community Federal Savings Bank of Bridgeport is on the list of vulnerable institutions compiled by the Resolution Trust Corporation, the Federal agency that is trying to develop plans for troubled savings and loans.</p>
        <p>The savings and loan failures were ''stupid'' and are ''going to be very costly,'' Dr. Mandell said. ''But what is the alternative?'' If the Federal Government does not bail out the banks, the depositors lose their savings, he said, and the real estate speculators would be no worse off than they are now.</p>
        <p>The money to keep the banks solvent will come out of income taxes, and because Connecticut residents earn more, they will pay more. Also, because so few banks have failed in Connecticut - one federally chartered bank closed last November in Meriden but reopened within a week after it was purchased by another bank - few of the dollars paid into the bailout fund will flow back to Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Loss of $1,237 a Person</p>
        <p>An analysis of the plan to save ailing savings and loans around the country, compiled by Prof. Edward W. Hill of Cleveland State University, showed that the net cost per person in Connecticut will be $1,237. In only three other states and the District of Columbia, will the cost exceed $1,000 a person. In all, 37 states will lose money under the bailout plan, and 13, most of them in the Southwest, will gain.</p>
        <p>The biggest winner will be Texas, where the net cash inflow will be $4,775 per person, according to Professor Hill's analysis.</p>
        <p>He estimated a total bailout cost of $203 billion, but Dr. Mandell said it could approach $300 billion, and some say it could go higher than that.</p>
        <p>The problem is particularly troubling, Mr. Brown said, because while Federal regulators are seeking massive amounts of money from Connecticut's economy to pay for the bailout, they are taking steps that will slow the state's economy down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said Federal examiners left the failed savings and loans of Texas and came to Connecticut earlier this year and began imposing strict limits on bad loans.</p>
        <p>Even state-chartered savings institutions have to comply with some Federal regulations, including requirements about reserves. An institution must put some of its surplus or capital into a reserve to cover loans that are not being paid on time and might go into default. Mr. Brown said that before this year, Federal regulators required 35 or 40 percent in reserves, but they have boosted that to about 66 percent.</p>
        <p>Fresh in the Minds</p>
        <p>''The rules are being applied much more stringently in the Northeast than they have been in the past,'' Mr. Brown said. He blamed that on the fact that the Texas disasters were still fresh in the minds of the examiners, and they want to prevent that from happening again in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''Had regulators been doing their job as diligently all along as they are in Connecticut now, none of this would have happened,'' Dr. Mandell said. He said if the first losses in Texas in 1981 and 1982 triggered a similar response, the losses might have been contained to $50 billion.</p>
        <p>''The real scandal is that they took some of the toughest and best administrators and tried to put them in Texas, and the bankers and their politician friends forced them out,'' Dr. Mandell said.</p>
        <p>A result of the new rules on reserves is that banks are showing less of a profit, which is causing their stock prices to plunge. As a result, Mr. Brown said, banks are tightening up credit, so they do not have to put so much into reserves. Lending activity at federally chartered banks in Connecticut has dropped $1.2 billion since last September, while at state-chartered banks, it has dropped about $640 million.</p>
        <p>''The mind set of certain bankers right now is to not make loans, to wait until this blows over,'' Mr. Brown said. Even good credit risks, he said, are finding it difficult to obtain loans.</p>
        <p>''As a regulator I have mixed feelings about all this,'' Mr. Brown said. While he wants to see the banks solvent, he does not want to see the economy choked, he said.</p>
        <p>Reaction of Senators</p>
        <p>But officials said an even larger problem looms, as Federal tax dollars begin to flow out of the state to help failed savings and loans throughout the Southwest.</p>
        <p>''I'm outraged about what happened,'' Senator Lieberman said. ''The numbers of the transfer of money are so galling it leads me to take a look at the formulas involved.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman said there has long been debate about the fact that Connecticut gets back less in Federal aid than its residents pay in taxes. Congressmen from other states point to the fact that Connecticut has long received a disproportionate share of defense spending. But that is because Connecticut workers are skilled, Mr. Lieberman said, ''not because we've had a lot of crooks stealing from our savings and loans.''</p>
        <p>The Senator said he was so concerned about the problem that he submitted legislation that would enable the Secret Service to investigate bank fraud. The Federal Bureau of Investigation is so backlogged, with more than 1,000 cases involving fraud of $100,000 or more, that it would welcome the help, Mr. Lieberman said, and Secret Service officials have told him they could field 100 agents on the cases immediately and another 200 agents during the next 6 to 12 months.</p>
        <p>''We have to do what we can to catch and punish those people who are responsible for this rip-off,'' Mr. Lieberman said. ''And then we have to put a cap on it.''</p>
        <p>His bill was incorporated last week into a bill to stiffen the investigation into savings and loans that was introduced by Senator Joseph M. Biden, Democrat of Maryland, chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee. That should improve its chances of success, Mr. Lieberman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dodd, a member of the Senate Banking Committee, said he would push for a full investigation of the savings and loan industry and its regulators.</p>
        <p>He also said that his ''strong temptation would be to craft some funding scheme to allow states that are paying so much of this money for the savings and loan bailout to get favored treatment for things they need, such as housing and transportation for Connecticut.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''whether or not you can equitably do something like that is another matter.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mandell said that while the cost to Connecticut taxpayers sounds high, it will not have as great an impact as people expect, because the bailout will take place over a long period of time.</p>
        <p>''It'll probably be paid our over 10 years, which amounts to another $100 per person per year,'' Dr. Mandell said. ''That's just a rough number, but that's the magnitude of what we're talking about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
