<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At NOW Convention, Goal Is Putting More Women in Office</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ORGANIZATION FOR WOMEN (NOW)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSS, JANE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YARD, MOLLY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D6113AF932A35754C0A966958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At NOW Convention, Goal Is Putting More Women in Office</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GROSS, JANE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Calling these the best of times and the worst of times, 2,000 delegates to the National Organization for Women gathered here this weekend to rage over recent Supreme Court rulings limiting abortion access and to celebrate a record number of women running for high political office this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Calling these the best of times and the worst of times, 2,000 delegates to the National Organization for Women gathered here this weekend to rage over recent Supreme Court rulings limiting abortion access and to celebrate a record number of women running for high political office this year.</p>
        <p>Calling these the best of times and the worst of times, 2,000 delegates to the National Organization for Women gathered here this weekend to rage over recent Supreme Court rulings limiting abortion access and to celebrate a record number of women running for high political office this year.</p>
        <p>''What's happening to us at the hands of the Reagan court and the Bush Administration is that we're losing fundamental rights as women in this society,'' said Molly Yard, the president of NOW, the nation's largest feminist organization. ''That's a tremendous catalyst for pulling people into the political process. The outrage of women in this country, and the many men who support them, will express itself at the ballot box.''</p>
        <p>In the year since the Supreme Court gave the states new power to restrict abortion, NOW has grown in size and power; its ranks and its annual budget have nearly doubled, to 270,000 members and $10.6 million in donations. These new resources, Ms. Yard said, will be plowed into selected primary and general election campaigns this fall, when 10 women will be running for governor, 7 for the United States Senate and 54 for the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>'Feminization of Power'</p>
        <p>''Some will win this year and more will win in 1992,'' Ms. Yard said, ''and so we are on the way to the feminization of power. We aren't doing well right now, but we are on the threshold of change. Our hope for the future rides on these women who are running.''</p>
        <p>The featured speakers at the annual convention at the Hilton Hotel were several of those women, including Dianne Feinstein, former Mayor of San Francisco, who is the Democratic candidate for governor in California. Ms. Feinstein used her speech to fire the opening salvo in her race against Senator Pete Wilson by itemizing the contradictory positions he has taken on Federal financing for abortion and parental-consent requirements for teen-age girls seeking abortions.</p>
        <p>The California race is considered the most important in the nation because the state will gain at least six Congressional seats with the 1990 census, and the governor has a significant voice in reapportioning the districts.</p>
        <p>Ms. Feinstein, never a favorite of feminists while Mayor, was received with jubilant applause by the NOW delegates, who had withheld an endorsement during her primary race with State Attorney General John Van de Kamp.</p>
        <p>Cheers for Helms's Opponent</p>
        <p>The only candidate here who attracted more adulation than Ms. Feinstein was the only man to address the convention: Harvey Gantt, Jesse Helms's Democratic opponent in the United States Senate race in North Carolina. Mr. Gantt is fervently supported by feminist, gay-rights activists and arts organizations, who say their freedom has been curtailed by bills sponsored Mr. Helms. Mr. Gantt was the main speaker today at an abortion rights rally in Union Square.</p>
        <p>''You make me stronger,'' Mr. Gantt told the cheering women. ''You empower me to go out and challenge those who would repress you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gantt promised support of the Equal Rights Amendment, pay equity for women, abortion rights, family leave and affordable child care.</p>
        <p>In speeches and at workshops, the women here expressed unguarded anger at the most recent Supreme Court rulings regarding abortion, two decisions last week that upheld parental-consent laws in Minnesota and Ohio. They were additionally roused on Friday by President Bush's veto of a bill that would have protected the jobs of those taking time off to care for sick children or parents. That veto followed Mr. Bush's veto of a child care bill.</p>
        <p>''It sounds great to say you're in favor of the family,'' said Barbara Roberts, the Democratic candidate for governor in Oregon. ''But if you don't want to talk about leave and you don't want to talk about child care, what are you pro-family about?''</p>
        <p>Equality of Sexes Stressed</p>
        <p>Ms. Yard and others said they had reluctantly concluded that the Government will be responsive to womens' concerns only when women hold half the positions of power. With that in mind, there was much talk here about ''gender balance,'' one of NOW's longtime tenets and lately the law of the land in Iowa, North Dakota and Delaware, where governors' appointments to boards and commissions have to be divided equally between men and women.</p>
        <p>All the candidates for governor here said they supported ''gender balance,'' which this week became a hot issue in the California race. In an exchange of fax messages, Mr. Wilson accused Ms. Feinstein of supporting ''quotas,'' a buzzword that packs an emotional wallop. Ms. Feinstein replied that balance for men and women and parity for minority members was not a ''quota,'' but rather a ''goal'' to make California's government more reflective of its population.</p>
        <p>Study of New Political Party</p>
        <p>In other action here, Ms. Yard announced the appointment of a 40-member commission to study the possibility of starting a new political party that would include more women and minority members, a notion first advanced at last year's convention.</p>
        <p>The women here also expressed themselves in less formal ways, including changing the signs on restrooms in the section of the hotel where they were meeting. Where once the doors said ''Ladies'' and ''Gentlemen,'' this weekend they all said ''Women,'' a change that no one took credit for but everyone seemed to enjoy, except a handful of men who wandered the corridors, confused and uncomfortable. Had the men ventured into the restroom that was once theirs, they would have found a cozy touch - potted ferns and philodendrons in the urinals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
