<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants' Injuries Create Job Openings</title>
    <meta content="11giants" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/11/sports/football/11giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1803834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Chicago Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chicago Bears</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Strahan, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3D71F3FF932A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants' Injuries Create Job Openings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giants’ Injuries Create Job Openings</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL S. SCHMIDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmidt, Michael S</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants' locker room was a raucous place two days before the team's showdown with the Chicago Bears. Players stole one another's shoes and criticized one another's clothing. The target of most of the jokes was Adrian Awasom, the chubby-faced second-year defensive end out of North Texas.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Awasom was on the practice squad, but when LaVar Arrington was lost for the season with an Achilles' injury and Osi Umenyiora sustained a hip injury against the Cowboys on Oct. 23, Awasom was promoted to the roster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Second-year defensive end Adrian Awasom, who has never started a game in the N.F.L., could replace Michael Strahan on Sunday, who is sidelined two to four weeks with a sprained right foot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants' locker room was a raucous place two days before the team's showdown with the Chicago Bears. Players stole one another's shoes and criticized one another's clothing. The target of most of the jokes was Adrian Awasom, the chubby-faced second-year defensive end out of North Texas.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Awasom was on the practice squad, but when LaVar Arrington was lost for the season with an Achilles' injury and Osi Umenyiora sustained a hip injury against the Cowboys on Oct. 23, Awasom was promoted to the roster.</p>
        <p>Awasom, who has never started a game in the N.F.L., could replace Michael Strahan, who is sidelined two to four weeks with a sprained right foot.</p>
        <p>''We have all of those defensive linemen working together in different spots and that will end up being a game-time decision,'' Coach Tom Coughlin said. ''He is ready to go.''</p>
        <p>Umenyiora and another defensive end, Justin Tuck, will most likely miss the Bears game, along with linebacker Brandon Short (quadriceps). ''I am not worried about the guys that are playing right now,'' Coughlin said. ''We've just got to put the emphasis on those that are playing and make sure they are prepared. They know what they are doing and they know what their responsibilities are.''</p>
        <p>In spite of the injuries -- including wide receiver Amani Toomer (knee), who is out for the season -- the Giants have won five consecutive games and the locker room was upbeat Friday after practice.</p>
        <p>Sitting at his locker, Awasom talked about how he was different from Strahan because he was more of a run stopper then a pass rusher.</p>
        <p>''I am not nervous,'' Awasom said. His neighbor to his right, linebacker Chase Blackburn, interrupted. He gave Awasom a piece of gum, telling him his breath was bad.</p>
        <p>Awasom, who is black, turned around and joked with Blackburn, who is white, saying that he was only on the defense because of ''reverse affirmative action.'' Both laughed.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Awasom was swarmed at his locker by the news media after the announcement that Strahan would miss considerable time.</p>
        <p>As Awasom spoke, Blackburn tried to tame Awasom's small but burgeoning Afro by placing a hat on his head. Awasom refused to wear the hat, telling Blackburn that he looked fine for the cameras and that he was going to have his hair put in cornrows for the Bears game.</p>
        <p>Why was Awasom an easy target for his teammates? ''It all started with us calling him G.I. because all he wears is Giants-issued clothing,'' cornerback Frank Walker said.</p>
        <p>Walker explained that Awasom's wardrobe seemed only to include the T-shirts, sweatpants and sweatshirts the Giants give their players. He jokingly speculated that Awasom was too lazy to buy other clothes.</p>
        <p>Awasom played in only five games last season, mostly on special teams. At the start of this season he was put on the practice squad.</p>
        <p>''I was a little disappointed,'' he said. ''I looked at it as taking a step back. But I know this is a process. I graduated fast. This is the best place to play. They all come with all that ammunition and hate and I throw it right back at them.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Plaxico Burress, who sat out last week's game with back spasms, practiced and will most likely play.  Wide receiver Sinorice Moss (quadriceps) practiced and was listed as questionable.  Linebacker Carlos Emmons (groin muscle) practiced, but his availability was still in doubt.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
