<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Foes for Surgeon General Nominee</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950225T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGEON GENERAL (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYSTERECTOMIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ILLEGITIMACY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACQUIRED IMMUNE DEFICIENCY SYNDROME (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONDOMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PREGNANCY AND OBSTETRICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MENTAL RETARDATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ACT UP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, HENRY W JR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIDEN, JOSEPH R JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Condoms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Retardation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DC173AF932A25751C0A963958260" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Foes for Surgeon General Nominee</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware, usually an ally of the Clinton Administration, today called the President's choice for Surgeon General "a political blunder in the extreme," and said he would oppose it.</p>
        <p>But in a sign that the White House is still committed to the nomination of Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. for Surgeon General and can flex some muscle to preserve it, Mr. Biden retracted his statement several hours later after Administration aides urged his office to do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware, usually an ally of the Clinton Administration, today called the President's choice for Surgeon General "a political blunder in the extreme," and said he would oppose it.</p>
        <p>But in a sign that the White House is still committed to the nomination of Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr. for Surgeon General and can flex some muscle to preserve it, Mr. Biden retracted his statement several hours later after Administration aides urged his office to do so.</p>
        <p>The Delaware Democrat issued a new statement, which the White House then distributed, saying he would "withhold my final judgment" until a vote on the nomination. He continued to criticize the way the nomination was handled, however, even as medical groups reaffirmed their support for Dr. Foster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Biden had met with President Clinton to discuss the crime bill shortly after making his first comments about the nomination. Leaving the White House, he insisted that the nomination had not come up. But in his second statement, late this afternoon, the Senator again sharply criticized the way the White House had handled the matter.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, in an indication of its eagerness to spread the word that Mr. Biden had changed his stance, the White House distributed the new statement about the nomination.</p>
        <p>The Administration also planned to take Dr. Foster to Capitol Hill on Monday, and made senior officials available to discuss the nomination on weekend television news programs.</p>
        <p>Tonight, The Associated Press, quoting an unidentified senior Administration official, reported that Dr. Foster performed hysterectomies on severely retarded women in the 1960' and 1970's. The news agency said the doctor wrote about the procedures in an article in The Southern Medical Journal in 1976.</p>
        <p>Dr. Foster, The Associated Press said, wrote that he performed the sterilizations because he had believed that the women would derive "significant hygienic benefit." The article said he performed six hysterectomies between 1963 and 1973.</p>
        <p>As medical thinking on the subject changed by the late 1970's, the Administration official said, the doctor stopped performing the procedure.</p>
        <p>Earlier today, the nominee was defended by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. "In spite of Dr. Foster's illustrious record, there are some who would deny him a hearing before the nomination process has even begun," said Dr. Ralph W. Hale, executive director of the group. "The key word here is process, that is, a full-fledged discussion of his qualifications before the United States Senate."</p>
        <p>A dozen other medical groups, including the American College of Physicians, the National Medical Association and the Tennessee Medical Association, also supported the nomination, and the American Medical Association reaffirmed its support.</p>
        <p>But even as the White House intensified its efforts, the nominee found himself under attack from both sides of the aisle and from both ends of the political spectrum -- with the Religious Right and members of the AIDS activist group Act Up demanding that his nomination be withdrawn.</p>
        <p>Senator Don Nickles, an Oklahoma Republican who opposes the nomination, said on the Senate floor that Dr. Foster, the acting director of Meharry Medical College in Tennessee, had performed abortions in Alabama that he had not acknowledged.</p>
        <p>The new waves of trouble crashed on the nominee even as the Administration stepped up its campaign to save the nomination -- sending him to Capitol Hill today to lobby for political backing and to a medical school here to seek public support. But these stops did not go exactly as the White House had planned.</p>
        <p>Senator Biden's initial announcement dampened any joy Dr. Foster might have found on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>"I'm not going to vote for a nominee where no deep thought was given before the nomination was sent up," Mr. Biden said. "It was a political blunder in the extreme."</p>
        <p>But hours later, after a White House meeting on the crime bill, Mr. Biden backed off his earlier remarks.</p>
        <p>"My comments earlier today concerning the nomination of Dr. Foster were a reflection of my anger and great frustration with the way the White House has handled this nomination," he said in a statement that was circulated by the White House. "My comments were not directed at the nominee, but at the Administration's nominating process. Therefore, in fairness to Dr. Foster, I will withhold my final judgment until the vote on his nomination."</p>
        <p>Dr. Foster, in his speech before a group of medical, science and public health students at the George Washington University School of Medicine, was interrupted by a heckler who criticized him for his policy of promoting abstinence rather than the widespread distribution of condoms as the main preventative to the spread of sexual diseases and to teen-age pregnancy.</p>
        <p>"How dare you be opposed to condom distribution!" Wayne Turner, a spokesman for the AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power, or Act Up, yelled from the back of the auditorium. "Condoms save lives!"</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner was quickly rushed out of the hall, but moments later appeared on the opposite side of the room and tried to continue his protest before being escorted out again.</p>
        <p>Senator Nickles, an Oklahoma Republican, based his new charges on a story circulated today by The Associated Press quoting a relative of Dr. Foster's and a former medical colleague as saying that the nominee performed an unspecified number of emergency abortions from 1965 to 1973 in Tuskegee, Ala. At the time, Dr. Foster, who is black, was the lone obstetrician in a racially segregated hospital.</p>
        <p>"He had to perform some for medical emergencies," said William Hill, who was identified as Dr. Foster's uncle. "He wasn't an abortion doctor."</p>
        <p>In his speech, Dr. Foster said: "My opponents say that this nomination is about abortion. I believe in the right of a woman to choose. And I also support the President's belief that abortions should be safe, legal and rare."</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 25, 1995, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Feb. 11 about a speech to college students by the nominee for Surgeon General, Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr., misidentified the campus in some copies. It was George Washington University, not Georgetown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 25, 1995, Saturday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Feb. 11 about a speech to college students by the nominee for Surgeon General, Dr. Henry W. Foster Jr., misidentified the campus in some copies. It was George Washington University, not Georgetown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
