<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="865223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3DE1F39F934A25754C0A960958260" item-length="495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street's Big Tumble Echoes Around the Globe As Wall Street rode a record-breaking roller coaster, stock exchanges across the globe took their cues from Monday's bloodbath. Though the declines were less severe than in the United States, the global selloff was a panicky reaction to the carnage. [Pages A1 and D7.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wall Street's Big Tumble Echoes Around the Globe As Wall Street rode a record-breaking roller coaster, stock exchanges across the globe took their cues from Monday's bloodbath. Though the declines were less severe than in the United States, the global selloff was a panicky reaction to the carnage. [Pages A1 and D7.]</p>
        <p>Treasury prices ended higher, jostled by a rocky stock market. The yield of the  30-year Treasury bond fell to 7.02 percent. [D4.] G.M. Profits Fall on Charge General Motors reported a 16.7 percent decline in second-quarter net income because of a charge, but profits from continuing operations were better than expected. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Clinton Acts on Cuban Plants  Faced with conflicting domestic and foreign pressures in an election year, President Clinton announced a compromise measure intended to tighten the economic noose around Cuba and avert European retaliation. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Upbeat Forecast on Economy  The White House predicted that the economy would grow by 2.6 percent this year,  up from its previous forecast of 2.2 percent. [D21.].</p>
        <p>Kerkorian Group to Buy MGM Again  Kirk Kerkorian, who twice bought and sold Metro Goldwyn Mayer, is buying the ailing film company again. Credit Lyonnais, the French bank that owns the studio, accepted a $1.3 billion bid from a group led by Tracinda, Mr. Kerkorian's holding company. The Kerkorian group includes MGM's chairman, Frank  Mancuso. [D18.]</p>
        <p>An Inquiry Finds for Mattel  An investigation of Mattel has concluded that there were no irregularities in the toy maker's accounting practices. [D3.]</p>
        <p>Philip Morris Profit Up 15 Percent  Philip Morris earnings rose 15 percent as the company's food business turned around and its overseas tobacco business grew. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Results Vary for Two Bank Mergers  Chase Manhattan posted better-than-expected earnings, but Wells Fargo came in well short of forecasts as the two big bank mergers showed different results. [D3.]</p>
        <p>Earnings Rise at Eli Lilly and J.&amp; J.  Johnson &amp; Johnson reported a 19.7 percent gain in earnings for the quarter and Eli Lilly &amp; Company reported a 12 percent advance. [D6.]</p>
        <p>Time Warner Cash Flow Up Sharply  Time Warner reported that operating cash flow for the second quarter jumped 20 percent to $1.031 billion. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch Tops Forecasts  Merrill Lynch reported a 53 percent surge in second-quarter earnings that exceeded analyst expectations. [D4.]</p>
        <p>A New, Old Name For an Ad Agency  The name of Theodore F. MacManus, one of the most famous individuals in advertising, whose 1915 slogan for the Cadillac, "The Penalty of Leadership" is  still quoted, will soon adorn the ad agency D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles. The board of the agency voted to adopt a new name, the MacManus Group. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [D5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
