<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Winning Couple, One at a Time</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="541947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGE (CARD GAME)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71038F931A25754C0A964958260" item-length="417" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Winning Couple, One at a Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A STRANGE streak is in progress at national championships for Larry Mori of Ballston Lake, N.Y. In 1990 he won the North American Open Swiss Teams partnering Kitty Bethe of Manhattan. Last year he won the National Open Pairs with her husband, Henry Bethe. And in March in Pasadena, Calif., he won the National Mixed Pairs title with Kitty. The cognoscenti are now wondering which event he will win next year with Henry.</p>
        <p>In the Mixed Pairs in Pasadena, Kitty Bethe opened the West hand with one heart. An optimistic South player leaped to four spades after his partner had used a Michaels cue-bid, showing length in spades and one of the minor suits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A STRANGE streak is in progress at national championships for Larry Mori of Ballston Lake, N.Y. In 1990 he won the North American Open Swiss Teams partnering Kitty Bethe of Manhattan. Last year he won the National Open Pairs with her husband, Henry Bethe. And in March in Pasadena, Calif., he won the National Mixed Pairs title with Kitty. The cognoscenti are now wondering which event he will win next year with Henry.</p>
        <p>In the Mixed Pairs in Pasadena, Kitty Bethe opened the West hand with one heart. An optimistic South player leaped to four spades after his partner had used a Michaels cue-bid, showing length in spades and one of the minor suits.</p>
        <p>After leading the club king and winning the first trick, West shifted to a heart. South won with dummy's ace, crossed to the diamond ace and took a spade finesse. He could have made his game by cashing the spade ace, although it is not easy.</p>
        <p>South did not cash the spade ace, however. Instead, he hopefully led a diamond and was disconcerted when West ruffed. And the ruff was not with the obvious ten but the deceptive king. The position was now this: [ DIAGRAM ]</p>
        <p>South was now convinced, quite naturally, that the two missing trumps, the ten and the nine, were on his right. Consider how this would affect the play if West led a club at this point, forcing a ruff in the dummy.</p>
        <p>The contract could now be made by drawing the missing trumps, and that is how South would have proceeded if West had routinely overruffed with the ten. But that play would fail if, as assumed, the missing trumps were in the East hand. The right play in that case would be to ruff a diamond, draw trumps, and surrender a diamond trick to make the game. But South would be startled when West overruffed with the improbable spade ten, and would go down to defeat after a heart lead from West. South would have to ruff high, and after a diamond ruff, East's spade nine would be promoted as the setting trick.</p>
        <p>West, however, made a more risky return of a heart in the diagramed position. She was not sure that East was about to ruff, but South knew it: West had opened the bidding with one heart, showing a five-card suit.</p>
        <p>South thought that defeat was inevitable, and discarded a diamond from the dummy. He achieved his aim of failing by one trick, but not in the way he expected. When East ruffed and led a diamond winner, South was disconcerted to find that West could overruff with the spade ten, a card she was "known" not to hold. The result was down one.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
