<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spare the Shears and Spoil the Yard</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="542006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3D91F3BF931A25754C0A964958260" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spare the Shears and Spoil the Yard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOSE untidy looking sprouts that appear at the bases of many trees should be pruned away -- now! These unwanted growths, called suckers, add nothing to the tree's ornamental appearance. What's more, suckers are extraneous and can sap energy from the tree. They distract from its appearance and use vital nutrients and moisture when they are not removed. Suckers can become woody and strong; untended, the base of the tree eventually has the look of a shrub growing at its base.</p>
        <p>These suckers are quite easy to remove. Just take sharp pruning shears and cut them off flush with the trunk. Be sure the shears are sharp and make the cuts flush with the trunk. Add these clippings to compost, as they decompose readily. If the suckers are small and succulent, as they often are when growing on the tree's trunk, snap them off between thumb and forefinger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOSE untidy looking sprouts that appear at the bases of many trees should be pruned away -- now! These unwanted growths, called suckers, add nothing to the tree's ornamental appearance. What's more, suckers are extraneous and can sap energy from the tree. They distract from its appearance and use vital nutrients and moisture when they are not removed. Suckers can become woody and strong; untended, the base of the tree eventually has the look of a shrub growing at its base.</p>
        <p>These suckers are quite easy to remove. Just take sharp pruning shears and cut them off flush with the trunk. Be sure the shears are sharp and make the cuts flush with the trunk. Add these clippings to compost, as they decompose readily. If the suckers are small and succulent, as they often are when growing on the tree's trunk, snap them off between thumb and forefinger.</p>
        <p>This is particularly important for shade trees, like the silver maple. If unwanted shoots are not removed, the tiny growths remain to develop into woody limbs. These rather weak limbs can cause havoc with roads and utility wires during wind or ice storms because they break off easily.</p>
        <p>Many trees have this exuberant habit. Magnolias are prone to suckers. So are ash trees, locusts, many of the maples and many of the shrubs as well, especially lilacs.</p>
        <p>Why do plants form suckers? In most cases it is their nature to do so. Sometimes it is traceable to over-fertilization, sometimes excess moisture. This year's rains have caused sucker growth to abound.</p>
        <p>Many old-school gardeners like to save suckers and root them in a moist sand-peat mixture. Since the sucker has the same genetic characteristics as the mother plant, this is a logical way to duplicate a plant. It is also a quick method of propagation. But caution if you know that the plant has been grafted.  The root stock can often send up suckers, particularly the old-fashioned lilacs. And suckers rooted from this type of growth would not be desirable, just the root stock.</p>
        <p>Another form of sucker growth, called a water sprout, may appear on the branch itself. These water sprouts are vegetative shoots and are stirred by latent buds on the trunks or limbs. This type of sucker growth is particularly common on dogwood trees.</p>
        <p>A dogwood grows naturally in layers and the branches have a handsome horizontal architecture that is highly desirable. But mature dogwood trees, particularly the native species, Cornus florida, form these upright water sprouts on the elegant horizontal branches. These sprouts must be pruned out if the tree is to maintain its handsome horizontal network of branching. Water sprouts are easy to prune. Just clip them flush with the trunk with sharp shears.</p>
        <p>Once the pruning is done, it should be completed for the season. But do check the trees again at the end of summer to be sure there are no more water sprouts.</p>
        <p>If water sprouts are left in place to grow, the elegant horizontal form of the dogwood is lost. When this type of growth is left untamed, as in the case of many natural understory forest dogwoods, the trees often lose their elegant horizontal appearance because suckers have taken over. But on the homefront, where the tree is grown mainly for its ornamental look, the water-sprout growth can be controlled.</p>
        <p>And while the pruning shears are out, it might also be practical to check some of the landscape plants. Not all of the trees and shrubs will need attention, but those that are growing out of the allotted spaces may need some discipline.</p>
        <p>Pruning is especially important if the woody plants are blocking views for walks or driveways. Or if the shrubs are growing up above the windows and blocking out the light, there is no reason to tolerate this obstructing greenery.</p>
        <p>Also, if the shrubs have flowered, now is the time to cut them back. Particularly exuberant growers, like forsythia, need to have their limbs trimmed back. The shrubs will have ample time to grow new shoots and form flower buds long before the cooler fall season.</p>
        <p>Other shrubs such as azaleas or deutzias may need a limb or two cut back to keep them in shape or to control their size, but generally these shrubs look best when allowed to grow on their own. The same is true for most rhododendrons. But do cut off the faded flowers of rhododendrons, lilacs and laurels to prevent the wasteful seed pods from forming.</p>
        <p>When pruning any plant, the important thing is to step back from time to time and observe what shape the plant is growing in and then try to accentuate its natural look.</p>
        <p>The clipping of shrubs into globes, triangles, rectangles and pyramids is not the natural way a plant grows and the contrived look is often far less pleasing to the eye.</p>
        <p>GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
