<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gas Tax Could Help Our Cities</title>
    <meta content="11ROHA$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohatyn, Felix G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DC113BF932A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gas Tax Could Help Our Cities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Felix G. Rohatyn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohatyn, Felix G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felix Rohatyn Op-Ed article argues in favor of 4.3-cent-per-gallon increase in gasoline tax, which was included in Pres Clinton's 1993 budget, but which has come under attack; says repealing it would be bad energy policy and bad economic policy; says such funds could be available to state and local governments for public investment, and could be used especially for rebuilding cities; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A decade ago, in response to the abysmal state of New York City's public school buildings, the Municipal Assistance Corporation, with the support of Mayor Edward I. Koch and Gov. Mario Cuomo, committed $400 million of its surplus funds to creating a new School Construction Authority. This became the cornerstone of a five-year, $4.5 billion construction program aimed at providing decent schools and allowing for increasing enrollments over the next few years.</p>
        <p>Yet today the system is more overcrowded than ever. The buildings are often decrepit and, in many cases, dangerous for the children and the teachers. In part, this is the result of poor management by the construction authority, and could be helped by holding year-round classes and moving students to less-crowded schools around the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A decade ago, in response to the abysmal state of New York City's public school buildings, the Municipal Assistance Corporation, with the support of Mayor Edward I. Koch and Gov. Mario Cuomo, committed $400 million of its surplus funds to creating a new School Construction Authority. This became the cornerstone of a five-year, $4.5 billion construction program aimed at providing decent schools and allowing for increasing enrollments over the next few years.</p>
        <p>Yet today the system is more overcrowded than ever. The buildings are often decrepit and, in many cases, dangerous for the children and the teachers. In part, this is the result of poor management by the construction authority, and could be helped by holding year-round classes and moving students to less-crowded schools around the city.</p>
        <p>But most of the problems are the result of the city's and the state's budgetary constraints and their limits on the ability to issue additional debts.</p>
        <p>In 1994, Ramon Cortines, then the Schools Chancellor, and the city's Commission on School Facilities and Maintenance Reform, led by Harold O. Levy, submitted a $7.5 billion five-year capital request. Mayor Rudolph Giuliani, struggling with the city's budget gap, gradually reduced this to $2.9 billion.</p>
        <p>This summer, Mayor Giuliani and Peter Vallone, the speaker of the City Council, agreed to provide an additional $1.4 billion to schools over the next five years. This will help, but there will still be a significant shortfall.</p>
        <p>Such problems are not limited to New York City or to schools. Practically every large city and state face deteriorating schools, roads, bridges, mass transit systems, sewers and pollution-control plants. Few have the money to make repairs or build anew, and many have legal restrictions on their debt capacity. They need Federal assistance -- specifically, a program that would return an existing source of Federal revenue over to state and local governments.</p>
        <p>During the Presidential campaign, the 4.3 cent-a-gallon increase in the gas tax that was included in President Clinton's 1993 budget package has come under attack. Repealing it would be bad energy policy and bad economic policy. But it is worth considering a better use for the gas tax than Federal deficit reduction: making it available to state and local governments for public investment.</p>
        <p>Localities could spend the money directly on construction and renovation, or leverage the funds with secured borrowing. State and city governments have been cutting back on public investment because of budgetary problems and legal limits on their abilities to issue bonds.</p>
        <p>The income from a 4.3 cent Federal gasoline tax has the benefit of being highly predictable. It would provide about $5 billion to states every year, making it ideal for very long-term bonds issued for public investment.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, this could comfortably support from $75 billion to $100 billion in new programs by state and local governments over five years, assuming that they would pay an additional 20 percent to 25 percent of the cost beyond their take of the gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>With its share, New York State could generate $5 billion to $7 billion over the period. Each state would decide how best to use the money, but a significant portion would be committed to new schools and education technology.</p>
        <p>Such a program could result in more than buildings. It could create at least two million new jobs, public and private. Most would likely be well-paying jobs related to construction; others would be less-specialized jobs that could be opportunities for young people who need a chance to break the cycle of welfare.</p>
        <p>Under the new Federal law, finding work for welfare dependents is a hidden time bomb for state governments.</p>
        <p>Yes, the money will be lost to the Federal Treasury. But replacing $5 billion each year in a $1.5 trillion Federal budget is a small challenge compared with the benefits of $100 billion of additional investment in cities over five years. The program would undoubtedly receive strong support from mayors and governors, Republicans and Democrats, business and labor.</p>
        <p>A program that would give city and state governments $75 billion to $100 billion would provide only a fraction of the more than $2 trillion needed nationwide for public improvements. But, if successful, the program could be extended and increased over time.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has recognized the need for Federal assistance to state and local governments by signing a bill sponsored by Senator Carol Moseley Braun, Democrat of Illinois, providing interest rate subsidies for local school construction. This was a good beginning, but it is not nearly enough.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has long called for greater public investment, yet neither party has put forward a program to meet the challenges facing urban America.</p>
        <p>Turning the revenue from the gas tax into schools and other badly needed public buildings would be a large part of Bill Clinton's bridge to the 21st century.</p>
        <p>Felix G. Rohatyn, a managing director at Lazard Freres, investment bankers, was chairman of the Municipal Assistance Corporation from 1975-93.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Felix G. Rohatyn, a managing director at Lazard Freres, investment bankers, was chairman of the Municipal Assistance Corporation from 1975-93.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
