<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NETANYAHU GAINS DELAY IN KEY VOTE ON REMOVING HIM</title>
    <meta content="08ISRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Netanyahu, Benjamin (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DA143AF93BA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NETANYAHU GAINS DELAY IN KEY VOTE ON REMOVING HIM</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Dec. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Govt of Prime Min Benjamin Netanyahu narrowly averts collapse as Israeli lawmakers postpone no-confidence vote, first step toward dissolving Parliament and calling new elections; move gives Netanyahu approximately two weeks to seek way out of political bind; situation, coupled with violent Palestinian protests in almost every West Bank city, creates uneasy backdrop for Pres Clinton's upcoming three-day visit to region, which many Israeli politicians already oppose as endorsement of Palestinian sovereignty; Netanyahu's troubles, which began with signing of land-for security agreement with Palestinians in October fracturing his right-wing coalition, discussed; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Israelis called it Big Monday.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu was almost toppled. In what was seen as the most critical day yet for his faltering Government, Israeli lawmakers postponed a vote, at the last minute, to take the first step toward dissolving Parliament and calling new elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Israelis called it Big Monday.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu was almost toppled. In what was seen as the most critical day yet for his faltering Government, Israeli lawmakers postponed a vote, at the last minute, to take the first step toward dissolving Parliament and calling new elections.</p>
        <p>At the same time, in almost every West Bank city, Palestinian protests grew into violent confrontations both with Israeli soldiers and with the Palestinian police.</p>
        <p>Together with the political chaos in Israel, the unrest on the Palestinian streets created an uneasy backdrop for President Clinton's three-day visit to the region, scheduled to begin on Saturday.</p>
        <p>All day, legislators marched in and out of Mr. Netanyahu's office in Parliament as he struggled to avert what appeared to be the strong likelihood of a humiliating defeat.</p>
        <p>At the last minute, just before a 9 P.M. vote was to be taken, Mr. Netanyahu succeeded in delaying his destiny. He persuaded a rigorously Orthodox party, United Torah Judaism, to attach a motion of no confidence in his Government to the bill calling for early elections. For procedural reasons, that postponed the vote and bought Mr. Netanyahu about two weeks to bargain his way out of a political dead end.</p>
        <p>''The faith in this guy is gone,'' Haim Ramon, a leader of the opposition Labor Party, said tonight.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Netanyahu loses the no-confidence vote, elections would be held within the next 60 days.</p>
        <p>Troubles in Israel -- between the Israelis and the Palestinians, and within Palestinian society -- have come to a boil, just days before Mr. Clinton's trip. At the same time, still more Israeli political leaders added their voices today to opposition to the visit, which many see as an endorsement of Palestinian sovereignty. Joining a majority of members of the Prime Minister's Cabinet who have already opposed the visit, Dan Tichon, the Speaker of Parliament, said he would refuse to take part in any ceremonies with Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu's troubles began when he signed a land-for-security  agreement in October promising to turn over a sizable chunk of the West Bank to the Palestinians. This fractured his right-wing coalition, forcing him to rely on the Labor Party to get the peace deal approved by Parliament. As his coalition grew steadily more dysfunctional, he sought to realign it, most significantly by inviting his former Foreign Minister, David Levy, back into the Government.</p>
        <p>Negotiations with Mr. Levy and his five-member Gesher Party broke down on Sunday. The Labor Party, which had aligned itself with Mr. Netanyahu only on the issue of peace, seized the opportunity to call a vote on dissolving the Government.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Levy's faction, Labor counted a majority in favor of removing the Prime Minister. Judging by the insults flying from every corner today, Mr. Netanyahu could count on few friends willing to endorse him publicly. ''The Prime Minister cheats all of the time, but not all of us are willing to be cheated,'' said Uzi Landau, a hard-line member of Mr. Netanyahu's Likud Party.</p>
        <p>Legislators shuffled in and out of the Prime Minister's office. The first to come and go were members of the right-wing Land of Israel front, a small coalition vehemently opposed to any Israeli withdrawal from the West Bank. They were told that the peace agreement would be frozen.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Netanyahu sent out a written message to Israeli Arab legislators, saying any freeze would be temporary. ''They asked for a two-week extension, after which they would promote the peace, but we would not agree to that,'' said Abdul Wahab Darawshe, leader of the United Arab List.</p>
        <p>Notes were compared, and National Religious Party members went racing in to ask for a clarification. They apparently left unclarified. One member, Zvi Hendel, said, ''There comes a point where they're spitting at us, and it's not rain.''</p>
        <p>In one of the clearest signs of his desperation, Mr. Netanyahu offered the hard-right party Moledet a seat in his Cabinet. It turned him down.</p>
        <p>Standing in the hallway, observing the scurrying, Mr. Ramon, of the Labor Party, smirked and called it a ''disgrace.''</p>
        <p>''All this for another day or two, another week or two,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the end, by buying himself time, Mr. Netanyahu took a gamble that the sooner new elections were held, the better he would fare. The requirement for elections within 60 days if he loses the no-confidence vote would bring elections sooner than would occur under the original opposition bill, in which elections would have been three months off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu is not expected to broaden his appeal over time. And he would fare better in a scenario in which he himself would be initiating the vote.</p>
        <p>Addressing Parliament tonight, the Prime Minister criticized both the Palestinians and the Israeli opposition, almost in the same breath. Lashing out at Labor, he accused it of ''cynically using the right wing's pain.'' And he tried to distance himself from the peace agreement, allying himself instead with his old stance as defender of the Greater Land of Israel.</p>
        <p>In discussions today, Mr. Netanyahu made it clear that he would trade on the events of the next two weeks. If the peace effort seems to be moving forward during and after Mr. Clinton's visit, he could sell himself as the hard-liner who won peace by talking tough to the Palestinians. Or if Palestinian unrest seems to justify a freeze in carrying out the agreement, he could try to win back the right wing.</p>
        <p>Some on the right were indeed hopeful that everything could turn around in two weeks. ''Today I would definitely have voted no confidence,'' said Benny Elon of Moledet, the hard-right party. ''But maybe over the next two weeks people will sober up and recognize the fact that the entire peace process should be abandoned.''</p>
        <p>The violence in the West Bank continued to feed Israeli anxieties today. For weeks, there have been Palestinian protests and marches seeking the release of political prisoners from Israeli jails. Many of the protests have led to confrontations with Israeli soldiers.</p>
        <p>In Bethlehem today, the relatives of prisoners were joined by youths who hurled stones at Israeli soldiers as if it were sport, stopping once in a while for a cigarette break or to repair slingshots. The Israeli soldiers near Rachel's Tomb responded with shooting, wounding about 10 Palestinians before using tear gas to  disperse the crowd.</p>
        <p>At the same time, in Nablus, Mr. Arafat's police forces intervened to prevent hundreds of protesters from clashing with Israeli soldiers guarding Joseph's Tomb. They used wooden clubs, beating the protesters, and ended up in a shooting match with members of Mr. Arafat's party, Al Fatah. After the police headquarters was besieged, the Palestinian authorities shot and wounded 19 rioters.</p>
        <p>In Abu Dis, a West Bank town, the Palestinian police stood back and allowed the clashes to go on, as they did most everywhere else. A 20-year-old student, Nasser Erekat, was hit in the head by a rubber bullet and was listed in critical condition at a hospital tonight.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials said four Israeli police officers and two civilians were wounded in the violence today. One man, a Jewish settler, was shot while driving between the settlement of Kadim and the Palestinian town of Jenin in the northern West Bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
