<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE CAMPAIGNS FOR THE SENATE</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL BRIEFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIRGINIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENTUCKY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALABAMA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIRGINIA, USA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN JOHN W WARNER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0DD1E39F933A05756C0A960958260" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE CAMPAIGNS FOR THE SENATE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN JOHN W WARNER;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virginia Fraternal Fight Gets Tougher</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Virginia Fraternal Fight Gets Tougher</p>
        <p>Things get curiouser and curiouser in Virginia's Republican Senate primary. James C. Miller 3d, who is mounting a conservative challenge to his fellow Republican, Senator John W. Warner, calls Mr. Warner a liberal -- twice -- in a  new radio commercial.</p>
        <p>"Why is Warner running in the Republican primary, anyway?" the Miller advertisement asks. The subtext, of course, is Mr. Warner's break in 1994 with the conservatives who dominate his party, when he refused to embrace the Republican nominee for the Senate, Oliver L. North.</p>
        <p>Mr. Warner is ahead in the polls and hardly friendless in his party as the June 11 primary approaches. Senator Trent Lott, the majority whip and leading contender for majority leader, came to Virginia this week to endorse Mr. Warner, and said of the effort to brand him a liberal, "I snicker at that idea."</p>
        <p>But some say Mr. Warner has some of his strongest support outside his party,  among independents and Democrats who can vote in Virginia's open primary. Mr. Warner and his staff have clashed internally over how blatantly to appeal to these voters. But the signals from the Warner camp clearly alarm the head of the Virginia Democratic Party, Sue Wrenn, who held her second news conference in a week yesterday to urge Democrats not to vote in the Republican primary.</p>
        <p>Both Republicans are campaigning hard, and trying hard not to look like Beltway insiders. When Mr. Miller, a budget director in the Reagan Administration, lost a tassled loafer in the mud at a tractor pull, he hastened  to point out that the shoe was mail order. Mr. Warner, for his part, has taken to campaigning on weekends in a Panama hat and khakis.</p>
        <p>As he shed his tie before plunging into a lakefront crowd, Mr. Warner proclaimed, "I don't need the Bob Dole memo. I know how to dress!"</p>
        <p>Alabama A Packed Field To Replace a Senator</p>
        <p>Alabama's Senate primary is on Tuesday, but in the way of many Southern primaries it is probably only the first winnowing of the field.</p>
        <p>The seat is held by Senator Howell Heflin, one of the cannier Democrats in the art of surviving in a realigning South, who is retiring after 18 years in the Senate. Republicans see Mr. Heflin's retirement as a prime opportunity to pick up a seat, asserting (with considerable evidence) that the trend in that deep South state is solidly conservative.</p>
        <p>On the Republican side, Attorney General Jeff Sessions is widely seen as leading the crowded field, with Sid McDonald, a former state legislator and businessman, and Charles Woods, another businessman and unsuccessful candidate for statewide office in both Alabama and Nevada, closest behind.</p>
        <p>The Democratic field is dominated by Representative Glen Browder of Anniston, State Senator Roger Bedford of Russellville (who recently picked up the endorsements of two major black political organizations in the state) and Natalie Davis, a political science professor and pollster.</p>
        <p>Even by Alabama standards, this primary is hard to read, some analysts say, generating much less of the buzz that normally attends a good statewide campaign in Alabama. As a result, some predict that turnout might be quite low.</p>
        <p>Kentucky G.O.P. Optimistic, Democrats Are, Too</p>
        <p>There are the obvious battlegrounds in the race for the Senate, like Massachusetts and Illinois, and then there are the less obvious, like Kentucky.  Some Democrats tout it as the sleeper of 1996.</p>
        <p>Senator Mitch McConnell, a two-term Republican, easily won renomination in Tuesday's primary and begins his quest for a third term with a formidable war chest and a clear edge in the polls. He has tried to keep an appropriate distance from the much-talked-of Gingrich revolution; at his campaign kickoff earlier this year, Mr. McConnell presented himself as a legislator "with the common sense and the clout to take some of the rough edges off the Republican revolution when Kentucky's vital interests are at stake."</p>
        <p>He has prevailed in two hard-fought statewide campaigns.</p>
        <p>But Steve Beshear, who won the Democratic nomination on Tuesday, has a few advantages of his own.  Kentucky is a swing state with two intensely competitive parties, but the Democrats have a big edge in voter registration and were energized by their victory in last year's race for governor. Mr. Beshear has run three times for statewide office and won twice, for lieutenant governor and attorney general, before his unsuccesful campaign for governor in 1987. He has strong support within his party, too.</p>
        <p>Frank Greer, Mr. Beshear's consultant, argued yesterday that for all Mr. McConnell's talk of independence, "he has voted down the line with the Republican agenda." Moreover, Mr. Greer asserted, the Senator will pay a price with the voters because of his long opposition to Democratic efforts to enact new campaign financing laws.</p>
        <p>Kyle Simmons, campaign manager for Mr. McConnell, countered that the campaign finance issue would have little impact on voting.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Simmons cited Mr. Beshear's "liberal leanings" and background as a "lawyer-lobbyist" as big vulnerabilities.</p>
        <p>The two sides have already exchanged charges in radio commercials.</p>
        <p>ROBIN TONER</p>
        <p>POLITICAL BRIEFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
