<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Honor a Fallen Hero</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOMESTIC VIOLENCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATTACKS ON POLICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUIDICE, VINCENT (POLICE OFFICER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON,ROBERT (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DC1E39F933A05756C0A960958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Honor a Fallen Hero</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death of Police Officer Vincent Guidice was a tragedy for New York City as well as for his family and friends. Officer Guidice died from an injury he received while responding to a report of a family dispute. Domestic violence is  a dangerous and difficult area of police work. At the time he was wounded, Officer Guidice was visiting the same Bronx apartment for a second night running, even though the woman who lived there had declined to press charges the day before. His death will not make the fight against spousal abuse easier, but  his fellow officers will honor his memory by emulating his brave persistence.</p>
        <p>It would be a second tragedy if the story of Mr. Guidice's hard work and dedication was obscured by the controversy over the prosecution of his alleged assailant. Mayor Rudolph Giuliani has been harshly critical of Bronx District Attorney Robert Johnson for failing to charge Anthony Richard Rivers with second-degree murder. Mr. Johnson asked a Bronx grand jury to indict Mr. Rivers  for manslaughter, but the grand jury refused to go even that far, and settled on a lesser charge of criminally negligent homicide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death of Police Officer Vincent Guidice was a tragedy for New York City as well as for his family and friends. Officer Guidice died from an injury he received while responding to a report of a family dispute. Domestic violence is  a dangerous and difficult area of police work. At the time he was wounded, Officer Guidice was visiting the same Bronx apartment for a second night running, even though the woman who lived there had declined to press charges the day before. His death will not make the fight against spousal abuse easier, but  his fellow officers will honor his memory by emulating his brave persistence.</p>
        <p>It would be a second tragedy if the story of Mr. Guidice's hard work and dedication was obscured by the controversy over the prosecution of his alleged assailant. Mayor Rudolph Giuliani has been harshly critical of Bronx District Attorney Robert Johnson for failing to charge Anthony Richard Rivers with second-degree murder. Mr. Johnson asked a Bronx grand jury to indict Mr. Rivers  for manslaughter, but the grand jury refused to go even that far, and settled on a lesser charge of criminally negligent homicide.</p>
        <p>People who knew Officer Guidice, as well as average citizens who appreciated his service to the city, naturally want to see whoever caused his death punished as severely as possible. But the officials who enforce our criminal laws cannot  always bend them to satisfy public opinion. Mr. Johnson judged that the facts of the case could not support a second-degree murder charge, since, as he put it, "there was no evidence the defendant intended to injure -- let alone kill -- Officer Guidice." The grand jury then made a surprising and regrettable decision not to grant Mr. Johnson the manslaughter indictment. Given Mr. Johnson's reputation as a seasoned and careful prosecutor who seldom overreaches, the grand jury might better have returned the requested indictment and left it to a  trial jury to decide whether downgrading to a lesser charge was appropriate.</p>
        <p>The issue, as Mayor Giuliani has presented it over the last week, is less about how many years in prison Mr. Rivers would have to serve if convicted than  about underlining how seriously the city takes the death of a police officer. The Mayor has charged the Bronx District Attorney with sending the wrong message to police. Mr. Giuliani insists that the evidence shows Mr. Rivers demonstrated  the kind of callous, outrageous disregard for human life that a second-degree murder indictment would require. He has vividly demonstrated for reporters his understanding of how Mr. Rivers picked up a 30-pound mirror and flung it at the  officers, then shoved Officer Guidice into a shard of jagged glass.</p>
        <p>But the District Attorney's office has a different version of the events leading to Officer Guidice's fatal injury. By this account, Mr. Rivers was the one who phoned in the domestic-dispute call, and let the officers into the apartment where he was arguing with his common-law wife. While the officers tried to stop the dispute, Mr. Rivers allegedly pulled the mirror from the wall, and flung it in the direction of the woman, who was standing near one of the officers. The officers told her to go into the bathroom where she would be safe, and calmed down Mr. Rivers.</p>
        <p>When police backup arrived, however, and Officer Guidice tried to arrest Mr.  Rivers, he resisted. Mr. Rivers and several of the officers fell to the floor, according to the District Attorney's office, and Officer Guidice fell against the mirror, cutting his thigh on the glass.</p>
        <p>These conflicting details are important, and can best be weighed in court. The most crucial service a public official can perform in a sensitive, emotion-laden situation like this is to clear away misperceptions, and help the  public understand the reasons behind hard-to-accept decisions. When an officer kills a civilian in the line of duty, and community residents protest, city officials rightly beg the public to wait until the facts of the case are clear before jumping to a conclusion. Mr. Giuliani's passionate advocacy of the police is understandable, given the heavy burden he places upon them. But he is not doing the city a service by encouraging the rank-and-file police to make quick judgments, or by telling them that the District Attorney's office is not acting  in their interest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
