<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vincent Van Gogh, Meet Adam Smith</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="323205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUCTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOTHEBY'S</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN GOGH, VINCENT (1853-90)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7103BF937A35751C0A966958260" item-length="3251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vincent Van Gogh, Meet Adam Smith</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL; Peter Passell writes about economics for The New York Times.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: No one really knows whether the unexpected return to the market of Vincent van Gogh's ''Irises,'' whose November 1987 auction price of $54 million made it the most expensive painting ever sold, will signal the end of the long bull market in contemporary and Impressionist masterpieces. The value of art, unlike that of stocks or bonds or barrels of crude oil, is determined largely by psychology, and the factors that make one van</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: No one really knows whether the unexpected return to the market of Vincent van Gogh's ''Irises,'' whose November 1987 auction price of $54 million made it the most expensive painting ever sold, will signal the end of the long bull market in contemporary and Impressionist masterpieces. The value of art, unlike that of stocks or bonds or barrels of crude oil, is determined largely by psychology, and the factors that make one van</p>
        <p>No one really knows whether the unexpected return to the market of Vincent van Gogh's ''Irises,'' whose November 1987 auction price of $54 million made it the most expensive painting ever sold, will signal the end of the long bull market in contemporary and Impressionist masterpieces. The value of art, unlike that of stocks or bonds or barrels of crude oil, is determined largely by psychology, and the factors that make one van Gogh worth $54 million rather than, say, $34 million or $74 million are especially elusive.</p>
        <p>But one consequence is clear. The return to market of ''Irises,'' along with Sotheby's tightening of its controversial credit policy, which in 1987 had enabled the buyer to borrow half of the purchase price, are not likely to dampen the demand for very expensive art. Nor is it likely that a dip in the fortunes of the wheeler-dealers who add speculative froth to the auctions would undo what economists believe is the most fundamental change in the market in recent years: the transformation of art into a practical vehicle for investment.</p>
        <p>Increased competition among dealers, auction houses and innovative marketing outlets has sharply reduced the costs of buying and selling art. Sources of information about the market value of art have multiplied, making it far more attractive for newcomers to play the investing game. And these signs of increased efficiency are not limited to the upper reaches of the art world. The markets for prints by brand-name artists and oils by relative unknowns are also changing. It is now becoming practical for individuals with, say, $10,000 to $50,000 available, to invest in art the way they invest in gold coins or building lots in Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Many observers see only grief in this aggressive mixing of culture and mammon. But there is a brighter side. The drive for profit could broaden the appeal of art, improve popular taste and help preserve the best work for future generations.</p>
        <p>''Irises'' was sold at auction to Alan Bond, an Australian with interests ranging from beer to 12-meter racing yachts. It was later revealed that Sotheby's had agreed in advance to lend half the $53.9 million bid by Mr. Bond, an arrangement that brought cries of foul from consumer advocates as well as critics offended by the slick marketing of great art.</p>
        <p>Part of the ''Irises'' loan was paid off when Mr. Bond unloaded a Manet in November 1989. But an undisclosed portion was not: The van Gogh is again for sale. And in an apparent attempt to placate critics and lessen the risk of defaults, Sotheby's has decided not to allow bidders to use paintings they do not yet own as collateral for loans.</p>
        <p>Where Do We Go From Here?</p>
        <p>Experts are divided over what impact the Bond affair is likely to have. Richard Feigen, a New York gallery owner, argues that the availability of precommitted credit from Sotheby's inflated the 1987 sale price for ''Irises,'' which in turn legitimized the $47.9 million paid for a Picasso self-portrait in May 1989. But he points out that another controversial (and perhaps inflationary) Sotheby practice, guaranteeing sellers a minimum price for their work, remains in force. He offers no specific prediction on prices, saying only that the return of ''Irises'' ''leaves the real market level in question.''</p>
        <p>Ivan Karp, the director of the O. K. Harris Gallery, harbors no doubts. He predicts a 20 percent fall in ''grotesquely distorted'' prices when the next big auctions take place this spring. The definitive test may, in fact, come in May, when Christie's auctions another van Gogh painting, ''Portrait of Dr. Gachet,'' thought to be worth as much as $50 million.</p>
        <p>But the collapse of Mr. Bond's fortunes does not reflect any larger economic event that could dry up interest in very expensive paintings. The art market bulled its way through the mid-1980's energy crash and the October 1987 stock market debacle without a stumble. And as Mr. Karp readily concedes, ''there is so much wealth in the market -especially ignorant money - that 'Irises' could happen again.''</p>
        <p>Nor is the change in Sotheby's lending policy likely to reduce the number of big-time bidders. According to Michael Ainslie, the president of Sotheby's Holdings, Ltd., almost all the people who buy very expensive canvases pay cash: prearranged house credit has not been used to finance any of his firm's last 32 auction sales over $5 million.</p>
        <p>In any event, credit will still be available after purchase. Sotheby's, like many banks, remains ready to make multimillion-dollar art loans when rich borrowers are prepared to back them with personal guarantees as well as the art itself. ''We are not margin lenders,'' Mr. Ainslie said, making a distinction that may not impress his critics. But it does suggest that the credit base is a less important source of instability in the art market than in, say, the highly leveraged markets for pork bellies or Houston real estate.</p>
        <p>And even if the high-flying market were to hit an air pocket, argues Jeffrey Deitch, a former Citibank official who now advises well-heeled collectors, the basic trends that have made art a more attractive investment are unlikely to be reversed. Until very recently, it was hardly more practical to trade artistic masterpieces than it was to trade spouses. But in the last decade increased competition and innovative marketing have made it possible for individuals and corporations to buy and sell paintings like diamonds or shares in mutual funds.</p>
        <p>Mammon May Not Be All Bad</p>
        <p>This phenomenon is most apparent in the upper reaches of the market, where Swedish real estate tycoons and Japanese insurance companies slug it out for possession of the best of van Gogh, Picasso and Jasper Johns. But the changes in the middle of the art market, where investors and dealers hope to make fortunes on $25,000 oils and $5,000 prints, may prove equally important.</p>
        <p>A focus on commerce, it is widely believed, distorts the values of both those who create art and those who buy it. Moreover, much of the newly stimulated demand for art is coming from abroad, raising the prospect that the cream of contemporary work will find homes far from America.</p>
        <p>Often overlooked, however, are the benefits. Wealthy, investment-minded collectors in search of the next Frank Stella or Robert Rauschenberg are casting their nets wider, offering undiscovered artists a better chance for recognition and wealth in their lifetimes. More people in more places are being exposed to good art. Richard Sandor, a Chicago collector and investment banker, argues that the trend is bound to improve the prospects for preserving good contemporary art for future generations.</p>
        <p>There have always been collectors who worried about the resale value of their portfolios. But until the last few years it was generally considered unseemly to buy and sell for quick profit. More important to investment-minded collectors, points out Mr. Deitch, it was rarely profitable. Finding a buyer who would pay a good price often took years. And once a buyer was found, dealers' commissions ate up a third or more of the sales price. That made it unrealistic to invest in art without, according to Mr. Deitch, a lot of knowledge - and the deep pockets to commit your money for half a decade.</p>
        <p>Revving Up The Market</p>
        <p>Capitalism abhors a poorly developed free market the way nature abhors a vacuum. It was probably inevitable that more efficient methods for trading art would evolve. Robert Miller, a New York gallery owner, believes the evolution really began in the 1960's, when it became fashionable for big American corporations to polish their images by hanging expensive paintings in lobbies and boardrooms.</p>
        <p>But to Mr. Deitch and many other analysts, the most important change came in 1983, when an American real estate tycoon named Alfred Taubman bought Sotheby's and set out to erase the staid old English auction house image.</p>
        <p>Rich bidders were courted with beautiful catalogues, straightforward explanations of bidding procedures and, as is now well known, prearranged lines of credit (at the prime rate plus 2 to 4 percentage points) for up to half the estimated value of works for auction. Sellers were wooed with easy credit, minimum price guarantees and discounted fees that could be negotiated down to zero if a work was valuable enough. Says Mr. Ainslie, ''We saw no reason why the bulk of transactions should be in the galleries.''</p>
        <p>Sotheby's timing could not have been better. The stock market, real estate and investment banking booms of the 1980's created hundreds of multimillionaires in search of the social respectability associated with owning a Pollock or a Renoir. And a combination of the decline of United States currency in 1985 and rapid economic growth in Japan and Western Europe sharply increased the demand for art bought and sold in dollars.</p>
        <p>Great Impressionist canvases, worth as much as Rolls-Royces in the 1970's, now trade at parity with Boeing 757's. Works by blue-chip modern artists like de Kooning, Rauschenberg and Stella increased in value 10- or 20-fold. And the auction houses benefited accordingly. Sotheby's turned over $2.93 billion in art in 1989, 61 percent more than the record 1988 sales. Christie's, its London-based rival, grossed $2.08 billion, a 48 percent jump over the previous year.</p>
        <p>Spreading the Market Beyond the Auctions</p>
        <p>But while the proportion of sales through auctions has surely increased, auction houses have not gained a monopoly on upscale art. Since auctions are strictly a resale market, galleries remain the principal go-betweens for contemporary artists and their collectors. And many dealers are scrambling to find other market niches that the auction houses cannot easily fill.</p>
        <p>Some dealers serve as consultants to rich collectors, advising them on trends, finding bankers who will help finance their acquisitions, and bidding on their behalf at auctions. Some go on the road, exhibiting wares at art fairs where half-million-dollar sales are commonplace.</p>
        <p>The 10-year-old Chicago International Art Exposition, which drew 200 dealers and 45,000 visitors last year, has become a leading showcase for trendy American and European art, and fairs in Basel, London, Milan, New York and Los Angeles are not far behind. Two big exhibitions are being planned for Tokyo.</p>
        <p>But most dealers do what they have always done, cultivating clients with personal service, acting as brokers for publicity-shy buyers and sellers, and catching the overflow business generated by the auctions. With total annual turnover in art running to at least $10 billion, as estimated by Forbes magazine, that hardly amounts to crumbs. Ken Goldglit, an accountant for galleries and other art-related businesses, says flatly that ''1989 was the best year dealers have ever had.''</p>
        <p>What has been good for the auction houses and dealers also seems to have worked in the interests of private collectors. Increased competition has made it easier to search out potential buyers and has reduced commissions. And the option to borrow against collections has enabled cash-strapped sellers to hold out for the best price.</p>
        <p>Smaller Players Get Into the Game</p>
        <p>Parallel changes are taking place in what Lynda Deppe, the head of the Novo Arts consulting firm in New York, calls the second tier of the art market, ''where young professionals are looking for investments with more status than stocks.'' Auctions now routinely offer paintings and sculpture in the $10,000-to-$35,000 range, creating a fluid secondary market for works by the few hundred contemporary artists who are known primarily to specialized collectors and curators.</p>
        <p>But much of the mid-market action, Ms. Deppe says, is in prints by brand-name artists in the Warhol, Baldassari and Rosenquist class. Typically they are published in editions of 75 to 200 and distributed through informal networks of dealers and galleries, much the way new securities are retailed through stock brokers. Lively secondary markets, with most of the transactions from dealer to dealer, allow investors to realize profits (or losses). Michael McKenzie, a New York art dealer and prints publisher, also notes the growth of very sophisticated independent galleries from Miami to Minneapolis, which typically feature prints.</p>
        <p>Museums Are The Big Losers</p>
        <p>The big losers in the art-as-investment boom are museums. The 1986 Tax Reform Act sharply circumscribed deductions from charitable gifts of property. And both the higher value and greater ease of selling masterpieces is leading potential donors to think twice about how to dispose of the Sargent that grandma hung over the mantelpiece.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people who might have given are tempted by the auction houses,'' says Philippe de Montebello, the director of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. That temptation apparently explains the imminent fate of van Gogh's ''Portrait of Dr. Gachet.'' The painting, on loan to the Met since 1984, is to be auctioned by its owner, the heirs of the New York collector Siegfried Kramarsky.</p>
        <p>Among American museums, only the Getty in Los Angeles and the Kimbell in Fort Worth have the endowments to buy paintings in the van Gogh price range. Museums could, of course, pocket a multibillion-dollar windfall by selling small portions of their collections. But they are reluctant to play the trading game on a scale necessary to make up for the loss of gifts for fear of alienating the private collectors who have always been their biggest benefactors.</p>
        <p>And What Of the Artists?</p>
        <p>The net impact on artists is harder to evaluate. The new market has made some of them fabulously rich and encouraged galleries to scour the garrets for the next generation of great talent. But as Robert Miller notes, the number of young artists actually benefiting is limited. And there are risks even for those who do catch the brass ring.</p>
        <p>Fame and fortune at a young age, Mr. Miller believes, can stunt artistic development. More tangibly, it can make an artist vulnerable to rapidly changing fashions. The price of paintings by Sandro Chia, for example, rose from $10,000 to $60,000 after the influential collector Charles Saatchi bought seven. But when Mr. Saatchi sold them all without explanation, the Chia star fell as fast as it had risen.</p>
        <p>The broader cultural impact of art as investment can't yet be determined. It is not known, for example, whether the great art now being snapped up by individuals and corporations will eventually find its way to public display. While there are new incentives for selling rather than donating art, it also makes financial sense to give the public a good look. Daniel Lazare, a writer for Art and Antiques magazine, argues that the auction value of ''Irises'' was greatly enhanced by its prominent placement at the Metropolitan's 1986 van Gogh show.</p>
        <p>Nor is it easy to predict the course of the newly rich who now buy expensive art with nothing more in mind than an invitation to join the hunt club. Will they eventually be bitten by the competitive challenge of amassing specialized collections and become what Richard Sandor calls the ''custodians of culture,'' preserving lesser-known art and supporting lesser-known artists?</p>
        <p>Perhaps most important, will the mid-market - the lawyers from Minneapolis and engineers from Houston who are seduced by the prospect of a quick 50 percent profit on the latest set of Warhol prints - stay on to form a powerful middle-class lobby that nourishes artists and defends them against the philistines?</p>
        <p>BUT IS ART A GOOD INVESTMENT?</p>
        <p>Judging by the figures in the chart above, Old Master paintings look like a very good investment indeed. But as Bruno S. Frey and Angel Serna, economists at the University of Zurich, pointed out last year in Art and Antiques magazine, the raw numbers overstate the case for making the plunge.</p>
        <p>The rates of return shown are based on actual sales at Sotheby's; paintings withdrawn from auctions because bidding did not reach the predetermined minimum price are not counted. Also, the financial return on art must be adjusted downward to account for sales charges. It costs a few percent at most to trade stocks or gold or Treasury bills. But auction houses still charge 10 to 20 percent to turn over a painting.</p>
        <p>The experience of Gerald Guterman, an American collector studied by Mr. Frey and Mr. Serna, is probably not atypical. Mr. Guterman nearly doubled his money in five years by auctioning off 14 paintings in 1986. But after adjustment for inflation and sales fees, the annual return was about 3 percent - roughly half what he would have earned on randomly chosen stocks or United States Government bonds.</p>
        <p>IT'S GUARANTEED</p>
        <p>Of the financial lures used by major auction houses to attract major art collections, the guarantee has become increasingly important. Under a guarantee, the auction house agrees to pay a minimum price to a seller, even if no buyer is found for the art. For this no-risk arrangement, the seller may pay a higher commission if the art is sold; if it is not sold, the object becomes the property of the auction house.</p>
        <p>In the fall season of 1989 Sotheby's guarantees represented about 10 percent of its sales, which totaled $1.5 billion. The figure was more than three times the guarantees ever granted during a comparable period in the past. Last week Sotheby's announced that in May it would auction the guaranteed collection of 20th-century European and American art from the estate of Lydia Winston Malbin. It is valued at $60 million.</p>
        <p>Christie's, Sotheby's arch-rival, does not offer guarantees on the artworks it auctions, but will attempt to arrange guarantees through a third party, possibly a London merchant bank. Two other auction houses - Butterfield &amp; Butterfield of San Francisco and Los Angeles and Habsburg, Feldman of Geneva and New York, do offer guarantees. ''Guarantees are a very potent kind of lure,'' said David Tunick, a New York art dealer. ''A guarantee is money in the bank. I don't have any problem with the auction house making guarantees, as long as the public is made aware that the auction house has what is tantamount to an equity interest in what it is selling.''</p>
        <p>Guarantees were introduced at Sotheby's in London about 20 years ago. Last fall the increased use of guarantees caused some critics of the practice to raise questions about whether Sotheby's role as potential owner compromised its function as agent.</p>
        <p>Until now Sotheby's guaranteed properties were identified in catalogues as those in which the auction house ''has an interest,'' without saying what that interest is. This is now to be changed. ''We have decided that we will make our guarantees explicitly known in our catalogues and that we will follow this procedure on a worldwide basis,'' said Michael L. Ainslie, president of Sotheby's Holdings, owner of the auction house. The most ambitious offering of guaranteed property to date was the sale in October of the collection of John T. Dorrance Jr., an heir to the Campbell Soup Company fortune. The auction, which totaled $131.3 million, was criticized because Sotheby's did not disclose until December that it had guaranteed the collection. Diana D. Brooks, president of Sotheby's in North America, said that the guarantee was ''less than $100 million.''</p>
        <p>The most important painting offered with a guarantee was Picasso's ''Mirror'' (detail in photograph), which was sold in November for $26.4 million.</p>
        <p>- Rita Reif</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
