<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TONIGHT'S TV LISTINGS: What's on Tuesday Night</title>
    <meta content="0220tvcol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/20/arts/television/0220tvcol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Tonight's TV Listings"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DC123EF933A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TONIGHT'S TV LISTINGS: What's on Tuesday Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What’s on Tuesday Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHRYN SHATTUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>10 P.M. (VH1) THE AGENCY They call it grooming. This new reality series sidles up to seven booking agents at the Wilhelmina Modeling Agency in Manhattan as they take the raw goods and mold them into some of the city's beautiful people. It's not always pretty.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Fox) AMERICAN IDOL The top 12 male contestants, including Sanjaya Malakar, the first Indian-American contestant and, at 17, the youngest man, perform in this two-hour episode. Others to watch include Sundance Head, whose father, Roy Head, had a No. 1 song in 1965 with ''Treat Her Right,'' and Brandon Rogers, who has sung backup with Christina Aguilera and Anastasia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>10 P.M. (VH1) THE AGENCY They call it grooming. This new reality series sidles up to seven booking agents at the Wilhelmina Modeling Agency in Manhattan as they take the raw goods and mold them into some of the city’s beautiful people. It’s not always pretty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>10 P.M. (VH1) THE AGENCY They call it grooming. This new reality series sidles up to seven booking agents at the Wilhelmina Modeling Agency in Manhattan as they take the raw goods and mold them into some of the city's beautiful people. It's not always pretty.</p>
        <p>8 P.M. (Fox) AMERICAN IDOL The top 12 male contestants, including Sanjaya Malakar, the first Indian-American contestant and, at 17, the youngest man, perform in this two-hour episode. Others to watch include Sundance Head, whose father, Roy Head, had a No. 1 song in 1965 with ''Treat Her Right,'' and Brandon Rogers, who has sung backup with Christina Aguilera and Anastasia.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (13) NEWS WAR: SECRETS, SOURCES AND SPIN In this four-part ''Frontline'' special, Lowell Bergman uses more than 80 interviews with media figures as well as behind-the-scenes access to news organizations to trace the recent history of American journalism - from the Nixon administration's attacks on the media and the post-Watergate popularity of the press to new obstacles presented by the war on terror and changing economics in the media business. Tonight, Mr. Bergman interviews journalists facing jail for refusing to reveal their sources and examines just how much the press can reveal about secret government programs in the war on terror without jeopardizing national security. ''News War'' will continue on Feb. 27 and March 27.</p>
        <p>9 P.M. (NBC) LAW &amp; ORDER: CRIMINAL INTENT When his wife is found murdered, a televangelist (Tom Arnold, in a guest role) has a hard time explaining the company he has been keeping. Meanwhile, Detective Goren (Vincent D'Onofrio) runs into his long-lost brother (Tony Goldwyn) while visiting their mother (Rita Moreno) in the hospital.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (13) HIP-HOP: BEYOND BEATS AND RHYTHM Masculinity. Sexism. Violence. Homophobia. These issues are the basis for hip-hop and rap music, says Byron Hurt, a quarterback cum activist and a self-proclaimed ''hip-hop head.'' In what he calls a ''loving critique'' created for ''Independent Lens,'' Mr. Hurt interviews rappers like Mos Def, Fat Joe, Chuck D, Jadakiss and Busta Rhymes; moguls including Russell Simmons and Chris Lighty; and young women at Spelman College, a historically black college in Atlanta, to examine the gritty intersection of culture, commerce and gender in all its complexity.</p>
        <p>10 P.M. (Golf) BIG BREAK VII: REUNION Sixteen memorable swingers (including Dave Gunas Jr. of Hebron, Conn., who golfed barefoot until he stepped on a bee last year) from this golf competition's previous six seasons bring back their A games for another chance to compete in a PGA championship tour. Here, a preview of what to expect when a new round begins on Feb. 25. KATHRYN SHATTUCK</p>
        <p>Tonight's TV Listings</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
