<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridge</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGE (CARD GAME)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DD1131F930A15757C0A962958260" item-length="340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A dark horse squad has taken the lead in the prestigious Von Zedtwitz Double Knockout Team Championship after five rounds of play. Jerry Goldberg of Yonkers, Bob Jaffe of Long Island City, Queens, and Jane Dillenberg, Nancy Kalow and Jeff Rothstein, all of Manhattan, form the only unbeaten team and are awaiting an opponent from the losers' bracket.</p>
        <p>Playing April 13 at the Honors Club, 42 East 74th Street, the Goldberg team, originally seeded 22d in the field of 34 teams, won by more than 90 imps against a strong group led by Charles Reich of Manhattan. In the diagramed deal a bad trump split was heavily punished.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A dark horse squad has taken the lead in the prestigious Von Zedtwitz Double Knockout Team Championship after five rounds of play. Jerry Goldberg of Yonkers, Bob Jaffe of Long Island City, Queens, and Jane Dillenberg, Nancy Kalow and Jeff Rothstein, all of Manhattan, form the only unbeaten team and are awaiting an opponent from the losers' bracket.</p>
        <p>Playing April 13 at the Honors Club, 42 East 74th Street, the Goldberg team, originally seeded 22d in the field of 34 teams, won by more than 90 imps against a strong group led by Charles Reich of Manhattan. In the diagramed deal a bad trump split was heavily punished.</p>
        <p>In one room, as shown, North-South reached four hearts after a transfer response to one no-trump. This would succeed with normal breaks, but Goldberg as East was happy to double. South won the spade lead with the ace and led to the heart king, confirming his suspicions about the bad split. He then tried the queen and another club, hoping for tricks in that suit. East ruffed and led the spade jack.</p>
        <p>Rothstein as West overtook with the queen and shifted to the diamond jack. This was ducked to South, who won and led a high club, throwing a diamond from the dummy. East ruffed and led the heart queen, and the closed hand was now useless. South had to lose one more trump trick and two diamond tricks, for a penalty of 800, a heavy punishment for reaching a normal contract.</p>
        <p>In the replay Dillenberg opened one club with the South hand, and West tried to take advantage of the vulnerability by jumping to two spades. Kalow bid three hearts as North, and East tried to apply pressure by bidding four spades. Perhaps he feared an opposing five-club contract, unaware that his partner held length in that suit.</p>
        <p>Four spades was doubled and could have been defeated by two tricks after a passive lead. But after the normal lead of the heart king West was able to escape for down one by establishing a heart trick in the East hand. The result was a gain of 14 imps to the Goldberg team en route to victory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
