<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Car Of Future Looks Much Like Today's</title>
    <meta content="11TRAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980712T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1030963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DE1531F932A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Car Of Future Looks Much Like Today's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Model of new New York City subway cars does not look significantly different from its predecessors on this outside, but exterior masks many changes on inside; changes include fold-up seats to accomodate wheelchairs, emergency intercom system that allows riders to talk to conductor, electronic maps and information displays, and new handrails (M)a</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first glance, New York City Transit's subway train of the future looks a lot like the train of the present.</p>
        <p>At least that was the impression of many of the people who gathered yesterday to see a wooden mock-up of the front half of the new subway car at the transit agency's maintenance yard on 207th Street in Inwood, Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At first glance, New York City Transit's subway train of the future looks a lot like the train of the present.</p>
        <p>At least that was the impression of many of the people who gathered yesterday to see a wooden mock-up of the front half of the new subway car at the transit agency's maintenance yard on 207th Street in Inwood, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A prototype of the train has already been running along the Eighth Avenue line, and the model on display yesterday incorporated changes that resulted from public comments about those cars.</p>
        <p>Some of the people who examined the new model noted yesterday that although it looked like other subway cars on the outside, its exterior masked many changes inside. Transit officials hope those changes will make for smoother riding in the future.</p>
        <p>The transit agency hopes to buy 1,081 of the cars, using them to replace older models on the lettered subway lines. Transit officials plan to have all the new cars in place on these lines by 2001.</p>
        <p>Richard F. Timone, a Bronx man who uses the subway primarily to shuttle between home and the doctor's office, said he liked the new design, except for one detail. ''There should be no bumps in the seats,'' Mr. Timone said. ''When you are as fat as me, that is really important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Timone was commenting on the sloping indentations in the new seats, one of several changes. Other innovations include fold-up seats to accommodate wheelchairs, an emergency intercom system that allows passengers to talk to the conductor, electronic maps and information displays and new handrails, including some that hang from the center of the train, and curved handholds.</p>
        <p>The changes were generally well received by many of the people who visited during the five-hour open house, though not everyone was pleased.</p>
        <p>William Stanford of the Bronx said he disliked the electronic technology in the train, which will, among other things, tell riders what stop is next. Transit officials hope the displays will carry advertisements, announcements, the time and other information for riders.</p>
        <p>''Forget these display messages,'' Mr. Stanford said. ''Come on, this is a train, not an answering machine or a clock. Do it the old way, not this new and confusing way.''</p>
        <p>He also called for something that is a rare commodity in New York City subway stations and on streets. ''Put bathrooms on the cars,'' he said. ''If you can do it on a Greyhound, you can do it on a train.''</p>
        <p>The open house attracted more than 100 people, mainly subway enthusiasts, retirees and schoolchildren who were off for the summer. Albert W. O'Leary, a spokesman for New York City Transit, said that in the next few weeks the agency planned to compile the answers to a 10-page questionnaire about the cars that visitors filled out. ''The point is to make our customers as happy as possible,'' Mr. O'Leary said.</p>
        <p>The full-scale mock-up was designed based on focus group suggestions and changes being made in other cities, transit officials said. The transit agency contracted with Sigi Meeslinger and Masamichi Udagawa of Antenna Design New York Inc. to develop the prototype.</p>
        <p>Mr. Udagawa said the new train's most important features were the new information display systems, including an electronic map that indicates the train's location at each stop and a monitor that tells riders inside a car which way the train is going and other information.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Leary said that although there are many changes to the new cars, riders can expect only so much, because ''fundamentally, when it comes out of the wash, it is still a big subway train.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 12, 1998, Sunday  An article yesterday about a new model of subway car to be introduced by New York City Transit over the next three years misstated the number of the cars the agency expects to buy. It is 100. (The figure of 1,081 referred to a different model that the agency has already ordered.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 12, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a new model of subway car to be introduced by New York City Transit over the next three years misstated the number of the cars the agency expects to buy. It is 100. (The figure of 1,081 referred to a different model that the agency has already ordered.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
