<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inflation Whimpers. What's Next for Fed?; New Stresses at Home and Abroad</title>
    <meta content="Y31ALAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, Alan (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDB123AF932A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inflation Whimpers. What's Next for Fed?; New Stresses at Home and Abroad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve and its chairman, Alan Greenspan, no longer have to worry about bringing inflation down sharply, but they face formidable challenge in keeping it down and in keeping economy on track amid powerful crosscurrents; some of issues Federal Reserve and Greenspan are concerned about include change in gross domestic product, increased wages and strong housing market, which is pushing up home prices; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Soviet Union collapsed, the makers of American foreign policy lost their lodestar. Similarly, the prospect of Federal budget surpluses after decades of deficits has transformed the debate over taxes and spending.</p>
        <p>Now, Alan Greenspan and his colleagues at the Federal Reserve seem to have reached a turning point of their own for monetary policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Soviet Union collapsed, the makers of American foreign policy lost their lodestar. Similarly, the prospect of Federal budget surpluses after decades of deficits has transformed the debate over taxes and spending.</p>
        <p>Now, Alan Greenspan and his colleagues at the Federal Reserve seem to have reached a turning point of their own for monetary policy.</p>
        <p>Having been driven since the late 1970's by a single-minded determination to squeeze inflation out of the economy, the central bank is now confronting the possibility that it has won -- at least for now -- its battle for price stability.</p>
        <p>But if the Fed and Mr. Greenspan, its chairman, no longer have to worry about bringing inflation down sharply, they face a formidable challenge in keeping it down and in keeping the economy on track amid powerful crosscurrents.</p>
        <p>The Government's report today that the economy grew at a real 4.3 percent annual rate in the fourth quarter was just the latest evidence that the domestic expansion continues to be so buoyant that it threatens to reignite big wage increases. Yet the Asian financial crisis seems certain to dampen American exports and bring a flood of cheaper imports, forcing many companies to hold down prices. That global pressure would tend to restrain inflation and even -- in the view of at least some analysts --  put the world in danger of deflation.</p>
        <p>''For most of the past 20 years, the challenges confronting monetary policy makers centered on addressing the question of how inflation could be brought down with as little economic disruption as possible,'' Mr. Greenspan said in a speech in Chicago this month. ''Given the progress that has been made in reducing inflation, and the very solid economic performance that this low-inflation environment has helped to promote, a new set of issues is now emerging on the policy agenda.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Greenspan has had to shift his sights from a single big target -- completing the process begun under his predecessor, Paul A. Volcker, of bringing inflation from double digits down to almost nothing -- to a welter of conflicting and often confusing pressures that could threaten a remarkable period of prosperity and stability.</p>
        <p>''The sense in which it is harder,'' said Alan S. Blinder, a former Fed vice chairman who is a professor at Princeton University, ''is that you now have a much more subtle task of fine-tuning, which Alan Greenspan is very good at.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the clearest sign of how deep the uncertainties run even in Mr. Greenspan's mind came in a single sentence during his testimony to the Senate Budget Committee on Thursday. Stressing the need to ''be vigilant to the re-emergence of destabilizing influences'' on an economy he characterized as exceptionally healthy, Mr. Greenspan cited a very broad spectrum of possibilities. From one side, he fretted about higher inflation; from the other, he was clearly just as worried about the risk of pressing ''the disinflation process too far, too fast.''</p>
        <p>Despite heady rates of growth -- the 4.3 percent fourth-quarter growth rate reported by the Government today was nearly twice what the Fed believes is sustainable without ultimately generating significantly higher inflation -- there is still almost no sign of widespread price increases.</p>
        <p>The measure of inflation contained within the report on the gross domestic product today found that prices rose just 1.5 percent in the fourth quarter, leaving the figure for all of 1997 at 2 percent, the lowest since 1965. The more widely quoted Consumer Price Index, excluding volatile food and energy prices, registered a rise of just 2.2 percent last year, also the smallest increase in 32 years.</p>
        <p>There is considerable debate among economists and even within the Fed about how much credit the central bank deserves for reducing the inflation rate. There is also widespread disagreement about whether prices are being held down only by a confluence of temporary factors such as intense competition in the computer industry, the cap on health care costs from the rise of managed care and the decline of import prices because of the strong dollar.</p>
        <p>But now the talk has turned from whether the Fed should take advantage of any economic downturn to push the inflation rate lower -- so-called opportunistic disinflation -- to whether inflation has already been essentially eradicated.</p>
        <p>A few economists are even worried about a deflation -- the broad decline in the prices of goods, services and assets -- that could make it extraordinarily difficult for some otherwise healthy businesses to meet their obligations and for many borrowers to pay their debts.</p>
        <p>''We're now getting to a point where a relevant question becomes whether the Fed wants inflation to go higher or lower,'' Mr. Blinder said. ''Relatively few people right now would say we want inflation higher, but if the C.P.I. were to drop another notch, to 1 percent, the question would become a very live one.''</p>
        <p>Given the imprecision of inflation gauges, the Fed must be very careful about any move to raise or lower interest rates, economists said.</p>
        <p>''It is quite possible that the actual inflation rate is near zero or even below zero because inflation estimates are not foolproof,'' said Sung Won Sohn, an economist at the Norwest Corporation. ''If they were to respond to the rising wage pressures by raising rates, there's a possibility the Fed could push the economy into deflation if it were already at zero inflation.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Sohn said, Mr. Greenspan is faced with a delicate balancing act.</p>
        <p>''To some extent it's easier to slaughter inflation, as chairman Volcker did in the 1980's,'' he said. ''You clearly know the direction you're going, and you have lots of room to maneuver if you make a mistake. That is no longer the case.''</p>
        <p>In many ways, the case for concern about resurgent inflation is clear cut. Unemployment, at 4.7 percent, is near a 25-year low. As employers struggle to find enough workers to help them meet strong demand, wage gains are starting to edge up, often the first step toward rising prices.</p>
        <p>But consumer prices have hardly budged, largely because companies have been able to offset rising costs through productivity gains from heavy investments in new equipment and technology. Intense competition in many industries has also restrained price increases.</p>
        <p>Although consumer confidence has fallen somewhat in the last month, it remains at historically high levels, suggesting that people remain willing to spend.</p>
        <p>The Fed has responded by keeping the short-term interest rates it controls steady for nearly a year. Mr. Greenspan said on Thursday that in keeping the Federal funds rate steady at 5.5 percent even as inflation has declined, the Fed has consciously been allowing the inflation-adjusted, or real, rate to drift up.</p>
        <p>But he acknowledged that strategy had had no significant restrictive impact on the economy because long-term interest rates have been falling.</p>
        <p>Indeed, lower long-term rates may well be stimulating economic activity. They make it cheaper for people to buy homes and cars and provide an incentive to refinance existing mortgages, which allows homeowners to lower their monthly payments or take out cash to spend elsewhere. As a result, key interest-sensitive sectors of the economy like housing have remained robust.</p>
        <p>Long-term rates have been falling in part because of declining inflationary expectations and in part because investors around the world have plowed money into United States Treasury securities as a haven during the Asian crisis.</p>
        <p>The Fed and most private economists are now counting on the Asia crisis to slow the economy sufficiently to avoid a continuing buildup in inflationary pressures.</p>
        <p>Many economists think the Asian crisis will slow the economy substantially this year, probably to around a 2.5 percent annual growth rate. ''Such a moderation would appear helpful at this juncture,'' Mr. Greenspan said.</p>
        <p>But in testimony today before the House Banking Committee, Mr. Greenspan raised a more worrisome specter, suggesting that growth might slow too much if the Asia financial crisis spreads.</p>
        <p>There is ''a small but not negligible probability,'' he said, ''that the upset in East Asia could have unexpectedly negative effects on Japan, Latin America and Eastern and Central Europe that in turn could have repercussions elsewhere, including the United States.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
