<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Things They Carried</title>
    <meta content="002BOWDET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/02/books/review/002BOWDET.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowden, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swofford, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jarhead (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Swofford, Anthony</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DC153DF931A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Things They Carried</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Jarhead': A Marine's Desert Song</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mark Bowden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowden, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Bowden reviews book Jarhead: A Marine's Chronicle of the Gulf War and Other Stories by Anthony Swofford; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JARHEAD</p>
        <p>A Marine's Chronicle of the Gulf War and Other Battles.</p>
        <p>By Anthony Swofford.</p>
        <p>260 pp. New York: Scribner. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Out of the 1991 war against Iraq comes Anthony Swofford, a Marine sniper, to say in his book that he had a ball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JARHEAD</p>
        <p>A Marine's Chronicle of the Gulf War and Other Battles.</p>
        <p>By Anthony Swofford.</p>
        <p>260 pp. New York: Scribner. $24.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has ever been a soldier, or spent time around them in an informal setting, knows that the unvarnished experience -- and the unvarnished language -- would take more than an army of punctilious editors to make presentable to polite society. Take a group of healthy, testosterone-drenched young men away from home, subject them to daily indignities, abuse and hardship; nurture their youthfully grandiose sense of omnipotence and invincibility and then arm them with terrifying modern weaponry (and teach them how to use it); move them from one remote place to another around the world (so old community and family ties are broken, and new ones outside their military unit have little chance to form); feed them a steady diet of macho conditioning and pornography and give them just enough money to get drunk, go forth and act out; immerse them in the astringent cynicism of the veteran grunt; thrust them into war zones where they must either kill or be killed; and you begin to understand the need for harsh codes of military justice.</p>
        <p>The true voices of soldiers are rarely heard, particularly since, after Vietnam, the military stopped letting reporters live with frontline units in the field. What we usually get these days is a spruced-up, ready-for-prime-time version of events. In his terrific new memoir, ''Jarhead,'' the former Marine sniper Anthony Swofford tells the story of a visit paid to his platoon by reporters in the Saudi desert in the months before Operation Desert Storm. His sergeant preps the unit for the show by issuing what Swofford refers to as a ''gag order'':</p>
        <p>''Listen up,'' the sergeant says. ''I've gone over this already. But the captain wants you to hear it again. Basically, don't get specific. Say you can shoot from far away. Say you are highly trained, that there are no better shooters in the world than marine snipers. Say you're excited to be here and you believe in the mission and that we'll annihilate the Iraqis. Take off your shirts and show your muscles.''</p>
        <p>Years later, out of uniform or promoted to some more dignified rank, old soldiers clean up their memories. It is considered noblesse oblige. Reality gets filtered through a gauzy lens of patriotism, pride and the overall dignity of the cause.</p>
        <p>Rare is the marine who is willing to share the raw experience, and rarer still is one like Swofford -- the marine who can really write. ''Jarhead'' is some kind of classic, a bracing memoir of the 1991 Persian Gulf war that will go down with the best books ever written about military life. It is certainly the most honest memoir I have read from a participant in any recent war. Swofford writes with humor, anger and great skill. His prose is alive with ideas and feeling, and at times soars like poetry. He captures the hilarity, tedium, horniness and loneliness of the long prewar desert deployment, and then powerfully records the experience of his war. As he moves through a nightmare landscape of exploding ordnance, raining petroleum, the threat of invisible killing gases, and death, his terror and his joy are one.</p>
        <p>Violence, sex and male camaraderie are the big draw for many adolescent men who enlist. As a 14-year-old, Swofford was moved by pictures of the bombing of the Marine barracks in Lebanon in 1984: ''The marines were all sizes and all colors, all dirty and exhausted and hurt, and they were men, and I was a boy falling in love with manhood. I understood that manhood had to do with war, and war with manhood, and to no longer just be a son, I needed someday to fight.''</p>
        <p>But the clincher comes three years later, from a Marine recruiter: ''He gleefully talked to me about buying sex in the Philippines and Italy and Sweden and Panama -- information my mother would never see in the brochures. The recruiter guaranteed me I could book a threesome for 40 American dollars in Olongapo. . . . I'd just turned 17. I'd had sex three times. . . . I was sold.'' Swofford also felt that he had a family tradition to uphold. His father served in Vietnam; his uncle died during peacetime in the Marines; his grandfather served in the Army Air Forces during World War II.</p>
        <p>Swofford begins his story as an older man unable to fit back into his old desert cammies, and at the end he is again a sobered adult, fully civilian once more, no longer able to relate to his old marine buddies. ''Jarhead'' is a coming-of-age story, an account of a wild passage familiar to millions of young men but rarely so well revealed.</p>
        <p>There are more than 150,000 American soldiers in the deserts around Iraq as these words are written. Swofford remembers back to August 1990, when his unit -- the Surveillance and Target Acquisition Platoon, scout/snipers, of the Second Battalion, Seventh Marines -- is put on standby for deployment to Saudi Arabia after Saddam Hussein's forces rumbled into Kuwait. As far as he and his buddies are concerned, the geopolitics of the situation boil down to fighting and dying for old white guys ''and others who have billions of dollars to gain or lose in the oil fields,'' but the perceived injustice is hardly a deterrent. They are gleeful. The news of their impending deployment prompts them to hold a drunken war-movie marathon. They particularly like Vietnam War movies, most of which are purportedly antiwar.</p>
        <p>''But actually,'' Swofford explains, ''Vietnam War films are all pro-war, no matter what the supposed message, what Kubrick or Coppola or Stone intended. . . . The magic brutality of the films celebrates the terrible and despicable beauty of their fighting skills. Fight, rape, war, pillage, burn. Filmic images of death and carnage are pornography for the military man.''</p>
        <p>Swofford's war was brief, but long enough for him to nearly be killed several times, and for him to witness the horrid slaughter of the overmatched Iraqi forces. There is one haunting, surreal scene in which he stumbles alone into an encampment of Iraqis who have all been killed, dismembered and partly incinerated around their campfire, frozen in the postures of their last moments of life:</p>
        <p>''I could bend at the waist, close my eyes, and try to join these men in their tight dead circle, but I am not yet one of them. I must not close my eyes. . . . The presence of so much death reminds me that I'm alive, whatever awaits me to the north. I realize I may never again be so alive. I can see everything and nothing -- this moment with the dead men has made my past worth living and my future, always uncertain, now has value.''</p>
        <p>This kind of writing can easily become pretentious -- indeed, the ''literary'' soldier keeping notes for his eventual novel is a joke in most military units. Swofford was always a different kind of marine, one who spent years as a child living in Japan, who curled up not just with a book -- most soldiers do a lot of reading -- but with Céline or Homer or Camus. But Swofford is never pretentious. His vision is unsparing and honest, and his emotions ring true.</p>
        <p>Relish for battle is experienced by many soldiers, even those repelled by the idea of it. It is a truth that we don't like to face about ourselves, or about the young men who bloody their hands for us in this violent world. Celebrating the war's end, Swofford and his buddies, relieved and exhausted, engorged with pagan glee, explode captured enemy ordnance in the smoking desert and fire off the ammunition from Iraqi machine guns:</p>
        <p>''We fire and fire the AK's, a factory of firepower, the fierce scream of metal downrange and discharged cartridges and sand flying everywhere, now all of us shooting in the air, shooting straight up and dancing in circles, dancing on one foot, with the mad, desperate hope that the rounds will never descend, screaming, screaming at ourselves and each other and the dead Iraqis surrounding us, screaming at ourselves and the dead world surrounding us, screaming at ourselves, at the corpses surrounding us and the dead world. . . . And I know we'll soon carry that mad scream home with us, but that no one will listen because they'll want to heard the crowd-roar of victory.''</p>
        <p>In other words, the raw thrill of killing and escaping danger will be subsumed by the war's rationale, the politics, the rightness of the cause.</p>
        <p>''The warrior becomes the hero, and the society celebrates the death and destruction of war, two things the warrior never celebrates. The warrior celebrates the fact of having survived, not of killing Japs or Krauts or gooks or Russkies or ragheads. That large and complex emotional mess called national victory holds no sway for the warrior. It is necessary to remind civilians of this fact, to make them hear the voice of the warrior.''</p>
        <p>That voice isn't pretty -- it's just terribly and despicably beautiful.</p>
        <p>Mark Bowden is the author of ''Black Hawk Down'' and ''Killing Pablo.'' His most recent book is ''Finders Keepers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark Bowden is the author of ''Black Hawk Down'' and ''Killing Pablo.'' His most recent book is ''Finders Keepers.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
