<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q.&amp;A.</title>
    <meta content="31QNA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Garden Q.&amp;A." name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="947367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Garden Q.&amp;A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4DA1E3AF932A05754C0A961958260" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q.&amp;A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Disappointing Carrots</p>
        <p>Q.  We were looking forward to superior flavor from our home-grown carrots, but so far the ones we have harvested taste worse than the ones from the store. I know they are fresh: we're picking them as soon as they are ready. Is there something wrong with our soil?</p>
        <p>A.  Carrot flavor is almost entirely genetically determined, so your problem is probably not in the soil but in your choice of variety or in that otherwise tasty phrase ''as soon as they are ready.'' Amsterdam and Nantes carrots are sweeter and juicier than Chantenays, which are the best storage types, or Danvers, which have only durability to recommend them. But no matter what kind you grow, maturity is all; those little guys sold as ''baby'' carrots are full-grown miniatures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Disappointing Carrots</p>
        <p>Q.  We were looking forward to superior flavor from our home-grown carrots, but so far the ones we have harvested taste worse than the ones from the store. I know they are fresh: we're picking them as soon as they are ready. Is there something wrong with our soil?</p>
        <p>A.  Carrot flavor is almost entirely genetically determined, so your problem is probably not in the soil but in your choice of variety or in that otherwise tasty phrase ''as soon as they are ready.'' Amsterdam and Nantes carrots are sweeter and juicier than Chantenays, which are the best storage types, or Danvers, which have only durability to recommend them. But no matter what kind you grow, maturity is all; those little guys sold as ''baby'' carrots are full-grown miniatures.</p>
        <p>Sugars are the carrots' winter energy supply, and they don't start building it up in quantity until after the roots are full size. Before this happens, the carrots have developed most of their genetic allotment of turpenoids, the compounds that give them their characteristic taste. There is a reason the word sounds like turpentine, and until sugar balance is achieved, turpenoids are something only a carrot could love.</p>
        <p>The only readiness test is taste, but carrots will keep in the soil for weeks after their best flavor is attained, especially if the weather is cool. They won't keep improving, though, and will eventually become woody.</p>
        <p>Pull the roots in the evening; they build up sugar during the day.</p>
        <p>Snail Patrol</p>
        <p>Several colorful and pleading letters arrived in the spring from readers plagued with slugs and snails. The problem may have abated for a while with the drought, but with the rains they will be back, as inevitable as death, taxes and telemarketers at dinnertime. Snails and slugs cannot be vanquished, but you can control them.</p>
        <p>Not counting predators, of which there are mercifully many (ducks, geese, chickens, toads and snakes, among others) control methods include barriers, hand picking, traps and poison.</p>
        <p>The poison is metaldehyde, a chemical that is also toxic to mammals and birds. The traps are filled with something to attract the slugs, most commonly beer, and are buried just below ground level. Slugs come to drink, fall in and drown. Traps can often be effective, but can sometimes attract more snails than they kill, thus compounding rather than solving the problem.</p>
        <p>Hand picking is self-descriptive: you wander around at night, when slugs and snails are most active, finding them with a flashlight and plucking them off the plants. Then, to kill them, you either sprinkle them with salt or drop them in a can of soapy water. Hand picking is time consuming, messy, and in the case of the salt, somewhat grisly.</p>
        <p>The most commonly recommended barrier is diatomaceous earth, the powdery remains of prehistoric shellfish. It feels smooth to the touch but is unbearably gritty to slugs and snails, which will not crawl over it when it's dry. Unfortunately, once it becomes wet it does no good, so it's useless just when you need it most. Cedar chips are a better bet: dampness doesn't soften them and the odor also seems to be repellent.</p>
        <p>But the best barrier is copper, which reacts electrochemically with the beasts' slime so they will not cross it. Strips of copper at least 1 1/2-inches wide around a raised bed will keep lettuce safe in a rainstorm, which is really saying something. Be sure to install the strips in dry weather and to patrol the bed the first couple of nights. The pests can't get in, but they can't get out, either.</p>
        <p>Sources of slug traps and copper strips include Worm's Way, 7850 North Highway 37, Bloomington, Ind. 47404; (800) 274-9676 (free catalogue), and Peaceful Valley Farm Supply, P.O. Box 2209, Grass Valley, Calif. 95945; (916) 272-4769 (free catalogue).</p>
        <p>Scrawny Glories</p>
        <p>Q.  Every year, I grow morning glories in tubs on my roof. For the last few years, the vines have had the same problem: after they've gotten quite tall and started flowering, the bottom leaves turn yellow and drop off. New growth doesn't re-cover the naked stems. The tops of the plants look normal and healthy, but the whole effect is less than pretty. Is there anything I can do?</p>
        <p>A.  Attrition of the lowest leaves of annual vines is normal -- they're just relatively old. But if the problem extends up more than two feet or so, and it has been more than three years since you changed the soil, plan to use fresh earth next year.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, try to be consistent about watering; plants under drought stress often drop their lower leaves. Consider using an organic mulch like compost, which will conserve moisture, help keep roots cool and protect against the distant possibility that a fungus like Verticillium is being splashed from the soil onto the leaves.</p>
        <p>There is also a chance your plants are suffering from ozone damage, though the discoloration it causes is usually whitish, not yellow. If your roof is in a high-traffic area, exhaust rising from the hot streets could be bothering your morning glories as much as it is bothering you.</p>
        <p>Thrills in the Mail</p>
        <p>Readers seeking advice have taken to sending samples of their afflictions: diseased leaves, pressed bugs, bits of discolored bark. The senders are right in believing that these are important aids to correct diagnosis, but they are misguided in thinking this is the place to send them.</p>
        <p>The people equipped, nay eager, to receive this sort of material are the master gardeners and extension agents who work for land-grant universities in the outreach offices known as cooperative extensions.</p>
        <p>In New York City, there is Cornell, but every state has a participating school, and almost every county has an extension office. They were originally set up to make sure farmers had access to the latest agricultural technology, but home gardeners are equally welcome to avail themselves of this happy example of their tax dollars at work.</p>
        <p>Finding the telephone number of an extension office is not always easy; in New York, it is listed under Cornell Cooperative Extension, but the one that helps me in Maine is listed under ''Extension'' in my local directory.</p>
        <p>Remember: Words only, please, for Garden Q. &amp;A.</p>
        <p>Address questions to Garden Q.&amp; A., The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036, or to gardening@nytimes.com for E-mail. Those of general interest will be published. Unpublished questions cannot be answered individually.</p>
        <p>Garden Q.&amp;A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
