<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Candidate's Record; Perot Pursued Charges Against Official for Years</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="539043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEWITT, KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLY, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARMITAGE, RICHARD (ASST SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DC163BF93BA15755C0A964958260" item-length="1726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Candidate's Record; Perot Pursued Charges Against Official for Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DE WITT with MICHAEL KELLY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The rivalry between Ross Perot and Richard L. Armitage, the senior Pentagon official on prisoner of war issues in the Reagan Administration, is now a well-known part of the lore surrounding Mr. Perot's candidacy.</p>
        <p>To counter the impression that he is vengeful and prone to vendettas, Mr.  Perot has depicted his involvement with investigations of Mr. Armitage as an isolated incident motivated by patriotic concern and inspired largely by a chance meeting with a police officer who brought his suspicions of Mr. Armitage to Mr. Perot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The rivalry between Ross Perot and Richard L. Armitage, the senior Pentagon official on prisoner of war issues in the Reagan Administration, is now a well-known part of the lore surrounding Mr. Perot's candidacy.</p>
        <p>To counter the impression that he is vengeful and prone to vendettas, Mr.  Perot has depicted his involvement with investigations of Mr. Armitage as an isolated incident motivated by patriotic concern and inspired largely by a chance meeting with a police officer who brought his suspicions of Mr. Armitage to Mr. Perot.</p>
        <p>But a review of the matter shows that Mr. Perot's pursuit of accusations against Mr. Armitage stretched over more than three years and involved an elaborate set of purposeful contacts.</p>
        <p>As recently as Wednesday, in an interview on the NBC News program "Today," Mr. Perot left the impression that his interest in Mr. Armitage began and largely ended with accusations brought, unsolicited, to him by a police officer from Arlington, Va. in 1986.</p>
        <p>"An undercover police officer brought me a complete file," Mr. Perot told the interviewer, Bryant Gumbel. 'I Handed It to the F.B.I.'</p>
        <p>"People said he wanted to talk to me, asked me to call him, set up a meeting," Mr. Perot said. "I asked him if he wanted to see me. He came to my hotel room. He presented this information. And here is what I did with it: I gave it to the appropriate law-enforcement authorities, walked away from it, and that's it. Now, that is not chasing down information on someone. That's having someone bring it to you. And I handed it to the F.B.I., and that's the end of that."</p>
        <p>In interviews and public statements since he became an unannounced Presidential contender in late February, Mr. Perot has often described his meeting with the police officer, James L. Badey, as being at Mr. Badey's instigation, a mysterious encounter in which Mr. Badey appeared out of the night, knocked on Mr. Perot's hotel room door, and handed over a file on Mr. Armitage. But after Mr. Badey began challenging that account in interviews over the last few weeks, Mr. Perot began to back off his earlier story, saying, when pressed, that he could not really recall the details.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Perot did not drop the matter after simply passing the information on to the F.B.I. For more than three years after this initial encounter, he sought information about Mr. Armitage, then the Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs, and encouraged Government investigations into the case.</p>
        <p>James Squires, Mr. Perot's campaign spokesman, says Mr. Perot took up the issue with the Vice President, George Bush, with the Secretary of Defense and with the F.B.I. director at the time, William H. Webster. He also broached the matter with reporters. He served as a conduit for a wide array of assertions about Mr. Armitage, supplying, among other items, information to the F.B.I. in 1986 on Mr. Armitage's relationship with a Vietnamese-American restaurant owner, a woman who had been convicted of running an illicit gambling operation, a football pool, in Northern Virginia. Cleared After Investigation</p>
        <p>An F.B.I. investigation cleared Mr. Armitage of any criminal activity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Armitage, who now coordinates United States aid to the former Soviet Union, has said he was a longtime friend of the Vietnamese-American woman and her family. He acknowledges that he erred in writing a recommendation of leniency for the woman on Pentagon stationery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Badey, the police officer who provided information to Mr. Perot, said in an interview on Wednesday that he had discovered the connection between Mr. Armitage and the Vietnamese-American woman and had become frustrated by the lack of response when he had given the information to "the respective Federal authorities." Mr. Badey said that he put out word among "activists and concerned citizens" that he would be willing to share his information with someone who could make the Government pay attention.</p>
        <p>"I'm sure someone along the line said, 'Would you share this with Perot,' " said Mr. Badey. "In the summer of '86, he called and we had a conversation. He said, 'Do you want to share this information.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Badey said he met Mr. Perot in the Texan's room at the Madison Hotel here. "I just went over and knocked on his door," he said. Elaborate Conspiracy Theory</p>
        <p>In that same period, Mr. Perot was also in touch with Daniel Sheehan about Mr. Armitage. Mr. Sheehan is general counsel to a not-for-profit investigative group in Washington, the Christic Institute, which uses civil suits as its primary weapon in support of leftist political causes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Squires says Mr. Perot cannot remember who initiated his contact with Mr. Sheehan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan had named Mr. Armitage as a defendant in a Federal civil lawsuit that also charged two dozen leaders of the contra rebels in Nicaragua and a number of former Central Intelligence Agency and military officials with being part of an elaborate conspiracy. The suit said Mr. Armitage had been involved in arms and narcotics smuggling in Southeast Asia in the 1970's and that this was tied to financing for covert activities stretching from Central America to the Middle East.</p>
        <p>In 1988, Judge James L. King of Federal district court dismissed the suit as baseless, accused Mr. Sheehan of fraud and fined the Christic Institute $1 million, a verdict later upheld by the Supreme Court. A Call From Perot</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan said Mr. Perot first telephoned him on Oct. 21, 1986, after seeing Mr. Sheehan giving televised testimony before a Congressional committee. "He said, 'Hello, this is Ross Perot. I heard you've got all kinds of important information about some really bad actors. I've gotten wind of the same stuff, and we need to talk about it.' "</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Sheehan, the suspicions about Mr. Armitage were only a small part of a gigantic conspiracy he described as arching over several decades and continents, stretching from the Vietnam War to the Iran-contra affair, with stops at various smaller wars and scandals in between.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan is the principal author of that conspiracy theory, an elaborate construct involving assertions about a cabal of Nicaraguan contra leaders, drug lords, United States military officers, intelligence agents and other Government officials. Mr. Sheehan claims this group, which he calls the Secret Team, had plotted and executed something called the Enterprise, a vast and almost impossibly complicated scheme of smuggling drugs and weapons, assassinations and the corruption of United States foreign policy. In his suit, Mr. Sheehan's written explanation of the conspiracy consumes 287 pages of densely plotted story.</p>
        <p>Mr. Squires said today that Mr. Perot met Mr. Sheehan only once and that he "had no influence at all on his feelings about Armitage." Mr. Squires could not say whether Mr. Perot accepted Mr. Sheehan's conspiracy theory. 'Only Contact They Ever Had'</p>
        <p>"Mr. Perot remembered Sheehan spilling out his ideas about what was going on in Nicaragua," said Mr. Squires. "That's the only contact they ever had, that plane ride, and Perot remembers that as a conversation primarily being about Nicaragua. He does not have a precise recollection that mirrors what Sheehan's theory was. It's very difficult for me to characterize what Mr. Perot believed or did not believe. I cannot characterize what he believed."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheehan, however, says there at least six occasions, giving dates and circumstances, when he discussed the conspiracy theory with Mr. Perot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot, Mr. Sheehan said, proposed taking information to George Bush, then the Vice President. But Mr. Sheehan suggested to Mr. Perot that Mr. Bush was part of the conspiracy and advised Mr. Perot to go instead to the F.B.I. Director, Mr. Webster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot did, and he apparently took Mr. Sheehan's accusations to several other high Government officials, including Mr. Bush, as well.</p>
        <p>"I believe he had repeated them to a number of people in Washington, to Bill Webster, to people in the White House and to the Secretary of Defense," said Oliver B. (Buck) Revell, who was then the assistant deputy director of the F.B.I. in charge of field investigations, and is now the chief of the agency's Dallas bureau.</p>
        <p>When President Bush nominated Mr. Armitage in April 1989 to be Secretary of the Army, Mr. Revell authorized a standard White House investigation into the nomination, including the charges about him that Mr. Perot had raised with Mr. Webster.</p>
        <p>Mr. Revell said he was speaking on the Armitage matter because Mr. Armitage had asked him to and because he felt strongly that Mr. Armitage had been wrongly accused and unfairly treated. "I don't blame Armitage for being sick of the whole thing," he said. "When you get down to questions of a man's character like this, based on wild charges, it's pretty tough."</p>
        <p>He added: "I have never found anything the Christics have said of any substance to be accurate. They follow an agenda that has nothing to do with the facts, and it's unfortunate that people give credence to this sort of stuff."</p>
        <p>The outcome of the F.B.I. investigation was "absolutely no evidence of complicity in drug smuggling on the part of Mr. Armitage or that he was covering up the existence of M.I.A.'s," or of any criminal activity whatsoever, Mr. Revell said. "I don't blame Perot for this; if he had allegations of this sort, he had not only a right but an obligation to bring them forward," Mr. Revell said. "But I think the whole thing was unfair to Armitage."</p>
        <p>On May 25, 1989, Mr. Armitage withdrew himself from consideration for the job of Secretary of the Army. "He knew this stuff was going to continue, and he had already been through Iran-contra, the Christic stuff and our investigation, and I think he felt it just wasn't worth it any more," Mr. Revell said.</p>
        <p>In an interview this week, Mr. Armitage said the suggestions of impropriety "have been investigated and found groundless," and then, referring to Mr. Perot, he added: "There's no there there. Why am I being pilloried by this guy?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Squires said Mr. Perot "had obviously concluded after getting that information that what he saw in it disqualified Mr. Armitage from continuing in high Government office and he made that clear to Mr. Armitage and to other people in the Government."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
