<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concrete Work, Big or Little, Requires Special Materials</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="539409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCRETE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Concrete</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D81630F93BA15755C0A964958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concrete Work, Big or Little, Requires Special Materials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST minor flaws in concrete, like flaking, pitting, cracks and chipped corners, can be repaired easily if one knows which mending materials to choose and how to apply them.</p>
        <p>Flaking or scaling, in which the surface of concrete sloughs off like peeling paint, usually results when concrete is smoothed excessively during pouring. If the problem is minor -- that is, leaving the surface still virtually smooth -- sweep, vacuum and scrub the concrete with a wire brush and a solution of strong household detergent and water. Repeat the procedure with a fiber brush and then rinse with clean water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST minor flaws in concrete, like flaking, pitting, cracks and chipped corners, can be repaired easily if one knows which mending materials to choose and how to apply them.</p>
        <p>Flaking or scaling, in which the surface of concrete sloughs off like peeling paint, usually results when concrete is smoothed excessively during pouring. If the problem is minor -- that is, leaving the surface still virtually smooth -- sweep, vacuum and scrub the concrete with a wire brush and a solution of strong household detergent and water. Repeat the procedure with a fiber brush and then rinse with clean water.</p>
        <p>When the concrete is dry, apply a commercial penetrating sealer like Thompson's Water Seal Concrete Protector or Amstone Concrete Sealer. Use a paint brush or a garden-hose attachment, which is available with some sealers. A homemade remedy is to mix equal parts of turpentine and boiled linseed oil and apply two coats of the mixture to the concrete, allowing each to soak in thoroughly.</p>
        <p>Sealer or the turpentine-oil mix should be applied to outdoor concrete annually to keep moisture from entering it. Water inside concrete can freeze and expand, causing the concrete to crack. Painted concrete will not accept sealer. To protect those surfaces from moisture, repaint them.</p>
        <p>Fixing major flaking, pitting and other conditions that produce shallow damage to concrete requires resurfacing. Use a self-bonding, cement-based resurfacing compound. Two common brands are Amstone Top 'N Bond and Bondex Concrete Patcher and Resurfacer. Both come in powder form, for mixing with water.</p>
        <p>Resurfacing compound is intended for applying in a single layer generally no more than a half-inch thick. First sweep and wash the surface as described, then rinse it thoroughly with plain water.</p>
        <p>Before the concrete dries, mix and apply the compound according to the instructions, using a large mason's trowel or wood masonry float. When spreading resurfacing compound, make broad arcing sweeps with the trowel or float. Keep the leading edge raised slightly to prevent it from digging in, but press hard enough with the tool to force the compound into the pores and to squeeze out excess air.</p>
        <p>When finished, scratch the compound lightly with a broom to create a slightly ridged nonslip surface. Do that neatly, because the pattern of the bristles will show. Then allow the compound to cure according to the directions, usually for 24 hours.</p>
        <p>To patch cracked concrete and to fill holes and repair chipped steps, the easiest material to use is a fast-setting concrete-patching compound containing vinyl or acrylic latex. A popular brand is Mr. Mac's Concrete Fix.  For cracks and holes, begin by chiseling away all loose concrete from the damaged area with a hammer and cold chisel. Slope the sides of the area with the chisel so that the area to be filled is larger at the bottom than at the surface. Wear safety goggles and gloves to avoid injury when hammering.</p>
        <p>Afterward, scrub the area and remove dust and debris by brushing, vacuuming or blowing with fireplace bellows. The directions for some compounds recommend scrubbing with paint thinner or another solvent, instead of detergent and water. Mix the compound with water, following directions.</p>
        <p>Use a thin mixture for cracks and a thicker blend for holes. Dampen the area, if the directions specify, and apply the compound with a mason's trowel. When filling a crack, force compound into it with the trowel's edges. Complete the repair by smoothing the surface of the patch, and allow the compound to cure before stepping on it.</p>
        <p>To repair chipped steps, chisel away any cracked and crumbling concrete from the damaged area and clean the concrete. Then make a form -- one or two boards wrapped smoothly with plastic sheeting -- to place against the step to contain the repair.</p>
        <p>To make smoothing easier, the top of the form should be level with the top of the step being repaired. Place the form against the step and brace it with heavy weights like stones or concrete blocks. Mix a thick batch of patching compound and fill the damaged area with it. Smooth and compress the surface with a trowel.</p>
        <p>For larger repairs like restoring broken steps or a sidewalk slab, use ordinary concrete mix, which is sold in bags. They contain all the necessary dry ingredients, namely portland cement, sand and gravel. Only water is needed. Remove the broken concrete from the area and clean the sides. Build a sturdy form to contain the repair -- forms for concrete can be coated with oil instead of plastic -- and anchor it with stakes driven into the ground.</p>
        <p>Clean the sides of the damaged area and brush them free of dust. After preparing the concrete mix, brush the sides of the area with concrete-bonding liquid. Next, shovel the concrete into the form and stab the filled area several times with the point of a trowel to settle it. Level the surface of the repair by dragging a board across it, using the top edges of the form as a guide. Hold the board on edge across the form and move it back and forth with a sawing motion as you slide it.</p>
        <p>Smooth the concrete with a trowel or a float after it has stiffened for about an hour and an impression made with the thumb no longer fills with water. Slide a curved metal edging tool called an edger between the concrete and the form to separate the two and then round over the sharp edges of the concrete.</p>
        <p>Remove the form after 24 hours, but keep the repair damp for about five days, or until the concrete has completely cured. During this time, stay off the step.  HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
