<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Denyce Graves in 'Carmen,' Her Met Debut</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OPERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN OPERA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOMMASINI, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRACE, DENYCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIZET, GEORGES (1838-75)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CARMEN (OPERA)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DC143BF93AA35753C1A963958260" item-length="442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Denyce Graves in 'Carmen,' Her Met Debut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOMMASINI, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not often that a crew from "60 Minutes" covers a debut at the Metropolitan Opera. But Denyce Graves, a mezzo-soprano who made her debut in the title role of Bizet's "Carmen" on Saturday night, has lived a quintessential American success story.</p>
        <p>Raised in a black ghetto of Washington, Ms. Graves was working as a secretary, close to giving up on her operatic ambitions, when a chance to audition for the Houston Grand Opera came. That led to engagements in Europe, eventually a "Carmen" at Covent Garden with Placido Domingo and now, the Met. The pressures on her must have been as intense as the expectations were high. But for the most part, she met them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not often that a crew from "60 Minutes" covers a debut at the Metropolitan Opera. But Denyce Graves, a mezzo-soprano who made her debut in the title role of Bizet's "Carmen" on Saturday night, has lived a quintessential American success story.</p>
        <p>Raised in a black ghetto of Washington, Ms. Graves was working as a secretary, close to giving up on her operatic ambitions, when a chance to audition for the Houston Grand Opera came. That led to engagements in Europe, eventually a "Carmen" at Covent Garden with Placido Domingo and now, the Met. The pressures on her must have been as intense as the expectations were high. But for the most part, she met them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Graves has a classic mezzo-soprano voice with dusky colorings and a wide range, from her chesty low voice to her gleaming top notes. She is a compelling stage actress who exuded the sensuality that any Carmen must have but few do. If anything, Ms. Graves underestimates her charisma. She didn't need to do all that standard-issue hip-swiveling to entice Don Jose. Much more effective was the moment when after her arrest outside the tobacco factory in Seville, sitting on a table with her hands tied behind her back, she slowly lifted her skirt above her knees with her teeth. From that moment, Ms. Graves had the Met audience enthralled.</p>
        <p>That said, there was some cause for concern in her performance. There were signs -- pitch that sometimes turned sharp, some inadequately supported midrange singing -- that Ms. Graves is pushing her voice beyond its limits. Her innate sound is clear and vibrant, so she doesn't have to force to project. She need only have listened to her Don Jose, Richard Margison, for a cautionary example of what can happen. Mr. Margison has a hefty physique and a voice to match: a bright, ringing sound. But he seems locked into singing everything full out. He basically ignored the pianissimo turns of phrase that Bizet asked for in the "Flower Song."</p>
        <p>There were two other debuts of note. Singing Micaela was the Italian soprano Barbara Frittoli, whose creamy, lyrical voice turned a bit hard-edged when she delivered the forte top notes that cap Micaela's Act III aria, yet overall, Ms. Frittoli's performance was sensitive and involving. In the role of Zuniga was a young American bass, Richard Bernstein, who with his trim, dark looks and resonant voice, has Don Giovanni written all over him.</p>
        <p>The excellent Russian baritone Sergei Leiferkus sang Escamillo. The conductor, John Fiore, elicited a rather unsettled, poorly balanced performance from the Met orchestra. But the news was Ms. Graves, who received a tumultuous standing ovation.  MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
