<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haves and Have-Nots Revisited</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GENEVA (SWITZERLAND)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANDLER, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Geneva</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DF113EF93AA35753C1A963958260" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haves and Have-Nots Revisited</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LANDLER, MARK</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Oct. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Visitors can hardly miss the theme of Telecom 95. The slogan "Connect!" appears on everything from giant placards to palm-sized telephone calling cards at the quadrenniel meeting of the international telecommunications industry, which continues through Wednesday. But in the view of some skeptics, a better slogan might have been "disconnect."</p>
        <p>Although more than 50 countries constructed elaborate national pavilions to illustrate the explosive growth of their telecommunications industries, the poorest nations of the world are clearly not sharing in the wealth. According to a study by the International Telecommunication Union, which sponsors the convention, the poorest 48 countries are falling even further behind developed nations in the growth of telecommunications infrastructure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Visitors can hardly miss the theme of Telecom 95. The slogan "Connect!" appears on everything from giant placards to palm-sized telephone calling cards at the quadrenniel meeting of the international telecommunications industry, which continues through Wednesday. But in the view of some skeptics, a better slogan might have been "disconnect."</p>
        <p>Although more than 50 countries constructed elaborate national pavilions to illustrate the explosive growth of their telecommunications industries, the poorest nations of the world are clearly not sharing in the wealth. According to a study by the International Telecommunication Union, which sponsors the convention, the poorest 48 countries are falling even further behind developed nations in the growth of telecommunications infrastructure.</p>
        <p>The hard facts do not invalidate the central theme of Telecom 95 -- that digital technology is revolutionizing telecommunications and erasing the boundaries that separate the telephone, computer and media industries. But the revolution's inequality does take some of the shine off a business that has celebrated itself here as both a one-stop shop for the Information Age and a force for positive political change in the world.</p>
        <p>"The present reality is that the technology gap between developed and developing nations is actually widening," said Nelson Mandela, the President of South Africa, who spoke at the gathering's opening ceremony. "Most of the world has no experience of what readily accessible communications can do for society and the economy."</p>
        <p>Even the most enthusiastic of industry executives acknowledged that the world could find itself divided into telecom "haves" and "have-nots." Michael T. Masin, vice chairman of the GTE Corporation, described telecommunications in a speech on Thursday as a "liberation technology." But he conceded that some major regions of the world, notably Africa, had not benefited from its emancipating influence.</p>
        <p>In fact, the rate of growth of telephone lines in African countries like Chad, Zaire and Niger, badly lags behind the growth even in other developing countries like China, Egypt and India. The I.T.U., an agency of the United Nations, has organized a new development fund called Worldtel that aims to help poor countries build rudimentary telephone networks.</p>
        <p>Pekka Tarjanne, the Secretary General of the I.T.U., said Worldtel hoped to raise $500 million from public and private sources in the next year. "These are countries that need help to pull themselves out of their misery," he said.</p>
        <p>But some countries may be beyond help, at least for now. Bert de Graeve, a vice president of Alcatel Trade International, a division of Alcatel-Alsthom, the French telecom giant, which specializes in bringing phone service to developing countries, said that companies had little incentive to invest in Africa because of political instability on much of the continent and a dearth of investors willing to share the risk of building networks there.</p>
        <p>In the telephone-rich economies of Western Europe and the United States, there are no lack of companies vying to offer services -- particularly to high-volume business customers. The current craze is the multinational alliance: a group of companies that pool their communications networks, marketing and sales forces to offer one set of services to customers across several geographic markets.</p>
        <p>MCI Communications and BT (the former British Telecommunications) promoted their joint venture, called Concert. The Sprint Corporation and its two European partners, France Telecom and Deutsche Telekom, sought to allay fears that government regulators would spike their proposed venture, Phoenix. And AT&amp;T tried to explain its World Partners venture, a loose federation of telephone companies from Europe and Asia.</p>
        <p>But while these alliances look and sound formidable, customers who do business with them are considerably less enchanted.</p>
        <p>"Most alliances are almost worthless," said Arthur F. Cipolla, the director of telecommunications and information security at Motorola. He said the existing alliances have been consistently unable to provide his company with reliable, affordable phone service outside major financial centers like London and Frankfurt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cipolla and his counterparts at nearly two dozen multinational corporations have formed a consortium to voice their opinions to major phone companies. Among their chief goals: Persuading the big alliances that it is more important to offer dependable phone service in more remote locations like Nairobi, Kenya, or Kiev, Ukraine, than it is to offer high-speed data-transmission services between New York and London.</p>
        <p>"Anyone can do that," Mr. Cipolla said. The trick, he said, is getting a good phone line to Nairobi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
