<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Craziness Pays</title>
    <meta content="24FRIE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iraq-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D8173EF937A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Craziness Pays</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says agreement between United Nations Sec Gen Kofi Annan and Pres Saddam Hussein granting weapons inspectors unfettered access to Iraqi sites is not solution, but short-term arrangement for coping with Saddam; says US has to decide whether it wants to resolve contradictions between itself and allies or go it alone and live with contradictions of its own policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another deal with Saddam Hussein? Hmmmmm. Why does it leave me feeling uneasy -- as if I had just agreed that Ted Kaczynski could be my mailman, because he's promised, this time, for sure, no more letter bombs? You just know that sooner or later something is gonna go boom.</p>
        <p>Still, President Clinton is right to test whether this deal can meet three basic conditions. First, it really must provide free and unfettered access for U.N. weapons inspectors everywhere in Iraq. Second, the accord should be codified as a Security Council resolution so that there is no ambiguity about it in the future. Third, the U.S. has to make clear to Iraq and U.S. allies that if there is any violation America will use force, without negotiation, hesitation or U.N. approval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another deal with Saddam Hussein? Hmmmmm. Why does it leave me feeling uneasy -- as if I had just agreed that Ted Kaczynski could be my mailman, because he's promised, this time, for sure, no more letter bombs? You just know that sooner or later something is gonna go boom.</p>
        <p>Still, President Clinton is right to test whether this deal can meet three basic conditions. First, it really must provide free and unfettered access for U.N. weapons inspectors everywhere in Iraq. Second, the accord should be codified as a Security Council resolution so that there is no ambiguity about it in the future. Third, the U.S. has to make clear to Iraq and U.S. allies that if there is any violation America will use force, without negotiation, hesitation or U.N. approval.</p>
        <p>But even if we get such a deal, have no illusions -- it's not a solution. It is another short-term arrangement for coping with Saddam. We have not heard the last of him. What about the long term? Before we look at that, let's note an important lesson from this last round: Saddam blinked. He backed down to Kofi Annan because he became convinced that despite all the contradictions in U.S. policy, despite all the protesters at Ohio State and despite all the whining of U.S. allies, Mr. Clinton was ready to use massive force against him. Mr. Clinton had defined Iraq's behavior as a clear national threat. Not everyone in America understood that, but Saddam did, and he didn't want to get hit.</p>
        <p>Because Saddam is a dictator there is a tendency to assume that he has no domestic politics to worry about. U.S. networks contribute to this view by interviewing all these Iraqis in Baghdad who say they would happily sacrifice their sons for Saddam. Nonsense. None of these people are free to speak their minds (which the networks should remind their viewers of occasionally). Saddam has real domestic politics. He can't just expose his army to another savage bombing from the U.S., he does not want to lose his palaces built at great expense, and he can't just take one punch after another without exposing himself to even greater risk from his own military. Watch those film clips of Saddam meeting with his generals. Why do you think he's the only one in the room with a gun in his belt?</p>
        <p>But while the threat of force may have worked, for now, we also have to cite another lesson: Had Saddam not blinked and had the U.S. blasted him, the U.S. would have been virtually alone. The world was not with us. I regret that, but it's a fact.</p>
        <p>So what to do for the long run? The Administration needs to decide: Does it want to resolve the contradictions between the U.S. and its allies, or go it alone and live with the contradictions of its own policy?</p>
        <p>America's contradiction with its allies is summarized by the Middle East expert Stephen P. Cohen: ''For the French, the Russians and the Arabs there are no conditions under which they really believe it is O.K. to use violence against Saddam, and for the U.S. there are no conditions under which it believes sanctions on Saddam should ever be lifted.''</p>
        <p>That is, the allies simply do not believe you can bomb Saddam because of any ''potential'' threat posed by his weapons, but only if there is an actual threat or usage. And the U.S. believes that given Saddam's evil character, there is no way sanctions should ever be lifted, even if he complies with the U.N. inspectors.</p>
        <p>One option, therefore, is to strike a deal with the allies. Russia, France and the Security Council would formally agree that if Saddam violates the Annan accord, the U.S. can use force. And the U.S. would agree that if the U.N. ever certifies Iraq as bomb-free, the U.S. will lift the sanctions (but there would still have to be ongoing inspections).</p>
        <p>The other option is for the U.S. to live with the contradictions of its own policy. U.S. policy is that Saddam is Hitler, but the U.S. will not go after him personally, but it will bomb Iraq, knowing that this will only deter Saddam temporarily, while alienating the rest of the world. As a policy, it's not pretty.</p>
        <p>But neither is the Middle East. That's why it's worth trying to sort out the contradictions with our allies. But if we cannot, we have to be ready to live with our own contradictory policy. Sure, it doesn't make perfect sense. But maybe it was the sheer bull-headed craziness of it that intimidated Saddam. After all, in his neighborhood, crazy buys you a lot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
