<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: Syracuse; Good Show! Cricket Becomes Intramural Sport</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="448006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D71739F935A15756C0A967958260" item-length="642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: Syracuse; Good Show! Cricket Becomes Intramural Sport</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>SYRACUSE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wickets stood sturdily on the pitch, and the bowlers and batsmen were in fine fettle last week as the graduate-student side trounced the faculty side in cricket on the playing fields of -- no, not Eton -- Syracuse University. The match, at Hookway Field, lasted three hours -- a mere interlude, as cricket aficionados know -- and the score was respectably cricket: 136 runs to 122.</p>
        <p>The match was the premiere of intramural cricket at Syracuse, which has added the sport to its summer recreation schedule primarily as an outlet for its 1,374 international students, who constitute 8.2 percent of the student population.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The wickets stood sturdily on the pitch, and the bowlers and batsmen were in fine fettle last week as the graduate-student side trounced the faculty side in cricket on the playing fields of -- no, not Eton -- Syracuse University. The match, at Hookway Field, lasted three hours -- a mere interlude, as cricket aficionados know -- and the score was respectably cricket: 136 runs to 122.</p>
        <p>The match was the premiere of intramural cricket at Syracuse, which has added the sport to its summer recreation schedule primarily as an outlet for its 1,374 international students, who constitute 8.2 percent of the student population.</p>
        <p>"I was surprised at how good some of these players were," said John Rennie Short, a geography professor and recent arrival from Scotland who is on the staff-faculty team. "For an intramural league, it's a very high standard."  It May Be a First</p>
        <p>Robert Wilson, associate director of the university's Office of Support Services, said he believed that Syracuse was the only American university that offered intramural cricket. A handful of schools, including Syracuse, have cricket clubs that participate in intercollegiate matches, said Mr. Wilson, who is the secretary of the university's cricket club.</p>
        <p>Intramural cricket is open to all Syracuse students and faculty and staff members, but it appeals particularly to the international students, many of whom cannot return home during the summer, Mr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>Most of the players who signed up for one of four teams are graduate students from India and Pakistan, he said. Others hail from Australia, Britain and the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>But Nimish Radia, a graduate student in computer engineering from India and captain of the cricket club, said, "The main idea was to make the game popular so that we can attract students of different cultures."</p>
        <p>The university has budgeted about $600 for the intramural cricket program, said Nicklaus J. Wetter, director of recreation services. Finding the equipment was not easy; most was shipped in from a Philadelphia supplier.</p>
        <p>Intramural cricket is a slightly modified version of the popular game, Mr. Wilson said. The field is shorter, teams have eight players rather than the customary 11, and matches last about three hours. International cricket matches, even those limited to one inning for each team, can last two days.  Playing by the Rules</p>
        <p>Cricket is played on an area called a pitch. On either end of the pitch is a wicket -- three stumps standing in the ground with two horizontal wood pieces, or bails, across the top. At one end of the pitch stands the bowler (and an observant umpire), and the bowler hurls a cricket ball to a batsman standing in front of the wicket at the opposite end of the pitch.</p>
        <p>The bowler tries to throw the ball in such a way -- generally with a bounce on the ground -- that it evades the batsman's bat, hits the wicket and knocks off the bails, thus bowling the batsman out.</p>
        <p>The batsman, in turn, tries to hit the ball and score runs by running back and forth between wickets. A batsman who successfully makes it to one wicket scores one run. A ball hit beyond the boundary of the pitch without hitting the ground counts as six runs. If it bounces on its way, it counts as four runs.</p>
        <p>Catching the ball on the fly is one of several ways for an opposing team -- called a side -- to get a batsman out.</p>
        <p>Although both Syracuse teams last week aimed to win, the atmosphere was relaxed. "We're basically here for fun," said K. N. Subramanya, a graduate student in environmental engineering from East Bombay, India.</p>
        <p>Even William John Readings, a professor of English from Britain and perhaps the most intense player in the match, joked as the team for which he was the bowler and captain fell to the slim defeat. "I'm just glad no one had a heart attack," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
