<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: New School; Masterpieces Of Fresco Painting Inspire a Course</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="46" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="448088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D71F3AF935A15756C0A967958260" item-length="509" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: New School; Masterpieces Of Fresco Painting Inspire a Course</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The simple act of painting a wall takes on new meaning when the wall is at the Parsons School of Design, a division of the New School for Social Research, and the painters are students and faculty members.</p>
        <p>But even by Parsons' standards, last week's wall-painting foray had the feel of innovation, as eight students and three instructors completed the first fresco at the school since Jose Clemente Orozco painted his towering 20th-century work -- a five-wall fresco -- in the New School cafeteria in 1928.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The simple act of painting a wall takes on new meaning when the wall is at the Parsons School of Design, a division of the New School for Social Research, and the painters are students and faculty members.</p>
        <p>But even by Parsons' standards, last week's wall-painting foray had the feel of innovation, as eight students and three instructors completed the first fresco at the school since Jose Clemente Orozco painted his towering 20th-century work -- a five-wall fresco -- in the New School cafeteria in 1928.</p>
        <p>"The process is incredibly engaging; I think it's fabulous," said Beatrice Banu, dean of undergraduate liberal studies at the New School and chairwoman of the Parsons liberal studies program. "I would support a class in fresco as long as we can sustain it."</p>
        <p>The fresco, a 6-foot by 10-foot work recounting the history of fresco, is a kind of final exam for Parsons' first course on the subject.</p>
        <p>During the last week, from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., students learned the centuries-old art of applying pigments to wet lime plaster. They also studied the Orozco painting. Their work now adorns the wall of a fifth-floor painting and sculpture workshop at Parsons' main building at West 13th Street and Fifth Avenue in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>"There has been a strong increase in interest in the art of the fresco, some of it spurred by the restoration of the Sistine Chapel," said Lesley A. Doyel, coordinator of the Parsons liberal studies program for art history and one of three instructors who developed the new fresco course. Form 'Makes You Humble'</p>
        <p>Ms. Doyel has been teaching one-day fresco workshops as part of her art history classes, assisted by Sheila Rechtshaffer, an instructor of fresco painting through Parsons' continuing education program. They were joined by a visiting instructor, Stoney Conley, an adjunct professor of fine arts at Boston College. Mr. Conley is a professional mural and fresco painter.</p>
        <p>Rima Vargas-Vetter, a senior from New York majoring in sculpture and a member of the wall-painting team, called the work "an art form that makes you humble." Ms. Vargas-Vetter says she has a deep respect for fresco as social art.</p>
        <p>"After this," she said, "I'd like to paint a fresco on AIDS because it is such a deeply public problem involving lovers and children and parents, everyone."</p>
        <p>With the students looking on, a professional prepared the workshop wall with rough and smooth underlayers of plaster, called arriccio. Then the students drew a cartoon on paper, life-size outlines of the images they wanted to paint, perforating the outlines with tiny holes. After putting down a fresh layer of plaster, the students placed the cartoon on the wall, took a porous bag filled with charcoal and beat it over the outline, leaving guidelines on the plaster. Finally, they applied the pigment -- quickly, before the plaster dried.</p>
        <p>"It was a lot of physical work," said Grady Avant, a junior from Detroit majoring in photography. "The hardest part is that if you mess up your brush work, it stays there. It's permanent."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
