<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soviet Republics Are Coming Into Their Own</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D9133BF93BA35754C0A967958260" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soviet Republics Are Coming Into Their Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a banker and businessman who spends all his time on transactions involving the United States and Russia or the Ukraine, I continue to be appalled by information gaps on both sides. These gaps are most evident in the discussion and plans surrounding Soviet economic reform and economic assistance to the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a banker and businessman who spends all his time on transactions involving the United States and Russia or the Ukraine, I continue to be appalled by information gaps on both sides. These gaps are most evident in the discussion and plans surrounding Soviet economic reform and economic assistance to the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>On this subject, the information gaps in Moscow seem to reinforce those about the Soviet Union in the United States, making the picture surrealistic for someone like myself, who spends time in other parts of the Soviet Union, as well as in Moscow.</p>
        <p>Western reporters continue to be largely centered in Moscow and primarily exposed to the central press (as is the case with most Muscovites). The central press has almost stopped writing about what is happening in the republics. At the same time, the press in the republics has largely stopped reporting Moscow events, except for key actions in the Parliament of the Russian Republic.</p>
        <p>Moscow is thus becoming isolated from real events and toying with solutions that our combined, well-meaning academics propose, but which are grounded on the survival of an entity, the Soviet Union, that exists more and more only on paper.</p>
        <p>A more accurate picture of the true dynamics has begun to appear in the last few weeks in The Financial Times, which seems to have posted its own permanent correspondent in Kiev. The sobering reality is that:</p>
        <p>(1) The republics feel empowered and are not likely to be spoken for by the center.</p>
        <p>(2) The republics are not pushing grand requests for Western aid and loans. In fact, the Ukraine has stated that it is willing to discuss how to prorate existing Soviet debt, but that it will not consider itself obligated by any future Soviet debt incurred without its specific agreement. A new National Bank of the Ukraine was created last month to set directions for the Ukraine's own fiscal policy.</p>
        <p>(3) The republics, with different degrees of effectiveness, are beginning to co-opt organs of central power on their territories. This is being done subtly but consciously in the armed forces and the K.G.B.</p>
        <p>In summary, drawing too many plans and too many conclusions from our past experience with the Soviet Union and from the current mood in Moscow may be very misleading and illusory. GEORGE B. YURCHYSHYN Boston, June 28, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
