<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Top Pick Ready for N.H.L., Which Isn't Ready for Him</title>
    <meta content="27NHL$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/27/sports/hockey/27nhl.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1592736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Capitals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ovechkin, Aleksandr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lockouts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Capitals</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Hockey League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E6D91738F934A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Top Pick Ready for N.H.L., Which Isn't Ready for Him</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Unlike N.H.L., No. 1 Pick Is Ready</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Washington Capitals select left wing Aleksandr Ovechkin with first pick at NHL entry draft, but it is uncertain whether or not 18-year-old Russian will play right away, assuming NHL season is not jeopardized by looming lockout; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Being chosen first in the National Hockey League draft on Saturday was a singular honor for Aleksandr Ovechkin of Russia, but it also thrust him into a changing business climate filled with wrangling and uncertainty.</p>
        <p>When the Washington Capitals took Ovechkin, a 6-foot-2, 200 pound left wing from Dynamo Moscow, he became the second player from Russia to be selected with the first pick over all. The other was Ilya Kovalchuk, by Atlanta in 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Washington took Aleksandr Ovechkin of Russia, making him only the second player from his country selected by the N.H.L. as the best among amateur players.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Being chosen first in the National Hockey League draft on Saturday was a singular honor for Aleksandr Ovechkin of Russia, but it also thrust him into a changing business climate filled with wrangling and uncertainty.</p>
        <p>When the Washington Capitals took Ovechkin, a 6-foot-2, 200 pound left wing from Dynamo Moscow, he became the second player from Russia to be selected with the first pick over all. The other was Ilya Kovalchuk, by Atlanta in 2001.</p>
        <p>Ovechkin said that he was eager to make his North American debut at the elite World Cup tournament in late summer and that he was capable of playing in the N.H.L. next season. Although both would be rare for an 18-year-old player, most scouts seem to agree with him.</p>
        <p>''I've been waiting for this day for two years,'' Ovechkin said. ''If you go first, you are the best. I always want to be the best. Yes, I can play in the N.H.L. I can score goals. I can play defense. I like a physical game. I love hockey.''</p>
        <p>Although the World Cup tournament should proceed as scheduled in late August and early September, the regular season could be delayed by a labor lockout unless N.H.L. owners and the N.H.L. Players Association can negotiate a new collective bargaining agreement. The current one expires Sept. 15.</p>
        <p>Even if that is settled, the N.H.L. and the International Ice Hockey Federation need to negotiate a new policy for transfer payments for European players like Ovechkin when they are signed by North American teams.</p>
        <p>In particular, the Russian federation is demanding a better deal. With Ovechkin picked first and Yevgeny Malkin of Russia selected second, by the Pittsburgh Penguins, the Russians have leverage. When a television interviewer asked Ovechkin to greet fans from back home, he smiled and said in his native language: ''Russia, let's go! In Russia, we are the best!''</p>
        <p>Among other intriguing first-round selections was the Rangers' choice of goalie Al Montoya of the University of Michigan with the sixth pick.</p>
        <p>The Islanders used the 16th pick to take Petteri Nokelainen, a center from Finland; the Rangers traded up with Calgary to choose 19th, selecting Lauri Korpikoski, a forward from Finland; and the Devils traded up with Dallas for the 20th pick to take Travis Zajac, a center from Winnipeg, Manitoba. Of the 30 players selected in the first round, 13 were from Europe, 11 from Canada and 6 from the United States. The Czech Republic led the European nations with four picks.</p>
        <p>The N.H.L. formula for rookie salaries is a dilemma for Washington. Should the Capitals sign Ovechkin before the collective bargaining agreement expires, they would have to pay him $1.295 million in addition to guaranteed performance bonuses that could significantly increase his income.</p>
        <p>Should the Capitals wait for a new labor deal, perhaps in hope that the rookie rates will be decreased, they could alienate Ovechkin, who could return to Russia, play professionally there indefinitely and request that his rights be transferred to another N.H.L. team.</p>
        <p>George McPhee, the general manager of the Capitals, said, ''There's a lot of uncertainty as to what's going to take place in the future, so we'll take our time.''</p>
        <p>Ovechkin's father played professional soccer and his mother won Olympic gold medals in basketball. The N.H.L.'s central scouting report describes Ovechkin as ''a complete package; superb skater; excellent acceleration and top speed; superb stick handler, passer and playmaker; skates well through traffic; superb hockey sense; can hit and take a hit; has all the tools, including attitude, on and off the ice.''</p>
        <p>Although everyone agrees about Ovechkin's skills, not everyone agrees about who holds his rights. Ovechkin said, ''I'm free, I don't have a contract with Dynamo.''</p>
        <p>But Don Meehan, his agent, was not so sure. ''He's under contract to date,'' Meehan said, choosing his words carefully. ''In relation to next year, there is an issue involved, a rather complicated issue.''</p>
        <p>Bill Daly, the N.H.L.'s executive vice president and chief legal officer, said, ''I've been told Dynamo has a claim of a contractual status for next year.''</p>
        <p>Rene Fasel, the president of the International Ice Hockey Federation, said by telephone from Switzerland that he would travel to Moscow on Monday to try to negotiate with the Russian federation, which wants a separate agreement for transfer fees for its players, something that the N.H.L. is resisting.</p>
        <p>Until now, the league has dealt only with the international federation, which has distributed money among European teams for transfers. Fasel said the Russians, under the old agreement, would have received $220,000 to $250,000 for Ovechkin's rights. ''He is worth more,'' Fasel said. ''He is one of the reasons the Russians do not want to join the other European teams.''</p>
        <p>Ovechkin indicated that he understood his economic value. One of his ambitions, he said, was to buy a new car, a BMW.</p>
        <p>Bonk in Three-Team Trade</p>
        <p>In a three-team trade Saturday, Montreal acquired Ottawa forward Radek Bonk and Los Angeles goaltender Cristobal Huet.</p>
        <p>The Senators traded Bonk to the Kings for a third-round pick, then Los Angeles dealt him and Huet to Montreal for goalie Mathieu Garon and the Canadiens' third-round choice, No. 95 in the draft. With that pick, Los Angeles selected Paul Baier, a defenseman from Deerfield Academy in Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Bonk is due to become a restricted free agent Thursday, and the Senators would have had to make a $3.5 million qualifying offer to retain his rights. (AP)</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
