<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keilbas and All the Fixings, Home Style</title>
    <meta content="27CTDINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1592472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Polish National Home (Hartford, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0DB1E39F934A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keilbas and All the Fixings, Home Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Polish National Home restaurant in Hartford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE last thing I could have imagined coming upon the 1930's building that houses the Polish National Home in Hartford is that there was a restaurant in there. A school, maybe. Or a courthouse.</p>
        <p>With its masculine, rather austere Art Deco design, the place has a distinctly institutional look. The front door was locked. There was a sign that directed you to a side door; that didn't look promising, either. But down a short hall was an unusual and remarkable restaurant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE last thing I could have imagined coming upon the 1930's building that houses the Polish National Home in Hartford is that there was a restaurant in there. A school, maybe. Or a courthouse.</p>
        <p>With its masculine, rather austere Art Deco design, the place has a distinctly institutional look. The front door was locked. There was a sign that directed you to a side door; that didn't look promising, either. But down a short hall was an unusual and remarkable restaurant.</p>
        <p>I love a place that makes me feel that, somehow, on my way to a restaurant, I fell down a rabbit hole and ended up in some entirely unexpected new world. Polish National Home is certainly that. The restaurant is comprised of two rooms. There is a very large, high-ceilinged bar area dominated by an elaborate dark wood, old-world style bar that must measure 40 feet in length. The tan-tiled wall opposite the bar is lined with wooden booths unrelieved by cushions. In the center are tables with low, plastic upholstered chairs, best described as 1950's bowling alley décor.</p>
        <p>I was reminded of my first trip to Eastern Europe as a kid in the 70's; the experience of living in the austere culture of East Berlin unsettled my insular American eye. At Polish National Home, however, the room feels intimate as well, creating a comfortably lived-in, if somewhat institutional, atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The dining room looks like a cross between a high school auditorium and a German beer hall. If you go in for Sunday lunch, as I did the first time I ate here, you will run into a radio broadcast of Polish polka music that is presented by the restaurant every Sunday afternoon. The dining room was full; there were lots of large parties (lots of families), and everyone was having a great, relaxed time.</p>
        <p>The food is Polish home cooking. In addition to some American plates such as roast turkey, sirloin, prime rib, pork loin and fried fish, Polish National Home serves a selection of Polish specialties. The more American food is good if some is rather well done for my taste: the pork loin is melt-in-your-mouth tender and the prime rib, while grey, is tasty.</p>
        <p>But it is the Polish food that makes this place worth the drive. The ''Polish plate'' combines kielbasa, pirogi (stuffed with potato), sauerkraut and stuffed cabbage. The kielbasa is some of the best I've ever eaten: juicy without being too fat, a nice balance of smoke and seasonings, and not too salty. (And you can slather it with the excellent horseradish found on every table: it is prepared in some mysterious way that makes it mild enough to eat a lot of it, and really taste the vegetable, without burning your mouth off.)</p>
        <p>The sauerkraut, unlike what we find in New York delis, is not particularly sour or acidic and some may not like it for that reason. Seasoned with black pepper and bits of pork and kielbasa, it has a lovely, mellow flavor, and is a little rich, which, granted, one doesn't really need with this food. The pirogi are tender with a good ratio of potato to dumpling. (I would get them as an appetizer, though, where you can appreciate their delicious dressing of melted butter (or is it chicken fat?) and bacon; they get a little lost on the Polish Plate.)</p>
        <p>I'm not wild about the stuffed cabbage, although it may be authentic. I don't like the sweetness of the meat and rice filling and it doesn't taste enough like cabbage to suit me.</p>
        <p>Potato pancakes, (three huge pancakes to a plate listed as an ''appetizer'') have just the right amount of onion to potato; they could be a little crisper. Cabbage soup is excellent, seasoned with kielbasa and just enough tomato to balance the fat in the soup.</p>
        <p>When you get tired of summer food, give this place a shot. There are several Polish beers on tap -- Okocim is a favorite of mine -- and the prices are rock-bottom diner prices. The most extensive menu is the Sunday lunch; there is a leaner menu for lunch and dinner during the rest of the week. (The Polish plate is always on the menu.)</p>
        <p>Polish National Home  60 Charter Oak Avenue, Hartford  (860)247-1784</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Casual, a little austere and institutional. Bustling Sunday lunches; quieter during the week.  NOISE LEVEL -- Moderate.  SERVICE -- Friendly, charming.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Potato pancakes, pirogi, cabbage soup, kielbasa, kielbasa sandwich, ''Polish Plate,'' pork loin, Polish beers.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: 85 cents (for a pirogi) to $3. Main courses: $8 to $13.95; Desserts: $2.95.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards accepted.  HOURS -- Monday through Saturday, lunch 11 a.m. to 3 p.m., then a limited menu served until 8 p.m. or 9 p.m. (or whenever people leave). Sunday lunch 11 a.m. to 3 p.m.  RESERVATIONS -- Necessary for very large parties.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Difficult.  Reviewed by The Times June 27, 2004.  Ratings -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
