<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chairs, Not Always With Comfort in Mind</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="708705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CRAFTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM (TRENTON)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREUDENHEIM, BETTY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDF1039F93BA1575BC0A962958260" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chairs, Not Always With Comfort in Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETTY FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREUDENHEIM, BETTY</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMFORT counts when it comes to picking a new chair. Today, no one would even consider buying one without first sitting down to see how it feels. By contrast, formal styles were the primary consideration in antique American furniture.</p>
        <p>The 18th- and 19th-century varnished chairs lined up along the four walls of a gallery in the New Jersey State Museum don't look comfortable. Considering the pristine condition of the elaborate, decorative details, they must have received only upright individuals who never scratched or marred their glistening surfaces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMFORT counts when it comes to picking a new chair. Today, no one would even consider buying one without first sitting down to see how it feels. By contrast, formal styles were the primary consideration in antique American furniture.</p>
        <p>The 18th- and 19th-century varnished chairs lined up along the four walls of a gallery in the New Jersey State Museum don't look comfortable. Considering the pristine condition of the elaborate, decorative details, they must have received only upright individuals who never scratched or marred their glistening surfaces.</p>
        <p>The museum has been developing its 18th- and 19th-century furniture collection since 1972. All examples were made or used in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>"The designs reflect changes in social customs, styles and the technology of production," said Susan Finkel, curator of cultural history. Locally made furniture was constructed of native woods, while the elaborate chairs, with hand-carved motifs and silk upholstery, were often imported.</p>
        <p>In the second half of the 19th century, the industrialization of furniture making was accompanied by new materials and technical advances like the use of laminated or bent wood. Prices dropped, and the market expanded.</p>
        <p>A Windsor-style, comb-back armchair is dated 1770-1800. The distinctive spindles extending down the back were fashioned from local hickory wood that can be turned on a lathe.</p>
        <p>In a contemporary variation on the same theme, George Nakashima fashioned his 1980 "Conoid Chair" to fit the body's form. It has only two legs, set at a diagonal, but the spindle back and saddle seat echo the distinctive Windsor styling.</p>
        <p>Curvilinear lines and knobs ornament the back of an early 18th-century Chippendale-style side chair. The ball-and-claw feet are likely to symbolize the discomfort of anyone who might be obliged to sit on it for an extended time. No wonder this chair looks unused.</p>
        <p>A late 19th-century chair features a curved back and seat combination that is perforated with holes. The tiny openings, which assume the outlines of a star and two Gothic church arches, must have had a cooling effect on hot summer evenings. Wheels on the feet would allow the sitter to move from one conversation to another with very little effort.</p>
        <p>Today's new parents might be delighted if their infant furniture store stocked a late 19th-century invention from Hackettstown. The label says that "the use of mechanization to improve efficiency was sometimes taken to extremes" and that "gears, springs, locking devices and wheels allowed a multipurpose chair to be converted from a highchair to a stroller or a rocker."</p>
        <p>Why hasn't this multipurpose contraption been widely copied? It would certainly cut back on the equipment required for a weekend trip to see grandma and grandpa.</p>
        <p>This newly opened but permanent installation is in the second-floor galleries. The New Jersey State Museum is at 205 West State Street in Trenton. Hours are Tuesday through Saturday from 9 A.M to 4:45 P.M. and Sunday from noon to 5 P.M. Admission is free.  CRAFTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
