<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connections, Connections</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="708842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMALL BUSINESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUSINESS OUTREACH CENTER NETWORK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, RANDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EFDD1139F93BA1575BC0A962958260" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connections, Connections</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KENNEDY, RANDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S just after 10 A.M. and John R. Fratianni and his team are brainstorming.</p>
        <p>Their client is an independent filmmaker, Ayoka Chenzira, whose movie, "Alma's Rainbow," will soon be released on video. The problem: how to draw attention to her film, which has been showing at one small Harlem theater since June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S just after 10 A.M. and John R. Fratianni and his team are brainstorming.</p>
        <p>Their client is an independent filmmaker, Ayoka Chenzira, whose movie, "Alma's Rainbow," will soon be released on video. The problem: how to draw attention to her film, which has been showing at one small Harlem theater since June.</p>
        <p>One woman narrows her eyes. "Maybe we could get into the schools, publicize it to kids, hit our target audience that way," she suggests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fratianni frowns. "Dealing with the school system -- it's going to be a painfully slow process," he says.</p>
        <p>Another woman leans in. "I have a friend who's a schoolteacher. All you need is one person on the inside, right? Bypass the system," she says, to approving nods around the table.</p>
        <p>This is clearly not the conversation of TriBeCa movie executives. The office -- a cramped, second-floor conference room -- overlooks the teeming sidewalks of Flatbush Avenue in Brooklyn. And the strategists, who pepper their conversation with phrases like "guerrilla financing," and "bootstrap equity," are soon on to their next client, a cash-poor Caribbean bodybuilder from Flatbush who desperately wants to market his own line of power juices.</p>
        <p>Here, in a sense, is a frontier of economic development in New York -- not the courting of large corporations or manufacturers but the effort to help small entrepreneurs, many from minority communities and most with fewer than 20 employees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fratianni and his team are among the leaders of a rapidly expanding program that aids ambitious small business owners who have been hindered by cultural isolation and neighborhood redlining policies. The program, called the Business Outreach Center Network, builds business connections, helps position products and lines up loans to fuel startups and expansions.</p>
        <p>The program follows a nationwide trend toward small entrepeneurs.</p>
        <p>"This is part of a tremendous shift in the entire framework of economic development," said Mitchell L. Moss, director of the Urban Research Center at New York University. "It's very important for New York City, because these types of businesses have by and large been neglected by policy makers until recently."</p>
        <p>He added that New York's often balkanized communities are only now beginning to fully realize that their small business interests are the same. "And I know of nothing more powerful than capitalism to overcome ethnic cleavages," he said.</p>
        <p>The nonprofit network was created four years ago by Orthodox Jewish leaders in the close-knit community of Borough Park, Brooklyn, to help small business owners there, many of them Yiddish-speaking Russian immigrants, get on their feet or expand thriving young businesses.</p>
        <p>It started with the help of $4 million in city, state and Federal grants. Connected by computer, the network now has seven offices around the city -- in Borough Park, Flatbush, Chinatown, the largely Hispanic neighborhood of Hunts Point in the Bronx, in minority areas of Far Rockaway and Staten Island and on West 116th Street in Harlem. Next month it plans to open an office in Bridgeport, Conn.</p>
        <p>The program sheds light on the forces that constrain small entrepreneurs. For example, a Chinatown business owner's spotty English and distrust of big banks keep him from getting a loan to expand his store. A counselor who speaks his Cantonese dialect helps him put together a business plan and then finds a bank or other loan program that is likely to give him the money.</p>
        <p>Ethnic divisions often work against economic self-interest. Counselors put together business partners from areas whose residents rarely communicate or whose ethnic groups have sometimes been hostile -- a meat distributor from Hunts Point and an exporter from Chinatown agree to find new markets in Taiwan, or a Jewish business finds that its services are needed by a group of black Muslims, for example.</p>
        <p>"What most of these businesses need is just someone to hold their hand for a little while," said Paul Chernick, director of operations for the Council of Jewish Organizations, and the man who came up with the idea for the network. "There've been precious few places they can go to."</p>
        <p>Tom Lam, who co-owns an audio parts distributorship in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, said he came to the network in Chinatown after he and his partner tried to negotiate a loan. "We took one look at what you have to do to get it and we put the application away," he said recently, on a visit to his business counselor, Vicky Cheng, on Canal Street.</p>
        <p>"By the time we got through, we wouldn't need the loan," said Mr. Lam, who was born in Hong Kong. "We would be out of business." But with Ms. Cheng's help he found that much of the $90,000 in speakers, receivers and other stereo parts he had in inventory could serve as collateral.</p>
        <p>"Tom speaks English very well and even used to work for a bank," said Ms. Cheng. "There are many others in Chinatown who were raised to think that a bank is only a place where you put your money. To borrow other people's money is something we have to work to make them comfortable with."</p>
        <p>The network has now served more than 1,000 businesses, with about half of its active clients having been open less than six months. It has drawn up formal agreements with dozens of service organizations around the city -- ranging from banks and accounting firms to business colleges and government agencies -- to make them aware that it will be sending business owners their way for money or technical help.</p>
        <p>"The time was ripe for an invention like this," said Samuel M. Ehrenhalt, regional commissioner for the Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics. "There's been no real infrastructure out there to help small businesses of this kind and so somebody finally got the bright idea to help it develop an infrastructure of its own."</p>
        <p>The network is just now beginning to have the capability to connect two merchants, or lead a buyer to a seller, a service that officials hope to expand dramatically as its information becomes more sophisticated and neighborhoods learn to work together.</p>
        <p>In one recent successful case, Bernard Samet, the co-owner of Great Neck Party Rental on Long Island, originally went to the Borough Park network office for help with an expansion loan, which he received.</p>
        <p>But in doing so he also found out that the Malcolm Shabazz Mosque in Central Harlem, the sponsors of the newest network site, needed to rent a large canvas tent and 1,000 folding chairs for an outdoor speech. The deal was struck early this month, for a reduced rate, and Mr. Samet is negotiating another, larger deal with the mosque that could help him in paying off his loan.</p>
        <p>"I have to say I don't think I had ever set foot in that part of Harlem before the day I went to set up the tent," Mr. Samet said. "But before you know it, we were happily ever after. We needed each other, you know? A tent's a tent and a chair's a chair."  NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
