<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daed in the Water</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="709037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASON, DEBORAH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'BRIEN, PATRICIA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LADIES' LUNCH, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DA1E30F93BA1575BC0A962958260" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daed in the Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Mason;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASON, DEBORAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE LADIES' LUNCH By Patricia O'Brien. 284 pp. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE LADIES' LUNCH By Patricia O'Brien. 284 pp. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
        <p>THE steady deluge of Washington intrigue novels may be the town's purest expression of democracy at work: almost anyone who spends time there gets to write one, from the First and Second Family scribes Margaret Truman and Marilyn Quayle to strivers like the Watergate wife Maureen Dean, whose perfect nose was to remain ever pressed against the glass. Patricia O'Brien, author of "The Candidate's Wife" and now "The Ladies' Lunch," an earnest new D.C. caper, is a former journalist and was Michael Dukakis's press secretary in his 1988 Presidential campaign -- another front-line soldier who knows her way around the Washington land mines.</p>
        <p>So do her four leading characters, a flying wedge of preternaturally powerful Washington women with "high, strong cheekbones" and "strong, rolling" voices who stream into the wine room at Galileo restaurant once a month for their ladies' lunch. The Supreme Court nominee Sara Marino, single by choice, is the cool, moral center of the group, but so ardent in her pursuit of justice that by the end of the first page, she has wiped her courtroom floor with a "milk-faced," fee-fixing doctor; "I can't stand characters who think nothing's at stake except money," she mutters. The journalist Maggie Stedman, a widowed mother, is driven by principle, too, walking away from her secure Washington Post job as a matter of conscience even though it means that she has to let her health insurance lapse. And then there is Maryland Congresswoman Carol Lundeen, who ferociously works for family causes at the sacrifice of her own. Next to these three, the socialite-caterer Leona Maccoby may seem like a twit, but that is only because her natural thirst for truth is thwarted daily by her husband, the oily power broker Justin Maccoby -- and far too often eased by chablis.</p>
        <p>At lunch, the women learn that their fifth regular, Faith Paige, White House press secretary, will not be joining them. Paige, whose voice "was like a bell, ringing true across meadows and fields in still air," has been found dead in the Potomac rapids.</p>
        <p>Instinctively, each woman focuses her innate networking gifts on a higher, more selfless goal -- piecing together the mystery of her friend's death. Transformed into a kind of Junior League Weather Underground, the women refuse to abide by the town's politely amoral gentlemen's agreements, and soon attract secret helpers -- one at the highest level of power, as they say -- who revere the group's noble ministry: the pursuit of justice for all.</p>
        <p>As a proponent of the women-as-morally-superior school of fiction, Ms. O'Brien has created characters who err on the side of sainthood and whose sins are never intentional, but more due to misplaced loyalties or to excessive zeal in the service of truth. And when they are tempted to betray the sisterhood -- by a big-bucks book contract, by an unsavory husband, by self-absorption -- they always, always do the right thing. All this breathy purity prevents the novel from ever cutting loose. Just beneath these women's willed bravado are two eerily familiar voices that don't mean to interrupt, but do anyway -- the oddly girlish tones of Nancy Drew and her faithful sidekick Bess.</p>
        <p>MS. O'BRIEN is persuasive in her description of Judge Marino's confirmation hearing and the plot to undermine her. She has her women, usually Maccoby, drop exactly the right names: "Let me tell you what Donnie Graham said to me at this party last night." But books in this overworked genre, like Washington's old pols, are better at giving the illusion of revelation than delivering any new insights.</p>
        <p>In the end, Patricia O'Brien seems torn between writing a sly, insider's Capitol caper and a treatise on women's friendship and virtue. But placing public women on a pedestal turns them into lightning rods for the culture's gripes and fears about powerful females. What a relief it would be, instead, if two years after the 1992 wave of women swept into Washington, a refreshing revisionism had set in, allowing women in politics to be merely professional, not perfect. Unlike these ladies who lunch, who, alas, are simply too good to be true.  Deborah Mason's reviews have appeared in Vogue, Lear's and Mirabella.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deborah Mason's reviews have appeared in Vogue, Lear's and Mirabella.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
