<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Touches of Weird, Done Best in Japan</title>
    <meta content="14GAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/14/technology/circuits/14game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041016T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1619036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herold, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Namco</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nintendo Company Limited</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DD1F3BF937A25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Touches of Weird, Done Best in Japan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Touches of Weird, Done Best in Japan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles Herold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herold, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Herold Game Theory column reviews Katamari Damacy, Pikmin 2, Silent Hill 4: The Room, Fable and A Dog's Life; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO one does weird quite as well as Japanese game designers and animators, who come up with concepts so bizarre that one feels a mix of admiration and astonishment, best expressed as admironishment. What other word would fit Namco's Katamari Damacy, a game in which the King of All Cosmos sends his inch-high son to earth to collect star material by rolling things up?</p>
        <p>Specifically, the prince has a ball called a katamari that will fasten to any smaller objects it rolls over. As more things stick to the katamari, it grows larger and can absorb larger objects. You may begin by rolling up tacks, proceed to dominoes, then move on to mice, shoes, the table the tacks were on, young children, cows and trees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No one does weird quite as well as Japanese game designers and animators. In this spirit, three new video games bring the bizarre home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO one does weird quite as well as Japanese game designers and animators, who come up with concepts so bizarre that one feels a mix of admiration and astonishment, best expressed as admironishment. What other word would fit Namco's Katamari Damacy, a game in which the King of All Cosmos sends his inch-high son to earth to collect star material by rolling things up?</p>
        <p>Specifically, the prince has a ball called a katamari that will fasten to any smaller objects it rolls over. As more things stick to the katamari, it grows larger and can absorb larger objects. You may begin by rolling up tacks, proceed to dominoes, then move on to mice, shoes, the table the tacks were on, young children, cows and trees.</p>
        <p>One will also be expected at various times to roll up eggs that promptly hatch into birds or steamrollers. Bring your ball back to the king, an eccentric individual who accidentally destroyed the stars and says things like, ''The sky is looking a little tired, much like your eyes,'' and he will place it in the heavens.</p>
        <p>You control the prince as he pushes his katamari through a number of colorful places, each with its own goofy theme song. The two analog sticks on the controller move the prince's arms; you change direction by pushing one stick and move forward by pushing both simultaneously. I've never seen a control scheme like that before, but then I've never seen a game where you could roll a ball over a cat before. The way the ball rolls is affected by what is stuck to it. Roll up a lamppost, and the ball will bump along awkwardly until enough additional objects round it out.</p>
        <p>The game gives the player a time limit for gathering enough star material, so you need to find the largest things you can absorb while avoiding objects that are so large they will knock pieces off your katamari.</p>
        <p>Because the ball always takes up the same amount of screen space, it feels less like the ball is growing and more like the rest of the world is shrinking, with gigantic boulders becoming pebbles. As your katamari grows, you can get into fenced-in areas by rolling up the fences.</p>
        <p>But unlike more ordinary games like The Sims or Commandoes, odd games like Katamari Damacy don't inspire attempts at emulation. That explains why there was no other game like Nintendo's Pikmin until Pikmin 2 arrived recently.</p>
        <p>While less calculatedly weird than Katamari, Pikmin 2 is a game like no other (except, as I say, Pikmin). In a world of giant flowers and lumbering insects, two spacemen search for treasure aided by pikmin -- tiny ambulatory flowers. While individual pikmin are weak, 50 of them can knock down a barrier or best a huge bug. Pikmin come in various colors, which denote their speed or special talents. White pikmin, for example, can dig for underground treasure and are poisonous when ingested by enemies.</p>
        <p>Pikmin are ingested a lot. They are also burned, stomped on and set afire. It's a little sad, because the pikmin army sings happy marching songs as it travels, and individual pikmin wail as they give up the ghost, but there are always more: flowers and dead bugs can be turned into pikmin seedlings.</p>
        <p>A sequel to one of the most original and well-designed games of all time, Pikmin 2 adheres to the ''if it's not broken, don't fix it'' philosophy, repeating the same formula with some minor tweaks and the addition of way too much product placement. (Among the treasures is a giant brand-name battery.)</p>
        <p>Alas, the designers of Konami's Silent Hill 4: The Room, have meddled with their own brilliant formula.</p>
        <p>In Room, the protagonist, Henry, wakes up to find his front door chained shut; his cries for help go unheard. Soon he discovers a tunnel leading to a monster-filled alternate version of his town. Occasionally you can return to Henry's room to spy on his next door neighbor through a crack in the wall or look out your window at the beguilingly peaceful town out of reach.</p>
        <p>The idea is intriguing, and I began the game with the excitement generated by anything with Silent Hill in the title. But the more I played, the unhappier I became.</p>
        <p>Uuntil now, the Silent Hill games have been about creepy atmosphere, exploration, puzzle solving and fighting monsters (though you could often choose to simply run past them rather than fight). Now the game has been tweaked in an apparent attempt to compete with the more successful, action-oriented Resident Evil series. Battle is more prominent, as the game's narrow alleyways force you into confrontations, and puzzles are fewer and simpler, although there are a couple of clever ones where you must glean information in Henry's real-world room to use in the game's alternate world.</p>
        <p>Silent Hill's biggest failing is its shortage of true terror. Unlike previous games that started eerily, then ratcheted up the terror until it was almost unbearable, Room starts spooky but quickly levels off, becoming increasingly monotonous until it rallies near the end. Earlier this year, The Suffering effectively melded action to Silent Hill-style creepiness, but Room fails in the same goal. While the game is decent over all, it feels like a pale imitation of its predecessors.</p>
        <p>While Room is disappointing compared with previous Silent Hill games, Fable, an action role-playing game from Big Blue Box, is disappointing compared with its own hype: it was supposed to be the most amazing game I ever played.</p>
        <p>Designed by the legendary video game creator Peter Molyneux, Fable was touted as a game that would let you lead your character from childhood through old age, making moral decisions that would affect not only your reputation and skills but also your physical appearance: evil actions would give you horns, and the frequent use of magic would make you glow.</p>
        <p>It sounded great, but turned out to be just a cute gimmick. The player can choose to be a good or evil man, but there are no moral dilemmas, and player's choices are driven not so much by conflict as by whim; you wonder how the game will play differently if you are a hero or a thief. The game has an enjoyable battle system and some interesting ideas -- you can flirt with and eventually marry women, and if you play as a hero, villagers will cheer as you walk by -- but its wandering, episodic structure fails to tie these elements together. It is interesting but not absorbing.</p>
        <p>I actually had just as much fun playing Frontier Development's equally aimless A Dog's Life, a whimsical action adventure game in which you control a plucky dog jumping chasms, solving puzzles and digging up bones as you search for a missing friend. The gimmick is a special smell mode in which odors appear as colored plumes of smoke, and much of the game involves tracking down all the smells in a region, allowing the game to indulge in juvenile humor as the dog sniffs and exults, ''Gosh, armpits.''</p>
        <p>While A Dog's Life is a simple, unassuming game and Fable is ambitious and multifaceted, to me both were fun but forgettable. I was expecting something more: the feeling of complete and utter admironishment.</p>
        <p>KATAMARI DAMACY  Published and developed by Namco for PlayStation 2 ($19.99) and Nintendo for GameCube ($49.99); for all ages.</p>
        <p>PIKMIN 2  Developed and published by Nintendo for GameCube ($49.99); for all ages.</p>
        <p>SILENT HILL 4: THE ROOM  Developed and published by Konami for Windows 98SE and later ($29.95) and PlayStation 2 and the Xbox ($39.95); for ages 17 and older.</p>
        <p>FABLE  Developed by Big Blue Box and published by Microsoft for the Xbox; $49.95; for ages 17 and older.</p>
        <p>A DOG'S LIFE  Developed by Frontier Developments and published by Hip Games for PlayStation 2; $19.99; for ages 13 and older.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 16, 2004, Saturday  Because of an editing error, a list of games in Circuits on Thursday, with the Game Theory column about bizarre themes, misstated the publisher, game console and price for one entry, Katamari Damacy. It is published by Namco for the PlayStation 2, at $19.99; there is no GameCube version.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 16, 2004, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a list of games in Circuits on Thursday, with the Game Theory column about bizarre themes, misstated the publisher, game console and price for one entry, Katamari Damacy. It is published by Namco for the PlayStation 2, at $19.99; there is no GameCube version.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Herold@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
