<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking Long and Hard</title>
    <meta content="14MORA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/14/arts/design/14mora.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041020T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1619040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kimmelman, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morandi, Giorgio (1890-1964)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3DD1F3BF937A25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking Long and Hard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Looking Long and Hard at Morandi</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL KIMMELMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kimmelman, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Kimmelman reviews works by Giorgio Morandi at Lucas Schoormans Gallery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Not another day should pass without noting that the most wonderful little show in memory has landed in town. It consists of just six paintings and two drawings by the Italian artist Giorgio Morandi. And if the world were a perfect place, it would be on view forever at the Lucas Schoormans Gallery at 508 West 26th Street in Chelsea, so that we might remind ourselves at any time what heaven looks like. The world not being perfect, the show is around only through Dec. 4. Consider yourself forewarned.</p>
        <p>Lucas Schoormans is clearly a patient man, with a perseverance befitting the object of his devotion. He spent 12 years struggling to assemble this Morandi exhibition, the first in New York in a long while. He cajoled loans from museums and collectors who were understandably reluctant to part with their art even for a few weeks. Fortunately, they did.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most wonderful little show in memory has landed in town. It consists of just six paintings and two drawings by the Italian artist Giorgio Morandi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Not another day should pass without noting that the most wonderful little show in memory has landed in town. It consists of just six paintings and two drawings by the Italian artist Giorgio Morandi. And if the world were a perfect place, it would be on view forever at the Lucas Schoormans Gallery at 508 West 26th Street in Chelsea, so that we might remind ourselves at any time what heaven looks like. The world not being perfect, the show is around only through Dec. 4. Consider yourself forewarned.</p>
        <p>Lucas Schoormans is clearly a patient man, with a perseverance befitting the object of his devotion. He spent 12 years struggling to assemble this Morandi exhibition, the first in New York in a long while. He cajoled loans from museums and collectors who were understandably reluctant to part with their art even for a few weeks. Fortunately, they did.</p>
        <p>Morandi, who died at 73 in 1964 in the modest house on Via Fondazza in Bologna where he had lived his whole life with his mother (until her death in 1950) and with three unmarried sisters, devoted his career to painting pretty much the same dusty bunch of bottles, bowls and biscuit tins. He worked in a studio that doubled as his bedroom. ''One can travel the world and see nothing,'' he said, ''To achieve understanding it is necessary not to see many things, but to look hard at what you do see.''</p>
        <p>That is the message of his pictures: there is a universe in life's little things. And even when just shuffling a few humble objects around a table, unending variety and humor can be achieved through the subtlest distinctions of color and brushstroke. Look closely, Morandi instructs us. The moral implications are clear.</p>
        <p>The show consists only of mature examples, works from 1950 to 1963. As always with Morandi, forms are stripped to their essence, and the art dwells on the precipice of abstraction. The same row of bottles may summon images of ducklings following their mother, or throngs of people in a sunny city square, or the skyline of a town spilling down the side of hill. See a row of brown boxes huddled behind two preening long-necked bottles -- one white, one blue -- while an oval box gently nudges another swanning bottle to the side.</p>
        <p>Suitors at a dance, perhaps.</p>
        <p>Pure heaven.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 20, 2004, Wednesday  Because of a production error, a photograph of a painting on Thursday with an art review of a show of eight works by Giorgio Morandi in Manhattan was published in mirror image. In the painting, ''Natura Morta, 1956,'' the small white bottle is at the left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 20, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, a photograph of a painting on Thursday with an art review of a show of eight works by Giorgio Morandi in Manhattan was published in mirror image. In the painting, ''Natura Morta, 1956,'' the small white bottle is at the left.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
