<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Under Pressure, Mischaracterizations and Misstatements</title>
    <meta content="14FACT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20041015T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1619207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE POLICY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6DE163AF937A25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Under Pressure, Mischaracterizations and Misstatements</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM; Edmund L. Andrews, Michael Janofsky and Edmund L. Andrews contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mischa racterizations and misstatements by Pres Bush and Sen John Kerry in their presidential debate on variety of domestic issues noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As they traded charges and countercharges on the economy, health care and other domestic issues, President Bush mischaracterized who received the tax cuts that have been the centerpiece of his legislative record, and Senator John Kerry exaggerated when he said he was proposing clear ways to raise revenue to pay for his spending proposals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As they traded charges and countercharges on the economy, health care and other domestic issues, President Bush mischaracterized who received the tax cuts that have been the centerpiece of his legislative record, and Senator John Kerry exaggerated when he said he was proposing clear ways to raise revenue to pay for his spending proposals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry was also wrong in saying the president's refusal to allow the government to negotiate drug prices had contributed to the increase in Medicare premiums next year.</p>
        <p>Taxes</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said most of the tax reduction in his presidency had gone ''to low- and middle-income Americans.'' In fact, Internal Revenue Service figures compiled by the Tax Policy Center of the Brookings Institution and the Urban Institute show that half of all the tax cuts in effect this year go to the wealthiest 10 percent of taxpayers, those with incomes above about $70,000. One-quarter of the cuts go to the richest 1 percent, those with incomes above about $290,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also said the cuts were needed ''to get us out of the recession.'' But he proposed the cuts in his last presidential campaign, in 2000, before anyone knew that a recession was at hand, and he justified them by saying the surplus should be returned to the taxpayers.</p>
        <p>The president said, as he often has elsewhere, that Mr. Kerry had voted for tax increases 98 times. That is probably true. But many, if not most, of those were multiple votes on the same bills or on nonbinding resolutions and motions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry has voted for two large tax increases -- the 1990 budget law backed by the president's father that put the country on the road to a balanced budget and President Bill Clinton's 1993 bill, which imposed most of the increases on upper-income taxpayers.</p>
        <p>Budget</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said Mr. Bush had proposed $3 trillion in new spending, and Mr. Bush said Mr. Kerry had proposed $2 trillion. Neither claim can be proved, because the details of their proposals are so vague.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry was correct when he said the budget picture had declined from a projected $5.6trillion surplus over 10 years when Mr. Bush took office to large deficits for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kerry was not accurate when he said he had shown ''exactly how'' he intended to pay for all his spending proposals. In fact, he lists as revenue raisers vague promises like closing corporate loopholes and making the government more efficient.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry was right that Mr. Bush had opposed pay-as-you-go rules that required tax cuts and spending increases to be offset by other tax increases or spending cuts. Those rules were put in effect in the administration of Mr. Bush's father and remained throughout the Clinton years. With Mr. Bush's encouragement, they were allowed to expire. Had they been in effect, his tax cuts could not have been enacted.</p>
        <p>Border Security</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said 95 percent of the cargo containers entering American ports were not inspected. Mr. Bush said, ''We're doing everything we can to protect our borders and ports.''</p>
        <p>According to the Congressional Research Service, seven million cargo containers a year enter American ports. The fear is that a nuclear explosive that would be hard to smuggle through Customs could be hidden on a ship and detonated in a port. The 5 percent inspection rate is correct, according to Congressional testimony. It takes five agents three hours to inspect a typical containership for contraband when it arrives.</p>
        <p>Since 2002, under new Container Security Initiative, American and foreign customs officials have started to inspect some suspicious cargoes at overseas ports, based on screening criteria that focus on certain ports, shipping companies and the like. Some ports are equipped with radiation detectors.</p>
        <p>Legislation has been introduced in Congress to require inspection overseas of all cargoes bound for the United States. The Associated Press said a report to be released today would show that the inspector general of the Homeland Security Department acknowledges that some progress has been made but says better detection equipment and searches continue to be needed.</p>
        <p>Social Security</p>
        <p>Both candidates hedged on Social Security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush never answered how he would pay the cost, estimated at more than $1 trillion, of going from an entirely federal retirement system to one in which workers could put part of their Social Security taxes into private retirement accounts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry never answered what he would do to make sure that the Social Security system would have the resources to pay benefits to all the retirees in the baby boom generation.</p>
        <p>Jobs</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has been, as Mr. Kerry said, the first president since Herbert Hoover to have the number of jobs in the country decline in his term. As of the end of last month, there were at least 585,000 fewer jobs than existed when Mr. Bush took office. But jobs are much more a function of the business cycle than they are of government policies, and Mr. Kerry has not offered a surefire way to guarantee employment growth.</p>
        <p>Pell Grants</p>
        <p>In a sense, both candidates told pieces of the truth about Pell Grants, which are essentially college scholarships for low-income students.</p>
        <p>It is true, as Mr. Kerry implied, that the average size of Pell Grants has decreased, shrinking slightly, to $2,399 in 2005 from $2,457 in 2003, with few students receiving the maximum $4,050.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assertion, ''We've increased Pell Grants by one million students,'' says little about administration policy, leadership or budgeting, because students obtain grants based on eligibility and tuition costs. It is true, however, that the government has in the last two years increased spending on Pell Grants, to $12.8 billion from $11.3 billion in 2003.</p>
        <p>As more middle- and low-income students qualify for aid, and with tuition vastly outpacing inflation, the shortfall between financial aid and the cost of tuition has widened.</p>
        <p>Race Relations</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry criticized Mr. Bush for poor relations with ''the civil rights leadership,'' saying he was ''the first president ever, I think, not to meet with the N.A.A.C.P.'' and had never met the Congressional Black Caucus. Mr. Bush is the first president since Hoover to have never spoken at the annual N.A.A.C.P. meeting, but he has met members of the caucus at least twice and has also appeared before the Urban League.</p>
        <p>Osama bin Laden</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush incorrectly denied saying last year that he was no longer concerned about finding Osama bin Laden.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry, criticizing the president as shifting his attention from that search to the Iraq war, said: ''Six months after he said Osama bin Laden must be caught dead or alive, this president was asked, 'Where's Osama bin Laden?' He said: 'I don't know. I don't really think about him very much. I'm not that concerned.'''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush denied making the remark. ''Gosh, I don't think I ever said I'm not worried about Osama bin Laden,'' he said in the debate. ''That's kind of one of those exaggerations.''</p>
        <p>But at a news conference on March 13, 2003, Mr. Bush said just that when asked why he rarely mentioned Mr. bin Laden any more. ''I don't know where he is,'' Mr. Bush replied. ''I just don't spend that much time on him really, to be honest with you.''</p>
        <p>He added at the time: ''I'll repeat what I said. I truly am not that concerned about him.''</p>
        <p>Veterans</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said that the administration ''hasn't fully funded'' the Veterans Affairs Department and that ''veterans are complaining.'' Mr. Bush said financing for the department had increased $22 billion since he became president. ''We're meeting our obligation to our veterans,'' he said, ''and the veterans know that.''</p>
        <p>Budget authority for the department increased, from $47.4 billion in the 2001 fiscal year, which began the month before the last election, to $60.3 billion in the 2004 fiscal year, which ended two weeks ago. The administration's budget request for this year is $65.2 billion.</p>
        <p>In dollar terms, that increase is a bit less than Mr. Bush said. The increase in Mr. Bush's first three years was 27 percent; in Mr. Clinton's eight years, it increased 31 percent.</p>
        <p>One reason is that middle-income veterans have increasingly turned to veterans' benefits, which have a generous prescription drug feature, according to FactCheck.org. In January 2003, the administration said that despite the budget increases it would have to turn away many middle-income applicants. It proposed, and Congress rejected, making the drug benefit slightly less generous.</p>
        <p>Veterans' groups have sought more money, and Secretary of Veterans' Affairs Anthony J. Principi told a Congressional committee this year that he had requested $1.2 million more in the 2005 budget than the White House had approved.</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: THE POLICY</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 15, 2004, Friday  An article in some copies yesterday that examined statements by President Bush and Senator John Kerry in their debate on Wednesday misstated Mr. Kerry's vote on a 1990 budget law that raised taxes, a measure cited by Mr. Bush as one of many in which Kerry voted for increases. Mr. Kerry voted against it.</p>
        <p>The article also misstated the annual income figures that place taxpayers in the categories of wealthiest 10 percent and wealthiest 1 percent, as calculated by the Tax Policy Center of the Brookings Institution and the Urban Institute. The wealthiest 10 percent earn more than $112,000 (not $70,000), and the wealthiest 1 percent earn more than $357,000 (not $290,000).</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 16, 2004, Saturday  An article on Thursday examining statements made by the presidential candidates during their Wednesday debate misstated the date of a news conference in which President Bush said he was ''not that concerned'' about Osama bin Laden. (In the debate, Mr. Kerry criticized him for having made that comment six months after declaring that Mr. bin Laden must be ''caught dead or alive,'' and Mr. Bush denied having made it.) He spoke in March 2002 -- not 2003.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 15, 2004, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in some copies yesterday that examined statements by President Bush and Senator John Kerry in their debate on Wednesday misstated Mr. Kerry's vote on a 1990 budget law that raised taxes, a measure cited by Mr. Bush as one of many in which Kerry voted for increases. Mr. Kerry voted against it.</p>
        <p>The article also misstated the annual income figures that place taxpayers in the categories of wealthiest 10 percent and wealthiest 1 percent, as calculated by the Tax Policy Center of the Brookings Institution and the Urban Institute. The wealthiest 10 percent earn more than $112,000 (not $70,000), and the wealthiest 1 percent earn more than $357,000 (not $290,000).</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: October 16, 2004, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday examining statements made by the presidential candidates during their Wednesday debate misstated the date of a news conference in which President Bush said he was ''not that concerned'' about Osama bin Laden. (In the debate, Mr. Kerry criticized him for having made that comment six months after declaring that Mr. bin Laden must be ''caught dead or alive,'' and Mr. Bush denied having made it.) He spoke in March 2002 -- not 2003.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
