<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paris After Sundown: With Gallic Subtlety, Even More Light</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC BUILDINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONUMENTS AND MEMORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGES AND TUNNELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARIS (FRANCE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROCKWELL, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4DA1338F936A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paris After Sundown: With Gallic Subtlety, Even More Light</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROCKWELL, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paris calls itself the City of Light. In the daytime, despite subtle shifts caused by pollution and worldwide weather patterns, the diffuse northern sunlight has remained fairly constant over the centuries. Or so paintings, photographs and novelistic descriptions suggest.</p>
        <p>But nighttime is different, and the notion of a city of light, a slogan adopted with the widespread electrification of Paris in the late 19th century, has meant different things in different decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paris calls itself the City of Light. In the daytime, despite subtle shifts caused by pollution and worldwide weather patterns, the diffuse northern sunlight has remained fairly constant over the centuries. Or so paintings, photographs and novelistic descriptions suggest.</p>
        <p>But nighttime is different, and the notion of a city of light, a slogan adopted with the widespread electrification of Paris in the late 19th century, has meant different things in different decades.</p>
        <p>Now, reflecting rapid technological evolution in the last 15 years -- and the rapidity with which the centralized French bureaucracy can respond to such changes -- the nighttime illumination of Paris has become more pervasive, striking and subtly beautiful than ever.</p>
        <p>Unlike public lighting in Manhattan, most notably the multicolored adornment of the tops of prominent skyscrapers, Paris lighting is everywhere, bathing entire ancient neighborhoods in a soft, enveloping glow. And typically of the French, the art of public lighting has grown into a full-fledged, artistically self-conscious profession, with public support, the active involvement of politicians and, now, an influence that is spreading throughout Western and Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>The most dazzling recent addition to the illuminated Paris skyline came last fall, when the Cour Napoleon of the Louvre was lighted for the official opening of the Richelieu wing. That elaborate and costly display, with thousands of tiny lights pinpointing every architectural detail of the palace's vast central courtyard, turned out to be an all the more flamboyant expenditure of public funds by being merely temporary. It has been dismantled now, with the Grand Louvre awaiting a comprehensive lighting scheme when the refurbishment of the entire museum is completed in 1997. Two Bright Bridges</p>
        <p>The latest Paris lighting project will be equally ambitious. Jacques Chirac, the Mayor of Paris, had long sought to illuminate the historic bridges over the Seine. On July 4, the Pont Notre-Dame and the Pont au Change, which are the first two bridges to the east of the Pont Neuf on the northern side of the Ile de la Cite, were introduced in their new electrified dress. By the end of 1995, 11 more bridges in the heart of the city will be similarly illuminated.</p>
        <p>The bridge project reveals the roles played by the various personalities and agencies in the lighting of Paris. The initiative came from Mr. Chirac and the Street Directorate of the mayor's office, which is responsible for the illumination of monuments and for basic street lighting. (The national Ministry of Culture only gets involved when a building is a state-run national monument, like the Louvre.)</p>
        <p>Until recently, nearly all French public lighting was handled both conceptually and technically by the state electricity monopoly, Electricite de France. The company has a special division, the Service Eclairage Public, devoted solely to public lighting.</p>
        <p>In 1987, Electricite de France established a Fondation Electricite de France, which aids in the dissemination of ideas about lighting. The company also has its own Paris art gallery, the Espace Electra on the Left Bank. Among recent exhibitions there were "Paris Ville Lumiere," which offered projects by international artists including the Americans Bill Fontana and Max Neuhaus, and a one-man show devoted to Yann Kersale, whose lighting projects and building illuminations have been installed all over the world.</p>
        <p>Electricite de France's lighting division remains the principal resource for the technical realization of lighting designs, but the designs themselves are now often farmed out to the growing field of independent lighting designers and to lighting artists like Mr. Kersale. Using Computer Images</p>
        <p>For the first two bridges in the Seine bridge project, the mayor's office organized a competition in which four finalists emerged, each of whose projects were estimated to cost about the same. The Service Eclairage devised computer realizations of what the projects would look like, which consisted of computer-screen images resembling brilliantly realistic color photographs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chirac then requested their display on four adjacent monitors, said Dominique Kaczmarek of the Service Eclairage, strode into the room, cast a glance and made his personal decision "very quickly." This imperious process contrasts sharply, for better and for worse, with the more cumbersome American tradition of public hearings and political clashes in the commissioning of public art.</p>
        <p>The design Mr. Chirac chose, the softest and subtlest of the four, epitomizes French esthetics and technology in this field. Conceived by a father-son team called Etudes et Creations d'Ambiance, it uses a myriad of small, high-efficiency lights mounted directly on the bridges to cast a searching but sensuously indirect glow onto the structures. The most obvious contrast to this scheme was a proposal to place strong spotlights on the banks of the Seine, casting black, dramatic shadows under the bridges' arches.</p>
        <p>"In the 1950's, the idea was to show a monument as if it were day," said Pierre Bideau, a creator of what he likes to call "mises en lumiere" who is based in Tours, France. It was Mr. Bideau who, eight years ago, designed the golden new lighting for the Eiffel Tower, which remains the most striking single piece of public lighting in all of Paris.</p>
        <p>"Now," Mr. Bideau continued, "we try to translate the night, to evoke different sentiments than the day, to reveal different details. We seek to create an atmosphere, an ambiance." A Range of Color</p>
        <p>All this has been made possible by the commercial development since the late 1970's of small, high-efficiency halogen lights, which permit a range of color without the use of filters and which brought the cost of electricity for such projects, to public officials made nervous by the energy crisis of the 70's, to within reasonable limits.</p>
        <p>Electricite de France has been particularly active in exploring such technology (although it was Philips, the Dutch electronics concern, that handled the Eiffel Tower). In the workshops of the Service Eclairage Public, alongside the computer realization room, are a host of newly designed rigs and housings that can project and reflect strings of small lights and be installed directly onto the ledges and cornices of ornately decorated Renaissance, Baroque, rococo and 19th-century structures.</p>
        <p>"These buildings were conceived at a time when electricity did not exist," Mr. Kaczmarek said. "You can't illuminate buildings from above, like the sun; you blind the people below. But illuminating from the bottom up reverses natural light. You need small reflectors to avoid dark pits and shadowy blackness and to diffuse the light in a harmonious manner."</p>
        <p>There is not yet an official course of training for French public lighting designers, Mr. Bideau said. Some come from the theater, some from film, some from what he called "show biz." Experience in all those fields is helpful, he added, but the best basic education is still an all-purpose school of fine arts.</p>
        <p>Not all public lighting designers are French, but most of them are, and it is the French whose ideas and techniques are spreading throughout Europe. Electricite de France last year combined with the state electricity company of Italy to illuminate several major Italian monuments. And the French recently completed another project to light the castle that broods over Prague. No Flamboyance for Them</p>
        <p>It is in France, however, that French ideas have been most extensively and elaborately realized. And those ideas most definitely reflect a French sensibility. Despite the color possibilities opened up by halogen lights, the color range in Paris remains primarily white through a warm yellow to gold, a palette that Mr. Bideau called "more subtle, more refined" than the sometimes garish public lighting in New York.</p>
        <p>That harmonious sameness reflects the unanimity, or perhaps the uniformity, of the Paris cityscape. It is comparable to the 19th-century architecture that defines the "newer" parts of the city and whose facades are religiously preserved no matter how high-tech the interiors behind them.</p>
        <p>That conformity is enforced by a fierce attention to building and lighting codes, mixed with an unwritten pressure against deviation from accepted esthetic norms. Which pressure, in turn, might seem to dampen any French equivalents to the unbridled individuality that characterizes much American public lighting.</p>
        <p>"Every project, from state to municipal to private, has to conform to the rules of the city of Paris," Mr. Kaczmarek said. "But above all, there is a consensus."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
