<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Carroll Wins His First Against a Super Team</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BUFFALO BILLS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARROLL, PETE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0DA1338F936A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Carroll Wins His First Against a Super Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>ORCHARD PARK, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PETE CARROLL doesn't remember the exact moment somebody handed him a 1994 National Football League schedule with the notation: Sept. 4, Jets at Buffalo. He does remember his general reaction: "Look what we have to do."</p>
        <p>The Bills have merely set the standard for prolonged excellence and sheer cussedness by appearing in four straight Super Bowls -- winning none of them, but refusing to apologize for that oversight. Pete Carroll would begin his career as a head coach against those Bills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PETE CARROLL doesn't remember the exact moment somebody handed him a 1994 National Football League schedule with the notation: Sept. 4, Jets at Buffalo. He does remember his general reaction: "Look what we have to do."</p>
        <p>The Bills have merely set the standard for prolonged excellence and sheer cussedness by appearing in four straight Super Bowls -- winning none of them, but refusing to apologize for that oversight. Pete Carroll would begin his career as a head coach against those Bills.</p>
        <p>Carroll is currently an undefeated head coach because his assistants and his players put together a dominant 23-3 victory yesterday. Carroll's face used to light up the Jets' sideline when he was the defensive coordinator for Bruce Coslet, but yesterday he was even more effervescent as he danced and darted on the sidelines.</p>
        <p>"They came in here with a new style, and their attitude was different from Pete Carroll as opposed to Bruce Coslet," volunteered Thurman Thomas, the Bills' running back who perseveres after four disappointing Super Bowls. "They're all excited for him, and they all came in here and played very well."</p>
        <p>It was a nice thing for Thomas to say, and probably reflected the positive intensity he felt on the playing field and the gossip he heard in the tunnel after the game.</p>
        <p>Truth is, Carroll seems to have been consciously working on a kinder, gentler mood. Or maybe that's exactly the kind of guy he is, in which case this Jets' era might be a bit of fun. During training camp, Carroll sent a message to his players by rigging up a basketball court at the Jets' bunker on Long Island, and allowing a soccer shootout against Tony Meola, the World Cup goalkeeper who was trying out as a place-kicker.</p>
        <p>Carroll encouraged the offense and defense, the players and coaches, to mingle. Anything that might cut a decade's worth of bad vibes, sour faces and sullen mumbles was worth a try.</p>
        <p>Any Super Bowl aspirations for any American Football Conference team must always begin directly through the Bills, who had won six straight opening games while the Jets had been losing five of their last six openers. If this was going to be a new era, it had better happen quick.</p>
        <p>"Super Bowls Are Our Hobby/ See You at Joe Robbie." That's what a banner said yesterday. The Bills lost in Tampa Stadium, the Metrodome, the Rose Bowl and the Georgia Dome. You hear remarks that the Bills should be banned from appearing in the Super Bowl, that the networks don't want them around, that it's bad for the league. You have to consider the source. This is football thinking. The fans here will take their chances in South Florida.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the day that officially made baseball irrelevant for the rest of this year. Have a nice life, Bud Selig and Richard Ravitch and Donald Fehr. By blundering into a three-week strike, the owners and the players have outlasted the dog days of August. And now there is the United States Open of tennis, and college football, and starting yesterday there was Italian soccer on Sunday morning television in New York City, and all over this gristly 7-11 beer-belly land of ours, there were these mammoth bulked-up brutes plying their trade on national television.</p>
        <p>Some Jets took a lot on their shoulders by talking about reaching a new level of respectability over the Bills. Carroll sent a message to his players in his first noticeable game decision, at the end of the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The Jets had fourth down and officially a yard to the end zone when the clock ran out. They were losing, 3-0, after 15 minutes, and as they jogged to the other end of the field, they seemed to veer toward the Jets' bench, which is not always the case when players do not want to see the anxiety on the head coach's face.</p>
        <p>But here was the new head coach, his face as craggy as the Irish west coast, telling his behemoths to "Go for it." Even Nick Lowery, who was excluded by the decision to run rather than kick, wanted to hear those words, that meant there was no fear on the Jets' sideline.</p>
        <p>"From the half-yard mark?" Lowery asked. "You've got to score from there."</p>
        <p>The Jets scored a touchdown. They ran up 17 points in that quarter, and the Bills were never much in the game. The Jets overturned their container of Gatorade on Carroll near the end of the game, which gave him a bit of a shiver, but Carroll didn't seem to want to talk about this being a victory for him. He preferred to talk about the game plan of his new offensive coordinator, Ray Sherman, and the work of his new defensive coordinator, Greg Robinson.</p>
        <p>"We held Buffalo to 3 points up here, and that's not something I was ever able to do," said Carroll, who was the defensive coordinator under Coslet. "We just want to enjoy this in peace and quiet, not have a crazy celebration."</p>
        <p>At least the Jets were celebrating a victory over the habitual Super Bowl team. That doesn't happen much up here.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
