<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GIULIANI JOB CUTS STARTING TO HAVE IMPACT ON SERVICE: Transportation; Biggest Collapses Hidden at First</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSPORTATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E2D91338F936A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="486" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GIULIANI JOB CUTS STARTING TO HAVE IMPACT ON SERVICE: Transportation; Biggest Collapses Hidden at First</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More potholes, fewer repairs to sidewalks, longer delays in getting new signals installed and more hassles getting permits for digging up a street. Those are among the consequences that Transportation Department officials foresee from losing about 1,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>"When you whittle away like this, you take away our ability to do things," said one senior transportation official, who, like most in the department, insisted on anonymity. "It's not like the ferry is going to look any dirtier, but it's not going to look any cleaner."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More potholes, fewer repairs to sidewalks, longer delays in getting new signals installed and more hassles getting permits for digging up a street. Those are among the consequences that Transportation Department officials foresee from losing about 1,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>"When you whittle away like this, you take away our ability to do things," said one senior transportation official, who, like most in the department, insisted on anonymity. "It's not like the ferry is going to look any dirtier, but it's not going to look any cleaner."</p>
        <p>Some small programs have been erased. They include five inspectors who used to search city streets for potholes. Another unit of five employees who checked streetlights is gone.</p>
        <p>A two-employee office that taught schoolchildren how to safely cross a street has also been eliminated, although the city is looking for private donors for it. The department is also abandoning its planned crackdown on illegal van operators, saving seven positions.</p>
        <p>Repairing broken sidewalks when a property owner fails to has been cut back drastically. About 15 workers who made $20 million worth of repairs in the last fiscal year have been eliminated or transferred. Some Streets Might Sink</p>
        <p>Other cuts will be little noticed at first. The Mayor has cut 52 inspectors who monitor construction by utilities and plumbers -- more than a third of that inspection force.</p>
        <p>Since the streets are torn up 180,000 times a year in New York, officials say more plumbers are likely to get away with illegal or shoddy work on weekends. And over time, some streets might sink because the underlying material will not have been packed tightly enough.</p>
        <p>The administration has also trimmed by 22 -- about half -- the engineers who do the required traffic studies before new signs or signals can be installed. The wait for a study is already about 9 months and is almost certain to grow.</p>
        <p>While those cuts are likely to anger many residents, others may actually be popular.  This month the department will cut 40 tow-truck drivers, reducing the number of cars towed at least 15 percent in many places. The cuts will not affect downtown Brooklyn and midtown Manhattan, where Federal clean-air laws require more towing.</p>
        <p>Also, the department will lose 84 of the nearly 1,000 agents who write traffic tickets. But officials hope that the use of handheld computers and incentives for writing tickets will increase productivity.</p>
        <p>The department plans other small nips and tucks, like cutting in half the 14-person crew that cleans the Staten Island ferries. It has eliminated 14 of the 70 workers on bridge repair crews, 7 of the 49 bridge inspectors and 4 of the 14 overseers of road resurfacing projects. Since cuts were imposed last year, the city now plans to resurface only 800 miles of lanes rather than 1,000. Officials expect far more potholes this year than before.</p>
        <p>JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
