<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mark-Me-Down Elmo</title>
    <meta content="03SHOP$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/03/business/03shop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1631760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Target Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Thomson Financial Securities Data</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Wal-Mart Stores Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EFDD1631F930A35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mark-Me-Down Elmo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Early in Season, Wal-Mart Changes Sales Strategy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wal-Mart Stores is changing some selling strategies after poor showing over Thanksgiving weekend; will mark down two dozen of its most popular toys and electronics, run full-page ads in 15 major markets and 35 secondary markets and introduce seven 15-second television spots; will also run Internet 'circular' for first time, giving it flexibility to reduce prices again if competition gets too aggressive; Wal-Mart recorded only 0.7 percent sales increase for November among stores open at least a year, compared with its own projections of a 2 to 4 percent increase; Target, major competitor, was up 3.2 percent, in line with estimates; Thomson Financial index of overall retail sales rose 1.5 percent in November, missing 2.5 percent estimate and below last month's 4 percent; excluding Wal-Mart, index rose 2.8 percent; sales figures at other major retailers noted; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The empire strikes back.</p>
        <p>Stung by its poor showing over the Thanksgiving weekend, Wal-Mart Stores -- which accounts for about 10 percent of the nation's retail sales, excluding autos -- is quickly changing some selling strategies, executives said yesterday. Starting today, it is marking down two dozen of its most popular toys and electronics, from Elmos (now $16.88, they were $26.78) to portable DVD players ($149.87, formerly $179.87) to Black &amp; Decker electric jar openers ($28.42, down from $34.88).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stung by its poor showing over the Thanksgiving weekend, Wal-Mart Stores is quickly changing some selling strategies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The empire strikes back.</p>
        <p>Stung by its poor showing over the Thanksgiving weekend, Wal-Mart Stores -- which accounts for about 10 percent of the nation's retail sales, excluding autos -- is quickly changing some selling strategies, executives said yesterday. Starting today, it is marking down two dozen of its most popular toys and electronics, from Elmos (now $16.88, they were $26.78) to portable DVD players ($149.87, formerly $179.87) to Black &amp; Decker electric jar openers ($28.42, down from $34.88).</p>
        <p>Yesterday's across-the-board retailing numbers for November were mixed, with the gap widening between the ''haves,'' namely luxury stores, and the ''have-nots,'' discounters and midlevel department stores whose customers are suffering most from high gasoline prices. And while retailers reported that the day after Thanksgiving was strong, the rest of the weekend, for many, did not live up to expectations.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart will also begin an unusual advertising blitz this morning. Wal-Mart, which does not usually advertise in newspapers -- preferring the monthly color circular -- will run full-page ads in 15 major markets and 35 secondary markets, Mona Williams, the vice president for communications, said yesterday. Next week, Wal-Mart will introduce seven 15-second television spots.</p>
        <p>In addition, Wal-Mart, with $253 billion in sales last year, will run an Internet ''circular'' for the first time, giving it flexibility to reduce prices again if the competition gets too aggressive.</p>
        <p>More than a month ago, Wal-Mart announced that it would not join in the kind of ''price-beater'' and ''early-bird'' specials its competitors traditionally run the day after Thanksgiving, and Ms. Williams yesterday dismissed that approach again, labeling such limited-time, limited-quantity offers as ''gimmicks,'' and ''loss leaders.'' But she acknowledged that Wal-Mart had to do something to reverse its disappointing sales numbers for November -- and the corresponding bad publicity, which she called an ''overreaction.''</p>
        <p>For November, Wal-Mart recorded only a 0.7 percent sales increase among stores open at least a year, compared with its own projections of a 2 to 4 percent increase.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Target, a major competitor, was up 3.2 percent, in line with estimates. Target, analysts say, has a slightly different core customer than Wal-Mart. It has managed to project itself as a more ''aspirational'' brand, they say -- customers call it ''tar-jay'' (French, you know) -- as well as hiring Michael Graves to design tea kettles, and Isaac Mizrahi to design clothes.</p>
        <p>Americans, apparently, like feeling they are buying a ''cool'' brand or a brand that looks expensive -- preferably both.</p>
        <p>To prove the point, retail sales at Neiman Marcus stores rose 8.4 percent in November. Saks Fifth Avenue, which has had some rocky results lately, said sales rose 6.8 percent. But both May Department Stores, which owns Lord &amp; Taylor, and Federated Department Stores, owner of Macy's, had disappointing numbers.</p>
        <p>Terry J. Lundgren, Federated's chief executive, said the company was revising its fourth-quarter same-store sales downward, now projecting a figure between flat and a 1.5 percent increase, compared with prior predictions of a 1.5 to 3 percent increase.</p>
        <p>At Neiman Marcus, Burton M. Tansky, the chief executive, said best-selling items thus far into the holiday season had been ''anything with fur: fur collarettes and collars; those Prada 'key tricks' that hang from your purse; 7 Jeans with Swarovski crystals; and Etro men's striped shirts.'' A glance at Neiman's Web site would certainly leave someone used to shopping at Wal-Mart, or even Target, with a bad case of sticker shock.</p>
        <p>Analysts have widely written that Wal-Mart's strategy did not work, particularly on the day after Thanksgiving, generally called Black Friday because that is the day retailers count on to bring their stores into the black for the year.</p>
        <p>Some analysts criticized what they called deeper problems at the chain, including crowded display space; 27-inch television sets, for instance, were being sold off trailer trucks in the parking lots of some stores. Ms. Williams said the trucks were a once-a-year tradition at Wal-Mart, intended to ease checking out.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart said yesterday that December sales would probably increase in a range of 1 to 3 percent from a year earlier. Last year, comparable sales rose 4.3 percent.</p>
        <p>Because of its size, Wal-Mart's weak performance brought down many composite November retail indexes, in some cases more than a point. Last night, Thomson Financial said Wal-Mart made up 40 percent of the index, and therefore, ''skewed the entire mean.'' Thomson said its index of overall retail sales, compared with figures a year earlier, rose at ''an anemic 1.5 percent, missing the 2.5 percent estimate and below last month's 4 percent.'' Excluding Wal-Mart, the index rose 2.8.</p>
        <p>Analysts said J.C. Penney continued to turn around: it reported a 12 percent increase in sales yesterday, in contrast to a fall of 0.8 percent a year ago.</p>
        <p>Although Wal-Mart's stock has fallen $3 since the day before Thanksgiving, closing yesterday at $53, many analysts said yesterday that the company's stock was still worth buying. Of the 28 analysts tracked by Bloomberg, 19 rated the shares a buy. Seven advised clients to hold, and only two recommended selling.</p>
        <p>''Wal-Mart took a rational view of the whole process, and they're getting hammered for it,'' said Eric Beder, a retail analyst with JB Hanauer in New York. ''Why was their approach wrong? Black Friday is a joke -- these stores like Best Buy were giving away product. What does that do for Best Buy?''</p>
        <p>The answer is easy. Sales at Best Buy for the third quarter of 2004, which ended Nov. 27 -- the day after Black Friday -- were up 3.2 percent. (The chain does not break out monthly sales.) Yesterday morning, Best Buy's chief executive, Brad Anderson, said that ''outstanding execution drove a higher ticket price, and overcame softness in lower-priced categories such as CD's and DVD's.'' In other words, the chain was able to sell higher-priced items, more than making up for the weaker demand for less-expensive items.</p>
        <p>Among all stores, the worst-performing category last month was neither discounters nor department stores, but specialty clothing stores like Talbots, Hot Topic and Gap.</p>
        <p>Gap, which appeared to be securely in the midst of a turnaround last summer, seems to have stumbled with its fall fashion: sales fell 4 percent, registering negative numbers at both Banana Republic and Old Navy stores. And yesterday, Ann Taylor, a national chain that appeals to the career woman, cut its fourth-quarter profit projection, as its same-store sales in November fell 8.3 percent.</p>
        <p>For many, the continuing puzzle is the Hot Topic chain, which only a year ago, was still boiling, up double-digits almost every month. At that time, its chief executive, Betsy McLaughlin, was hailed for her constant monitoring of fickle teenagers. The question yesterday, as Hot Topic's sales dropped 8 percent, was whether the teenagers had cooled toward the Goth-inspired, music-driven clothes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
