<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inspections With Teeth</title>
    <meta content="20KRIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/20/opinion/20KRIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1425097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Nicholas D Kristof</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DF1130F933A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inspections With Teeth</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inspections With Teeth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nicholas D Kristof Op-Ed column, reporting from Baghad, says there is no sign of new conciliatory mood and Pres Bush is right to be exceptionally skeptical of Saddam Hussein's intentions; says, even so, administration is too dismissive of inspections; says only hope to avert war is inspections that are completely restructured and greatly empowered (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there's a new conciliatory mood here in Baghdad, it's even better hidden than Iraq's Scud missiles.</p>
        <p>The first thing a visitor sees after arriving at Saddam International Airport is a set of angry slogans in both English and Arabic declaring ''Down USA'' and ''Down With America.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there's a new conciliatory mood in Baghdad, it's even better hidden than Iraq's Scud missiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there's a new conciliatory mood here in Baghdad, it's even better hidden than Iraq's Scud missiles.</p>
        <p>The first thing a visitor sees after arriving at Saddam International Airport is a set of angry slogans in both English and Arabic declaring ''Down USA'' and ''Down With America.''</p>
        <p>Then after a spin down a lovely airport highway, it was time to step into the Al-Rasheed Hotel -- with its floor mosaic of the first President Bush scowling satanically at arriving guests. You have to step on his face to enter the hotel.</p>
        <p>''If the U.S. bombs Baghdad again,'' my taxi driver mused, ''maybe they'll add a picture of the younger Bush as well.''</p>
        <p>So while it's nice that weapons inspectors may return, there's not much sign of a change of heart in Baghdad. President Bush is right to be exceptionally skeptical of Saddam's intentions.</p>
        <p>Yet even so, the administration is too dismissive of inspections. The present structure is unworkable, but it just may be possible to put teeth in the inspections so that they really are meaningful, so that they could avert a war. Saddam's paramount aim is to survive, and if faced with tough ''comply or die'' inspections, he might choose his life over his Scuds. Certainly Iraq is jittery about an invasion.</p>
        <p>''So you're an American?'' an immigration official asked me in surprise when he saw my passport. He called me over, and I thought he was going to grill me about my visa (which took seven months of cajolery).</p>
        <p>''Is there going to be war?'' he asked worriedly.</p>
        <p>At customs, as officials were confiscating my mobile phones, which are banned in Iraq, they were much less interested in the phones themselves than in whether I would pay a bribe and whether there would be an invasion. And the talk quickly turned to war, since they acknowledged that nothing could rescue my mini-satellite phone, which the authorities worry about because spies could use them to call in air strikes.</p>
        <p>''He would have my throat cut if you were found with it,'' explained one official, pointing to a poster of Saddam, ''and you would be executed, too.'' (That dampened my own interest in holding on to the telephone.)</p>
        <p>Rigorous inspections are worth a try, because Saddam is a shrewd survivor. Indeed, it's a tribute to his survival talent that he's outmaneuvered the U.N. and rebuilt Iraq since the gulf war -- and that many Iraqis seem to blame Americans for a decade of sanctions and suffering, rather than him. In any case, there is no longer any sign of war damage, and the bazaars are bustling with Pepsi, Tom-and-Jerry school bags, Barbie coloring books, and 50-cent pirated videodiscs for movies like ''Unfaithful,'' ''Rush Hour'' and ''Snow Dogs.''</p>
        <p>The booming economy (the C.I.A. says the Iraq economy grew 15 percent in 2000) reflects smuggling, illegal oil surcharges and the eclipse of effective sanctions. Indeed, I came in from Damascus on a sanctions-busting flight, which shouldn't exist under the U.N. rules. But it was a Boeing 747, and every seat was full. That's not to say it was smooth: the plane had started down the runway when the crew realized that they had forgotten to close one door. They stopped, closed the door, and then we all chanted ''Allahu Akbar'' three times and took off.</p>
        <p>The only hope to avert war is inspections that are completely restructured and greatly empowered. One of the best ideas comes from Corey Hinderstein and David Albright of the Institute for Science and International Security: they suggest that Iraqi weapons scientists and their entire families could be taken out of Iraq and interviewed where they would be beyond retaliation.</p>
        <p>The earlier U.N. inspections have been justly criticized, but for all their weaknesses they did manage to destroy ''far more of Saddam Hussein's weapons of mass destruction'' than the gulf war itself did, the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace reported in March. Really tough and aggressive inspections could do even better and just might be able to neutralize Iraq without a war.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the mood here in Baghdad seems not just defiant but also rather unreal. This turns out to be Iraqi Tourism Week, and so travel agents from many countries are trampling over President Bush's face at the Al-Rasheed Hotel. One official noticed my incredulity about the tourism conference and explained, ''This was planned long ago.''</p>
        <p>E-mail: nicholas@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: nicholas@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
