<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Yale, a Photographer's Images of Pain</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE UNIVERSITY ART GALLERY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALGADO, SEBASTIAO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DA123DF936A35757C0A964958260" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Yale, a Photographer's Images of Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN RAYNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEBASTIAO SALGADO'S fame began in the 1980's with his photographs that showed the effects of starvation sweeping across Africa. Then came the shots of the Serra Pelada gold mine in his native Brazil. These were taken for The New York Times Magazine, as was a scene of a Kuwaiti oil field, one of a series published in the issue of June 9, 1991.</p>
        <p>Though the photographer has not focused exclusively on human anguish, it would seem that during his 19-year career he has been on hand for just about every major disaster, except for Bhopal, Chernobyl and the Challenger explosion. Hence, there are those who regard him as something of global ambulance chaser. Otherwise, the response to his images has been widespread admiration together with honors on the order of the W. Eugene Smith Memorial Award in 1982 and citation as Photojournalist of the Year by the International Center for Photography in 1986.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEBASTIAO SALGADO'S fame began in the 1980's with his photographs that showed the effects of starvation sweeping across Africa. Then came the shots of the Serra Pelada gold mine in his native Brazil. These were taken for The New York Times Magazine, as was a scene of a Kuwaiti oil field, one of a series published in the issue of June 9, 1991.</p>
        <p>Though the photographer has not focused exclusively on human anguish, it would seem that during his 19-year career he has been on hand for just about every major disaster, except for Bhopal, Chernobyl and the Challenger explosion. Hence, there are those who regard him as something of global ambulance chaser. Otherwise, the response to his images has been widespread admiration together with honors on the order of the W. Eugene Smith Memorial Award in 1982 and citation as Photojournalist of the Year by the International Center for Photography in 1986.</p>
        <p>Now Connecticut viewers have a chance to form their own opinions. The Yale University Art Gallery is offering a score of Salgado black-and-whites excerpted from "An Uncertain Grace," a show generated by the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art that is touring the nation. The Yale display was inaugurated by the photographer when he recently visited the university as a guest of the Chubb Fellowship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salgado's subjects seldom inspire anything less than awe. In Mali he records a solitary naked figure who stands supported by a stick on the desert that has filled in a lake bed. It is hard to tell if the figure is a man or a boy, and it hardly matters, for he's barely more than the sum of his bones, which echo the branches of a dead tree in the background. A younger skeleton, also in Mali, hangs in a sling being weighed in order to establish how much food he needs. The dial is illegible, but the needle is only one-quarter the way around.</p>
        <p>But the final word on starvation is the picture of a man laying out a child according to the Coptic rite in Ethiopia. The corpse is as desiccated as a mummy except for swollen hands that lie, little curled paws, on what was once a belly, while the bent-over father hovers above. It seems safe to say that in all of art there is no Pieta as affecting, and there it is, in a small tent made of translucent plastic.</p>
        <p>When interviewed by John Bloom in the November 1990 issue of Photo Metro magazine, Mr. Salgado expressed admiration for Cartier-Bresson, W. Eugene Smith, Walker Evans, Alvarez Bravo and others. He also mentioned writers -- Gabriel Garcia Marquez, for one. His photographs, however, speak of 19th-century French Realism -- in word and paint -- and none more so than those in the gold-mine series. In a cut that looks as deep as the Grand Canyon and twice as wide, labor myriad figures, including one who has just scaled one of the countless ladders lashed to the rock walls. In panoramic views of the scene, the figures swarm as if they were larvae just hatched from the eggs of a monstrous insect.</p>
        <p>Noting that he is concerned with paying homage to the working class, Mr. Salgado said in this interview that the old ways of producing are "fast disappearing." Yet his pictures suggest the very opposite. In the age of high technology, the need for backbreaking labor is clearly as great as ever, if not greater.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Salgado may be a hard-core romantic and optimist. The son of a cattle rancher and a former economist, he said that the working class is one group he can get "inside of." Whether or not this is the case, he always leaves his subjects their dignity, as did Lewis Hine, with whom he has often been compared.</p>
        <p>Most photographers would italicize aspects of horror in order to convey their own feelings and to make the viewer feel guilty. Mr. Salgado lets a situation speak for itself. He does not, he says, interfere with "anything in reality" or with the people that he photographs; he does not want to give his audience "a bad conscience," nor does he seek out the picturesque aspects of pain and destitution, although his Madonna and Child from Ethiopia seem too good to be true.</p>
        <p>There are pictures of suffering that should never have been taken -- notably the famous shot of the Vietnamese child on fire. But whatever the outrage engendered by Mr. Salgado's prints, it is not directed at the photographer, because somehow he seems trustworthy.</p>
        <p>Still, that is only one opinion. At their first publication, the Kuwait pictures, in which the landscape is nothing but sludge and lakes of oil, came with an essay by Martin Wade. This tells of Mr. Salgado burying an Iraqi soldier he found under a coat of oil. A fellow journalist asked him if he did this "so that no other photographers would get the shot." Oddly enough, Mr. Salgado dignified the question with an answer. In Brazil, he explained, the soul of a body left unburied would get no rest for all eternity.</p>
        <p>The photographs of Sebastiao S</p>
        <p>al</p>
        <p>gado rem</p>
        <p>ain through April 19 at the Yale University Art Gallery, 1111 Chapel Street in New Haven.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
