<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Uncommon Notes Herald Easter</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EASTER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARLES, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Easter and Holy Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB133FF936A35757C0A964958260" item-length="2598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Uncommon Notes Herald Easter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARLES, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSIC for the Easter season, as prepared by choirmasters and organists throughout Westchester, traditionally hews to the classic and predominantly solemn repertory. This year the programs are plentiful, as usual, and some music directors have dug deep to find works that are less frequently played but nonetheless inspiring.</p>
        <p>Among them is the "Dettingen Te Deum and Anthem" by Handel, a part of which will be performed at the Larchmont Avenue Presbyterian Church under the direction of Judith Brown. The work was composed to celebrate the June 1743 victory at Dettingen, near Frankfurt, by the English, Hanovarians and Austrians over the French in the War of the Austrian Succession. The composition was first sung at the Chapel Royal of St. James's in London in November of that year, and the text begins "The King Shall Rejoice."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSIC for the Easter season, as prepared by choirmasters and organists throughout Westchester, traditionally hews to the classic and predominantly solemn repertory. This year the programs are plentiful, as usual, and some music directors have dug deep to find works that are less frequently played but nonetheless inspiring.</p>
        <p>Among them is the "Dettingen Te Deum and Anthem" by Handel, a part of which will be performed at the Larchmont Avenue Presbyterian Church under the direction of Judith Brown. The work was composed to celebrate the June 1743 victory at Dettingen, near Frankfurt, by the English, Hanovarians and Austrians over the French in the War of the Austrian Succession. The composition was first sung at the Chapel Royal of St. James's in London in November of that year, and the text begins "The King Shall Rejoice."</p>
        <p>Among the first musical computers to be put to work in Westchester churches is the midicomputer system recently installed at St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church in White Plains. Brother Richard Biernacki, the music director, notes that it can reproduce 350 assorted instruments, voices and other sounds wired into the pipe organ. He will use it in performances of the "Missa Criolla" by Ramirez, an Argentine folk mass, and in Dave Brubeck's "40 Days in the Desert."</p>
        <p>Faure's Requiem, the composer's best-known work, was completed in 1890. While it was warmly received in France, it garnered almost no recognition elsewhere until after World War II. Today, Faure is considered one of France's greatest composers with a delicacy and elegance all his own. He studied with Saint-Saens and taught Maurice Ravel, Nadia Boulanger and Georges Enesco, among other musicians and composers. His Requiem can be heard in Pelham at the Huguenot Memorial Church and his Messe Basse for women's voices will be sung at the Larchmont Avenue Presbyterian Church.</p>
        <p>A sampling of music programs countywide is listed here, including those that include parts of Handel's "Messiah," first performed in Dublin on April 13, 1742. BRONXVILLE -- Christ Episcopal Church, 17 Sagamore Road. April 12, 10 A.M., "Hosannah to the Son of David" by Thomas Weelkes, "Solus ad Victimam" by Kenneth Leighton, excerpts from "St. John Passion" by Bach, with choir and organ. April 16, 8 P.M., "Mass in Four Voices" by William Byrd, "Drop, Drop, Slow Tears" by William Walton, "Ubi Caritas et Amor" by Maurice Durufle, "Salvator Mundi" by Thomas Tallis, with choir and organ.</p>
        <p>April 18, 5 P.M., Te Deum from "Collegium Regale" by Herbert Howells. April 19, 9:15 A.M., "The Day of Resurrection" by Thomas Matthews, "Victimae Pascale Laude" by Victoria, with organ and brass quartet. At 11:15, "Missa Collegium Regale" by Howells, "Ye Choirs of New Jerusalem" by Charles Stanford, "Haec Dies" by Byrd, with organ and brass quartet. Geoffrey Clark-Smith, music director. BRONXVILLE -- Concordia College, Sommer Center for Worship and the Performing Arts, 171 White Plains Rd. April 12, 3 P.M., "St. John Passion" by Bach, Louise Wohlafka, soprano; Stephen Oosting, tenor; Todd Fennel, baritone; Evelyn Reynolds, alto; Jeong-Jin Lee, tenor; John Packard, bass; with chorus and orchestra, conducted by Dr. Ralph C. Schultz. $10; students and elderly, $8. 337-9300, ext. 2171. IRVINGTON -- Church of St. Barnabas, 15 North Broadway. April 12, 10 A.M., "Allegro" by Giuseppe Fiocco, "My Song Is Love Unknown" by John Ireland, "Palm Sunday Procession" by T. Frederick Candlyn, "O Sacred Head" by Jean Langlais, with organ and Royce Janszen, trumpeter. April 16, 7:30 P.M., "The Celestial Banquet" by Olivier Messiaen, plainsong "Where True Charity and Love Dwell," "Jesus, Word of God Incarnate" by David Williams, "Deck Thyself, My Soul" by Brahms, with choir and organ.</p>
        <p>April 17, 8 P.M., "Forgive Our Sins" from the Sacred Harp Collection, "Adoramus Te" by Theodore Dubois, "Out of the Depths" by Handel, "Like as the Hart" by Herbert Howells, "O Dearest Lord" by Charles Callahan, "Ave Verum" by Elgar, "Here Lies He Now" by Bach, with choir and organ. April 19, 10 A.M. "Awake Thou Wintry Earth" by Bach, "Easter Fanfare" by Shirley Whitecotton, "Alleluia, Christ the Lord Is Risen" by Bach, "Prelude for a Te Deum" by Marc-Antoine Charpentier, with Royce Janszen, John Walters, trumpeters; Howard Howard, French horn; John Dexter, trombone, choir and organ. Donald Butt, music director. IRVINGTON -- Irvington Presbyterian Church, North Broadway. April 12, 11 A.M. "Marche Solemnelle" by Felix Borowski for choir; "Little Gray Donkey" by Natalie Sleeth, with children's choir; "Ride On, O King" by John Dressler, with Robert Joyner, tenor, "The Holy City" by Stephen Adams, "Praise to the Lord" by Max Reger, with choir and organ. At 4 P.M., "The Crucifixion" by John Stainer, with Juliana Bishop, soprano; Scott Walter and Robert Joyner, tenors; Robert Hoch, baritone; Marge Hone, flutist, and organ and choir. April 19, 11 A.M., "Ring Joy" by Allan J. Lorenz, with handbell choir, "Rondeau" by Jean Joseph Moret, "Alleluia, for the Lord Is Risen" by Bach, "Hallelujah" and "I Know That My Redeemer Liveth" from Handel's "Messiah," with Juliana Bishop, brass quintet, choir and organ, "Every Morning Is Easter Morning" by Avery and Marsh, with youth choir and organ. Thomas Zachacz, music director. LARCHMONT -- Larchmont Avenue Presbyterian Church, 60 Forest Park Avenue. April 12, 10 A.M., "Christus Factus Est" by Bruckner, "Lord Come Away" by Vaughan Williams, with Kyle Frey, tenor, and viola, choir and organ. April 17, 8 P.M., "Crucifixion" by Barber, with Patricia Kelby, mezzo-soprano, and two settings of Faure's Messe Basse for women's voices. April 17, 5:30 P.M., "Here, Come Bide We Still," from Bach's "St. Matthew Passion," "O Mensch Bewein" by Bach, "Kyrie Eleison" by Rutter, with Joyce Parry, soprano; Patricia Kelby, alto; Kyle Frey, tenor; Chandler Carter, baritone, and choir and organ.</p>
        <p>April 19, 9 and 11 A.M., excerpts from the "Dettingen Te Deum" by Handel, "Hallelujah Chorus" from Handel's "Messiah," "Alleluia Christ Is Risen" by William Byrd, excerpts from Handel's "Music for Royal Fireworks," "The Lord Is Risen" by Ian Pitt-Watson and Geoffrey Atkinson, with brass, timpani, organ and choir. Judith Brown, music director. MOUNT KISCO -- St. Marks Episcopal Church, Main Street. April 12, 10 A.M., "Hosannah to the Son of David" by Gibbons, "Benedictus" by Faure, "Christus Factus Est" by Bruckner, "Ex Ore Inoccentium" by John Ireland, with choir and organ. April 16, 6:30 P.M., "Ubi Caritas" by Durufle, "Ave Verum Corpus" by William Byrd, with choir and organ. April 17, noon, "O Crux Ave" by Palestrina, final chorus from "St. John Passion" by Bach, "Ye That Like Heedless Strangers Pass Along" by Gibbons, "Cross of Jesus, Cross of Sorrow" by Stainer, with choir and organ. April 19, 9 A.M., "Haec Dies" by Byrd, "I Know That My Redeemer Lives" by Johann Michael Bach, final chorus from Cantata 21 by J. S. Bach, "O Sing Joyfully" by Batten, with choir, organ and brass. At 11 A.M., repeat of 9 A.M. program, with addition of Missa Brevis by Palestrina. David Graf, music director. NORTH TARRYTOWN -- Old Dutch Church, North Broadway near Pierson Avenue. April 12, 4 P.M., "Olivet to Calvary" by Maunder, with choir, piano, and Lynn McReddi, soprano; William Orser, baritone; Richard Schlauch, tenor; John Dirrigl, bass. April 19, 8 A.M., "The Church of God Lifts Up Her Voice" by von Brachel, "O Sing a Song of Bethlehem" by Vaughn Williams, "We All Rejoice on This Glad Day" arranged by Strube, French carol "Love Is Come Again," with a capella Old Dutch Singers. Barbara VanderHart, music director. OSSINING -- Trinity Church, 7 South Highland Avenue. April 12, 10 A.M., "Christ, Now at Thy Passion" by d'Atorga, with choir and organ. April 16, 8 P.M., "Adoramus Te" by Mozart, with choir and organ. April 18, 7 P.M., "Alleluia, for Christ the Lord Is Risen" by Bach, with organ and choir. April 19, 10 A.M., "A Song for Easter" by Gordon Young, "Now the Green Blade Rises" by Marty Haugen, with handbells, choir, organ and Andrew Clarke, trumpeter; Carolyn Lavallee, French horn. Janet Vines, music director. PELHAM -- Parish of Christ the Redeemer, 1415 Pelhamdale Ave. April 12, 9:30 A.M., "Christus Factus Est" by Bruckner, "O Vos Omnes" by Michael Haydn, with choir and organ. April 19, 10 A.M., "The Trumpet Shall Sound" and "Hallelujah Chorus" from Handel's "Messiah," with choir, trumpets and organ, "Regina Coeli" by Mozart and Toccata from Widor's Symphony No. 5 for organ. John Lettieri, music director. PELHAM -- Huguenot Memorial Church, 901 Pelhamdale Ave. April 12, 10:30 A.M., Faure's Requiem with choir, orchestra and Serena Kanig, soprano; Jonathan Keeley, baritone. April 16, 8 P.M., Faure's Messe Basse, with choir and organ. April 19, 10:30 A.M., selections from "The Redemption" and "Faust" by Gounod, and Faure's "Cantique de Jean Racine," with choir, organ and soloists. Clark E. Anderson, music director. PLEASANTVILLE -- United Methodist Church, 70 Bedford Road. April 12, 10 A.M., "All Glory, Laud and Honor" by Bach, "Crown Him With Many Crowns" arranged by John Innes, with organ, choir and Bernice Banker, pianist. "The Palms" by Faure, "Hosannah" by Craig Courtney, "Now Enter Your Jerusalem" by Eugene Butler, with Peter Riss, drummer, and choir and organ.</p>
        <p>April 16, 7:30 P.M., "My Heart Is Filled With Longing" and "O Blessed Jesu" by Brahms, "Who Is That Man?" by Don Besig, with Peggy Derivan, flutist, Miriam Derivan, soprano. "Blute Nur" from Bach's "St. Matthew Passion." April 19, 10 A.M. "I Know That My Redeemer Liveth" from Handel's "Messiah," arranged by Lani Smith, "Christ the Lord Is Risen Today," arranged by John Innes, with soprano, choir and Ted Derivan, trumpeter, "Exultation for Easter" by Arnold Sherman, "Now, O Death Where Is Thy Sting?" by Russell Nagy, "Hallelujah Chorus" from Handel's "Messiah." June Riss, music director. RYE -- Presbyterian Church, Post Road at Parsons Street. April 12, 10 A.M., "Piece Heroique" by Cesar Franck, "Hosannah to the Son of David" by Victoria, "Carol of the Hill" by Stephen Paulus, "Sanctus" and "Benedictus" from Mozart's Missa Brevis in F, with choir and organ. April 16, 8 P.M., complete Missa Brevis in F by Mozart, with string quartet, and Lucille Beer, mezzo-soprano, excerpts from Bach's "St. Matthew Passion." April 17, 8 P.M., excerpts from Handel's "Messiah," with choir, organ and soloists.</p>
        <p>April 19, 6:30 A.M. in the courtyard, folk music sung a cappella by Robert Moncrief, with recorded accompaniment. At 9 and 11 A.M., music of Gabrieli, "Hallelujah Chorus" from Handel's "Messiah," "Lift High the Cross" by Todd Wilson, "We Know That Christ Is Raised" by Stanford, "Gabriel's Message Does Away" by Carl Schalk, with brass quartet, choir and organ, Toccata from Widor's Symphony No. 5 for organ. Robert Moncrief, music director. RYE -- Church of the Resurrection, 910 Boston Post Road. April 12, 10 A.M., "At the Name of Jesus" by Vaughan Williams, "Ride On in Majesty" by David Johnson, "Holy Eucharist" by John Rutter, with trumpets, choir and organ. April 17, 3 P.M., "Emproperia" by Victoria, "Locus Iste" by Bruckner, "O Jesu Christe" by Del Mel, "God So Loved the World" by Stainer, "O Sacred Feast" by Healy Willan, with a capella choir.</p>
        <p>April 18, 8 P.M., "Thanks Be to Thee" by Handel, "The Day of Resurrection" by Thomas Mathews, "Hail Thee, Festival Day" by Vaughan Williams, "Te Deum" by Jean Langlais for organ, "King of Glory Mass" by William Maul, with choir and organ. April 19, 10 A.M., "Trio Sonata in E flat" and "Prelude in D major" by Bach for organ, "St. Andrew Mass" by Tuk, with handbells, "He Is Risen, Hallelujah" by Engert, with choir and organ. William Maul, music director. SCARSDALE -- Congregational Church, 1 Heathcote Road. April 12, 10:30 A.M., "Hosannah to the Son of David" by Thomas Weelkes, "Christus Factus Est Pro Nobis" by Bruckner, "Chant Heroique" by Jean Langlais, with choir and organ. April 19, 11 A.M., "This Joyful Eastertide" by Charles Wood, "Festival Te Deum" by Britten, Peter Hurford's setting of "Magdalen, Cease From Sobs and Sighs" and "Light's Glittering Morn Bedecks the Sky" by Horatio Parker, with choir and organ, "Sarabande for the Morning of Easter" by Herbert Howells, Toccata from Widor's Symphony No. 5 for organ. Dr. John F. Schuder, music director. TARRYTOWN -- The Reformed Church of the Tarrytowns (formerly Second Reformed Church), 42 North Broadway. April 19, 10:30, "Jesus Is a Friend of Mine" by Mazak, with children's choirs; "Easter Triptych" by Mansfield; "Early Easter Morning" by Schultz, with bell choirs; "They Have Taken Away My Lord" by Stainer; "Hallelujah, Amen" from Handel's "Judas Maccabeus," with choir and organ. Barbara VanderHart, music director. WHITE PLAINS -- St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church, Sterling and Prospect Streets. Today, 10 A.M., "Forty Days in the Desert" by Dave Brubeck, Agnus Dei from "Missa Criolla" by Ramirez, with choir, organ and computer. April 12, 10 A.M., "Do You See That Man?" by Nagy, "Hosannah in Excelsis Deo" by Kauffmann, with choir and organ. April 16, 8 P.M., "Ave Verum" by Mozart. April 17, noon to 3 P.M., "Weepin' Mary" by Burleigh, Kyrie, Agnus Dei from "Missa Criolla" by Ramirez, "Crucifixion" by Hayes, with choir, organ and computer. April 19, 8 and 10 A.M., music for two trumpets and organ by Purcell and Vivaldi, "Hallelujah, Hearts to Heaven Raise" by Butler, "Now, O Death Where Is Thy Sting?" by Nagy, with choir and organ. Brother Richard Biernacki, music director. WHITE PLAINS -- Grace Episcopal Church, 33 Church St. Today, 10 A.M., "The Revival" by Edmund Rubbra, "Lord for Thy Tender Mercy's Sake" by Christoper Tie, organ works of Frank Bridge and Louis Vierne. April 12, 10 A.M., "Hosannah to the Son of David" by Gibbons, "Alas, They Have Taken Jesus" by Thomas Morley, works of Bach played by Gabriella Mangini, guitarist. April 15, 8 P.M., Tenebrae responsories by Victoria, "See How the Righteous One Dies" by Handel.</p>
        <p>April 16, 8 P.M., "Ubi Caritas" by Durufle, "O Sacre Convivium" by Tallis, organ works of George Shearing and Olivier Messiaen. April 17, noon, "The Reproaches" and "St. John Passion" of Victoria, "Adoramus te Christe" by Monteverdi, "O Crux Ave" by Palestrina, "O Vos Omnes" by Victoria, organ works of Buxtehude and Papadakos. April 18, 8 P.M., "Like as the Hart" by Howells, "Easter Anthem" by Billings, "Since by Man Came Death" by Handel, music for trumpet and organ by Reiche and Purcell, with Thomas Freas, trumpeter. April 19, 10 A.M., "Surrexit Dominus" by Handel, "Christ Our Passover" by Dirksen, antiphonal music for organ, timpani and the Kammer Brass Quintet, Toccata from Widor's Symphony No. 5. Timothy M. Lewis, music director. YONKERS -- St. John the Baptist Church, 670 Yonkers Ave. April 17, 9 A.M., Gregorian chants, a capella soloists from the choir. At 3 P.M., music for Good Friday by Michael Ward and Bruno Casolari, with chamber orchestra. At 7:30 P.M., music by Palestrina, Hassler and Bach. April 18, 7:30 P.M., gospel songs, Gregorian chants and psalms by Michael Ward, with choir and organ. April 19, 10 A.M., works by Michael Ward, "Christus Resurgenti" by Couperin, "Alleluia" from Bach's "Christmas Cantata," with choir and organ. Bruno Casolari, music director. YONKERS -- Messiah Baptist Church, 76 Warburton Ave. April 17, 7 P.M., "Crown Him King" by John Innes, with choir and organ. Thomasena Riggs, music director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
