<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chic Bar, Yes, But Babies Clearly Make This Party</title>
    <meta content="Y07WID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/07/nyregion/07WIDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1421561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TRACES OF TERROR: THE WIDOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cipriani (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santora, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cantor Fitzgerald Lp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DF103EF934A3575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chic Bar, Yes, But Babies Clearly Make This Party</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Chic Bar, Yes, but Babies Clearly Make This Party</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santora, Marc</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>'Baby shower' is held at Cipriani in Manhattan for widows who gave birth after Sept 11; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the bar at Cipriani yesterday, it was babies and not Bellinis. The lounge of the fashionable Midtown restaurant was transformed into a nursery to accommodate the widows who gave birth after Sept. 11, who gathered yesterday in preparation for the first anniversary of the attacks.</p>
        <p>The event, organized by the Independent Women's Forum, a conservative research institute based in Arlington, Va., was billed as a baby shower of sorts. In fact, it was part shower, part support group and part celebration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the bar at Cipriani yesterday, it was babies and not Bellinis. The lounge of the fashionable Midtown restaurant was transformed into a nursery to accommodate the widows who gave birth after Sept. 11, who gatheredyesterday in preparation for the first anniversary of the attacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the bar at Cipriani yesterday, it was babies and not Bellinis. The lounge of the fashionable Midtown restaurant was transformed into a nursery to accommodate the widows who gave birth after Sept. 11, who gathered yesterday in preparation for the first anniversary of the attacks.</p>
        <p>The event, organized by the Independent Women's Forum, a conservative research institute based in Arlington, Va., was billed as a baby shower of sorts. In fact, it was part shower, part support group and part celebration.</p>
        <p>At least 102 women were pregnant when their husbands died in the attacks, said Judy Hill, director of the group's infant care project. Mrs. Hill said the group's goal was to help the widows, not just financially but in ways that ease the burden of caring for a newborn without the help of a spouse.</p>
        <p>''Can you imagine how difficult it has been for these women?'' Mrs. Hill asked. She said that if the $4,000 the forum has given to each widow helped them get one night of better sleep, it was worth it.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's lunch, which was attended by about 60 of the mothers, was an opportunity for many of the women to meet for the first time.</p>
        <p>Little James Carson, 6 months old, looked happy in the lounge, which was filled with toys, playpens, stuffed monkeys and dolls. His mother, Debbie Carson, said she named her son after her husband, who died in the World Trade Center.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Carson came to the lunch with her good friend Lisa Reina and Mrs. Reina's toddler, Joseph, named after his father. The two women had much in common: their husbands both worked at Cantor Fitzgerald, both couples were married on the same day and the two women met during their honeymoons in 1999. Unfortunately, they also shared the devastation of losing their husbands. But Mrs. Carson said the friendship of the other women was a comfort.</p>
        <p>Sheila Ornedo -- whose husband, Ruben, was a passenger on the hijacked plane that crashed into Pentagon -- and her baby, Robin, flew in from Los Angeles for the lunch. She was meeting Haven Fyfe and her son, Parker, for the first time. The two compared notes on exercise and cooed over the babies.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Fyfe said that nearly a year after she lost her husband, Karleton, who was aboard one of the planes that crashed into the World Trade Center, ''the low times are still harder to manage.''</p>
        <p>Heather Higgins, vice chairwoman of the group, said the idea for the program to help the widows was simple. She said she kept noticing pregnant women on television in the days after Sept. 11. The task of getting a list together was not at all simple, however.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hill said she called 385 companies over the course of two months to compile the list. She cautioned that she was still being contacted by widows, so the list may not be complete. In addition to the 102 mothers, there is one man who was given a $4,000 check by the group. His wife, who waited on tables at Windows on the World, had given birth shortly before she was killed. The group has raised about $500,000 so far. The money given to the widows is intended for child care.</p>
        <p>At the lunch, Joyce Rumsfeld, the wife of Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld, read a letter from the first lady, Laura Bush, wishing the women well.</p>
        <p>Then Jenna Jacobs, the mother of Gabriel and the widow of Ariel, who was killed in the trade center, gave an emotional speech. She found the words for what many of the women said was difficult to express.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I get the impression that people think we are the sum total of our loss,'' Mrs. Jacobs said. But that is not true. ''Above all, we are mothers.''</p>
        <p>TRACES OF TERROR: THE WIDOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
