<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albert Maysles' Camera Sees And Says It All</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940227T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="668416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOND, JAMIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAYSLES, ALBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDA1738F930A25751C0A962958260" item-length="1990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albert Maysles' Camera Sees And Says It All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE DIAMOND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOND, JAMIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT THE TIME "LEAVE IT TO Beaver" reached its apex, a handful of film makers set out to make a new kind of documentary. Armed with modified lightweight cameras and sound equipment, they could follow a child who disappeared into a crowd at a race track or record the blows of a fist fight as it roared through a bar and spilled into an alley. And so these intrepid film makers began to shatter the granite face of the documentary. Critics called their work direct cinema; in France, they called it cinema verite.</p>
        <p>Albert Maysles, now 67, was one of those pioneers; his latest documentary, "Umbrellas" (made with Henry Corra and Grahame Weinbren and featuring Christo's umbrella project as it unfolded in Japan and California in 1991), has been selected to have its premiere on Friday at the Berlin International Film Festival. A year ago, "Abortion: Desperate Choices," which Mr. Maysles (pronounced MAY-zuls) made with Susan Froemke and Deborah Dickson, won an Emmy for Outstanding Informational Special after it was shown on HBO.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT THE TIME "LEAVE IT TO Beaver" reached its apex, a handful of film makers set out to make a new kind of documentary. Armed with modified lightweight cameras and sound equipment, they could follow a child who disappeared into a crowd at a race track or record the blows of a fist fight as it roared through a bar and spilled into an alley. And so these intrepid film makers began to shatter the granite face of the documentary. Critics called their work direct cinema; in France, they called it cinema verite.</p>
        <p>Albert Maysles, now 67, was one of those pioneers; his latest documentary, "Umbrellas" (made with Henry Corra and Grahame Weinbren and featuring Christo's umbrella project as it unfolded in Japan and California in 1991), has been selected to have its premiere on Friday at the Berlin International Film Festival. A year ago, "Abortion: Desperate Choices," which Mr. Maysles (pronounced MAY-zuls) made with Susan Froemke and Deborah Dickson, won an Emmy for Outstanding Informational Special after it was shown on HBO.</p>
        <p>Sitting at his desk in his midtown Manhattan office, where editing machines make the sounds a drainpipe would if strangled, Mr. Maysles is explaining his newest theory. He thinks he understands why people reveal themselves to him.</p>
        <p>"For the first 20 years of my life, I must have uttered about 20 sentences. So they sent me to therapy and told me my mother was dominant and my father was submissive." Mr. Maysles waves his hand around his office, which is filled with editors wearing white cotton gloves. "That was nonsense! It was all because I had a learning disability. I was so afraid I wasn't getting everything that the intensity of my listening became greater than anybody else's. In college I would listen so fiercely that sooner or later -- even if he had a thousand kids in front of him -- the instructor would find me, and from then on, it would be just the two of us. A learning disability makes you concentrate as a visual person."</p>
        <p>O.K. Mr. Maysles' learning disability made people -- from Mick Jagger and Marlon Brando to a young woman literally undergoing an abortion -- drop their guard. Anything else? Little gestures, Mr. Maysles suggests. "People sense -- from the way you handle the camera, even the way you introduce yourself -- if you're going to intrude on them or hurt them. They sense it when you are really paying attention. To attend means to wait," Mr. Maysles says. "That perfectly describes what we do."</p>
        <p>For more than three decades Maysles Films has been making documentaries in which the camera seems to be a fly waiting on the walls of some very interesting places: the Beatles making up Marlboro commercials in their limo as they visit America for the first time; Truman Capote making a drink at home ("It has to be perfect. You wouldn't want to have a rather good oyster, would you?"); Vladimir Horowitz listening to his rehearsal playback and, with his eyes closed, conducting the piece; the artist Christo, variously, over the years, hanging an orange curtain across a Colorado valley, unfurling umbrellas in Japanese rice paddies and on the crests of California hills, wrapping 11 Miami islands in hot pink and the Pont Neuf in a tarnished golden fabric.</p>
        <p>Christo's work, like Mr. Maysles' films, leaves room for the unexpected; things fall as they may, sometimes even an umbrella. "Christo loves a lack of control," Mr. Maysles says. "He starts with umbrellas but then counts on the forces of nature. Chaos theory is almost the way we both work."</p>
        <p>Oddly, the idea behind cinema verite -- choosing moments where action might occur instead of creating it -- did not enter the world the day hand-held cameras and tape recorders appeared in the late 1950's. (No one ran out, as they do today, to buy a camcorder to record police beatings and birthday parties.)</p>
        <p>The idea was the brainchild of Robert Drew, an editor at Life magazine. He believed the magazine enjoyed its success because it brought into the home pictures of action in the midst of happening -- four soldiers struggling to plant the flag at Iwo Jima, for instance -- and he wanted to extend that concept to documentaries. "I thought all we had to do was put a Life photographer who valued candid photography behind a motion picture camera, and we could make a new kind of film." But thanks to an eight-man crew that had to stop and set heavy equipment on tripods, action eluded capture.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Drew started to experiment with lightweight cameras and sound recorders. In 1959, under the banner of Drew Associates, he put together a film crew, all of whom went on to write their names on the pages of documentary history: Albert Maysles, Terence Filgate (a film maker well known in his native Canada), Richard Leacock ("Monterey Pop") and D. A. Pennebaker ("Don't Look Back," "The War Room").</p>
        <p>The film makers set out in the dark: they were making documentaries with no directors, no scripts, no sets, no lights, little or no narration and no interviews. To be at the right place at the right moment was everything. They considered themselves neutral observers who merely recorded ongoing events and had, as much as possible, no point of view. Their first important work was "Primary," which tracked Senators John F. Kennedy and Hubert H. Humphrey through the cold 1960 Wisconsin Democratic Presidential primarily.</p>
        <p>"They took a big chance on me," says Mr. Maysles, who as a psychology instructor at Boston University had been to the Soviet Union several times and shot a silent film about Russian mental hospitals in 1955. "I came out of nowhere. The others were film makers, and my father was a postal clerk and my mother was a schoolteacher. I'd only learned to use the camera the night before, and I spent the next five days with Kennedy and Humphrey."</p>
        <p>Richard Leacock, who had worked as a cinematographer for Richard Flaherty ("Nanook of the North"), says, "We felt like a bunch of jewel thieves. We felt like we were out there stealing things."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pennebaker was equally undaunted by the scriptless challenge. "What would have been a problem was getting those important people to wait while you set up tripods and lighting," he says.</p>
        <p>Their approach, says Mr. Filgate, offered an alternative to the Edward R. Murrow style of documentaries. "It was as if we were butterfly hunting. We knew there were butterflies in the woods, but we didn't know what kind, and we didn't know how we were going to catch them; whereas in the journalistic documentary, a reporter says, 'On my left, hidden in the bushes, are thousands of butterflies.' And then the camera cuts away to the bushes. Drew, with 'Primary,' broke that mold."</p>
        <p>In 1962, Albert Maysles left Drew Associates and formed Maysles Films with his younger brother, David (who died in 1987). While Albert had been filming mental patients, David had been working as a production assistant on two Marilyn Monroe films. With David on sound and Albert behind the camera, the Maysles brothers began their bifurcated career, making award-winning commercials for companies like I.B.M., Shell Oil and Merrill Lynch in order to finance award-winning documentaries like "Salesman" (1968), a bleak study of four down-on-their-luck Bible salesmen; "Gimme Shelter" (1970), an account of the Rolling Stones's Altamont concert that unexpectedly captured a murder on film, and "Grey Gardens" (1976), a look so close as to be uncomfortable at a mother and daughter, relatives of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, in their decaying East Hampton mansion.</p>
        <p>When Maysles Films began, the brothers could afford to wait around for the days or months that filming a single documentary could take. "We had an apartment for $36. So we broke it down to $18 each," says Mr. Maysles. "Now I'm spending 10 times that much just to park my car in a garage."</p>
        <p>Even though the days of double-digit rents have passed, Mr. Maysles still adheres to the original Drew Associates principles -- waiting and nonintervention. His position is not fashionable with the film makers who came of age in the 1960's and saw documentaries as a way to convey their messages. Like Michael Moore, whose "Roger and Me" was a dark-humored indictment of General Motors; or Errol Morris, whose "Thin Blue Line" revealed an accused murderer to be innocent; or Barbara Kopple, whose films "Harlan County U.S.A." and "American Dream" showed the awful plight of striking workers.</p>
        <p>But how objective can a film maker be? Something as simple as the part of the body the camera focuses on (long shot? close-up?) conveys a value (this is interesting, that is not). And who believes the effect of a camera's presence can be dismissed? "Any work of art is a combination of objective and subjective," Mr. Maysles admits. "But I try to minimize my effect. I don't interview people, for instance. If you ask a question, that determines the answer. Making a film isn't finding the answer to a question; it's trying to capture life as it is, so the audience can say, 'Oh, my God, I'm right there, and I didn't have to make a film to see it.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Corra says, "Albert has a spiritual faith that life is going to unfold before him. He believes that with enough patience and time and care telling moments are eventually going to happen, and we will be there to capture them. In his most idealistic mind, our films would be an assemblage of these pure moments that just sort of occur and are captured on film."</p>
        <p>Some of Maysles Films' documentaries don't fit the purist mold, like their three HBO specials (and best-selling home videos) that take dirtysomething looks behind the scenes of the Sports Illustrated Swimsuit issues.</p>
        <p>"That isn't such a complication for Al because Al is looking for experience behind the camera," Mr. Pennebaker explains. And what is the experience behind the camera? "The selecting and the focusing down on a face is very similar to what you do when you bond with your children or your beloved. If you do it long enough, that face starts to fill you with a certain pleasure. It's not unlike falling in love with somebody." So it's not that the camera had a love affair with Marilyn Monroe, it was all those cameramen.</p>
        <p>But love is a two-way street. What makes people permit a camera to record their private moments? (See Mr. Jagger watching the Maysles' footage of a man in a green suit being stabbed to death while the singer was snarling out "Sympathy for the Devil.") "I read a book on family therapy," Mr. Maysles says, "and the therapist said that between the urge to conceal and the urge to reveal, the urge to reveal is always stronger."</p>
        <p>In 1987, after his brother's death, Mr. Maysles brought two new partners to Maysles Films, the film makers Ms. Froemke (her work with Mr. Maysles has earned four Emmys) and Mr. Corra. In both his company's reality-based commercials and its documentaries, Mr. Maysles sees a through line. "Our work doesn't depend on so-called beauty shots."</p>
        <p>Mr. Corra agrees. "Al's not about camera technique, or lighting or beautiful composition. He doesn't have a painterly quality or the things that are often attributed to great directors of photography. There's a way Al goes around the room and sees all the characters, and after, you feel like you've had a really intimate experience with all of them."</p>
        <p>These days, the bespectacled and diminutive Mr. Maysles has the air of a child in the midst of discovery. "People understand Al by looking at him," says Mr. Drew. "He communicates with his eyes, and there's no pretense of falseness about him. He can walk into a room with any kind of person anywhere and understand what they're up to and capture some of that on film."</p>
        <p>His success may lie with the fact that he has invented a life's work in perfect harmony with his character. Says Mr. Pennebaker, "What makes Al a good cameraman is that he's nonjudgmental. At least in certain areas. I don't know what he'd be like if he were filming Hitler."  FILM  Correction:  February 27, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 13 about Albert Maysles and other documentary-film makers misstated the first name of the director of "Nanook of the North." He was Robert Flaherty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 27, 1994, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 13 about Albert Maysles and other documentary-film makers misstated the first name of the director of "Nanook of the North." He was Robert Flaherty.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
