<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Welcoming Place to Raise a Glass</title>
    <meta content="13rest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/13/dining/reviews/13rest.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3DB1531F930A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Welcoming Place to Raise a Glass</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Welcoming Place to Raise a Glass</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Bruni</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS a chef on a path to running his own restaurant, Ralf Kuettel did what anyone would expect, spending most of the last two decades in professional kitchens. He cooked at Union Square Cafe in its early years. He cooked at Cena before it closed.</p>
        <p>But it's the unexpected thing he did when he stepped away from the stove that had the most important impact on Trestle on Tenth, which he opened in Chelsea about two months ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The wine list at Trestle on Tenth favors small over large producers, spirited over lulling wines, adventure over surefire accessibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS a chef on a path to running his own restaurant, Ralf Kuettel did what anyone would expect, spending most of the last two decades in professional kitchens. He cooked at Union Square Cafe in its early years. He cooked at Cena before it closed.</p>
        <p>But it's the unexpected thing he did when he stepped away from the stove that had the most important impact on Trestle on Tenth, which he opened in Chelsea about two months ago.</p>
        <p>From 2001 to 2005, Mr. Kuettel wallowed in wine. He started out as a salesman at the Chelsea Wine Vault. Then he was the buyer and store manager there. His arc matters less than his destination. He became a grape geek of the most fetching, infectious kind.</p>
        <p>I say this not because I know him (I don't), but because I know the wine list he has put together for Trestle on Tenth, a principled document that favors small over large producers, spirited over lulling wines, adventure over surefire accessibility.</p>
        <p>While so many other wine lists seem to have been assembled by a computer program -- with France and California meted out in predetermined measure and enough generically velvety pinot noir to fill an Olympic-size swimming pool -- this one has a real point of view.</p>
        <p>On it you'll find as much cabernet franc as cabernet sauvignon, and you'll find more Italian lagreins (two) than Chiantis (none). You'll find a white wine called a savagnin from the Jura region of France, a red wine called a gamaret from Switzerland and other wines that seldom claim attention from wine-producing areas that seldom command adulation.</p>
        <p>And you'll have enough confidence in Mr. Kuettel's judgment to be tempted to order them, because when you do find a wine you know -- I spotted and drank a beloved Breton Bourgueil, Clos Sénéchal -- you'll recognize it as a prudent choice.</p>
        <p>What's more, you're likely to feel you can afford to take a chance. Most of the bottles on the list, which encompasses about 75 wines, are around or under $50, in part because Mr. Kuettel tends not to mark his wines up more than about double the retail price.</p>
        <p>That's gracious and reasonable, and it's a reason to single out Trestle on Tenth, an otherwise uneven neighborhood restaurant whose individualism doesn't work as well when it comes to food.</p>
        <p>The first part of its name refers to the High Line tracks nearby. The second part refers to the address of the restaurant, which extends the recently formed restaurant row on 10th Avenue a bit farther north.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuettel is obviously betting on new development in the area: the low-key, unselfconsciously handsome environment he's fashioned from what used to be the Chelsea Commons is the kind of warm little hug that beckons those at hand. Diners who live more than a dozen blocks away can probably find these sorts of exposed brick walls, wide-plank wood floors and even a back garden like Trestle's closer to home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuettel was born and trained in Switzerland, and his menu, like his native country, is stamped with German and French influences. But what's most striking about it is the force with which it hits rebelliously hearty notes. It seems to anticipate winter long before the first frost, and it challenges vain, health-conscious New Yorkers to wade into the starchy and dive headlong into the flabby.</p>
        <p>Cuts of meat came with what must have been the legal limit of fat stippling, striping or skirting them. Each of three pudgy, pale red slices of meltingly tender saddle of lamb, for example, was encircled by a shockingly broad white border.</p>
        <p>I mention this not in protest but in gratitude, and it's in that same vein that I salute a bracingly rich crépinette that pulled together pulled pork shoulder, braised Savoy cabbage and an intense pork reduction.</p>
        <p>As for starchy indulgences, there was a side dish of dumplings called pizokel, pleasantly thickened with Gruyère. A crunchy potato pancake that accompanied sautéed veal kidneys in a Trappist ale sauce was the shape and size of half a Frisbee.</p>
        <p>It was also an example of the way homey joins hearty as one of the menu's guiding adjectives. Trestle on Tenth is the kind of restaurant at which, no matter what you ate, you feel as if you had brisket.</p>
        <p>Sure, there are two salads on the dinner menu, but the good one showered a rich buttermilk dressing and hunks of bacon over butter lettuce. The other salad, a collection of field greens with a sherry vinaigrette, was a wan throwaway.</p>
        <p>Yes, there's fish, but it didn't stand out. And in the cases of both an appetizer of Arctic char gravlax and a salmon entree, there were additional elements -- pumpernickel bread for the char, lentils and horseradish for the salmon -- that turned the dishes into heavier affairs.</p>
        <p>In fact too much at Trestle on Tenth didn't stand out or succeed. A restaurant with a lineup of dishes this peculiar and concise (about eight appetizers and eight entrees) can't afford to serve an oxtail and pig's foot terrine as gelatinous and unfocused as the one here. Or a cauliflower soup, sautéed frogs' legs, a roasted chicken and a sirloin steak as bland.</p>
        <p>It needs a stronger finish than it gets from a merely serviceable roster of desserts -- the worst being an alarmingly sour chocolate cake.</p>
        <p>But before that final act, there's plenty of available pleasure, including the selections on the wine list, commendably tailored to the robustness and pedigree of the food. It's predominantly European and emphasizes colder climes in its search for wines with more structure and presence than immediate fruitiness.</p>
        <p>It doesn't pander by trotting out oak-choked, numbingly buttery California chardonnays, and when I was there (the list changes), there wasn't a pinot grigio to be had. All in all this list is a model of what a restaurateur can do without tons of money or storage space. He can target affordable discoveries. Coax diners to take chances.</p>
        <p>And keep secrets from his wife. Mr. Kuettel is married to Juliette Pope, the beverage director for Gramercy Tavern. In a telephone interview, he said that if he happens across two cases of a treasured wine, ''I might snag the first case and tell her there's a second.''</p>
        <p>''But generally,'' he added with a laugh, ''I don't.''</p>
        <p>Trestle on Tenth  * [Rating: One Star]  242 10th Avenue (24th Street), Chelsea; (212) 645-5659.</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A bar near the entrance, a garden out back, lots of exposed brick and wide-plank wood floors create a warm, casual feel.  SOUND LEVEL -- A very lively buzz.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Pork crépinette; butter lettuce with buttermilk; lamb saddle; veal kidneys; pork loin; pizokel with Gruyère; beets; strawberry sundae; walnut and caramel torte.  WINE LIST -- An exemplary selection of interesting and affordable wines from small producers (most of them European) that's a model for restaurants without enormous wine budgets. A fine beer selection as well.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch appetizers, salads and sandwiches, $6 to $13. Entrees, $10 to $14. Dinner appetizers, $8 to $12.50. Entrees, $18 to $25. Desserts, $8.50.  HOURS -- Lunch from noon to 3 p.m. Tuesday through Friday. Dinner from 5:30 to 10:30 p.m. Tuesday through Thursday, to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday and to 10 p.m. Sunday. Weekend brunch to be added.  RESERVATIONS -- For prime dinner times, call at least a day in advance.  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- One step up to main entrance and no available ramp. Restrooms not accessible.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:  (None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  ***Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>PAST REVIEWS from The Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics: nytimes.com/dining</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
