<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SATURDAY INTERVIEW -- Bruce Karatz; Gearing Up For Slowdown In Housing</title>
    <meta content="01interview" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/01/business/01interview.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1751085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Saturday Interview With Bruce Karatz"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kb Homes</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karatz, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bajaj, Vikas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D91230F932A35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SATURDAY INTERVIEW -- Bruce Karatz; Gearing Up For Slowdown In Housing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gearing Up for Slowdown in Housing</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIKAS BAJAJ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bajaj, Vikas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with KB Homes chairman Bruce Karatz, who comments on his try-anything style and housing market slowdown; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Karatz subscribes to the ''jump in with feet first'' philosophy of life, an approach that has proved tremendously successful.</p>
        <p>When he was assigned to run KB Home's French operations in 1976, Mr. Karatz, now KB's chairman and chief executive, asked that his secretary speak only French, even though he had taken just three days of language lessons before leaving.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Karatz subscribes to the "jump in with feet first" philosophy of life, an approach that has proved tremendously successful.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bruce Karatz subscribes to the ''jump in with feet first'' philosophy of life, an approach that has proved tremendously successful.</p>
        <p>When he was assigned to run KB Home's French operations in 1976, Mr. Karatz, now KB's chairman and chief executive, asked that his secretary speak only French, even though he had taken just three days of language lessons before leaving.</p>
        <p>''It absolutely forced me to muddle my way through,'' he said in a recent telephone interview from his office in Los Angeles, where KB is based. ''And really in about six months you speak the language.''</p>
        <p>While in France, Mr. Karatz, 60, started successful operations in Lyons and Marseille and created a stir by building a model home atop a department store in Paris, which with 500,000 visitors in five months attracted more people than all other KB Home properties did all year.</p>
        <p>Raised in Minnesota, where his family owned a movie theater, Mr. Karatz's try-anything style and marketing finesse have paid off handsomely for KB Home -- the company's stock has more than tripled in the last four years -- and for him, with his stock and pay package frequently making him the highest paid executive in California.</p>
        <p>That record, however, will face its greatest test this year as the housing market slows. Following are excerpts from the interview:</p>
        <p>Q. Tell me about the thinking behind the homes you are building with Martha Stewart.</p>
        <p>A: Of everything I've been involved in, the Martha venture is by far the best. And the reason it's the best is that it's not a promotion. It's not just a marketing idea. There is real substance to it. She is a talent when it comes to knowing how people want to live, like to live.</p>
        <p>Q. You have announced that you are building up to 20,000 homes outside New Orleans and plan to do more. Is this a good-will gesture or will it be a profitable business?</p>
        <p>A. The initial motivation was let's go in on a humanitarian basis and build quickly and well-quality homes, and get it moving. The problem with that is our heart was in the right place but we couldn't find lots to actually build. So as we stepped back, we said, O.K., this is going to be a longer-term process. We're going to have to go through planning and go through all of those administrative steps. Let's go in and set up a division and do it on a for-profit basis. We know how to do that.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the biggest challenge to making money there?</p>
        <p>A. The challenge is trying to determine what the demand is. In any market you go into, you can extrapolate from the past building cycle and job growth to anticipate what the future will bring. There is no way to know in New Orleans. There has been such a major displacement of population that you can be, on the one hand, quite optimistic that there are hundreds of thousands who want to move back to New Orleans. But there's another side, which is maybe these people aren't coming back.</p>
        <p>Q. Recently, KB Home said that orders fell 12 percent in the first quarter from a year ago. Is that indicative of the rest of the year, will it get better or worse?</p>
        <p>A. My personal view is that the market is adjusting downward from a market that was very heated, generally along both coasts. The speculators, investors who were in the market, that varied from, let's say, 10 to 15 percent of sales in any given -- of the so-called hot markets -- are gone.</p>
        <p>I believe when that all settles, we're going to have very strong demand on any historical basis; not as good as it was a year ago, but still very strong. And big home builders are going to be able to operate very well. I don't think there's going to be any significant price depreciation.</p>
        <p>Q. So if prices are not falling how do you attract buyers, are you using incentives?</p>
        <p>A. We don't believe in incentives. We're selling buyers choice, and we sell buyers quality. And this is the single most serious purchase, economic decision made by a family. So we do not believe telling people that they can get $50,000 off on a particular home is going to move them to whether they buy it or not. There are more serious criteria than that.</p>
        <p>Q.  But doesn't, at some point, the price give?</p>
        <p>A. Sure. If in a submarket you were to have a serious correction in value driven by all your competition, there would be, theoretically, a point where you would have to adjust your prices. It's one thing, to be the best design, best quality, best service, but value has to be there.</p>
        <p>Saturday Interview With Bruce Karatz</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
