<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chess</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BYRNE, ROBERT (BYLINER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D6113AF936A15751C0A964958260" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chess</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Byrne</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BYRNE, ROBERT (BYLINER)</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is an awful lot of speculating going on these days. That might be because the standard time limit has been changed from 40 moves in two and a half hours to 40 moves in a flat two hours, the thought behind the faster play being, "My opponent will never find the right defense to my complicated attack in that short a time."</p>
        <p>And most of the time, the gambiteers are right. The great virtuosos of the defensive game are mostly in or close to their retirement years. Sammy Reshevsky is over 80 years old and cannot give these pirates their comeuppance as in the old days. Viktor Korchnoi is finally declining at the age of 61. Anatoly Karpov is probably the last top player whom no one takes liberties with (except, of course, the world champion, Gary Kasparov).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is an awful lot of speculating going on these days. That might be because the standard time limit has been changed from 40 moves in two and a half hours to 40 moves in a flat two hours, the thought behind the faster play being, "My opponent will never find the right defense to my complicated attack in that short a time."</p>
        <p>And most of the time, the gambiteers are right. The great virtuosos of the defensive game are mostly in or close to their retirement years. Sammy Reshevsky is over 80 years old and cannot give these pirates their comeuppance as in the old days. Viktor Korchnoi is finally declining at the age of 61. Anatoly Karpov is probably the last top player whom no one takes liberties with (except, of course, the world champion, Gary Kasparov).</p>
        <p>In the Bohemians International Tournament in Prague, Jan. 7 to 20, organized by the club of the same name, it was not surprising that the shoot-from-the-hip William Watson was in his element. At his best, the 29-year-old British grandmaster strikes fear into the hearts of his opponents. He did it often enough to take first prize in Prague with an 8 1/2-3 1/2 score in the round-robin, invitational event.</p>
        <p>A typical effort from this swashbuckler was his victory over the Czechoslovak grandmaster Eduard Meduna in the ninth round.</p>
        <p>The Caro-Kann Defense, 1 . . . c6, is perhaps the most cautious method of countering 1 e4. Black yields his strong point in the center with 3 . . . de and then braces his position on three ranks to hold off the enemy.</p>
        <p>Within the Caro-Kann, Aron Nimzovich's 3 . . . Nd7 is the most careful of all: Black prepares to develop with 4 . . . Ngf6 and exchange pieces without getting doubled f pawns.</p>
        <p>The recent idea with 5 Ng5 is to avoid early exchanges and to develop various traps. For example, 5 . . . h6 can be met by 6 Ne6! Qa5 (6 . . . fe? 7 Qh5) 7 Bd2 Qb6 8 Nf8 Nf8, which gives White a favorable two-bishop position.</p>
        <p>In a game between Nick De Firmian and Anatoly Karpov in Biel, Switzerland, in 1990, 5 . . . Ndf6 6 Bc4 e6 7 Ne2 c5 8 O-O h6 9 Nf3 a6 10 a4 cd 11 Ned4 Bd6 offered Black an easy game. One wonders what Watson had in mind against that. And after 5 . . . Ngf6 6 Bd3 e6 7 N1f3 Bd6 8 Qe2 h6 9 Ne4 Ne4 10 Qe4 Nf6 11 Qe2, White has only a slight advantage in space. So it is not evident why Meduna diverged with 6 . . . g6.</p>
        <p>After 8 Qe2, it may be that Meduna was wise in omitting 8 . . . h6 because 9 Ne6!? fe 10 Bg6 Kf8 11 Qe6 Qa5 12 Bd2 Qd5 13 Qe2 does give White unclear attacking chances. Still, after 8 . . . O-O, Watson started an attack with 9 h4.</p>
        <p>Meduna hoped to simplify and gain freedom with 9 . . . h6 10 Ne4 Ne4 11 Qe4 Nf6, but Watson boldly sacrificed a knight with 10 h5!? to press his attack. Perhaps Meduna could, with equal boldness, have taken it. Thus, 10 . . . hg 11 h6 Bh8 12 Ng5 Nb6 13 h7 Kg7 14 Nf3 Ng4 15 Ne5 Qd4 16 Ng4 Bg4 17 f3 (17 Qe7? Rfe8! 18 Bh6 Kh7 19 Be3 Kg8 wins for Black) Bf5 18 Bh6 Kf6 19 O-O-O may leave the black king brain-dead, but his heart is still beating.</p>
        <p>If he lacked all that courage, he might have tried 10 . . . gh 11 Nh3 Nb6 12 Nf4 Bg4 because it is not at all obvious how the white attack can get through. But Meduna picked the worst choice, 10 . . . Nh5?, which encountered Watson's 11 g4! Nhf6 12 Ne6! fe 13 Qe6 Rf7 (13 . . . Kh7 14 Bh6 Bh6 15 g5 Nc5 16 Rh6 Kg7 17 Rg6 Kh8 18 Rh6 Kg7 19 Rh7! Nh7 20 Qg6 Kh8 21 Qh7 mate) 14 Bg6 Qf8 15 g5!</p>
        <p>Had Meduna understood how bad things really were, he might have played 15 . . . Nb6 16 Qf7 Qf7 17 Bf7 Kf7 18 gf ef, but the rook for bishop endgame would be lost for Black after 19 Bh6. Instead, he kept fighting with 15 . . . Nd5 16 gh Ne5. And fell into Watson's annihilating 17 Bh7! Since 17 . . . Kh7 (17 . . . Kh8 18 hg Qg7 19 Be4 Kg8 20 Qe5 wins a piece) 18 hg Kg7 19 Qh6 Kg8 20 Qh8 mate did not fit into Meduna's plans, he gave up.  CARO-KANN DEFENSE</p>
        <p>White</p>
        <p>Black</p>
        <p>Watson</p>
        <p>Meduna</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>e4</p>
        <p>c6</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>d4</p>
        <p>d5</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Nd2</p>
        <p>de</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Ne4</p>
        <p>Nd7</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Ng5</p>
        <p>Ngf6</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Bd3</p>
        <p>g6</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>N1f3</p>
        <p>Bg7</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Qe2</p>
        <p>O-O</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>h4</p>
        <p>h6</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>h5</p>
        <p>Nh5</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>g4</p>
        <p>Nhf6</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Ne6</p>
        <p>fe</p>
        <p>13</p>
        <p>Qe6</p>
        <p>Rf7</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Bg6</p>
        <p>Qf8</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>g5</p>
        <p>Nd5</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>gh</p>
        <p>Ne5</p>
        <p>17</p>
        <p>Bh7</p>
        <p>Resigns</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
