<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Struggles to Advance 2.23, to 3,282.42</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="509734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1339F936A15751C0A964958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Struggles to Advance 2.23, to 3,282.42</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock prices were mixed yesterday, as trading eased with investors expressing concern over a weak bond market and rising interest rates. Still, blue chips drew some interest, nudging the Dow Jones industrial average to another high, 3,282.42, up 2.23 points.</p>
        <p>The bellwether average of 30 industrials was the only index to reach a closing high yesterday -- its 12th record this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock prices were mixed yesterday, as trading eased with investors expressing concern over a weak bond market and rising interest rates. Still, blue chips drew some interest, nudging the Dow Jones industrial average to another high, 3,282.42, up 2.23 points.</p>
        <p>The bellwether average of 30 industrials was the only index to reach a closing high yesterday -- its 12th record this year.</p>
        <p>Paul J. Kronlokken, a technical analyst with Piper, Jaffray &amp; Hopwood in Minneapolis, was surprised by the resiliency in the market as it came back late in the session. "However, the story was the broader market, which was not able to bounce back" from earlier lows, he added.</p>
        <p>As interest rates tick higher, investors become increasingly concerned about the impact on corporate profits and look to the more attractive bond yields that would begin to compete with the equities for investors' money. Yesterday, the yield on the Treasury's 30-year bond was up 2 basis points, or two-hundredths of a percentage point, to 7.96 percent.</p>
        <p>"There's nothing wrong with locking your cash at 8 percent and being able to get a good night's sleep," Mr. Kronlokken said.</p>
        <p>Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was 181.3 million shares, down from 261.7 million on Friday.</p>
        <p>The Big Board composite gained 0.16 point to finish at 227.62, as losing issues outpaced gainers by 1,013 to 726.</p>
        <p>Investors' interest in blue-chip stocks also helped the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks to gain 0.81 point, 412.27, while the American Stock Exchange index dropped 1.05, to 411.80. In Nasdaq trading, the composite fell 4.82, to 624.93, while the Russell 2,000 dropped 1.51, to 208.89.</p>
        <p>General Motors announced a 1991 fourth-quarter loss of $4.25 a share, a record for the industry, including a one-time charge of $2.8 billion relating to its previously announced plans to close 21 plants and cut 74,000 jobs by 1995. The announcement had little impact on the market because most analysts expected it. The stock fell 5/8, to 37 3/4.</p>
        <p>Birinyi Associates, a Wall Street research firm, pointed to Merck, up 3 1/4, to 149 1/2, on expectations of a 3-for-1 stock split; Walt Disney, up 1 1/2, to 154 3/8; Texaco, up 1 3/8, to 58 3/4, and J. P. Morgan, up 1 1/4, to 59 3/4, as the big movers on the Dow.</p>
        <p>In other market activity, Home Depot closed at 61 3/4, up 1/8, but not before rising 1 1/4 after the chain of building materials and home improvement stores reported fourth-quarter earnings of 31 cents a share, better than most Wall Street expectations of 26 cents to 28 cents a share.</p>
        <p>Shares of Du Pont fell 1 1/8, to 47 1/8, after the publication of reports that one of its fungicides, Benlate, was responsible for contaminating farms in Florida. The fungicide, which was taken off the market a year ago, has cost the manufacturer more than $205 million in damage claims.</p>
        <p>A breakthrough that would enable users of Macintosh personal computers to make commands by voice, without the use of a keyboard or mouse, sent Apple Computer stock up 1 1/8, to 66 1/8. Analysts said the event was significant in the race to develop computers that respond to voice commands, but a company spokesman said, "It's not ready for prime time yet."</p>
        <p>Zenith Laboratories, a manufacturer of generic pharmaceuticals based in Northvale, N.J., jumped 3 5/8 yesterday, to 23 3/4, after a court in New Jersey ruled on Friday that its Cefadroxil drug did not infringe Bristol-Myers Squibb's patent for Duricef. Bristol-Myers rose 1/4, to 78 7/8.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
