<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Slap and an Old Man's Shame Amid All the Mischief-Making</title>
    <meta content="21PASQ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="966735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donizetti, Gaetano (1797-1848)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Don Pasquale (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7D8163EF932A15753C1A961958260" item-length="814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Slap and an Old Man's Shame Amid All the Mischief-Making</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews New York City Opera's production of Donizetti's Don Pasquale at New York State Theater; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Don Pasquale'' is to Donizetti's career what ''Cosi Fan Tutte'' was to Mozart's. Both operas came toward the end of composing lives. Timeworn models notwithstanding, both achieved a theatrical momentum unusual to opera then and now. In both, stories are told by means of duets, trios and quartets. The arias are there, and they are beautiful. But they exist as breathing points, eloquent clearings of the throat that allow otherwise continuous narrative to catch its breath.</p>
        <p>Donizetti's 64th opera (an amazing number for a composer who died at 50) reappeared on Sunday afternoon in an eminently workable production put on by the New York City Opera and shared by its sophisticated upstate country cousin, the Glimmerglass Opera. Leon Major's directorial imagination offers a few odd anomalies but no unpleasant surprises.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Don Pasquale'' is to Donizetti's career what ''Cosi Fan Tutte'' was to Mozart's. Both operas came toward the end of composing lives. Timeworn models notwithstanding, both achieved a theatrical momentum unusual to opera then and now. In both, stories are told by means of duets, trios and quartets. The arias are there, and they are beautiful. But they exist as breathing points, eloquent clearings of the throat that allow otherwise continuous narrative to catch its breath.</p>
        <p>Donizetti's 64th opera (an amazing number for a composer who died at 50) reappeared on Sunday afternoon in an eminently workable production put on by the New York City Opera and shared by its sophisticated upstate country cousin, the Glimmerglass Opera. Leon Major's directorial imagination offers a few odd anomalies but no unpleasant surprises.</p>
        <p>Blessedly absent is the cartoonlike mockery that has infected so many American revivals of bel canto repertory. Television has so thoroughly done its work on an emerging generation of opera directors that the difference between human beings who act ridiculously and faceless objects of ridicule has been hopelessly confused. Donizetti helps Mr. Major along with some significant moments of pathos.</p>
        <p>The outlines of ''Don Pasquale'' have a boilerplate familiarity. A rich man, aging and self-delusionary, competes (unwittingly) for the love of his nephew's life. An inheritance hangs in the balance. There is the obligatory outside agent (Dr. Malatesta) who will scheme to make things right. Norina accepts Don Pasquale's suit and orchestrates a domestic reign of terror that eventually puts her back in the arms of her true partner, Ernesto.</p>
        <p>There is, however, a moment in Act III that sends ''Don Pasquale'' not only out of its genre but out of its period as well. Norina, in the middle of an argument over money with her aged bridegroom, slaps his face. Comedy stops. We wince at the old man's shame. Norina winces along with us and sings of her regret. Without this incident, ''Don Pasquale'' would still represent an important humanizing of commedia dell'arte. With it, we are provided the kind of emotional ambivalence that also makes ''Cosi'' what it is.</p>
        <p>Mr. Major has the odd idea that Norina should be an actress, an interpretive discovery based essentially on her declaration that she will attend the theater unaccompanied. He has also moved the setting from 1843 (when Donizetti finished the piece) almost two centuries earlier. Neither conceit does much harm, but I do wish Mr. Major had said he was doing these things simply because he felt like it and not out of halfhearted intellectual reasoning.</p>
        <p>Mark McCullough's lighting emulates the candlelit atmosphere Moliere would have known. Allen Moyer's set is three walls inside Don Pasquale's house. Their painted surfaces are quite reasonable when we look at them in 1997, that is, after three centuries of fading. But wouldn't the colors have been fresher in 1660? One is reminded of the Hollywood designers entrusted with reproducing the creation of the Sistine Chapel who insisted on including all the cracks.</p>
        <p>No matter. Nothing in this production gets in the way in what is essentially a humane, graceful and nicely sung enterprise. Its conductor, Lucinda Carver, is a find. Music from all quarters was made to move with disciplined yet buoyant energy. Kevin Glavin in the title role never overplayed its humor, and Mr. Major's introduction of an errant wig passing from hand to hand was both deft and funny.</p>
        <p>The low voices dominated Sunday's performance. Christopher Schaldenbrand's Malatesta led this small cast with presence, command and dignity. John Osborn as Ernesto found himself caught in the middle of one of Donizetti's high-tenor parts. Thin but mostly true, Mr. Osborn's singing never really had a chance to relax and spread.</p>
        <p>Laura Claycomb, who sang Norina, is a stylish soprano. She throws off Donizetti's decorative passages with ease. She is a graceful actress, comfortable with Mr. Major's comic style. I wish I could have heard her better. For all its quality, the voice does not carry as well as it might, at least not in the New York State Theater. Norina was too easily crowded by other ensemble singers or simply drowned in orchestra accompaniments. Donizetti wrote often for small opera houses. Ms. Claycomb's singing on Sunday would have fit any one of them perfectly.</p>
        <p>DON PASQUALE</p>
        <p>Opera in three acts by Donizetti; libretto by the composer and Giovanni Ruffini; conductor, Lucinda Carver; director, Leon Major; sets and costumes by Allen Moyer; lighting by Mark McCullough. Performed by the New York City Opera at the New York State Theater.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kevin Glavin (Don Pasquale), Christopher Schaldenbrand (Doctor Malatesta), John Osborn (Ernesto), Laura Claycomb (Norina) and Eric Dillner (a Notary).</p>
        <p>OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
