<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Huang Yong Ping</title>
    <meta content="RV001513" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1364108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ART IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huang Yong Ping</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DC173DF932A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Huang Yong Ping</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews installations by Huang Yong Ping at Barbara Gladstone Gallery (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barbara Gladstone  515 West 24th Street, Chelsea  Through Feb. 9</p>
        <p>''Festival art,'' as the critic Peter Schjeldahl christened the entertaining installations that dominated the 1999 Venice Biennale, is less an art trend than a syndrome. Its symptoms include big, handsome works in which Conceptual concerns tend to outweigh everything else, despite often pyrotechnic displays of material and skill. Its practitioners are frequently artists whose Dadaist intent and scant means resulted in early careers devoted to performance or ad hoc installation art. With advancing age and success, they progress to increasingly large finished pieces, a tendency that makes Chris Burden and Vito Acconci early festival artists of a sort.</p>
        <p>Within his third solo show in New York, Huang Yong Ping, a Chinese-born, Paris-based denizen of the international circuit, joins the category. His past work has tended toward scruffy and alternated between effective and ineffective; his second New York solo, at the Tilton Gallery in SoHo in 2000, was a found- and made-object installation that included a globe housing battling scorpions, insects and other creatures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barbara Gladstone  515 West 24th Street, Chelsea  Through Feb. 9</p>
        <p>''Festival art,'' as the critic Peter Schjeldahl christened the entertaining installations that dominated the 1999 Venice Biennale, is less an art trend than a syndrome. Its symptoms include big, handsome works in which Conceptual concerns tend to outweigh everything else, despite often pyrotechnic displays of material and skill. Its practitioners are frequently artists whose Dadaist intent and scant means resulted in early careers devoted to performance or ad hoc installation art. With advancing age and success, they progress to increasingly large finished pieces, a tendency that makes Chris Burden and Vito Acconci early festival artists of a sort.</p>
        <p>Within his third solo show in New York, Huang Yong Ping, a Chinese-born, Paris-based denizen of the international circuit, joins the category. His past work has tended toward scruffy and alternated between effective and ineffective; his second New York solo, at the Tilton Gallery in SoHo in 2000, was a found- and made-object installation that included a globe housing battling scorpions, insects and other creatures.</p>
        <p>Things at Gladstone are imposing and even slick. The centerpiece is a giant replication of a Tibetan Buddhist prayer wheel that has been dismantled, perhaps by violence, into its constituent parts: a bronze-and-copper lid, a trunk-size wood handle and a bronze-and-copper cylinder containing the consecrated scroll. The piece is initially breathtaking in a familiar Oldenburgian way, and the giant paper scroll is especially beautiful.</p>
        <p>An architectural model set on a Turkish carpet reveals that Mr. Huang originally intended the wheel for the Chapelle St. Louis de la Salpetrière in Paris, where it was to be surrounded by prayer rugs, creating a juxtaposition of Christianity, Islam and Buddhism. (Proposed for the 2000 Festival d'Automne, but never executed.)</p>
        <p>Religious confrontation is the theme of ''Two Typhoons,'' which consists of two giant scrolls extended into towers of Babel -- one covered with Arabic script, the other with Sanskrit. It is the show's most accessible and most physically modest piece. A fourth work consists of a large wooden cart carrying a statue of a man in Chinese dress who points toward the distance; the cart has an unsettling tilt because its wheels, covered with Chinese characters, are different sizes. It can seem like a metaphor for inefficiency, but its source is an ancient Chinese vehicle equipped with a system of gears that kept the statue facing south, regardless of the cart's direction.</p>
        <p>Without such explanations -- this one is provided by a gallery handout -- festivalism is the new formalism.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA SMITH</p>
        <p>ART IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
