<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Here Come The Discountmobiles</title>
    <meta content="28ARCHINT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="68" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/28/magazine/28ARCHINT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1522862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="STYLE: THE WAY WE DRIVE NOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fishman, Ted C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D71E3AF93BA1575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="2060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Here Come The Discountmobiles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Here Come the Discountmobiles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ted C. Fishman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fishman, Ted C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ted C Fishman article on possibility that China may eventually make good $6,000 car for United States market; notes most big international automakers are building vehicles in China, where it still costs more to make car than in West; holds China must put in place hyperefficient industrial infrastructure before it can export cars that will bust open low end of US market; drawing (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, The People's Daily, one of the Chinese government newspapers, ran a short, tantalizing item announcing that 252 Chinese-made economy cars had been shipped to Port Everglades in Florida, the first Chinese cars exported to the United States. A Boca Raton company planned on receiving 25,000 of these cars, known as Xialis, over the next five years. The small cars are the same models that swarm Beijing as bumpy red taxis, getting a miraculous 56 miles to the gallon and costing under $6,000 in China.</p>
        <p>The news took hold in the recess of my brain reserved for browsing at Costco, where I have become hopelessly addicted to deflation. I have become a kind of retail Manchurian Candidate, reflexively piling my cart with ever-cheaper DVD players, T-shirts and socket-wrench sets. If Chinese manufacturers do to cars what they have done to toys, clothes and electronics, a Chinese economy car might just qualify as an impulse item.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Chinese manufacturers do to cars what they have done to toys, clothes and electronics, a Chinese economy car might just qualify as an impulse item.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, The People's Daily, one of the Chinese government newspapers, ran a short, tantalizing item announcing that 252 Chinese-made economy cars had been shipped to Port Everglades in Florida, the first Chinese cars exported to the United States. A Boca Raton company planned on receiving 25,000 of these cars, known as Xialis, over the next five years. The small cars are the same models that swarm Beijing as bumpy red taxis, getting a miraculous 56 miles to the gallon and costing under $6,000 in China.</p>
        <p>The news took hold in the recess of my brain reserved for browsing at Costco, where I have become hopelessly addicted to deflation. I have become a kind of retail Manchurian Candidate, reflexively piling my cart with ever-cheaper DVD players, T-shirts and socket-wrench sets. If Chinese manufacturers do to cars what they have done to toys, clothes and electronics, a Chinese economy car might just qualify as an impulse item.</p>
        <p>Alas, the Xiali never made it to the streets of America. The importer folded. The cars, which even Chinese drivers buy only as a last resort, were re-exported out of Florida to downmarket climes where warranty service comes cheap. But the brief flicker of news about the Xialis shed light on possibilities both promising and dangerous: can China make a good $6,000 car for the U.S. market? What might it look like? And is there any chance I'll ever be able to buy one at Costco?</p>
        <p>Supercheap cars already exist all over the world. Brazilians and Russians make frumpy sub-$10,000 cars by the hundreds of thousands, but they know better than to bring them to the United States, where they would fall perilously short of safety and performance standards. The Korean company Kia Motors currently makes the lowest-priced sedan in the United States, the Rio, which lists with no extras at $9,665. That buys basic transportation: 104 horsepower and the road feel of a kangaroo. One reviewer, struggling to say something nice, wrote that if you ''keep engine r.p.m. up . . . the Rio can stay with the flow of traffic on the highway.''</p>
        <p>The earliest Chinese export car might not be much better. ''A first automotive product here,'' speculates Kevin Smith, the editor of Motor Trend, ''would represent the bottom of the market in features, refinement and quality, but it won't be too far behind its competition.'' Smith points out that it took the Koreans 10 years to get their cars up to a quality acceptable to American buyers. He says he thinks the Chinese may get there in significantly less time.</p>
        <p>As it stands right now, virtually every big international automaker is building vehicles in China. The first Chinese car exported to the United States may well be a model of car already sold here; a Chinese-made Volkswagen Jetta or Honda Civic perhaps. Those, however, would not be the Chinese cars that bust open the low end of the market. That car would probably come into the States under a name few Americans will have heard of. And it will arrive, just as dirt-cheap consumer electronics did, only after China puts in place the hyperefficient industrial infrastructure that will allow it to cut prices to the bone. There is a long way to go on this; most cars still cost more to make in China now than in the West, Japan and Korea because the industry is so diffuse -- factories are relatively small, many parts have to be imported and infrastructure like roads are unreliable.</p>
        <p>But the price slope is getting slippery. Michael J. Dunne, who runs a Beijing-based consulting firm called Automotive Resources Asia, describes China's auto business as the most exciting, fast growing and unpredictable in the world today. The market is voracious. Car sales in China rose an astonishing 82.4 percent in the first six months of this year, to 842,800. By 2010, the country should surpass Germany as the No. 3 auto producer, and some speculate that it will catch the United States by 2020. Though the number of cars sold in China is a fraction of the 17 million sold here last year, the market potential, like everything else in China, is mind-boggling. The Chinese middle class will soon top 100 million, and they will want cars not only as transportation but as an emblem of their place in society.</p>
        <p>How will that land a cheap car in the United States? The only way a Chinese car will be able to compete in the American market, at least initially, is if it's the cheapest possible. And right now Chinese manufacturers are rushing to expand their capacity; as they do this, prices are dropping precipitously. Last year the price of a car in China fell by 20 percent, and this year it will drop between 10 and 20 percent again.</p>
        <p>China has nearly 100 automobile manufacturers (roughly the number of American carmakers early in the last century), and a good many of them are small firms cobbling together cars any way they can. Some make models based on old Soviet cars and European compacts several generations past. Others jerry-build their own using whatever parts can be had -- often dubiously -- in the market. ''Many Chinese consumers are so hungry for cars that they don't care what they look like if the price is right,'' Dunne says. ''Right now there is a budding demand on the low side of the market, and upstart Chinese companies are building knockoffs that buyers who just want transportation can settle on.''</p>
        <p>Adding to the chaos is that Chinese businesses are rarely stand-alone entities -- so intertwined are many companies, including direct competitors, that it can be hard to tell where one firm begins and another ends. This produces an extremely idiosyncratic industry that baffles and surprises even the most sophisticated foreign companies. VW, for example, found its parts in a domestic rival's cars. G.M. is currently investigating a Chinese manufacturer that released a subcompact car this summer for $6,000 that looks suspiciously like a $9,000 model of their own. China's car industry is like a potluck supper where everyone's technology is sampled by everyone else. So by the time a Chinese car lands here, it may well include features from all the world's top car and parts makers.</p>
        <p>These cars could also have technology that established car companies won't. ''R and D capability in China is ramping up at a dizzying pace,'' says Paul Lienert, whose newsletter Global Auto Insider often alerts Detroit to China's growing critical mass and capabilities in the car industry. For example, China has already built its own fuel-cell vehicle.</p>
        <p>''It is unofficial Chinese policy to encourage companies to incubate their own design teams,'' notes Brad Huang of Lotus Capital, an investment group that is putting together a huge industrial park in Haining, 100 miles from Shanghai, for Japanese and American automotive companies. ''The government,'' Huang says, ''hopes that the joint ventures with foreign auto companies can train a team of engineers who can design auto models that are 100 percent Chinese.''</p>
        <p>Lienert sees the Chinese exporting a car with a lot of Western technology to North America within the next five years, offering ''cars that some Americans will find acceptable for six or seven thousand dollars.'' A fully Chinese car will take longer. Huang estimates that one will hit the world market by 2018.</p>
        <p>Auto insiders can only speculate on what the Chinese car might actually look like. Dunne says he believes it will be a plain vanilla knockoff of some other country's economy car. Lienert expects it will have licensed or ''borrowed'' technology on the inside; come equipped with a decent four-cylinder engine, radio and AC; and have a clean, contemporary design.</p>
        <p>Geoff Wardle, of the Art Center College of Design in Pasadena, Calif., one of America's top automotive design schools, suggests that the shape of the Chinese car will depend largely on who brings it in and how it is sold. ''Young people in the U.S. and Europe are rapidly losing interest in cars as a status symbol,'' Wardle says. This indifference to the family trucks and Camry clones in Big Auto's showrooms has left American and Japanese carmakers struggling for ways to capture market share among first-time car buyers. It's a generation gap that a cheap Chinese car could drive straight through -- so long as the car can be body-pierced.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Chinese consumers are enamored of adding their own touch of cheap glitz to standardized products. The makers of elegantly simple European and American mobile phones discovered this when China's handset manufacturers attracted customers by offering options like prismatic trim and rhinestones.</p>
        <p>''There is a subculture emerging where kids can order all sorts of bits and bops online,'' Wardle says, ''and a Chinese car could capture a piece of that market by building to it.''</p>
        <p>A primary market, then, would be young male tinkerers who turn their cars into exotic expressions of their own identities. The so-called aftermarket performance-parts business is growing rapidly, up fivefold in the last five years. Companies like Nopi, one of the nation's largest sellers of aftermarket parts, work directly with manufacturers to develop the molded plastic parts that can turn a plain, cheap car into wheels fit for a superhero. The term of art is ''accessorizable.'' Models at the low end of the market are often the ones that get jazzed up because their relatively plain styles offer the greatest opportunity for reinterpretation by their owners. That's how Honda Civics and other small Asian models have become the vehicles of choice among young buyers. In the United States, young Asian-American men have a strong consumer presence in the custom-parts aftermarket, and the makers of these plastic accessories are almost always Chinese.</p>
        <p>To bring in an entirely new car and keep the price down, a new entrant would have to find an alternative to a dealer network, which both adds costs and takes time to develop. Costco and other big-box retailers are a possibility. Costco already parks S.U.V.'s at store doors and has negotiated no-haggle prices with car dealers around the country. Wal-Mart experimented this year with used-car sales in Texas. The superlow price of a Chinese car is what might open up new sales venues. Currently the most expensive items in most Wal-Marts are high-definition flat-screen TV's, priced near $5,000.</p>
        <p>Jean Jennings, the editor of Automobile Magazine, suggests an even more direct approach: eBay. Low-cost cars fill the same market niche as used cars, so why not go where the used-car buyers, especially younger ones, already browse in droves? Since eBay Motors started three years ago, it has become the biggest conduit for used cars in the world, on track to handle more than $4 billion in car-related sales this year. ''They sell more cars before noon than the largest dealers sell all year,'' Jennings says.</p>
        <p>Asked whether an importer could sell a cheap new car on the site, Simon Rothman, eBay Motors's vice president, enthusiastically pitches the idea back. ''The Internet is probably the most natural approach for a new car trying to build brand awareness,'' he said. ''EBay has 75 million users, and it's not unfathomable for anyone who wants a cheap, controllable and speedy distribution network center to move online.'' Infomercials are another possibility; you can hear the pitch -- buy one car and get another one free.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, few people in China could drive. Today the Chinese have in their sights an auto industry that can rival any in the world. While international automakers rush in to capture China's domestic buyer, China's long view looks outward. ''The West greedily eyes China for its market of 1.3 billion people,'' Wardle observes, ''but the Chinese see the rest of the world as 5 billion customers for its products.''</p>
        <p>STYLE: THE WAY WE DRIVE NOW Ted C. Fishman is a contributing editor for Harper's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ted C. Fishman is a contributing editor for Harper's.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
