<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Marketer Is Chosen By Interactive Network</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="647483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERACTIVE NETWORK INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEALEY, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADELSON, ANDREA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA1E3FF936A35752C1A965958260" item-length="406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Marketer Is Chosen By Interactive Network</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ADELSON, ANDREA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Sealey, a former Coca-Cola marketing executive, yesterday was named president and chief operating officer of Interactive Network Inc., a Silicon Valley start-up company that runs an interactive television service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sealey, 53, who has been described as a consumer marketing futurist, left the soft drink maker in July. He will begin his new job on Jan. 3.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Sealey, a former Coca-Cola marketing executive, yesterday was named president and chief operating officer of Interactive Network Inc., a Silicon Valley start-up company that runs an interactive television service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sealey, 53, who has been described as a consumer marketing futurist, left the soft drink maker in July. He will begin his new job on Jan. 3.</p>
        <p>At Coke, Mr. Sealey was responsible for the "Always Coca-Cola" campaign and was considered the marriage broker between the soft drink maker and its unconventional association with the Creative Artists Agency, a major Hollywood talent agency. He had previously been president of marketing at Columbia Pictures when the studio released films like "Ghostbusters" and "Stand By Me," and was owned by Coke. One-Year Time Sequence</p>
        <p>In an interview from Atlanta, Mr. Sealey said he would now have a chance to use his skills at a company already on the information superhighway. "We can take it national in a year," he said.</p>
        <p>Interactive's system does not need a new cable line running into homes. Already used by 3,000 subscribers in Sacramento and San Francisco, the system transmits television programming over the air. Subscribers pay $15 a month for a decoder to receive the signals, plus $199 for a transmitting unit using an FM radio frequency that allows viewers to interact with the programs. One's Own Game Show</p>
        <p>For example, viewers can answer questions on a game show, for which the system tallies points, comparing totals for all viewers and awarding prizes to the winners. The system is being introduced in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sealey is one of a growing number of executives from Hollywood studios and technology companies joining fledgling firms that are hoping to benefit from the emerging field of interactive entertainment.</p>
        <p>"Pete Sealey brings us an ideal combination of resources," said David B. Lockton, who will remain as chief executive of Interactive Network, based in Mountain View, Calif.</p>
        <p>Although little known by consumers, Interactive Network already has ties to established companies in the field. NBC, Tele-Communications Inc., Gannett and A. C. Nielsen are Interactive's largest shareholders.</p>
        <p>In the nine months that on ended Sept. 30, the company had a loss of $13.5 million and revenue of $581,000. It cited costs from an expansion of network operations and production, and the beginning of a marketing program in Chicago.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
