<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Trail of the Monarch, With the Aid of Chemistry</title>
    <meta content="29ISOT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Butterflies and Moths</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monarch Butterflies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Isotopes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hobson, Keith (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Butterflies and Moths</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DC143FF93AA15751C1A96E958260" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Trail of the Monarch, With the Aid of Chemistry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three new studies report new technique to pinpoint where monarch butterflies spend their time, including migration routes; biologists discover that isotopes, present in different amounts in different regions, can leave distinctive chemical signature written in bird's feather or butterfly's wing; photos; map showing monarch butterfly's North American breeding areas and migratory route; Dr Keith Hobson of Saskatoon sees major breakthrough (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every winter, after flying south from the Eastern United States, millions of monarch butterflies festoon fir trees in the mountains of Mexico, creating one of the world's most dazzling and famous biological spectacles. But in spite of intense interest in these beloved insects, the details of their travels, like those of so many creatures that do not submit to tagging or to voyeuristic techniques like radio-transmitters, have largely remained a mystery.</p>
        <p>Now three new studies, including one released Dec. 22 on monarchs, herald the arrival of a powerful new technique that can identify, sometimes to within a few miles, where migrating animals -- from butterflies to mastodons to humans -- have been. The new technique takes advantage of different forms, known as isotopes, of chemical elements. Biologists have begun discovering that these isotopes, present in different amounts in different regions, can leave a distinctive chemical signature written in the feather of a bird or the wing of a butterfly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every winter, after flying south from the Eastern United States, millions of monarch butterflies festoon fir trees in the mountains of Mexico, creating one of the world's most dazzling and famous biological spectacles. But in spite of intense interest in these beloved insects, the details of their travels, like those of so many creatures that do not submit to tagging or to voyeuristic techniques like radio-transmitters, have largely remained a mystery.</p>
        <p>Now three new studies, including one released Dec. 22 on monarchs, herald the arrival of a powerful new technique that can identify, sometimes to within a few miles, where migrating animals -- from butterflies to mastodons to humans -- have been. The new technique takes advantage of different forms, known as isotopes, of chemical elements. Biologists have begun discovering that these isotopes, present in different amounts in different regions, can leave a distinctive chemical signature written in the feather of a bird or the wing of a butterfly.</p>
        <p>By pinpointing crucial places where animals spend their lives, for example the major breeding grounds of monarch butterflies, the studies are not only illuminating the paths of these travelers, but are showing where conservationists should be focusing their efforts. In the case of monarchs, much of their breeding ground now appears to be on some of the most heavily farmed regions, heavily sprayed with pesticides, in the United States.</p>
        <p>''This has been a massive breakthrough,'' said Dr. Keith Hobson, a research scientist at the Canadian Wildlife Service in Saskatoon, who carried out the monarch work along with Dr. Len Wassenaar, a research scientist with Environment Canada, also in Saskatoon. ''These are questions we could get at no other way.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Page Chamberlain, a geochemist at Dartmouth College and another of the leaders in this newly developing field, said that when he first heard that researchers were using isotopes to trace elephant movements, ''We thought, 'Hey, we can do that. We can do it with fish too.' Now within a couple of years we've gone from fish to birds to insects. It has a lot of promise.''</p>
        <p>It turns out, to biologists' delight, that the world is peppered and painted with many different kinds of isotopes whose levels in a region vary depending on factors like temperature, rainfall, bedrock and soils.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen, for example, which comes in its standard form as well as the heavier form deuterium, shows a distinctive pattern of distribution. Depending on whether hydrogen in any particular molecule of water is heavy or light, the water will be heavy or light. When clouds move inland from over the ocean, heavy water rains out first and lighter water further inland, creating a stable gradient that can be mapped. Those differences get translated into plants that take up the water and then into insects that eat the plants, birds that eat the insects and so on, leaving an indelible mark on even the flightiest creatures.</p>
        <p>Researchers can refine their ability to pinpoint locations by using multiple isotopes with different specificities. Strontium, for example, an element that has been used to trace salmon movements, can vary greatly between streams just a few miles apart.</p>
        <p>To track monarchs, researchers used carbon and hydrogen, first developing a detailed isotope map. Working with Dr. Chip Taylor, an ecologist at the University of Kansas and the director of Monarch Watch, a nonprofit research and education group, Dr. Wassenaar and Dr. Hobson enlisted the help of 90 amateur butterfly enthusiasts, many of them schoolchildren. These volunteers around the country raised monarch caterpillars on milkweed plants, the insect's food plant, from their area. The carbon and hydrogen in the wings of the resulting butterflies revealed the variation in isotope ratios from the Rocky Mountains to the Atlantic -- the breeding range of the monarchs that migrate to Mexico.</p>
        <p>Researchers were then able to study the wings of monarchs that had died naturally in 13 wintering  sites in Mexico. They showed for the first time that these butterflies dangling together like crowded Christmas tree ornaments came from all parts of the breeding range, flying in and mingling after having grown up as caterpillars in places as distant as Massachusetts, Illinois and Maryland. The work put to rest a theory that different roosts were populated by butterflies from distinct geographic regions.</p>
        <p>The new findings are a big step forward because earlier attempts to track the monarchs had been limited to tagging. ''The odds of recovery with little guys, like monarchs, are pathetically low,'' Dr. Wassenaar said, about one recaptured monarch for every several thousand tagged.</p>
        <p>The most surprising discovery, however, was that, while the monarchs' breeding range is quite large, half of all the butterflies collected from Mexico had come there from a fairly restricted and highly agricultural area including Kansas, Nebraska, Iowa, Missouri, Wisconsin, Illinois, Michigan, Indiana and Ohio -- soybean and corn country. The bad news, said Dr. Lincoln Brower, a monarch researcher at Sweet Briar College, is that ''pesticides are killing milkweed plants on a grand scale in this very region, what they've shown is the most important breeding region for monarchs.''</p>
        <p>More worrisome still, Dr. Taylor said, is the use of transgenic plants, genetically altered to withstand pesticide sprays that competing weeds, like milkweeds, cannot. Other transgenic plants, like those that produce toxins in their tissues, are of great concern to biologists who note that it remains entirely unknown what effect these novel plants might have on insects in these regions that are not targets, including monarchs.</p>
        <p>''There is a revolution coming along in agriculture,'' Dr. Taylor said, ''that has great potential to eliminate a lot of milkweeds.''</p>
        <p>The reach of the new isotope studies is becoming so broad that even the dead are not immune from these investigations.</p>
        <p>Dr. T. Douglas Price, archeologist at the University of Wisconsin, and an international team of colleagues are tracking the movements of ancient humans using strontium deposits in teeth and bones.</p>
        <p>''The beauty of this is that in people, your tooth enamel forms at birth and doesn't change and your bone represents where you lived the last 10 years of your life,'' he said. ''If the ratios are different, we know that the person moved.'' Using such simple principles, Dr. Price said his team had just completed a study of the peoples of the Mexican city of Teotihuacan, testing the idea that different parts of the city were ethnic neighborhoods of people from different regions of Mexico. ''We've looked at their bones and they're definitely outsiders,'' Dr. Price said. ''The potential of this technique is really remarkable.''</p>
        <p>In addition, others are tracking declining songbirds and salmon, and two paleontologists, Kathryn Hoppe at Princeton University and Dr. Paul Kock at the University of California at Santa Cruz, are reconstructing the movements of fossil mastodons and mammoths. Meanwhile, there remain many untapped isotopes and as many new questions to be asked.</p>
        <p>''I think we can look at just about any animal, you name it,'' Dr. Hobson said. ''Forensic applications are also quite possible. If someone wanted to know if marijuana was grown in the Southern United States or Canada, that would just be a piece of cake.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
