<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gotti Rejects Plea Bargain In Mafia Case</title>
    <meta content="29GOTT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gambino Crime Family</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raab, Selwyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotti, John Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotti, John Sr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DE153FF93AA15751C1A96E958260" item-length="1270" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gotti Rejects Plea Bargain In Mafia Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELWYN RAAB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raab, Selwyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John A Gotti, man accused of being acting boss of Gambino crime family, heeds advice of his imprisoned father and rejects plea bargain that would have sent him to prison for up to eight years; negotiations collapse after months of intensive bargaining with Federal prosecutors; case reviewed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John A. Gotti, the man accused of being the powerful acting boss of the Gambino crime family, heeded the advice of his imprisoned father and rejected a plea bargain yesterday that would have sent him to prison for up to eight years, close associates of Mr. Gotti said.</p>
        <p>Negotiations collapsed after months of intensive bargaining with Federal prosecutors, defense lawyers said. ''There is no deal,'' Gerald L. Shargel, a lawyer for Mr. Gotti, said yesterday. ''Negotiations are finished.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John A. Gotti, the man accused of being the powerful acting boss of the Gambino crime family, heeded the advice of his imprisoned father and rejected a plea bargain yesterday that would have sent him to prison for up to eight years, close associates of Mr. Gotti said.</p>
        <p>Negotiations collapsed after months of intensive bargaining with Federal prosecutors, defense lawyers said. ''There is no deal,'' Gerald L. Shargel, a lawyer for Mr. Gotti, said yesterday. ''Negotiations are finished.''</p>
        <p>Relatives and friends of Mr. Gotti who spoke on the condition of anonymity said his decision was heavily influenced by his father, John J. Gotti, who is serving a life prison term without the possibility of parole after being convicted in 1991 on charges of being the Gambino family boss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti's associates said that the son's lawyers recently met with the elder Mr. Gotti at the Federal Penitentiary in Springfield, Mo., and that the former Gambino boss advised his son to turn down the offer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shargel said he notified Government lawyers yesterday afternoon that the younger Mr. Gotti would not accept what prosecutors said was a final proposal for a reduced sentence in return for a guilty plea to reduced charges: six and a half to eight years in prison and a $1 million fine.</p>
        <p>And while it is still possible that the Government could make another offer, Mr. Shargel said it seemed unlikely. ''As far as I am concerned, and apparently as far as the Government is concerned, the negotiations are over and this case will be tried,'' he said.</p>
        <p>By standing trial in a broad racketeering case, Mr. Gotti, 34, will face a possible prison sentence of 20 years and confiscation of about $10 million of his assets if he is convicted. Prosecutors contend that the assets, including two luxury homes on Long Island, real estate in Queens and $358,000 in cash that was seized from a safe, were obtained with profits from criminal enterprises.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gotti's rejection of the deal also means that seven co-defendants, including three men whom prosecutors identified as high-ranking capos, or heads of Gambino family units known as crews, will go on trial. Lawyers and law enforcement officials said those defendants had been prepared to plead guilty to lesser charges, but those deals fell apart when Mr. Gotti rejected the offer made to him.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors had insisted that all eight defendants accept what was termed a global agreement under which they would all plead guilty to racketeering allegations.</p>
        <p>In fact, the officials said, such a deal was almost completed over the weekend. One defendant, John J. D'Amico, 64, who investigators say is a Gambino capo, was scheduled to plead guilty yesterday in Federal District Court in White Plains, but the hearing was canceled when Mr. Gotti turned down the deal offered to him.</p>
        <p>Marvin Smilon, a spokesman for Mary Jo White, the United States Attorney for the Southern District of New York, whose office is prosecuting Mr. Gotti, declined to comment yesterday on the breakdown in bargaining.</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials said Ms. White's office had refused to consider individual pleas from Mr. Gotti's co-defendants because doing so would have undercut the evidence against Mr. Gotti, the lead defendant. Associates of Mr. Gotti said his trial lawyers, Mr. Shargel and Bruce Cutler, recently reviewed the Government's final plea terms with the elder Mr. Gotti, who is recovering from throat cancer surgery in a prison hospital. According to the associates, Mr. Gotti, 58, told the lawyers to inform his son that he opposed the deal and believed that his son would be acquitted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cutler and Mr. Shargel declined to comment on their discussions with the elder Mr. Gotti.</p>
        <p>''All I can say,'' Mr. Cutler said, ''is that the son wants to fight the case and clear his name, and the father believes he will win.''</p>
        <p>Another defense lawyer, James M. LaRossa, said plea deals for the other seven defendants had collapsed. ''There will be a trial,'' said Mr. LaRossa, who is representing Gregory DePalma, 66. Prosecutors have identified Mr. DePalma as an acting Gambino capo.</p>
        <p>The younger Mr. Gotti was indicted in January on charges that he had led an organized-crime enterprise that had engaged in extortion, illegal gambling, loan sharking and labor racketeering. Most of the original 23 defendants in the case have pleaded guilty to reduced charges.</p>
        <p>People close to the defense team said most of the remaining eight defendants had agreed to deals after reviewing the evidence implicating them, including 7,000 electronically intercepted conversations.</p>
        <p>The evidence against Mr. Gotti, prosecutors said, includes testimony by one Mafia defector and taped conversations in which his co-defendants talked about his role in extorting more than $1 million from Scores, a strip club in Manhattan, and of turning over to him $50,000 in protection payments from a construction company.</p>
        <p>Federal and state experts on organized crime said the proposed deal would have been a significant victory in a long campaign by the Federal Bureau of Investigation and prosecutors to undermine the Gambino family, which until the early 1990's was the nation's most influential Mafia group.</p>
        <p>And imprisoning the younger Mr. Gotti, the experts said, would have sent a far-reaching message: All Mafia leaders are vulnerable.</p>
        <p>It would also have weakened the influence of the Gottis in the Gambino family, law enforcement officials said.</p>
        <p>Investigators contend that the son  has been safeguarding his father's financial interests and trying to insure that a share of the crime group's profits is funneled to the Gottis. He is under house arrest in Oyster Bay on Long Island and free on $10 million bail.</p>
        <p>Although the younger Mr. Gotti had the title of acting boss bestowed on him by his father and was a ranking leader in the family, investigators said, he looked out mainly for his own and his father's financial interests. And, until recently, the investigators said, a three-man committee was responsible for most of the family's day-to-day activities and its links to the New York metropolitan region's four other mob families.</p>
        <p>The convictions of the elder Mr. Gotti and other high-ranking Gambino leaders in the late 1980's and early 1990's led to the Gambino family's being supplanted by the Genovese crime group as the nation's largest and most potent Mafia faction. Both groups use the New York area as their base of operations.</p>
        <p>Investigators say the Gambino family is far from finished, with an estimated 150 inducted or sworn members and extensive profits from illegal gambling, loan sharking and labor racketeering.</p>
        <p>If he had accepted a plea deal, Mr. Gotti would have spared the Government a long, complex trial and the nagging possibility of an acquittal because of several questionable prosecution witnesses.</p>
        <p>Lawyers who have studied the evidence said the prosecution's pivotal witnesses would confront fierce cross-examination and would have to admit that they had agreed to testify against Mr. Gotti only after making deals to avoid harsh sentences for violent crimes and multimillion-dollar frauds.</p>
        <p>The trial is scheduled to begin in February in White Plains. But Mr. Shargel said yesterday that he would ask for a delay because of his involvement in another trial that is under way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
