<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Start the U.N. Search Now</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="437606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ DE CUELLAR, JAVIER (SEC GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDC1F3CF936A25757C0A967958260" item-length="545" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Start the U.N. Search Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wanted: Experienced manager and fluent communicator skilled in politics, to manage unwieldy multinational enterprise. Salary $192,000; perks include Sutton Place mansion, travel, entertainment allowances. Must deal with quarrelsome board and 159 demanding shareholders.</p>
        <p>The search for such a paragon has already begun at the United Nations, which by year's end must find a successor to Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar. The job is important and prized. Yet in years past, the feckless way it was filled would have shamed a mom-and-pop grocery store. That helps explain how the U.N. twice chose Kurt Waldheim, whose resume failed to mention his service as a Wehrmacht officer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wanted: Experienced manager and fluent communicator skilled in politics, to manage unwieldy multinational enterprise. Salary $192,000; perks include Sutton Place mansion, travel, entertainment allowances. Must deal with quarrelsome board and 159 demanding shareholders.</p>
        <p>The search for such a paragon has already begun at the United Nations, which by year's end must find a successor to Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar. The job is important and prized. Yet in years past, the feckless way it was filled would have shamed a mom-and-pop grocery store. That helps explain how the U.N. twice chose Kurt Waldheim, whose resume failed to mention his service as a Wehrmacht officer.</p>
        <p>U.N. delegates insist that such carelessness won't be repeated. But the decision is made by governments, not diplomats. And bigger powers tend to view the U.N. as a necessary nuisance. Over the years, they have delayed their choice until the last frantic moment. They also prefer competent but unassertive bureaucrats; that the process yielded someone with Mr. Perez de Cuellar's integrity and decency was an unforeseen bonus.</p>
        <p>The U.N. has outgrown this dubious employment practice. A Security Council no longer paralyzed by Soviet vetoes has just fought a war and imposed onerous but fair cease-fire terms on Iraq. Enforcing these conditions will require the total involvement of the new Secretary General.</p>
        <p>He or she will also need demonstrated management skills to discipline a torpid bureaucracy of 14,000 civil servants scattered in 26 baronies. Not to mention the political savvy necessary to bridge the gap between rich nations that pay most of the bills and the poor nations that benefit from U.N. largesse. The U.N. Charter says only that the Secretary General "shall be appointed by the General Assembly upon the recommendation of the Security Council." Herewith some suggestions:</p>
        <p>Begin the search now. If a successor is chosen by October, he or she will have a three-month transition in which to work with the incumbent. The Council can also avoid the last-minute frenzy that yielded a Waldheim. But the timetable can be advanced only if the permanent members -- the United States, Soviet Union, China, Britain and France -- begin now to develop a list of qualified candidates.</p>
        <p>Open up the field. There's no reason for the Council to confine its search to diplomats. Serious consideration of former heads of government, business executives or foundation officials will add stature to the job and interest to the quest.</p>
        <p>Avoid regional formulas. The idea that this is "Africa's turn" has no basis in policy or tradition. That successful candidates have come from Europe, Asia and Latin America confers no automatic rights to other continents like Africa, or for that matter, Australia.</p>
        <p>Weigh a longer term. A Ford Foundation study proposes a single seven-year term instead of a renewable five-year appointment. That would avert unseemly campaigning by Secretaries General to prolong their stay. And seven years is enough.</p>
        <p>The choice may well be the most important single decision the U.N. will make this year. Having relearned the value of the world organization, Americans can add to its effectiveness by pressing for a prompt and systematic search.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
