<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="04DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="999679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFDE1331F937A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gates Defends Microsoft In Congressional Testimony  William H. Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, delivered a spirited defense of his company's business practices during his first Congressional testimony, portraying Microsoft as the standard-bearer of the nation's high-technology economy.</p>
        <p>At a time when Microsoft is defending itself against an antitrust suit by the Justice Department and criticism that it is abusing its power in the marketplace, Mr. Gates minced no words about where he believes the real threat to the information age lies: government regulation. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gates Defends Microsoft In Congressional Testimony  William H. Gates, the chairman of Microsoft, delivered a spirited defense of his company's business practices during his first Congressional testimony, portraying Microsoft as the standard-bearer of the nation's high-technology economy.</p>
        <p>At a time when Microsoft is defending itself against an antitrust suit by the Justice Department and criticism that it is abusing its power in the marketplace, Mr. Gates minced no words about where he believes the real threat to the information age lies: government regulation. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Utility Draws Another Top Bid  The bidding war for Energy Group, the British utility, continued, with Texas Utilities raising its offer to $7.3 billion, $100 million more than Pacificorp has offered. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Sale of Ryder Consumer Fleet Seen  The owner of Budget rental cars is expected to buy Ryder TRS, which rents trucks for do-it-yourself moving, for about $250 million. Budget is seeking to reduce its exposure to the recent price wars in the rental car industry. [D3.]</p>
        <p>Which Way for Economy?  The index of leading economic indicators was unchanged in January for the second consecutive month, perhaps portending a moderation of economic growth. But sales of new homes surged 10.3 percent, to an unexpectedly strong rate. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Chrysler Sales Above Expectations  Chrysler said domestic car and truck sales rose 3.1 percent in February, beating estimates, with a surge in truck sales offsetting a sharp drop in car sales. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Bonds Are Hammered Again  The strength in housing hurt the inflation-wary bond market, with yields rising sharply again. The yield on the 30-year Treasury rose to 6.07 percent from 6 percent. [D9.]</p>
        <p>Despite the rising bond yields and an early selloff in the technology sector, the stock market edged higher again. A late rally pushed the Dow Jones industrial average up 34.38 points, to 8,584.83. [D9.]</p>
        <p>A Warning to Indonesia  Top Administration officials told Congress that the White House could not support additional emergency aid to Indonesia from the I.M.F. unless President Suharto makes ''adequate progress'' toward economic reforms he agreed to in January. [A1.]</p>
        <p>2 Retailers' Profits Increase  Earnings rose, beating expectations, at two big department store companies, Dayton Hudson and Federated. [D6.]</p>
        <p>Japanese Policy Maker Accused  Eisuke Sakakibara, the top international official at the Japanese Finance Ministry -- known as ''Mr. Yen'' because of the impact his comments often have on the foreign-exchange markets -- was accused by an opposition party of influence peddling. The yen dropped in response to the news, snapping a three-day rally. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Gephardt Backs I.M.F. Financing  The Democratic leader of the House, Richard A. Gephardt, threw his support behind the Clinton Administration's efforts to win $18 billion in new financing for the I.M.F., declaring that he had been misrepresented as a protectionist. To polish his free-market credentials, he also met with major players on Wall Street. [A15.]</p>
        <p>$25.8 Billion for Ford Unit's Holders  Ford Motor said that it would complete the spinoff of its Associates First Capital subsidiary next month, giving shareholders $25.8 billion in stock and cash. [D3.]</p>
        <p>New Look From Jockey  Jockey is introducing an advertising campaign intended to imbue the once-hidebound underwear company with a hipper image, particularly among younger shoppers. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [D6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
