<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Grateful Dead Will Tour Again (Just Don't Call It a Reunion)</title>
    <meta content="04POPL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="999594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE POP LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grateful Dead</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Other Ones, The (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hornsby, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellis, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Stan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kreutzman, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Jerry (1942-95)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weir, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/The Pop Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DD1231F937A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Grateful Dead Will Tour Again (Just Don't Call It a Reunion)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Surviving members of Grateful Dead will reunite under new name, the Other Ones, and play some 30 dates in June and July with Rusted Root and Hot Tuna; Bruce Hornsby, an occasional member, is to play with band, but Bill Kreutzman, one of band's drummers, is lone holdout, opting not to join the Other Ones; there will be no replacement for late Jerry Garcia, but band will be joined by two musicians who have played with Dead's Bob Weir in other bands: Dave Ellis and Stan Franks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although there are no huge stadium tours planned for the summer, there is big news: the surviving members of the Grateful Dead announced yesterday that they would reunite under a new name, the Other Ones,  and play some 30 dates in June and July with Rusted Root and Hot Tuna.</p>
        <p>Bruce Hornsby, an occasional member, is to play with the band, but Bill Kreutzmann, one of the band's drummers, was the lone holdout, opting not to join the Other Ones. There will be no replacement for Jerry Garcia, who died in August 1995 at the age of 53, but the band will be joined by two musicians who have played with the Dead's Bob Weir in other bands: Dave Ellis on saxophone and, on guitar, Stan Franks, whose credits range from performing with Tupac Shakur to David Murray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although there are no huge stadium tours planned for the summer, there is big news: the surviving members of the Grateful Dead announced yesterday that they would reunite under a new name, the Other Ones,  and play some 30 dates in June and July with Rusted Root and Hot Tuna.</p>
        <p>Bruce Hornsby, an occasional member, is to play with the band, but Bill Kreutzmann, one of the band's drummers, was the lone holdout, opting not to join the Other Ones. There will be no replacement for Jerry Garcia, who died in August 1995 at the age of 53, but the band will be joined by two musicians who have played with the Dead's Bob Weir in other bands: Dave Ellis on saxophone and, on guitar, Stan Franks, whose credits range from performing with Tupac Shakur to David Murray.</p>
        <p>If it works out, some in the concert industry say, this might mean the return of the Grateful Dead as a touring force for years to come.</p>
        <p>''Please don't call it a reunion,'' said  Dennis McNally, the band's publicity agent. ''A reunion suggests picking up where you left off. They will play the same material, they may even get to the same places, but they'll get there different ways. This is an evolution. It's going to be very different.''</p>
        <p>Though Lollapalooza began the decade as one of the hottest summer tickets, its cachet has declined along with the quality and success of its bread and butter: alternative rock. Many in the industry say Lollapalooza should swallow its pride, put on a farewell tour selected from the bands that have been on its stages (Jane's Addiction, Nine Inch Nails, Smashing Pumpkins, Beck, Snoop Doggy Dogg and Hole) and promote it as the last Lollapalooza. But that doesn't seem to be what the festival bookers are planning. They have offered the headliner slot to more than a half-dozen bands, all of whom have refused to join the tour, which may include Scott Weiland of the Stone Temple Pilots, Green Day and the surviving members of Sublime.</p>
        <p>Most festivals this year are having problems finding headlining acts as they turn from experiments conceived by the musicians themselves to high-profile, money-making rituals run by music executives  more worried about failing financially than artistically.</p>
        <p>The one exception to this is the Lilith Fair, last year's most successful festival tour, because everybody likes a winner. Now making arrangements to appear on different dates of the tour this summer are Shawn Colvin, Missy Elliott, Sinead O'Connor, Bonnie Raitt, Natalie Merchant, the Indigo Girls, Erykah Badu, Fiona Apple and, of course, the woman who created the festival: Sarah McLachlan.</p>
        <p>In the men's department, Ozzy Osbourne will bring back his heavy-metal Ozzfest this year. Mr. Osbourne will be headlining, with Tool and others supporting. In addition, the hard-rock band Korn is starting its own tour, called Family Values, with Limp Bizkit and Orgy.</p>
        <p>And the Warped tour of punk-rock and ska, which begins on June 30 in Phoenix, will feature Rancid, Bad Religion, NoFX, the Specials, Deftones and CIV. If that isn't enough to qualify the 1998 concert season as the summer of testosterone, the heavy metalers Iron Maiden, W.A.S.P., Dio, U.F.O. and Yngwie Malmstein are to be touring together, competing with the bill of Warrant, Slaughter, Quiet Riot and L.A. Guns.</p>
        <p>On a gentler note, the Horde tour has scheduled Ben Harper, Benna, Alana Davis, the Barenaked Ladies and the festival founders Blues Traveler. The Guinness Fleadh will begin taking its mostly Irish music and all-Irish drink on the road, with a festival in New York on June 13 and 14 followed by performances in Chicago and the San Francisco Bay area. Among those to play at select dates are the Chieftains, Sinead O'Connor, Chumbawumba, Richard Thompson, Shane MacGowan, John Lee Hooker, Los Lobos, Nanci Griffith and the Indigo Girls.</p>
        <p>The Tibetan Freedom Concert run by Adam Yauch of the Beastie Boys will be in Washington on June 12 and 13 this year, with the Beastie Boys, Radiohead, a Tribe Called Quest and many others.</p>
        <p>Though many see the American touring festival in decline (as opposed to the popular, eclectic one-shot European festivals), Bob Grossweiner of Performance magazine disagrees.</p>
        <p>''Festivals are not dying,'' he said. ''From the acts' points of view, festivals offer a very safe situation. The bands don't have to go out and be at risk. They'll be seen by more people than if they do their own tour. For the fan, they can see many acts for the same amount of money they'd spend on one act. The problem is there's so many packages people have trouble deciding which to see, and they're all overlapping.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the festivals, other big tours planned for the summer include the long-awaited return of Pearl Jam, Eric Clapton, Hanson, Jimmy Page and Robert Plant, Michael Bolton with Wynonna, LeAnn Rimes, the Allman Brothers, a Brian Wilson-less Beach Boys, the Backstreet Boys, Ani DiFranco, the Spice Girls, Janet Jackson with Blackstreet, Elton John, Phish, George Strait, Van Halen, Shania Twain and most likely Madonna.</p>
        <p>Happy About Anthrax</p>
        <p>When two men were arrested by the F.B.I. in Las Vegas last week on suspicion of plotting to release anthrax bacteria in the New York subway system, five New Yorkers were excited by the prospect. It was the first time they had been on the front page of so many newspapers in their career.</p>
        <p>''My mom said, 'Boy, you're getting a lot of press,' '' said Scott Ian of Anthrax, a heavy-metal band that named itself after the lethal bacteria  13 years ago.</p>
        <p>''New York is such an insane city, any possible doomsday situation gets my blood up,'' he said. ''Especially when you wake up in the morning and see your name on the front of the paper.''</p>
        <p>''I was like: 'What did we do? I didn't break into Yankee Stadium again,' '' he said of his arrest last year when he was caught on camera trying to take a chair and an eight-foot foam mat from a field where the Yankees have spring training.)</p>
        <p>As disturbing as the real Anthrax  event might have been to most New Yorkers, even after the suspects were found to be carrying an anthrax vaccine instead of the bacteria the timing was opportune for Anthrax: the band, which recently added guitars to a song by Sean (Puffy)  Combs, is completing its first new album in two years.</p>
        <p>Now it has a marketing plan, which will begin with a cryptic poster hinting at the album's release, reading ''Anthrax: The Threat Is Real. June 23.'' Then there's Mr. Ian's plan to release Anthrax in the subway. ''We talked to the record label about playing in the subway,'' he said. ''Either we'll try to get a permit and do it, or just leak the announcement on the Internet and play until we're told to stop or we get arrested.''</p>
        <p>As to what inspired the band's name in the first place, Mr. Ian said he first heard of anthrax in biology class as a junior in high school. ''When I was forming the band, all the other bands had names like Killer or Deceiver or Ripper,'' he said. ''Then I learned about this crazy disease that kills you and kills millions of people, and it sounded great.''</p>
        <p>THE POP LIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
