<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japan Adopts Laws Strengthening Military Powers</title>
    <meta content="Y07JAPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/07/international/asia/07JAPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1494885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Koizumi, Junichiro</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DE1739F934A35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japan Adopts Laws Strengthening Military Powers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Japan Adopts Laws Strengthening Military Powers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan's Parliament today passed a series of war contingency bills that give the government significantly increased powers in military emergencies.</p>
        <p>After two years of debate, passage of the three contingency laws was driven by sharply heightened concern in Japan over the possibility of attack by North Korea, whose ballistic missiles could reach this country in as little as 10 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan's Parliament passed a series of war contingency bills that give the government significantly increased powers in military emergencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japan's Parliament today passed a series of war contingency bills that give the government significantly increased powers in military emergencies.</p>
        <p>After two years of debate, passage of the three contingency laws was driven by sharply heightened concern in Japan over the possibility of attack by North Korea, whose ballistic missiles could reach this country in as little as 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi praised the laws, saying, ''Setting up a legal framework on ways to safeguard the state and the public was an outstanding issue for the country's security policy.''</p>
        <p>Japan has one of the most richly financed and technologically advanced militaries, but its armed forces are constitutionally barred from use in settling international disputes. Officially Japan's military is known as a self-defense force.</p>
        <p>In recent months Japan has been seen by many regional analysts as edging away from its constitutional ban on the use of force with more determination than at any time since the country's so-called peace Constitution was written by American occupiers at the end of World War II.</p>
        <p>Japan has used its maritime forces in coordination with the United States to guard shipping and refuel American Navy vessels during the wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.</p>
        <p>It is planning a major upgrade of its antimissile defense, also in cooperation with the United States. And Japan is acquiring midair refueling capacity for its potent air force, to enable it to strike back at North Korea in case of conflict.</p>
        <p>There is talk among conservative politicians of a renewed push to rewrite the Constitution to become a ''normal nation'' once again. In Japan, the term means a nation capable of fighting wars.</p>
        <p>While the North Korean tensions have provided an unexpected windfall to politicians in the conservative, long-governing Liberal Democratic Party, the recent moves risk backlashes from two major quarters.</p>
        <p>Many of Japan's neighbors, victims of this country's imperialist expansion in the last century, remain firmly opposed to its rearmament. Public opinion in Japan, too, remains deeply pacifist.</p>
        <p>South Korea's governing Millennium Democratic Party reacted immediately, criticizing the new laws and demanding further explanation.</p>
        <p>''Japan should be blamed for its actions that irritate neighboring countries while failing to repent for its past, which imposed tremendous human and material sacrifices on those countries,'' the party said in a statement posted on its Web site. The passage of the bills came during a visit to Japan by the South Korean president, Roh Moo Hyun.</p>
        <p>One of the new laws is intended to enable coordination with the United States military.</p>
        <p>Another is aimed at smoothing the operation of the Self-Defense Forces, allowing them to begin certain ground operations before the prime minister issues a mobilization order.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
