<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Balkan Milk Run: Trucking Through Mortars</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="763626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WREN, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINSTAD, ROY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD9143AF933A15756C0A963958260" item-length="1536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Balkan Milk Run: Trucking Through Mortars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WREN, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
      <dateline>TUZLA, Bosnia and Herzegovina</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roy Finstad apologized for lighting yet another cigarette. "It's difficult to stop smoking in this work," he said. "I have to wait till I come back to Norway."</p>
        <p>Mr. Finstad, a 36-year-old taxi driver from Lillehammer, leads one of the convoys bringing food and other aid to those trapped by war in Bosnia, where up to 2.7 million people depend to varying extent on relief sent by the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roy Finstad apologized for lighting yet another cigarette. "It's difficult to stop smoking in this work," he said. "I have to wait till I come back to Norway."</p>
        <p>Mr. Finstad, a 36-year-old taxi driver from Lillehammer, leads one of the convoys bringing food and other aid to those trapped by war in Bosnia, where up to 2.7 million people depend to varying extent on relief sent by the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.</p>
        <p>In the last year and a half, Mr. Finstad, who works for the Norwegian Refugee Council, which is financed largely by the Government, has made more than 160 runs in and out of Sarajevo, Tuzla and other hot spots in one of the world's riskiest trucking operations.</p>
        <p>He and his fellow drivers -- 60 to 70 in all -- work daily under the threat of artillery fire, roadside land mines, snipers and hijackers. They navigate not only treacherous roads but also petty bureaucracy at each checkpoint, where a misplaced digit in a serial number on the manifest can give officials a pretext for turning back the convoy just short of its destination.</p>
        <p>"The heroes of this operation are the drivers; without them, we do nothing," said Enda P. Savage, 44, a former Irish Army officer who manages the United Nations refugee agency's logistics operation in Metkovic, the Croatian border town near the Adriatic coast from which 65 percent of the aid is trucked into Bosnia. For all the risks the drivers encounter, Mr. Savage said, "They never once said, 'No, we're not going in.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Savage said his operation tried to avoid putting the drivers and their loads at risk. "If there is any doubt about the security situation, we will not send them," he said.</p>
        <p>But they continue to go, partly because the wages are good. Including a generous living allowance, some drivers have earned $90,000 a year or more, though many drivers earn less.</p>
        <p>Lars Tangen, the leader of the Norwegian team of six convoys, considers the checkpoint harassment part of the job. "They say, 'These guys have been running for a long time, let's make some problems,' " said Mr. Tangen, 27, who learned tough patience as a paratrooper in the French Foreign Legion. "The only way to beat them is to smile and let them think you don't care."</p>
        <p>Since it opened in November 1992, the Metkovic base has moved 350,000 tons of food and relief supplies into Bosnia. The Bosnian Serbs take a share for their people as the price for letting the rest go through to Muslims and Croats. Some of the supplies end up feeding combatants on all sides.</p>
        <p>"We would hope that it goes to the people that need it," Mr. Savage said. "But perhaps it's being optimistic."</p>
        <p>The overriding problem now is a sharp drop in pledges of food and money. The European Union stopped financing five Danish convoys, forcing them to pull out by June. That will reduce Mr. Savage's trucking capacity by 40 percent.</p>
        <p>With no donated wheat flour in the international pipeline for July and August, the United Nations refugee agency is stretching what remains by cutting food deliveries in half to nearly every Bosnian destination. An exception is Sarajevo, the besieged Bosnian capital, where the airlifts have been blocked since April 8, so more food must be trucked in.</p>
        <p>"We're running into a lack of interest; we're running into a lack of money," Mr. Savage said of the dwindling support after more than three years of war in Bosnia. "I think people just have gotten tired."</p>
        <p>One such convoy took 13 hours over two days to travel less than 200 miles from Metkovic to Tuzla, a Bosnian city flanked on three sides by Bosnian Serb forces. The seven Scania trucks, big 10-wheelers provided by the Swedish Rescue Board, were loaded with 90 tons of American flour and cooking oil, canned beef from Italy and sleeping bags from Scotland. Mr. Finstad's crew included two other Norwegians and five local drivers -- four Croats and a Serb.</p>
        <p>The convoy's journey into the devastation of Bosnia began with a detour through the town of Ljubuski, because Metkovic residents object to the convoy traffic. Mr. Finstad led the way in a four-wheel-drive Nissan, briefing the drivers by radio on the traffic and road hazards ahead.</p>
        <p>A couple of years ago, 15 convoys, with more than 100 vehicles, backed up at Ljubuski after the military police found a flashlight that they said did not belong in a medical kit. This time, the convoy spent a scant 15 minutes clearing the border.</p>
        <p>The harassment gets worse at Serbian roadblocks, where gunmen have grabbed satellite radios from the aid trucks, and on one occasion more than $7,000 in German marks, contending that these were not listed on the manifest.</p>
        <p>Outside Mostar, an old town battered by fighting between Croats and Muslims in 1993, Mr. Finstad halted his convoy. He ordered everyone to put on helmets and flak jackets before driving under the mountain crags held by Serbian forces. Last December a Serbian artillery shell blew out the windows of one Norwegian truck. The injured driver accelerated into a tunnel ahead as eight more shells exploded behind him.</p>
        <p>"You are close to the front line in a number of places, and you never know what they will do," said Mr. Finstad, who had his drivers break out helmets and flak vests three times on the run to Tuzla. A convoy leader has authority to turn back if he decides the trip is too dangerous.</p>
        <p>With almost all the bridges blown up, the trucks crossed the Neretva River over a fragile-looking pontoon bridge built by Slovak Army engineers and climbed out of the river gorge into rugged mountains and through the town of Jablanica.</p>
        <p>At one of many United Nations military checkpoints, a Malaysian soldier stopped the convoy outside Konjic, with word that the town was being shelled. An officer later gave permission to proceed. "You must drive quickly," he said.</p>
        <p>The trucks spread out and raced through Konjic. Mr. Finstad peeled off his flak vest after he saw pedestrians on the road. "If there is shelling, you see no people," he said.</p>
        <p>The convoy wove past lush mountain pastures, pine forests, whitewashed farmhouses, a small mosque with a slender minaret. Fruit trees blossomed in destroyed villages. A schoolyard held several dozen graves of children caught by a mortar barrage this year.</p>
        <p>"This country is very beautiful," Mr. Finstad said. "It's a shame they destroy it in this way."</p>
        <p>At Tarcin, about 11 miles from Sarajevo, the convoy swung onto a precarious dirt road winding over another mountain. A Danish convoy truck went over the edge last year; it still dangles upside down in the undergrowth of a steep ravine. The driver survived, with virtually every bone broken. French Army engineers in flak jackets are now improving the road.</p>
        <p>So many other convoys were backed up at Kiseljak, awaiting clearance to enter Sarajevo, that the Norwegian convoy was routed to a warehouse compound in Zenica for the night. The drivers slept inside their cabs. The convoys do not move after 6 P.M. because of the danger after dark.</p>
        <p>The next morning, the convoy set out in heavy drizzle, which restricted visibility and pleased Mr. Finstad. "It's anti-sniping weather," he announced. A sniper killed a convoy interpreter on the Mostar road two years ago. A Danish driver later died in cross-fire.</p>
        <p>In time, the sunshine broke through and set green fields aglow. The trucks veered onto another back road from Breza to Vares. Two other Norwegian aid vehicles had been hijacked on the same muddy road two days earlier. It is one reason why the convoys stay in constant touch with their base in Metkovic.</p>
        <p>Serbian military music filtered from the radio receiver. Mr. Finstad said the Serbs piggy-backed on the convoy's frequency to take advantage of the booster transmitter. The song, accompanied by an accordion, celebrated a young man's love for his assault rifle.</p>
        <p>"Serbian brothers," urged the lyrics, "you must care for your gun just as your mother cared for you."</p>
        <p>The convoys travel unarmed, consistent with their relief mission. But at Ribnica, three Pakistani armored personnel carriers escorted Mr. Finstad's convoy along the line separating Bosnian and Serbian fighters. To the left, across a small river, lay Serbian positions, to the right the charred remains of five local trucks that tried to run the gantlet at night. Serbian artillery incinerated them.</p>
        <p>Life looked more normal on the road into Tuzla, though Serbian forces had shelled the city a few days earlier, wounding 11 people. The convoy passed an elderly couple in a horse-drawn wagon, a girl riding sidesaddle on the back of her boyfriend's bicycle, a roadside sale of black and white tombstones.</p>
        <p>Once their cargo was unloaded at the warehouse, the drivers headed to a nearby Norwegian Army compound for hot showers and cold beer. It had been, they agreed, an easy trip. Jan Norheim, a Norwegian driver, recalled sitting stuck at Sarajevo for 18 days last December.</p>
        <p>Over a beer, Mr. Finstad spoke of his wife, Lena, and their two children in Lillehammer. "Of course she's worried," he said. "She listens to the news, to what's happening in Bosnia."</p>
        <p>He plans to quit in a few months and go home. He has stayed out here, he said, because "I built a house in 1985, and it cost a lot of money."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
