<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Impromptu Air Trips? Possible, but Not Easy</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="408564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FARES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCOUNT SELLING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE1F3CF936A25751C1A966958260" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Impromptu Air Trips? Possible, but Not Easy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last-minute vacation flights during the Christmas-New Year holiday, especially to Florida and the Caribbean, are at a premium. They can be found, even a rare few at bargain prices, but travelers will have to look hard and be flexible.</p>
        <p>Most discount fares are long gone, although some might become available just before a planned departure date. And fares in general continue to cover wide ranges, with such a variety of prices charged on most popular routes that even sophisticated travelers may be thoroughly confused. Be Wary of Airline Promotions</p>
        <p>The lowest fares are generally nonrefundable, must be bought in advance and limit departures to the middle of the week. But even so, because a majority of the holiday flights will be heavily booked, the airlines are setting aside just a handful of inexpensive seats from their remaining inventory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last-minute vacation flights during the Christmas-New Year holiday, especially to Florida and the Caribbean, are at a premium. They can be found, even a rare few at bargain prices, but travelers will have to look hard and be flexible.</p>
        <p>Most discount fares are long gone, although some might become available just before a planned departure date. And fares in general continue to cover wide ranges, with such a variety of prices charged on most popular routes that even sophisticated travelers may be thoroughly confused. Be Wary of Airline Promotions</p>
        <p>The lowest fares are generally nonrefundable, must be bought in advance and limit departures to the middle of the week. But even so, because a majority of the holiday flights will be heavily booked, the airlines are setting aside just a handful of inexpensive seats from their remaining inventory.</p>
        <p>Don't be confused by new promotions that some airlines are offering. Delta Air Lines, American Airlines, Northwest Airlines and United Airlines are offering members of their frequent-flier clubs a free ticket for making as few as two round-trip flights between today and March 15.  But the free tickets will be only for travel starting in the middle of next year.</p>
        <p>The problems that last-minute travelers are likely to face in the next three weeks come at a time of unusual turmoil for the airline industry.  Overall airline fares have risen by at least 15 percent since fuel prices rose abruptly after Iraq invaded Kuwait last summer, one of the biggest increases in history over such a short period.</p>
        <p>In addition, less than two weeks ago Continental Airlines, the nation's fifth-largest air carrier, filed for protection under the bankruptcy laws, succumbing to the double pressure of higher fuel costs and a weakening economy. Few Seats, Fewer Bargains</p>
        <p>"Travel for the holidays, -- it's very rough," said Phil Davidoff, the owner of Belair Travel, an agency in Bowie, Md., and president of the American Society of Travel Agents.  "If you want to go outbound from Dec. 21 to Dec. 24 and want to return on Jan. 1 or Jan. 2, you're going to pay top dollar."</p>
        <p>Lorna Greene, a travel agent at Reliable Travel in Cedarhurst, L.I., put it this way: "Never mind any kind of bargains. How about a seat?  People are saying to their travel agents, 'Just find me something.' "</p>
        <p>So the first advice for anyone looking for airline seats to a popular warm-weather vacation spot in the next few weeks is: Be willing to make changes. Be prepared to fly on a different day, at a different hour and probably on a different airline than you had sought.</p>
        <p>"It's a trial-and-error kind of thing," said Julia Nystrand, director of electronic services for the Official Airline Guide, which compiles information on airline fares and schedules.</p>
        <p>John Unger, president of the Travel Network, a travel agency in Tampa, Fla., said: "Tell your travel agent that you are flexible on either side of the trip. Ask the agent to take a look at the availabilities and give the agent time to do the research."</p>
        <p>If you get a reservation, though, expect to pay one of the highest fares.  For example, round-trip coach fares from New York to Orlando, Fla., or Fort Lauderdale, Fla., currently range from $198 to $664.</p>
        <p>"If you look at the fine print, you see that airlines say 'prices from,' " said Marilyn B. Cicero, president of Colpitts Travel Center, a travel agency in Lexington, Mass. "People call expecting the discounted fares and they just won't find it. It takes a lot of explaining on our part."</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, some travelers find bargains. Mary O'Neill, a spokeswoman for American, suggested that travelers who are willing to book flights on their own "call reservation agents and ask them to search for the lowest possible price."</p>
        <p>"They have short cuts to find the discount fares and the flights that they are available on," she said.</p>
        <p>A tougher approach was recommended by Christopher J. Witkowski, director of the Aviation Consumer Action Project, an organization founded by Ralph Nader. "Consumers who call an airline in response to an advertisement, particularly when the ad appears that day, should be insistent on getting either the reservation agent or his supervisor to honor the advertised fare," he said.</p>
        <p>"If the low fare is sold out and the consumer cannot afford the higher fare, that should be made clear to the agent or supevisor," Mr. Witkowski said. "You might just land a lower fare in the last few days."</p>
        <p>That, however, means travelers have to be able and willing to wait and content to spend the holidays where they are if nothing works out.</p>
        <p>Another way to get to a holiday destination, possibly at a discounted price when flights are otherwise fully booked, is to take a package tour.  Travel agencies often offer packages combining air fare, hotel and possibly other vacation expenses, and tour wholesalers sometimes sell these packages directly to the public.</p>
        <p>Joel Cutler, president of the Vacation Outlet at Filene's Basement in Boston, said his agency is now selling one-week packages from Boston to Cancun, Mexico, starting Dec. 21, that are "hundreds of dollars" less than they would be if the various elements were bought separately. One package consisting of air fare and seven nights at an "inexpensive" hotel costs $429, based on double occupancy, while another at a "moderate" hotel costs $529.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
