<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Handy People Who Just Have to Put a Sharp Edge on It</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="663945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFD81330F930A15752C0A962958260" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Handy People Who Just Have to Put a Sharp Edge on It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE principle of sharpening tools and cutlery is simple. Grind one or both sides of a blade so that the surfaces meet at an angle. But the catches include which angle is correct, how to hold the blade steady and which sharpening device is the best.</p>
        <p>For most ordinary people, the simplest and least expensive device is a combination oilstone called a coarse-fine India stone. This is a man-made block of aluminum-oxide abrasives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE principle of sharpening tools and cutlery is simple. Grind one or both sides of a blade so that the surfaces meet at an angle. But the catches include which angle is correct, how to hold the blade steady and which sharpening device is the best.</p>
        <p>For most ordinary people, the simplest and least expensive device is a combination oilstone called a coarse-fine India stone. This is a man-made block of aluminum-oxide abrasives.</p>
        <p>One side consists of coarse particles that remove metal quickly. The other is made of smoother particles that hone the coarsely sharpened surface to a cutting edge.</p>
        <p>An oilstone has to be kept saturated with lightweight oil during use. The oil captures particles from the blade. A 2-inch-wide stone measuring 6 to 8 inches long is usually adequate. The average price is about $18.</p>
        <p>The correct angle, or bevel, to which the side or sides of a blade should be ground varies depending on the tool and its uses. For chisel and plane blades, an edge with two bevels is excellent for most jobs and easy to create and maintain.</p>
        <p>To hold a blade steady, buy a honing guide, a device with a clamp that holds the blade at a uniform angle to the stone. Two basic styles of guides are available for chisels and planes. Generally those that rest entirely on the stone are easier to use and more accurate than those that glide along a bench top or other surface on which the stone rests.</p>
        <p>To sharpen a chisel or plane blade in poor condition, start by saturating the oilstone's coarse side with cutting oil and clamping the honing guide to the blade so that the blade's bevel forms a 25-degree angle to the stone's surface. Sharpening is done with the blade upside down.</p>
        <p>Place the blade -- and guide, if appropriate -- on the stone and begin sharpening by moving the blade back and forth over the stone from one end to the other. To prevent uneven wearing, move the blade and guide in an S-shaped or figure-8 pattern.</p>
        <p>Apply moderate pressure with the fingers to the tip of the blade or guide. After about 50 strokes, reverse the stone end for end if additional coarse sharpening is necessary.  Wipe the stone clean and apply fresh oil when the stone blackens. The darkening is owing to the presence of metal particles and is a sign of sharpening.</p>
        <p>Check the beveled surface frequently and adjust the pressure if part of the surface wears more quickly than the rest. Use a carpenter's square to check that the cutting edge remains perpendicular to the sides.  Continue coarse sharpening until the beveled edge is completely shiny and you can feel a lip of rough metal, called a burr, on the flat side of the blade along the entire cutting edge. Then turn the stone over, saturate the smooth side with oil and hone the blade.  Begin by placing the underside of the blade flat on the stone. Do not remove the honing guide. Rub the blade briefly in small circles to grind away the burr. Be sure that the blade stays absolutely flat on the stone. When the burr is gone, turn the blade over and repeat the sharpening procedure until a new burr forms.</p>
        <p>Remove that burr also by rubbing the flat side on the stone. The result should be a sharpened edge with a single bevel and suitable for general carpentry. To create a second bevel, giving the blade a sharper, longer-lasting edge, follow these steps:</p>
        <p>*Reposition the honing guide to hold the beveled surface at a 30-degree angle to the stone. Hone the blade on the stone's smooth side until a burr forms. That should produce a very narrow secondary bevel, uniform in width, across the cutting edge.</p>
        <p>*Strop the blade by alternately stroking the underside and the beveled side several times against a strip of oil-softened leather, dry cardboard or thick newspapers. Move the tool as you would a paint brush.</p>
        <p>*The secondary bevel can be rehoned and stropped several times before rehoning the entire blade is necessary. Only if the edge is damaged or becomes very dull should future coarse sharpening be needed, regardless of whether the blade has a single or secondary bevel.</p>
        <p>Honing guides for knives are available, but they are awkward to use and seldom enable sharpening better than by hand. The technique for sharpening a knife on an oilstone is similar to that of sharpening a chisel or a plane, except that a knife blade has to be turned over after each stroke to preserve the original bevel on both sides.  HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
