<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Halts Recruitment of Cancer Patients For Studies, Pointing to Flaws in Oversight</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="677456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BREAST</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAMOXIFEN (DRUG)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL CANCER INSTITUTE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, BERNARD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Tamoxifen (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4D8173FF933A05750C0A962958260" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Halts Recruitment of Cancer Patients For Studies, Pointing to Flaws in Oversight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal officials at the National Cancer Institute yesterday took sweeping action intended to correct serious deficiencies of oversight in several large studies being carried out at the University of Pittsburgh to determine new standards of care for cancer patients.</p>
        <p>The action included a temporary halt in recruiting women into an experimental study of the drug tamoxifen to determine whether it can prevent breast cancer among women at higher risk of the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal officials at the National Cancer Institute yesterday took sweeping action intended to correct serious deficiencies of oversight in several large studies being carried out at the University of Pittsburgh to determine new standards of care for cancer patients.</p>
        <p>The action included a temporary halt in recruiting women into an experimental study of the drug tamoxifen to determine whether it can prevent breast cancer among women at higher risk of the disease.</p>
        <p>The institute, the nation's premier center for cancer research, acknowledged deficiencies in its own efforts to monitor the quality of the tamoxifen study and many other large clinical trials. To correct them, it said it would conduct a thorough review of its internal oversight procedures. Halt Ordered in Enrollments</p>
        <p>The institute ordered the university to suspend the enrollment of patients in the 14 cancer studies, including that of tamoxifen, that have been coordinated there by Dr. Bernard Fisher. The tens of thousands of patients now enrolled in the studies will continue to receive treatment and follow-up care, institute officials said. Normally, more than 1,000 patients are enrolled each month into the 14 studies, Dr. Greg Curt, an institute official, said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh researchers will not be allowed to resume enrollment until the institute completes the investigation of the Pittsburgh operation that began last week. The suspension will last at least a month and will delay results of all the trials, including the tamoxifen one.</p>
        <p>The tamoxifen study needs to enroll 16,000 women to be able to assess with sufficient statistical power the efficacy and safety of the drug in preventing breast cancer. More than 10,000 women have been enrolled. Researcher Asks for Leave</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Dr. Fisher said in a statement that he had asked for administrative leave as principal investigator of the 14 studies, which are financed by the cancer institute and are known as the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project. They are widely recognized for having changed the standard of care for those types of cancer. Federal officials praised Dr. Fisher's contributions to medical practice even as they demanded his ouster.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher, 75, was granted the leave, Dr. Thomas Detre, the university's senior vice chancellor for health sciences, said in a separate statement. He will continue as a senior clinical researcher and adviser on the science of the 14-study project.</p>
        <p>The broad actions came a day after the cancer institute, citing a new discrepancy in a breast cancer study, asked the university to replace Dr. Fisher as principal investigator of the project.  Extraordinary Public Rebuke</p>
        <p>The public rebuke was extraordinarily harsh punishment of a visible and distinguished scientist. Officials at the National Institutes of Health said they could not immediately recall any similar case.</p>
        <p>The severity is all the more surprising since the cancer institute has repeatedly said it stood behind the conclusions of Dr. Fisher's studies.</p>
        <p>Institute officials demanded the disciplinary action after repeated criticism of Dr. Fisher for delays in detecting falsified data submitted to the Pittsburgh center by Dr. Roger Poisson of St. Luc Hospital in Montreal. The falsifications were first detected in 1990 and were not reported to the cancer institute for months.</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Fisher has given the institute re-analyses of the findings excluding Dr. Poisson's data, institute officials have criticized him for not submitting a paper to The New England Journal of Medicine, which published the original reports in 1985 and 1989. Publication of the revised data is a standard way for correcting information in medicine.</p>
        <p>In addition, on Monday the institute said it had found a discrepancy in a breast cancer study at a second hospital in Montreal, St. Mary's. The institute harshly criticized Dr. Fisher's administrative abilities by saying his team had failed to follow up in a timely way after it detected the irregularity at St. Mary's.</p>
        <p>The health officials said they had not yet determined whether the irregularity was significant. But they said Dr. Fisher's team violated its own guidelines for conducting the breast cancer studies. Explanation of Move</p>
        <p>In explaining why his agency had ordered a halt in recruiting new patients, Dr. Curt said: "We don't have any problem with the design of the studies and their conclusions. The major problem is the studies have become very large and there is a need to focus on the administration, particularly in terms of the timeliness of the audits."</p>
        <p>The institute's actions also reflect growing concern in Congress and among the public over reports of scientific misconduct. Scientists, without citing data, insist that such incidents are rare, but new examples keep cropping up. And many critics say universities, hospitals and the Government have been lax in disciplining errant scientists.</p>
        <p>On April 13, Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, plans to hold hearings by the House Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, which he heads.</p>
        <p>In another corrective process, the cancer institute has asked the Pittsburgh team to come up with a way to solve its administrative difficulties.</p>
        <p>The institute says it was responsible for many of the deficiencies in the Pittsburgh program. "We let things slip as well," Dr. Curt said. "The audit process fell behind, and we share that responsibility." Value of Studies</p>
        <p>Emphasizing that the conclusions of the studies were not in question, Dr. Curt said that what was in question was a less-than-100-percent compliance rate in enrolling patients. "We know that it hasn't been 100 percent," he said, "and we are going to work together with the Pittsburgh group to make it as close to 100 percent as it possibly can be."</p>
        <p>To discuss ways of improving quality control and compliance by participating scientists and hospitals, the cancer institute plans to hold a meeting later this week of the heads of cooperative trials. A larger meeting will be held on April 26.</p>
        <p>Federal officials have not given details of the irregularity at St. Mary's. Dr. Bruce A. Chabner, a top official of the cancer institute, said information about it has been turned over to the Office of Research Integrity, a unit of the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>The office led the investigation of Dr. Poisson's falsified data. Lyle W. Bivens, its head, did not return calls to his office yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
