<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Real Estate;The News Corporation finds a home for its Fox cable news channel coming in the fall.</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="868614"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOX BROADCASTING CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUST FOR FEET INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARRISON JAMES (NYC STORE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1439F932A05754C0A960958260" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Real Estate;The News Corporation finds a home for its Fox cable news channel coming in the fall.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mervyn Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHSTEIN, MERVYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE News Corporation, the media behemoth controlled by Rupert Murdoch, has leased an additional 120,000 square feet at 1211 Avenue of the Americas to house the new 24-hour Fox cable news channel it plans to introduce in the fall.</p>
        <p>The company already occupies about 385,000 square feet in the 44-story, 1.7-  million-square-foot building between 47th and 48th Streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE News Corporation, the media behemoth controlled by Rupert Murdoch, has leased an additional 120,000 square feet at 1211 Avenue of the Americas to house the new 24-hour Fox cable news channel it plans to introduce in the fall.</p>
        <p>The company already occupies about 385,000 square feet in the 44-story, 1.7-  million-square-foot building between 47th and 48th Streets.</p>
        <p>David W. Levinson of the Edward S. Gordon real estate company, who represented the News Corporation, said the space was on three levels and would include street-level studio space like that of the "Today" show "but bigger, the largest of its kind."</p>
        <p>"The studio space will be two studios, open to view through 30-foot windows," Mr. Levinson said. "There potentially will be audience participation in the plaza outside on the street. A news zipper will move around the building, and there will be things happening 24 hours a day."</p>
        <p>As part of the deal, he said, the News Corporation has extended the lease on  its current space so that its commitments on the total of 505,000 square feet expire at the same time, in 2015. "And there's a potential for News Corporation's expansion in the building that could go over a million square feet," he said.</p>
        <p>Financial details of the transaction, one of the largest in the city so far this year, were not disclosed. But people in the industry familiar with the deal said that with annual rent over the term of the lease ranging between $35 and $45 a square foot, the aggregate value is about $400 million. Don O'Brien of Heitman Properties is the leasing agent for the building.</p>
        <p>Store for 42d Street</p>
        <p>Just for Feet Inc., a superstore retailer that specializes in brand-name athletic and outdoor footwear, is taking its dancing feet to what is rapidly becoming not-so-naughty, not-so-bawdy 42d Street.</p>
        <p>The company has signed a lease for 25,000 square feet of selling space on the south side of the street in the planned 375,000-square-foot Forest City Ratner Companies entertainment and retail complex, between the 25-screen AMC multiplex  movie house and Madame Tussaud's Wax Museum. The site is down the block from the Walt Disney Company's New Amsterdam Theater, whose renovation is expected to be  completed next spring. The 25-year lease was valued at $60 million.</p>
        <p>Harold Ruttenberg, Just for Feet's chairman and chief executive, said he had  chosen the location because it would have "a lot of traffic and a lot of tourists -- it fits in perfectly with what we're doing." He said the store would open near the end of 1997. Just for Feet has 38 company-operated and 6 franchise stores in 14 states. Faith Hope Consolo and Joseph Aquino of the Garrick-Aug brokerage represented the tenant.</p>
        <p>Where Cary Toiled</p>
        <p>A landmark six-story turn-of-the-century town house at 5 West 54th Street that once housed an office for Cary Grant will by early fall be home -- rather appropriately -- to an upscale men's furnishings store.</p>
        <p>The men's fashion executive Alan Katzman, who recently left Bijan to form his own company, Harrison James, has leased the entire 15,000-square-foot town house, which includes 14 working fireplaces, a private elevator, an outdoor garden patio and a mahogany spiral staircase. The 20-year lease was valued at $15 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Katzman said the Harrison James store would feature suits, coats, knitwear, formal wear, accessories and gift items, as well as two restaurants -- one in a rooftop greenhouse -- a club room, a barber shop and a humidor room.</p>
        <p>"You cannot duplicate space like this," Mr. Katzman said. "You have woodwork  here in pristine condition that's a century old. If I had to replace it today I would spend about $6 million. It has a staircase that's out of a movie and 14  marble fireplaces that are to die for."</p>
        <p>The Renaissance-inspired town house just off Fifth Avenue was built between 1897 and 1899 by the architect Robert H. Robertson for the eminent neurologist Moses Allen Starr and is one of five adjacent late-1890's town houses that have  landmark status. Its base is limestone, and the exterior of the upper floors is  Roman brick trimmed with limestone.</p>
        <p>The building most recently was the corporate headquarters of Petrola House, a Greek shipping concern. An earlier tenant was Faberge; Mr. Grant, a Faberge board member, used his ground-floor office when he was in New York.</p>
        <p>Alan Victor of the Lansco Corporation represented Harrison James. Grubb &amp; Ellis New York represented the building's owner, the Latsis family of Greece.</p>
        <p>Family Fun Center</p>
        <p>Skyline Multimedia Entertainment has leased 37,000 square feet at the Empire  State Building, where it plans to create a family-oriented urban entertainment center.</p>
        <p>Skyline currently leases 26,000 square feet on the building's second floor, where it operates New York Skyride, a big-screen flight-simulation attraction in two theaters that takes audiences on a ride under, over or through the sights of New York City. Mark Messersmith, executive vice president of Skyline, said the company was considering various combinations of entertainment, retail and dining for the new space, most of the rest of the second floor and part of the third floor.</p>
        <p>Stephen A. Tole, general manager and director of leasing at the building, said the 20-year lease was valued at more than $18 million.</p>
        <p>MFS Lease</p>
        <p>The MFS Communications Company, a provider of high-speed telephone and data services to businesses, has leased 75,000 square feet on the 12th floor at 111 Eighth Avenue, the 15-story, 2.3-million-square-foot former Port Authority headquarters building between 15th and 16th Streets.</p>
        <p>MFS, whose New York City headquarters are at 33 Whitehall Street, plans to use the space for administrative offices and a switching station. The 15-year lease was valued at about $16 million. David Falk of the Williams Real Estate Company represented the tenant.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
