<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amy Knoblauch Wed to David Dubin</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="131324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KNOBLAUCH, AMY (AMY DUBIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUBIN, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D81539F93BA15750C0A96E948260" item-length="214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amy Knoblauch Wed to David Dubin</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At Congregation Rodeph Sholom in New York, Amy Gail Knoblauch, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Sidney G. Knoblauch of Reading, Pa., and James David Dubin, a son of Dr. and Mrs. Samuel S. Dubin of State College, Pa., were married yesterday by Rabbi Gunter Hirschberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At Congregation Rodeph Sholom in New York, Amy Gail Knoblauch, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Sidney G. Knoblauch of Reading, Pa., and James David Dubin, a son of Dr. and Mrs. Samuel S. Dubin of State College, Pa., were married yesterday by Rabbi Gunter Hirschberg.</p>
        <p>At Congregation Rodeph Sholom in New York, Amy Gail Knoblauch, the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Sidney G. Knoblauch of Reading, Pa., and James David Dubin, a son of Dr. and Mrs. Samuel S. Dubin of State College, Pa., were married yesterday by Rabbi Gunter Hirschberg.</p>
        <p>The bride, until recently the director of development at Landmark Restorations, a real-estate company in Brooklyn, restores town houses on the West Side of Manhattan. She attended Wellesley College, graduated from Stanford University and received a master's degree in city planning from Harvard University. Her father is the president of Murry &amp; Sidney Knoblauch Inc., a commercial real-estate company in Reading.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, who is known as David, is an associate director and a co-chief of the energy finance group at Bear, Stearns &amp; Company in New York. A cum laude graduate of Yale University, he received an M.B.A. from Harvard, where he was a Sidney J. Weinberg-Goldman Sachs Fellow. Mr. Dubin is chairman of the New York Grand Opera and a national trustee of the Washington Opera. His father is a professor emeritus of psychology at Pennsylvania State University and a former director of the human performance laboratories at the University of Southern California. His mother, Lydia Dubin, is a painter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
