<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On a Cultural Battlefield: Women in the Military</title>
    <meta content="23BERN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BOOKS OF THE TIMES" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="939037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Francke, Linda Bird</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ground Zero (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D6113EF930A15755C0A961958260" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On a Cultural Battlefield: Women in the Military</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews book Ground Zero by Linda Bird Francke; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GROUND ZERO  The Gender Wars in the Military</p>
        <p>By Linda Bird Francke</p>
        <p>304 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GROUND ZERO  The Gender Wars in the Military</p>
        <p>By Linda Bird Francke</p>
        <p>304 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
        <p>Nobody will accuse Linda Bird Francke of bad timing in ''Losing Ground,'' her well-reported account of the sexual wars in the military. Ms. Francke, who has written books on abortion and divorce and has collaborated on several books by women involved in politics, is, as they say, on the news with this new work.</p>
        <p>The main thread of her interesting narrative runs through the long and, so far, unsuccessful campaign to repeal the ban imposed by law against women's serving as combat soldiers. But as Ms. Francke deals along the way with such matters as sexual harassment and other forms of anti-female discrimination, she makes it clear that she is really writing about the ongoing culture wars in America, of which the battle over women in the military is especially hard fought.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke is a reliable observer of this cultural clash, even as she makes no secret of where she stands on the battlefield. She calls her book ''a narrative of the cultural and biological forces at work within the military culture that divide the sexes, dictate women's harassment and demean their achievements.'' The disdainful and sometimes violent treatment of women shows, she writes,  ''the male attitudes ingrained in the military culture -- the institutional promotion of male dominance, the aura of hypermasculinity, the collective male imperative to disparage women in general and specifically women in the military.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke gives some graphic evidence of this untrammeled sexism and, as she does so, she makes an unignorable case that women would be discriminated against in the Army, the Navy and the Air Force even if it could be proved that they performed certain tasks better than men.</p>
        <p>''Ground Zero,'' in short, is a tough-minded defense of the proposition that women should enjoy the same equality of opportunity in the armed forces as they have sought in other areas of life. At the same time, it is a book that one wants to argue with, in large part because Ms. Francke's presentation of the issue as almost entirely one of male sexism keeps her clear of other important questions, moral and practical.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke treats the armed forces as though they were the same as any other major institution of American life, say, college sports or medical school, assuming that the objections raised to women's performing combat roles are nothing more than rationalizations for underlying prejudice. ''Successful Women, Threatened Men'' is the subtitle of her concluding chapter. ''Women cleared for combat positions are on a collision course with the male need for masculine reassurance,'' she argues.</p>
        <p>But as the ultimate defender of the nation against outside enemies, the Army is a unique institution, one whose ultimate purpose is not to be fair to its members but to kill enemy soldiers, as many of them as possible, and that task inevitably involves getting killed as well. Ms. Francke does not weave that essential fact into her argument. She assumes that realizing complete sexual equality requires no cost in military effectiveness, an assumption that requires a good deal more scrutiny than she  gives it.</p>
        <p>She further assumes, in the event of a major conflict with substantial casualties, that there is no moral or practical difference if women do substantial amounts of the killing and dying, eliminating what has until now been an exclusively male area of responsibility. This has the effect of limiting Ms. Francke's persuasiveness for those readers who may be uncertain that sexual equality ought to extend to the task of slaughtering the nation's enemies, or, indeed, to making the ultimate sacrifice.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke argues from the example of the Persian Gulf war, during which there were 15 female dead of the total of 375 American fatalities, that the public is ready to accept casualties among women. But what would the public's reaction -- indeed, what would Ms. Francke's reaction have been -- if the American soldiers beaten, killed, mutilated and dragged through the streets in the failed intervention in Somalia had been women, perhaps one or two of them pregnant?</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke is certainly right that there is terrible anti-female discrimination in the Army. But the matter of combat is morally perplexing in a way that other issues -- rape or cadence songs demeaning to women -- are not.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francke, by the way, gives some vivid examples of those cadence songs, one of many areas in which her reporting is extremely telling in the richness of its detail. Moreover, in some areas her arguments are close to definitive, particularly when the treatment of women, the effort to diminish their accomplishments, does reveal simple male bias at work. Ms. Francke shows that  women are not in the military as a matter of political correctness but as a matter of national need: there simply aren't enough men enlisting.</p>
        <p>She deals vigorously and convincingly with the commonly expressed worry that pregnancy will sap American combat readiness, showing that absenteeism from various tasks is as least as high among men as it is among women. Her chapter on sexual harassment and sexual violence against women is stark and disturbing. Anyone who might have been inclined to dismiss the harassment issue as a kind of boys-will-be-boys mischievousness needs to take in Ms. Francke's portrayal of military life for women.</p>
        <p>There are some questions that she does not deal with. Why, given the rampant libidos of 18-year-olds, is it preferable to have sexually integrated basic training? The Israelis, who pioneered active roles for women in the military, have segregated training. The Israelis have also banned women from combat largely on the grounds that their male counterparts are overly protective of them in battle, a subject that Ms. Francke deals with only glancingly.</p>
        <p>In other words, to treat the matter of women in the military almost exclusively as a question of the larger culture war is to see the matter too narrowly. But Ms. Francke is undeniably correct that cultural attitudes, and not some presumed physical shortcomings among women, explain a major part of the problem. On that subject, she has produced a volume that will have to be taken into account as the debate rages on.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
