<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move on Bosnia By U.S. Alarms Allies in NATO</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="724852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBARGOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DC1631F931A25752C1A962958260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move on Bosnia By U.S. Alarms Allies in NATO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>BONN, Nov. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>European allies expressed alarm today over the Clinton Administration's decision to end Washington's role in enforcing an arms embargo against the Bosnian Government, warning that the unilateral move undermined NATO and could diminish the chances for peace in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>The decision seemed to thrust the United States into its most serious diplomatic rift over the Balkan war since early 1993, when Washington failed to convince NATO partners to lift the embargo and to bomb Serbian forces who were trouncing Bosnia's mainly Muslim Government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>European allies expressed alarm today over the Clinton Administration's decision to end Washington's role in enforcing an arms embargo against the Bosnian Government, warning that the unilateral move undermined NATO and could diminish the chances for peace in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>The decision seemed to thrust the United States into its most serious diplomatic rift over the Balkan war since early 1993, when Washington failed to convince NATO partners to lift the embargo and to bomb Serbian forces who were trouncing Bosnia's mainly Muslim Government.</p>
        <p>The Administration's decision to exempt Government forces from the embargo was not wholly unexpected, since Congress had voted to cut off all funds for enforcing the ban on Nov. 15 if the Serbs had not agreed to a peace accord.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the move drew a baffled response from European allies, who apparently had not taken the pressure from Congress very seriously. The step seemed to worry particularly Britain and France, which have thousands of troops as United Nations peacekeepers in the former Yugoslavia and have joined the United States, Russia and Germany in seeking a negotiated peace.</p>
        <p>"It is a worry because this is a mandatory resolution of the Security Council and an agreed policy of the alliance," the British Foreign Secretary, Douglas Hurd, told BBC.</p>
        <p>France called for a meeting of foreign ministers of the major powers to seek a "clarification" of the new United States policy.</p>
        <p>In a telephone call to Secretary of State Warren Christopher, Foreign Minister Alain Juppe "conveyed the French Government's deep worries about this unilateral decision, which we can only regret," a ministry statement said.</p>
        <p>The statement said France would reassess the safety of the more than 3,600 troops it has in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>The Administration's decision, effective on Saturday, means that the United States Navy will no longer divert ships carrying arms to Bosnia or Croatia or share intelligence information on the shipments with Western European allies.</p>
        <p>The move is not expected to have an immediate effect on the battlefield, since the Bosnian Government has been receiving clandestine arms shipments, mostly by air, for some months. But it seems likely to erode cooperation among the allies and strengthen the resolve of France and other European governments to move away from dependence on the United States for their defense.</p>
        <p>"This example proves just how much Europe needs to be autonomous where intelligence-gathering, satellite reconnaissance and logistic support are concerned," said Sir Dudley Smith, a British Member of Parliament who is also head of the legislative assembly of the 12-nation European Union's military arm, the Western European Union.</p>
        <p>The Western European Union takes part in the naval embargo on arms shipments to all the belligerents in the Bosnian war. But in practice it has few intelligence resources, communications installations or effective command structures of its own and relies on NATO's because most of its members belong to the alliance as well.</p>
        <p>"The United States has just taken sides," a ranking NATO officer said.</p>
        <p>The Dutch Government said it regretted the move, and the Spanish Foreign Ministry warned that exempting any Bosnian combatants from the embargo would intensify the war.</p>
        <p>Even officials in Bonn, often the most stalwart ally of the United States during the cold war, cautioned that a one-sided lifting of the embargo could lead to intensified war rather than negotiated peace.</p>
        <p>The Russian Government said it was withholding formal reaction until it received notification from Washington. It was not clear tonight how long President Boris N. Yeltsin would continue to resist political pressure to lift the embargo against the Serbs, whom Russian nationalists view as Slavic brethren.</p>
        <p>While neither NATO nor the United Nations has been effective in stopping the fighting in Bosnia, until now the United States had always acted in concert with its European allies. In January 1993, the question was whether the Clinton Administration could get its NATO allies to agree to let arms reach the Muslims and to bomb Serbian forces who were attacking outgunned Muslim towns. The initiative failed, and today the allies confronted one of the results of NATO's reluctance to act aggressively to halt the war.</p>
        <p>In August 1993, the Administration dragged the allies reluctantly to a decision to threaten the Bosnian Serbs with NATO air strikes unless they stopped the strangulation of Sarajevo and five other towns designated as civilian "safe areas."</p>
        <p>In drawn-out negotiations in Brussels last February, the United States persuaded the allies again to agree to make the threat real, and sent warplanes to bomb Bosnian Serb targets when they disregarded it.</p>
        <p>Now, in effect, the United States has told the alliance it leads that American troops will stand aside while the other allies go on trying to enforce the embargo.</p>
        <p>NATO officials predicted that the decision would have a limited practical effect. "In two years, we've monitored 42,000 ships in the Adriatic and only three of them have been found to be carrying weapons," a civilian official said.</p>
        <p>Only two of the 18 NATO ships now stationed in the Adriatic are American, commanders say, but they provide most of the intelligence and electronics surveillance NATO has there. Officers said other ships could fill the gap.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>U.S. SEEKS TO PRESSURE SERBS</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, Nov. 10 (Special to The New York Times) -- Responding to complaints by Western European nations, senior Administration officials said today that the decision to halt enforcement of the arms embargo was intended to increase pressure on the Bosnian Serbs to agree to a peace settlement.</p>
        <p>"The Serbs are the aggressors in this war," said a senior Pentagon official. "It is the Bosnian Serbs who are the only parties, even including Belgrade, who have not signed up for the contact group proposals which would end the fighting."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
