<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Eat a Church Supper Is to Want to Cry 'Amen'</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="376379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELIGION AND CHURCHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNIONVILLE (VA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BETHEL BAPTIST CHURCH (UNIONVILLE, VA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'NEILL, MOLLY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6153BF936A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="2707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Eat a Church Supper Is to Want to Cry 'Amen'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOLLY O'NEILL; Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'NEILL, MOLLY</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONVILLE, Va., Aug. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Last week, Edna Lewis and her sister Jen Ellis drove the gentle thread of asphalt that weaves through the cornfields and pastures of rural central Virginia toward the grocery. The white-haired women puttered past the brick house where their grandmother had served as a slave, past the meadow where their childhood home once stood and where their brother Lue Stanley Lewis still keeps 18 head of cattle and a pair of pigs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Last week, Edna Lewis and her sister Jen Ellis drove the gentle thread of asphalt that weaves through the cornfields and pastures of rural central Virginia toward the grocery. The white-haired women puttered past the brick house where their grandmother had served as a slave, past the meadow where their childhood home once stood and where their brother Lue Stanley Lewis still keeps 18 head of cattle and a pair of pigs.</p>
        <p>Last week, Edna Lewis and her sister Jen Ellis drove the gentle thread of asphalt that weaves through the cornfields and pastures of rural central Virginia toward the grocery. The white-haired women puttered past the brick house where their grandmother had served as a slave, past the meadow where their childhood home once stood and where their brother Lue Stanley Lewis still keeps 18 head of cattle and a pair of pigs. They steered past Bethel Baptist Church, which their grandfather helped found 100 years ago.</p>
        <p>Miss Lewis, the 74-year-old chef at the Gage &amp; Tollner restaurant in Brooklyn, and Miss Ellis, who is 76 and has always lived near the 72-acre sprawl of farm land where they grew up, were going to buy the fixings for Bethel Baptist's annual church supper. They didn't have a shopping list. They had memories.</p>
        <p>Country ham. Barbecued lamb. Corn cut off the cob and baked into a tender corn pudding. Roast turkey. Sermons. Dry seasons. Poll taxes. Beets with onions and tomatoes. The Great Depression. The taste of chickens that scratched in the backyard. Hymns and hallelujahs. The civil rights march. The way Cousin Douglas looked in his Air Force uniform! Aunt Edna in her first tie-dyed African dress!</p>
        <p>Remember? Homecoming, the second Sunday in August, when all who have ever raised a voice at Bethel Baptist come back to raise forks and long glasses of iced tea to each other, to what they have become and to where they have come from.</p>
        <p>Around the United States, daily family mealtimes are becoming a memory, fast food has eclipsed home cooking, pastors worry about dwindling congregations. But church suppers persist. Hand-painted signs for the dinners dot the nation's roadsides and crowd the classified section of small-town gazettes. Some of the meals thrive as fund-raisers. Some bespeak a region more than a religion. The most authentic are small suppers that ethnic enclaves continue to serve, the fragile ties that bind, the shy fingers that beckon the outside world.</p>
        <p>All are mutable feasts. They reflect changes: ''We're going to have to buy ham and chicken this year,'' Edna Lewis said. Her brother Lue is 78 now, and can't keep as many chickens and hogs as before. The menus also reflect a resistance to change: the Lewis women will bake their plump, fatty hams for three days and pan-fry their chicken in lard.</p>
        <p>And it may be the slow dance of change and staying the same that continues to pull hundreds of thousands of Americans back to the long folding tables set out in church basements and on front lawns. Although the congregation at the Bethel Baptist Church has shrunk to six families, strands of those families that had unfurled to work in cities across the country rolled back to Unionville for the centennial homecoming today. More than 300 people showed up to ohh-and-ahh and eat.</p>
        <p>Some nibbled on memories. Others, like 8-year-old Neiman Johnson, whose family had driven from Illinois, got the first taste of something that would become a memory. ''I used to like pizza the best,'' he said. ''But now I like Aunt Jen's chicken.'' Such changes of heart have given church suppers an irresistible nostalgic appeal and have made them prime fund-raising opportunities.</p>
        <p>Along the Rhode Island, Connecticut and Massachusetts coasts, clambakes became a mainstay of hundreds of church treasuries. In the Carolinas, it was low-country barbecue; in Texas, pit barbecue pulled crowds so large that commercial catering eventually eclipsed the family-honed potluck meals. Connection - with family, place and past - often gave way to carnival.</p>
        <p>But recently, noncommercial church dinners have made a comeback. Like an unbroken circle, the old-time meals have returned to their less efficient beginnings.</p>
        <p>In Maine, for instance, the beanhole dinner is the rock that many churches are built on, regardless of denomination. Based on the cheap Saturday-night dinners once served in the state's northern lumber camps, the meal was originally a pot of beans and pork fat, set over coals in a sand pit and slow-cooked. But in the late 1970's, as churches began serving the dinner to crowds, the sand pit gave way to the crock pot.</p>
        <p>''You can't serve over 50 people from a sand pit,'' said Bernard Staples, who for the past 20 years has organized the annual beanhole dinner at the Episcopal Church of Our Father in Hulls Cove, Me. Fifteen years ago, he said, a dozen church members began slow-baking the beans in their home ovens in lieu of the sand pit. That yielded greater numbers of beans and greater diversity, as cooks steadfastly prepared their favored bean. Red kidney, pinto, yellow-eye, pea and navy beans, each with varying levels of molasses sweetness or salt-pork richness, joined the traditional white bean at the suppers.</p>
        <p>But the variety of beans (and the genteel competition among the cooks) wasn't what motivated State Representative Sherman Hutchins and his family to start a ''traditional beanhole'' 10 years ago to benefit the Penobscot Historical Society in Maine. Their labor-intensive meals hearken back to the intimacy and cooperation of the old-style dinners.</p>
        <p>''I was worried about the decentralizing of tradition,'' he said at the annual dinner last month. With one foot on a spade that was sunk next to a pot in the 15-foot-wide sand pit, he continued: ''The more it goes to individual homes, the less cooperation you have.'' For three days, Mr. Hutchins, his wife, Patty, and his parents, Hoyt and Polly Hutchins, worked to dig the three-foot-deep pit, parboil the 52 pounds of dried beans needed to feed 150 people and cook them in 12 pots over a cord of wood for nine hours.</p>
        <p>''It's the only way you get the flavor of the earth,'' said Mr. Hutchins, who hopes that churches in the area will follow him backward in time in their beanhole technique. ''You remember where you came from.''</p>
        <p>The need to remember is crucial to the mystique of church suppers, said Geoff Lorenz, the president of the Lorenz Corporation, a distributor of liturgical music in Dayton, Ohio. Traveling to churches all over the Midwest, he has not been surprised to see more and more church suppers in recent years.</p>
        <p>''The church of the past couple decades concerned itself with the hereafter,'' he said. ''The church of the near future is concerned with the here and now. That's what people want.''</p>
        <p>Occasionally, the past collides with the here and now, calling the future into question. At the First Lutheran Church in Duluth, Minn., for instance, the annual lutefisk and Norwegian meatball supper began causing inter-generational consternation last year. Lutefisk - lye-cured cod that Scandinavians have traditionally relished as much for its old-country appeal as for its pungent taste - is ''obnoxious'' to the generation raised on milder flavors, said Phyllis Matheson, the congregation's cook.</p>
        <p>''My daughter won't come to church as long as it smells like lutefisk,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The clash between young and old is different in northern Wisconsin. This week, Belgian Roman Catholic churches there begin celebrating seven weeks of Kermis, the harvest celebration that starts with Sunday services and proceeds from home to home in a kind of progressive dinner.</p>
        <p>The young people still savor the dinners of rich beef soup, thick beef stew, cabbage salad and thick Belgian pies with their yeasted crusts. But ''they just don't have time for that kind of kitchen work anymore,'' said Lorraine Rutz, who has been cooking meals for the celebration at St. Paul's Evangelical Church in Algoma, Wis., for most of her 70 years.</p>
        <p>At Our Lady of Guadalupe Roman Catholic Church in East Los Angeles, the men of the parish are making time for the kitchen. In 1923, the churchwomen began cooking menudo, a rib-sticking tripe and hominy stew that they served after Mass to beckon their husbands to church.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, as more and more women took jobs outside the home, they had less time to prepare the weekly ritual breakfast, with its time-consuming main dish. ''Then men started helping,'' said Marie Colores, adding that attendance has been increasing every year.</p>
        <p>Despite the revivals across the country, historians like Dr. Barbara J. Flint of Howard University fear that small church suppers could be fading feasts. For three years she has studied historic churches along the Eastern Seaboard.</p>
        <p>''Financially, big churches in touristy urban areas stand a chance,'' she said as she continued her study at the Bethel Baptist Church homecoming dinner. Noting that the congregation had once been 200 families, she asked: ''What's going to keep little places like this alive?''</p>
        <p>Maybe it will be something that persists, despite waning numbers and light collection baskets.</p>
        <p>Behind the linen-covered plank tables, four generations of Lewis women were dishing up supper. The 60-odd cars packing the churchyard had license plates from Virginia, Maryland, New York, Pennsylvania, Georgia and Illinois. Frederick Douglass Boulware, now in his 40's, admired the little clapboard church, which his Uncle Lue had given a coat of whitewash just the day before. Distant cousins a third his age, Cordell Richardson and Tony and Neiman Johnson, happily chomped Aunt Jen's chicken nearby.</p>
        <p>A steady line of people in their Sunday best passed by the Lewis sisters, cousins, daughters and aunts. Plates proffered, they sidled up to memory, fortifying themselves for the future.</p>
        <p>Praise the Lord and Pass the Norwegian Meatballs</p>
        <p>Coleslaw</p>
        <p>(Adapted from St. Paul's Evangelical Roman Catholic Church, Algoma, Wis.)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 30 minutes, plus 2 hours for sitting</p>
        <p>1 medium-size head white cabbage, shredded fine</p>
        <p>1 medium-size head red cabbage, shredded fine</p>
        <p>2 cups sour cream</p>
        <p>1 cup mayonnaise</p>
        <p>1/4 cup bacon fat</p>
        <p>1/2 cup vegetable oil</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons sugar</p>
        <p>3/4 cup cider vinegar</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons celery seeds</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons mustard seeds</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon dry mustard</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons salt</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon white pepper</p>
        <p>2 carrots, peeled and shredded</p>
        <p>1 medium-size green pepper, cored and minced</p>
        <p>1 medium-size red pepper, cored and minced.</p>
        <p>Rinse cabbage and dry well. In a large bowl, mix cabbage with sour cream, mayonnaise, bacon fat, vegetable oil, sugar, vinegar, celery seeds, mustard seeds, dry mustard, salt and pepper, and stir well to combine. Let sit 2 hours. Add carrots and green and red pepper and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Belgian Pie</p>
        <p>(Adapted from Charlotte Bero of Algoma, Wis.)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 40 minutes, plus one hour for resting</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 50 minutes</p>
        <p>For the crust:</p>
        <p>3 eggs, separated</p>
        <p>1/4 cup sugar</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon butter, softened</p>
        <p>1 package active dry yeast</p>
        <p>1/4 cup lukewarm water</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cups flour, plus additional flour to dust board</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon salt</p>
        <p>For the filling:</p>
        <p>2 cups raisins</p>
        <p>1 cup water</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons heavy cream</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons sugar</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons flour</p>
        <p>For the topping:</p>
        <p>4 cups creamy cottage cheese</p>
        <p>3 egg yolks</p>
        <p>1 cup sugar</p>
        <p>3/4 cup heavy cream.</p>
        <p>1.To make crust, beat egg whites until stiff but not dry. Add egg yolks, sugar and butter and beat to combine. Dissolve yeast in the water and add to egg mixture. Using a fork, gently work the flour and salt into the egg mixture. Let mixture rise 1 hour.</p>
        <p>2.Flour a board and knead dough on it until satiny, about 3 minutes. Roll into two circles to line two 9-inch pie pans and put dough in the pans, pricking dough all over with fork and crimping the edges.</p>
        <p>3.To make filling, put raisins in the water and simmer 10 minutes. Drain and cool; add cream, sugar and flour. Spread the mixture evenly in pie shells.</p>
        <p>4.Preheat oven to 350 degrees.</p>
        <p>5.To make topping, use a food mill or processor to blend cottage cheese with the egg yolks and sugar, until smooth. Add cream and mix until fluffy. Spread evenly over the pies. Bake pies in oven for 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 pies.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Meatballs</p>
        <p>(Adapted from Beatrice Ojakangas, First Lutheran Church, Duluth, Minn.)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 45 minutes, plus 15 minutes for cooling</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>1/2 cup butter</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon minced onion</p>
        <p>Z cup soft bread crumbs</p>
        <p>1 cup water</p>
        <p>3/4 pound ground beef</p>
        <p>1/4 pound ground pork</p>
        <p>Salt</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon allspice</p>
        <p>White pepper</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon nutmeg</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons flour</p>
        <p>2 cups beef broth.</p>
        <p>1.In a large skillet, melt 1 tablespoon butter and cook onion until soft. Add bread crumbs and water and stir to combine. Remove from heat. Stir in beef, pork, 1 teaspoon salt, allspice, 1/2 teaspoon pepper and nutmeg.</p>
        <p>2.Beat meat mixture at high speed in a mixer for 5 minutes, until meat is light in color and fluffy. Use 2 spoons dipped in ice water to form meat into small balls. Put on a tray lined with wax paper; refrigerate 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>3.Melt remaining butter in a skillet over medium heat and brown meatballs on all sides. Remove meatballs and stir the flour into the skillet, cooking it until golden. Using a whisk, beat in beef broth and simmer 10 minutes to make gravy. Add salt and pepper to taste, return meatballs to the gravy and serve over mashed potatoes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Virginia Fried Chicken</p>
        <p>(Adapted from Edna Lewis)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 20 minutes, plus an hour for resting</p>
        <p>Cooking time: about 50 minutes</p>
        <p>1 cup unbleached flour</p>
        <p>1 cup whole-wheat flour</p>
        <p>3 teaspoons salt</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>2 2 1/4- to 2 1/2-pound chickens, cut into 8 pieces each</p>
        <p>1/2 cup lard at room temperature</p>
        <p>1/2 cup butter at room temperature.</p>
        <p>1.In a wide, flat dish, combine flours, salt and pepper and mix well. Roll chicken in the mixture and put on a tray lined with wax paper. Let rest an hour, so flour will adhere to chicken.</p>
        <p>2.In a large skillet over medium-high heat, warm lard until nearly smoking and add butter. When butter is melted, add the chicken. The cooking fat should come halfway up the sides of the chicken, so that when the pieces are turned, they brown evenly. Each side should take 10 to 12 minutes. After cooking, drain on a paper towel and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>&gt;St. Mark's Shrimp Creole</p>
        <p>(Adapted from ''Community Suppers'' by Jeanne Voltz, Scribner's, 1987)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 2 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons bacon drippings</p>
        <p>1 small white onion, minced</p>
        <p>6 ribs celery, chopped</p>
        <p>1 clove garlic, minced</p>
        <p>1 medium-size green pepper, cored and minced</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons minced parsley</p>
        <p>3 ounces tomato paste</p>
        <p>6 cups canned plum tomatoes, drained</p>
        <p>1 3/4 cups water</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons Worcestershire sauce</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon chili powder</p>
        <p>1 bay leaf</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon sugar</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons salt</p>
        <p>2 pounds medium-size shrimp, shelled and deveined</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon file powder</p>
        <p>3 cups cooked white rice.</p>
        <p>1.In a large pot over medium heat, warm bacon drippings. Add onion, celery, garlic, green pepper and parsley and cook until onion is soft, about 5 minutes. Add tomato paste, tomatoes, water, Worcestershire, chili powder, bay leaf, sugar and salt. Cover and simmer 2 hours, stirring occasionally.</p>
        <p>2.Add shrimp and simmer 10 minutes. Stir in file powder, remove from heat and remove bay leaf. Ladle over rice and serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Beanhole Beans</p>
        <p>(Adapted from State Representative Sherman Hutchins of Maine)</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 10 minutes, plus 45 minutes for soaking</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 3 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>1 pound dried white beans</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon dry mustard</p>
        <p>Y cup molasses</p>
        <p>1/4 cup brown sugar</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon salt</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>1 large white onion, peeled and cut in half</p>
        <p>1 pound pork fatback.</p>
        <p>1.Put beans in a large bowl, cover with cold water and let soak 45 minutes. Drain.</p>
        <p>2.Preheat oven to 300 degrees.</p>
        <p>3.In a large, heavy casserole or cast-iron pot, combine beans, mustard, molasses, sugar, salt and pepper. Put onion halves, cut side down, on top of beans. Using a sharp knife, slice fatback nearly to the rind, like an accordion: horizontally every 1/2 inch for the length of the fat. Put pork on top of onion.</p>
        <p>4.Add cold water to cover mixture by one inch. Cover pot and put in oven for 3 1/2 hours, until beans are tender.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
