<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Disrupting the Unabomber Trial, but to What End?</title>
    <meta content="11GLAB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unabom Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaczynski, Theodore J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unabom Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06EEDE1739F932A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Disrupting the Unabomber Trial, but to What End?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article examines tactics by Unabom suspect Theodore J Kaczynski, who halted start of his trial with last-minute complaints about his attorneys; queries whether he was engaged in calculated disruption of legal process; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER Theodore J. Kaczynski threw the Unabom trial into chaos and apparently tried to hang himself last week, his lawyers said it was proof that the defendant was too mentally ill to be able to endure hearing himself described in court as crazy.</p>
        <p>There were plenty of people who said the man's agony was obvious. And they said his trial showed how inept the legal system is at handling  mental illness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER Theodore J. Kaczynski threw the Unabom trial into chaos and apparently tried to hang himself last week, his lawyers said it was proof that the defendant was too mentally ill to be able to endure hearing himself described in court as crazy.</p>
        <p>There were plenty of people who said the man's agony was obvious. And they said his trial showed how inept the legal system is at handling  mental illness.</p>
        <p>But as the bizarre events unfolded, a debate began to emerge across the country. To some, Mr. Kaczynski seemed to be engaging in a calculated disruption of the legal process, much as the Unabomber once planned to upend society by killing people. What if he was figuratively hurling bombs at the system from the defense table?</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kaczynski is the Unabomber, who spent some 30 years living an austere life of discipline and denial, he might be capable of trying to send his message another way after he was captured. If he is the man who thought he could save society by killing people he did not know and by sending sneering letters to those he had maimed, why would he shrink at turning his trial into a circus?</p>
        <p>A Thin Line</p>
        <p>''The line between the paranoid defendant and the political defendant is not an easy line to draw, and Kaczynski seems to have his feet in both worlds,'' said Ronald L. Kuby, the New York attorney who has represented both types of defendants and once practiced law with William M. Kunstler, the embodiment of the political defense lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaczynski waited until the final moment before his trial was set to begin on Monday to raise for the umpteenth time ''very important'' issues about his lawyers that he had already spent days debating with his lawyers and the judge in closed-door sessions. Then he tried to dismiss the lawyers and represent himself.</p>
        <p>Plan of Attack</p>
        <p>During the long bombing campaign that killed 3 people and injured 28, the Unabomber tracked news coverage of the attacks meticulously. Eventually, through a calculated plan aimed at maximum exposure, the mystery bomber managed to get his manifesto published and widely read.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Kaczynski's actions occurred while the national press corps, the jurors, the victims of the Unabomber's crimes and his own brother and mother were assembled here for his trial.</p>
        <p>It seems likely that he would have known that this was the moment of maximum impact. ''Disruption of the trial would meet his purposes more than cooperating with his lawyers and planning a defense,'' said John J. Lucas, a forensic psychiatrist and a professor at Cornell University Medical College.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lucas said if Mr. Kaczynski was a delusional paranoid schizophrenic, as defense experts have concluded, then the power of his delusions would be likely to wax and wane. When the delusions were weakest, Dr. Lucas said, Mr. Kaczynski might see the rationality of his lawyers' assertions that the only way he could hope to avoid the death penalty would be to tell the jurors that he was a troubled man.</p>
        <p>But, Dr. Lucas said, ''The only purpose he would have at the time of maximum delusions, the most important thing, would be to prove whatever was his original purpose, to follow through with his delusional systems.''</p>
        <p>In that state, Mr. Kaczynski would doubtless see himself as a political prisoner whose goal in a trial might be to spread the anti-technology message that the Unabomber worked painstakingly to send to the world for years. To that end, creating turmoil in his trial could be seen as more useful disruption. ''It would be better,'' the Unabomber wrote in his manifesto, ''to dump the whole stinking system and take the consequences.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kaczynski at times remains persuaded that the Unabom campaign was justified, as defense psychiatric experts have suggested, he might view even his own defense lawyers as tools of the system.</p>
        <p>In journals found in Mr. Kaczynski's Montana cabin, prosecutors say there are extensive comments showing that he would view any attempt to portray him as disturbed as an act of sabotage directed at the Unabom campaign.</p>
        <p>The Unabomber wrote that if he had murdered enough people by the time he was killed or caught, society was bound to label him a ''sickie'' to undermine his credibility.</p>
        <p>Us Versus Them</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuby said people who perceived themselves as political defendants were likely to view their conventional defense lawyers as political opponents. And often, he added, they would be right in a sense.</p>
        <p>''If Jesus had lawyers,'' he said, ''I'm sure they said, 'Please, keep your mouth shut when they ask you if you're the son of God.' ''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kaczynski views himself as a revolutionary, the notion of turning his trial into a spectacle like the Chicago Seven trial might have some appeal. Even before last week's events, Mr. Kaczynski had sent signals that he had a different agenda from that of his lawyers.</p>
        <p>While the defense lawyers were busy preparing a ''mental defect'' defense, Mr. Kaczynski suddenly refused to submit to any examination by prosecution psychiatrists. Lawyers watching the case said they felt certain the defense team would have told Mr. Kaczynski that such a course would inevitably sabotage the defense they were planning. But sabotage, some commentators have suggested, was just what he may have wanted.</p>
        <p>Adding to such speculation was a skirmish in recent weeks indicating that Mr. Kaczynski may have tried to violate the first rule of most defense lawyers: Don't talk to reporters. Lawyers for Christine Craft, a reporter for The Sacramento News &amp; Review, an alternative weekly, filed legal papers asserting that a friend of Mr. Kaczynski's had passed word to her that Mr. Kaczynski wanted to give her an exclusive interview. She was ready, she said, but the defense lawyers refused to add her name to Mr. Kaczynski's prison visiting list.</p>
        <p>For defense lawyers, a client who wants to disrupt the very system they are sworn to uphold poses an impossible challenge. Before last week, Mr. Kaczynski's competence to stand trial had not been seriously challenged in court. And defendants who are competent enough to stand trial have a right to control what type of defense is made on their behalf.</p>
        <p>But the rules do not make it clear how a lawyer should handle a client who wants to throw a wrench into the system.</p>
        <p>And by Mr. Kaczynski's design or not, disorder prevails: On Friday he was ordered to undergo mental competency tests, forcing a delay of his trial until at least Jan. 22.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
