<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 1998, a Rainbow Of New Perennials</title>
    <meta content="11GARD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EEDD1E30F932A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 1998, a Rainbow Of New Perennials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT'S new in annuals and perennials? Each gardening year begins with enticing offerings of a plethora of seed catalogues.</p>
        <p>Since it is impossible to cover everything new, a selection of highlights makes sense. Some can be grown from seed, while others will be on display at garden centers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT'S new in annuals and perennials? Each gardening year begins with enticing offerings of a plethora of seed catalogues.</p>
        <p>Since it is impossible to cover everything new, a selection of highlights makes sense. Some can be grown from seed, while others will be on display at garden centers.</p>
        <p>One new perennial has received so much publicity that it is hard to resist. Named Perennial of the Year for 1998 by the prestigious Perennial Plant Association, is the purple coneflower Magnus (Echinacea purpurea). This highly praised cousin of the black-eyed Susan is a native plant that was sent to Sweden. There it was refined by the noted nurseryman, Magnus Nilsson, and has now come back to us.</p>
        <p>The echinacea's refinement consisted of eliminating plants with sloppy drooping ray petals and washed out color. Mr. Nilsson was on the lookout for flat flower form and better color, particularly red. The result, Magnus, a fine sun-loving daisy with good color and stamina. The best part is the length of bloom season: up to six weeks.</p>
        <p>Although Magnus may be late in making its appearance in the spring perennial border, once the hot growing weather takes hold, it thrives. The stiff stems and large blooms make excellent cut flowers and last well indoors.</p>
        <p>Another new one that holds great promise is a hardy gazania named Colorado Gold. It was introduced by Plant Select, a cooperative program at the Denver Botanic Gardens and Colorado State University. This remarkable gazania hails from the mountain regions of South Africa and is described as being hardy to Zone 4 in this country. A popular bedding and container flower, with  sprightly daisylike flowers, it is ideal for sunny locations. Since it is rather dwarf, less than a foot tall, Colorado Gold gazania is recommended for rock gardens. It is said to be trouble-free, but as with all gazanias, the plants can become thirsty in hot spells.</p>
        <p>Anyone who has struggled with the disfiguring mildew on monarda plants by midsummer can welcome the new monarda named Petite Delight. It was developed at the Morden Research Station in Manitoba, Canada and its claim to fame is mildew resistance. All of this station's introductions have excellent winter hardiness. This newcomer is especially welcome for its unique dwarf habit,  just over a foot tall. The blooms have a wide color spread, anywhere from light lavender to a deep purple.</p>
        <p>Among the new annuals is an exciting innovation, two new heliotropes named Midnight and Twilight. Midnight is said to grow to a height of about a foot, while Twlight is another four inches taller.</p>
        <p>As with the delightful old-fashioned annual, Midnight and Twilight have the intense, wonderful fragrance that strongly suggests vanilla. Heliotrope combines well with yellow flowers and makes a spectacular summer display, especially  when set in patio containers with, say, petunias or marigolds.</p>
        <p>This sprightly plant does not fail to flower during the onslaught of summer's hottest days. It even does well if the season proves to be dry, although watering does help to keep it going. A new easy-to-grow-from-seed introduction named Million Gold holds great promise.</p>
        <p>The much heralded All-America Selections, annuals tested by members of the seed trade, are identified by the red-white-blue shield and the A.A.S. designation on seed packets and often in seed catalogue pages.</p>
        <p>This seems to be the year for the color yellow. A new yellow-flowered petunia has won the coveted honor for 1998. Named Prism Sunshine, it has large grandiflora flowers that do not fade out in bright sunshine. The plants are vigorous and bloom for a long season. The best part, this one is both heat and drought tolerant.</p>
        <p>A.A.S. has also honored a new lemon basil named, Sweet Dani. Those who relish making their own pesto can appreciate the facts that this excellent basil has a strong lemon scent and thrives if it is cut back several times a season. Herb gardeners will be delighted. This is another easy grow-from-seed introduction.</p>
        <p>New impatiens arrive each year and 1998 offers a fine new A.A.S. impatiens named Victorian Rose. Although this one is described as a single-flowered, the blooms have extra petals that make them seem to be double. As with all impatiens, the plants are self cleaning and keep going all summer long.</p>
        <p>For those who seek new flower colors in impatiens, this year will see such innovations as Dazzler, an apricot orange bloom; Show Stopper, a rich rose and super Elfin Sunrise with salmon orange flowers edged with purple. Also look for Tempo Punch with scarlet flowers and light green foliage and Wild Blue Yonder with exceptionally large flowers.</p>
        <p>These newcomers, whether from  seed catalogues or as seedlings on sale in six-packs at the local garden centers, are well worth watching for. The goal will be to simmer down the colorful possibilities when planning the garden for next spring.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
