<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Japanese Are Impressed, But They Plan to Leap Ahead</title>
    <meta content="Y16RIV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/16/international/asia/16RIVA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1527577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CHINA IN SPACE: THE RIVALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEED9163EF935A25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="526" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Japanese Are Impressed, But They Plan to Leap Ahead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Japanese Are Impressed, but They Plan to Leap Ahead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Oct. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Space programs of China and Japan have roughly similar annual budgets, but programs speak volumes about their two worldviews; China's muscular, go-it-alone space flight announces its superpower ambitions, even though it is duplicating American and Soviet feats of four decades ago; Japan's program is low-key but involves high science; it has joined American-led Space Center consortium, finding comfort in a group and walking slightly behind United States (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space programs of Asia's two most powerful nations have roughly similar annual budgets: $1.7 billion for Japan and about $2.2 billion for China. But the programs speak volumes about their two worldviews.</p>
        <p>China's well-publicized space flight duplicates the American and Soviet feats of four decades ago. This muscular, go-it-alone bid announces China's superpower ambitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By joining the American-led Space Center consortium, Japan once again finds comfort in a group.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space programs of Asia's two most powerful nations have roughly similar annual budgets: $1.7 billion for Japan and about $2.2 billion for China. But the programs speak volumes about their two worldviews.</p>
        <p>China's well-publicized space flight duplicates the American and Soviet feats of four decades ago. This muscular, go-it-alone bid announces China's superpower ambitions.</p>
        <p>''It is quite an achievement,'' Prime Minister Junichiro Koizumi said Wednesday night. ''It proved the high level of space technology and science'' in China.</p>
        <p>Japan's program is low-key but involves high science. By joining the American-led Space Center consortium, Japan once again finds comfort in a group, walking half a step behind Uncle Sam.</p>
        <p>''Japan wants to leapfrog into orbital space plane capabilities, rather than reinventing what is fairly dated technology,'' Lance Gatling, an American aerospace consultant, said.</p>
        <p>Still, the Chinese manned space flight left many here meditating on the reality of being No. 2.</p>
        <p>''Japan Shocked at Being Placed Way Behind'' was the headline in the daily Tokyo Shimbun this afternoon next to a front-page photo of the Chinese launching. Others meditated on the incongruity of Japan's giving $1.2 billion a year in developmental aid to China.</p>
        <p>Regarding space, Japan has chosen practicality over prestige. Instead of orbiting a manned spacecraft, Japan is working on cheaper, more reliable rockets and building a $4.6 billion module for the International Space Station, a 15-nation venture led by the United States.</p>
        <p>Japanese space officials emphasized to the public that they could have done what China had, if they had wanted to. ''China chose the capsule type, which Japan could also develop in relatively short period of time,'' Yasunori Matogawa, a spokesman for the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency, said on the state-run NHK television. ''So I feel desolation, but not frustration.''</p>
        <p>Still, the fact is that Japan's own on-again-off-again rocket launching program has, for now, been suspended for the fish.</p>
        <p>After mechanical trouble delayed a rocket launching three times in September, Japan's rocket engineers ran into an annual October-to-December ban on launchings from Tanegashima Island, home to Japan's $1 billion space center. Faced with militant fishermen, the space agency long ago agreed to limit launchings to a calendar when fish would not be bothered, about 190 days of the year.</p>
        <p>In India, whose strategic rivalry with China is strong, there was no official reaction on Wednesday to the Chinese space flight. India was focused instead on its neighbor to the west, Pakistan, which announced Tuesday that it had completed three tests of a medium-range missile able to carry a nuclear warhead.</p>
        <p>But the Chinese success seems likely to concentrate Indian minds even more on their own space agenda: sending an unmanned spacecraft to the moon by 2008.</p>
        <p>The aim is both scientific -- to look for traces of water on the moon, study the radiation environment in its vicinity and more -- and nationalistic: to inspire Indians much as the Shenzhou did for the Chinese.</p>
        <p>CHINA IN SPACE: THE RIVALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
