<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And for the B-52's, the Alert Is Finally Over</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="477233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BUSH'S ARM PLAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STRATEGIC AIR COMMAND (SAC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1F31F93AA1575AC0A967958260" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And for the B-52's, the Alert Is Finally Over</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American armada of B-52 Stratofortresses that for four decades has stood the role of nuclear centurion, ready at a moment's notice to fly into the nightmare of global war, is going to get a rest under the arms control package announced by President Bush on Friday.</p>
        <p>The fleet of eight-engined planes, which has come to symbolize the threat of nuclear war as much as the mushroom cloud over Hiroshima demonstrated its impact, has been rebuilt, re-winged and re-engined a dozen times since it was first shaped at the Boeing Company in the Korean War. The prototype first flew in April 1952.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American armada of B-52 Stratofortresses that for four decades has stood the role of nuclear centurion, ready at a moment's notice to fly into the nightmare of global war, is going to get a rest under the arms control package announced by President Bush on Friday.</p>
        <p>The fleet of eight-engined planes, which has come to symbolize the threat of nuclear war as much as the mushroom cloud over Hiroshima demonstrated its impact, has been rebuilt, re-winged and re-engined a dozen times since it was first shaped at the Boeing Company in the Korean War. The prototype first flew in April 1952.</p>
        <p>When the first bombers roared into Strategic Air Command bases in June 1955, their swept wings, 185 feet from tip to tip, sitting atop hulking fuselages and cavernous bomb bays, spoke volumes about American nuclear invincibility at the outset of the cold war.</p>
        <p>In their first full decade in service, the B-52's, loaded with nuclear bombs, flew continuous circuits above the United States so as not to be caught on the ground during a surprise attack. These flights ended in 1968 and were replaced by the ground alert force of bombers, still loaded with their nuclear freight and ready to go aloft in an instant.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said today that he had issued orders stating that "United States strategic bombers shall stand down from their alert postures and their nuclear weapons shall be removed and stored in secure areas."</p>
        <p>The Pentagon order goes out today to 11 Strategic Air Command bases where about 40 strategic bombers stand on alert during a 24-hour cycle awaiting a Presidential order to fly and preserving the President's option to launch a retaliatory strike in the event of a surprise nuclear attack from the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>With such cold war scenarios, the kind immortalized by films like "Dr. Strangelove," more remote than at any time since the end of World War II, the nuclear mission of the aging B-52's has effectively come to an end.</p>
        <p>The 11 Air Force bases that are home to the fleet of nuclear bombers are Barksdale in Louisiana, Griffiss in New York, Wurtsmith in Michigan, Carswell in Texas, Fairchild in Washington, K. I. Sawyer in Michigan, Minot in North Dakota, Dyess in Texas, Ellsworth in South Dakota, Grand Forks in North Dakota and McConnell in Kansas.</p>
        <p>Aside from the fleet of about 250 B-52 bombers, Mr. Cheney's order will also affect the 97 B-1 bombers that became operational in June 1985 and that have been plagued with technical problems. Mr. Cheney said that for the immediate future, the nuclear bomber fleet would remain in a high state of readiness.</p>
        <p>"This process can be reversed if need be," he said, adding, "It would take something less than 24 hours to restore the bombers to their former alert status."  BUSH'S ARM PLAN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
