<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Class Struggle</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="477210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEXTBOOKS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUGHTON MIFFLIN CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D61431F93AA1575AC0A967958260" item-length="4973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Class Struggle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY ROBERT REINHOLD;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON A LEAFY SIDE STREET IN THE Los Angeles suburb of Glendale, parents and children are playing out the American ritual of going back to school. The youngsters, still adjusting to the unfamiliar surroundings of classes at the Columbus Elementary School, clutch glossy new textbooks. About 30 of them file into John Robertson's fifth-grade classroom, where the walls are decorated with Presidential portraits, diagrams of the 50 states and Navajo sand drawings. From all appearances, a traditional setting. But appearances are deceiving.</p>
        <p>That becomes evident when Robertson addresses his charges, with names like Aram, Razmik, Sarkis, Su Chin, Pierre and Angela. The classroom, a typical one in the new California, is filled with immigrant children from Soviet Armenia, Mexico, El Salvador, Korea and Hong Kong, plus a few Americans. At the rear, a Filipino-American teacher's aide, Nanette Morales, prepares to help Armenian and Korean children learn English.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON A LEAFY SIDE STREET IN THE Los Angeles suburb of Glendale, parents and children are playing out the American ritual of going back to school. The youngsters, still adjusting to the unfamiliar surroundings of classes at the Columbus Elementary School, clutch glossy new textbooks. About 30 of them file into John Robertson's fifth-grade classroom, where the walls are decorated with Presidential portraits, diagrams of the 50 states and Navajo sand drawings. From all appearances, a traditional setting. But appearances are deceiving.</p>
        <p>That becomes evident when Robertson addresses his charges, with names like Aram, Razmik, Sarkis, Su Chin, Pierre and Angela. The classroom, a typical one in the new California, is filled with immigrant children from Soviet Armenia, Mexico, El Salvador, Korea and Hong Kong, plus a few Americans. At the rear, a Filipino-American teacher's aide, Nanette Morales, prepares to help Armenian and Korean children learn English.</p>
        <p>It is Robertson's task to bring these mostly foreign-born youngsters into the American fold, and one of his main tools is the new blue textbook that each child carries. It is entitled "America Will Be," and is one of a series of new schoolbooks published by the Houghton Mifflin Company. Robertson directs the children to start reading a literature selection from the book -- a Cherokee Indian version of the tortoise and the hare fable.</p>
        <p>These youngsters and Robertson are at the front edge of a revolution in the teaching of history and social studies, one that has been building in many states for years but has reached its fullest flower in California. Four years ago, the state Board of Education adopted a history and social studies "framework," or curriculum, devised by a team that included Charlotte Crabtree, a professor of education at U.C.L.A., and Diane Ravitch, an Assistant Secretary of Education who was then an adjunct professor of history and education at Teachers College, Columbia University. It then invited publishers to submit a series of textbooks based on the new framework.</p>
        <p>By all accounts, it was an intimidating invitation. The framework called for stretching the study of world and American history to three years each, introduced social studies into the earliest grades, restored the study of religion as a key factor in world history, emphasized history as a dramatic chronicle to be taught as "a story well told," reintroduced literature in historical instruction and fully integrated geography with history. And it demanded that the public schools "accurately portray the cultural and racial diversity of our society" while emphasizing the "centrality of Western civilizations as the source of American political institutions, laws and ideology."</p>
        <p>The new books are the most visible product yet of this campaign to inject new life and relevance into the teaching of history. The express purpose of the undertaking is to force a sharp reversal of the decades-old trend of watering down textbooks to avoid controversy and appeal to the widest possible market.</p>
        <p>And where the history is spicier, controversy is sure to follow, as was evident at the San Francisco School Board's public hearing on the books this June at the Everett Middle School. As the packed meeting got under way, most people stood for the Pledge of Allegiance. Indians, Chinese Americans, blacks, Hispanic Americans, Jews, Christians and Muslims all fell silent, placed hands over hearts and intoned "One nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all."</p>
        <p>But the raucous hearing that followed was anything but indivisible. In four and a half hours of shouting, a parade of speakers stepped before the microphone to denounce the books. Mary R. Hoover, professor of black studies at San Francisco State University, asserted that the new books distorted the history of blacks and other minorities "so Europe could be celebrated."</p>
        <p>Christina Edwards, a lecturer in American Indian Studies at San Francisco State, introduced herself with the Lakota name of Cungleska Lutawin, and complained that the third-grade book trivialized Indian history. "It reduces our sun dance and medicine dance to a toilet-paper project," she said. She drew cheers when she envisioned the uproar that would follow if children were asked to make a crucifix out of two Popsicle sticks and a clay Christ figure daubed with ketchup.</p>
        <p>A smaller number of witnesses stood to defend the books as better than anything ever before available to youngsters. They were jeered.</p>
        <p>While its critics have been numerous and vociferous, the project has enjoyed the forceful support of California's pugnacious Superintendent of Public Instruction, Bill Honig. In an interview in his office in Sacramento, Honig stoutly defended the framework against what he calls "the victimization crew," the "tribalists" and "separatists" in universities who "make a livelihood on discrediting broader cultural ideas."</p>
        <p>And despite widespread complaints about its purported insensitivities to minorities, subtle and not-so-subtle stereotyping and outright biases, the California framework has begun to make wide ripples across American education. With 3.7 million pupils in grades kindergarten through eighth, California represents 11 percent of the $1.7 billion national market for school texts. Already the texts tailored to the California curriculum are beginning to be adopted elsewhere, in West Virginia, Indiana, Arkansas and Oregon, as well as Newark and Dubuque, Iowa.</p>
        <p>The process by which these books were written, debated, adopted, amended and refined sheds light on the enormous complexity and political contentiousness of teaching history in this polyglot country. It is a debate that has gained urgency in New York and many other ethnically diverse states but nowhere more than in California. By the turn of the century, according to various projections, well under half the children of California will be "Anglos," or people of European origin, and more than a third will be Hispanic and one in eight Asian.</p>
        <p>The question for educators and parents is this: Can these children, from the earliest school years, be exposed to the full diversity of cultures and traditions that make up the United States and still arrive at the conclusion that we are united by ideals, bonds and legal instruments that support the national motto, E pluribus unum, or "Out of many, one"?</p>
        <p>Alternatively, are those common ideals, and the immigrant-absorption model on which they are based, fundamentally white European formulations that have excluded and failed the people of color whose ancestors came not in steamers from Europe but in shackles from Africa or, in the case of Indians, were here long before Columbus?</p>
        <p>SINCE THE 1978 PASSAGE OF Proposition 13, which limited the taxing authority of local governments, California schools have turned increasingly to the state government for money, greatly enhancing the power of the state board and the Superintendent of Public Instruction. California is one of 22 "adoption" states, in which the state government reviews books for statewide use. While local districts are not obliged to buy the state-approved books, they must spend 70 percent of the $28.90 a year the state supplies for textbooks for each pupil on the approved books. Their alternative is to seek a waiver or put the money aside for future spending on state-approved books. California has been using this considerable power in recent years to promote its new approach to teaching history.</p>
        <p>Indeed, when the Glendale fifth graders opened their new history books, they unwittingly marked the end of a lengthy process that began even before California formally adopted the new framework in 1987. And closely watching the California process from the very beginning were representatives of Ligature Inc., a small company based in Chicago and Boston that specializes in textbook development.</p>
        <p>Ligature and companies like it develop an idea for a book, engage the authors and then seek a partnership with a publisher. By 1987, Ligature, headed by co-owners Stuart J. Murphy and Richard M. Anderson, had already produced an outline for a history series and chosen three authors: Gary B. Nash, professor of history at the University of California at Los Angeles, a leading academic proponent of "multicultural ism"; Christopher L. Salter, chairman of the geography department at the University of Missouri, and a crusader for geography education, and Beverly J. Armento, the director of the Center for Business and Economic Education at Georgia State University, and an expert in teaching economics to elementary-school children.</p>
        <p>After California announced the adoption of the new framework, Houghton Mifflin, with no existing history series and, thus, no investment to protect, quickly contracted with Ligature to produce the books. Calculating that the California market alone could yield sales of $52.9 million, the company provided more than half the working capital of $20 million. It also brought in a fourth author, Karen K. Wixson, professor of education at the University of Michigan, who is an expert on reading pedagogy.</p>
        <p>The books' developers relied heavily on the latest visual techniques, according to Ligature's Murphy. "Some kids are visual learners," he says. "We attempted to give kids a real capability to learn from maps, variations in color." Whereas previous textbooks usually used pictorial material as decoration to break up blocks of text, these books often use it to deliver the main message.</p>
        <p>To show children that history is not just a lot of dates, the books make extensive use of features like "A Moment in Time," a vivid full-page drawing of some typical person in history -- like an 18th-century Parisian market woman in a muddy skirt, a 10th-century crusader in chain mail, a 19th-century Cherokee mother and son. "Not one page was done without a designer, writer and editor sitting together," Nash says.</p>
        <p>Critics and admirers alike agree that the new books are superior to the soporific history texts used by generations of American students. Never before have elementary-school texts made such an effort to include the broad sweep of history and the divergent cultures that flow into the American mainstream. The series consists of one book for each grade from first to eighth, and a separate fourth-grade book for six other states, including California. Each is filled with colorful charts, graphs, time lines, maps and photographs in a format suggestive of the newspaper USA Today.</p>
        <p>The first three grades depart from the traditional practice of focusing on the family in the first grade, neighborhood in the second and the larger community in the third. Instead, the first-grade text ranges from the school, to town and country, city and suburb and "all around the big world," including a train trip across Canada. As an exercise, students write a letter to a cousin in Mexico.</p>
        <p>The second-grade book focuses on family and citizenship, celebrating American institutions like the Presidency. But it also branches out, discussing Cambodian immigrants and people like Roberto Clemente, the Puerto Rican baseball star and humanitarian who died in an airplane crash while trying to deliver relief supplies to earthquake victims in Central America. The third-grade book takes children across the American continent, a geographical excursion that touches on rivers, forests, Pilgrims, prairie dogs, Indians, farmers and steelworkers.</p>
        <p>The California version traces the state's history from pre-Columbian Indians to modern-day smog problems. The national volume offers a broader view of the American land, touching on different regions, and detailing the development of highways and factories. The fifth-grade book traces American history from the Indians to early 20th-century industrialization.</p>
        <p>In the sixth grade, children are given their first introduction to the ancient world, including Mesopotamia, Egypt, China, Greece, India and Rome. The seventh grade continues this journey, explaining the slave trade in the Kongo (the non-Anglicized spelling of Congo) and early American civilizations like the Mayas. And finally, the eighth-grade books bring all this together into a chronicle of the American experience from the early European settlement to the Bush Presidency.</p>
        <p>The series tries to correct the traditionally Eurocentric views of older texts. For example, the fifth-grade book (entitled "America Will Be," after a Langston Hughes poem) covers early American history and plunges students into the American ethnic rainbow with devices like a two-page color spread of different kinds of bread: pita for Greeks and Syrians, matzoh for Jews, corn bread for Indians, tortillas for Mexican and Central American Indians and so on.</p>
        <p>The fifth-grade volume devotes roughly 50 pages to slavery in the South, with vivid, firsthand descriptions of its cruelty, and contains fairly frank treatment of the brutality visited on American Indians by European settlers. Among the primary sources quoted are Olaudah Equiano (an African slave), Abigail Adams, Marco Polo, Black Hawk and Jane Addams, the founder of Hull House. It quotes the writings of an escaped slave, the Rev. Josiah Henson, who described his mother, on her knees, begging the man who had just bought her to buy her baby too; she was kicked senseless.</p>
        <p>The seventh-grade book, "Across the Centuries," devotes 51 pages to the history of Sub-Saharan Africa, tracing the Bantu migration, the rise of the Zimbabwe State and the Kongo Kingdom. It also covers Asian, pre-Columbian American and other civilizations, as well as Europe in the Renaissance, Reformation and the ages of colonialism and imperialism.</p>
        <p>The fourth-grade book, "Oh, California," on the state's history, tries to describe the cruelties the Spanish mission system visited on the Indians of California. The books sometimes go to amusing lengths to achieve political correctness. The fourth-grade book has a full-page picture of a "vaquera" -- a Mexican cowgirl -- at a rodeo in 1820.</p>
        <p>IN THE SPRING OF 1990, nine publishers submitted entries to the state board's Curriculum Commission, which set up three panels of teachers to evaluate them. Only Houghton Mifflin offered books for all grades through eighth. In the end, the commission approved just the Houghton Mifflin series and a single eighth-grade entry from Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston Inc., "The Story of America: Beginnings to 1914." But it insisted upon certain changes, which started a process known in publishing jargon as "corrigenda," literally a list of errors to be corrected before publication.</p>
        <p>For example, the original fifth-grade book credited John Wesley Powell with being the first person to lead a group the length of the Grand Canyon. That was changed to read that he was the first white person to do so, since Indians had traveled the route for centuries. And some changes were made to accommodate Muslim sensibilities. They deleted three pictures of Mohammed -- in Islam, literal images of Mohammed are considered blasphemous -- and a suggestion in the teacher's manual to have children impersonate Mohammed and his family, suggesting instead that they interview a Muslim scholar.</p>
        <p>Other changes were made to avoid misinterpretations. For instance, a sixth-grade lesson on the life of Jesus and the rise of Christianity was originally titled "An Age of Transition." To Jewish groups, this implied that Judaism was just a way station to Christianity. The lesson is now called "Religious Developments."</p>
        <p>But the commission rebuffed numerous demands that it delete unhappy events or blemishes in history. "The purpose of history cannot be to expunge all such episodes from this record in the mistaken interest of filiopietism or children's self-esteem, but instead must be to help children to learn from them," the commission stated in its formal recommendations to the state board, which accepted the books last October.</p>
        <p>THE PUBLISHERS WERE stunned by the bitterness of the protest that surrounded the process of public hearings and comment. That debate has now filtered down to nearly every one of the state's school districts, and even to every school in decentralized districts like Los Angeles Unified. Given little choice, most local boards have accepted the new books, with the notable exceptions of Oakland and Ravenswood City, a heavily minority school district in East Palo Alto. In those areas, they were rejected as insufficiently multicultural.</p>
        <p>The debate this summer in San Francisco, where minorities make up 83 percent of the student population, typifies the controversy surrounding the books. While the school board ultimately voted 5 to 1 for adoption -- joining the approximately 600 of California's 1,016 school districts that had approved the texts by Labor Day -- it did so with no great enthusiasm. And it tacked on a lengthy supplementary reading list that included such titles as "Black Heroes of the Wild West," "Chinese Americans, Past and Present" and "Gays in America."</p>
        <p>Even supplementary reading, however, is unlikely to placate all the critics, who understandably focus on religion and race issues as particularly problematic. Jewish groups complain about what they see as invidious comparisons between Judaism and Christianity. In one sentence about Jews, for example, the sixth-grade book refers to "their god," with a lower-case "g." Three paragraphs later, discussing Christianity, the text refers to "a vision from God."</p>
        <p>Muslims say they would like to see more pictures of people and fewer of camels when their religion is discussed. "When it comes to Islam, there are virtually no people," says Shabbir Mansuri, director of the Council of Islamic Education, based in Tustin. "The faces of real people disappear in the text. There is no relevance to the student. They will come away thinking this is a religion that does not deal with the rational thinking of the modern day, the religion of the terrorists."</p>
        <p>Critics also have attacked the treatment of the Spanish missions in California, citing passages like this one in the fourth-grade texts about Father Junipero Serra: "Father Serra would also teach the Indians farming skills and trade crafts so that they would be able to support themselves." The Indians had no trouble getting by before Father Serra destroyed their culture, critics note sarcastically.</p>
        <p>And many opponents say the books, for all their improvements over past materials, remain essentially, if unintentionally, racist. One of the most determined of these critics is Joyce E. King, director of teacher education at Santa Clara University, who was a dissenting member of the state Curriculum Development and Supplemental Materials Commission that approved the books.</p>
        <p>She cites the sixth-grade book's treatment of the early development of human culture, starting two million years ago with Homo habilis on the plains of eastern Africa. The original version of the text urged children to imagine themselves there as "two naked dark-skinned people walk down to the lake not far from you. . . . You point to your open mouth to show them you are hungry. . . . One person walks off toward a field. . . . Soon the first person returns with a bloody bone. . . . They invited you to eat the red marrow oozing from the bone." (After complaints, the published version omitted the words "dark-skinned," "bloody" and "oozing.") Three pages later, the text moves forward to 12,011 B.C. and shows a Cro-Magnon man, a handsome clean-shaven fellow in buckskins. A few pages farther on, the text says, "In terms of physical features, the Cro-Magnons looked like people today."</p>
        <p>King, who is black, finds that objectionable, saying it draws unfavorable comparisons between the savage Homo habilis of Africa and the clean-shaven Cro-Magnon of Europe. "The chapter begins with an imaginary excursion to Africa," she says. "Then three pages later we have a shaved white guy near a cave in France. That juxtaposition was problematic. They deleted 'dark-skinned,' but those kinds of problems cannot be fixed. We are putting these books in the hands of children who already have stereotypes."</p>
        <p>She also criticizes sections on slavery, saying they depict slaves as animals devoid of human thoughts and emotions, and the black migration to the northern cities and the ghetto life they met there. "The discussion of the experiences of African Americans in the urban North perpetuates a negative stereotype of black life," she says. "Black ghettos appear to be just naturally crime-ridden and dirty."</p>
        <p>THE STARKEST paradox of the tempest aroused by the books is that the principal historian, Nash of U.C.L.A., is a man with impeccable left-liberal credentials. His books, "Red, White, and Black: The Peoples of Early America" and "Forging Freedom: The Formation of Philadelphia's Black Community," have been widely admired by black and American Indian scholars. That Nash, who is white, should now be painted as a racist is a source of considerable frustration and pain to him. "If I'm the bad guy," he asks, "who are your allies?"</p>
        <p>California casual in a sweatsuit one recent morning, Nash spreads the books over his dining-room table in the affluent Pacific Palisades section of Los Angeles. Nash counters the criticism about the Spanish missions by pointing out that the books also describe the whippings and other cruelties suffered by Indians at the hands of Father Serra. He concedes some of King's points but stoutly defends the overall treatment of African history and slavery.</p>
        <p>"I had never heard of the Bantu migration and the rise of the Zimbabwe state when I got my Ph.D. at Princeton," he says. "We have 80 pages on African history for 12-year-olds. This is what bugs me. Joyce King and other critics will not take notice of this and continue to say this is a Eu rocentric series."</p>
        <p>Some critics have said the books should have omitted contemporary Southern arguments in favor of slavery. "I am not willing to make concessions on this," Nash says. "The Southern arguments are so patently false -- the kids see this." He argues that the eighth-grade book offers as harsh a portrait of slavery as ever given in an elementary text, reprinting lengthy passages from the powerful autobiography of Frederick Douglass, an escaped slave. "I do not think anyone reading this would think this trivializes slavery," he says.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Nash argues, the issue comes down to the political one of whose vision of America one accepts. "You can turn American history into a story of unremitting oppression of exploited minorities," he said. "That's just as distorted as the old view." Nash, at least, clings to the optimistic notion that all Americans can find common ground in the "ongoing struggle for greater equality and social justice -- this society sooner or later must be what it says it intends to be."</p>
        <p>This is where the books come under the toughest ideological attack from critics who argue that the immigrant model marginalizes people of color. Chief among them is a Jamaican woman, Sylvia Wynter, who holds a joint appointment in African and Afro-American Studies and Spanish and Portuguese at Stanford University. Her lengthy critique of the fifth-grade book, "America Will Be," argues that it tends to equate the prejudice once experienced by white immigrants from Europe with the racism suffered by black, brown and yellow peoples, thereby justifying their exploitation.</p>
        <p>What is needed, she wrote in a commentary to the state Curriculum Commission, is an entirely new framework that "seeks to go beyond the model of a nation-state coterminous only with Euro-immigrant America, to one coterminous as a 'world' civilization, with all its peoples: and therefore, for the first time in recorded history, coterminous (as a land that's not been yet but yet must be) with humankind."</p>
        <p>State Superintendent Honig bristles at such arguments. "They do not like the idea of common democratic principles," he says. "It gets in the way of their left point of view that this country is corrupt. This country has been able to celebrate pluralism but keep some sense of the collective that holds us together. Everything is not race, gender or class. The whole world cannot be seen just through those glasses.</p>
        <p>"Democracy has certain core ideas -- freedom of speech, law, procedural rights, the way we deal with each other," Honig continues. "If everything becomes hostile race and class warfare, we are going to lose this country. The issue is not multiculturalism. We agree with that. The question is, Are you also going to talk about the political and moral values that are essential for us to live together?"</p>
        <p>THE BOOKS ARE MOSTLY welcomed by teachers and students in schools districts that have been testing the books for the last year. At the Oak Hills Elementary School in Agoura, a suburb about 40 miles northwest of Los Angeles, the principal, Anthony W. Knight, calls them balanced and, more important, interesting to children. "The old methods of social studies were clearly boring to children," he says.</p>
        <p>One fifth-grade teacher, Enid Miller, says many of her pupils were startled to learn from the texts that they were</p>
        <p>all</p>
        <p>immigrants. She had them interview their own families, and the class became what she called a "tapestry" of different ethnic groups -- Iranian, Israeli, Chinese, Korean and Indian, among many others.</p>
        <p>She says the chapters on slavery and the treatment of American Indians made a particularly strong impression on her students. "They are very sensitive," she says. "They feel outraged when they see what it really entailed." The Oak Park Unified School District recently adopted the books with little if any protest.</p>
        <p>The visuals and graphics earn universal acclaim. In Tustin, a bedroom suburb in Orange County, 11 teachers piloted the book last year. One spring morning at the Currie Middle School, Sue Kraus's sixth-grade class was working on a crossword puzzle about the ancient Israelites. The pupils seemed genuinely absorbed. "It explains everything better, like daily life and religion, so you have a better idea of what things looked like," says Sarah Angle, a student.</p>
        <p>Sheralin Conkey, a seventh-grade teacher at the Hewes Middle School in Tustin, says she jumped directly to the chapters about Islam and the Middle East when American troops went to Saudi Arabia last fall. "I found the book so much more detailed and comprehensive than the others," she says. "This book had two chapters on Islam and even went into the Shiites and the Sunnis and the lines of succession from Mohammed."</p>
        <p>But the reception has been rougher in heavily minority districts, most notably the Oakland Unified School District -- 91 percent minority, mainly black (57 percent) and with a dropout rate of about 35 percent. Despite some reservations, the teachers and administration recommended adoption. "They were not perfect, but they were much better than what we had been using," said Robert L. Newell, associate superintendent for the division of instruction.</p>
        <p>But in June the seven-member school board decisively rejected the books. "Almost 92 percent of our students are persons of color," said one board member, Toni R. Cook, who is black. "These books did very little for those children. We have 74 languages spoken in our schools. This is what the 21st century will be like.</p>
        <p>"It's important for youngsters to see themselves," Cook insists. "How do we balance what they see on TV, lots of violence and crime. Their self-esteem is way down. They are portrayed as Willie Hortons. Oakland's challenge is how to truly have a multicultural curriculum. Ninety-one percent of our children are not European. How do we best excite them to the learning process?"</p>
        <p>Two weeks into the school year, however, many Oakland youngsters weren't seeing anything. Parents, educators and activists still had not agreed on a new curriculum, and many students faced the new year without any textbooks at all.</p>
        <p>THE ISSUES THAT have been raised by multicultural education have rubbed the rawest nerves, even in an America that is fundamentally pluralistic. A sharp debate broke out in New York State in late June over a paper prepared by a special panel for the State Commissioner of Education, Thomas Sobol, that urged a new curriculum that de-emphasizes the centrality of European thought and influence in the American experience. Noisy dissent came from some members of the panel, especially the historian Arthur Schlesinger Jr., who complained that "Europhobia" and a "cult of ethnicity" were turning America into a "quarrelsome splatter of enclaves."</p>
        <p>The problem, in the view of Laurie Olsen, a former history teacher who is now with California Tomorrow, an educational group that develops and runs programs to deal with the increasingly multi-ethnic nature of California, is not the texts themselves. Rather, she says, it is "how polarized we are, how much fear there is about diversity, and how the schools have become the battleground." Lewis H. Butler, an Assistant Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare in the Nixon Administration and now chairman of California Tomorrow, says the whole episode has been a "rather sad event" that pits white liberals against black and Indian scholars. "People who thought they were good guys found themselves bad guys, called racists or separatists," he says.</p>
        <p>If the concept of the melting pot is outdated, what is to replace it? History, some say, is a kind of property whose owner controls the future. From that perspective, the future in California still belongs, however tenuously, to the proponents of traditional Western values. The current debate suggests, however, that an increasingly polyglot America has yet to come to grips with the full depth of its diversity.</p>
        <p>Robert Reinhold is Los Angeles bureau chief of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Reinhold is Los Angeles bureau chief of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
