<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yugoslavia Catching East Europe's Political Fever</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="318936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="UPHEAVAL IN THE EAST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D71E3DF932A15752C0A966958260" item-length="1791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yugoslavia Catching East Europe's Political Fever</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia, Jan. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For months, this nation of scrappy and independent burghers and farmers watched calmly as other East European nations swept away in anger the Communist systems that unlike the one here were imposed by Moscow.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For months, this nation of scrappy and independent burghers and farmers watched calmly as other East European nations swept away in anger the Communist systems that unlike the one here were imposed by Moscow.</p>
        <p>For months, this nation of scrappy and independent burghers and farmers watched calmly as other East European nations swept away in anger the Communist systems that unlike the one here were imposed by Moscow.</p>
        <p>Then, a month ago, that vision shattered as the Rumanian revolution erupted. Now Yugoslav Communists and their opponents agree that in this nation with a long history of civil strife, a fear of a violent anti-Communist backlash has suddenly grown.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Yugoslavia had stood up to the Soviets four decades earlier, and party bosses here, used to tinkering with Communism, seemed convinced that even in these days of change the country's home-grown system could be adjusted slowly by Communist guides.</p>
        <p>But after stunned Yugoslavs watched round-the-clock television broadcasts from Rumania and saw a neighbor they knew well rise up and execute its dictator and jail other Communist leaders, a high party official was moved to say: ''Rumania was the turning point here. Now there is a sense of panic. Rumania suddenly made the possibility of violence and revenge very real.''</p>
        <p>Others who agree quickly note that Yugoslavia's lenient form of Communism is not comparable to Rumania's long rule of terror. But even Communist Party officials now express unease that Yugoslavia, long the maverick and most reform-minded Communist nation, is left with tiny, hermetic Albania as the only countries west of the Soviet Union where one-party Communist rule has remained untouched.</p>
        <p>Communists Fear Backlash</p>
        <p>Fear of anti-Communist backlash here has now propelled even conservative Communist leaders to scramble and rally behind the slogans for broad democratic change. Party bosses who even two months ago said they had no intention of giving up the Communist commanding role in setting policy now openly call for a multiparty system and a full market economy. In private conversations, committed Communists say the party needs to find ''a decent way'' to surrender or share power as soon as possible.</p>
        <p>How and when those changes will be made is a focal point of the crucial three-day party conference that opened today in Belgrade. Hard-liners blocked immediate adoption of a document that backs free elections and a multiparty system and proclaims the party's readiness to give up its guaranteed grip on power. [Page 16.]  But more than ideology, what obsesses many delegates is the question of whether the old, passionate rivalry among Yugoslavia's ethnic groups may tear apart the Communist Party or even the nation.</p>
        <p>As political controls have eased and the economic crisis deepened, the recurrent ethnic antagonisms have sharpened. In recent weeks party bosses from Croatia, Serbia and Slovenia, the most powerful of the six republics, have been openly hostile to one another. A widely held view is that some regional party bosses, as they maneuver for survival, are using and even fueling the ethnic conflicts to enhance their power and popularity.</p>
        <p>Boost to Opposition And Entrepreneurs</p>
        <p>The unexpected, staggering sight of change in Rumania has given a sudden boost of confidence to political opponents and entrepreneurs who had been mobilizing cautiously in the months before the upheaval in Eastern Europe. Around the country, reports show that the malaise and boredom that came with the litany of unfulfilled promises are turning into political fever.</p>
        <p>In the last weeks, a handful of opposition groups have suddenly bolted from the Communists into more than 30 organizations that are technically still illegal. They are organizing parties along Europe's Christian Democratic or Social Democratic lines, or groups to protect the environment and to promote Croatian citizens' rights.</p>
        <p>The press, which was never altogether muzzled, but long obedient to Communist directives, is producing a cascade of interviews with dissidents, accounts from ghastly prisons, stories of corruption.</p>
        <p>The three most-read books in recent weeks are memoirs of former political prisoners, reportedly selling more than 40,000 copies each, a rare sight in a country where books not officially recommended often have a circulation of two or three thousand.</p>
        <p>Even the figure of Tito, long above ideological reproach as a cross between Yugoslavia's superman and national treasure, is increasingly the target of scathing analysis as the 10th anniversary of his death approaches.</p>
        <p>There are other unexpected changes coming from the top. Christmas, long anathema even in Yugoslavia's flexible Communist model, has become a holiday for the first time since 1945. In fact, it was so openly and deliberately celebrated, with the messages of Catholic bishops and Orthodox patriarchs so prominently projected onto front pages and in television broadcasts that even adherents looked for a hidden meaning. Could it be a sign of hostility toward Yugoslavia's Muslim minority, some people asked.</p>
        <p>Deep Divisions Persist Despite Communist Rule</p>
        <p>Forty-five years of Communist rule, it appears, has done little to soften the deep divisions in the unmelted pot of cultural, ethnic and religious groups. Rather, the differences remain so pervasive that they seem to affect or overwhelm every issue.</p>
        <p>Ask a Yugoslav where she or he comes from and the chances are that the answer begins around the seventh century when the Slavs arrived from Russia. A Croatian will then wax on about the first Croatian kingdom of the ninth century, a Serb will become eloquent on the late medieval kingdom of Serbia. A short cut will begin in 1918 when Yugoslavia was formed as a multinational state, joining more than a dozen ethnic groups with three religions and four principal languages. Except for brief intervals, they never stopped quarreling.</p>
        <p>Today the six republics have equal rights but deeply unequal levels of development. A formidable frontier divides the Roman Catholic, pro-European north from a more inward-looking and poorer Eastern Orthodox and Muslim south.</p>
        <p>The dispute among Albanians and Serbs, Serbs and Croatians and several other permutations proves to be a major handicap today, even as thousands of Yugoslavs are busy organizing, collecting signatures for new parties and setting their sights on an open democracy. Regional loyalties keep opposition groups divided across the country and appear to make impossible the emergence of any movement or candidate with whom a majority of Yugoslavs can identify. This country has no Solidarity movement, there is no Walesa, no Havel.</p>
        <p>The President of Serbia, Slobodan Milosevic has gained wide support at home but caused deep distrust and even hatred elsewhere by stirring Serbian nationalism and re-establishing control over the two autonomous provinces of Kosovo and Vojvodina.</p>
        <p>Another nationalist group wants to restore the realm of Great Serbia, redrawing the old borders and advocating the deportation of ethnic Albanians to Albania.</p>
        <p>Serbs have the same rights and voting powers as citizens of other republics of the federation, but like Russians they feel they are the first among equals as the center of the nation, with the largest population and the heart to which other states were attached.</p>
        <p>Croats and Slovenes Demand Major Changes</p>
        <p>The problem comes into focus in Zagreb, the capital of Croatia, where the fastest-growing and best-organized group is the Croatian Democratic Union, which has national aspirations equal to those of Serbs.</p>
        <p>Last week, its headquarters, a sober and low wooden building, was buzzing with people coming and going, bundled up against the raw January wind. Inside, party workers were writing bulletins and putting out the latest copy of their magazine called Glasnik, or Messenger. The group, which says it is comparable to Christian Democrats, has received contributions from Croats in the United States, Australia and Europe.</p>
        <p>''Our main goal is to restore the values of Croatia,'' said Josip Manolic, a former Communist official and one of the party leaders, ''the Catholic religion, the family, the culture of Croatia, which the Communists tried to take away from us.'' Croats, he continued, ''like Greeks and Celts, are the oldest people of Europe and should be preserved. We are against our women aborting.''</p>
        <p>Franjo Tudman, the party president, has taken this view of Croatian growth one step further. In a speech, he said that people who helped Croatian women abort were ''traitors'' against Croatia.</p>
        <p>In Slovenia, Communists and democrats have said they want a separate status within the republic. They resent the use of their foreign exchange to prop up an inefficient bureaucracy and the poor southern regions. Last month, the republican assembly voted itself the right to secede.</p>
        <p>''Our intention is not to secede,'' said Peter Bekes, the information director of Slovenia's Communist Party, ''but to pressure for democratic changes.''</p>
        <p>Only two organizations, the Social Democrats and the Association for Democratic Initiatives, have succeeded in reaching across Yugoslavia's internal borders. In the republics of Bosnia-Herzegovina, Macedonia and Montenegro, new groups are organizing along local interest lines.</p>
        <p>Stalemated Republics And Western Ideas</p>
        <p>Since 1974, republican party bosses have run their regions as competing nations. With each republic holding the right of veto, federal decisions became enormously lengthy and sometimes impossible.</p>
        <p>''This system means that Montenegro, with 2.5 percent of the population, has the same federal weight as Serbia, with 38 percent,'' said Alexander Prlja, Serbia's Foreign Minister. ''It's a diabolical system to keep Serbia down.''</p>
        <p>For different reasons, others, including non-Serbians, are also planning for a stronger federal government. They say it is the only way for Yugoslavia to function as a more efficient and market-oriented nation.</p>
        <p>The encroachment of Western thought is measured in large and small gestures. The northern city of Llubljana, reformers hastened to say, is starting the nation's first stock exchange. New rules have spurred new restaurants, stores and small workshops, most of them founded by Yugoslav emigrants to the West, who have the funds and the skills to do business.</p>
        <p>There is talk of closing inefficient factories, the need to lay off perhaps as many as one million workers. The talk of change, though, appears not to inspire many young people.</p>
        <p>Political parties have not attracted them. This week, a group of students gave their views in the university library at Zagreb. ''Politics is completely useless,'' said Suna Petrovic. ''It's how old people waste their time. Said Gordan Horvat: ''Most of us want to leave the country. We have no money. There will still be Communists. They live here. It would be easier if they were foreigners.''</p>
        <p>UPHEAVAL IN THE EAST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
