<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BLACKS In ART;   Art as a Decoding Exercise</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="318705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSHLER, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D81139F932A15752C0A966958260" item-length="365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BLACKS In ART;   Art as a Decoding Exercise</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Although I'm sympathetic to the exhibition based on the black image in American art, I believe that Mr. McElroy's formulation of the relationship between art and politics is invalid.</p>
        <p>He asserts that ''all art is by nature a political statement,'' but he does not show how this must be true for ''all art,'' nor does he say how he defines and detects what this ''nature'' is. Instead, his supporting argument is that ''it represents a way of life in society primarliy as seen by the majority culture.'' Mr. McElroy and the other authorities cited apprently see works of art as representations that must be ''decoded.'' The public cannot turn with confidence to these experts, though, because they disagree amongst themselves and are evidently writing only for each other in any case. But surely the reasons why one looks at art must include such matters as form, composition, color, and the way an artist interprets rather than simply represents reality; I am not convinced that such factors are less important than the denotative aspect of painting. Furthermore, the reality painted may be abstract; would such paintings be dismissed as mere escapism because they avoid overt political content?</p>
        <p>I believe that Mr. McElroy means to say that all works of art can be viewed from a political standpoint. No one can argue with this formulation, which avoids overwrought statements about the nature of ''all art.'' From a political viewpoint, some works of art will probably seem more significant than others, and perhaps some will not seem significant at all (and with luck may escape the army of academic ''decoders'').</p>
        <p>To claim, however, that viewing works of art from a political standpoint is the most important or insightful way of viewing them is quite another matter. The artistic merit of a work of art would, by most definitions, depend on such factors as the way the medium and the subject are handled.</p>
        <p>The relationship between art and politics is one that needs careful definition. History, some of it quite recent, shows that when politcs intrudes upon art, the results are not beneficial to artists, their works or the public.</p>
        <p>DAVID BUSHLER</p>
        <p>Brooklyn</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
