<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="318658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D91239F932A15752C0A966958260" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>PING CHONG</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>PING CHONG</p>
        <p>PING CHONG</p>
        <p>Ping Chong, the Manhattan installation artist, writer and choreographer, will be in Hartford this week where one of his works of art and one of his theater pieces will be presented at Trinity College.</p>
        <p>His installation, called ''In the Absence of Memory,'' opens tomorrow in the Widener Galler of the college's Austin Arts Center with a reception from 4 to 6 P.M. The artist will give a slide presentation about the piece at 4. It remains on view to Feb. 16.</p>
        <p>Like all his work, ''In the Absence of Memory'' reflects his preoccupation with cultural history and his unconventional approach to the visual. The piece is a floor-to-ceiling light installation in which bits of text appear to be floating on light beams focused across the gallery, accompanied by the sound of running water. As if history were flowing from the ceiling through the floor, the date at the top is 3700 B.C. and the information is of the first reports of domesticated dogs and metal mirrors.</p>
        <p>Other historical data varies from being similarly quirky to darker recollections of atrocities, but all are meant to remind us of what we have forgot or never knew. The gallery is open free of charge from 1 to 5 P.M. daily.</p>
        <p>The theater piece is called ''Kind Ness'' and it received the U.S.A. Playwright's Award in New York after its premiere at La Mama four years ago. A comedy with serious undertones, it takes a gorilla from Rwanda through his experience as a new student in an American school, his subsequent adolescent relationships, and his marriage to a human. The last scene finds the couple visiting the monkey cage at the zoo with their first child.</p>
        <p>Curtain times are 7:30 and 10 P.M. Friday in the J. L. Goodwin Theater of the Arts Center. Tickets are $10, students and the elderly $5. Call 297-2199 for reservations.</p>
        <p>BENEFIT FOR ANIMALS</p>
        <p>Antique furniture, jewelry, china, fireplace equipment, bric-a-brac, glass and collectibles will be displayed by 50 dealers from New York State and New England from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. today in the Roger Ludlowe School on Unquowa Road, Fairfield.</p>
        <p>An admission donation of $2 will help Homeless Animals, a 20-year-old volunteer organization based in Southport to continue its work in feeding, spaying, neutering and caring for abandoned pets at its shelter, until the animals are placed in selected homes. The show is one of two annual fund-raising events.</p>
        <p>MEMORIES OF COPLAND</p>
        <p>Vivian Perlis spent 10 years working with Aaron Copland on his biography, ''Copland: Since 1943,'' published last year by St. Martin's Press. Ms. Perlis will talk about her association with the 89-year-old composer and her interviews with many of his colleagues and friends, including Benny Goodman, Martha Graham, Ned Rorem and Lukas Foss, at noon Wednesday in the Westport Library. Bring lunch; coffee and tea will be available. For more information call 227-8411.</p>
        <p>OUT OF SURREALISM</p>
        <p>''Paul Outerbridge: A Singular Esthetic; Photographs and Drawings 1921-1941,'' the first retrospective of the American artist's work, is on view at the Yale Art Gallery in New Haven until March 4. Outerbridge died in 1954.</p>
        <p>Unlike other American photographers who followed the straight photographic style of Alfred Steiglitz, Outerbridge drew his inspiration from the surrealists, including Man Ray, Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, Max Ernst, Constantin Brancusi and Marcel Duchemp, all of whom he encountered during his years in Europe after World War I. Those associations served him well when he returned to the United States and became a successful commercial photographer in the 1930's.</p>
        <p>More than 50 items in the Yale show contain examples of his painterly compositions of common objects, female nudes and the surreal treatment of objects and individuals that recurred frequently in his work.</p>
        <p>Sheryl Freedland, a graduate student in the history of art will give gallery talks on the exhibition at 2 P.M. on Feb. 6 and at 1 P.M. on Feb. 8. The gallery, at Chapel and York Streets, is open 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Tuesday to Saturday, 2 to 5 P.M. Sunday, and Thursday evenings until 8 P.M. free of charge. Call 432-0600 for more information.</p>
        <p>DECORATIVE ARTS</p>
        <p>When the British destroyed the White House in 1814, one of the less noted results in history was the surge of French influence on the decorative arts in the United States. Lorraine Pearce, who was named curator of the White House by President Kennedy in 1961, will address the subject of ''The French Influence on American Decorative Arts from 1780-1830'' in a talk at 10 A.M. tomorrow in the Bruce Museum in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>According to Mrs. Pearce, President Monroe took an active part in the restoration of the executive mansion and in encouraging the importation of French furnishings and accessories, a preference that was repeated during the Kennedy Administration.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pearce was a Fulbright scholar at the University of Strasbourg and a Winterthur Fellow at the University of Delaware, where she received her master's degree. She wrote the first guidebook on the White House while serving as curator there. Admission to the lecture is $5. Reservations may be made by calling 869-0376.</p>
        <p>CENSORSHIP</p>
        <p>Censorship of controversial art exhibitions and subject matter is the theme of a meeting in Hartford tomorrow of the New England Museum Association of the American Association of Museums. It will be held from 9:30 A.M. to 3 P.M. in the Wadsworth Atheneum.</p>
        <p>Under discussion will be the exhibition of Robert Mapplethorpe photographs that had an extended run at the Atheneum after being withdrawn from the Corcoran Gallery in Washington. Also to be discussed are cuts in Congressional support for the National Endowment for the Arts censorship) and the termination of financial support by the city of Chicago for the Art Institute of Chicago when an American flag included in a student installation was deemed indecorous.</p>
        <p>Admission for members is $20, non-members will be charged $25; the feeincludes lunch. The snow date is Friday. Call 278-2670 for reservations. $90ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
