<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE TRIUMPH OF THE UNOFFICIAL</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="319059"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SVEDE, MARK ALLEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOWN, MATTHEW CULLERNE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONTEMPORARY RUSSIAN ART (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD1530F932A15752C0A966958260" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE TRIUMPH OF THE UNOFFICIAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK ALLEN SVEDE; Mark Allen Svede is a curator who has organized exhibitions of Eastern European art.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SVEDE, MARK ALLEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>CONTEMPORARY RUSSIAN ART</p>
        <p>By Matthew Cullerne Bown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 127 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Philosophical Library. $34.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>CONTEMPORARY RUSSIAN ART</p>
        <p>By Matthew Cullerne Bown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 127 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Philosophical Library. $34.95.</p>
        <p>CONTEMPORARY RUSSIAN ART</p>
        <p>By Matthew Cullerne Bown.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 127 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Philosophical Library. $34.95.</p>
        <p>The recent spate of Soviet art exhibitions in America has occasioned the complaint among some art critics that these shows somehow fail to present a concise sense of Soviet culture today. The unmet expectation is that a country beyond the mainstream of contemporary art might contribute at best a single tributary to the international waters. The British artist Matthew Cullerne Bown, the author of ''Contemporary Russian Art,'' recognizes an opposite effect: the composite nature of the Soviet Union and its remove from the homogenizing West has engendered a multifarious art. Hoping to present a concise survey of diverse developments, Mr. Bown has restricted himself to Russian culture and has attempted to distinguish it from the broader Soviet culture. Consequently, his book, unlike previous efforts to describe Soviet accomplishments in contemporary art, is noteworthy for its defined scope and its achievement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bown concentrates on artists among whom he spent a year working in Moscow and efficiently traces their legacy from pre-Revolutionary and avant-garde art through the reactionary doctrine of Socialist Realism to the present phase in which ''unofficial'' art has transcended official tolerance to become the representative culture. Befitting the psychic and political intensity of his illustrations, his commentary is rapidly paced without rushing his insightful and often poetic elucidations. He anticipates and dispels possible misreadings of Soviet art that are caused by common Western prejudices. In one painting, the cacophonous lettering that surrounds a man asleep before a radio speaker does not indicate an Orwellian brainwashing; it simply serves as an example of the universal information glut. Mr. Bown, however, is unafraid of criticizing the Government's interference in cultural matters as he recounts specific bureaucratic absurdities. However, he also broadly observes, ''Prohibition would sometimes appear to be the mainspring of the Soviet system.''</p>
        <p>He democratically attends to 58 artists, judiciously limiting discussion of painters, like Erik Bulatov and Ilya Kabakov, who have already received extensive coverage in the West. While some of his characterizations of the Russian people may be too encompassing to enhance our understanding of individual artists, this benign art-historical compulsion to determine national traits does structure much of the current literature. More helpfully, Mr. Bown contrasts the Russians' perception of their artistic heritage (the avant-garde) with our Western view, although his observations, like many remarkable anecdotes here, would benefit from footnotes.</p>
        <p>In his preface, Mr. Bown states, ''For all my attempts to narrow the focus of the book, it could never claim to be more than a whistle-stop tour.'' But, thankfully, it can.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
