<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whatever Foie Gras Is for Humans, It's Murder for the Geese</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="490177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIET AND NUTRITION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEART</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNAYER, ERIC (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB103DF93BA15752C1A967958260" item-length="382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whatever Foie Gras Is for Humans, It's Murder for the Geese</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Can Foie Gras Aid the Heart? A French Scientist Says Yes" (front page, Nov. 17) quickly dismisses concerns about the treatment of the ducks and geese. One farmer claims that the process of causing fatty livers in ducks and geese is natural because birds, before migration, develop fatty livers to store energy. She further claims that since her ducks "don't run away from me," she can't be mistreating them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Can Foie Gras Aid the Heart? A French Scientist Says Yes" (front page, Nov. 17) quickly dismisses concerns about the treatment of the ducks and geese. One farmer claims that the process of causing fatty livers in ducks and geese is natural because birds, before migration, develop fatty livers to store energy. She further claims that since her ducks "don't run away from me," she can't be mistreating them.</p>
        <p>These claims hide the facts -- feeding birds for foie gras causes them suffering.</p>
        <p>The development of fatty livers in force-fed ducks and geese is a pathological, not a physiological, process. The diet, largely corn based, is deficient in protein, certain amino acids and other vital nutrients. These nutritional deficiencies prevent the liver from efficiently metabolizing lipids, and fat accumulates. The result is a dysfunctional liver -- four to five times normal size.</p>
        <p>The accumulating fat swells liver cells, and they burst, interfering with normal liver function. Many vital liver functions are disrupted, including detoxification of normal metabolic products. Noxious substances accumulate in the blood, upsetting normal cell function, causing the animal to feel sick and, if untreated, eventually leading to coma and death. The farmer's birds probably don't run away because they are too ill to move.</p>
        <p>In addition, the birds are kept in small pens and deprived of exercise and natural behavior. They are force-fed multiple times a day, which overloads their stomachs and leads to digestive disturbances. These conditions increase stress, and the bird's health further deteriorates.</p>
        <p>The cruelty inherent in foie gras production cannot be justified, even with these dubious health claims. If someone is looking for a diet that will reduce the risk of heart disease, a vegetarian diet is superior. Men and women who are vegetariams have a much lower rate of heart disease than those who eat meat.</p>
        <p>Also, a diet that omits animal fats and cholesterol, and is high in fiber, has been associated with decreased risk of stroke, cancer, adult-onset diabetes, gallstones, osteoporosis. A vegetarian diet has the advantage of being not only healthier, but also cruelty-free. ERIC DUNAYER Doctor of Veterinary Medicine Rockville, Md., Nov. 18, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
