<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuba Blames U.S. in Downing of Planes</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="833019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHINA-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CUBAN-AMERICANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CUBA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CUBA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BROTHERS TO THE RESCUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROHTER, LARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7DA1139F934A15751C0A960958260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuba Blames U.S. in Downing of Planes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROHTER, LARRY</byline>
      <dateline>HAVANA, Feb. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By turns scornful, angry and defiant, the Cuban Government blamed the United  States today for fomenting the incident in which two light planes were shot down over the Straits of Florida on Saturday and accused the Clinton Administration of lying about the attack for political ends.</p>
        <p>At a news conference marked by belligerence and personal insults directed at  Secretary of State Warren Christopher, Ricardo Alarcon, the head of the Cuban Parliament and the country's third-highest official, said Cuba was justified in  attacking the planes to protect its sovereignty. It is not the Government of Fidel Castro that is guilty of terrorist acts, he maintained, but the United States, which has allowed Cuban exile groups to run rampant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By turns scornful, angry and defiant, the Cuban Government blamed the United  States today for fomenting the incident in which two light planes were shot down over the Straits of Florida on Saturday and accused the Clinton Administration of lying about the attack for political ends.</p>
        <p>At a news conference marked by belligerence and personal insults directed at  Secretary of State Warren Christopher, Ricardo Alarcon, the head of the Cuban Parliament and the country's third-highest official, said Cuba was justified in  attacking the planes to protect its sovereignty. It is not the Government of Fidel Castro that is guilty of terrorist acts, he maintained, but the United States, which has allowed Cuban exile groups to run rampant.</p>
        <p>Who is responsible?" he asked. "Us, because we made our laws and rights respected? Or those who, knowing who was violating their own laws and norms, let them enter and leave freely in their airplanes until the day before yesterday?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Alarcon was asked several times about international agreements that prohibit military aircraft from shooting down civilian planes. Each time, he avoided a direct answer, instead responding with attacks on the United States and Cuban exile groups and dismissing as American propaganda any evidence that indicated the planes may have been over international waters.</p>
        <p>If the United States insists on seeking a condemnation of Cuba by the United  Nations Security Council over the incident, Mr. Alarcon said, his Government will point its finger right back at Washington.</p>
        <p>"The great responsibility, along with the perpetrators of this provocation, lies with the irresponsible people who run a Government incapable of making its  own laws respected," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alarcon said Cuban exiles and American officials were lying when they maintained that the aircraft were attacked over international waters, citing as  evidence an American request to look for possible survivors in Cuban waters. He  said debris from the planes had been recovered in Cuban territorial waters, proving that the planes were well within the country's 12-mile territorial limit when they were shot down.</p>
        <p>Cuba had repeatedly complained to the United States about incursions into its airspace by Cuban exile groups flying civilian planes, Mr. Alarcon complained, but has never received a satisfactory response. He said the United States had a  long history of complicity in attacks on Cuban aviation, citing the case of a Cuban exile leader who in the 1970's blew up a Cuban airliner, killing all those on board.</p>
        <p>"Why are we going to perennially tolerate this type of activity?" he asked. The American Government's attitude, he continued, was one "of pure hypocrisy, pure demagoguery."</p>
        <p>Mr. Alarcon's remarks, which lasted for more than an hour and a half, constitute the most comprehensive Cuban Government statement yet on Saturday's attack off the Cuban coast. They came after a Cuban Government statement earlier in the day which seemed to imply that Cuban intelligence had an informer in Brothers to the Rescue, the exile group whose planes were shot down, and had now called him home.</p>
        <p>Tonight, the agent, Juan Pablo Roque, appeared on Cuban television and said the two main leaders of Brothers to the Rescue were longtime agents of the C.I.A. who took part in "terrorist actions in Cuba and Central America." He accused Brothers to the Rescue of organizing efforts to assassinate Mr. Castro,  attack Cuban military bases and power stations and interfere with military radio frequencies.</p>
        <p>In language notable for its lack of diplomatic nuance, Mr. Alarcon, who was formerly Cuba's delegate to the United Nations, accused President Clinton of pandering to Cuban exile groups in Miami. It was "pathetic," he said, to see a Government that aspires to world leadership acting like "a bunch of city councilmen in Hialeah," a Miami suburb whose population is overwhelmingly Cuban-American.</p>
        <p>At several points, Mr. Alarcon argued that the Clinton Administration was acting out of "cheap political motives" aimed at assuring the President's re-election. Cuban exile groups were being allowed to violate American law "because it is convenient to raising funds for the electoral campaign," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alarcon disputed American statements that the three planes attacked on Saturday afternoon were unarmed, saying there was no proof, only American allegations. "Many things can fit in a light plane," he said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Alarcon was speaking, aides handed him a summary of the measures of retribution Mr. Clinton had just announced in Washington. As he read the list out loud, he reacted with a mixture of amusement and contempt to each of the various American actions. "I don't know what else they can freeze," he said with a laugh when he came to a point that suggested the United States intends to use  Cuban funds in American banks to compensate the families of the four fliers who  appeared to have perished in the attack on their planes. "Our funds are already  deep-frozen."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Alarcon's harshest words came in response to the announcement that Washington was placing further restrictions on the movements of Cuban diplomats  in the United States. American diplomats here, he threatened, could be subjected to retribution if they continue their contacts with dissident groups.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
