<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Battle of the Strawberry Fields</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRAWBERRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNIONIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIGRANT LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WATSONVILLE (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED FARM WORKERS OF AMERICA UNITED FARM WORKERS OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RODRIGUEZ, ARTURO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, CAREY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migrant Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unionization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DF1039F930A35754C0A960958260" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Battle of the Strawberry Fields</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, CAREY</byline>
      <dateline>WATSONVILLE, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The strawberry fields stretch as far as the eye can see here, the pickers jackknifed over the low-growing leaves as their knuckles graze through them, their fingers stained a sweet, sticky maroon.</p>
        <p>This is the strawberry capital of the world, where a great strawberry festival is held each June and the nation's biggest growers produce the oversized beauties that get dipped in chocolate and sold in gourmet shops, each  at a price almost equal to what some pickers earn in an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The strawberry fields stretch as far as the eye can see here, the pickers jackknifed over the low-growing leaves as their knuckles graze through them, their fingers stained a sweet, sticky maroon.</p>
        <p>This is the strawberry capital of the world, where a great strawberry festival is held each June and the nation's biggest growers produce the oversized beauties that get dipped in chocolate and sold in gourmet shops, each  at a price almost equal to what some pickers earn in an hour.</p>
        <p>And here, on California's central coast, is where the United Farm Workers union has begun what its officials and independent experts call the biggest organizing campaign now under way in American labor: a drive to unionize all the region's 15,000 strawberry pickers, whom the U.F.W. describes as among the most  exploited workers in the country.</p>
        <p>"If the consumer only realized the horror and pain and suffering that goes into the strawberries they eat so pleasantly," said Arturo Rodriguez, president  of the U.F.W. and son-in-law of the late Cesar Chavez, the legendary farm labor  organizer who helped found the union.</p>
        <p>The drive reflects a new dynamism within the U.F.W. and, if successful, will  swell the union's membership, now 25,000, by 60 percent.</p>
        <p>But it could hardly come at a worse time for the hundreds of strawberry growers in the area, already reeling from recent floods and from warnings in June, later withdrawn, that California strawberries could carry a parasite called cyclospora.</p>
        <p>While the state's largest growers decline to comment on the organizing campaign, they are loudly crying foul at the union's depiction of the $600-million-a-year industry, saying the U.F.W. has found a few bad growers and  smeared all the rest with the same accusations of slave wages, cruel treatment and poor conditions.</p>
        <p>"The rest of the growers are all following the state laws, which are the toughest in the world," said Karen Miller, a Watsonville strawberry farmer with  a relatively large spread of 235 acres. "We're growing and working hard -- but we're the ones they're after."</p>
        <p>State inspectors, who monitor compliance with California standards like a $4.25-an-hour minimum wage and requirements for sanitary drinking water and clean toilets in the fields, agree that working conditions in strawberries are largely no worse than in other crops. But where there are violations, said Jose  Millan, California's assistant labor commissioner, they can seem all the worse,  because the picking of the very fragile strawberry cannot be mechanized like the harvesting of most other crops and so remains especially "backbreaking, arduous manual labor."</p>
        <p>The U.F.W. campaign began last summer and is now shifting into high gear as scores of organizers fan out to the farms of the Salinas and Pajaro Valleys. Already organizers and opponents have come to blows at least once, in an incident that the police attribute to an organizer's use of profanity as he spoke with workers. The propaganda and counterpropaganda is flying in leaflets and at workplace meetings.</p>
        <p>The labor heavyweights are also involved. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. "and all its resources, are 100 percent behind the strawberry campaign," said Karla Garland,  a spokeswoman for the labor federation, to which the U.F.W. belongs.</p>
        <p>"Not just financially, but we're looking to assist them any way we can," said Ms. Garland, who confirmed that the campaign was the biggest now under way in organized labor.</p>
        <p>Though most strawberry growers provide wages that easily meet state standards -- they average $6.11 an hour, according to California government statistics --  and maintain equally decent conditions in work that lasts virtually year round,  accounts of misery are not uncommon.</p>
        <p>On a recent evening, an exhausted Marco Garcia sat in the four-room house in  Salinas he shares with 11 other young men, all pickers, and described having been walloped on the head last year by a steel bar on a truck that carried strawberry crates. The injury still hurts, Mr. Garcia said, but with no medical  insurance, no disability pay and no other recourse, he has gone back to picking  strawberries for $35 per eight-hour day, a rate barely above the minimum wage.</p>
        <p>After a day of picking, the 24-year-old Mr. Garcia said, "my whole head hurts, and I don't see well, and I get very nervous."</p>
        <p>"I can only pick about 35 percent of what I used to," he said. "Sometimes I do something and can't remember it."</p>
        <p>A compatriot from the Mexican state of Hidalgo -- virtually all the pickers are from Mexico -- hiked up his pants to show his rash-covered leg, a collage of pustules and blotches that appeared, he said, after he had started working among the pesticides of the fields here.</p>
        <p>A third man said a rancher known as the meanest around had forced him and other workers to eat the green strawberries that they had erroneously picked, punishment meant to encourage them to pick only ripe berries. A 16-year-old said he earned only $150 a week for six 12-hour days; a 17-year-old said he earned the same, well below the California minimum.</p>
        <p>Yet as they lounged around the living room, redolent of frying tortillas, in  the languor of after-work fatigue -- some leaning against the wall because there were not enough chairs for all of them in the house, for which they pay rent of  $1,000 a month -- they showed no unanimous enthusiasm for the union message that two organizers had brought them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia said he thought a union would make growers respect the workers more, but a housemate pulled out a leaflet he had received at work, a question-and-answer sheet that bore a heavy slash through the letters "U.F.W."</p>
        <p>"We don't need outsiders to solve our problems," the unsigned leaflet said in Spanish, the universal language among pickers here.</p>
        <p>The leaflet also called on workers to heed the fate of a farm that the U.F.W. chose last year for the first unionization vote in the current campaign. After the workers there had voted for union representation, the farm went out of business and plowed under its strawberries in what many workers took as a direct warning that if they voted union, they would lose their jobs altogether.</p>
        <p>The U.F.W. learned a lesson from that, said Mr. Rodriguez, its president, and this year is making a target of the entire industry at once, including the giants that also order, process or ship the berries: Driscoll Strawberry Associates Inc., Well-Pict and Naturipe.</p>
        <p>It is also putting a premium on preparation, not rushing into any new votes despite some pressure from workers and from the change in yields as various fields peak and wane.</p>
        <p>"We need an election soon, because the crops are going down," one worker told Miguel Angel Lopez, a U.F.W. organizer, during a lunchtime field gathering of two dozen pickers. "If we don't do it, the bosses can say, 'We don't need to pick anymore anyway.' "</p>
        <p>The potential pressure on growers, however, appears even greater than that on the organizers. Union officials say they chose to make a target of strawberries  in part because they are so fragile.</p>
        <p>"If they don't pick every two or three days, the fruit is not going to be good," said Efren Barajas, the union's vice president. "So if workers organize,  you can strike and do a lot. Lettuce can last in the field two or three weeks, grapes on vines a month. So that's a pressure point."</p>
        <p>But the union says the main reason it decided on the campaign among the strawberry pickers is that their wages have barely increased during the last decade and that they usually lack medical insurance, grievance procedures and protection against arbitrary dismissal.</p>
        <p>Still, while "there has been a lot of aggressive organizing activity," as of  yet "there are no organized farms," said Teresa Thorne, spokeswoman for the California Strawberry Commission, a quasi-governmental marketing group that promotes the industry.</p>
        <p>The U.F.W. says its efforts are already having a significant effect nonetheless, prompting growers to improve working conditions -- adding more portable toilets, better drinking-water supplies and the like -- pre-emptively.</p>
        <p>"There are lots of improvements, and many companies are giving increases to workers after 10 years, " Mr. Barajas said. "So it's already working."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
