<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GIULIANI ATTACKS RECYCLING GOALS AS A SUIT IS FILED</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS ANDCLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEFFLER, SHELDON (COUNCILMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOY, VIVIAN S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DE1039F930A35754C0A960958260" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GIULIANI ATTACKS RECYCLING GOALS AS A SUIT IS FILED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOY, VIVIAN S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with a lawsuit that charges his administration with violating the city's own recycling law, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani yesterday denounced the goals contained in the law as "absurd" and "irresponsible" and vowed he would work to scale them back.</p>
        <p>"It is impossible to reach a mandated recycling level," Mr. Giuliani said, "unless you take all the people in New York City, put them in prison, and force them to recycle."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with a lawsuit that charges his administration with violating the city's own recycling law, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani yesterday denounced the goals contained in the law as "absurd" and "irresponsible" and vowed he would work to scale them back.</p>
        <p>"It is impossible to reach a mandated recycling level," Mr. Giuliani said, "unless you take all the people in New York City, put them in prison, and force them to recycle."</p>
        <p>5 The Mayor was careful to say that recycling should remain a part of the city's program for dealing with the 30,000 tons of commercial and residential trash generated by New Yorkers every day. But he stressed, as Mayor David N. Dinkins did before him, that meeting the goals set by the 1989 law -- recycling  25 percent, or 4,250 tons a day, of the city's residential garbage -- would cost the cash-strapped city too much money.</p>
        <p>"Recycling is a valuable alternative in a group of other alternatives to deal with waste," Mr. Giuliani said. "It is not a religion. It is not the be-all and  end-all of life." He strongly implied that the city would not agree to comply with a law that the administration considers "impossible."</p>
        <p>"There's a certain theory in the law that says if a law is impossible, you can't follow it," Mr. Giuliani said. "And this law is impossible."</p>
        <p>But Eric A. Goldstein, a senior attorney with the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group, said: "Impossibility is an extremely narrow legal defense. It's only applicable if, for example, a hurricane wiped out the entire fleet of Department of Sanitation trucks."</p>
        <p>The city now recycles about 14 percent, or 2,200 tons a day, of its residential garbage, and in fact has been in violation of the recycling law since 1991. Although the Dinkins and Giuliani administrations both challenged the recycling requirements in court, the goals have been upheld in four court decisions within the last five years.</p>
        <p>In support of his position, the Mayor cited an article in The New York Times  Magazine last Sunday that called recycling a waste of time and money and suggested that the national drive to increase recycling was prompted by an irrational fear that available landfill space was rapidly disappearing. It said  many communities look to landfills as sources of income and economic development.</p>
        <p>Recycling rates grew slowly but steadily from 1989, when New Yorkers first started separating out their bottles, cans and newspapers, until 1993, when the  rate topped out at 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The rate has dropped slightly since, and environmentalists and City Council members are fearful that it will drop even more later in the year when the city  reduces recycling pickups from once a week to once every two weeks in most of New York. That change, which is to go into effect in September, was proposed by the Mayor and approved by the City Council last month as a budget-cutting measure, although many Council members said they would press the Mayor to restore the money.</p>
        <p>With yesterday's comments, Mr. Giuliani laid down a direct challenge to the City Council and to the environmental groups that have fought to enforce the Council's recycling goals.</p>
        <p>"I think the law is absurd," the Mayor said. "The City Council should negotiate a reasonable result here that the city can achieve."</p>
        <p>In response yesterday, Peter F. Vallone, the Council Speaker, said of the recycling law that has been copied by other cities: "We're not about to give up  on it."</p>
        <p>"This law is far from absurd," Mr. Vallone said. "It's sensible and it sets benchmarks, which is how you're supposed to run government. Aim as high as you can."</p>
        <p>Environmental groups, joined by Councilman Sheldon S. Leffler, the primary sponsor of the law, filed a lawsuit in State Supreme Court in Manhattan yesterday, asking the court to enforce the latest deadline -- July 14 -- for reaching the 25 percent recycling requirement. That deadline was set by the State Supreme Court in 1994 as it rejected one of the city's earlier efforts to  wipe out the law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leffler asserted that the goals were reasonable, though he conceded that  it was impossible for the city to nearly double recycling rates in less than two weeks.</p>
        <p>"We don't expect miracles," Mr. Leffler said. "This is not the Ten Commandments we're following." He said he hoped that the court would uphold the  goals but give the city more time to meet them. The original mandates gave the city two years to move to 25 percent from 15 percent, and he suggested that such a time span was still achievable.</p>
        <p>The Councilman said, however, that the Giuliani administration had not put any effort into increasing recycling. Mr. Leffler and other Council members have harshly criticized the Mayor for cutting this year's recycling program by $29 million, virtually eliminating the recycling education and outreach program and  cutting back residential pickups. When the cuts take effect later this year, only parts of Manhattan and Brooklyn will have weekly pickups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani called his administration's scaled-back program a responsible one. He said recycling at the mandated volumes would actually hurt the city because the additional tons of recyclables would flood the recycling market, drive prices for recyclable goods down and thus wind up costing the city even more money.</p>
        <p>The markets for recyclable items have always been extremely volatile. Newsprint, for example, earned the city $160 a ton last year, but this year is costing the city $5 a ton just to get rid of it. The city recycles about 300,000 tons of newspapers annually.</p>
        <p>While his critics also assailed him for announcing plans to shut down the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Islanmd by 2001 without stepping up the city's recycling program, Mr. Giuliani again insisted that the city should turn to out-of-state landfills as an alternative for the 13,000 tons of garbage that goes to Fresh Kills every day.</p>
        <p>"New York City should not be in the position of having to be able to take care of all the garbage that it produces," he said. "That's absolutely impossible for the most densely populated city in the United States."</p>
        <p>He added that "landfills are much more available than people realize' and that they represent a thriving industry in other parts of the country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
