<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Look At the Old West</title>
    <meta content="09road" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/09/travel/09road.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060616T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1767682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Dakota</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5D91531F93AA35755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Look At the Old West</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Look at the Old West</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHERE does the West begin? That's a matter of opinion. But on the high plains, a good argument can be made that it starts in the Black Hills in western South Dakota.</p>
        <p>The brick-red soil of the rolling, ponderosa-pine-covered Black Hills also extends into Wyoming, and this part of the region is less well known. Its landscape, and that of the high plains and mountains to the west, holds a fascinating history of settlement and conflicts, from Indians to cowboys to the cavalry, including George Armstrong Custer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A road trip that begins on the South Dakota-Wyoming border takes you through a classic Western landscape, with more horses than people and many miles between gas stations and good restaurants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHERE does the West begin? That's a matter of opinion. But on the high plains, a good argument can be made that it starts in the Black Hills in western South Dakota.</p>
        <p>The brick-red soil of the rolling, ponderosa-pine-covered Black Hills also extends into Wyoming, and this part of the region is less well known. Its landscape, and that of the high plains and mountains to the west, holds a fascinating history of settlement and conflicts, from Indians to cowboys to the cavalry, including George Armstrong Custer.</p>
        <p>A road trip along Interstate 90 that begins on the South Dakota-Wyoming border takes you through wide-open country -- a classic Western landscape, with more horses and cows than people and many miles between gas stations and good restaurants.</p>
        <p>MILE 2 -- Vore Buffalo Jump: Just over the South Dakota border on I-90 is the tiny, cottonwood-tree-shaded village of Beulah, Wyo. -- population 33, the sign says. A few miles east of town, stop and see a large 45-foot-deep hole called the Vore Buffalo Jump, sandwiched between I-90 and the frontage road.</p>
        <p>It doesn't look like much -- a large red hole in the ground with a locked metal door over a hole at the bottom. But a small sign on top says it is one of the most spectacular archaeological sites in the world, and a larger visitor center is planned. Some 20,000 bison were driven over the edge and to the bottom of the pit between about 1300 and 1800 (according to carbon dating), where they were attacked by Indians with spears, arrows and clubs who turned them into dinner and left behind the bones and many weapons.</p>
        <p>Beneath the door at the bottom lies a pile of buffalo bones, projectile points and other artifacts more than 20 feet deep. The years of accumulation have carefully preserved a record in annual layers and have created an unusually vivid portrait of the lives of the Indians who lived on these rocky plains. While visitors can't see the artifacts -- the visitor center hasn't been built yet -- you can stand at the top or hike to the bottom and imagine a herd of bison galloping toward you across the sagebrush-studded plains and then suddenly finding, in terror, the ground giving way beneath them.</p>
        <p>MILE 50 -- Devils Tower: From Beulah, stay on Interstate 90, exit at State Highway 14 and follow the signs to Devils Tower, the nation's first national monument, set aside by President Theodore Roosevelt in 1906. In Steven Spielberg's ''Close Encounters of the Third Kind'' it was the place where the aliens landed.</p>
        <p>Even without hovering spacecraft, on a windy and gray day, the tower was still stunning, a dark, almost dreamlike silhouette that resembled a giant tree stump glimpsed through low-lying clouds. Its vertical pillar rises 1,267 feet above the ox-bowing Belle Fourche River.</p>
        <p>Indian tribes called it Bear Lodge, and legend has it that when seven young girls prayed to be saved from a rampaging grizzly bear, the ground started to push up and the tower grew higher and higher to keep them out of reach of the attacking bear -- so high eventually that they became the seven sisters in the sky, the constellation Pleiades.</p>
        <p>When you leave the tower, follow Highway 14 to Moorcroft and get back on I-90 there, instead of retracing your steps. The trip now winds for many miles through the dun-colored prairie of the Powder River Basin, once the great hunting grounds of the northern tribes.</p>
        <p>MILE 180 -- Buffalo, Wyo.: This quaint little town with a historic downtown was a stage where many Western dramas were played out. (In the snow-mottled mountains to the west of town a Western drama of a different kind was set -- the Bighorn Mountains are the setting of the story on which the movie ''Brokeback Mountain'' was based.)</p>
        <p>Much of historic Buffalo remains, including the frontier-era Occidental Hotel, a carefully restored barbershop, a saloon and the Virginian restaurant, all in the same block. Many of the West's legends stayed at the Occidental, including Buffalo Bill Cody, Calamity Jane, Butch Cassidy, the Sundance Kid and Theodore Roosevelt. It was founded in 1878, the era of gunslingers and vigilantes, expanded and rebuilt in the early 1900's, and meticulously restored almost a century later.</p>
        <p>The region was always heavily trafficked, and several Indian, trader and exploration routes ran through the area around Buffalo. In the mid-1860's, the Bozeman Trail, a spur off the Oregon Trail that led to the rich gold fields that had recently been discovered in Montana, was established over the same route.</p>
        <p>Later, in 1892, the Johnson County War took place between cattle barons and small ranchers (who were accused of being rustlers) in the area around Buffalo. Large ranchers, backed by about 50 out-of-state gunmen, attacked the cabin of Nate Champion, a small rancher who operated the KC Ranch. Of the four men staying there, two were killed and two captured. A posse from Buffalo, led by the sheriff of Johnson County, then besieged the cattle barons' men at a nearby ranch. The big cattlemen were eventually rescued by federal troops. All this and more is interpreted at the Jim Gatchell Memorial Museum downtown, part of which is in the town's historic library.</p>
        <p>MILE 192 -- Indian Wars Sites: The Cheyenne, Sioux and other tribes deeply resented the invasion of whites into their last great hunting ground and they constantly attacked settlers along the Bozeman Trail. Fort Phil Kearny, named after a Union general, was built in 1866 to protect settlers heading to look for gold in Montana and to keep warring tribes apart. From Buffalo, take I-90 north about 17 miles and follow the signs to the historic site. The huge fort is gone -- it was burned to the ground after the Army abandoned it -- but a section of the stockade, with its eight-foot-high log walls, with the ends like sharpened pencils, has been rebuilt. Signs all around the grounds show how the fort -- which was really a town within walls -- was laid out here at the foot of the mountains.</p>
        <p>This is one of a cluster of sites in the area related to the Indian Wars, all within a short drive of each other. The Fetterman Fight -- formerly called the Fetterman Massacre -- started when Capt. William J. Fetterman took 80 men from the fort to rescue some wagons that were under Indian attack in 1866. Despite orders not to ride out of view, when he got outside the fort he was lured over Lodge Trail Ridge by a small band of Indians.</p>
        <p>It was a trap, and Fetterman and his 80 men were done in by 1,000 or more waiting warriors -- a setback that presaged Custer's Last Stand. A stone monument marks the site of the fallen on the largely undeveloped landscape. To get there from the fort, follow the signs to Old Highway 87, take a left and go a quarter mile to the memorial.</p>
        <p>The Army abandoned the fort and the Bozeman Trail in 1868, and the land was ceded to the tribes forever -- but forever proved temporary. Gold was discovered in 1874 in the Black Hills, in the heart of Indian territory. In 1875, the tribes were ordered to move to reservations or be treated as enemies. Sitting Bull, Crazy Horse and other chiefs refused, leading to war the next year.</p>
        <p>MILE 215 -- Trail End State Historic Site, Sheridan, Wyo.: From Fort Phil Kearny, get back on I-90 and drive north about 20 miles. Take the Fifth Street exit, continue west on Fifth and turn left on Clarendon Avenue.</p>
        <p>After the last of the tribes were gone, the cattlemen came to the oceans of grass on the northern range. One of them was an orphan named John B. Kendrick. A poor cowpoke hired for a trail drive during the days of the open range, Kendrick married the boss's daughter and became one of the great ranchers in the region -- owning more than 200,000 acres in Wyoming and Montana. He would go on to be elected governor of Wyoming in 1914. Two years later, he became the first United States senator from the Cowboy State to be elected by popular vote.</p>
        <p>Kendrick's stately 39-room Trail End mansion, with its dark wood interior (crafted back East) and its spacious top-floor ballroom, sits high on its four-acre grounds overlooking Sheridan. Built in 1913, the home was an elegant refuge against the harsh and still untamed frontier.</p>
        <p>MILE 285 -- The Custer Battlefield: Get back on Interstate 90 and continue into Montana. About 60 miles from Sheridan, in the rolling hills at the foot of the Wolf Mountains you can stand atop the grassy knob of Last Stand Hill at the Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument, where it all ended for Lt. Col. George Armstrong Custer on a sweltering June day in 1876.</p>
        <p>The overconfident Custer attacked several thousand Indians with a few hundred men. As he led one group of troops splashing across the meandering Little Bighorn River on horseback, however, they were attacked by the Indians and forced to retreat. Surrounded, they made a last stand in the long grass.</p>
        <p>MILE 343 -- Pictograph Cave: A state park and national historic landmark, Pictograph Cave is actually a complex of caves -- Pictograph, Middle and Ghost -- in an impressive sandstone cliff a few miles south of Billings. To reach it, drive west on I-90 from Hardin, near the Custer Battlefield, heading to Billings, and look for signs. The complex has produced more than 30,000 artifacts going back more than 4,500 years and is considered Montana's most important archaeological site.</p>
        <p>On the edge of Montana's largest city, a short dirt road takes you a few miles out of town and thousands of years into the past. A trail through a quiet rimrock canyon loops past the mouths of three caves. Most pictographs in Montana are red, but here they are red and black and include a warrior figure with spiked hair and a weeping eye. They were drawn before Rome was an empire.</p>
        <p>IF YOU GO</p>
        <p>Out Where the Buffalo Once Roamed</p>
        <p>THE trip can be made in either direction. If you start in the east, you would fly into Spearfish or Rapid City, S.D. Billings, Mont., is served by major airlines and car rental companies, with all the major hotel chains.</p>
        <p>In Billings, the 282-room Sheraton (27 North 27th Street, 406-252-7400) is in the heart of the historic downtown. The tallest building -- 23 stories -- in Montana, it is within walking distance of restaurants, coffee bars and shopping. In Buffalo, Wyo., the Occidental Hotel (10 North Main Street, 307-684-0451) offers performances by cowboy poets and old-time fiddle players in the summer. Rooms are $110 for a queen to $265 for a three-bedroom suite. A room with a shared bath is $75.</p>
        <p>The Virginian Restaurant (which is in the hotel) features locally grown buffalo, lamb and beef, as well as salmon and chicken. Entrees are $19 to $25. Reservations recommended; 307-684-5976.</p>
        <p>In Beulah, Wyo., the Buffalo Jump Steakhouse, 307-643-2297, serves beef and buffalo steaks, and has a full bar.</p>
        <p>Devils Tower National Monument is open 24 hours a day all year. Admission is $10 a car and camping is $12 a day. The visitor center is open April through November. At other times, information can be obtained by calling the administration building at 307-467-5283</p>
        <p>In Buffalo, the Jim Gatchell Memorial Museum, 100 Fort Street, 307-684-9331, is open from June 1 to Sept. 1, seven days a week, 9 a.m. to 6 p.m. In October and November, it is open Monday to Friday. It then is closed until April. Admission is $4.</p>
        <p>The Fort Phil Kearny State Historic Site, 307-684-7629, is open May 15 through Sept. 30 from 8 a.m. to 6 p.m. From Oct. 1 to May 14, hours are noon to 4 p.m. or by appointment. The grounds are open dawn to dusk.</p>
        <p>The Trail End State Historic Site, 400 Clarendon Avenue, Sheridan, Wyo., 307-674-4589, is open March 1 to Dec. 14. Tours of the mansion are self-guided.</p>
        <p>The Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument, 406-638-2621, is open year round. The fee is $10 for private vehicles.</p>
        <p>Pictograph Cave State Park (also a national historic landmark), 406-247-2940, is seven miles southeast of Billings, Mont., off I-90; take the Lockwood exit, then go six miles south on Coburn Road. It is open May 1 to Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 16, 2006, Friday  An information box with an article last Friday about a driving tour along Interstate 90 in Wyoming and Montana referred incorrectly to the Sheraton hotel in Billings, Mont. With 23 stories, it is the second tallest building in the state. (The tallest is First Interstate Center, also in Billings, which is 12 feet taller, even though it has only 20 stories.)</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 23, 2006, Friday  An information box with an article on June 9 about a driving tour along Interstate 90 in Wyoming and Montana gave an incorrect telephone number for the Buffalo Jump Steakhouse in Beulah, Wyo. It is 307-643-7173.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 16, 2006, Friday</p>
        <p>An information box with an article last Friday about a driving tour along Interstate 90 in Wyoming and Montana referred incorrectly to the Sheraton hotel in Billings, Mont. With 23 stories, it is the second tallest building in the state. (The tallest is First Interstate Center, also in Billings, which is 12 feet taller, even though it has only 20 stories.)</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Correction: June 23, 2006, Friday</p>
        <p>An information box with an article on June 9 about a driving tour along Interstate 90 in Wyoming and Montana gave an incorrect telephone number for the Buffalo Jump Steakhouse in Beulah, Wyo. It is 307-643-7173.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
