<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>School's Python Bites Student Who Was Feeding It a Mouse</title>
    <meta content="29PYTH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1013346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snakes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corchado, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DB173EF93AA15757C0A96E958260" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>School's Python Bites Student Who Was Feeding It a Mouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matthew Corchado, 14-year-old student at High School for the Humanities in midtown Manhattan, is bitten near his right eye by Burmese python as he tries to feed snake in science classroom; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 14-year-old student at a Manhattan high school was bitten near his right eye by a Burmese python yesterday as he tried to feed the snake in a science classroom, the police said.</p>
        <p>According to the police and school officials, the student, Matthew Corchado, was bitten at the High School for the Humanities, at 351 West 18th Street, in a classroom that houses the school's zoology program, with snakes, an iguana, rabbits, turtles and guinea pigs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 14-year-old student at a Manhattan high school was bitten near his right eye by a Burmese python yesterday as he tried to feed the snake in a science classroom, the police said.</p>
        <p>According to the police and school officials, the student, Matthew Corchado, was bitten at the High School for the Humanities, at 351 West 18th Street, in a classroom that houses the school's zoology program, with snakes, an iguana, rabbits, turtles and guinea pigs.</p>
        <p>Matthew, a freshman, was bitten just above his right eye. ''It opened a gash,'' said Betsy Herzog, a Police Department spokeswoman. The Burmese python, which is more than three feet long, is not poisonous, Ms. Herzog said.</p>
        <p>There was no teacher in the classroom at the time, school officials said.</p>
        <p>Officials said that they would investigate why Matthew, who was not in the zoology class, was allowed to feed the snake and also why students were feeding the reptile without adult supervision.</p>
        <p>Matthew was taken to Jacobi Medical Center in the Bronx, which has a special snakebite treatment center in partnership with the Bronx Zoo, which supplies antivenin when necessary. Matthew, who did not need antivenin, was released from the hospital after receiving five stitches above his right eye, said Nina Johnson, a hospital spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it was the snake's fault, and I don't think it's my fault,'' Matthew said yesterday, after returning home from the hospital. ''I think it just got scared and reacted the way any animal would.''</p>
        <p>The boy's uncle, Manuel Corchado, said the boy was lucky the snake was not poisonous. ''He's going to be O.K.,'' Mr. Corchado said. ''He's an excellent kid and he comes from a good family. Very religious. He loves animals; maybe that's how this happened. Why do they have a snake at school, anyway?''</p>
        <p>The python was kept in a fourth-floor room that houses its zoology class, where 39 students learn about the care and handling of animals.</p>
        <p>Although Matthew was not one of the students in the zoology class, he had been feeding mice to the snake just before noon along with a friend who was a zoology student. His friend, who was not identified, had been trained to feed the snake, said J. D. LaRock, a spokesman for the Board of Education.</p>
        <p>''They had just fed it one mouse when it happened,'' Mr. LaRock said. ''They were about to feed it another when the snake attempted to get out of its tank. The first student, who was in the class, went to close the door so it couldn't escape. The second student remained behind with the snake. He approached the snake a bit too quickly and the snake responded by biting him.''</p>
        <p>Matthew said he saw the snake coming at him out of the corner of his eye.</p>
        <p>''I was trying to stay calm,'' he said, ''but it was hard when I felt the blood on the side of my head.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
