<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Great, Not-So-Exclusive Open Seats</title>
    <meta content="25BERK0AB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Backtalk" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="873232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Backtalk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcelroy, Kathleen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DA1739F936A1575BC0A960958260" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Great, Not-So-Exclusive Open Seats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHLEEN McELROY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcelroy, Kathleen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses roles of the 11 officials who monitor play at the US Open; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Excess in pro tennis even extends to the sport's officiating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Excess in pro tennis even extends to the sport's officiating.</p>
        <p>This is not in support of players who cry injustice about being defaulted ''prematurely'' because the rules should have allowed them one more profane observation about the chair umpire.</p>
        <p>The issue is that there even is a chair umpire. And net-cord judge. And a center-service linesperson. Compared with other professional sports, tennis relies on a whopping number of officials, some of whom have nothing to do after the point begins.</p>
        <p>A typical Stadium Court match during the United States Open will have 2 players and 11 officials on a court that totals 2,106 square feet for singles. By comparison, 7 National Football League officials run up and down a field totaling 57,600 square feet while they track 22 players.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, downsizing is a global sport, too. This summer Wimbledon eschewed the net judge for a beeping device that essentially looked like a tiny microphone taped to the net.</p>
        <p>Actually, the net-cord job is one of three positions - including those at the service line and the center service line - that have no function after a serve is ruled good. The net judge's chief duties are to signal if any serve hits the net and to occasionally measure the net to make sure it is at the right height. It would be the best seat in the house if the position were not so dangerous, with net judges recently resorting to donning goggles or helmets to prevent injury.</p>
        <p>The center-service linesperson has an equally quick-hit job: he decides if the serve is within the center service line and then makes like a palace guard for the rest of the point. And he has to work only every other game while his counterpoint across the court takes over.</p>
        <p>But center-service linespeople often spend their time dodging balls traveling at more than 120 miles an hour. This is no joke - at the 1983 Open, a linesman died after having been stuck by Stefan Edberg's serve in a junior match and falling on the asphalt.</p>
        <p>My Open officiating fantasy - a la Kramer of ''Seinfeld''- is to be the linesperson on the service line on the Stadium Court. You get to sit on the court but you're not too close to the action. You get to stretch your legs when you switch sides every game. And in terms of official duties, you have to remember to press the Cyclops button on serves and make calls if the ball is really, really out. It's my kind of responsibility.</p>
        <p>One suspects most people crave the spotlight and would want the ultimate seat - The Chair. But consider that of all the officials on the court, he would be the one least needed if professional tennis players could hit topspin lobs and keep score at the same time.</p>
        <p>If all is going smoothly, the chair umpire usually confirms what we all know: the score. If something is amiss, he might overrule another linesperson, decide it's raining too hard to keep playing or penalize a player for acting petulant. Extra points go to chair umpires at Roland Garros because they burn calories by climbing in and out of their high chairs to check the marks on the clay and subject themselves to ridicule by calling the score in French even if they're from Alabama.</p>
        <p>But chair umpires have the last word and they are using it more these days: ''default.''</p>
        <p>Despite their overwhelming numerical superiority, tennis officials once seemed overmatched against players, especially the star anti-heroes of the 1970's. However, the defaults of Andrew Agassi this month and Jeff Tarango and Tim Henman at Wimbledon last year prove that umpires are now less willing to put up with antics of players.</p>
        <p>Still, linespeople are berated more than your average football referee, who gives up more in height and weight but seems to command more respect on the field.</p>
        <p>The answer? Maybe go with all-electronic lines-calling, which the Open has tested. Or create a balls and strikes rule, as baseball has. Batters cannot argue balls and strikes, so why allow tennis players to argue serves?</p>
        <p>On the other hand, players who argue calls on the Open's outside courts deserve a smidgeon of sympathy. The courts are squeezed in tighter, the crowd is a distraction event o spectators themselves and the players get two fewer linespersons. Whoever is on the center service line dashes to a corner to call a sideline.</p>
        <p>The lesson here is win more often, get better courts and more people to yell at. It's the only way tennis would have it.</p>
        <p>Backtalk  Kathleen McElroy is an assistant sports editor at The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kathleen McElroy is an assistant sports editor at The Times</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
