<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PROGRESS ON TALKS HINTED BY ISRAELI</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SYRIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVY, DAVID (MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FITZWATER, MARLIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D7123CF935A35755C0A967958260" item-length="859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PROGRESS ON TALKS HINTED BY ISRAELI</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Foreign Minister David Levy of Israel said today that a Mideast peace conference might take place within a matter of weeks, but only hours earlier he had reiterated Israel's view that the United Nations should not take part.</p>
        <p>During a visit to Paris for talks with French and other Western European officials, he told a local radio station that "I am sure that all sides know that this is a historic occasion that must be seized."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Foreign Minister David Levy of Israel said today that a Mideast peace conference might take place within a matter of weeks, but only hours earlier he had reiterated Israel's view that the United Nations should not take part.</p>
        <p>During a visit to Paris for talks with French and other Western European officials, he told a local radio station that "I am sure that all sides know that this is a historic occasion that must be seized."</p>
        <p>Asked if the peace conference being promoted by the United States could take place soon, Mr. Levy replied: "I believe the answer is yes. Perhaps within two, three or four weeks. I cannot say, but certainly soon, I'm sure of that."</p>
        <p>In Washington, Reuters quoted the White House spokesman, Marlin Fitzwater, as saying that there was no sign that enough progress had been made to hold a Middle East peace conference within weeks. Dispute Over U.N. Role</p>
        <p>"If you're just talking about time and schedules, certainly," he said. "If that is an assessment, however, of everybody agreeing to the talks and a consensus to have them, that's a different question and I'd say we don't have the evidence to support that at this point."</p>
        <p>The Egyptian Foreign Minister, Amr Moussa, said today in Cairo that Egypt and Syria agreed on the need to hold a Middle East peace conference as soon as possible, Reuters reported. "There is total agreement between Egypt and Syria to start the peace process as soon as possible," Mr. Moussa said after three hours of talks between President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and President Hafez al-Assad of Syria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said on Tuesday night after a meeting with the French Foreign Minister, Roland Dumas, that Israel wanted bilateral talks with Arab countries, with the role of the United Nations in the peace process limited to being informed by the parties once they have settled their differences.</p>
        <p>In recent meetings with Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d, Syrian officials have insisted on United Nations participation in the peace conference. Europe's Ties to Israel</p>
        <p>While Israel merely wants the conference to begin a series of two-way negotiations, Syria has also argued that it should have broader authority.</p>
        <p>In his radio interview today, Mr. Levy refused to speculate on how Israel and Syria might settle those differences. Asked about Palestinian representation in the conference, he said, "You are now entering into the kind of details that can endanger the current move towards the holding of this conference."</p>
        <p>Earlier, after a meeting with the Foreign Ministers of Luxembourg, Italy and the Netherlands, he was quoted as saying that Israel now accepted that the European Community take part in the Mideast peace conference alongside the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Foreign Minister Jacques Poos of Luxembourg, which currently holds the rotating presidency of the 12-nation community, said the European Community also emphasized its interest in strengthening economic ties with Israel. The community is already Israel's principal export market.</p>
        <p>During the Persian Gulf war, Israel's relations with several Western European governments were strained by its anger that they had sold Iraq sophisticated weapons and technology for developing chemical weapons. Until now, Israel had also resisted European involvement in the peace conference.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Israeli Concession Stance</p>
        <p>JERUSALEM, June 5 (Special to The New York Times) -- While Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir is still preparing his reply to President Bush's letter urging compromise for the sake of the American peace initiative, Government officials here say the Bush Administration is likely to be disappointed.</p>
        <p>Israel, they say, has already offered all the concessions it intends to make. They quickly pointed to the agreement in Paris today for a European Community role in any peace conference as ample evidence of that.</p>
        <p>Several powerful members of the Israeli Government, including Housing Minister Ariel Sharon, have made it clear that they oppose any European role in the proposed conference. Foreign Minister Levy, who came to agreement with the European Community in Paris today, is likely to face criticism and opposition from Mr. Sharon and others when he returns here.</p>
        <p>At the same time, without mentioning the Bush Administration directly, this morning Mr. Shamir asked for recognition of the other concessions Israel has made -- chief among them that Israel is willing to discuss limited autonomy for West Bank and Gaza Strip Palestinians one day.</p>
        <p>"There must be appreciation of the concession we made when agreeing that the sovereignty on Judea, Samaria and Gaza be subject to negotiations, despite our heart-felt belief that these areas are an organic part of the land of Israel, the land of the people of Israel," he said.</p>
        <p>In a speech last week, Mr. Shamir once again stated that belief when he said the strength of the state lay in "a generation of faithful, powerful and strong Jews in Israel, one that will never abandon even a clod of soil of the Land of Israel, even if it must be watered with a sea of sweat and tears."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
