<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; Political Correctness Versus Open Expression on Campus</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM OF SPEECH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC BROADCASTING SERVICE (PBS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WNET (TV STATION) (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SAFE SPEECH, FREE SPEECH (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D71E3EF935A35755C0A967958260" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; Political Correctness Versus Open Expression on Campus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>About halfway through "Safe Speech, Free Speech and the University," what some academics might call the subtext of the evening emerges: what some critics call the pressure for political correctness on campus. The site of tonight's offering in the Columbia University Seminars on Media and Society, at 9 on Channel 13, is Stanford University, whose speech code and multi-cultural curriculums have become flash points of the debate. Donald Kennedy, Stanford's president; Thomas Grey, the Stanford law professor who drew up the code, and two Stanford students are on hand for the defense.</p>
        <p>Fred W. Friendly, acting as peripatetic moderator, begins with the speech code, which Stanford's Mr. Kennedy calls "a vaguely worded entreaty to behave well." The conversation does not go much beyond affirmations of a standard difference of opinion. The students, a black woman and an Asian-American man, defend the code as a weapon against insults to minorities and women. Nadine Strossen, the president of the American Civil Liberties Union, and Nat Hentoff, a columnist for The Village Voice, rebut with the principles of the First Amendment. Ms. Strossen is daring enough to say that she sort of enjoys being whistled at: "I don't mind being flattered for my appearance."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>About halfway through "Safe Speech, Free Speech and the University," what some academics might call the subtext of the evening emerges: what some critics call the pressure for political correctness on campus. The site of tonight's offering in the Columbia University Seminars on Media and Society, at 9 on Channel 13, is Stanford University, whose speech code and multi-cultural curriculums have become flash points of the debate. Donald Kennedy, Stanford's president; Thomas Grey, the Stanford law professor who drew up the code, and two Stanford students are on hand for the defense.</p>
        <p>Fred W. Friendly, acting as peripatetic moderator, begins with the speech code, which Stanford's Mr. Kennedy calls "a vaguely worded entreaty to behave well." The conversation does not go much beyond affirmations of a standard difference of opinion. The students, a black woman and an Asian-American man, defend the code as a weapon against insults to minorities and women. Nadine Strossen, the president of the American Civil Liberties Union, and Nat Hentoff, a columnist for The Village Voice, rebut with the principles of the First Amendment. Ms. Strossen is daring enough to say that she sort of enjoys being whistled at: "I don't mind being flattered for my appearance."</p>
        <p>The most eloquent statement against a speech code comes from Benno C. Schmidt Jr., the president of Yale University, who calls it "an engine of suppression." The special mission of a university, he reminds the group, is the search for truth, which requires "the right to speak the unspeakable, think the unthinkable and challenge the unchallengeable," offensive though it may be to one group or another. Professor Grey responds that a racial epithet has as much to do with the search for truth as spitting in someone's face.</p>
        <p>Andy Rooney, the "60 Minutes" humorist, whose past comments about minorities got him into trouble, is taken to task here when he says he finds words like "nigger" and "kike" amusing. Under pressure, he says he meant only that he gets a laugh out of the sort of people who utter such words. The explanation does not seem to mollify anyone.</p>
        <p>The evening picks up after the essayist Roger Rosenblatt decries universities' tendency to emphasize self-esteem, to "make everybody feel good," at the expense of plain speaking -- and he speaks the words "political correctness." Others pitch in, with reports that students and teachers who do not take the politically correct lines on such matters as affirmative action and abortion are being intimidated in class and ostracized outside.</p>
        <p>The evidence is anecdotal, and Randall Kennedy, a Harvard Law School professor, dismisses it as part of an attack on the political and cultural tendencies that grew out of the 1960's. He says he supports a speech code against racial insults and also upholds the right to "mobilize opinion" against views that some deem offensive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friendly derails this revealing interchange, possibly as a courtesy to his Stanford hosts, who have been taking heat from mockers of multi-culturalism and its multiple implications. He turns to the issue of what part race should play in the selection of professors. The matter is not irrelevant, but the arguments are familiar and the steam goes out of the discussion. SAFE SPEECH, FREE SPEECH AND THE UNIVERSITY Produced by Abigail Pogrebin, Michael Quinn and Ruth Friendly; Fred Friendly, moderator. At 9 tonight on Channel 13.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
