<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bulgaria Presses Inquiries Into the Communist Past</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BULGARIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPE (JOHN PAUL II)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC1338F935A35755C0A967958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bulgaria Presses Inquiries Into the Communist Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TAGLIABUE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an effort to put the Communist past to rest, the Bulgarian authorities are conducting sweeping investigations into allegations of crimes by the former Government ranging from corruption to the attempt on the life of Pope John Paul II.</p>
        <p>Since February the Government has been trying the nation's former leader, Todor Zhivkov, on corruption charges, and looking into the transport of tens of thousands to prison camps under the Communists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an effort to put the Communist past to rest, the Bulgarian authorities are conducting sweeping investigations into allegations of crimes by the former Government ranging from corruption to the attempt on the life of Pope John Paul II.</p>
        <p>Since February the Government has been trying the nation's former leader, Todor Zhivkov, on corruption charges, and looking into the transport of tens of thousands to prison camps under the Communists.</p>
        <p>But the most spectacular case involves charges that the secret police, possibly with aid from the Soviet K.G.B., ordered the attempt by a right-wing Turk to assassinate Pope John Paul II in 1981. Other longstanding allegations under inquiry contend that the secret police were responsible for wounding a Bulgarian defector, Vladimir Kostov, in Paris in 1978 and killing Georgi Markov, another defector, who died after he was stabbed with a poisoned dart in London soon afterward.</p>
        <p>In interviews last week in Sofia, the Bulgarian capital, senior officials of the Government that is dismantling the old Communist system said that they were confident fresh inquiries could prove secret police complicity in the attacks on Mr. Markov and Mr. Kostov but that they harbored serious doubts of Bulgarian involvement in the plot against the Pope.</p>
        <p>Christo Danov, the new Interior Minister, who belongs to no political party but describes himself as "anti-Communist," said he believed that responsibility for the assaults on Mr. Markov and Mr. Kostov "came from very high places."</p>
        <p>But he said that while many theories had been offered about the attack on the Pope, "I believe the weakest of all is the Bulgarian connection."</p>
        <p>This week, an Italian newspaper, Il Giorno, published what it said was the transcript of a tape by a former Bulgarian secret policeman, Konstantin Karadzhov, which implicted Bulgaria and the Soviet Union in the plot against the Pope. He also suggested that the Central Intellignce Agency had learned of the plot in advance but did not warn the Vatican, hoping instead to catch the assassins in the act and pin the crime directly on the Kremlin.</p>
        <p>But officials in Bulgaria said the language and content of the tape convinced them that it was bogus. They said several Bulgarian newspapers had refused to buy it before it was offered for sale to the Italian press.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karadzhov himself, through intermedaries, has since denied the tape's authenticity. His links with the Bulgarian secret service have also been questioned.</p>
        <p>At the Government's criminal investigative office, Leonid Katsamunski, the official in charge of the reopened inquiry into the poison-dart attacks on Mr. Markov and Mr. Kostov, said investigators believed that the two cases were closely related.</p>
        <p>He said magistrates would seek to interrogate Gen. Oleg Kalugin, a former senior officer in the K.G.B., who is now one of President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's most vocal critics in Parliament. He has accused the K.G.B. of having supplied Bulgaria with the poisonous devices used in the attacks.</p>
        <p>For Bulgarian investigators, a major obstacle to finding the truth lies in the lingering loyalties among intelligence officials, many of whom remain in office and could either destroy evidence or refuse to testify against former colleagues. Such concerns appear reinforced by the flight to the Soviet Union this week of a senior Bulgarian security official, Lieut. Gen. Vladimir Todorov, who before he bolted admitted to having seven volumes of files on the Markov case destroyed because they were "uninteresting."</p>
        <p>Mehmet Ali Agca, the Turk convicted of wounding the Pope in 1981, declared that Bulgaria's secret services had ordered and paid for the assassination attempt at the behest of the K.G.B.</p>
        <p>Now, as a sign of good faith, Sofia has agreed to permit unlimited access to secret Government files and officials for a new international inquiry.</p>
        <p>Allen Weinstein, president of the Center for Democracy, a Washington-based policy group, who will head the international inquiry, said while in Sophia to accept the documents that he would seek the cooperation of other nations, including Turkey and Italy, to test "all possible hypotheses."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
