<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Real Political Reform Can't Wait</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="591910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICAL ACTION COMMITTEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOLEY, THOMAS S (SPEAKER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D91331F932A15751C0A965958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Real Political Reform Can't Wait</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"We must begin again to make Government work for ordinary taxpayers, not simply for organized interest groups and that beginning must start with real political reform," President Clinton said midway through his economic address on Wednesday. "Believe me," he improvised after the applause died down, "they were cheering that last section at home."</p>
        <p>The television offered a richly symbolic image at that moment. Visible over the President's left shoulder was the genial face of House Speaker Thomas Foley. It was not possible to tell from his expression what Mr. Foley thought of this remark, but Mr. Foley did seem to be clapping his hands.  Now he needs to use them to open up the legislative throttle if the country is to get the campaign finance and lobbying laws that are needed to clean up Congress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"We must begin again to make Government work for ordinary taxpayers, not simply for organized interest groups and that beginning must start with real political reform," President Clinton said midway through his economic address on Wednesday. "Believe me," he improvised after the applause died down, "they were cheering that last section at home."</p>
        <p>The television offered a richly symbolic image at that moment. Visible over the President's left shoulder was the genial face of House Speaker Thomas Foley. It was not possible to tell from his expression what Mr. Foley thought of this remark, but Mr. Foley did seem to be clapping his hands.  Now he needs to use them to open up the legislative throttle if the country is to get the campaign finance and lobbying laws that are needed to clean up Congress.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Foley has given theoretical assent to campaign reform, but has made the House calendar a hostage to recalcitrant Democrats who hope that Mr. Clinton's idealism will burn itself out and that public demand for reform will wilt in the summer doldrums.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton called in his speech for action on campaign finance reform "this year." That may have sounded good to most viewers at home. But it's a clear retreat from his commitment to put the issue at the top of his legislative agenda. In the Congressional lexicon, "this year" could just as well be never, and it is a troubling signal that Mr. Clinton may be swayed by Mr. Foley's private warning that pushing campaign reform will endanger his economic legislation.</p>
        <p>It is easy to understand why fund-raising-obsessed House incumbents would want to delay any action to make them less beholden to the special interests that finance their campaigns (see chart). Yet, why Mr. Clinton would go along is baffling, especially given the strong conflicting advice from the Senate majority leader, George Mitchell. Mr. Mitchell has put campaign finance legislation on a fast track in his chamber, with the hope of moving it to the floor for a vote as early as next month.</p>
        <p>Just as baffling is Mr. Clinton's warm endorsement of the lame lobbying disclosure bill proposed by Senator Carl Levin of Michigan. In his speech, he called on Congress to pass it "quickly" as a step "to deal with the undue influence of special interests." What Mr. Clinton didn't say, but what every senator and House member well knows, is that the bill doesn't require disclosure of the sort of embarrassing details that might actually shame the typical member to quit mooching off lobbyists for expensive meals and exotic vacations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton may be hoping that speedy approval of a flawed lobbying bill would detract attention from the laggard path of campaign finance reform. If the President wants to play this shell game, he should be prepared to be exposed as phony and fainthearted on this issue.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Clinton would level with Americans on political reform, as he has on the economy, he would gain in popularity and respect. The next step is for Mr. Clinton to say how he would toughen the campaign finance bill passed last year by Congress and vetoed by President Bush, and to demand from Congress a firm timetable for getting the legislation to his desk. And the next time he is standing at the lectern in the House, it would not hurt to turn around and tell Mr. Foley to quit clapping and get on with the people's business.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
