<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awash in Pain, Sarajevo Is Sinking Into Despair</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="591768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SARAJEVO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA-HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DB1E3DF932A15751C0A965958260" item-length="1869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awash in Pain, Sarajevo Is Sinking Into Despair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early one morning last week, long before the sun burned the mists out of the mountain-ringed bowl in which Sarajevo sits, a lone figure emerged from an apartment building high above the city center and set out on crutches for the one-mile walk to work.</p>
        <p>Mirza Hadzanovic, a 35-year-old police officer, was the only pedestrian on Mose Pijade Street at 6:45 A.M., and his progress, on the one leg left to him after he was hit by a mortar shell last summer, was painful to watch. It was also dangerous: his journey was punctuated by the whistle of shells fired from the mountains and by huge blasts as they exploded into apartments, the Kosevo Hospital complex and other buildings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early one morning last week, long before the sun burned the mists out of the mountain-ringed bowl in which Sarajevo sits, a lone figure emerged from an apartment building high above the city center and set out on crutches for the one-mile walk to work.</p>
        <p>Mirza Hadzanovic, a 35-year-old police officer, was the only pedestrian on Mose Pijade Street at 6:45 A.M., and his progress, on the one leg left to him after he was hit by a mortar shell last summer, was painful to watch. It was also dangerous: his journey was punctuated by the whistle of shells fired from the mountains and by huge blasts as they exploded into apartments, the Kosevo Hospital complex and other buildings.</p>
        <p>Outsiders who have been here since the siege began sense a depth of desperation now that is worse than anything they have seen and an erosion of spirit even in those who had managed to remain positive through 10 months of food shortages and brutal bombardments of much of this once-lovely city.  'Completely Demoralized'</p>
        <p>"After 10 months eyeball-to-eyeball with death, people are completely demoralized," said Gordana Knezevic, 42 years old,an associate editor of Oslobodjenje, the daily newspaper that continues to chronicle the miseries of the siege six months after its two 15-story buildings in the western reaches of Sarajevo were pounded into rubble.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Knezevic has lost more than 25 pounds during the siege -- typical of the weight losses of most people here. She said people were beyond misery, suffering from a kind of emotional and psychological paralysis.</p>
        <p>In the chaos of the siege, few accurate figures have been kept on anything. But those that are available, most of them broadly supported by observation, tell a terrible story.</p>
        <p>The Government said last week that 8,327 people for whom it has names have been killed in Sarajevo or have been missing for three months or more, and 63,451 others have been wounded. If accurate, this means that about one resident in every six here when the siege began have been direct victims of the snipers and shells directed at the city by Serbian nationalist forces.  Suicide Rate Soaring</p>
        <p>The Health Ministry and doctors at the hospitals say the strain on residents' health has spread much wider. Apart from the severe weight losses, there is evidence of a soaring suicide rate, of a near doubling in abortions, a 50 percent drop in births.</p>
        <p>The figures are supported by a wealth of experiences. In a symbolically telling episode, an Oslobodjenje reporter went to the Kosevo Hospital maternity clinic on New Year's Eve to report on the first babies of the year. Normally, about 15 babies are mentioned; this year, there were none.</p>
        <p>On the morning that Mr. Hadzanovic was spotted hobbling down Kosevo Hill, gravediggers were at work barely 300 yards away on what used to be a soccer field, filled past the midfield line now with 1,500 new graves. As they toiled in the mist, another 20 bodies were unloaded from battered trucks and laid out on the muddy ground. Most of the burials, Muslim and Christian, were so hurried by the constant shellfire that the handful of mourners dispensed with all ceremony, save tossing a few handfuls of earth atop the dead before scurrying off to somewhere safer.</p>
        <p>At the central market, traders were laying out wares at open-air stalls, their exorbitant prices for food and cigarettes pushed higher almost daily by a near-total blockade of supplies. A week ago the Muslim-led Government, whose forces control most of Sarajevo, announced that it was barring any further United Nations relief shipments to the city until peacekeeping forces pushed aid convoys through to besieged Muslim communities in eastern Bosnia that have had no help, or virtually none, since the war began in April.  For Ramadan, No Feasts</p>
        <p>The Government-imposed food blockade came immediately before the start on Tuesday of the month of Ramadan, when Muslims fast from dawn to dusk, then traditionally engage in substantial family meals.</p>
        <p>Thus, it was almost the last straw for many people, even for the many who supported the Government's move. Many larders were virtually bare when the Government blockade was imposed. Having no sure prospect of supplies, many people cut back still further on the spare meals of bread, rice and macaroni that are virtually all that many families have eaten for 10 months.</p>
        <p>If that was not bad enough, Sarajevo was once again entirely without main-line electricity and running water as a result of a new round of brutal fighting on heights to the northwest, where the only transmission line still operating was cut last week by mortar shells.</p>
        <p>For all except the privileged in strategic buildings like the Presidency and the Army headquarters, which have diesel fuel to power generators, and the few families who have candles, another commodity almost as scarce as gold, the cutting of the power lines meant being plunged back into nights of total darkness and days spent trundling through the city's murderous streets to the few places, like the brewery, where plastic canisters can be filled with water. A Psychological Blow</p>
        <p>Today was the ninth day that no United Nations food or medical supplies reached the city, and the eighth day since the United Nations canceled the airlift to Sarajevo airport, saying it would not risk the lives of aircrews if the supplies were just going to end up stockpiled at the field. It was at least the fifth time that the airlift had been suspended, but only the first time for reasons other than attacks on the aircraft.</p>
        <p>For many in the city, there was a psychological blow in not seeing the C-130 Hercules and twin-engined French-built Transall transports in their steep approaches and take-offs against the backdrop of the western mountains, the aircrafts' paths marked by magnesium flares to protect against air-to-ground missiles. Among the planes flying the airlift have been American planes based in Germany, and the distant sight of planes with the Stars and Stripes on their tails has stirred many hopes.</p>
        <p>For months, even after the Bush Administration made it clear it would not use military force against the Serbian nationalists, many people here clung to the prayer that Washington would eventually spur its European allies into some form of military rescue. But even that slim hope appeared to die here after the Clinton Administration outlined its policy last week.  Hopes Have Been Doused</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Warren Christopher, while condemning "ethnic cleansing" and saying that Washington had a strong interest in stopping it, specifically excluded the two measures sought by the Bosnian Government: lifting a United Nations embargo that has kept the Bosnian Army from acquiring heavy weapons to match the Serbian forces, and bombingSerbian gun positions and other strategic targets.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Christopher said Washington would monitor the relief operations more closely to see whether United States support, perhaps in the form of troops to augment the United Nations force, might be needed.</p>
        <p>In the days since the United States statement, the gloom here has reached new depths. Suddenly, reporters moving about the city were no longer being approached by soldiers and mothers and old men outside mosques asking, "Clinton? What will Clinton do?"</p>
        <p>While the Bosnian Government put a brave face on Mr. Christopher's statement, saying that it welcomed the commitment to a greater diplomatic involvement, most ordinary people, particularly the Muslims, who now make up about 80 per cent of the population of 380,000 people, appeared to have concluded that they were finally and perhaps irretrievably alone in the face of the Serbian Juggernaut.  Worse Every Day</p>
        <p>"The situation is worse and worse every day," said Sakir Dzirlo, 43 years old, an electrical engineer who, with his wife, Amra, a 41-year-old architect, struggles to maintain their four children in an apartment on Marshal Tito Street in an area that has been heavily pounded with artillery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dzirlo, like other devout Muslims, is observing Ramadan and fears that his family will have to pass their days fasting only to sit down in the evening to meals that will consist of little but dwindling supplies of pasta from the United Nations "family packages" delivered before the aid convoys were halted.</p>
        <p>While the Government and many people in Sarajevo have clung to the belief that they are fighting for the right to a "citizens' state" in which Muslims, Serbs and Croats and other ethnic groups can live in harmony, as they did in Sarajevo before the war, the stresses are increasingly polarizing feelings within the city.</p>
        <p>Many Serbs complain of being harassed by angry Muslims, particularly after heavy shelling from Serbian guns in the mountains, and Muslims complain that the dwindling number of Serbs and Croats in the city, perhaps 50,000, have advantages that Muslims lack.  Less Aid for Muslims</p>
        <p>Among these, many Muslims say, are regular aid packages from Serbian and Croatian relief organizations, Dobretvor in the case of the Serbs and the Roman Catholic Church in the case of the Croats, that are allowed through the siege lines by Serbian troops who have blocked attempts by Muslim organizations, even those based outside Bosnia, to bring in relief supplies. Muslims who see Serbian or Croatian neighbors returning home with the telltale cardboard boxes of food say the arrival of the packages is yet another form of victimization.</p>
        <p>On the war front around Sarajevo, too, the mood is increasingly radicalized. While Serbs and Croats continue to fight in the Bosnian forces, units that hold forward positions against the Serbian nationalists are overwhelmingly Muslim.</p>
        <p>After a period in the fall and early winter when the forces defending the city were gaining strength from an increased flow of clandestine arms and ammunition, recent battles have re-established the overwhelming advantage of the Serbian forces, and the casualties among the mostly Muslim defenders are appalling.</p>
        <p>The main battle has been for a strategic stretch of open ground at Azici, on the western end of the city, where Bosnian defenders have attempted to hold trenches that guard the western entrance to the city.  Relentless Fire</p>
        <p>The scene at Azici is reminiscent of the trenches in France in World War I, with Bosnian soldiers with rifles and antitank weapons heading out in twos and threes toward their trenches under relentless fire from Serbian tanks and antiaircraft machine-guns that flank the Bosnian positions on three sides.</p>
        <p>The ground provides no cover other than blasted houses here and there that are hit again as soon as any Bosnian troops take refuge in them. On some days, casualties among the Bosnians run close to 50 percent, and reporters approaching the Bosnian forward positions encounter a steady stream of men returning from the front covered in blood.</p>
        <p>One man who was lightly wounded asked a reporter to take him to a hospital in the city, and remained silent for most of the 15-minute journey.</p>
        <p>Finally, he spoke up.</p>
        <p>"There is no hope out there," he said. "If I stay out there long enough, I will end up dead."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
