<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Saratoga Sales Reflect Drop in Market</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="549860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SARATOGA RACE TRACK (NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1E3FF930A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Saratoga Sales Reflect Drop in Market</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., Aug. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decline in the horse market seemed to be steepening today after Saratoga's 72d annual summer sales opened and the average price for a yearling dropped 26 percent from last year's auction.</p>
        <p>The Saratoga sales opened Tuesday night, one month after prices slipped 19 percent at the more prestigious Keeneland sales in Kentucky, and the same pattern was reflected here: Foreign buyers, notably the Arabians and Japanese, the big spenders of the last decade, showed much less interest and cash. And D. Wayne Lukas, the most active American spender in recent years, wasn't even on the scene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The decline in the horse market seemed to be steepening today after Saratoga's 72d annual summer sales opened and the average price for a yearling dropped 26 percent from last year's auction.</p>
        <p>The Saratoga sales opened Tuesday night, one month after prices slipped 19 percent at the more prestigious Keeneland sales in Kentucky, and the same pattern was reflected here: Foreign buyers, notably the Arabians and Japanese, the big spenders of the last decade, showed much less interest and cash. And D. Wayne Lukas, the most active American spender in recent years, wasn't even on the scene.</p>
        <p>On the opening night at Saratoga, a total of 52 horses went into the auction ring, 40 were sold and 12 were bought back by their owners when the prices stayed too low. The average yearling brought $79,025, a plunge of 50 percent from last year's opening-night average of $158,257, and a decline of 26 percent from last year's three-night average of $121,105. 'Good Group of Horses'</p>
        <p>"They're a good group of horses, physically," said D. G. Van Clief, president of the Fasig-Tipton horse-auction company. "But we're obviously still looking at a market decline. This sale is probably as realistic a market barometer as we've seen this summer. If there's one favorable sign, it may be that 23 percent of the horses were not sold, against 36 percent who were returned last year."</p>
        <p>Although foreign investors avoided the skyrocketing prices of the 1980's, when a record price of $13.1 million was paid for a yearling, they still set the pace at more modest levels. The highest price for a yearling was the $325,000 paid by Sheik Mohammed bin Rashid al-Maktoum of Dubai for a daughter of Fappiano and half-sister to Housebuster. The most active buyer was Lillian Oung, a business executive from Hong Kong, who took 5 of the 40 horses sold. Narrow but Interesting Field</p>
        <p>In the closest thing to a match race, only three horses went to the post for the seventh race after Her She Shawklit and Lady Lear were scratched from the original field of five. So, only win betting was allowed. You either put the money on somebody's nose, or you sat and watched a three-horse race.</p>
        <p>Either way, Lilac's Star beat the odds at 5-2 and won by two lengths over Wiggles Law, the even-money favorite, followed in a tight photo by Maxamount, who went off at 6-5. The time for the mile and one-eighth was 1:51 flat, and the return was $7.40 for $2. The way it came out, you could have bet on all three horses and still won. Fourstars Allstar Moving Along</p>
        <p>Twice as many horses showed up for the feature race, the 34th running of the Bernard Baruch Handicap, and this one went strictly to form. Richard Bomze's 4-year-old campaigner, Fourstars Allstar, outran Yoshiki Akazawa's Lotus Pool by half a length, with John T. L. Jones Jr.'s Maxigroom third.</p>
        <p>Fourstars Allstar, trained by Leo O'Brien with Mike Smith riding, ran as a solo after his full brother Fourstardave was scratched. Both horses are sons of Compliance and the mare Broadway Joan. The winner covered the mile and an eighth on the grass in 1:46, paid $4.60 to win, came home with $70,680 of the purse of $117,800 and probably won a trip to England.</p>
        <p>Bomze said he was "90 percent sure of going to Ascot," and O'Brien added: "We're thinking of running him in the Queen Elizabeth II Stakes next month. It's a mile with a right-hand turn. The turn concerns me, but we'll try to work him that way before we go."</p>
        <p>Fourstars Allstar has now won 8 of his 28 starts and run in the money 20 times.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
