<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Opens Inquiry On Breaches Of Computers</title>
    <meta content="12hack" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/12/us/12hack.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1789507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwarzenegger, Arnold (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Speeches and Statements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speeches and Statements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Schwarzenegger, Arnold</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDC1531F931A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Opens Inquiry On Breaches Of Computers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">California Opens Inquiry on Breaches of Computers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California opens investigation into outside breaches of computer system used by aids to Gov Arnold Schwarzenegger to store downloaded audio files; in those files, some of which were leaked to news media, governor is heard making remarks about passions of Latinos because of their 'blood'; he apologized for remarks after they were made public (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The California Highway Patrol is investigating outside breaches of a computer system used by aides to Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger to store downloaded audio files, a spokesman for the patrol said Monday.</p>
        <p>In those files, some of which were leaked to The Los Angeles Times, the governor was heard telling Susan Kennedy, his chief of staff, that Cubans and Puerto Ricans were naturally passionate because of their combination of ''black blood'' and ''Latino blood.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The California Highway Patrol is investigating outside breaches of a computer system used by aides to Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger to store downloaded audio files.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The California Highway Patrol is investigating outside breaches of a computer system used by aides to Gov. Arnold Schwarzenegger to store downloaded audio files, a spokesman for the patrol said Monday.</p>
        <p>In those files, some of which were leaked to The Los Angeles Times, the governor was heard telling Susan Kennedy, his chief of staff, that Cubans and Puerto Ricans were naturally passionate because of their combination of ''black blood'' and ''Latino blood.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwarzenegger, who is seeking re-election, apologized for the remarks on Friday after they were reported by the newspaper, and he was criticized by his Democratic opponent, Phil Angelides.</p>
        <p>''We are looking into the security of the governor's office computer system,'' said Fran Clader, a spokeswoman for the Highway Patrol, which is in charge of policing state facilities.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clader would not provide details of the investigation, but a person associated with the governor said that three times over the last week of August and the first week of September a person or group of people gained access to the governor's staff computers from outside the Sacramento offices. The person spoke on the condition of anonymity because the matter could become the subject of a criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>There are no immediate theories, the person said, as to who is responsible for the breach, first reported by The San Francisco Chronicle.</p>
        <p>The governor's legal affairs secretary, Andrea Lynn Hoch, issued a statement Monday night saying that an internal audit had revealed some information about the person involved in the breach and that the information had been turned over to the Highway Patrol.</p>
        <p>In remarks to Ms. Kennedy and Gary Delsohn, a speechwriter, Mr. Schwarzenegger praised the legislative style of State Senator Bonnie Garcia, who is of Puerto Rican descent, saying: ''I mean Cuban, Puerto Rican, they are all very hot. They have the, you know, part of the black blood in them and part of the Latino blood in them that together makes it.''</p>
        <p>On Friday, Ms. Garcia held a joint news conference with Mr. Schwarzenegger in Los Angeles to announce that his remarks had not bothered her in the least, but the governor said that reading the remarks in the newspaper made him ''cringe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Delsohn records conversations with the governor to use as reference material when he is writing his speeches, but shares them with a limited number of sources, The Chronicle reported.</p>
        <p>Some experts on computer security said the person or people who entered the governor's system most likely knew what they were looking for -- rather than randomly stumbling across the files -- and could have easily stolen the password needed to get them. They said it was likely that the files were not properly secured.</p>
        <p>Sondra Schneider, the chief executive of Security University, a company that provides training in protecting electronic assets, theorized that someone sent an e-mail message that compromised the governor's computer system when it was opened, allowing the sender to steal the password.</p>
        <p>''Anyone at any time of any day can do that to anyone,'' Ms. Schneider said. ''It happens every minute of the day.''</p>
        <p>In the case of the governor's office, Ms. Schneider said: ''They just had to know that those audio files were in existence. I don't think someone was fishing around on the site looking for it. They knew it was there and it was made available because it was not secured properly.''</p>
        <p>The governor's press office referred all calls to the California Highway Patrol. David Garcia, a spokesman for The Los Angeles Times, said in an e-mail message that the paper had not been contacted by the patrol.</p>
        <p>Governor Schwarzenegger is in a tough re-election battle. He has been known to get into hot water with his remarks, including once calling a group of legislators ''girlie men.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
