<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Did a German Scientist Prevent Catastrophe in World War II?</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD WAR II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POWERS, THOMAS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEISENBERG'S WAR: THE SECRET HISTORY OF THE GERMAN BOMB (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF103CF93BA35750C0A965958260" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Did a German Scientist Prevent Catastrophe in World War II?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heisenberg's War The Secret History of the German Bomb By Thomas Powers Illustrated. 608 pages. Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
        <p>Thomas Powers's important new book, "Heisenberg's War: The Secret History of the German Bomb," is a detailed account of the race to develop an atom bomb during World War II as seen from both the German and Allied sides. It is full of fascinating characters, deeds of heroic daring and graphic accounts of important developments in modern physics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heisenberg's War The Secret History of the German Bomb By Thomas Powers Illustrated. 608 pages. Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
        <p>Thomas Powers's important new book, "Heisenberg's War: The Secret History of the German Bomb," is a detailed account of the race to develop an atom bomb during World War II as seen from both the German and Allied sides. It is full of fascinating characters, deeds of heroic daring and graphic accounts of important developments in modern physics.</p>
        <p>It describes how the great scientists Niels Bohr and Werner Heisenberg together puzzled out both the quantum theory and the impossibility of establishing at any given instant the momentum and the location of a nuclear particle. It recounts how the mysterious Moe Berg, best known as the learned major league baseball catcher with a passion for obscure languages, attended a 1944 Heisenberg lecture in Zurich with instructions from his superiors in the United States Government to assassinate the German physicist if it appeared that he was close to producing an atomic bomb.</p>
        <p>But at its heart "Heisenberg's War" makes a stunning assertion. In the game of heads or tails that Germany and the United States played with each other during the war -- heads, they're making a bomb; tails, they aren't -- the Americans got it wrong. Germany never seriously undertook the nuclear program whose hypothetical existence made it so urgent that the United States succeed with the Manhattan Project. In fact, Heisenberg, who was in charge of the German effort, consciously obstructed the development of a bomb.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers's proof of this conclusion is difficult not only to summarize but also to accept. First, his evidence is sometimes sketchy, and, as he himself observes: "Inference is a tricky tool for the historian; things that may have, might have, or must have happened, often reveal a strained effort to bridge troubling gaps in evidence."</p>
        <p>Second, that same evidence is often highly ambiguous. For instance, in 1941 Heisenberg visited his old friend Niels Bohr in Copenhagen and said things that upset the Danish physicist, who was a neutral in close touch with the Allies. Historians have assumed that Heisenberg was trying to stall the Allied effort to gain an advantage for Germany. But Mr. Powers, by placing the Heisenberg-Bohr discussion in a larger context, concludes that what Heisenberg was really saying was that since Germany wasn't making a bomb, why should the Allies bother?</p>
        <p>Finally, the notion that Germany was not trying to produce a bomb reflects profoundly on the American effort. Mr. Powers goes to considerable lengths to remind us how difficult it was for some of the physicists on the Manhattan Project to accept how much they had altered human existence. That one of their deepest reasons for making the bomb might have been baseless seems almost too much to bear.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Powers makes a forceful case in "Heisenberg's War." The author of "Diana: The Making of a Terrorist" (1971) and "The Man Who Kept the Secrets: Richard Helms and the C.I.A." (1979) among other books, he weaves hundreds of subtle details into a narrative so glacial in its movement that it is sometimes even tedious to read. But the main points of argument can be summarized as follows:</p>
        <p>As one of the world's most brilliant physicists, Heisenberg was the peer of any of the thinkers who came to understand what putting together a bomb entailed. Still, on 19 separate occasions, disaffected German scientists leaked information about the state of their nuclear program to Allied intelligence authorities; several of the messages indicated that work on a reactor was being done, but not on a bomb.</p>
        <p>As supporting evidence for this, during their 1941 meeting in Copenhagen, Heisenberg sketched for Bohr a box with sticks protruding from the top. Bohr in his ignorance concluded that the drawing was of a bomb, but when Hans Bethe, Edward Teller and several other Manhattan Project scientists got a look at this sketch in Los Alamos on the last day of December 1943 they concluded immediately that it was a sketch of a reactor.</p>
        <p>At a crucial meeting on June 4, 1942, between leaders of the German bomb project and Albert Speer, Hitler's newly appointed Reichsminister of Armaments and Munitions, Heisenberg told the assemblage that "yes, in principle we can make atomic bombs and can produce this explosive stuff, but all processes we know to produce these explosive substances are so enormously expensive and it would take perhaps many years and it would take quite enormous technical expenses of billions if we wanted to do it."</p>
        <p>Finally, there is the physical evidence of what the Germans actually accomplished. When a mission sent by the Office of Strategic Services finally got to look at the German program, it found, as Mr. Powers writes, "that research was going on at many different laboratories with little coordination or even ordinary communication among them, and that nothing had proceeded beyond the experimental stage -- as well as the many indications that 'energy production rather than an explosive is the principal German goal.' "</p>
        <p>Samuel A. Goudsmit, the Dutch-born scientific director of the O.S.S. mission and the physicist who shaped postwar thinking about the malign intentions of Nazi Germany's nuclear program, concluded that there were two reasons for the German failure: as Mr. Powers puts it, "goose-stepping Nazis had meddled in scientific matters they didn't understand, and Heisenberg had committed scientific errors so gross that he invented a fairy story of moral scruples to explain them."</p>
        <p>Goudsmit found further support for his conclusions in the transcripts of the discussions among the leading German scientists during their internment at the country house known as Farm Hall in the small town of Godmanchester, England, for the last half of 1945. But Mr. Powers argues that Goudsmit's reading of the Farm Hall transcripts was selective and highly prejudiced. In his view, a fuller reading of the transcripts, which were not declassified until Feb. 24, 1992, offers strong evidence that Heisenberg "well knew how to make a bomb," but "kept the knowledge to himself." As Mr. Powers concludes, "Small wonder that with such an adviser the German authorities concluded that a bomb was beyond them."</p>
        <p>As for why Heisenberg never troubled to admit or explain how he undermined the German nuclear-weapons program: Mr. Powers blames a combination of pride, personal reticence and an understandable fear of being accused of treason. This may be frustrating for posterity, but it was consistent with Heisenberg's character. As Mr. Powers concludes his powerful narrative, Heisenberg "always insisted that no praise, thanks or credit were owed to him for the way things turned out." If this powerful book is right, then its reticent hero may have saved humanity from an unimaginable catastrophe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
