<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Computer As Catalyst</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="EX MACHINA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD81038F936A35752C0A964958260" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Computer As Catalyst</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FRIEND who works at home discovered one morning that his personal computer's diskette drive would not accept a disk. His 3-year-old son observed him snarling and muttering as he tried repeatedly, without success, to get the computer to accept the disk.</p>
        <p>"Maybe there's a penny in the hole," the child suggested.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, dad spied a penny in the narrow slot and eventually extracted it with tweezers. The drive still wouldn't take the disk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FRIEND who works at home discovered one morning that his personal computer's diskette drive would not accept a disk. His 3-year-old son observed him snarling and muttering as he tried repeatedly, without success, to get the computer to accept the disk.</p>
        <p>"Maybe there's a penny in the hole," the child suggested.</p>
        <p>Sure enough, dad spied a penny in the narrow slot and eventually extracted it with tweezers. The drive still wouldn't take the disk.</p>
        <p>After another frustrating minute, the boy offered another thought: "Maybe there's lots of pennies in there."  A Rewarding Time</p>
        <p>A comprehensive lesson on the care and maintenance of personal computers followed for the youngster, while the parent learned a valuable lesson, too: Spending time with the children at a computer can be rewarding in more ways than one.</p>
        <p>According to a recent Gallup survey sponsored by Star Micronics America Inc., a personal computer printer company, 25 percent of American households report having a personal computer. Of those households, nearly 70 percent reported using the computer for schoolwork. Among all parents who said they owned or planned to buy a home computer in the near future, 78 percent said that they believed it could improve their children's performance in school.</p>
        <p>Many skeptics remain, but it seems that most parents and educators have agreed that personal computers are an important educational tool.</p>
        <p>Other national surveys show that all but a few elementary and secondary schools in the United States have at least one personal computer set aside for instruction. Financial realities, however, dictate that it will be many years before there is a computer on every student's desk.</p>
        <p>Computers are simply too expensive, and even if they were reasonably priced, few schools have enough electrical outlets to accommodate all that equipment. So parents who can afford a home computer, or who can take time to expose their children to computers at the office or library, will be helping to accelerate their children's exposure to an information technology that will someday be ubiquitous.</p>
        <p>All too often, though, parents simply plop the computer on a desk in the den, or plop their child in front of a computer in the office or local library, and use the machine as a teacher or television surrogate. 'Antidote to TV'</p>
        <p>"Computers are often presented as the antidote to TV, with people saying that TV is passive and the computer is interactive," said Tom Snyder, president of Tom Snyder Productions Inc., which develops educational software. "I have yet to see good evidence that the computer's level of interactivity is intuitively a good thing."</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Snyder said, "The interaction that happens in a computer program is about on the level of the worst conversation you had with the dumbest cat you ever had. You are making choices, but that's kind of like your kid having hundreds of TV channels to choose from. If they click around the channels, is that really interactive? There's none of the rich context that occurs in a conversation."</p>
        <p>Mr. Snyder, a former schoolteacher and now a parent, cited a theory called "contextual welding." The theory, in brief, is that children may be able to recall in a computer game that, working out from the Sun, Mars comes immediately after Earth and Jupiter comes next. But the same children may be unable to recall the planetary sequence in a conversation, or to understand it when it is applied to something other than a game.</p>
        <p>"The learning occurs when you get away from the computer and try your theory on someone else," he said. "Imagine if Pac Man had a pause button, and you could play with another person. You'd say, 'Hey, that monster is real close,' and the other person might say, 'We should go this way.' You introduce language that cements real learning. Those are things you can do with a computer, but not with TV."</p>
        <p>That is partly why many educators think the real value of a home computer is as a catalyst to spark interaction between parent and child, or among groups of playmates.</p>
        <p>Margaret Honey, a researcher at the Center for Technology at the Bank Street College of Education in New York, said that one experiment in an eighth-grade class in Roselle, N.J., a suburb of Elizabeth, shows that computers can be effective in creating student-parent partnerships.</p>
        <p>"Each kid has been given a laptop computer, which they trot back and forth between school and home," Ms. Honey said. "They do note-taking, writing, work with science data bases and they use the calculator. The computers are functioning kind of like the electronic notebooks that we talk about for the future.</p>
        <p>"One thing the teachers wanted is for the kids and parents to sign a contract that talks about working together. At the first open house at school, every single parent showed up. Until now, at a typical open house, five or six parents drifting in and out was considered a lot. The parents I met were very curious, very enthusiastic and eager to support what their kids do." A Good Locus</p>
        <p>Educators emphasize that parental involvement is crucial for successful education, and the personal computer is an especially good locus for such interactions.</p>
        <p>Some parents, perhaps intimidated by the technology, may not want to get involved in an area where the child probably knows more than the adult. By contrast, computer-literate parents may play the role of exacting know-it-alls with their children. Mistakes happen, however, and are essential to learning valuable lessons, like the fact that making errors will not cause the computer to explode and that there are ways to recover from them.</p>
        <p>Often, parents should be trying to train children in the basics of operating a computer, establish rules of use and then support the youngsters as either a technician on call or as a work partner. The basics include turning the computer on, adjusting the screen, keyboard and lighting, loading a diskette, copying and storing a file, beginning and ending a session and caring for diskettes.</p>
        <p>Rules vary by household. In some, they include no eating or drinking at the computer. Preserving the privacy of other people's files is also important. Some parents might want to stipulate no banging on the keyboard and no pennies in the disk drive.</p>
        <p>"Your biggest challenge will be to step back and let your kids take the lead," said Judy Salpeter, author of "Kids &amp; Computers, a Parent's Handbook" ($16.95, published by Sams, a division of Prentice Hall). "In general, if you spend too much time telling your kids how to use the computer, they will resent the intrusion and come to view computing as just another area in which parents get to tell the kids what to do."</p>
        <p>Ms. Salpeter is managing editor of Technology &amp; Learning magazine, a publication for educators who use information technology. Her book is a comprehensive and thoughtful guide for any parent, but particularly for parents of children ages 2 to 13.</p>
        <p>"In many cases there is an evening out of abilities," Ms. Salpeter said of parent and child interaction at the computer. "If you have a kid who's very familiar with computer games and you as a parent aren't, you have an opportunity to compete on an equal basis, or at least be in a situation where he is teaching you rather than the other way around."</p>
        <p>Even very young children can benefit, she said, noting: "Long before they can handle instructions or even handle the mouse, they can have a good time on your lap. A lot of good communication can result."</p>
        <p>Mr. Snyder said parents should choose educational software that interests them. With help, their children will be able to learn something from it -- if nothing more than that using a computer can be fun, since they will see enjoyment on their parents' faces.</p>
        <p>EX MACHINA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
