<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schools Trying to Cope With 'Crack Babies'</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRACK (COCAINE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COCAINE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN TASSEL, PRISCILLA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D8153DF936A35752C0A964958260" item-length="1448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schools Trying to Cope With 'Crack Babies'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PRISCILLA VAN TASSEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VAN TASSEL, PRISCILLA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JANE STEIN, a 29-year veteran of elementary school teaching, is seeing a different breed of pupils in her kindergarten class these days at the Joyce Kilmer School in Trenton.</p>
        <p>"Their attention span is much shorter," she said. "It's very difficult for them to sit still for a long period of time. I guess you'd call it itchiness. They plain can't pay attention."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JANE STEIN, a 29-year veteran of elementary school teaching, is seeing a different breed of pupils in her kindergarten class these days at the Joyce Kilmer School in Trenton.</p>
        <p>"Their attention span is much shorter," she said. "It's very difficult for them to sit still for a long period of time. I guess you'd call it itchiness. They plain can't pay attention."</p>
        <p>In Asbury Park, the situation isn't much different.</p>
        <p>"When you start dealing with these kids, they never stop," said Jeanne Brunetti, district supervisor of special education for the Asbury Park schools. "They never sit down; they're up the wall and across the ceiling."</p>
        <p>New Jersey elementary schools, particularly those in urban areas, are coming to recognize such behavior all too well as classic symptoms of prenatal exposure to crack cocaine and other drugs. The children currently attending early elementary school are the oldest of an emerging generation of so-called crack babies, born when the drug first hit the streets in the mid-1980's, and they are causing major instructional and financial problems.</p>
        <p>In one Asbury Park preschool class of seven children, two of whom are known to have been prenatally exposed to drugs, the school is finding that, even with the help of an aide, one teacher is not enough.</p>
        <p>"We are being beaten with the costs," Ms. Brunetti said. "The social problems are increasing, drug involvement is increasing, the brain damage is increasing, and the kids are coming to us damaged. The problem is just beating us to death."</p>
        <p>There are no firm statistics on the number of children in New Jersey with problems stemming from prenatal drug exposure, but estimates are frightening to educators.</p>
        <p>At the University of Medicine and Dentistry of New Jersey-University Hospital in Newark, some 30 percent to 50 percent or more of the 2,500 babies born at the hospital each year are thought to be drug-exposed, said Alice Angell, who runs a program for drug-exposed babies and their mothers at the hospital.</p>
        <p>A study of 43 hospitals by the National Association for Perinatal Addiction Research and Education, a Chicago-based institute focusing on problems caused from drug use during pregnancy, estimates that 11 percent to 15 percent of children nationally are exposed prenatally to illicit drugs.</p>
        <p>"This is just the tip of the iceberg," said Dan Griffith, a developmental psychologist with the association, at a workshop on crack babies that was held at the New Jersey Education Association's convention in Atlantic City in November. Mr. Griffith said the figures were based on urine toxicologies at the time of delivery and did not include alcohol use or mothers who used drugs after they became pregnant but, fearing prosecution, stopped before they gave birth.</p>
        <p>Efforts to get accurate information on drug use are usually futile, experts say. In Asbury Park, when parents were asked for information about their drug and alcohol histories, they reported virtually no use.</p>
        <p>"The denial is tremendous," said Dr. Linda Burgess, a child study team supervisor for Asbury Park. "They don't want to believe themselves that what they did harmed their babies."</p>
        <p>Educators say the problem is more complex than simple drug exposure. Poor health care and nutrition before and after delivery, continued drug use among parents after birth and other ills associated with poverty compound learning difficulties, making it hard to determine where the consequences of prenatal drug use end and environmental factors begin. 'No Typical Profile'</p>
        <p>Even the phrase "crack baby" rankles. "The term 'crack baby' is really a misnomer," said Michelle Murchison, a drug and alcohol awareness coordinator for East Orange public schools. "Most of these children are poly-drug-exposed. There is no typical profile, and there are also some who function quite well."</p>
        <p>Because each child who is exposed to the drug responds differently, the question of who is at risk becomes complicated. A delay in identifying children exposed to crack may be particularly harmful since there is growing evidence that early, intensive help may reduce or in some cases eliminate most behavorial and cognitive problems.</p>
        <p>"I've seen too many kids falling through the cracks," said Joan Blum, an elementary school drug and alcohol awareness coordinator in Pemberton Township. She spends much of her time trying to set up support groups and counseling for the more than 15 percent of students she estimates need help.</p>
        <p>While there are no set behavioral traits that are associated with crack-exposed children, certain patterns are common, experts say. Because the drug affects the nervous system, the brain frequently does not develop well and head size is small. The children are often irritable, hypersensitive to stimulation, prone to staring spells and tremors and unable to follow even the simplest directions. They become agitated in an unstructured environment and often have language and movement problems. Goals Being Challenged</p>
        <p>Some long-held educational goals and practices are being challenged as a result of this emerging problem. In Trenton, educators are reluctantly conceding that their recently installed all-day kindergarten program may be too much for children who cannot concentrate for long periods.  In other districts throughout the state, teachers are being told to change their routines.</p>
        <p>"It's opposite everything they've learned," said Frances Miceli, who advises schools on setting up programs for children with possible drug exposure for the Division of Drug, Alcohol and Addictive Services in the New Jersey Department of Health. "Like take everything off the walls, no stimuli in the room, lots of structure, short periods of time where there's an opening and a closing, and repetitive activities."</p>
        <p>In Asbury Park, a first-grade teacher has removed bulletin boards and taken to playing classical music to soothe children. In a quiet corner in her classroom in Trenton, while the other children have play time, Mrs. Stein works one on one with pupils who were too agitated to concentrate during lesson time.</p>
        <p>In Newark, adults known as "child associates" have been hired this year to talk and play with children in a specially designated room away from the classroom.</p>
        <p>The adults "are not certificated people, but just warm, loving, caring people the children can talk with," said Pat Joyner, an assistant director for Newark schools in charge of drug education. "It's not counseling, it's not treatment, but just a chance for the child to have someone to talk to because for the most part they can't have that at home." Many Districts Caught Short</p>
        <p>Although school districts have had years to prepare for cocaine-exposed students, many have been caught short.</p>
        <p>"We knew four years ago; all the districts knew," said Dr. Mark Raivetz, executive director of planning, research and evaluation for the Trenton school system. "On the one hand, we talked a good game and acknowledged the fact that this was coming to the school. But I really don't believe that we had a clue of exactly what we should have been expecting. And now it's here."</p>
        <p>But the adjustment is accelerating. In East Orange, administrators are beginning to train teachers to recognize cues from students who may have been exposed to drugs. In Camden, school officials are seeking information from neonatal intensive care units in the area about the number of drug-exposed babies so they can plan for the future.</p>
        <p>"We are asking them to tell us so we have some idea what's coming down the pike two and a half years from now in our preschool program," said Dr. Casimir Witkowski, the district's coordinator for special education.</p>
        <p>Schools are being pressured to keep the students in regular classrooms as much as possible, for philosophical reasons as well as financial ones. 'We Have to Be Careful'</p>
        <p>"We have to be careful about putting all these kids in special education programs," said a State Department of Education official who spoke on the condition of anonymity. "That designation follows kids all through school, and we don't know for sure whether these characteristics are transient or not.</p>
        <p>"And to the degree that the numbers might be so significant in the future, the cost of special education programs probably precludes putting all these kids in special education."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Brunetti of Asbury Park knows the pressure of the bottom line.</p>
        <p>"People keep asking why we're classifying everyone, not realizing that it started way before we ever saw them," she said. "We have to educate people about what's coming up, and it isn't pretty. I don't know what's going to happen in the next 10 years."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
