<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Like Strudel Without the Filling</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARENA PLAYERS REPERTORY THEATER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANK, LEAH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">IN ONE BED...AND OUT THE OTHER (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF1E3AF936A35752C0A964958260" item-length="653" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Like Strudel Without the Filling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEAH D. FRANK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANK, LEAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE new offering at the Arena Players Repertory Theater in East Farmingdale, "In One Bed . . . and Out the Other," makes a vain attempt at being a frothy turn-of-the-century romantic farce in the manner of Schnitzler's "Ronde." The authors, Mawby Green and Ed Feilbert, have concocted nothing more substantial than a strudel without the filling.</p>
        <p>The slim plot centers on a novelist named Didier, who has fallen in love with a married woman. He devises a plan to meet her and then have her husband invite him to stay as a house guest. Didier's best friend, Maurice, is posing as a butler to help expedite the affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE new offering at the Arena Players Repertory Theater in East Farmingdale, "In One Bed . . . and Out the Other," makes a vain attempt at being a frothy turn-of-the-century romantic farce in the manner of Schnitzler's "Ronde." The authors, Mawby Green and Ed Feilbert, have concocted nothing more substantial than a strudel without the filling.</p>
        <p>The slim plot centers on a novelist named Didier, who has fallen in love with a married woman. He devises a plan to meet her and then have her husband invite him to stay as a house guest. Didier's best friend, Maurice, is posing as a butler to help expedite the affair.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the husband's mistress shows up, as does Maurice's fiancee and his wealthy Aunt Alice. The heretofore virtuous wife is swayed by the novelist's attention. Didier and Maurice have switched names and identities, which adds to the confusion.</p>
        <p>Are you following this?</p>
        <p>Anyway, the action literally revolves around a large round bed set up in the middle of the living room. Across this playing field pass lovers and would-be lovers in various pairings. Who ends up with whom, and how they do it, constitutes two acts and three scenes with no surprises.</p>
        <p>As in any romantic farce, the marriage is never seriously threatened, and all the innuendoes and shielded lust serve to add necessary spice to marital bliss.</p>
        <p>Apart from the lack of substance or wit in the script, this production highlights the strong points and the weaknesses of work at the Arena. The actors give all they have to creating characters that the playwrights have barely sketched out.</p>
        <p>As the mistress, Linda Bub is a curvy blond melodramatic heroine right out of the silent movies. She bats her eyelashes, pouts and otherwise makes herself a paradigm of 19th-century sensuality. Christine Miller, as the enchanting wife, is virtue on two legs, with just enough of a twinkle to make one suspect that her virtuous nature is a very thin veneer.</p>
        <p>Aileen O. Kuss as the blustery Aunt Alice is a gust of wintry wind from the provinces, howling and moaning at all hours of the day and night. Nella Dawn Casalino manages to look ravishing in a small role that requires nothing more of her.</p>
        <p>The husband, the novelist and the friend are played by Don Frame, Joseph Vernon and Jeff Hoffman. The three outdo one another in strutting around like roosters hoping to attract the attention of the hens.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vernon makes the novelist into a debonair rake, while Mr. Hoffman turns the noble friend into a Long Island version of a French Woody Allen. Mr. Frame is a dithering gander who vacillates between lust and longing.</p>
        <p>What entertainment value exists in this production lies in the acting and in Frederic De Feis's flamboyant comic direction.</p>
        <p>The problem with the production is that the play is set in Paris at the turn of the century, and the Arena company is not equipped to provide even the most elemental necessities of the period.</p>
        <p>The actors cannot pronounce even minimal French, and the variations on monsieur are too numerous to count. Also, the costumes have little, if anything, to do with the times.</p>
        <p>Although the three female love interests are played by some of the most attractive actresses affiliated with Arena, their dresses make them appear awkward and even misshapen. For example, Miss Miller's red ruffled gown makes her look more like a stuffed tomato than a lush plum.</p>
        <p>The set is Paris in 1900 only because that is what the program says it is. Whatever lighthearted spirit might pervade in imaginative design is left out in the cold. The lighting is standard, and could serve for any script in any time frame.</p>
        <p>A play is more than the text. Good acting can go a long way to make a production enjoyable, as it often does at the Arena, but a full evening of theater demands that more belongings be pulled from the theatrical trunk.</p>
        <p>"In One Bed" will continue at the Main Stage through Jan. 19.  THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
