<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investment Banks Playing Key Roles in California Power Crisis</title>
    <meta content="Y26UTI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/26/national/26UTIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1265885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pg&amp;e Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Gas and Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse First Boston</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Gray (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hertzberg, Benjamin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2DA143FF935A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investment Banks Playing Key Roles in California Power Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wall Street investment banks with big financial stakes in success of energy deregulation are playing important behind-the-scenes roles as officials in California struggle to fix state's troubled electric power system; Goldman, Sachs, which has energy trading operations and has longstanding banking relationship with state's largest utility, seeks to become state's financial adviser on crisis; Credit Suisse First Boston, whose clients include independent power companies that sell electricity in California, has been retained by Benjamin Hertzberg, speaker of state Assembly, to help draw up legislation intended, in part, to make sure such companies are paid $12 billion they are owed by California utilities; Robert E Rubin, chairman of executive committee of Citigroup Inc, acting in private capacity, is advising Gov Gray Davis on strategies for dealing with state's energy crisis (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wall Street investment banks with big financial stakes in the success of energy deregulation are playing important behind-the-scenes roles as officials in California struggle to fix the state's troubled electric power system.</p>
        <p>Bankers from Goldman, Sachs, which has an energy trading operation and has a longstanding banking relationship with the state's largest utility, met in Sacramento and held conference calls this week with state officials to discuss becoming the state's financial adviser in the crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wall Street investment banks with big financial stakes in the success of energy deregulation are playing important behind-the-scenes roles as officials in California struggle to fix the state's troubled electric power system.</p>
        <p>Bankers from Goldman, Sachs, which has an energy trading operation and has a longstanding banking relationship with the state's largest utility, met in Sacramento and held conference calls this week with state officials to discuss becoming the state's financial adviser in the crisis.</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse First Boston, whose clients include independent power companies that sell electricity in California, has been retained by the speaker of the state Assembly to help draw up legislation intended, in part, to make sure such companies are paid the $12 billion they are owed by California utilities.</p>
        <p>In addition, Robert E. Rubin, the former Treasury secretary who is now chairman of the executive committee of Citigroup Inc., is advising Gov. Gray Davis on strategies for dealing with the state's energy crisis. Citigroup said yesterday that Mr. Rubin was acting as a private citizen, not in his corporate capacity. The Salomon Smith Barney unit of Citigroup has been a frequent adviser in deals between utilities and power companies.</p>
        <p>In San Francisco, the Utility Reform Network, a consumer advocacy group, issued a statement calling a measure introduced yesterday by the Assembly speaker, Robert Hertzberg, a ''complete bailout of the utility companies,'' and said Mr. Hertzberg and Credit Suisse shared the blame.</p>
        <p>''Not surprisingly, the bill gives the financial markets exactly what they have been lobbying for -- assurances that California consumers will pick up the entire tab for the state's failed deregulation experiment,'' the group said. The legislation would allow California to issue bonds to pay for power it would then resell to the state's utilities.</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse's role in drafting the legislation was widely known, and Paul Hefner, a spokesman for Mr. Hertzberg, said it made sense to turn to Wall Street for help in resolving the state's energy mess.</p>
        <p>''The speaker has felt all along that it is critical that we find a long-term solution that works in the financial world, so we sought counsel from people within the business,'' Mr. Hefner said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Credit Suisse said the firm ''provided advice strictly on a pro-bono basis at the request of Bob Hertzberg, based on our expertise in this area,'' but declined to say if it would seek paid business with the state related to the energy situation.</p>
        <p>The investment bankers' business interests in the California energy crisis take many forms. If the state proceeds with a bond sale, it would need to hire an investment bank, a job that could be worth millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The banks also have an interest in keeping energy deregulation alive amid the reactions whipped up by California's problems. They have brokered many of the purchases of generating plants by independent power companies from utility companies ordered to shed them as part of the restructuring of the power industry. Likewise, the banks have enjoyed the lucrative stock and bond underwritings that have stoked the rapid growth of those upstart power companies.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, Goldman, Sachs has perhaps the greatest interest in how the power crisis is resolved. The firm owns J. Aron &amp; Company, which sells natural gas to power generators in central and northern California, including the PG&amp;E Corporation, which operates the region's major utility, Pacific Gas and Electric.</p>
        <p>J. Aron supplies nearly 10 percent of Pacific Gas and Electric's daily gas requirements and would become a significant creditor if the utility is forced to file for bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>Indeed, worried that it would not be paid, J. Aron briefly cut off gas supplies to Pacific Gas and Electric earlier this week, flouting emergency federal orders by the Energy Department requiring that shipments continue, regardless of whether the utilities could guarantee payment.</p>
        <p>Goldman has long had a banking relationship with PG&amp;E, underwriting bonds for the company for years.  It is unclear whether the bank owns any PG&amp;E bonds, though it was granted the option to purchase some as part of underwriting work it performed for the company.</p>
        <p>A Goldman, Sachs executive, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said the bank was still assessing whether its various banking relationships would cause so many conflicts that it could not accept a role advising the state.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Goldman said the firm never commented on possible assignments. In any event, she said that the bank had ''Chinese walls that are absolute,'' meaning that the bank took care to avoid conflicts among its clients' interests.</p>
        <p>Norman Poser, a professor of securities law at the Brooklyn Law School, said it is clear that Goldman, Sachs is ''not a disinterested party'' in the California situation. But, he added, ''that kind of self- conflict is so widespread in the investment banking business that the key, really, is disclosure.''</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse also has a variety of interests in how the energy crisis is resolved. Its client list includes many power companies that generate or sell electricity to California's enfeebled utilities. They include the Enron Corporation, one of the industry's strongest proponents of deregulation; Dynergy Inc.; the Duke Energy Corporation; and the Calpine Corporation, among others.</p>
        <p>It is unclear what advice Mr. Rubin has given Governor Davis, but state officials said the two men had spent perhaps 25 hours in conversation about the months-long crisis. Citigroup and its investment banking unit, Salomon Smith Barney, historically have done banking work for Edison International and PG&amp;E, the parent companies of the state's biggest utilities.</p>
        <p>''In his personal capacity, from time to time, Bob has talked to the governor and his staff,'' said Leah Johnson, a spokeswoman for Citigroup. The company would not say if, separately from Mr. Rubin's contacts, it was seeking business from the state.</p>
        <p>The governor seems likely to support a bill to finance a solution by selling bonds, though he has criticized Mr. Hertzberg's proposal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
