<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Council Given Data It Sought, Deputy Mayor Says</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="418935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY COUNCILS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY CHARTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAYORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBPOENAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGES AND TUNNELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service"></org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIRE DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRANSPORTATION DEPARTMENT (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEISEL, NORMAN (DEPUTY MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEE, FELICIA R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D61538F933A05752C0A967958260" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Council Given Data It Sought, Deputy Mayor Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEE, FELICIA R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Dinkins administration said yesterday that it had turned over all the documents the City Council had threatened to subpoena as part of an investigation into bridge safety, but a Council spokeswoman said it was too early to tell if the administration had complied completely with the demands.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone, First Deputy Mayor Norman Steisel said that in making available the two-inch-thick pile of communications between Transportation Commissioner Lucius J. Riccio and the office of Mayor David N. Dinkins, the Mayor did not waive his right to withhold documents in the future in appropriate circumstances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Dinkins administration said yesterday that it had turned over all the documents the City Council had threatened to subpoena as part of an investigation into bridge safety, but a Council spokeswoman said it was too early to tell if the administration had complied completely with the demands.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone, First Deputy Mayor Norman Steisel said that in making available the two-inch-thick pile of communications between Transportation Commissioner Lucius J. Riccio and the office of Mayor David N. Dinkins, the Mayor did not waive his right to withhold documents in the future in appropriate circumstances.</p>
        <p>The letter also said information related to matters other than the Bureau of Bridges had been blanked out. Peg Breen, the Council spokeswoman, immediately objected to this procedure and insisted that the Mayor had no right to withhold information.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steisel said the information was released in part to assuage public fears about bridge safety. He also said in an interview that information that the Council's Public Safety Committee requested about firehouses would be made available today.  A Testing of Powers</p>
        <p>The letter was part of the first major battle as the Mayor's office and City Council test each other's power under the new City Charter. The Transportation Department information was considered especially sensitive. Mr. Riccio recently dismissed David Steinberger, his deputy commissioner for bridges, and Mr. Steinberger's assistant two days after a memorandum by Mr. Steinberger on the dangerous condition of the Manhattan Bridge was cited in a New York Times article.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinberger warned in the August memo that returning subway service to the bridge would endanger public safety. Train service resumed the next month but was halted in December, when state inspectors said they had discovered that a beam supporting the tracks was a fraction of an inch from slipping and causing a possible derailment.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the Council's Transportation Committee postponed a hearing on the issue because the Mayor's office had not provided important documents. The Council threatened on Monday to subpoena the information, which it can do according to the Charter, if it is not available by 5 P.M. tomorrow.</p>
        <p>City officials insisted yesterday that they never tried to hide anything from the Council committees. Needed More Time</p>
        <p>Victor A. Kovner, the city's Corporation Counsel, had said he needed more time to review requests by the Transportation Committee for personnel information within the bridge bureau.</p>
        <p>"There is no desire on the part of the administration not to provide information that they request," said Mr. Dinkins, who was in Albany most of the day meeting with legislators about his anti-crime plan. "In these two specific instances, Fire and the Department of Transportation, the information they want will be forthcoming. But we will make it very clear that not all of this information is information to which they are automatically entitled."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kovner said yesterday that under two common-law privileges -- public-interest privilege and executive privilege -- the Mayor can withhold information.</p>
        <p>The public-interest privilege weighs the need for confidentiality in government records against the public's need for information, Mr. Kovner said. He said executive privilege was analogous to executive privilege in the Federal sector, and addresses the need for executives to communicate with full candor on policy decisions, knowing that their communications are confidential.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
