<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Times to Seek Arbitration on New Plant</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="419122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR-MANAGEMENT RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWSPAPERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EDISON (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK TIMES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWSPAPER AND MAIL DELIVERERS UNION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, ALEX S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULZBERGER, ARTHUR OCHS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor-Management Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D81F31F933A05752C0A967958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Times to Seek Arbitration on New Plant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX S. JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONES, ALEX S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The publisher of The New York Times declared yesterday that negotiations had failed to resolve differences with a key union over operation of a new printing plant due to open at Edison, N.J., and that the paper would exercise its right to submit the dispute to binding arbitration.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the publisher, Arthur Ochs Sulzberger, said The Times must have "substantial cost reductions" from the seven unions that are to operate the $450 million Edison plant, which is highly automated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The publisher of The New York Times declared yesterday that negotiations had failed to resolve differences with a key union over operation of a new printing plant due to open at Edison, N.J., and that the paper would exercise its right to submit the dispute to binding arbitration.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the publisher, Arthur Ochs Sulzberger, said The Times must have "substantial cost reductions" from the seven unions that are to operate the $450 million Edison plant, which is highly automated.</p>
        <p>The company has said the plant will not be opened until settlements are reached, and it will then be used to print Travel, Arts and Leisure and some other sections of the Sunday paper in color as well as a portion of the press run of the daily paper, which will remain in black and white.</p>
        <p>John M. O'Brien, the paper's senior vice president for finance and human resources, said The Times would seek arbitration with the Newspaper and Mail Deliverers' Union, which represents the paper's truck drivers. The union's negotiating committee declined a final offer from The Times on Monday night.</p>
        <p>The Times is also negotiating with unions representing pressmen, mailers, stereotypers, paperhandlers, machinists and electricians, but Mr. O'Brien said the most critical negotiations were with the largest unions: the drivers, the pressmen and the mailers. Union Position</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien said that thus far The Times had reached an impasse in negotiations only with the drivers' union.</p>
        <p>No representative of the drivers' union responded to messages left at the union's office yesterday seeking comment.</p>
        <p>George E. McDonald, president of the Allied Printing Trades Council, the umbrella organization for the unions, said it was the unions' understanding from previous negotiations that they would be allowed to operate the new equipment for a time before negotiating such issues as staffing. He said this argument would be made in arbitration.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien has said that the equipment at Edison has been demonstrated to union leaders and that union members do not need to operate it to understand how it should be staffed.</p>
        <p>Except for references to a few jobs, the existing contract does not address whether negotiations would be conducted before or after the plant begins operation. Phrase at Issue</p>
        <p>In 1987 The Times and all the unions signed contracts that expire on March 30, 1993. Those contracts provide for "the orderly, successful and efficient start-up and operation" of a new plant, the phrase that is the basis of the current negotiations.</p>
        <p>The contract with the paper's pressmen, represented by New York Newspaper Printing Pressmen's Union Local 2, also expires in 1993 but guarantees that staffing on the presses at Edison will remain the same as on black-and-white presses until 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien said that all other areas of the pressmen's contract would be open to negotiation in 1993 and that The Times was trying to give the pressmen incentives, like cash payments, to reduce press staffing. Thus far, the pressmen's union has declined to negotiate on staffing, he said.</p>
        <p>The paper's final offer to the drivers' union has been withdrawn because of the decision to seek arbitration, Mr. O'Brien said. Payments Offered</p>
        <p>In his statement, Mr. Sulzberger said he was "astonished" that the offer had been rejected without a membership vote.</p>
        <p>The Times's offer provided for payment of $75,000 each for up to 100 of the 402 drivers over age 55 who voluntarily left their permanent positions. Each driver not leaving would be given a $15,000 bonus, and the number of drivers would be restored to 402 by hiring casual workers.</p>
        <p>But beginning no later than March 31, 1993, the number of permanent jobs would decline by attrition to 340.</p>
        <p>The Times also offered to make a $3 million contribution to the union's health and welfare fund, which Mr. O'Brien said was in jeopardy of bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>But The Times has also proposed redistributing the present number of working hours into a four-day week at Edision, a step that would greatly reduce overtime there and also reduce overtime at The Times's plant in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien estimated that the average driver now earns $44,000 in annual base pay and about $20,000 more in overtime.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
