<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Governing By Television</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD71E3AF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Governing By Television</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ross Perot is the most interesting thing that has happened to American politics in years. He is also the scariest.</p>
        <p>He has tuned in brilliantly to Americans' frustration with government, their perception that life in this country is growing worse and politicians do nothing about it. He has convinced an astonishing number of people that he can fix things if he is put in charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ross Perot is the most interesting thing that has happened to American politics in years. He is also the scariest.</p>
        <p>He has tuned in brilliantly to Americans' frustration with government, their perception that life in this country is growing worse and politicians do nothing about it. He has convinced an astonishing number of people that he can fix things if he is put in charge.</p>
        <p>He has not said what he would do about the hard problems, and voters do not seem to care. But he has indicated how he would govern. That is the scary part.</p>
        <p>"The electronic town hall" is Mr. Perot's idea. Every so often he would put on a television program about an issue: how to deal with the budget deficit, say. His people, Congressmen and others would argue different views. Then the public would vote -- by push-button telephone or postcard.</p>
        <p>"If we ever put the people back in charge of this country and make sure they understand the issues," Mr. Perot says, "you'll see the White House and Congress, like a ballet, pirouetting around the stage getting it done in unison."</p>
        <p>Direct democracy. But who will "make sure" the people understand the issues? The opportunities for manipulation are overwhelming.</p>
        <p>Few of the issues that confront governments are so simple that they can be decided by pushing a telephone button or checking a postcard. In fact, that kind of direct democracy is usually a device to transfer real power to a maximum leader.</p>
        <p>Mussolini made himself Il Duce by saying he would end political stalemate and make the trains run on time. At his behest crowds chanted "Duce! Duce! Duce!" and the Italian Parliament was reduced to a rubber stamp.</p>
        <p>Demagogues of all kinds have used popular referendums to overwhelm parliamentary opposition. Fidel Castro tried his opponents before chanting crowds in a football stadium. The image of politicians pirouetting at the people's command is not a happy one, given the history of this century.</p>
        <p>Doubts about Mr. Perot's proposed method of governing are strengthened when one looks carefully at the man who would be in charge. Ross Perot has a record of ruthless determination to get his way when he thinks he is right, which is always.</p>
        <p>Here is a small example, the more frightening because it is so small. John Wheeler, who was chairman of the fund that built the Vietnam War Memorial in Washington, told the story last week in The Los Angeles Times.</p>
        <p>Ross Perot was against Maya Lin's winning design for the memorial, the low black wall with the names of America's dead inscribed in the order of their death. He told Mr. Wheeler that unless the design was changed as he wanted, "I'll wipe you out."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot hired Roy Cohn, the New York lawyer, to stop the memorial from being built as designed. Mr. Cohn demanded the memorial fund's records, charging that it had misused money. An audit showed nothing wrong. Finally, after delay caused by Mr. Perot's obstruction, the memorial was built.</p>
        <p>Frank Borman, the former astronaut, was once hired by Mr. Perot to try out the electronic town meeting idea. But he told Michael Kelly of The New York Times that he had come to think it was a bad idea, one with "enormous potential for manipulating the emotions of people" and intimidating Congress.</p>
        <p>"You realize as you get older that a lot of issues are very profound and difficult to understand," Mr. Borman said. "I don't think you can govern 250 million people with a TV set."</p>
        <p>The founders of the United States, the men who wrote the Constitution, chose not direct democracy but a representative republic. And they created a system with many checks and balances, knowing that it would not be as efficient as a tyranny but preferring liberty to efficiency.</p>
        <p>The checks and balances have become frustrating in our day, with Congress and the Presidency politically divided. But safety is still better than efficiency. Robert Michel, the Republican Leader of the House, made the case when he warned last month against "the glib reply, the demagogue's gift for oversimplification." He said of Ross Perot:</p>
        <p>"He isn't the first, not going to be the last, to say that democracy isn't working and that if you trust me with power I'll solve your problems. That message, sometimes sinister, sometimes just downright silly, has been heard all over the world at various times in this century. That siren call has enchanted good, decent people who are frustrated and disillusioned . . ."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
