<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show of Creations by Artists Who Teach</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CRAFTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HANDICRAFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CERAMICS AND POTTERY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PETERS VALLEY CRAFT CENTER (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREUDENHEIM, BETTY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicrafts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ceramics and Pottery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA1F3DF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1238" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show of Creations by Artists Who Teach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETTY FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREUDENHEIM, BETTY</byline>
      <dateline>LAYTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRAFT collectors scour galleries, fairs and stores for well-designed, well-made contemporary pieces. Those in the know also go directly to the craft artists' studios. In New Jersey, connoisseurs and amateurs alike can find all these resources in one place: the Peters Valley Craft Center.</p>
        <p>The six studios at the center, which is actually a restored historic village, are open to the public from 2 to 4 P.M. daily through Aug. 31. Guided tours begin every Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. in front of the Craft Store porch. Free self-guided walking tour maps, which also are available there, include short histories of a Greek Revival house, a church, cottages and barns, all of which are more than 100 years old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRAFT collectors scour galleries, fairs and stores for well-designed, well-made contemporary pieces. Those in the know also go directly to the craft artists' studios. In New Jersey, connoisseurs and amateurs alike can find all these resources in one place: the Peters Valley Craft Center.</p>
        <p>The six studios at the center, which is actually a restored historic village, are open to the public from 2 to 4 P.M. daily through Aug. 31. Guided tours begin every Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. in front of the Craft Store porch. Free self-guided walking tour maps, which also are available there, include short histories of a Greek Revival house, a church, cottages and barns, all of which are more than 100 years old.</p>
        <p>A trip to the site, which is in the heart of the Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area, can include more than a search for contemporary and traditional crafts. This is a good spot for a spring or summer outing. The hillside site of the Peters Valley Annual Craft Fair, which will be held July 25 and 25, offers a vista of the Kittatinny Mountains.</p>
        <p>The first stop should be the Doremus Gallery, on the second floor of the office building, to view the high-quality work by the 36 craft artists who will be leading 70 workshops at the center this summer. Many are well-known artists who come from other states. Their work includes ceramics, fibers, wood, iron, fine metals and photography.</p>
        <p>Each piece is accompanied by a label outlining the content of a course the artist plans to teach. These descriptions can inform even casual visitors about the artist's technique and creative philosophy.</p>
        <p>Despite the wide variety of media and styles, there are no garish conflicts in the show. Many of the hues are natural, which gives added emphasis to the materials. Some works are functional, others not, but it is evident that these artists are aware of the functional origins of their crafts.</p>
        <p>The most dramatic work is Robert Turner's "Form III." His mat-black stoneware cylinder has the awesome austerity of a medieval tower. Occasional dents, rough spots and scratches imply the slight flaws that might be imposed by time and nature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner, whose home base is Alfred, N. Y., says he tries to be true to the nature of his material, to stay within its limitations. Although his work has been termed "minimalist," his concepts are complex. The shadowy interior of this form seems charged with hidden significance.</p>
        <p>Although the title of Kerr Grabowski's striking "Silk Jacket" gives no clue to her source of inspiration, the fabric looks like an ancient map on which the darkened contours of continents have dissolved into the surging seas. Even the latitudes and longitudes have broken down into squiggly lines. Vertical strokes across the shoulders could be a desperate mariner's notations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Grabowski, who uses the centuries-old batik process for dyeing her fabrics, will teach the traditional and contemporary methods. She is one of five resident artists who live and work the year round in Peters Valley.</p>
        <p>"Dark Portal" by Jennifer Morrow Wilson of Deer Isle, Me., has the ominous aspect of a deep sea creature from a sci-fi film. Working with handmade paper, she has cast a huge, open-mouthed mollusk shape in tones of iridescent blacks. Far within the dim interior are lumpy forms that seem to pulsate and glimmer in the shadows.</p>
        <p>Jere Osgood's small "Florida Table" features the arched and tapered legs that have become the trademark of this Wilton, N.H., artist. Their elegant lines, echoing the spreading roots of a tree, are Mr. Osgood's tribute to his sources. He will be teaching the lamination processes that he has developed during 35 years of furniture making.</p>
        <p>"Cattail Sculpture," by John Graney, the Peters Valley resident blacksmith, looks completely natural, as though it were nourished by the light from a nearby window. But its leaves and stems are rigid metal. Mr. Graney's course will relate plant forms to basic forging procedures and template and die making.</p>
        <p>"Viking Artist," by Nancy Kay Anderson of Metuchen, is an amalgam of basketry and clothing. Although the form resembles a crumpled turtleneck sweater, the fibers were interlaced with white pine and spruce bark. The stitched-together bottom edge and minuscule neck opening indicate that this is not wearable art.</p>
        <p>Her students in the summer workshop will experience the varied processes of basketry from the gathering of natural materials and their preparation to the weaving of decorative and functional pieces.</p>
        <p>Amy Roper's course is titled "Bone: A Jeweler's Alternative." This jewelry maker from Summit prepares and carves raw bones so that they can be used as substitutes for ivory. Her "Eldorado Brooch #1" is an abstract figure made of gold. A flat horizontal segment of bone forms the torso and outstretched arms. The title suggests the legendary South American king who, it was said, powdered his body with gold dust each morning and washed it off each evening in the lake.</p>
        <p>Jim Jansma, the resident ceramist, is showing his "Anagama Wall Piece." The texture of this thick slab is rough with cavities and projections. Fused and mottled tones of beige, brown and gray give it the aspect of a rock wall in the deep interior of a cave. A few incised lines are reminders of the cave drawings engraved by prehistoric artists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jansma will direct the loading and firing of a 50-foot-long Japanese-style anagama kiln that has been constructed on a hillside. The wood firing, which takes seven days, is scheduled for July 13 through 19. Participants will work in shifts to tend the slow but constant fire; smoke and flames surge from the kilns as the interior temperature rises to 2,400 degrees.</p>
        <p>Another week must pass before the kiln is cool enough to unload the ceramics. Melted wood ashes and smoldering coals create color variations on the clay, which range from warm earth tones to blue grays. The drama of this firing is one of the highlights of the summer sessions.</p>
        <p>The Doremus Gallery exhibition continues through Aug. 16. It will be followed by a show of work by the studio assistants from Aug. 22 to 30. The gallery is open from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. seven days a week. Admission is free.</p>
        <p>The Peters Valley Craft Store is featuring "A Vase by Any Other Name," a display of works in many media. James Holmes's glass containers look like miniature pumpkins that were dipped in Easter egg dyes of green, indigo and yellow. The stems are bright red.</p>
        <p>An elliptical vase by a ceramist, John Shedd, is sea green with drips of red glaze flowing down the side, like berry stains. John Garshwiler and Holiday Hays have stitched vessels of bark. One has woodpecker holes in the side.</p>
        <p>The white porcelain bowls by Andrea Joseph are delightful fantasies. Three or four tiny fish swim above each top opening as though they were trying to enter their fishbowls.</p>
        <p>These works will be shown through June. "Artipins," a selection of pins by 10 artisans, is scheduled for June and July. Other sections of the two-story store feature handcrafted furniture, toys, metalwork, wearable items and kitchen accessories. The shop is open throughout the year, seven days a week from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>Peters Valley, in Sussex County, can be reached by taking Route 206 north and turning left at Route 560. In the center of Layton, take Route 640 about a mile and turn right on Route 615 for another mile.  CRAFTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
