<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tough Market For Summer Jobs</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">YOUTH, EMPLOYMENT OF</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER PRIVATE INDUSTRY COUNCIL</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">YONKERS PRIVATE INDUSTRIES COUNCIL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINGER, PENNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D7103CF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tough Market For Summer Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SINGER, PENNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years ago, Ervin R. Schanes, then a product manager at General Foods in White Plains, was alarmed by the number of teen-age participants in the Watts riots in Los Angeles. He came up with an idea to help minority and disadvantaged young people in Westchester understand the workings of American business, by giving them a chance to work in the corporate world.</p>
        <p>"The management of General Foods thought the idea was good and decided to develop it into a program called Operation Opportunity," said Deborah Shields, manager of community affairs for the company, which is now Kraft General Foods. "Since Operation Opportunity began a quarter of a century ago, more than 1,500 junior and senior high school students have gone through the program."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWENTY-FIVE years ago, Ervin R. Schanes, then a product manager at General Foods in White Plains, was alarmed by the number of teen-age participants in the Watts riots in Los Angeles. He came up with an idea to help minority and disadvantaged young people in Westchester understand the workings of American business, by giving them a chance to work in the corporate world.</p>
        <p>"The management of General Foods thought the idea was good and decided to develop it into a program called Operation Opportunity," said Deborah Shields, manager of community affairs for the company, which is now Kraft General Foods. "Since Operation Opportunity began a quarter of a century ago, more than 1,500 junior and senior high school students have gone through the program."</p>
        <p>The program provides young people from low-income families with summer jobs. It also helps them go to college. "Every dollar they earn on the job is matched with a dollar from Kraft General Foods, which is put in an escrow account for them," Miss Shields said. 90 Companies Provide Jobs</p>
        <p>This summer, despite the worst job market in 50 years, 55 students from 8 Westchester high schools will be employed at Kraft General Foods in White Plains, in jobs ranging from working with computers and acting as sales and marketing assistants to serving as research laboratory helpers.</p>
        <p>Ninety other companies are also committed to providing jobs for young people this summer, under the Summer Jobs for Youth program, a public-private partnership designed to provide young people from low-income Westchester families with summer work experience. Summer Jobs for Youth matches job openings with qualified high school graduates or college students 16 through 21 years old.</p>
        <p>The program is a joint effort of the Westchester and Yonkers Private Industries Councils, with support each year from a different corporate sponsor. This year the lead organization is the New York Power Authority. Since its inception, the program has found summer jobs in Westchester companies for more than 6,500 students. The sponsors are responsible for recruiting corporate participants.</p>
        <p>"Finding jobs for the students has been harder this year," said John C. Brons, president of the Power Authority. "But in these tough times, it's doubly important to give young people a chance." Firms Asked to 'Dig Deeper'</p>
        <p>The program is one of the most successful in the nation, Mr. Brons said. "In the face of what has happened in Los Angeles, we have been urging companies to dig deeper and come up with the jobs," he added. "Education becomes more meaningful when students are able to use what they have learned in school on the job."</p>
        <p>For some students in the Kraft General Foods program, the summer job may lead to full-time employment and a career with the company.</p>
        <p>Allan Edgar is an example. Mr. Edgar, 24 years old and a graduate of Mercy College who majored in business administration, was a junior at Woodlands High School in Hartsdale when his adviser suggested that he apply for the Kraft General Foods program.</p>
        <p>"I was lucky," Mr. Edgar said. "I had an interview, and I got a job maintaining equipment in the audio-visual department, which I had for two summers. The experience gave me a jump start. Working at General Foods opened my eyes to real life. I saw the value of an education. I come from a family of five kids, so without that money to get me started in college, I would probably have procrastinated and maybe never gone."</p>
        <p>After graduating from college, Mr. Edgar, who lives in Greenburgh, said he explored various job possibilities by working as a temporary at General Foods. He feels that he has embarked on a good career as a members' service representative in the Kraft General Foods credit union. At 18, Her Fourth Summer</p>
        <p>"I give members advice and counsel them and help them with loans," he said. "It's interesting and rewarding work."</p>
        <p>Donna Catwell, 18 and a graduate of White Plains High School, has just finished her freshman year at Boston College in Chestnut Hill, Mass. Ms. Catwell spent the last three summers working in the sales and promotion department of the dessert division, known for Jell-O, puddings, cheesecakes and similar Kraft General Foods products.</p>
        <p>This year she is back at Kraft General Foods as a coordinator of the Operation Opportunity program. "Donna will be acting as my liaison with the students," Ms. Shields said.</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Catwell, who said she wants to be a lawyer, her work experience at Kraft "gave me a great chance to earn a salary and save money besides," she said. "The money deposited for me by Kraft General Foods paid for my freshman year at college."  Employers Are Said to Benefit, Too</p>
        <p>Underscoring the importance of the summer jobs program are countless success stories, said Mr. Brons, at the New York Power Authority. "In our company, for instance, a student who was turned on to science after spending a summer in our nuclear engineering department, has gone on to a promising career."</p>
        <p>And almost equally important, Mr. Brons said, the program benefits employers.</p>
        <p>"One thing I feel strongly about is to dispel any perception of the program as an exercise in charity," he said. "We are not giving these kids make-work. They are all qualified and trained and pre-screened before they go out on an interview.</p>
        <p>"What they are is a good source of employees for companies. And as a further inducement, the companies that hire them don't pay a cent in fees. Instead, they get a tax credit of $600 for hiring a student for a summer job, which goes up to $3,000 if a student is offered a permanent job." Fewer Jobs Than Last Year</p>
        <p>Renee Guy, director of the Westchester County Private Industry Council, and Dr. Marvin W. Lewis, director of the Yonkers Private Industry Council, both said that finding more and more jobs was crucial to the program's success.</p>
        <p>"In this economy it has been difficult," Dr. Lewis said. "Last year at this time we had 450 jobs committed. This year, 302. At the same time we have more young people, especially those of college age, who need jobs really badly this year."</p>
        <p>Dr. Lewis said he has been doing a lot of cold canvassing in search of jobs. "This year I have been trying to sell the value of the program to smaller companies that have never been in it before. I was able to get commitments from several retail stores in Yonkers, and from the Philharmonic Office in Dobbs Ferry."</p>
        <p>Raymond T. Murphy, general manager of the Westchester field division of the United States Postal Service in Mount Vernon, said the Postal Service has agreed to provide 20 jobs for the program.</p>
        <p>"We have been participating in this since 1985, and as an employer I can honestly say that the caliber of the employee we get is very high," Mr. Murphy said. "The young people we get are qualified for work as summer replacements such as clerks and mail distributors throughout our offices. We have about a 50 percent repeat every year." An Incentive for College</p>
        <p>The summer job she got through the program gave Claudette Anderson the incentive to go to college.</p>
        <p>Ms. Anderson, a recent graduate of Hampton University in Virginia, said that working summers while she was in high school at the Fairview Country Club in Greenwich gave her more confidence in her own abilities.</p>
        <p>"On the job, I found that I could handle responsibility, and I was pretty good at organization," she said. "I also realized the value of education if I wanted a career, not just a job."</p>
        <p>Employers or students who are interested in the Summer Jobs for Youth program can contact the project director, Nancy Gold, at 285-3398 for additional information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
