<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trial of a Swiss Au Pair Could Use Translators</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BABIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NANNIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARSON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RINER, OLIVIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISCHER, KRISTIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DE1F3DF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trial of a Swiss Au Pair Could Use Translators</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, June 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers have their own styles.</p>
        <p>Intense is the style of George L. Bolen, the prosecutor of Olivia Riner, the Swiss au pair charged with the arson murder of the baby in her care.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolen is sometimes so focused on details that he seems to lose track of the ordinary way people talk to one other. In Bolenspeak, the time 4:42 came out "four-point-four-two." Sometimes, the prosecutor will stop midsentence, look up at the ceiling and, after a pause, explain, "I'm looking for the word."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers have their own styles.</p>
        <p>Intense is the style of George L. Bolen, the prosecutor of Olivia Riner, the Swiss au pair charged with the arson murder of the baby in her care.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolen is sometimes so focused on details that he seems to lose track of the ordinary way people talk to one other. In Bolenspeak, the time 4:42 came out "four-point-four-two." Sometimes, the prosecutor will stop midsentence, look up at the ceiling and, after a pause, explain, "I'm looking for the word."</p>
        <p>Questions to witnesses are often a special thicket.</p>
        <p>Here is one Mr. Bolen posed last week: "During that time when you purchased it, and while you were working on it and during the process of your hanging it, were you able to determine the depth of the inside and the outside of the door that was hollow between the two? Do you understand what I'm saying?"</p>
        <p>Judge Donald N. Silverman of Westchester County Court translated: "How thick was the door altogether?"</p>
        <p>Judges have their own styles, too.</p>
        <p>Direct is Judge Silverman's. What to Make of Looks?</p>
        <p>At the defense table, Miss Riner has the same wide-eyed look of a doe caught in the headlights that she had in the chaos of her arraignment last December.</p>
        <p>Both sides have drawn attention to the young woman's docile appearance. Laura A. Brevetti, the defense lawyer, told the jurors to study her 20-year-old client: her stature, her hands and her light-brown hair that is cut in long bangs. The jurors should watch her, the lawyer said, to see if they could picture such a girl doing the horrible things the prosecution says she did.</p>
        <p>Miss Riner, Ms. Brevetti said, "has been under a microscope for six months -- she can stand to be under it a little longer."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bolen, too, had to confront the issue of Miss Riner's gentle appearance. But the way he did it set off an international literary discussion of sorts on the 14th floor of the Westchester County Courthouse.</p>
        <p>In his opening statement to the jurors, the prosecutor cited the title of a famous Swiss story by the 19th century writer Gottfried Keller. It is titled "Kleider machen Leute" in German, which the prosecutor translated as "Clothes Don't Make the Person." That, he said, was another way of saying, "Appearances can be deceiving."</p>
        <p>The trial has drawn a small contingent of Swiss journalists, who say readers back home are especially skeptical of the prosecution's claims against the young Swiss woman.</p>
        <p>Outside in the hallway after Mr. Bolen's remarks -- and for much of last week -- the Swiss reporters were kept busy retelling the Keller story and explaining how Mr. Bolen had incorrectly translated its title.</p>
        <p>In the story, famous in Switzerland, a poor man dresses in the clothes of the gentry and passes, for a while, for something he is not. The proper translation of the title, some of the Swiss journalists told their American counterparts, was something closer to an ironic "Clothes Make People," not Mr. Bolen's "Clothes Don't Make the Person."</p>
        <p>The Swiss reporters would not speculate on whether the theme of the story -- that people sometimes masquerade as something they are not -- could be applied to Miss Riner's case. Nor would they discuss the significance of the end of the famous tale: the imposter is unmasked. A Brittle Edge to the Routine</p>
        <p>In the normal to and fro of any courtroom case, the rhythm of the legal process usually takes over so that the participants can get through the days, no matter how appalling the topic.</p>
        <p>That has happened in Miss Riner's case. Still, there are times when there is a sharp reminder in the courtroom that all of these people are together to try to find out whether a young woman set fire to a 3-month-old baby girl one day this winter.</p>
        <p>One of those moments occurred last week when the defense lawyer, Ms. Brevetti, was cross-examining the infant's father, William Fischer.</p>
        <p>The defense lawyer seemed to think she had found an inconsistency in the testimony Mr. Fischer had given for the prosecution. She pursued that point, for every weakness in Mr. Fischer's account could be a benefit to Miss Riner. By the time the lawyer had forced Mr. Fischer to explain himself, it was too late to stop him from providing another one of those reminders of what the Fischers have lived through.</p>
        <p>A major point in the prosecution case is the contention that Miss Riner, in one unguarded moment immediately after the fire, admitted to Mr. Fischer and to his 22-year-old daughter, Leah, that Miss Riner had closed the door to the room where 3-month-old Kristie was found. Since then, the former au pair has maintained that she did not close the door and does not know why it was locked after the fire had begun.</p>
        <p>In his testimony for the prosecution, Mr. Fischer said he had been standing next to Miss Riner outside the still burning house on Dec. 2. He asked the au pair what had happened, he had testified, and the au pair told him she had gone to feed the family's four cats and closed the nursery door.  Mr. Fischer testified that the au pair told him that soon after that she saw or smelled smoke and found a fire on her bed in another room.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fischer had said that after Miss Riner had given him her account outside of the house, he had noticed for the first time that his adult daughter, Leah, was standing next to him. He turned, he said, and told Leah "what happened."</p>
        <p>That was the point the defense lawyer pursued. For if Leah Fischer had only heard from her father that the au pair had admitted closing the baby's door, no one could corroborate Mr. Fischer's account of the au pair's alleged admission.</p>
        <p>But that was not, Mr. Fischer told the defense lawyer, what he meant.</p>
        <p>What then, she asked, had he meant when he said he "told Leah what happened?"</p>
        <p>"I told her," Mr. Fischer said, "that the baby died in the fire."  REPORTER'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
