<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Repairing and Replacing the Many Types of Siding</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD153FF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Repairing and Replacing the Many Types of Siding</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVERAL styles of wood siding are popular. They include shingles, shakes, clapboards, lap siding, plywood panels and boards and battens.</p>
        <p>Properly applied and either sealed or painted about every five years, each kind should last at least 30 years. But damage to wood siding has to be repaired promptly to prevent worsening, especially in new houses that lack wood sheathing behind the siding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVERAL styles of wood siding are popular. They include shingles, shakes, clapboards, lap siding, plywood panels and boards and battens.</p>
        <p>Properly applied and either sealed or painted about every five years, each kind should last at least 30 years. But damage to wood siding has to be repaired promptly to prevent worsening, especially in new houses that lack wood sheathing behind the siding.</p>
        <p>Loose nails are a common problem. Try hammering them back by using a nailset to avoid marring the siding or cracking it if it is warped. If a nail does not hold when redriven, substitute a longer one or a screw. If those do not hold, either supporting material behind the siding is missing or the material may be decayed or damaged.</p>
        <p>Missing material usually occurs only in new houses having siding other than shingles or shakes. They are often sheathed with rigid foam insulation, except at the corners, and siding is fastened with long nails that pass through the foam into the wall studs. The studs are at 16- or 24-inch intervals.</p>
        <p>Note the positions of the nails above and below or on each side of the loose one. Aligning the nail with those when reinstalling it should solve the problem.</p>
        <p>Before driving a siding nail in a new position, blunt the point by striking it with a hammer. That will prevent the siding from splitting. When nailing near the end of a board or installing a screw, drill a pilot hole through the siding instead.</p>
        <p>If several nails in an area do not hold, look for moisture or pests behind the siding. Both can destroy wood sheathing or studs, as well as siding. Likely places for either to enter are near gutters, windows, doors, openings for pipes and other features, and where siding is damaged or the pieces are separated. Pests can also enter from near the ground. Signs of infestation include narrow tubes of dried mud or small piles of sawdust.</p>
        <p>Correct any actual or potential moisture and pest problems before repairing the siding. For moisture problems, be sure that gutters and downspouts are clear and that the sections fit together tightly or are caulked along the seams. Gutters must slope toward downspouts.</p>
        <p>All seams where siding meets other materials should be caulked. Rotted trim around windows and doors or above siding can also be a culprit. Investigate that and repair or replace the materials, if necessary. For pest problems, it is best to call an exterminator.</p>
        <p>To remove shingles, shakes, clapboards or lap siding during or after fixing the problems, remove the trim at the roof line and pry the siding away from the wall piece by piece with a flat prybar. Board and batten siding and plywood panels, neither of which overlaps like the other types, can be pried away by starting at any seam.</p>
        <p>In all cases, work carefully, so that the siding can be reattached if it is not badly damaged. Small areas of decay or pest infestations can be scraped away and coated with wood-hardening liquid available at hardware stores. Major damage to siding, sheathing or framing usually requires replacing pieces.</p>
        <p>Severe moisture and pest problems are relatively rare. Most of the time repairing wood siding amounts to mending or replacing individual pieces. Fill cracks with caulking or waterproof construction adhesive, and restore small broken areas with wood-restoring compound, a two-part filling product.</p>
        <p>To remove a badly damaged shingle or shake without disturbing others above it, first split it into several pieces with a hammer and chisel and pull out as many of the pieces as possible. Next, remove the nails holding it -- these are underneath the row of siding above -- by inserting beneath the siding the blade of a plunge-cutting hacksaw, a hacksaw with a handle at one end. Cut the nails in two close to the wall. Instead of a plunge-cutting hacksaw, an ordinary hacksaw blade can be used. Wrap tape around one end to create a handle.</p>
        <p>Measure and cut a replacement shingle or shake to fit the space and to align along its bottom edge with the rest of the row when installed. Slide the new piece into place, but leave the bottom edge extending below its neighbors by about half an inch.</p>
        <p>Install two siding nails through the shingle or shake at the top, below the row of siding above. Angle the nails so that they will straighten and slide beneath the overlapping siding when the new shingle or shake is tapped upward. Hold a piece of scrap wood against the bottom of the new piece and hit it with a hammer to drive it home.</p>
        <p>Replacing clapboard or lap siding is somewhat similar. First, drive wedges beneath the damaged board to hold it away from the one below. Place a protective scrap of wood against the lower board and use a backsaw to saw through the exposed part of the damaged board. Plan the cuts removing the damaged section so that they are over the centers of studs.</p>
        <p>Next, reinstall the wedges to lift the overlapping siding away from the damaged piece. Then use a compass saw to finish cutting beneath the raised board or boards.</p>
        <p>Pry out or saw through any nails holding the section, then slide it out. After cutting a piece of replacement siding to fit snugly, coat its ends, and those of the pieces on each side, with primer. Fasten the new piece by installing a single siding nail at each end so that it penetrates the stud, but does not enter the siding in the row below. Also install a nail in the original siding on each side of the patch. Finish by caulking the seams between sections.  HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
