<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bright, Shining or Dark: American Way of Lying</title>
    <meta content="16SCOT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980823T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Janny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DA113AF935A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bright, Shining or Dark: American Way of Lying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American ways of lying to avoid embarrassment, spare feelings or get one's own way discussed in light of Pres Clinton's upcoming testimony in Monica Lewinsky scandal; photo of Grant Wood's painting of George Washington confessing to arborcide (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LYING is bad. So Americans say. They tell pollsters they are no good at it, it is difficult, they rarely lie. In the tradition of Lake Wobegon (''where the women are strong, the men are good looking and all of the children are above average''), they think they are more honest than everyone else.</p>
        <p>Yet lying is everywhere: lies to children, lies to voters, lies to the Internal Revenue Service, lies under oath. People lie to avoid embarrassment, to spare feelings, to get their way. And, when confronted with a lie, they justify it: The lie was harmless, the truth would have hurt, the ends justified the means.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LYING is bad. So Americans say. They tell pollsters they are no good at it, it is difficult, they rarely lie. In the tradition of Lake Wobegon (''where the women are strong, the men are good looking and all of the children are above average''), they think they are more honest than everyone else.</p>
        <p>Yet lying is everywhere: lies to children, lies to voters, lies to the Internal Revenue Service, lies under oath. People lie to avoid embarrassment, to spare feelings, to get their way. And, when confronted with a lie, they justify it: The lie was harmless, the truth would have hurt, the ends justified the means.</p>
        <p>A Matter of Degree</p>
        <p>They are even willing to overlook lying in others. Mike Barnicle, the columnist at The Boston Globe, still has his job, even after misleading his readers or his editors or his viewers or all three. President Clinton is widely believed to have lied about his sex life, yet most Americans seem not to care.</p>
        <p>''Everyone lies about sex,'' Jerry Seinfeld said during his Broadway show when someone from the audience asked for a joke about Mr. Clinton. ''People lie during sex. If it weren't for lies, there'd be no sex.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is scheduled to tell the truth tomorrow in the grand jury investigation of his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky. But responding honestly to a narrowly defined question may represent a sin of omission that does not constitute honesty as most people know it.</p>
        <p>Sex may be the all-time favorite exception to the rule that honesty is the best policy, research on lying and anecdotal evidence suggest. But there are other common situations where many Americans think it may be all right not to tell the truth.</p>
        <p>* It is okay to lie to hide something that will be used unfairly against you or others, or to to conceal information that an inquisitor has no right to have (the classic Nazis-at-the-door-while-the-Jews-are-in-the-attic exception, stretched in contemporary life to justify paying the baby sitter off the books because the employer cannot afford child care otherwise).</p>
        <p>* Elected officials can lie in a national emergency to protect hostages, mislead the enemy, win the war. (Though Americans tend not to make a case for politicians lying, they take it for granted that their elected officials do as a rule.)</p>
        <p>* Little white lies are fine, many people insist, when the intent is benign (''What a beautiful baby, necktie, salad bowl!'')</p>
        <p>* Lies to help other people are more acceptable than those to help oneself. A friend might lie to a friend, or a parent to a child, when the truth could hurt and the deception would not.</p>
        <p>''The principle here, if there is a principle, is you must never lie unless you must,'' said Alexander Nehamas, a professor of philosophy at Princeton.</p>
        <p>''Ironically, one of the most necessary lies we tell our children is you must never lie. Then we turn around and, when it suits us, pretend to believe the principle ourselves.''</p>
        <p>There is, of course, little support for lying in religious literature. St. Augustine opposed it absolutely. Christian and Jewish traditions strongly discourage it. To the Catholic Church, it is a sin against God's gift of speech.</p>
        <p>Honesty, on the other hand, is the foundation upon which relationships and many societies are built. Without it, it is said, there can be no trust. Widespread lying destroys the fabric of democratic societies, in which the necessary assumption is that people mostly tell the truth.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to tell a lie, there had better be a serious moral reason for it,'' said Joseph C. Hough, professor of Christian ethics and dean of Vanderbilt Divinity School. ''Not every single thing that's unpleasant is a moral reason. I think you can find gentle ways to tell the truth.''</p>
        <p>Yet even the religious literature allows exceptions. In Catholic moral tradition, there is the so-called principle of overriding right, which recognizes that there are times when a more important principle than truth-telling is at stake, such as the principle of protecting human life.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Joel Roth, a professor of Talmud and rabbinic literature at the Jewish Theological Seminary in New York City, said that while there is little tolerance in rabbinic literature for lying, and while lying is always forbidden in a judicial proceeding, some white lying may be allowed.</p>
        <p>He cited a passage in chapter 18 of the book of Genesis in which God omits to mention to Abraham an unflattering comment by his wife. From that passage and at least one other, Rabbi Roth said, rabbis deduce that some white lies may be acceptable in preserving family harmony.</p>
        <p>There is little research on how and when Americans lie. But Bella M. DePaulo, a professor of psychology at the University of Virginia, recently studied everyday lying by 77 college students and 70 individuals in a community. All kept weeklong diaries detailing their interactions and the lies they told.</p>
        <p>Everyday Fibs</p>
        <p>Professor DePaulo found that virtually everyone lied. The students averaged two lies a day, the others one. The vast majority of lies were told to spare the liar embarrassment or to make him or her look better. The benefit was psychic, not material. In her studies of serious lying, as opposed to everyday lying, Dr. DePaulo has found that a quarter of all serious lies were told to cover an affair. She said scholarly literature on lying suggests that Americans also find lying more acceptable when the behavior it is concealing was discreet.</p>
        <p>''There is a very important distinction between the acceptability of the lie and the acceptability of the behavior that the lie is covering up,'' she said. ''If someone says, 'It's O.K. with me that he lied about it,' they are not saying, 'It's O.K. with me that he had an affair.' ''</p>
        <p>Some scholars, including Stephen L. Carter, the Yale law professor and author of ''Integrity'' (Basic Books, 1996), suspect that lying has increased. And when adults accept lying as natural, Mr. Carter says, children learn the lesson that the adult world's rules are unreliable and open to manipulation.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Alan Wolfe, the Boston University sociologist, who is researching a book on moral freedom, contends that Americans are simply learning to write their own moral rules, now that institutions like the church no longer manage to do it for them.</p>
        <p>''Americans are pretty savvy about this,'' said Amy Gutmann, director of the Center for Human Values at Princeton University. ''They think that some kinds of lies are far less bad than others. But they think that someone who can lie very well does not have good character.''</p>
        <p>THE NATION  Correction:  August 23, 1998, Sunday  Because of a production error, a picture of Grant Wood's painting ''Parson Weems' Fable'' on Aug. 16, illustrating the history of lying in America, was printed in mirror image. Parson Weems should appear at the right.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 23, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, a picture of Grant Wood's painting ''Parson Weems' Fable'' on Aug. 16, illustrating the history of lying in America, was printed in mirror image. Parson Weems should appear at the right.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
