<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sore Winner</title>
    <meta content="16SAFIRT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Crime and Law Enforcement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (Ethnic, Racial, Religious)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Howard Safir</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safir, Howard (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bratton, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DF163AF935A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="3045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sore Winner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeffrey Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Jeffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeffrey Goldberg profile of New York City Police Comr Howard Safir; says his predecessor, William Bratton, has claimed credit for impressive drop in crime in city, as has Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani, but Safir, who has contributed his fair share of new crime-fighting ideas, keeps low profile; says Safir studied lessons of Bratton's premature demise, and unlike Bratton, Safir defers to Giuliani in public, dissenting with him only in private meetings, and does not seek spotlight for himself; says this might explain in part why Safir and Giuliani get along so well; says members of city's minorities, as well as many civil libertarians, question some police methods and accuse department of being tolerant of police racism and brutality; notes Safir's heated denial of such charges; says Safir shares with Giuliani firm belief that Police Dept is made up of good people doing what is best for city's minority communities. even if some of leaders of those communities might think otherwise; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'So,'' says the Mayor, breaking his silence, ''how was the hearing?''</p>
        <p>''City Council?'' asks the Police Commissioner. ''The usual -- a battle of wits with unarmed men.'' The alpha males of the Giuliani administration, seated helter-skelter about the Mayor's office, get a kick out of that one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'So,'' says the Mayor, breaking his silence, ''how was the hearing?''</p>
        <p>''City Council?'' asks the Police Commissioner. ''The usual -- a battle of wits with unarmed men.'' The alpha males of the Giuliani administration, seated helter-skelter about the Mayor's office, get a kick out of that one.</p>
        <p>Silence again, as the Mayor continues reading. He is sunk low in his chair. Seated to his left is the Police Commissioner, the square-jawed Howard Safir, who sits erect, in the manner of Parris Island. The Mayor's men are jacketless, overweight and at ease. The Commissioner's men appear ready to salute.</p>
        <p>This is the Mayor's weekly police briefing, a Mamet-like gathering of Giuliani's hard men. It is also Safir's own personal Compstat. Compstat is the crime-tracking program instituted by Safir's predecessor, the hated (in this room) William Bratton. At Compstat, police commanders are grilled without mercy when they fail to beat down crime in their precincts. Safir is aware that a direct link exists between the city's falling homicide rate and Giuliani's national political ambitions. He also knows that police commissioners who fail to take note of that link are replaceable.</p>
        <p>''How's the crime stats?'' asks the Mayor, studying Safir's weekly report.</p>
        <p>''Best week ever,'' the Commissioner says.</p>
        <p>''Better than the blizzard?'' asks the Mayor.</p>
        <p>''Nope,'' Safir says. ''Except the blizzard.''</p>
        <p>''Tough to beat a blizzard,'' answers the Mayor. He scans the report as if it were a buffet, ignoring most of its bulleted items, raising only the subjects -- quality-of-life issues, mainly -- that move him.</p>
        <p>''What's our new euphemism for barricades?'' the Mayor asks.</p>
        <p>''Separators,'' the Commissioner says, to laughter again. ''Pedestrian separators.''</p>
        <p>An air of satisfaction, smugness even, permeates the office. Indeed, there is much to be satisfied about: crime is down beyond anyone's wildest imaginings, and the N.Y.P.D. has suffered no metastatic corruption scandals. There was the Abner Louima assault, of course, which critics say is proof that racism and brutality are baked into New York's police culture. But Giuliani's men blame only a tiny cell of rogue cops for Louima's trauma, and are quick to praise themselves for uprooting that cell.</p>
        <p>This meeting is taking place well before investigators exposed a nest of officers in the Midtown South Precinct suspected of frequenting a brothel, but Safir and Giuliani would find a way to turn even that Letterman-ready embarrassment to their favor: Safir said that it was his new anti-corruption procedures that led to the discovery of the dirty officers -- who, as he and the Mayor repeatedly noted, had escaped discovery by previous administrations.</p>
        <p>What seems to bother Giuliani most is when his Police Department doesn't receive sufficient credit for its good works. Though he is pleased to read in Safir's report that several weapons were seized in a raid on a Times Square pornography establishment, he is bothered that the press did not give the story prominent play.</p>
        <p>''We should have made more of this,'' Giuliani says. From the couch, the Chief of Department, Louis Anemone, pipes up. ''I'll see what else we got in the hopper,'' he says, a promise of more publicity for future raids.</p>
        <p>Talk turns to a recent move by Safir to institute merit bonuses for outstanding officers. The Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, like most unions, opposes such bonuses, and has been fighting the Mayor on the subject. The Commissioner now tells the Mayor to stand tough. ''If you ask the average cop what the Mayor's done for him, 'squat' is what they say, and from their perspective they're right,'' he says. The Mayor, who is not known for his love of dissension, merely nods in agreement. Safir's snub-nosed bluntness raises no eyebrows in this room. It seems as if everyone here has heard it before.</p>
        <p>Few people outside the room, however, have heard Safir talk this way to the Mayor -- and this is the secret of Howard Safir's success. When Mayor Giuliani dethroned William Bratton in 1996, he rid himself of a Police Commissioner whose crime-cutting innovations helped insure his re-election. But the minor miracle Bratton performed for the city didn't count for much with Giuliani, who believed, not incorrectly, that Bratton's miracle would have been impossible to perform without the direction of City Hall -- and who also believed that Bratton deliberately forgot that it was Giuliani who was the elected official.</p>
        <p>Safir studied the lessons of Bratton's premature demise, and he is a loyalist's loyalist. He has spent no time cultivating the press: he maintains arctic relations with most police reporters, and in any case he possesses none of Bratton's deftness and charm. Instead of the press, Safir cultivates the Mayor. Successfully, by all evidence.</p>
        <p>''Bratton was good at public relations and spending time at Elaine's and coming up with glossy presentations,'' Giuliani told me, ''but I had to supply the substance. Three-quarters of his ideas were ideas we gave him. The roles were reversed. I was the substantive person, and the Police Commissioner was the politician. With Howard, substance comes first. He's involved in the issues much more, so I am free to be Mayor.''</p>
        <p>Bratton, not surprisingly, sees Giuliani's attempt to play down his contribution as gross revisionism. ''The Mayor doesn't know what the hell he's talking about,'' Bratton says. ''Any attempt by the Mayor to diminish our role, that's where we push back. Sorry, fella. History is a difficult thing to rewrite.''</p>
        <p>The Mayor says that his trust in Safir, unlike his trust in Bratton, is near absolute. The two men grew close in the early 80's, when Safir served as operations chief of the United States Marshals Service, the fugitive-hunting branch of the Justice Department, and Giuliani was the No. 3 official at Justice. When President Reagan was shot, Giuliani turned to Safir to take charge of John Hinckley's safety. I once asked Giuliani why he didn't pick Safir at the outset of his mayoralty to serve as Police Commissioner, and he laughed and said, ''I've asked myself that question a few times.''</p>
        <p>Safir makes it clear that he would rather have come first. At the Marshals Service, Safir was known as an innovator who revamped the problem-plagued Witness Security Program and invented Con Air, the Federal prisoner transport service. But in his current role, he is known as a competent bureaucrat who implements the ideas of his larger-than-life predecessor. Jack Maple, Bratton's anticrime strategist, explains Safir's quandary: ''I think Commissioner Safir's doing an excellent job, but he's like Larry Holmes. He's following Muhammad Ali. Holmes was a very good champion, but he was never going to be the greatest.''</p>
        <p>Safir claims no resentment of Bratton, but the evidence contradicts him. ''I once went after Khun Sa'' (the Burmese drug baron), he told me, discussing his own career as an international drug-buster. ''No offense to Bill Bratton, but I wasn't some airport cop in Boston. I did things Bill Bratton couldn't even dream of.'' When I tell him of Maple's cutting comparison, he grows angry and says: ''He's saying I followed Muhammad Ali? I didn't follow Muhammad Ali. I followed P.T. Barnum.''</p>
        <p>P.T. Barnum?</p>
        <p>''Bratton didn't know what the hell was going on in this building,'' he says, referring to Police Headquarters. ''I'm not here for press relations. I'm here to reduce crime.''</p>
        <p>There is little doubt that Safir has contributed his fair share of new crime-fighting ideas. And crime has dropped under Safir at an even faster pace than it did under Bratton. If current trends continue, New York will see fewer than 600 homicides this year, down an astonishing 75 percent from six years ago. The expectation of ever-lower crime numbers has led police departments in some cities to intentionally underreport or reclassify crimes; the head of the N.Y.P.D.'s Transportation Bureau was forced to resign this year because his commanders had reclassified subway crimes as street crimes, but Safir insists that the overall crime numbers were not affected. New York is so much safer than it was even two years ago, in fact, that Giuliani and Safir are facing hard questions about their priorities.</p>
        <p>A recent spate of clumsily executed search warrants, in which innocent civilians were manhandled by police raiders, has civil libertarians and minority leaders asking whether the Police Department has gone too far in its war on crime. Even Bratton and Maple say that the new, lower-crime reality demands a fine-tuning of the department's priorities, including a reduction in the number of cops.</p>
        <p>The Mayor -- the taxi-bashing, hot-dog-cart-busting, sex-shop-closing Mayor -- will hear none of this, and neither will his Police Commissioner.</p>
        <p>If anything, Safir has intensified the department's crackdown on drugs. By training and belief, he is a hard-core drug warrior; already, the effects of his antidrug program, a mix of punitive and preventive measures, have been felt in the counties that surround the city, which have seen a spike in drug dealing. ''They're going to New Jersey and Westchester and Nassau to deal drugs,'' Safir says without apology. ''The police chief of one of these towns challenged me to a fistfight over this. But my job is to get rid of drug dealing in the five boroughs.''</p>
        <p>The effects have also been seen in the New York City neighborhoods -- Washington Heights, for example -- that have revived after police officers finished rousting the drug dealers. The question is, have they done this without sweeping up innocent people in the process? Many black leaders -- and the dwindling band of Manhattan civil libertarians who refuse to unambiguously endorse Giuliani's anticrime crusade -- say no. ''Based on the crime statistics, Safir should be applauded in every community, but he's not, because the black and Hispanic communities feel as if they're under siege,'' says Norman Siegel head of the New York Civil Liberties Union and Safir's most persistent critic.</p>
        <p>Another critic, Bill Perkins, a City Councilman from Harlem, says he himself has been a victim of police overzealousness. Last year, he says, he awoke to find three officers trying to enter his apartment. ''My son-in-law woke me and said there's someone at the door,'' Perkins says. ''These three cops come in and say they're looking for someone, and they give me the name. I said there's no one here by that name. They didn't believe me and asked for ID. I was cooperative because I know how to act in these situations. They asked rudely who my son-in-law was. I'm glad it wasn't my son-in-law who dealt with them, because he has dreadlocks and a Caribbean accent. He's not someone these three white cops could relate to. I kept telling the cops, 'Read your warrant.' It turns out they got the building wrong. It's 5 o'clock in the morning and these cops barge in without reading the damn warrant.''</p>
        <p>Perkins says he never received an apology from the Commissioner. The Commissioner says no apology is in order. ''Look, Perkins has a political agenda,'' Safir says. ''And no one threw anybody against the wall, or kicked in doors. The police left after they were told the person wasn't there.''</p>
        <p>Safir is consistently unapologetic. When I mention to him an incident in which an innocent civilian, hearing the police crash through his door with a battering ram, pulled out a handgun and fired over the top of the door, Safir says, ''Oh, yeah, the poor guy with the illegal gun in the Bronx.''</p>
        <p>When I note that the man had no arrest record, Safir responds, ''Only because he hadn't yet been caught with the illegal gun.'' I ask Safir why he finds incomprehensible the idea that a frightened, heretofore law-abiding citizen would use a gun to defend himself against an unknown intruder, but he changes the subject.</p>
        <p>''Look at this in context,'' he says. ''How many of these do we do?'' The department's numbers are on Safir's side: Of the more than 3,000 search warrants executed last year, the police raided only 6 wrong apartments. ''When the press calls it a wrong-door situation,'' he says, ''more frequently than not it's the right door but the wrong time. The guy is gone, the drugs are gone. The number of wrong doors is minuscule, but when it happens, it's a big story. The Norman Siegels of the world will see to that.''</p>
        <p>Safir's contempt for civil libertarians is total. ''People ask me about civil rights,'' Safir says. ''Well, the No. 1 civil right in my book is the right to be free from crime.''</p>
        <p>He is telling me this earlier this year on the way to the funeral of a black narcotics detective killed in the crossfire of the drug war. The day any Police Commissioner buries an officer is a difficult one; Sean Carrington's death has hit Safir especially hard, for Safir, like Carrington, once worked undercover. As a Federal drug officer, Safir posed as the LSD kingpin ''Eric Molofsky,'' infiltrating the Haight-Ashbury neighborhood of San Francisco. ''When you've had a gun in your face, and four guys surrounding you asking you if you're a cop, you try to keep your head.. . .'' He trails off. ''This is the worst. This is the worst. What you have to let the family know is that there's meaning to this.''</p>
        <p>Safir has no patience for those critics who say that department policies force black officers into the line of fire. Though the department is 13.6 percent black and 17 percent Latino, minority officers make up the majority of the undercover anti-narcotics units. It is often the quickest means to promotion for blacks and Latinos, but Safir says they are also ideologically committed to the drug war. ''These guys volunteer for this duty,'' he says. ''They believe in it.''</p>
        <p>And, he adds, so do the communities these officers serve. ''The demographics of crime are clear,'' he says. ''In minority neighborhoods, it's generally black-on-black and Latino-on-Latino. Eighty-four percent of African-Americans who are murdered in this city are murdered by African-Americans. So African-Americans are the No. 1 beneficiary of the crime reduction.''</p>
        <p>Then why is there still resentment of the Police Department in those neighborhoods?</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of activists who use these issues to advance their agendas,'' he says. ''That's an old story. I also think that there are cops who have the wrong attitude. I've fired more cops than the last two Commissioners combined. I don't tolerate racist and brutal cops.''</p>
        <p>A chasm separates Safir's understanding of the Louima case -- in which police officers allegedly forced the handle of a toilet plunger into the rectum of a Haitian immigrant -- from how it is interpreted in much of the black community. To Safir, the N.Y.P.D.'s reaction was profound and immediate. ''I basically suspended a whole precinct,'' he says. ''I knew I was temporarily hurting some innocent cops, but I wanted to send a message to the Haitian community that this is not something I took lightly.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Safir says, the incident holds no broad meaning for the department. ''There are cement-head cops, just like there are cement-head journalists,'' he says. ''But most police officers understand their role and how they're held accountable. The Louima case was a separate crime. It wasn't related to police activity. Police brutality by definition is, I go to arrest you, and you resist. I can use reasonable force. But after you're down, I hit you on the head five times. That's brutality. But taking someone 30 minutes after an event, taking them into a room and brutalizing them the way it allegedly happened, that's criminal.''</p>
        <p>But why would police officers feel they could do to Louima what they allegedly did inside an N.Y.P.D. precinct house? ''I don't know the answer to that,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Black community leaders believe they do. ''There's a tolerance for this kind of thing,'' Councilman Perkins says. Like many of the department's critics, Perkins says he believes that Safir is in denial about the impact of the Louima case. ''He can close his eyes to other incidents that don't make the press,'' Perkins says. ''The fact is, if you see a kid and a cop arguing on the street, you worry that that kid will get killed over nothing.''</p>
        <p>As Safir arrives at the black Pentecostal church where Carrington will be remembered, the Irishmen of the Police Department's Emerald Society Pipe Band are lining up in the rain. ''It was an Irish detective who shot the guy who killed Carrington,'' Safir tells me, in a manner suggesting that this fact explains what needs to be explained about race and the N.Y.P.D.</p>
        <p>Inside the church, the Commissioner joins the Mayor, the Governor and nearly every other politician of note in New York. Working the room, Safir bumps into Robert Johnson, the anti-death-penalty Bronx District Attorney. Safir gives him a thin smile. I tell Safir I'm surprised he even greets Johnson. ''We have polite relations,'' he says. I ask him if he respects Johnson.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he replies. ''Not at all.''</p>
        <p>Safir's unyielding illiberalism sets him apart from much of the city's elite. He is a conservative molded not on the Upper East Side but in the suburbs of Washington, where he lived until being pressed into service almost five years ago as Giuliani's Fire Commissioner. What he shares most with Giuliani is a firm belief that they are right about the drug war, right about the crackdown on quality-of-life crimes and right in thinking that the Police Department is made up of good people who are doing what's best for the city's minority communities, even if some of the leaders of those communities might think otherwise.</p>
        <p>In the end, Safir's relationship with the Mayor is uncomplicated: ''I've told Rudy that as long as he returns my phone calls, I'm here to stay. The day he doesn't, I'm gone.''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Goldberg is a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article, ''Big Tobacco's Endgame,'' appeared in June.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jeffrey Goldberg is a contributing writer for the magazine. His last article, ''Big Tobacco's Endgame,'' appeared in June.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
