<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nadal Returns to New York With Big Goal</title>
    <meta content="26tennis" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/26/sports/tennis/26tennis.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1785391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Nadal, Rafael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DA103EF935A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nadal Returns to New York With Big Goal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nadal Returns to New York With Big Goal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Watching Rafael Nadal cavort about the world's tennis courts as if he were plugged into an infinitely renewable source of energy, it is no stretch to envision him tackling all aspects of life with the same manic zeal.</p>
        <p>But Nadal, believe it or not, is not prone to scissors kicks and fist pumps when there is no racket in his left hand or bandanna holding his thick, dark locks more or less in place. A teen idol who is no longer a teenager, Nadal, a 20-year-old from Spain, also has a reflective side, and New York brings it to the fore like no other Grand Slam city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A teen idol who is no longer a teenager, Rafael Nadal has a reflective side, and New York brings it to the fore like no other Grand Slam city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Watching Rafael Nadal cavort about the world's tennis courts as if he were plugged into an infinitely renewable source of energy, it is no stretch to envision him tackling all aspects of life with the same manic zeal.</p>
        <p>But Nadal, believe it or not, is not prone to scissors kicks and fist pumps when there is no racket in his left hand or bandanna holding his thick, dark locks more or less in place. A teen idol who is no longer a teenager, Nadal, a 20-year-old from Spain, also has a reflective side, and New York brings it to the fore like no other Grand Slam city.</p>
        <p>He first visited in early 2001, not to take part in a tournament but to take part in a family vacation dreamed up by his father, Sebastián. Several members of Nadal's extended family, including grandparents and uncles, made the inter-island journey from their home in Majorca to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>One of their day trips took them to the top of the World Trade Center, and several months later, after coming off a tennis court in Madrid, Nadal stared at the television screen like so many others that Sept. 11 and felt a personal sense of loss as the dust rose and slowly, sickeningly dissipated.</p>
        <p>''For me, something is still missing here,'' he said this week. ''Whenever I come back to New York, I have this sad feeling somehow. I think if I hadn't come here before the towers were destroyed, it wouldn't have changed my feelings so much about the place, but the fact I was here at that age, that changed things a lot for me. Every year I come back, I go to ground zero.''</p>
        <p>Nadal has now returned four times since 2001, and although his connection with the city has deepened, he has yet to look entirely at home at the city's biggest tennis tournament. The world's No. 2 player, he has won the past two French Opens, he was a surprise Wimbledon finalist last month, and he has gotten the better of Roger Federer on a regular basis. But he has not made it past the third round at the United States Open.</p>
        <p>His second-round losses to Younes el-Aynaoui in 2003 and Andy Roddick in 2004 were not unexpected, but last year's loss to James Blake in the third round was a genuine upset, and it left Nadal determined to show the better side of his flashy game to New Yorkers, and to himself.</p>
        <p>''Last year was the first year where, before I came here, I had done some significant things, and I played poorly, quite poorly,'' he said from the overstuffed confines of a chair in the presidential suite of an elegant hotel in Midtown Manhattan. ''This year, we'll see. I've always said since the beginning of the season that this was one of my big goals for the year, what I really wanted.''</p>
        <p>The reviews from his early summer hardcourt tournaments have not been favorable. He took a month off after Wimbledon, during which he emerged unscathed from an automobile crash in Majorca and faced the paparazzi in earnest for the first time with his new Majorcan girlfriend. He returned to the courts for the Rogers Cup in Toronto, where he lost to Tomas Berdych in the third round two weeks ago. He lost in the quarterfinals last week in Cincinnati to his resurgent countryman Juan Carlos Ferrero, a former world No. 1.</p>
        <p>Ferrero, like all Spanish players, has been relegated to the shadows by the spotlight shining on the Nadal phenomenon. ''Sometimes is difficult because, you know, is like you stop to play tennis,'' Ferrero said in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Spanish tennis, for all its great talents in the past 20 years, has not seen anything quite like Nadal, a player with the charisma and precocious, consistent results to grab headline space from ''futbol.'' Carlos Moyà, Nadal's likeable Majorcan role model, also reached No. 1 in the world (in 1999), won the French Open (1998) and wore some cutting-edge tennis apparel. But he never won 60 matches in a row on clay or had a player like Federer for a foil. And Moyà never projected the sort of ratings-grabbing blend of youthful enthusiasm, gladiatorial instinct and a winning smile that Nadal does.</p>
        <p>Despite a brilliant season -- one that has eliminated all lingering suspicions that Nadal could dominate only on clay -- it has not been all sweetness and light. At the start of the year, he was exercising in a swimming pool instead of behind the baseline because of a small crack in a bone in his left foot. It forced him to miss the Australian Open, a tournament where the high-bouncing surface would seem to suit his game nearly as well as the crushed red brick in Paris.</p>
        <p>''People have forgotten,'' he said. ''These are difficult moments, moments where you never know whether when you come back, you're going to get back to a high level.''</p>
        <p>Using a new insert in his left tennis shoe, Nadal rebounded quickly, winning a hardcourt tournament in Dubai in early March, beating Federer in the final. In April, he defeated Federer on clay to win in Monte Carlo, and a week later, he was in Barcelona, breaking down in tears in the locker room before he took to the court for his semifinal against his countryman Nicolás Almagro.</p>
        <p>''To realize that I was back among the best was a very emotional thing,'' he said. He then beat another Spaniard, Tommy Robredo, for the title.</p>
        <p>Nadal had the same reaction inside the All England Club after beating Marcos Baghdatis to reach the Wimbledon final. ''I don't think it's good to control it too much sometimes; I think if you need to cry, you should cry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>During Wimbledon, the French newspaper Le Journal du Dimanche reported that Nadal was a target of a Spanish government investigation into doping that centered on cycling. The article had no byline. The International Tennis Federation and the Spanish government have since released statements denying that Nadal was a target.</p>
        <p>Clearly, that incident did not affect his play.</p>
        <p>''It might have been complicated to handle for someone who had doubts about whether they had doped or not,'' Nadal said. ''I'm totally convinced I never took anything in my life and never will take anything in my life. I love sports and love competition, and I prefer much more to lose than to cheat.</p>
        <p>''For this reason, I wasn't nervous about this. It hurt me, though, and what hurt me was that there are bad people who would write such things, such lies, and not even have the courage to sign their article.''</p>
        <p>Nadal and his coach, his uncle Toni Nadal, blame cycling for tarnishing all athletes' images, and Rafael said he was ''almost 100 percent'' convinced that tennis had no doping problem, despite several prominent cases of late.</p>
        <p>Mariano Puerta, who lost to Nadal in the French Open final in 2005, and Guillermo Canas, both Argentines, received suspensions that year for positive drug tests. Their suspensions were reduced on appeal.</p>
        <p>''You shouldn't exaggerate it too much,'' Nadal said. ''I think there are often little mistakes, but you don't need to treat these people like delinquents. To not allow Canas to enter the U.S. Open last year seemed to me one of the most pathetic things.''</p>
        <p>But Nadal has not soured on the Open in general. He likes the atmosphere of the night matches, which he says suit his flamboyant style.</p>
        <p>This year's draw has not been uncooperative. Nadal's quarter of the draw, which includes Robredo and the 19-year-old Gaël Monfils of France, is hardly the roughest neighborhood.</p>
        <p>His first-round opponent is Mark Philippoussis, the often-injured Australian who no longer plays the way he did when he reached the United States Open final in 1998.</p>
        <p>But if Nadal is to make the transition from slightly melancholy New York tourist to champion, he will have to play much more convincing hardcourt tennis than he has so far this year. If he manages it, he is prepared to let the emotions flow.</p>
        <p>''I'll cry again,'' he said. ''It's a sure thing.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
