<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swooning (and Bidding) for Something of Sinatra's</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="812725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUCTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRISTIE'S</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINATRA, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBER, BRUCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINATRA, BARBARA (MRS FRANKSINATRA) FRANCIS ALBERT 'FRANK' SINATRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D91139F931A35751C1A963958260" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swooning (and Bidding) for Something of Sinatra's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEBER, BRUCE;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The shoehorn sold. The Wyeth didn't.</p>
        <p>In the fanciest of shmancy garage sales, which brought international art collectors together with the most fervent of nostalgia buffs yesterday, Christie's, the Park Avenue auction house, helped Frank Sinatra and his wife, Barbara, dispense with many of the items that once decorated their Rancho Mirage, Calif., house, which they sold earlier this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The shoehorn sold. The Wyeth didn't.</p>
        <p>In the fanciest of shmancy garage sales, which brought international art collectors together with the most fervent of nostalgia buffs yesterday, Christie's, the Park Avenue auction house, helped Frank Sinatra and his wife, Barbara, dispense with many of the items that once decorated their Rancho Mirage, Calif., house, which they sold earlier this year.</p>
        <p>The auction room was jammed, and if it wasn't Ol' Blue Eyes at the Paramount in 1947, well, the audience appeared to be entertained nonetheless.</p>
        <p>In a performance of marathon glibness over four hours, the auctioneer, Christopher Burge, the chairman of Christie's America, presided over brisk bidding on 250 lots. The items, many of them gilded, varied from tchotchkes to china, posters to pianos, a golf cart to a Jaguar.</p>
        <p>There were cigarette cases, glass decanters, statuettes (no Oscars, alas), alarm clocks and vintage radios. The shoehorn, French-made, gold with the diamond-set monogram "FS," went for $5,520. (Sale prices included the auction-house premium of 15 percent of the first $50,000 and an additional 10 percent thereafter.)</p>
        <p>Some of the most spirited bidding was on behalf of a metal mailbox with "F. Sinatra" engraved on glass panels. With a presale estimate of $600 to $800, it sold to an unidentified buyer who bid by phone for $13,800.</p>
        <p>"A world record for a mailbox," Mr. Burge announced with wry glee as he closed the sale.</p>
        <p>Tim Luke, a collectibles specialist at Christie's, said the sale was unusual  even for a celebrity auction because Sinatra memorabilia rarely appears on the market. A spokeswoman for the Sinatras, Susan Reynolds, said the couple decided  to sell their belongings because their other California houses, in Malibu and Beverly Hills, are "fully furnished and decorated."</p>
        <p>"You only have so much wall space," she said.</p>
        <p>The total sale, reaching $2.07 million, was far above the presale estimate of $1.5 million. It was, of course, a testament to the lingering appeal of Mr. Sinatra, the pre-eminent crooner of the last half-century, who turns 80 on Dec.  12.</p>
        <p>And the event brought a disparate crowd to Christie's, many unused to an auction's rapidly escalating bids. Phil Piro, a 62-year-old insurance salesman from Ridgewood, N.J., arrived at Christie's at 7:45 A.M. for the 10 o'clock auction, and landed a seat in the front row.</p>
        <p>"I've been a Sinatra fan for 50 years," said Mr. Piro, who first saw Mr. Sinatra perform at the Paramount in 1942. He hoped to bid on a bronze statuette  of John Wayne with an inscription from Mr. Wayne: "To Old Blue Eyes Frank Sinatra." The figure was valued at $1,500 to $2,000, but when bidding opened at  $4,000, Mr. Piro was shut out.</p>
        <p>The same fate befell Jerry Sokol, a salesman from Seaford, L.I., who came to  the auction with his daughter-in-law, Jill.</p>
        <p>"The guy's been my life, really," said Mr. Sokol, 69, who as a young man aspired to be a singer and took a lesson from Mr. Sinatra's onetime coach, John  Quinlan. He has been collecting Sinatra recordings since he was 13, he said. He  now owns 1,400 of them.</p>
        <p>"I've duplicated his collection three times," Mr. Sokol said. "I've got 78's, LP's and now CD's. I got no more room in the house."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sokol was hoping to land some glassware for his curio shelf, but he, too, went home empty-handed.</p>
        <p>There were, indeed, some legitimate art objects for sale, including some 30 objects by Karl Faberge, all of which sold for a total of $818,685. Among them were two jeweled gold presentation boxes, made in St. Petersburg, which were bought by an unidentified Russian buyer for a total of $291,000.</p>
        <p>"There are some nice things," said Randall Reed, an art collector from Sydney, Australia, who bought half a dozen items in the several-hundred-dollar range. "They're being bid up. The associational value does that, of course."</p>
        <p>If there was one disappointment, it was the Sinatras' collection of American  paintings. Several of the most valuable failed to draw significant enough bids to sell, including Andrew Wyeth's "Erickson," a portrait whose estimated value was $100,000 to $150,000, and "A Memory: In the Italian Villa," by William Merritt Chase, the most expensive item in the sale, valued at $450,000 to $650,000.</p>
        <p>One painting that did sell was "The Happy Kitten," by Julius Adam, a highly sentimental oil depicting a fluff ball anticipating a bowl of milk. Nearly a dozen bidders excitedly bid up the price from the estimate of $1,000 to $1,500 to the sale price of $13,225.</p>
        <p>"Sinatra likes cats," explained Mr. Reed, who did not bid.</p>
        <p>In the end, it was less the art than the man that the crowd had come to purchase. Something that had touched him.</p>
        <p>"If they had his underwear for sale, it would sell for seven times the estimate," said Bert Malina, a 67-year-old art dealer from Brooklyn. Mr. Malina  had hopes of bidding on the Jaguar, a 1976 model that was a wedding gift from Mrs. Sinatra and was valued at $10,000 to $12,000. But it was the last lot to be sold, and halfway through the auction Mr. Malina, knew it would be hopeless.</p>
        <p>"If it goes for the minimum, I'll be happy to take it," he said. "But if you  buy something like that, where do you keep it? In the garage? Frank Sinatra's car? It'd be gone in half an hour."</p>
        <p>The car sold for $79,500 to a phone bidder, John A. Marta, a retired real estate developer from Wilmington, Del. But he didn't get it without a fight. In  the audience, Alan Spitzer, an auto dealer from Cleveland, matched Mr. Marta bid for bid.</p>
        <p>As the price climbed over $50,000, Mr. Spitzer, clearly tensing in the bout with his unseen opponent, shouted to Mr. Burge, "Is that Frank on the phone?" He bid $69,000 before throwing in the towel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marta, asked afterward how high he would have gone, replied: "I was willing to go to $20,000. That was my ultimate. But then you get in the heat of things. And my wife was edging me on. 'Go one more! Go one more!' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
