<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Superhighway or Couch Potato Heaven?</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="661970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DF1131F937A25752C0A962958260" item-length="296" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Superhighway or Couch Potato Heaven?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Russell Baker raises valid questions about promises being made for the "information superhighway" in "But Will It Fly?" (column, Jan. 4).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Russell Baker raises valid questions about promises being made for the "information superhighway" in "But Will It Fly?" (column, Jan. 4).</p>
        <p>Since humans found ways to control fire for cooking and heating, society has sought answers to the age-old seven deadly sins -- plus boredom -- in newer technologies. The process of technological breakthrough has speeded up in the last 150 years, but the seven deadly sins and boredom are as thriving as the cockroach.</p>
        <p>Another writer, at the beginning of this technologically-hyperactive century, predicted the worst possible outcome of an information superhighway. E. M. Forster, in his only science fiction work, "The Machine Stops," created a society of single inhabitants, each in his or her own underground bunker, in a recliner chair with push-button controls in the arm rests, facing a videolike screen.</p>
        <p>By pushing a particular button, one could obtain food, entertainment, information and whatever connection with others was desired -- without the messy and germ-laden contact of being in one another's company. On the screen appeared one's loved ones, again safely out of bodily contact.</p>
        <p>It is a horrific and all-too-possible vision of the couch potato writ large via the information superhighway.</p>
        <p>In the Forster novella, there is only one rebel who finally dares to climb out of his bunker and walk on the actual earth again and breathe the air and feel the sun. I wonder if Forster wrote this book as an alternative nightmare to H. G. Wells's "Time Machine," in which humans have lost racial memory, literacy and self-determination, and are used as food by an underground race of technological trolls. BARBARA ADAMS  Prof. of English, Pace University Newburgh, N.Y., Jan. 4, 1994</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
