<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swept at Home, Mount Piniella Finally Erupts</title>
    <meta content="19VECS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/19/sports/baseball/19VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piniella, Lou</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DB133EF93AA25753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swept at Home, Mount Piniella Finally Erupts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Swept at Home, Mount Piniella Finally Erupts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey, in Sports of The Times, comments on New York Yankees-Seattle Mariners' series; comments on Mariners' coach Lou Piniella's temper (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was quiet. Or, as they say in the sci-fi movies, too quiet.</p>
        <p>The latest Yankees-Mariner series has yet to live up to the testy rivalry that has developed since the Mariners got good. But stick around. The volcano is rumbling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>No sooner had the Mariners succumbed to the Yankees in Game 2 than Lou Piniella emitted loud noises and threatening smoke that has not been seen from him or his team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was quiet. Or, as they say in the sci-fi movies, too quiet.</p>
        <p>The latest Yankees-Mariner series has yet to live up to the testy rivalry that has developed since the Mariners got good. But stick around. The volcano is rumbling.</p>
        <p>No sooner had the Mariners succumbed, 3-2, to the Yankees tonight than Lou Piniella emitted loud noises and threatening smoke that has not been seen from him or his team.</p>
        <p>Spotting a long line of reporters outside the Mariners' clubhouse, Piniella volunteered his defiance without any prodding whatsoever.</p>
        <p>''I want you all to print this,'' Piniella barked. ''We're going to be back here for Game 6. Write it.''</p>
        <p>This was the tone we have learned to love from this manager and this rivalry. Up to now, there hasn't been a dramatic homer, a stunning late-inning rally, or a temper tantrum or legitimate buzzball just to keep the other side on its toes.</p>
        <p>In these somber days, there may not be much room for crabbiness, but Lou was working himself up to a rage for the cross-country flight his team was about to take.</p>
        <p>He said he was sore that Mariano Rivera got an extra five or six pitches to warm up in the bullpen after he was summoned, but really Piniella was mad about losing two straight, which is why they call him Sweet Lou.</p>
        <p>In the last seven years, things happened when these two teams played. Things like Alex Rodriguez and Paul O'Neill going down. Things like Piniella flailing his arms like a man swatting gnats.</p>
        <p>So far, things have been calm on the field. Managers Joe Torre and Lou Piniella kibitzed before Wednesday's opening game, and hugged during the introductions.</p>
        <p>This lovefest may have something to do with the terrible events in New York, after which the Yankees and Mets emerged as designated symbols for the brave people of that city.</p>
        <p>It may be hard for Piniella, who has great memories of the city and the Yanks, to work up one of his consuming rages at players who recently were wearing NYPD and FDNY caps.</p>
        <p>''I got a call from some friends in New York today,'' Piniella said before the game, ''and they said, 'Enough already with these Yankees. Get somebody else into the World Series.' ''</p>
        <p>His New York idiom was perfect, but he also understands how hard it is going to be to dislodge these people. But the Mariners won 116 games during the season, and frankly speaking, the baseball fans of the world expected something more out of them than this, and so did Piniella.</p>
        <p>More than any other team, the Mariners have stood up to the Yankees during this newest Bronx Age. The Mariners have won 41 and lost 35 during the regular season starting in 1995 but the Yankees now have an 8-5 postseason edge.</p>
        <p>The Mariners got the early advantage in 1995, when the Yankees won the first two games of the division series in Yankee Stadium. But out in the Kingdome the Mariners won once, won twice, won three times, after which George Steinbrenner dispatched Buck Showalter and hired Torre.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have won four of five World Series since, but the Mariners have always refused to be intimidated.</p>
        <p>Sometimes Piniella would have O'Neill brushed back -- just because. Piniella had managed O'Neill in Cincinnati, and the two hardheads had clashed, as difficult as that is to believe. And sometimes the Yanks would retaliate. Boomer Wells threw four inside pitches to the sainted Junior Griffey and later wondered why Junior could not take a joke.</p>
        <p>In last year's league championship series, Roger Clemens threw very, very inside at Rodriguez, and Piniella threatened reprisals. The Mariners scrapped back to extend the series to six games.</p>
        <p>Last night, Lou could not work up a good sense of outrage when the second-base umpire, Charlie Reliford, made a terrific call that Mike Cameron had trapped Chuck Knoblauch's line drive, not caught it. Piniella talks about not indulging in ''wasted energy,'' but sometimes it takes a spark of temper to turn a team around.</p>
        <p>Finally, in the seventh inning, there was a blast from the past, when Freddy Garcia threw a major-league inside pitch to O'Neill with a two-strike count.</p>
        <p>But Piniella was only warming up. After the game, he admitted he was more or less agitating about Rivera's warm-up pitches (''Just gave me something to argue about'') and then issued his guarantee, which pleased his players.</p>
        <p>''I like it,'' Mark McLemore said. ''We all feel that way. I like it, coming from the manager.''</p>
        <p>There is no lack of noise from the fans, but maybe the manager's burst of steam can make this series compelling.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
