<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="19MOVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D6153EF93AA25753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="3979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. The ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on  Page 15.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''APOCALYPSE NOW REDUX,'' starring Martin Sheen, Marlon Brando, Robert Duvall, Dennis Hopper and Laurence Fishburne. Directed by Francis Ford Coppola (R, 196 minutes). Nearly an hour has been added to Mr. Coppola's 1979 Vietnam epic, making the movie richer, stranger and more coherent. It has been rereleased in a stunning new print that showcases Vittorio Storaro's lustrous cinematography and Walter Murch's swirling, precise sound design, as well as Mr. Coppola's grand and sometimes murky vision. The movie's essential seriousness, its brave ambition and the dedication of its cast (now expanded to include Colleen Camp as a Playboy centerfold and Aurore Clément as a French widow) have grown more impressive with time. The current vogue for digitally enhanced computer-generated special effects in live-action movies, for jumpy, gestural editing and for glib pseudo-irony has lulled us into a pixilated, hyperactive slumber. With its grandeur and its horrific, exhilarating magic realism, ''Apocalypse Now Redux'' jolts us awake (A. O. Scott).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. The ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on  Page 15.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''APOCALYPSE NOW REDUX,'' starring Martin Sheen, Marlon Brando, Robert Duvall, Dennis Hopper and Laurence Fishburne. Directed by Francis Ford Coppola (R, 196 minutes). Nearly an hour has been added to Mr. Coppola's 1979 Vietnam epic, making the movie richer, stranger and more coherent. It has been rereleased in a stunning new print that showcases Vittorio Storaro's lustrous cinematography and Walter Murch's swirling, precise sound design, as well as Mr. Coppola's grand and sometimes murky vision. The movie's essential seriousness, its brave ambition and the dedication of its cast (now expanded to include Colleen Camp as a Playboy centerfold and Aurore Clément as a French widow) have grown more impressive with time. The current vogue for digitally enhanced computer-generated special effects in live-action movies, for jumpy, gestural editing and for glib pseudo-irony has lulled us into a pixilated, hyperactive slumber. With its grandeur and its horrific, exhilarating magic realism, ''Apocalypse Now Redux'' jolts us awake (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>''BANDITS,'' starring Bruce Willis, Billy Bob Thornton and Cate Blanchett. Directed by Barry Levinson (PG-13, 123 minutes). This shaggy-dog romantic heist comedy feels like a modern Classics Illustrated version of ''Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid'' and ''Bonnie and Clyde.'' It stars Mr. Willis and Mr. Thornton as charming bank robbers who don't resort to violence. They get involved in a semi-ménage à trois with Kate (Ms. Blanchett), a depressed housewife who ends up joining the boys on their rapidly swelling legendary crime spree. But ''Bandits'' is guilty of behaving like a petty thievery corporation; it steals from so many other sources that we're forced to realize that it has little of its own to offer. As such, it can't help but fail to meet expectations, given the talents involved (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''BREAD AND TULIPS,'' starring Licia Maglietta, Bruno Ganz, Giuseppe Massironi, Marina Massironi, Antonio Catania and Felice Andreasi. Directed by Silvio Soldini (PG-13, 104 minutes; in Italian, with English subtitles). This Italian comedy about a bored housewife who finds happiness among the scruffy Bohemians of Venice is hardly groundbreaking -- at least a half-dozen episodes of ''The Simpsons'' cover similar ground. But the movie does have a sweet, understated charm, some genuinely funny moments and a wise, sexy performance by Ms. Maglietta in the lead role, all of which make it easy to sit through and easy to like (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''THE CLOSET,'' starring Daniel Auteuil and Gérard Depardieu. Directed by Francis Veber (R, 86 minutes; in French with English subtitles). A classic French farce with a contemporary twist, this very funny comedy spoofs political correctness, homophobia and corporate hypocrisy in its story of a mousy divorced accountant (Mr. Auteuil) who pretends to be gay to save his job in a condom factory. He can't be fired, he reasons correctly, because of corporate fear of a lawsuit for discrimination. Mr. Depardieu is hilariously galumphing as an obsequious homophobe who goes to such ludicrous extremes to demonstrate his tolerance that he drives himself crazy (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>''DON'T SAY A WORD,'' starring Michael Douglas, Sean Bean, Oliver Platt, Famke Janssen, Brittany Murphy and Jennifer Esposito. Directed by Gary Fleder (R, 110 minutes). In this exhausting, incoherent thriller, Mr. Douglas plays Nathan Conrad, a Manhattan psychiatrist whose young daughter is kidnapped by a sadistic band of jewel thieves. The ransom they demand is the intensive treatment of a mentally ill young woman who has a piece of information they need to recover a ruby they stole 10 years earlier, which the young woman's father, one of their accomplices, snatched away from them. Adding to the confusion is a tough, sexy homicide detective (Ms. Esposito) whose investigation of a series of murders leads her to Conrad. The movie is as overelaborate as the criminals' scheme, and similarly doomed from the outset to fail (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''GHOST WORLD,'' starring Thora Birch, Scarlett Johansson, Steve Buscemi, Brad Renfro, Bob Balaban and Illeana Douglas. Directed by Terry Zwigoff (R, 111 minutes). Misanthropy was never so much fun, and the boredom of contemporary adolescence has rarely been so thrilling. Mr. Zwigoff's elegant adaptation of Daniel Clowes's comic concentrates on the friendship of Enid and Rebecca (Ms. Birch and Ms. Johansson), two sarcastic, defiantly nonconformist teenagers enduring a world that falls unredeemably short of their standards of coolness. Mr. Buscemi plays a middle-aged record collector whose accidental friendship with Enid propels her into one of the funniest and most convincing coming-of-age stories in recent years (Scott).</p>
        <p>''HARDBALL,'' starring Keanu Reeves, Diane Lane and John Hawkes. Directed by Brian Robbins (PG-13, 110 minutes). Daniel Coyle's nonfiction book about a children's baseball team in Chicago has been adapted into a mawkish, cutesy tearjerker. Mr. Reeves, as self-conscious as ever, is its reluctant coach, a down-and-out gambler who redeems himself (and pays off his debts) by leading these latter-day Bad News Bears to victory. The star is forced to deliver inspirational sound bites like the movie's meaningless tag line, ''The most important thing in life is showing up'' (Holden).</p>
        <p>''HEARTS IN ATLANTIS,'' starring Anthony Hopkins, Anton Yelchin, David Morse and Hope Davis. Directed by Scott Hicks (PG-13, 101 minutes). One of Stephen King's sappier novels has been pummeled into mush by Mr. Hicks's shallow magazine-glossy depiction of late-1950's America. He is aided by William Goldman's screenplay, which fills the mouth of its persecuted hero with kitschy inanities. That hero, a mysterious Christlike mind reader who becomes a young boy's surrogate dad, is played by the painfully miscast Mr. Hopkins. Compared to this bunk, even the movie of Mr. King's ''Green Mile'' seems austere (Holden).</p>
        <p>''JOY RIDE,'' starring Steve Zahn, Paul Walker, Leelee Sobieski, Jessica Bowman and Stuart Stone. Directed by John Dahl (R, 105 minutes). Though not quite up to ''Red Rock West'' or ''The Last Seduction,'' Mr. Dahl's earlier noir exercises, this suspenseful and surprisingly funny confection is head and shoulders above the usual dumbed-down, overplotted studio thriller. Mr. Zahn and Mr. Walker play brothers whose CB radio prank on an interstate trucker provokes psychopathic vengeance. Ms. Sobieski, a friend along for the ride, is the inevitable girl in distress. Not everything makes sense, but Mr. Dahl's clever direction and Mr. Zahn's hyperactive charm play off each other in tight, smart syncopation (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''MULHOLLAND DRIVE,'' starring Justin Theroux, Naomi Watts, Laura Harring, Ann Miller, Robert Forster and Dan Hedaya. Written and directed by David Lynch (R, 146 minutes). Mr. Lynch's epic nightmare of Hollywood, which began life as an open-ended television series (like his ''Twin Peaks'') and evolved into a movie, may be his masterpiece. A leisurely film noir that turns into a surreal montage, it is a portrait of Hollywood filtered through the director's personal iconography, which in many ways is more early 1960's than contemporary in mood. The story traces the loss of innocence of a dewy Hollywood hopeful (Ms. Watts) who befriends a mysterious amnesia victim (Ms. Harring) searching for her identity. Their journey figuratively plunges them through the looking glass into a phantasmagoric dream world (Holden).</p>
        <p>''THE OTHERS,'' starring Nicole Kidman, Alakina Mann and James Bentley. Written and directed by Alejandro Amenábar (PG-13, 104 minutes). At 29, Mr. Amenábar, a Spanish filmmaker directing his first English-language movie, shows an impressive mastery of the ghost-story form. He sends his camera down shadowy corridors and into cavernous rooms to create a mood of elegant dread. Though a bit too long and too cluttered in the middle, ''The Others'' is persuasively spooky and even manages to be poignant, thanks to a fierce performance by Ms. Kidman. She plays a woman living with her two children and three peculiar servants in a fog-shrouded house on the island of Jersey in the English Channel (Scott).</p>
        <p>''SERENDIPITY,'' starring John Cusack, Kate Beckinsale, Jeremy Piven and Eugene Levy. Directed by Peter Chelsom (PG-13, 87 minutes). Jon and Sara (Mr. Cusack and Ms. Beckinsale) meet at Bloomingdale's while Christmas shopping and then end up on a dream date. Because they're both involved with other people, Sara has qualms about exchanging information with him. Instead she writes her phone number in a book, which she hands off to a used-book seller, and makes Jon put his number on a $5 bill, which she spends. If these objects come back into their lives, she contends, then they're destined to be together. Cut to a few years later, and the two are setting off individually to find the clues that will lead them to each other. This movie is the cinematic equivalent of a plate made of spun sugar. Mr. Chelsom's touch shines with a kind of craftsmanship, but it's sticky to the touch; if you look hard enough, you can see the sugar granules gleaming just beneath the surface (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>* ''SOBIBOR, OCTOBER 14, 1943, 4 P.M., with Yehuda Lerner. Written and directed by Claude Lanzmann (not rated, 95 minutes; in Hebrew and French, with English subtitles). This powerful documentary, a follow-up to Mr. Lanzmann's monumental ''Shoah,'' is a self-contained story of individual heroism and organized resistance to the Nazis. The film is built around an interview with Mr. Lerner, who participated in a successful uprising at the Sobibor death camp in Poland. Mr. Lanzmann's methods are simple, unintrusive and precise, and they yield emotions as powerful as they are complex (Scott).</p>
        <p>''TRAINING DAY,'' starring Denzel Washington, Ethan Hawke and Scott Glenn. Directed by Antoine Fuqua (R, 120 minutes). Mr. Washington plays Detective Alonzo Harris, the Machiavellian figure in this intermittently successful police drama. Alonzo is the worst example a young officer could ever have to learn from. He is the teacher to Jake Hoyt (Mr. Hawke), who has just been assigned to undercover duties. When the picture dwells on dueling ambitions -- Jake's striving for permanent assignment to undercover work and Alonzo's constant conning of his rookie partner -- you lean in to listen. But eventually ''Training Day,'' despite Mr. Washington's virtuoso performance, becomes a glib potboiler torn from today's screaming headlines (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>* ''VA SAVOIR,'' starring Jeanne Balibar, Sergio Castellitto, Marianne Basler, Jacques Bonnaffé and Hélène De Fougerolles. Directed by Jacques Rivette (PG-13, 150 minutes; in French, with English subtitles). Mr. Rivette's gracious -- and graceful -- character comedy is droll and lovable, a piece that has earned all of the wrinkles on its brow and around its mouth. What's surprising is that on close examination those crinkles turn out to be smile lines. ''Savoir'' is a luminous, humid roundelay, as three men and three women tumble in and out of one another's minds, hearts and arms. Everyone is looking for something other than what he or she has. That lusty self-interest is the motor of all great farces. The film's title has been translated as ''Who Knows?,'' and it is a wistful, rueful shrug: an unforgettable gesture as sexy and controlled as Tony Bennett chugging his way through ''I Wish I Were in Love Again'' (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>* ''WAKING LIFE,'' starring Wiley Wiggins. Written and directed by Richard Linklater (R, 99 minutes). Free will versus determinism, dreams versus reality are among the topics addressed by Mr. Linklater's witty, ''trippy'' voyage into the Twilight Zone in which an assortment of characters spout contradictory theories of human consciousness. The technically innovative movie finds the perfect metaphor for the philosophic paradoxes in its visual style: live action transformed into a cartoon by digital animation. The spiels are funny and humane. Mr. Wiggins is the zonked-out everyman who absorbs them on a dreamlike journey from which he finds himself unable to awaken (Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''ZOOLANDER,'' starring Ben Stiller, Owen Wilson and Will Ferrell. Directed by Mr. Stiller (PG-13, 89 minutes). An evil band of international fashion designers want to end the tenure of a new prime minister of Malaysia, who plans to stop the exploitation of child labor. They force their subaltern Mugatu (Mr. Ferrell) to find a supermodel pawn to assassinate the beloved ruler. There's only one blunt instrument suited to this job: the dumb and monumentally earnest Derek Zoolander (Mr. Stiller), the unfortunate potential hero of this often unspeakably funny new comedy. ''Zoolander'' is a gleaming fashion-world tour. It makes sense that the film would have the stylish, high-resolution glaze of a fashion shoot. Mr. Stiller has also crammed the movie with energy; it seems still to be bouncing on the screen long after it has run its 89-minute course (Mitchell).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
