<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First-Ever Re-creation Of New Species' Birth</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFDF1539F934A35756C0A960958260" item-length="1838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First-Ever Re-creation Of New Species' Birth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONTEMPLATING the pageant of evolution, biologists have long wondered how much of a role chance played in determining history's course. If researchers could turn back the clock and allow life to evolve again and again, would leaping frogs and blooming orchids always reappear? Or might evolution's path, punctuated by asteroid crashes and random genetic mutations, meander to produce  something altogether different?</p>
        <p>Now, at last, a team of biologists has found a way to replay one piece of history, re-enacting the birth of a species three separate times and each time tracking the complex genetic changes of speciation. And they have shown that evolution, at least in this case, was much more repeatable and predictable than  scientists have imagined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONTEMPLATING the pageant of evolution, biologists have long wondered how much of a role chance played in determining history's course. If researchers could turn back the clock and allow life to evolve again and again, would leaping frogs and blooming orchids always reappear? Or might evolution's path, punctuated by asteroid crashes and random genetic mutations, meander to produce  something altogether different?</p>
        <p>Now, at last, a team of biologists has found a way to replay one piece of history, re-enacting the birth of a species three separate times and each time tracking the complex genetic changes of speciation. And they have shown that evolution, at least in this case, was much more repeatable and predictable than  scientists have imagined.</p>
        <p>In their study of the anomalous sunflower, or Helianthus anomalus, researchers report in the current issue of the journal Science that every time they recreated plants thought to be similar to the original anomalous sunflower, the genes in those plants went through nearly identical changes. Even more surprising, the genetic maps of these laboratory recreations turned out to be very much like the map of the wild sunflower itself.</p>
        <p>While researchers have long known that hybrids of any given cross can be quite similar (witness the reliability of producing a mule from a mating between a donkey and a horse), they were greatly surprised that the sunflower hybrids were nearly identical on the fine scale of a genetic map.</p>
        <p>"It's a remarkable study," said Dr. Richard Harrison, an evolutionary biologist at Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y. "What's most remarkable is that  you get the same product time after time. It's a very important paper, very elegant and thorough."</p>
        <p>Dr. Leslie Gottlieb, a plant evolutionary biologist at the University of California at Davis, said, "This is absolutely unexpected and extremely interesting."</p>
        <p>An inhabitant of sand dunes of the Great Basin desert between the Rocky Mountains and the Sierra Nevada, the anomalous sunflower, as its name suggests,  is about 100,000 years old as a species. Ethnobotanists say the Hopi Indians used the powder from dried petals as a facial decoration during traditional ceremonies and as a charm on hunting sticks. Researchers, particularly Dr. Loren Rieseberg, an evolutionary biologist at Indiana University in Bloomington and colleagues, took an interest in the anomalous sunflower for other reasons. It is a natural hybrid. The species, so named because researchers found it so unusual  and hard to place, turned out to be the product of the interbreeding of two other distinct sunflower species.</p>
        <p>That meant that re-enacting the origin of the species simply required interbreeding the original parents, the common sunflower, Helianthus annuus, and the petioled sunflower, Helianthus petiolaris. The resulting offspring would be  a modern approximation of hybrid plants that eventually became the anomalous sunflower species.</p>
        <p>But what would those first anomalous sunflowers have mated with? The species  from which they came, or other hybrids like themselves? To explore the various possibilities, researchers bred the hybrids into three distinct lineages. Each lineage underwent a different regime of mating with other hybrids and parental species to approximate three different situations for the continuing evolution of the species.</p>
        <p>After four generations of such breeding, researchers mapped the genomes of the hybrids to see what had happened during the ensuing reorganization and sorting of the original mix of genes.</p>
        <p>To do so, Dr. Rieseberg and colleagues borrowed techniques from plant breeders developed for the rapid genetic mapping of crops, using what are known  as RAPD markers. The markers, which are used to amplify small portions of DNA for study, allowed researchers to analyze 197 different segments of DNA in each  hybrid lineage. Because the researchers already knew what those 197 regions of the genome looked like in the common and in the petioled sunflower species, they were able to identify which regions in the hybrids were descended from which of  the original species. Researchers then used the information to construct detailed maps showing the patchwork of common sunflower and petioled sunflower DNA in the hybrids.</p>
        <p>If chance had played a major role in the evolution of anomalus, then the three different hybrid lineages should each end up with quite different genetic  maps, each displaying unique mixtures of common and petioled sunflower genes.</p>
        <p>Instead, what researchers found were incredibly similar maps in all three cases. When one lineage carried common sunflower genes on a particular portion of a chromosome, then the other lineages were likely to carry common sunflower genes there as well. Finally researchers compared the maps of experimental hybrids to a genetic map of the wild anomalus. They found, again to their surprise, that the experimental hybrids and the wild species were very similar.  Most often, where one had common sunflower genes or petioled sunflower genes, the other did as well.</p>
        <p>Researchers say the result indicates that not only were the initial genetic changes in the wild anomalous sunflower the same as those in the experimental lineages, but that even after some 100,000 years of evolution the evidence for those early changes was still clearly detectable.</p>
        <p>"I was pretty astonished," Dr. Rieseberg said. "I expected to see some similarities, some concordance, but I didn't expect to see anything like this. I think we'll find that much more about evolution is repeatable and predictable than we think."</p>
        <p>The similarities between the experimental hybrids and the wild species are even more striking given that the experimental plants were raised in the wet, rich conditions of the greenhouse quite unlike the extremely hot, dry conditions to which Helianthus anomalus became so well adapted.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rieseberg said if the researchers had raised the hybrids in conditions more similar to the environment favored by the anomalous sunflower, the closer match of initial environmental pressures for the wild and laboratory sunflowers  might have led to an even closer match of the resulting genetic maps.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rieseberg and colleagues suggest that the reason the hybrids did end up with the same genetic makeup so consistently is that whether in the greenhouse or the wild, certain combinations of genes from the common sunflower and the petioled sunflower consistently work better together than others. Some of these  combinations, it would seem, work so much better that they are essentially always found together in surviving hybrids. If that is the reason, then researchers say the question becomes just what are those particularly potent genes and gene combinations, and what are they doing for the anomalous sunflower?</p>
        <p>There may, however, be other explanations for the consistency as well. Researchers suggest the answer could be something much more mechanical. Perhaps, they say, in the inevitable mixing of common sunflower and petioled sunflower chromosomes in the hybrids, the physical interactions among the large gene-carrying structures somehow results each time in certain regions always sorting themselves out together.</p>
        <p>Just as the specific cause of the repeatability remains unclear, the bigger question of how widespread over evolution such repeatability is likely to be, remains a matter of debate.</p>
        <p>There are those, like Dr. Stephen Jay Gould, an evolutionary biologist at Harvard University, who have previously suggested that any replaying of evolutionary history would probably turn out a quite different result. Dr. Gould said in an interview that the evolution of the anomalous sunflower, while "fascinating," did not suggest that more major events in evolution, for example  the evolution of humankind, should be assumed to be deterministic or predictable.</p>
        <p>"It's a question of scale," Dr. Gould said. Whenever a person carries three copies of chromosome 21, he said, "you get Down syndrome."</p>
        <p>"That's not a general challenge to the notion of unpredictability," he went on. "You put those things together and that's how they're always going to work.  But as soon as you get into events whose evolutionary direction depends on interactions with large-scale environments that change unpredictably or the vagaries of interacting with other species through time, that's a different question."</p>
        <p>He suggested instead that the genetic machinations of the anomalous sunflower were perhaps more appropriately viewed as a detail in the wider picture. In a wholesale replaying of life, he suggested, perhaps sunflowers themselves would not even reappear.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jerry Coyne, an evolutionary biologist at the University of Chicago, cautioned, "You can't extrapolate this to the whole world." Dr. Coyne, who wrote an accompanying article in Science suggesting that the new study should perhaps  challenge such notions of unpredictability, added, "But in this case, which is the only existing case, you do get these changes that are very repeatable."</p>
        <p>One thing scientists do know is that the details of this sunflower's origins  are quite unusual.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nick Barton, a specialist in the evolution of hybrids at the University of Edinburgh in Scotland, said that in animals new species rarely arose from hybrids. Hybrids and hybrid species are much more common in plants, and some researchers estimate that as many as one in 10 species has hybrid origins. But the most common form of hybrid speciation in plants is very different from the one that gave rise to the anomalous sunflower.</p>
        <p>In the more common case, during the crossbreeding of two different species, the number of chromosomes in the hybrid offspring is somehow doubled, making it  impossible for the hybrid to breed again with the species from which it came. In contrast, the incipient anomalous species, when first produced, could still interbreed with its parents. As a result, researchers say, the results of the present study are probably not too relevant to these very different sorts of hybrid origins.</p>
        <p>Researchers say at least as important as the finding itself is the successful use of genomic mapping. "What's really important here is the demonstration of these tools," said Dr. Gottlieb of the University of California at Davis. "We are now in a position to ask much more specific questions than were previously possible. My intuition here is that the ability to ask these questions will finally tell us what it means to be a different species and this study is directly on that road."</p>
        <p>Dr. Coyne agreed, saying the new study should be emulated, ushering in an era of revitalizing experimentation to evolutionary biology, a field sometimes frustratingly restricted to theorizing and thought experiments.</p>
        <p>"You can't bring back the Burgess Shale," he said, referring to an ancient formation of fossils, "but you can do this over and over again and always get the same thing. This is an actual scientific test."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
