<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Iran Cooperating on Ways to End Afghan War</title>
    <meta content="Y15AFG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iran-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khatami, Mohammed (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DB173FF936A25751C1A961958260" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Iran Cooperating on Ways to End Afghan War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iran and US are working together in low-key meetings, exploring ways to end civil war in Afghanistan; talks are offering not only rare chance for direct contact between Iran and US, but also opportunity to establish longer-term relationship between Washington and Pres Mohammed Khatami, who recently offered olive branch to US (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For several months, in low-key  meetings at the United Nations that began after Mohammed Khatami took office in August as Iran's first popularly elected President, Iranians and Americans have been working together in a small group of interested nations to explore ways to end the civil war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The talks on the Afghan conflict -- which both countries want to end, though for different reasons -- provide not only a rare chance for direct contact between Iran and the United States but also an opportunity to establish some kind of longer-term working relationship between Washington and Mr. Khatami, who offered an olive branch to the United States at a news conference yesterday in Teheran, the Iranian capital.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For several months, in low-key  meetings at the United Nations that began after Mohammed Khatami took office in August as Iran's first popularly elected President, Iranians and Americans have been working together in a small group of interested nations to explore ways to end the civil war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The talks on the Afghan conflict -- which both countries want to end, though for different reasons -- provide not only a rare chance for direct contact between Iran and the United States but also an opportunity to establish some kind of longer-term working relationship between Washington and Mr. Khatami, who offered an olive branch to the United States at a news conference yesterday in Teheran, the Iranian capital.</p>
        <p>''We are hopeful that the Iranians will play a constructive role in bringing their influence to bear to see the fighting stop and negotiations begin for the establishment of a broad-based government in Afghanistan,'' said Karl F. Inderfurth, Assistant Secretary of State for South Asian Affairs, who has been meeting with the Iranians in New York.</p>
        <p>The United States, which has isolated Iran since the seizure of the United States Embassy in Teheren in 1979 and the holding of American hostages for more than 15 months, nevertheless has some experience in dealing with Iranians in the United Nations system. On occasion, most recently in arms control negotiations, the Iranians have often been less obstructive than, for instance, India, with which Washington has had a long, unbroken relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inderfurth left yesterday for a trip to London, Paris and Moscow to discuss the Afghan problem. He said in an interview on Thursday that since talks began here in the fall that include the United States and Russia as well as Iran and Afghanistan's other neighbors -- Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan, Pakistan and China -- other nations had shown an interest in joining in, signaling their hopes that progress can be made.</p>
        <p>The talks at the United Nations, led by Lakhdar Brahimi, a former Algerian Foreign Minister who is Secretary General Kofi Annan's special envoy on Afghanistan, are focused on how to bring the militant Taliban movement, which has taken control of more than 80 percent of Afghanistan, into power-sharing negotiations with a group of allied warlords in the north of the country.</p>
        <p>Although the Taliban are devoutly Islamic, they are ethnic Pathans and Sunni Muslims. The Iranians, who are Persian-speaking Shiite Muslims, have supported one of the groups resisting the Taliban, the ethnic Hazara Shiites' Hizbe Wahdat Party.</p>
        <p>The United States has withheld recognition of the Taliban, criticizing their human rights record, especially their treatment of women, and their unwillingness to compromise with other Afghan ethnic groups. American oil companies are interested in developing gas and oil pipelines from Central Asia to Pakistan or the Arabian Sea through Afghanistan, but they have been advised that finding financing will be difficult with a war going on and no functioning central government in Kabul.</p>
        <p>The United States now seems prepared to put pressure on the Taliban movement, to push it toward a political settlement that would allow it to be recognized internationally.</p>
        <p>Taliban leaders have been encouraged to visit the United States. The first delegation just completed a tour sponsored by Unocal, the California-based oil company that is a major partner in Centgas, one of two international consortiums bidding to build pipelines in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The Taliban delegation met in Washington with Mr. Inderfurth and other American officials and also visited the University of Nebraska at Omaha, which is setting up technical training programs in Afghanistan with a $900,000 Unocal grant. Before Communist governments came to power in Afghanistan in the 1970's, culminating in the 1979 Soviet intervention, the United States played a major role in Afghan development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inderfurth said he hoped that the Taliban officials visiting the United States were ''getting a more realistic sense of the view of the United States, about our desire to play a contructive role in ending the conflict in Afghanistan.''</p>
        <p>''But they can't have it all,'' he said. ''They will need to work out arrangements so that the legitimate interests of the other groups are taken into account.''</p>
        <p>Iran, with its history of anti-Communism, has competing commercial interests in the region, including plans for its own pipelines from Central Asia. But a war next door in Afghanistan that neither side seems capable of winning soon does not provide the climate for much confidence in Iran either. Iranians would also like to see nearly two million Afghan refugees return home.</p>
        <p>In taking a more active role in looking for solutions in Afghanistan, the Clinton Administration appears to be taking advantage of a confluence of events that may provide the best opportunity in years to stop the destructive cycle of civil wars.</p>
        <p>First, there is a widely held opinion that the Taliban have advanced as far as is likely in their attempt to conquer the country.</p>
        <p>Robert B. Oakley, a visiting fellow at the National Defense University and a former Ambassador to Pakistan, says time is not on the Taliban's side.</p>
        <p>''The Taliban are never going to be strong enough -- given the geographic problems, the ethnic problems and the military problems -- to conquer the entire country,'' Mr. Oakley said in an interview. ''The Shiites have become a very strong movement in the past two years because they have been fighting hard against the Taliban and because the Iranians have given them a tremendous amount of support.''</p>
        <p>A second factor is the politics of the region. In Pakistan, months of political turmoil have just ended, leaving Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif strong enough to turn his attention to neighboring Afghanistan. Pakistan has tended to support the Taliban unconditionally, a position Washington is urging it to reconsider.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inderfurth's role is also important, experts say. The third-ranking official in the mission to the United Nations when Madeline K. Albright was the American representative there, Mr. Inderfurth is known to have the confidence of Ms. Albright, now Secretary of State, and is expected to have considerable authority for policy in the region.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
