<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Statements by Abuse Victims and an Expert on the Church</title>
    <meta content="Y14OTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/14/national/14OTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1400522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roman Catholic Church</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Notre Dame University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Appleby, Scott</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DD123CF937A25755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Statements by Abuse Victims and an Expert on the Church</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Excerpts From Statements by Abuse Victims and an Expert on the Church</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from statements yesterday before the United States Conference of Bishops by two people who say they are victims of sexual abuse, Craig Martin and Paula Gonzales Rohrbacher, and the director of Notre Dame University's Center for the Study of American Catholicism, Scott Appleby. The speeches by Mr. Martin and Ms. Rohrbacher were recorded by The New York Times. Mr. Appleby's comments were taken from the Web site of the bishop's conference. The full texts of the statements are online at nytimes.com/national.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin</p>
        <p>I find it's easier to tell my story using the name John Doe. I can revisit my pain and not hurt myself again. I found different stories that have helped me to understand my suffering. I'd like to share some of those today so that others may be helped.</p>
        <p>In John's late 20's he meets his wife, Julie. This is a start to his recovery, yet John has no idea. John's wife brings him back to religion and also introduces him to a priest that helps in John's recovery. I wish I could say recovery started here. But John wasn't quite ready. John had to read an article out of Sports Illustrated dated Sept. 13, 1999, entitled ''Every Parents Nightmare.'' This describes to John why he was in a position to be hurt. It goes like this:</p>
        <p>''While society has no trouble envisioning the violent molester and the child who is forced to submit to a sexual predator, many people are baffled by how adult seducers are able to get kids to go along with them voluntarily. These men seduce children, in this case boys in exactly the same way men and women have been seducing each other since the dawn of mankind. In other words they flirt with them, laugh at their jokes, shower them with attention, with gifts, with affection. They size up their weaknesses, their vulnerability, their needs. They will target the kids who are more vulnerable.''</p>
        <p>The amazing part of when I allowed John to talk about his abuser was how this man also offered kindness and love. How this man became John's best friend. John has showed very little anger toward his abuser. I was amazed at who John directed his sorrow to. He directed his sorrow not at his abuser but at his parents.</p>
        <p>John tells a story of how his abuser wants to take John fishing. The abuser asks John's parents if it's O.K. John's parents thought it was a great idea for John to go on a fishing trip with a Catholic priest.</p>
        <p>John talks of how his relationship with his parents changed. How he no longer trusted them. How alone he feels.</p>
        <p>Mom and Dad, I'm terribly sorry for how I treated you. Please accept my apology. I know that only thing I have in my heart for you is love. I love you both dearly.</p>
        <p>You see a child who is abused is put in a frightening and confusing situation. They may have never heard of anything like this happening. Nobody has told them it's right. Nobody has told them it's wrong. Everybody may like and respect the person who is doing these things.</p>
        <p>John remembers this motel that night with the priest. But hardly anything else. John has no idea how he got home. It is only 35 years later that John is starting to remember what happened that horrible night.</p>
        <p>Abused children often hide their anger and distress from others so that no one will suspect that they're being abused. They may also keep their feelings under control while they're being abused to protect themselves from feelings of distress and pain, or because they don't want the abuser to see how much he is hurting them. Many adult survivors continue to cope by blocking feelings and trying to forget about the past.</p>
        <p>Survivors often have a low opinion of themselves and lack self-confidence and self-esteem. They may feel worthless, useless and unloved. Many survivors put on a front and present themselves as capable, cheerful, confident, while feeling wretched inside. Survivors may be so overwhelmed by their low opinion of themselves and lack of confidence that they may suffer bouts of depression making them unable to act positively or find pleasure in things.</p>
        <p>I say these words because they describe John's feelings exactly. John became sexually active shortly after his abuse. John describes some very unhealthy attitudes toward women, admits to seeking out women in a predatory way. Alcohol also started to control John's life. It was many years before he finally sought help for alcoholism.</p>
        <p>Although sexual compulsivity and alcoholism had major effects on John, it was his need for self-esteem that's kept him alive. John still admits today to having low self-esteem. John has shown symptoms of low self-esteem, depression, anger and the need to control. John has been able to survive only because of his family, his friends, his children and the therapy he continues to go through.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rohrbacher</p>
        <p>When I was a little girl, my family, at the request of Mount Angel Seminary in Oregon, befriended several Mexican seminarians who were students there. The seminary placed one of these young men with my family, who was also Hispanic, no doubt to ease his transition to life in the United States.</p>
        <p>My mother, who regarded him as a son and encouraged my siblings and me to treat him as a brother, generously welcomed him into our family. We housed him over school holidays and summer vacations. The young seminarian that my family sponsored was named Jose. Our family situation was difficult when I was a child. My father died in 1960, leaving my mother a widow with 14- and 8-year-old sons and myself, age 5. During summer vacations she had no choice but to leave us at home while she worked.</p>
        <p>The summer of 1967 Jose lived with us during his break from the seminary. He took advantage of my mother's trust in him and sexually molested me.</p>
        <p>As difficult as it is for me to reveal these deeply personal aspects of my life to you, and probably uncomfortable for you to hear, I feel it is important for you to understand the harm he did to me. Jose molested me by digital penetration of my vagina and fondling. I was terrified to do anything but keep quiet and not move while he violated me. He told me, ''Don't tell Mom.''</p>
        <p>Because I was afraid of Jose and the effect that I believed disclosing the abuse would have had on my family, I did not reveal his actions to anyone and hid my horror and shame for many years.</p>
        <p>Because of his status as an adult, a man and as a future priest, I believed at the time and continued to believe for many years that the abuse was somehow my fault. Jose continued to be treated as a member of my family. My mother was a special guest at his ordination to the priesthood and was as proud of him as if he were her own son.</p>
        <p>In 1984, when I was 29 years old and pregnant with my first child, Father Jose came to visit my husband and me in Juno, along with my mother. This visit precipitated a nervous breakdown. I disclosed the abuse to my husband after the visit and sought counseling at his urging.</p>
        <p>Dr. Appleby</p>
        <p>The root of the problem is the lack of accountability on the part of the bishops, which allowed a severe moral failure on the part of some priests and bishops to put the legacy, reputation and good work of the church in peril. The lack of accountability, in turn, was fostered by a closed clerical culture that infects the priesthood, isolating some priests and bishops from the faithful and from one another.</p>
        <p>No one can safely generalize about a group as huge, complex and amorphous as the laity. It is also wrong to generalize about you, the bishops. Indeed, many of you are not only blameless in the current scandal -- you have acted honorably in the incredibly difficult balancing act you are called upon to perform. You did not protect abusive priests, nor have you attempted to circle the wagons or clamp down on lay dissent when outraged parishioners and priests in recent months demanded accountability for episcopal misdeeds. Other bishops, however, have behaved atrociously, angering fellow bishops and priests, whose reputations have been tarnished by those whose actions have been marked by arrogance, lack of repentance, and repeated failure to be collegial and consultative, except in an upward direction. . . .</p>
        <p>Rome has been very cautious, to say the least, in granting authority to the national episcopal conferences, and I believe that the laity have or will have difficulty understanding what appears to be a counterproductive level of oversight. Please pardon the question, but it is a natural one: are you not trusted by the Vatican? It seems incredible to the interested outsider that on matters of faith and morals you would veer one millimeter from orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>Those of you who are canon lawyers know the challenge of applying canon law within a specific local and national environment. The state and civil society in, say, Honduras, or Poland, present different challenges to the church than does the U.S. government and legal system.</p>
        <p>To the extent possible, then, I urge you to formulate the policies that make the most sense for this environment, without anticipating how the Vatican might respond. Let Rome be Rome; it will be, in any case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from statements yesterday before the United States Conference of Bishops by two people who say they are victims of sexual abuse, Craig Martin and Paula Gonzales Rohrbacher, and the director ofNotre Dame University's Center for the Study of American Catholicism, Scott Appleby. The speeches by Mr. Martin and Ms. Rohrbacher were recorded by The New York Times. Mr. Appleby's comments were taken from the Web site of the bishop's conference. The full texts of the statements are online at nytimes.com/national. Mr. Martin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from statements yesterday before the United States Conference of Bishops by two people who say they are victims of sexual abuse, Craig Martin and Paula Gonzales Rohrbacher, and the director of Notre Dame University's Center for the Study of American Catholicism, Scott Appleby. The speeches by Mr. Martin and Ms. Rohrbacher were recorded by The New York Times. Mr. Appleby's comments were taken from the Web site of the bishop's conference. The full texts of the statements are online at nytimes.com/national.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin</p>
        <p>I find it's easier to tell my story using the name John Doe. I can revisit my pain and not hurt myself again. I found different stories that have helped me to understand my suffering. I'd like to share some of those today so that others may be helped.</p>
        <p>In John's late 20's he meets his wife, Julie. This is a start to his recovery, yet John has no idea. John's wife brings him back to religion and also introduces him to a priest that helps in John's recovery. I wish I could say recovery started here. But John wasn't quite ready. John had to read an article out of Sports Illustrated dated Sept. 13, 1999, entitled ''Every Parents Nightmare.'' This describes to John why he was in a position to be hurt. It goes like this:</p>
        <p>''While society has no trouble envisioning the violent molester and the child who is forced to submit to a sexual predator, many people are baffled by how adult seducers are able to get kids to go along with them voluntarily. These men seduce children, in this case boys in exactly the same way men and women have been seducing each other since the dawn of mankind. In other words they flirt with them, laugh at their jokes, shower them with attention, with gifts, with affection. They size up their weaknesses, their vulnerability, their needs. They will target the kids who are more vulnerable.''</p>
        <p>The amazing part of when I allowed John to talk about his abuser was how this man also offered kindness and love. How this man became John's best friend. John has showed very little anger toward his abuser. I was amazed at who John directed his sorrow to. He directed his sorrow not at his abuser but at his parents.</p>
        <p>John tells a story of how his abuser wants to take John fishing. The abuser asks John's parents if it's O.K. John's parents thought it was a great idea for John to go on a fishing trip with a Catholic priest.</p>
        <p>John talks of how his relationship with his parents changed. How he no longer trusted them. How alone he feels.</p>
        <p>Mom and Dad, I'm terribly sorry for how I treated you. Please accept my apology. I know that only thing I have in my heart for you is love. I love you both dearly.</p>
        <p>You see a child who is abused is put in a frightening and confusing situation. They may have never heard of anything like this happening. Nobody has told them it's right. Nobody has told them it's wrong. Everybody may like and respect the person who is doing these things.</p>
        <p>John remembers this motel that night with the priest. But hardly anything else. John has no idea how he got home. It is only 35 years later that John is starting to remember what happened that horrible night.</p>
        <p>Abused children often hide their anger and distress from others so that no one will suspect that they're being abused. They may also keep their feelings under control while they're being abused to protect themselves from feelings of distress and pain, or because they don't want the abuser to see how much he is hurting them. Many adult survivors continue to cope by blocking feelings and trying to forget about the past.</p>
        <p>Survivors often have a low opinion of themselves and lack self-confidence and self-esteem. They may feel worthless, useless and unloved. Many survivors put on a front and present themselves as capable, cheerful, confident, while feeling wretched inside. Survivors may be so overwhelmed by their low opinion of themselves and lack of confidence that they may suffer bouts of depression making them unable to act positively or find pleasure in things.</p>
        <p>I say these words because they describe John's feelings exactly. John became sexually active shortly after his abuse. John describes some very unhealthy attitudes toward women, admits to seeking out women in a predatory way. Alcohol also started to control John's life. It was many years before he finally sought help for alcoholism.</p>
        <p>Although sexual compulsivity and alcoholism had major effects on John, it was his need for self-esteem that's kept him alive. John still admits today to having low self-esteem. John has shown symptoms of low self-esteem, depression, anger and the need to control. John has been able to survive only because of his family, his friends, his children and the therapy he continues to go through.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rohrbacher</p>
        <p>When I was a little girl, my family, at the request of Mount Angel Seminary in Oregon, befriended several Mexican seminarians who were students there. The seminary placed one of these young men with my family, who was also Hispanic, no doubt to ease his transition to life in the United States.</p>
        <p>My mother, who regarded him as a son and encouraged my siblings and me to treat him as a brother, generously welcomed him into our family. We housed him over school holidays and summer vacations. The young seminarian that my family sponsored was named Jose. Our family situation was difficult when I was a child. My father died in 1960, leaving my mother a widow with 14- and 8-year-old sons and myself, age 5. During summer vacations she had no choice but to leave us at home while she worked.</p>
        <p>The summer of 1967 Jose lived with us during his break from the seminary. He took advantage of my mother's trust in him and sexually molested me.</p>
        <p>As difficult as it is for me to reveal these deeply personal aspects of my life to you, and probably uncomfortable for you to hear, I feel it is important for you to understand the harm he did to me. Jose molested me by digital penetration of my vagina and fondling. I was terrified to do anything but keep quiet and not move while he violated me. He told me, ''Don't tell Mom.''</p>
        <p>Because I was afraid of Jose and the effect that I believed disclosing the abuse would have had on my family, I did not reveal his actions to anyone and hid my horror and shame for many years.</p>
        <p>Because of his status as an adult, a man and as a future priest, I believed at the time and continued to believe for many years that the abuse was somehow my fault. Jose continued to be treated as a member of my family. My mother was a special guest at his ordination to the priesthood and was as proud of him as if he were her own son.</p>
        <p>In 1984, when I was 29 years old and pregnant with my first child, Father Jose came to visit my husband and me in Juno, along with my mother. This visit precipitated a nervous breakdown. I disclosed the abuse to my husband after the visit and sought counseling at his urging.</p>
        <p>Dr. Appleby</p>
        <p>The root of the problem is the lack of accountability on the part of the bishops, which allowed a severe moral failure on the part of some priests and bishops to put the legacy, reputation and good work of the church in peril. The lack of accountability, in turn, was fostered by a closed clerical culture that infects the priesthood, isolating some priests and bishops from the faithful and from one another.</p>
        <p>No one can safely generalize about a group as huge, complex and amorphous as the laity. It is also wrong to generalize about you, the bishops. Indeed, many of you are not only blameless in the current scandal -- you have acted honorably in the incredibly difficult balancing act you are called upon to perform. You did not protect abusive priests, nor have you attempted to circle the wagons or clamp down on lay dissent when outraged parishioners and priests in recent months demanded accountability for episcopal misdeeds. Other bishops, however, have behaved atrociously, angering fellow bishops and priests, whose reputations have been tarnished by those whose actions have been marked by arrogance, lack of repentance, and repeated failure to be collegial and consultative, except in an upward direction. . . .</p>
        <p>Rome has been very cautious, to say the least, in granting authority to the national episcopal conferences, and I believe that the laity have or will have difficulty understanding what appears to be a counterproductive level of oversight. Please pardon the question, but it is a natural one: are you not trusted by the Vatican? It seems incredible to the interested outsider that on matters of faith and morals you would veer one millimeter from orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>Those of you who are canon lawyers know the challenge of applying canon law within a specific local and national environment. The state and civil society in, say, Honduras, or Poland, present different challenges to the church than does the U.S. government and legal system.</p>
        <p>To the extent possible, then, I urge you to formulate the policies that make the most sense for this environment, without anticipating how the Vatican might respond. Let Rome be Rome; it will be, in any case.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
