<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Shun Clams, Just Cook Them Well</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="472303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1731F93BA3575AC0A967958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Shun Clams, Just Cook Them Well</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is ample evidence that clams, as delicious as they may be, pose serious health hazards when eaten raw. But that does not mean forswearing them. It just means serving them well cooked.</p>
        <p>Clams, like some other kinds of bivalves including mussels and oysters, constantly flush the water of their habitat through their bodies and easily pick up microorganisms. Thorough cooking -- for about six minutes after the clams have opened -- can destroy any disease-bearing microorganisms in the clams as well as any that might be transmitted by the shucker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is ample evidence that clams, as delicious as they may be, pose serious health hazards when eaten raw. But that does not mean forswearing them. It just means serving them well cooked.</p>
        <p>Clams, like some other kinds of bivalves including mussels and oysters, constantly flush the water of their habitat through their bodies and easily pick up microorganisms. Thorough cooking -- for about six minutes after the clams have opened -- can destroy any disease-bearing microorganisms in the clams as well as any that might be transmitted by the shucker.</p>
        <p>Broiling them on the half-shell, simply steaming them, adding them to seafood mixtures like paella or cioppino and chopping them to use in chowders and pasta sauces are just a few excellent ways to prepare cooked clams.</p>
        <p>Many seasonings can complement the briny sweetness of clams. Garlic, herbs and tomatoes are a few classics. Asian seasonings like ginger, fermented black beans and sesame oil are also excellent. Many Spanish and Portuguese recipes combine clams with pork or spicy pork sausage for another superb pairing. In this context, saffron is another seasoning to consider.</p>
        <p>The best clams for broiling on the half-shell or steaming with seasonings to serve whole are the tender littlenecks. Larger cherrystone and quahog or chowder clams can be chopped to use in soups, sauces and stuffings. The shells of any clams to be cooked whole, in the shell, should be scrubbed with a stiff brush to remove grit.</p>
        <p>Steamers, or soft clams, can also be steamed or shucked and coated with batter and quickly deep-fried. Razor clams, when they are available, are excellent grilled, the way they are served in Venice. Clams With Asian Noodles</p>
        <p>Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon fermented black beans</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons peanut oil  3 cloves garlic, chopped  1 tablespoon minced fresh ginger  1 teaspoon minced fresh hot green chili pepper  36 littleneck clams, scrubbed  1 1/2 cups salt-free chicken stock  1/4 cup rice wine  2 tablespoons sesame oil  12 ounces Japanese soba (buckwheat noodles)  1 tablespoon chopped scallions  1 tablespoon chopped coriander leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Rinse the black beans in several changes of water to remove excess salt. Pat them dry, then lightly crush them. Set them aside.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the peanut oil in a wok or a heavy casserole. Add the garlic, ginger and chili pepper and saute about a minute. Add the clams and stir.</p>
        <p>3. Add the chicken stock and rice wine, stir, then cover the pot and cook over medium heat until the clams have opened. Allow the clams to simmer in the broth another six minutes. Taste the broth. If it is too salty, add a little water or unseasoned chicken stock. Remove the pot from the heat.</p>
        <p>4. While the clams are cooking, bring a large pot of water to a boil, add the noodles and cook them about five minutes. Drain the noodles and place them in a warm serving dish. Toss them with the sesame oil.</p>
        <p>5. Reheat the clams, still in their shells, in their broth then pour the contents of the pot over the noodles. Sprinkle with scallions and coriander and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings. Clams and Sausage In Saffron Sauce</p>
        <p>Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2 cups chopped ripe tomatoes or a 1-pound can plum tomatoes  1/2 teaspoon saffron  6 tablespoons olive oil  1/2 pound chorizo, sliced  1/2 pound sweet pork sausage like Italian luganiga or Portuguese linguica, sliced in chunks</p>
        <p>1/2 cup chopped onion  1/2 cup chopped sweet red pepper  3 cloves garlic, minced  1/2 teaspoon dried oregano  2 dozen littleneck clams, scrubbed  4 slices day-old or dried French baguette or Italian bread about 3 inches across and 1/2-inch thick  2 tablespoons minced fresh parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Place the tomatoes, along with any liquid, in a saucepan, bring them to a simmer and allow them to cook about 10 minutes, until they release their juice. Strain the hot juice into a bowl, reserving the tomato pulp. Stir the saffron into the juice and allow to steep while continuing with the recipe. If using canned tomatoes, chop the pulp.</p>
        <p>2. Heat two tablespoons of the oil in a large, heavy casserole. Add the sausages and saute until they are lightly browned. Remove the sausages from the pan and reserve.</p>
        <p>3. Add the onion, red pepper and garlic to the pan and saute until they are soft but not brown. Stir in the oregano, the tomato liquid with the saffron, the tomato pulp, sausages and clams. Cover and cook for 12 to 15 minutes, until the clams have opened and have had a chance to cook, opened, for another six minutes.</p>
        <p>4. While the clams are cooking, heat the remaining olive oil in a skillet and fry the bread slices until they are lightly browned. Drain them on absorbent paper.</p>
        <p>5. To serve, place the fried bread in each of four shallow bowls. Spoon the clams and sausage, along with the liquid, over the bread. Sprinkle with parsley and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings. Clam and Mushroom Chowder</p>
        <p>Total time: 50 minutes</p>
        <p>2 cups sliced fresh mushrooms  2 tablespoons minced shallots  2 tablespoons unsalted butter  1 cup finely diced peeled boiling potatoes  1/2 cup fish stock or clam juice  1/2 cup dry white wine  1 1/2 cup chopped cherrystone or chowder clams  2 cups half-and-half  Salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Place the mushrooms, shallots and butter in a heavy saucepan. Cover and cook over low heat until the mushrooms are tender, about 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Add the potatoes, stock and white wine. Simmer, covered, until the potatoes are very soft, about 30 minutes. Add the clams and half-and-half and simmer uncovered, stirring from time to time, about 10 minutes longer.</p>
        <p>3. Season to taste with salt and pepper and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.  FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
