<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daily News Is Turning a Gamble Into a Rebirth</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="646444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK DAILY NEWS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZUCKERMAN, MORTIMER B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D71131F932A35752C1A965958260" item-length="1678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daily News Is Turning a Gamble Into a Rebirth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Daily News, bankrupt and battered when Mortimer B. Zuckerman bought it last January, is now a profitable business, its publishers say, reversing multimillion-dollar losses and defying predictions of doom that plagued the New York newspaper for a decade.</p>
        <p>About a hundred newly hired writers and editors are settling in. Advertising revenues are climbing, the publishers say. And the newspaper's pages are beginning to show some of their old zip. In effect, the owners are betting millions of dollars that the cheeky but rigorous style of tabloid journalism that The News virtually invented can thrive again in America's biggest city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Daily News, bankrupt and battered when Mortimer B. Zuckerman bought it last January, is now a profitable business, its publishers say, reversing multimillion-dollar losses and defying predictions of doom that plagued the New York newspaper for a decade.</p>
        <p>About a hundred newly hired writers and editors are settling in. Advertising revenues are climbing, the publishers say. And the newspaper's pages are beginning to show some of their old zip. In effect, the owners are betting millions of dollars that the cheeky but rigorous style of tabloid journalism that The News virtually invented can thrive again in America's biggest city.</p>
        <p>The bet appears to be paying off.</p>
        <p>The signs of rebirth at what is still, by far, New York City's largest-circulation tabloid newspaper have some in the newspaper industry saying that Mr. Zuckerman's News is likely to be a powerful contestant in a new tabloid war.</p>
        <p>"The News right now has more going for it than the others," said Gerald D. Reilly, a newspaper broker and financial consultant who has followed the New York City newspaper battles for decades. "Ultimately, Zuckerman may be the one who survives."</p>
        <p>The News has recently been selling about 775,000 copies a day. While that is less than a third of its 2.4 million circulation in 1947, it is almost double that of The New York Post, its closest tabloid competitor. The Post sells about 400,000 copies a day, and New York Newsday about 270,000, newspaper executives said. Predictions of Profit</p>
        <p>Fred Drasner, Mr. Zuckerman's co-publisher and owner of a minority share of The News, said in an interview that the newspaper would be "substantially profitable this year." Some newspaper industry executives said The News, which lost about $100 million over the last 10 years, could make a profit this year, perhaps as much as $10 million. Mr. Reilly said he thought the newspaper had become profitable, but perhaps not at that level.</p>
        <p>Because The News is privately owned, its profits do not have to be reported and cannot be verified.</p>
        <p>The New York Post has cut its annual losses to about $6 million, executives of the newspaper said. New York Newsday loses $8 million to $14 million a year, Newsday's publisher, Robert M. Johnson, said recently.</p>
        <p>Advertising revenue at The News is up more than 6 percent compared with year-earlier levels, News executives say, though they do not give figures. The newspaper has cut labor, newsprint and other costs.</p>
        <p>"We are committed to making this a first-rate paper," Mr. Zuckerman said in an interview. "You can't do that unless the paper is profitable and economically viable. The paper is economically viable."</p>
        <p>By all accounts, The News has a long way to go in its rebuilding. It is searching for a distinctive voice, it must build a new $135 million color printing plant, and it is still weakened by years of troubles that included a bitter five-month strike in 1990-91 against the Tribune Company of Chicago, then the newspaper's owner.</p>
        <p>Many of the business challenges that weakened The News in the first place have remained. Newspaper readership has been in decline nationally for decades and many of The News's loyal readers moved to the suburbs from working-class city neighborhoods that were traditional News strongholds.</p>
        <p>And as News management digs in for the war of the tabloids, it does not know how much money Rupert Murdoch, who controls The Post, and the Times Mirror Company, which owns New York Newsday, are prepared to pour into the battle.</p>
        <p>But inside The News, reporters, editors and business employees say that for the first time in a dozen years, they feel that they are part of an enterprise with a future. And outside The News's 42nd Street headquarters, the newspaper is beginning to attract attention again. A Sharper Focus</p>
        <p>For the first six months of Mr. Zuckerman's ownership, the newspaper appeared to drift under his first editor, Lou Colasuonno. In July, Mr. Zuckerman installed a new editor in chief, Martin Dunn, above Mr. Colasuonno, in what some at The News said was already a top-heavy newsroom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunn, who is British and the former editor of a Murdoch tabloid in London, has so far received high marks for unifying the staff and focusing the paper on the kinds of issue-oriented, snappily presented articles that were once typical of The News.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Dunn's early ideas resulted in "The Strippers," the newspaper's front-page article on a Sunday last month. The News had bought a 1985 Honda, parked it on a New York City street, and had its photographers watch. By the fourth day of the vigil, car strippers had reduced it to a bucket of bolts that was a "curbside blight and barely resembling a vehicle."</p>
        <p>That, Mr. Dunn said, was the kind of "hey, Mabel" article (as in "Hey, Mabel, look at this!") that The News must present.</p>
        <p>For the first time in a long time, News readers are beginning to find a regular mix of the humor and outrage that are the hallmarks of tabloid journalism. Last week, Larry Sutton, a writer, described what Leona Helmsley, the hotel executive who was convicted of tax evasion, would find in her new quarters at the Marquis Hotel halfway house. The account on the "new digs" of the "hotel queen" included a chart comparing the halfway house ("bathroom: yes; amenities: none") with the plush New York Palace that she used to run.</p>
        <p>Last month, a News reporter, Annette Fuentes, wrote "Separated at Birth," an account of "de facto segregation" in the maternity wards of Mount Sinai Medical Center. The article drew wide attention.</p>
        <p>"We still are the dominant tabloid paper," Mr. Dunn said, "We have to, really, by sheer force of journalism, impose ourselves back on the New York market."  New Money, New Sections</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman and Mr. Drasner have added new sections and pages for news, sports and cultural coverage and have hired new television and movie reviewers. The newspaper has started a full-color television guide on Sunday and, it says, has spent $3 million to promote it. Yesterday, The News began offering the syndicated magazine, USA Weekend.</p>
        <p>Some News veterans say the burst of investment has helped Mr. Zuckerman and Mr. Drasner win over employees. "You see money being put in," said Arthur Browne, a veteran News reporter and editor who is now the editorial page editor. "That tells the staff: 'They're interested. They're not just here to play around.' "</p>
        <p>Not everyone at The News is happy. Some News veterans say the publishers have appeared more interested in hiring gossip columnists and getting glitzy Hollywood coverage than in focusing on serious news.</p>
        <p>Last summer, one of the newspaper's most respected reporters, Lars-Erik Nelson, who was the Washington bureau chief, defected to Newsday. The move was a serious blow to The News because it was widely known that Mr. Nelson complained bitterly to Mr. Zuckerman about what he called a lack of emphasis on rebuilding news coverage.</p>
        <p>The News was also hurt when Mike McAlary, one of the best-known New York columnists, tried to break his contract with Mr. Zuckerman to join Mr. Murdoch's Post during the summer. That fight was being waged in court when Mr. McAlary was sidelined by an automobile accident in September. He is now recovering and is expected to return to writing, although it is not clear where.</p>
        <p>Despite such setbacks, Mr. Zuckerman appeared to feel vindicated by the progress at The News as he sat the other day with the telephone ringing off the hook in his midtown office. "Just look at the results," he said.</p>
        <p>During his bitter fight to win The News a year ago, Mr. Zuckerman, who is estimated to have made $300 million in the real estate business, often appeared offended by suggestions that he was something of a journalistic dilettante who would be overwhelmed by the complexities of a big-city daily.</p>
        <p>"I appreciate all the doubting Thomases," Mr. Zuckerman said in an interview last week. "What I'm always astounded by is that just because I have had some business success, people assume you do not have intellectual interests and intellectual capabilities."</p>
        <p>People at The News say Mr. Zuckerman is deeply involved in news and editorial decisions, personally hiring editors at all levels and pressing his views about coverage, story presentation and editorials.</p>
        <p>But everyone, including Mr. Zuckerman, credits much of the business progress to Mr. Drasner, an authentic new New York City personality. Mr. Drasner, 50, is a tough former real estate and tax lawyer who chews on big cigars and favors blunt talk.  'Mr. Inside'</p>
        <p>Mr. Drasner generally leaves the public policy and journalism to Mr. Zuckerman. But at The News, it is Mr. Drasner, the "Mr. Inside" of the pair, who is clearly in charge of the business operation. And the message, often delivered with biting sarcasm, is: win or die, and don't take any time off in the process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Drasner recently razzed his top deputy, Ira Ellenthal, about Mr. Ellenthal's desire to take a week's vacation. Mr. Ellenthal, The News's associate publisher, went anyway. He returned to find a new person at his desk and the nameplate on his office door changed. The new occupant turned out to be an actor hired by Mr. Drasner in an elaborate practical joke that played off Mr. Drasner's reputation as a relentless boss.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellenthal was unfazed. In the spirit that Mr. Drasner sets at The News, Mr. Ellenthal has his own somewhat competitive sign hanging on the wall of his office. It is a picture of Mr. Drasner with the following printed underneath: "1943-Soon."</p>
        <p>But it is clear that, for now, Mr. Drasner's approach to reviving The News is working. The other day, Mr. Ellenthal was pleased to point out two pages in the television magazine to a visitor in Mr. Drasner's office.</p>
        <p>The News, long starved of national advertising and never an important ad venue for high-cost items, had won a full-color, two-page Cadillac ad.</p>
        <p>"There's a Cadillac ad in The Daily News," Mr. Drasner said proudly. It was a businessman's way of saying The Daily News had come a long way.  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
