<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tehuacan Journal; Back of the New Mall, Age-Old Ritual of Slaughter</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="646420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOATS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TEHUACAN (MEX)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDEN, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED6143EF932A35752C1A965958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tehuacan Journal; Back of the New Mall, Age-Old Ritual of Slaughter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDEN, TIM</byline>
      <dateline>TEHUACAN, Mexico</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Past the Nissan dealership and Tehuacan Ford, just beyond the pastel-colored tract homes going up on the edge of town, the Slaughter of the Goats has begun again.</p>
        <p>As they have at every harvest, the goatherds have brought their animals over the Oaxaca mountains to this market town, and the matanceros, the butchers, have come from the nearby village of San Gabriel Chilac. Each day for two weeks, or as long as the herd might last, they will fill the courtyard of an old hacienda here with an ancient ritual of blood and death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Past the Nissan dealership and Tehuacan Ford, just beyond the pastel-colored tract homes going up on the edge of town, the Slaughter of the Goats has begun again.</p>
        <p>As they have at every harvest, the goatherds have brought their animals over the Oaxaca mountains to this market town, and the matanceros, the butchers, have come from the nearby village of San Gabriel Chilac. Each day for two weeks, or as long as the herd might last, they will fill the courtyard of an old hacienda here with an ancient ritual of blood and death.</p>
        <p>On the first and last mornings of the slaughter, there is still a dance -- dancing the goat, the Indians call it. And each afternoon, as the intestines hang from clotheslines and boys with wheelbarrows cart away the severed heads, the goat killers rise up on their knees as their fathers did, to pray at their chopping blocks for the Lord's protection.</p>
        <p>But almost four centuries after it took root in what were then still known as "the lands of the chieftains," the Matanza, as the ritual is called in Spanish, has taken on an air of uncertainty. Some of the dancers have begun to forget their steps, and no one seems to remember why one of them holds a flaming chalice toward the sky. Some in the courtyard say that this might be the last Matanza, or that at most there might be a few more. Guns Are Now Used</p>
        <p>It has been six or seven years since the matanceros could slash the necks of a thousand goats each day and let them stagger about the patio bleeding until they died. Because of the protests of animal-rights campaigners in Mexico City, 158 miles to the northwest, the killing is now done with guns, thick black livestock pistols that leave neat holes in the goats' heads.</p>
        <p>Bloody as it remains, the business seems less violent to the men than that of the rustlers who come out from the poppy and marijuana fields not far from where the goats are pastured. The rustlers carry assault rifles now; in a raid this spring, they shot two of the goatherds and left one of them dead.</p>
        <p>"We just do this to keep from giving up," says Inigo Garcia Peralta, a Huajuapan rancher who has brought his goats to Tehuacan (pronounced tay-wah-KAHN) for the last 44 of his 70 years. "We don't make money any more. And what is it worth if they kill you?"</p>
        <p>No one asks directly whether the ritual ought to continue right behind the new domed shopping mall, in a town that is trying to change its image, in a country that wants a free-trade agreement with Canada and the United States.</p>
        <p>The challenge is more complicated than that.</p>
        <p>There is the transport tax that the ranchers must pay because there is no longer enough open land to herd the goats from Oaxaca to Tehuacan, so they come by truck. There is sales tax on the meat and skins, income tax on any profits and bribes to pay some of the health inspectors and highway police. The Only One Left</p>
        <p>More important, goat-loin mole now costs about $10 a plate, more than poor people can afford for the spicy dish they have always eaten after the Matanza. Years ago, almost 100,000 goats were killed in a half a dozen slaughters in Tehuacan and the Oaxacan town of Huajuapan de Leon. Now, Mr. Garcia's slaughter is the only one left, and he will be lucky to kill and sell 6,000 goats.</p>
        <p>There is little record of the history of the slaughter, and some dispute over the prevalent notion that it supplanted rituals of human sacrifice that existed here before the Spaniards brought their goats and stockmen's guilds to the New World. But to view the slaughter as a way to butcher goat meat would seem to ignore the intensity and seeming symbolism of what takes place.</p>
        <p>At the beginning, hooves scrape across the cement patio as young men drag the goats from their pens in twos, a horn in either fist. They swarm around the captains, men in coarse aprons and cowboy hats, and the captains drop their arms quickly, firing between the goats' eyes.</p>
        <p>Older men wearing only shorts and T-shirts reach down and drive their knives into the goats' chests. Women with plastic buckets rush up to catch the blood, and the old men help them, holding the goats over their pails. Frenzy Yields to Order</p>
        <p>The younger men carry the animals away, dumping them across the patio in twitching piles of horns and legs and stained fur. For a while, the only sounds are the clacking and popping of the black guns and the thud of the goats being dropped on straw mats.</p>
        <p>After a while, the frenzy gives way to an almost mechanical order. The least experienced men move across a first row of mats, carving off tails and ears. Behind them, the more expert butchers set to the harder work, scoring the bellies of the goats and then digging their bare heels beneath the skin to pull it off whole. For a long time, they say almost nothing to one another. When they do, it is in Nahuatl, the language of the Aztecs and other Indian peoples of central Mexico. 'This Is Nothing'</p>
        <p>On the patio's edge, a 69-year-old woman named Fermina Romero de Rojas watched the carnage the other day and was unimpressed.</p>
        <p>"This is nothing," said the woman, who had come from nearby San Gabriel Chilac. "Each of us used to do 100, 150 heads every day. You did not have time to eat or sleep."</p>
        <p>Beside Mrs. Rojas, her husband, Eusebio Rojas, 71, watched quietly.</p>
        <p>"Before, they did not clean anything," he said after a while. "There wasn't any cement. It was the earth, and the earth consumed the blood."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
