<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Olmert Wants to Define Borders, Ally Says</title>
    <meta content="06mideast" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/06/international/middleeast/06mideast.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1744676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">West Bank</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Olmert, Ehud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DE1531F935A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="960" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Olmert Wants to Define Borders, Ally Says</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Olmert Wants to Define Borders, Ally Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG MYRE</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, March 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's acting prime minister, Ehud Olmert, will seek to evacuate additional West Bank settlements and define Israel's permanent borders if his Kadima Party wins this month's national elections, a top ally of Mr. Olmert said Sunday.</p>
        <p>The comments by Avi Dichter, a former chief of the Shin Bet security service and a parliamentary candidate for Kadima, reinforced previous remarks by Mr. Olmert and provided additional details about what a future government might do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's acting prime minister will seek to evacuate additional West Bank settlements if his party wins this month's elections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israel's acting prime minister, Ehud Olmert, will seek to evacuate additional West Bank settlements and define Israel's permanent borders if his Kadima Party wins this month's national elections, a top ally of Mr. Olmert said Sunday.</p>
        <p>The comments by Avi Dichter, a former chief of the Shin Bet security service and a parliamentary candidate for Kadima, reinforced previous remarks by Mr. Olmert and provided additional details about what a future government might do.</p>
        <p>''In the absence of a Palestinian partner, Israel will have to determine by itself its own permanent border,'' Mr. Dichter said on Israeli radio.</p>
        <p>He said planning for a West Bank pullout could begin soon after the March 28 election, in which Kadima is heavily favored. An estimated four years would be needed for Israel to set its boundaries unilaterally, he added.</p>
        <p>One idea under discussion calls for Jewish settlers in some of the smaller, more isolated settlements to be moved into the larger settlement blocs, Mr. Dichter said. But he emphasized that Israel would maintain security forces in the areas where settlers were evacuated.</p>
        <p>About 250,000 Jewish settlers live in the West Bank, land captured by Israel in the 1967 war. The figure does not include 200,000 Israelis who live in East Jerusalem, which Israel annexed after the war.</p>
        <p>The Palestinians are sure to object to any borders that Israel draws itself, but the two leading Palestinian factions offered contrasting opinions on Sunday on the prospect of a unilateral Israeli withdrawal from some settlements.</p>
        <p>The Palestinian Authority president, Mahmoud Abbas, and his Fatah movement favor a negotiated settlement with Israel and generally oppose one-sided Israeli actions. Saeb Erekat, the chief Palestinian negotiator, reaffirmed this position on Sunday, saying such Israeli moves would complicate any future negotiations.</p>
        <p>But Hamas, the militant Islamic group that is forming the new Palestinian government, raised no objection. ''Let them withdraw,'' Ismail Haniya, the Hamas leader who is the prime minister-designate, was quoted as saying by Reuters. ''We will make the authority stronger on every inch of liberated land, knowing that the borders and rights of the Palestinian people are known and will not change.''</p>
        <p>Hamas refuses to recognize Israel, and rejects negotiating with it. In Moscow on Sunday, a Hamas delegation wrapped up a three-day visit, where the group rebuffed Russia's call to moderate its positions. The trip to Russia was the first by Hamas leaders outside the Muslim world since its election victory in January.</p>
        <p>''Hamas must change its manners -- we know that very well,'' Muhammad Nazzal, a senior Hamas leader, told Agence France-Presse. ''But what we are saying is that we want a response from the Israelis. If you want Hamas to change its policies, you must also request that the Israelis change their policies.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Mr. Olmert spoke to President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia by telephone and told him it had been a mistake for Russia to hold talks with Hamas. Mr. Olmert said that the talks would only discourage Hamas from making changes sought by other countries, like the recognition of Israel, according to a statement from Mr. Olmert's office.</p>
        <p>Israeli settlers and their supporters denounced the talk of a new round of West Bank withdrawals. ''Who is the Palestinian fool who will sit in negotiations and will have to pay so that we evacuate territory, when he knows if he simply waits, Israel will evacuate the territory?'' said Uzi Landau, a prominent member of the right-wing Likud Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dichter was also quoted discussing a possible withdrawal in the Sunday editions of Yediot Aharonot, the country's largest-circulation newspaper.</p>
        <p>Citing Kadima officials, the newspaper reported that at least 17 settlements would be evacuated in the first stage of a withdrawal. Israel has about 120 settlements in the West Bank. Last August, Israel evacuated four small West Bank settlements immediately after completing the pullout in the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dichter has criticized the way that Israel handled the Gaza pullout, saying the withdrawal of Israeli troops allowed Palestinians to continue to carry out rocket attacks into Israel. He said that in future withdrawals, the Israeli security forces would remain in position.</p>
        <p>''It will be a civilian disengagement only,'' said Mr. Dichter, who stepped down as the head of Shin Bet last year, shortly before the Gaza withdrawal. ''It will not be a military disengagement.'' If Kadima wins the election, Mr. Dichter is considered a strong candidate for a senior security post.</p>
        <p>Mr. Olmert has not said where Israel may seek to set a future border, though it would most likely run along, or near, the separation barrier that Israel is building in the West Bank.</p>
        <p>Under the current plan for the route, the barrier would keep about 10 percent of the West Bank on the Israeli side, incorporating the major settlement blocs and East Jerusalem. But Mr. Olmert has also said that Israel cannot abandon the Jordan Valley, which includes many small settlements far beyond the West Bank barrier and near the border with Jordan.</p>
        <p>In another development on Sunday, the departing Palestinian prime minister, Ahmed Qurei, said Fatah should not join Hamas in the new Palestinian government. Fatah's Revolutionary Council is holding talks in the West Bank city of Ramallah, and by all indications, the group is planning to reject Hamas's offer to join the cabinet.</p>
        <p>Fatah has dominated Palestinian politics for decades, but won only 45 seats in the January parliamentary election. Hamas won 74 seats, giving it a majority in the 132-seat legislature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
