<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Speed Humps That Divide</title>
    <meta content="16BUMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973529"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BROOKLYN UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DB1538F935A25752C1A961958260" item-length="538" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Speed Humps That Divide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christopher R. Lynn was the most unpopular man in Brooklyn last week, at least among the borough's community boards. In district after district, Mr. Lynn, the Transportation Commissioner, was under fire for what critics described as an autocratic management style, characterized by a refusal to consult or advise the boards.</p>
        <p>The eye of the political hurricane was Board 14, which represents Flatbush and Midwood. Mr. Lynn had installed speed humps at several sites in the district. Officials said they had not been asked whether or where the humps should be installed, and residents had been complaining of increased traffic on nearby streets and screeching brakes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christopher R. Lynn was the most unpopular man in Brooklyn last week, at least among the borough's community boards. In district after district, Mr. Lynn, the Transportation Commissioner, was under fire for what critics described as an autocratic management style, characterized by a refusal to consult or advise the boards.</p>
        <p>The eye of the political hurricane was Board 14, which represents Flatbush and Midwood. Mr. Lynn had installed speed humps at several sites in the district. Officials said they had not been asked whether or where the humps should be installed, and residents had been complaining of increased traffic on nearby streets and screeching brakes.</p>
        <p>Board 14 is not the only one gunning for Mr. Lynn. On Wednesday night, Board 6 passed a resolution condemning Mr. Lynn for ''various and sundry acts performed by him in his capacity as a public official,'' said Craig Hammerman, the board's district manager. Mr. Hammerman said Mr. Lynn had repeatedly refused to send representatives to apprise the board of ongoing major capital projects.</p>
        <p>Some board officials also said when they had tried to follow up citizen complaints with the agency, they had been told to file Freedom of Information requests. The department, they said, seemed to be trying to circumvent their authority by encouraging citizens to call a help line (212 or 718 CALL-DOT) directly to report potholes, broken traffic lights and other problems.</p>
        <p>Robert Leonard, a spokesman for Mr. Lynn, said the Commissioner sought input from community boards during the budget consultation process but could not do so day to day. ''Does Howard Safir ask the commnity boards when he wants to arrest someone?'' Mr. Leonard asked, referring to the Police Commissioner.</p>
        <p>Community boards, he said, ''are not made up of engineers.'' He said that having citizens call the department directly would eliminate the time-consuming paper trail that community boards used to process citizen complaints.</p>
        <p>On the streets of Board 14, meanwhile, opinion on the humps was divided. Sandra Stein, the president of the board for Terrace Garden Plaza, a housing co-op on East 17th Street, was so upset by the humps on East 16th Street between Avenues I and J that she collected 250 signatures on a petition, which she presented to the community board.</p>
        <p>Her neighborhood was a warren of one-way streets and dead-ends, she said, and East 16th Street was the main egress for the emergency medical vehicles that Terrace Garden's elderly residents relied on. ''This is a safety issue for everyone,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But some neighborhood residents said they thought the humps enhanced safety, especially considering the Yeshiva of Flatbush High School at the corner. ''People were trying to make the light, and there's a school there,'' said Renee Saperstein, 65. ''So it's a good thing.''</p>
        <p>AMY WALDMAN</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BROOKLYN UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
