<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even Vassals Get Vacations</title>
    <meta content="16LICHTET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtenstein, Nelson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacoby, Sanford M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Modern Manors (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5D81739F935A25752C1A961958260" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even Vassals Get Vacations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Lichtenstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lichtenstein, Nelson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nelson Lichtenstein reviews book Modern Manors. Welfare Capitalism Since the New Deal by Sanford M Jacoby (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Modern Manors</p>
        <p>Welfare Capitalism Since the New Deal.</p>
        <p>By Sanford M. Jacoby.</p>
        <p>345 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Modern Manors</p>
        <p>Welfare Capitalism Since the New Deal.</p>
        <p>By Sanford M. Jacoby.</p>
        <p>345 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $35.</p>
        <p>Earlier this fall Working Mother magazine put TRW, the big aerospace and automotive-parts company, on its list of the most ''family friendly'' companies in America. Offering a full menu of benefits, including flexible hours and free adoption counseling, TRW has won the genuine loyalty of many employees. ''I've never once considered going to another company,'' the systems analyst Sandy Smallwood, a 14-year veteran, told a reporter. ''I've been very, very happy with TRW.''</p>
        <p>An enlightened management meeting the needs of a sophisticated work force in a tight labor market? Surely we have crossed a great divide: TRW's ''family friendly'' managers seem to have no ideological connection to the corporation's rabidly anti-union employers of three generations ago.</p>
        <p>But Sanford M. Jacoby demonstrates just such a linkage in a powerful and authoritative work that explores the hidden history of some of America's most celebrated companies. Jacoby, a professor of history, management and public policy at U.C.L.A., titles his book ''Modern Manors'' because he believes that 20th-century American corporations are not unlike the feudal baronies of old, offering security and identity in return for deference and fealty. Despite all the brutal downsizings of recent years and the job-hopping endemic to the technologically literate, the corporation, he says, has become the core social welfare institution of our time.</p>
        <p>The vigor of this system has come as a big surprise to the experts, because it was not so long ago that social theorists thought history was moving in just the opposite direction. In the usual tale, the welfare capitalism of the early 20th century, with its company towns and paternalistic employers, seemed to have been swept aside by the New Deal and the unions that waxed so strong after the Great Depression. Union-negotiated pensions supplanted corporate paternalism, suburban soccer teams replaced the company baseball league, and if the march to some kind of national health insurance was full of pitfalls, it also seemed inevitable.</p>
        <p>But in three fascinating case studies -- of Kodak; Sears, Roebuck; and Thompson Products (now TRW) -- Jacoby demonstrates that even at the height of labor power and government liberalism during the New Deal and after, determined managers could stave off unionization and win the loyalty of their work force by inventing an even more effective welfare capitalism. Men like Robert Wood of Sears and Frederick Crawford of Thompson Products, once thought to be corporate neanderthals, turn out in this insightful account to be corporate visionaries, pioneers of modern personnel management. The techniques these corporate conservatives invented have become industrial templates that now guide virtually every executive and human resource officer who wants to boost productivity and keep both the government and unions at bay. These leaders ''routinized paternalism,'' Jacoby writes, to create a ''modern welfare capitalism,'' one that was ''controlling yet consensual, coldly efficient yet cozily humane.''</p>
        <p>Jacoby calls Kodak a kind of ''corporate coelacanth,'' a living example of what welfare capitalism might have looked like had the Depression, the welfare state and mass unionism never occurred. For most of its corporate existence, Kodak was generous with its employees because of the profits it earned and the skill and responsibility it required from its work force. Kodak's no-layoff policy, abandoned only in the 1980's, generated such intense loyalty that unionization was never much of a threat. And even before World War II Kodak paid a sizable ''wage dividend,'' provided good pensions and gave blue-collar workers paid vacations.</p>
        <p>But if Kodak managers did not fear the unions, they did worry that an expansive welfare state might dilute the impact of the company's beneficence. So a Kodak personnel executive, Marion Folsom, worked long and hard to keep Social Security benefits as nothing more than a ''basic minimum protection.'' And he fought to insure that Federal tax policies were structured to subsidize, not obstruct, corporate welfare strategies.</p>
        <p>Thompson Products, on the other hand, would seem an unlikely pioneer of welfare capitalism. Headquartered in the heart of the industrial Midwest, it employed unskilled immigrants who might well have been recruited into a militant union like the United Automobile Workers. But Frederick Crawford, the company head, demonstrated that with enough legal talent, public relations and willpower a combative corporation could frustrate the National Labor Relations Board, stymie union organizers and build a wall of company unions that plausibly mimicked independent labor organizations.</p>
        <p>Crawford was a tireless advocate of what we would today call ''management by walking around.'' But he always kept the iron fist in reserve. He gleefully violated the Wagner Act, especially its prohibitions against employer interference in union elections. And as president of the National Association of Manufacturers he was a driving force behind passage of the 1947 Taft-Hartley Act, which finally legalized many of the stratagems in his anti-union tool kit.</p>
        <p>Jacoby's most chilling account of corporate welfarism involves your friendly neighborhood Sears store. Management again appears before its workers as Janus-faced. A generous profit-sharing program forged a set of ''golden handcuffs'' for many full-time male employees, while a diabolical program of employee surveys and interviews provided management with intelligence on its personnel (as well as offering employees a catharsis-like experience designed to relieve emotional stress). He calls this sophisticated Sears program, which was used to fight off unionism in the postwar years, ''dirty science.''</p>
        <p>Although his analytic arrows find many a managerial target, Jacoby concludes on a note of pessimism. Even as individual corporations remain inherently unstable -- last month Kodak announced another sweeping set of layoffs -- the ideological triumph of welfare capitalism is virtually complete. Jacoby himself offers no broader vision, but before we consign ourselves to this corporate end of history, Americans might first ponder the sober lessons to be drawn from this impressive book.</p>
        <p>Nelson Lichtenstein, who teaches history at the University of Virginia, is the author of ''Walter Reuther: The Most Dangerous Man in Detroit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nelson Lichtenstein, who teaches history at the University of Virginia, is the author of ''Walter Reuther: The Most Dangerous Man in Detroit.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
