<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="16BENE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971119T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DD1538F935A25752C1A961958260" item-length="2343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of Sales and Songs</p>
        <p>TODAY -- A dinner at Laura Belle, 120 West 43d Street, will feature an auction and a cabaret show starring James Naughton, Kate Burton, Laurie Beechman, Dana Reeve and others. Proceeds will go to the Williamstown Theater Festival in Williamstown, Mass. Joanne Woodward, a chairwoman of the event, will speak; she is also offering an evening at the ballet, accompanied by her, as one of the auction items. Drinks will be at 6, followed by dinner, the auction and the show. Tickets, $175, from (212) 228-2286.</p>
        <p>Pooling Resources</p>
        <p>MONDAY -- Help AIDS Resources Triumph is sponsoring a buffet dinner and auction from 7 to 11 at the Bulgari jewelry store on 57th Street and Fifth Avenue. The evening, which will feature a performance by cast members of ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum,''  will benefit the Community Research Initiative on AIDS and the Neuro-AIDS Research Program at Mount Sinai Medical Center. Tickets, $175, from (212) 924-3934.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of Sales and Songs</p>
        <p>TODAY -- A dinner at Laura Belle, 120 West 43d Street, will feature an auction and a cabaret show starring James Naughton, Kate Burton, Laurie Beechman, Dana Reeve and others. Proceeds will go to the Williamstown Theater Festival in Williamstown, Mass. Joanne Woodward, a chairwoman of the event, will speak; she is also offering an evening at the ballet, accompanied by her, as one of the auction items. Drinks will be at 6, followed by dinner, the auction and the show. Tickets, $175, from (212) 228-2286.</p>
        <p>Pooling Resources</p>
        <p>MONDAY -- Help AIDS Resources Triumph is sponsoring a buffet dinner and auction from 7 to 11 at the Bulgari jewelry store on 57th Street and Fifth Avenue. The evening, which will feature a performance by cast members of ''A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum,''  will benefit the Community Research Initiative on AIDS and the Neuro-AIDS Research Program at Mount Sinai Medical Center. Tickets, $175, from (212) 924-3934.</p>
        <p>For Spiritual Education</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- Ehud Barak, the leader of Israel's Labor Party, will be the keynote speaker at a black-tie dinner at the Pierre, to benefit the Jewish Theological Seminary. John S. Reed, the chairman of Citicorp, will receive the school's Louis Marshall Award. A cocktail reception at 6:30 will be followed by dinner and the award ceremony. Tickets, $1,000, from (212) 678-8924.</p>
        <p>Learn to Dance</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- The Coalition for Asian-American Children and Families, an advocacy group in New York, will hold its first ever fund-raiser, from 6 to 8:30 P.M., at Metronome, 915 Broadway (21st Street). Instructors from Dance Manhattan will give dance lessons at the party, which will also include an open bar, hors d'oeuvres and a silent auction. Music will be provided by George Gee and his Make-Believe Ballroom Orchestra. Tickets, $55, from (212) 809-4675, ext. 26, or $65 at the door.</p>
        <p>Fashions at the Toy Center</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The Partnership for the Homeless will hold its second annual fashion show and reception, in the lobby of the International Toy Center, 200 Fifth Avenue (23d Street). The event, from 6:30 to 9:30 P.M., will raise money for Peter's Place, a drop-in center in Manhattan for the frail and elderly. Tickets, $50, from (212) 627-1750.</p>
        <p>For the Families of Heroes</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- A dinner-dance at the New York Hilton will benefit the New York Police and Fire Widows' and Children's Fund. Rusty Staub, the former Mets baseball player, will present an award to James B. Lee Jr., a vice chairman of the Chase Manhattan Bank. Drinks at 6. Tickets, $500, from (718) 567-2258.</p>
        <p>Preserving Sight</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The New York Chapter of Prevent Blindness America will benefit from a reception and auction at the National Arts Club, 15 Gramercy Park South. The auction will be conducted by Benjamin Doller of Sotheby's, and will offer travel packages, jewelry, art and clothing. The evening will begin at 6 with a Champagne reception and preview of the items on sale. Tickets, $150, or $75 for admission at 6:45, from (212) 759-7812.</p>
        <p>Helping Wishes Come True</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- The Make-A-Wish Foundation will hold its seventh annual holiday auction at Christie's East, 219 East 67th Street. The event, from 6 to 10 P.M., will include an open bar and hors d'oeuvres. Tickets, $75, from (212) 605-0334.</p>
        <p>Honoring Theater Nobility</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- Edward Albee and Kitty Carlisle Hart will be honored at a black-and-white masked ball at the Neuberger Museum of Art, on the campus of the State University College at Purchase, N.Y. The black-tie evening will raise money for the museum's exhibitions and programs. A cocktail reception at 7 will be followed by dinner and dancing. Tickets, $250, from (914) 251- 6115.</p>
        <p>Impressionist Dining</p>
        <p>NEXT SUNDAY -- The Maimonides Medical Center in Brooklyn will benefit from a black-tie dinner and dance at the Brooklyn Museum of Art, 200 Eastern Parkway. Guests will be able to view ''Monet and the Mediterranean,'' an exhibition now at the museum, and there will be live musical performances. Drinks at 6. Tickets, $500, from (718) 283-7041.</p>
        <p>Arts and Business</p>
        <p>NOV. 24 -- Harry Belafonte, Al Hirschfeld and Harold McGraw 3d, the president of the McGraw-Hill Companies, will be honored at a black-tie dinner at the Plaza benefiting the programs of the Arts and Business Council. The actor James Naughton will be the master of ceremonies for the evening, and presenters of the awards will include Mario M. Cuomo, James Earl Jones, Betty Comden and Adolph Green. Cocktails at 6:30 P.M. Tickets, $500, from (212) 245-6570.</p>
        <p>Thicker Than Water</p>
        <p>NOV. 24 -- Willard Scott, the NBC television weather reporter, will be the master of ceremonies for a dinner-dance at the Waldorf-Astoria. The evening, sponsored by the New York Blood Center, will raise money for research on blood-related diseases. Drinks at 6:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 888-7003.</p>
        <p>Free Verdi</p>
        <p>DEC. 1 -- Vincent La Selva, the founder and artistic director of the New York Grand Opera Company, will be the master of ceremonies for a concert and reception in Weill Recital Hall at Carnegie Hall to raise money for the company's continuing project of staging free performances of all 28 Verdi operas. The performance, at 7:30 P.M., will feature arias and ensemble singing by members of the company. A champagne reception will follow the show. Tickets, $50 and up, from (212) 245-8837.</p>
        <p>A New Dance Season</p>
        <p>DEC. 1 -- The Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater will open its winter season at City Center, 131 West 55th Street, with a benefit performance and gala. The program will feature Mr. Ailey's ''Revelations'' and the world premiere of Donald Byrd's ''Fin de Siecle.'' The 7 P.M. show will be followed by a black-tie dinner and dance at 10, at the Sheraton New York. Tickets, $250, from (212) 957-3005, ext. 225, or $25 for the performance alone, from (212) 581-1212.</p>
        <p>Scholarships in the Arts</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- The 58th anniversary gala concert of the America-Israel Cultural Foundation, which awards more than 600 annual scholarships to young artists and musicians, will be given at Town Hall, 123 West 43d Street, at 8 P.M. The program will include former scholarship recipients, among them Denis Sedov, a bass, and Ohad Bar-David, a cellist. Marta Casals Istomin, the president of the Manhattan School of Music, and others will be honored. A reception at Laura Belle, across the street, will follow. Tickets, $100, from (212) 557-1600.</p>
        <p>Gala for Brooklyn Library, 100</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The Brooklyn Public Library, as part of its 100th-year celebration, will hold a black-tie gala in the Central Library, at Grand Army Plaza in Brooklyn. Lena Horne and Pete Hamill will be honored, with Earl Graves, the publisher, and Ric Burns, the documentary filmmaker. Harvey Fierstein will be the master of ceremonies. Dinner tickets are sold out. Dessert at 8:15, followed by the awards ceremony. Dessert tickets, $50, from (212) 921-9070.</p>
        <p>Towering Toy Soldiers</p>
        <p>FRIDAY -- The New York premiere of ''The IMAX Nutcracker,'' a 3-D version of the traditional story, is to benefit the Foundation for Treatment of Children with Aids, which gives grants to institutions for treatment improvements. The event, at the Sony IMAX Theater, Broadway and 68th Street, will begin with a reception for children at 5:30 P.M., followed by a screening at 6:30. Adults are invited to a cocktail reception at 7, followed by another screening at 9. Tickets, $100 for adults, $50 for those younger than 12, and $300 for families, at the door only. Information: (212) 734-5400.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 19, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Benefits column of Sunday Styles this week about a screening of ''The Imax Nutcracker'' at the Sony Imax Theater, to help the Foundation for Treatment of Children With AIDS, misstated the date, and the price of adult tickets at the door. The event is tomorrow, not Friday. Tickets are $125, not $100. For information: (212) 734-5400.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 23, 1997, Sunday  A report in the Benefits column last Sunday about the opening night of Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater's winter season at City Center misstated the date. It is Dec. 3, not Dec. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 19, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Benefits column of Sunday Styles this week about a screening of ''The Imax Nutcracker'' at the Sony Imax Theater, to help the Foundation for Treatment of Children With AIDS, misstated the date, and the price of adult tickets at the door. The event is tomorrow, not Friday. Tickets are $125, not $100. For information: (212) 734-5400.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: November 23, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>A report in the Benefits column last Sunday about the opening night of Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater's winter season at City Center misstated the date. It is Dec. 3, not Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
