<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flower District Considers a Repotting; Wholesale Market Feels Pressure As Neighborhood Is Transformed</title>
    <meta content="01FLOW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/01/nyregion/01FLOW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Flower Market Assn of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pristin, Terry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DB1030F932A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flower District Considers a Repotting; Wholesale Market Feels Pressure As Neighborhood Is Transformed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY PRISTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pristin, Terry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article contends that while for much of past century, wholesale flowers have been sold amid fur fabricators on Manhattan's West 20's; in recent years, many wholesalers have closed up shop and those that remain in flower market, now concentrated on two blocks of West 28th Street, say they may soon be pulling up roots; Flower Market Assn of New York, formed last year in reaction to wave of new construction, worsening traffic congestion and scarcity of parking spaces in their neighborhood, is meeting with city officials to find site where flower dealers can move en masse; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For much of the past century, wholesale flowers have been sold amid the fur fabricators of the West 20's. But in recent years, many wholesalers have closed up shop, and those that remain in the flower market, now concentrated on two blocks of 28th Street, say they may soon be pulling up roots.</p>
        <p>Reacting to a wave of new construction in their neighborhood, worsening traffic congestion and a scarcity of parking spaces, the wholesale florists banded together last year and formed the Flower Market Association of NYC. Not long ago they began meeting with city officials to try to identify a site where the dealers, who are determined to move en masse, can set up a market together.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For much of the past century, wholesale flowers have been sold amid the fur fabricators of the West 20's. But in recent years, many wholesalers have closed up shop, and those that remain in the flower market, now concentrated on two blocks of 28th Street, say they may soon be pulling up roots.</p>
        <p>Reacting to a wave of new construction in their neighborhood, worsening traffic congestion and a scarcity of parking spaces, the wholesale florists banded together last year and formed the Flower Market Association of NYC. Not long ago they began meeting with city officials to try to identify a site where the dealers, who are determined to move en masse, can set up a market together.</p>
        <p>''It's better if everyone is in one place,'' said Pete Sutton, the owner of Mutual Cut Flowers, a company that carries a broad line of what he described as ''middle of the road'' flowers. ''No one wholesaler can carry every type of flower.''</p>
        <p>Although it has never carried an official designation like the Hunts Point produce market or the Fulton Fish Market, New York's flower district once had a bigger footprint, stretching from 26th to 28th Street and running along the Avenue of the Americas.</p>
        <p>Today, many of these family-owned businesses are gone. The market has shrunk to about half its former size, now numbering 31 wholesale florists and several purveyors of pots, planters and baskets spread out along two blocks of side streets.</p>
        <p>Before 5 a.m. on a recent weekday, the sidewalks and curbs on 28th Street between Broadway and Seventh Avenue were already lined with orange dahlias and other seasonal products -- pumpkins, of course, but also branches of red-and-brown maple leaves and green gourds shaped like snakes, bottles and horns.</p>
        <p>As workers unloaded a refrigerated truck, flower buyers holding paper coffee cups and cell phones were circulating, indicating their choices with a pointed finger or a quick word. Vans were beginning to clog the narrow street.</p>
        <p>By 6 a.m., Luis Collazo, decked out in black leather, had already settled on $2,000 worth of merchandise for Lotus, his Greenwich Village flower shop. His van was filling up with varieties of flowers: the agapanthus from California, the eucharis lily, the hydrangea and the amaryllis from the Netherlands. He bought orchids that only a day or two before were growing in Thailand. The predawn visit to the flower market is a ritual for Mr. Collazo: he is there three times a week. ''You get an early start,'' he said, ''you pick up the best stuff.''</p>
        <p>No official sales figures have been compiled, but Gary W. Page, the president of the Flower Market Association, estimated that the market takes in about $100 million to $120 million a year in sales to retail florists, floral designers and buyers for restaurants, hotels, special events, parties and weddings. The market employs about 300 people, many of them immigrants from Spanish-speaking countries. (Another 300 or so people are employed by wholesalers in other boroughs, according to figures from the State Department of Labor. There are about 500 retail florists in New York City, employing about 1,800 people.)</p>
        <p>Heavy pressure on the flower market has come from rezoning on Seventh Avenue and the Avenue of the Americas over the past five years; the changes permit residential development in places that were once restricted to industrial uses. In an area that had little new construction for nearly a quarter-century, 2,100 units of housing are being added in seven buildings, ranging in size from 10 to 37 stories.</p>
        <p>Commercial rents in the area are climbing rapidly, raising fears among wholesalers like Mr. Page, the owner of G. Page, a company specializing in exotic flowers, which has only two years left on its lease.</p>
        <p>As retail florists and floral designers grow increasingly frustrated with the traffic and parking problems, the market is sure to suffer, the wholesalers predict. They worry that retail florists will be tempted to  give more of their business to the dozens of dealers who travel door to door and sell directly off their refrigerated trucks, a competing source of wholesale flowers that emerged 15 years ago. They are also concerned about the potential threat from the Internet and competition from wholesalers in the suburbs.</p>
        <p>Rob Houtenbos, the president of Dutch Flower Line, a tenant on 28th Street for 11 years, said the wholesale market has to move and modernize in order to survive. ''If we stay here,'' he said, ''we are suffocating ourselves. We need to create a market that sells flowers in a modern way.''</p>
        <p>Pronouncements like this one have been heard before. In the 1980's, the wholesalers said their market was facing extinction, and some talked about moving to College Point, Queens. A decade later, the focus shifted to the Harlem River Yards in the South Bronx. The market's largest wholesaler, Kiamos &amp; Tooker, moved to Zerega Avenue in the Bronx, but that company was the only defector from 28th Street.</p>
        <p>Jim Lebberes, the president of Kiamos &amp; Tooker, which now occupies 54,000 square feet of space and has three-quarters of an acre for parking, said that many of his Manhattan customers who used to go in person to 28th Street now buy from him by telephone or shop somewhere else. ''I would prefer for my own purposes that more come here and buy,'' Mr. Lebberes said. ''If they see the product, they would buy more.''</p>
        <p>While a few people in the industry are open to moving to another borough, most say that the high-end florists and the floral designers will not travel outside Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''I know where my customer base is,'' said Mitchell Vlachos, an owner of Harry Vlachos Inc., a company started by his father in 1930, when 70 percent of the flowers sold at the market were grown within 100 miles of the city.</p>
        <p>Michael George, a veteran floral designer, agreed that it would be a mistake for the market to move to another borough. ''I'm not schlepping to Hunts Point,'' he said. ''I'm not in the fruit business. If you're not in Manhattan, you might as well be in Hong Kong.''</p>
        <p>City Councilwoman Christine Quinn, whose district includes the flower market, said there are several sites that might be suitable, although she stressed that the discussions were only in the preliminary stages. Among the sites being mentioned are Pier 57 along the Hudson River, just south of Chelsea Piers; the wholesale meat market near Gansevoort Street; the Fulton Fish Market; La Marqueta, the marketplace in East Harlem; and the market on Essex Street on the Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>''As much as everyone would like to keep the flower market where it is,'' Ms. Quinn said, ''that isn't really viable anymore. At the end of the day, we need to find them a new space.''</p>
        <p>Ricardo Soto-Lopez, a former city planning official who recently became the director of planning and economic development for the Flower Market Association, said that the wholesale florists should be housed under one roof, with easy access to loading docks, and that they should have the capacity to pool services like maintenance, trucking, refrigeration and billing.</p>
        <p>If the wholesalers were housed in one place, said Juliette Babincak, the flower buyer for Surroundings, an Upper West Side florist, they could ban customers without proper identification, as is done at the flower market in Boston. She said this would address a common complaint among retailers: that wholesalers undercut their business by selling to the public. Wholesale prices can be one-third of retail prices or less, depending on the variety of flower.</p>
        <p>In its current location, said Lesly Zamor, the owner of Bloom, a florist in the Flatiron district, the market is too accessible to retail customers, including hotels and restaurants. ''I'd say we lose $250,000 to $400,000 a year just in restaurant business,'' Mr. Zamor said.</p>
        <p>People who shop for hotels and restaurants, however, can obtain resale licenses that entitle them to buy flowers wholesale, and most actually do function as floral designers, said Mr. Page, the association's president. Like other wholesalers, Mr. Page said he does very little retail business. But he said that if a new market is built, it should be closed to the public.</p>
        <p>''It's ridiculous to have an open market in New York,'' he said. ''People should be required to have badges to enter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Page and the other wholesalers said they hoped to get help from the city. In their view, the city needs to recognize that even though the flower market is small, it plays an important role in the city's restaurant and tourism industries. Officials at the City Economic Development Corporation did not respond to a telephone request for comment.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lebberes, the wholesale florist who moved to the Bronx, said his former neighbors on 28th Street were deluding themselves if they thought that city officials would be eager to help an industry that employs so few people.</p>
        <p>''I think the people that are left in the market have unrealistic expectations,'' he said. ''They can sit there forever waiting for the city to give them something they won't ever get.''</p>
        <p>Others in the industry are more hopeful. ''The flower market has been overlooked and taken for granted,'' said Mr. Sutton, the owner of Mutual Cut Flowers. ''This is one of those little sectors that adds so much to the city. People walk into a lobby and see the flowers -- and it never occurs to them how the flowers got there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
