<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Contracts With Noncompete Teeth</title>
    <meta content="01NOOC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/01/business/01NOOC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001104T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pratt Medical Center (Va)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mancini, Pamela (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ligos, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DE1330F932A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Contracts With Noncompete Teeth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA LIGOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ligos, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Workplace interview with Dr Pamela Mancini, Virginia pediatrician who has been forced out of practice by lawsuit over noncompete contract she had signed with previous employer, Pratt Medical Center; photo; Pratt's lawsuit has left Mancini bankrupt and seeking job out of area (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, Dr. Pamela Mancini was pulling in six figures as a pediatrician at a Fredericksburg, Va., medical center.</p>
        <p>Today, she's bankrupt, emotionally deflated and desperately searching for a job elsewhere in Virginia. ''This has been a hell of a year,'' said Dr. Mancini, who has been a pediatrician for more than 18 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, Dr. Pamela Mancini was pulling in six figures as a pediatrician at a Fredericksburg, Va., medical center.</p>
        <p>Today, she's bankrupt, emotionally deflated and desperately searching for a job elsewhere in Virginia. ''This has been a hell of a year,'' said Dr. Mancini, who has been a pediatrician for more than 18 years.</p>
        <p>The cause of Dr. Mancini's misfortune was an agreement she signed at the request of her employer, Pratt Medical Center, when it was bought by another company in 1998 -- eight years after she had begun her employment there. The new contract stipulated that she would not be able to practice pediatrics within 25 miles of the center for one year if she left Pratt.</p>
        <p>But last April, Dr. Mancini said, she had numerous conflicts with management, so she took a risk and left the company, opening her own practice in downtown Fredericksburg. In six months, working alongside her husband, David, the office's manager, she accumulated nearly 2,000 patients.</p>
        <p>But all that changed in September. After a lawsuit by Pratt, which contended she was in violation of the noncompete agreement, Dr. Mancini was ordered by a Virginia court to close her practice pending the outcome of the case. Now, she can no longer afford legal counsel. ''This whole thing has been a disaster,'' Dr. Mancini said.</p>
        <p>Officials from Pratt Medical Center are unsympathetic. ''She voluntarily signed this agreement and is therefore bound to its terms,'' said John R. Walk, Pratt's lawyer.</p>
        <p>The career limbo that Dr. Mancini finds herself in is ensnaring an increasing number of professionals these days. In the current hot economy, companies are taking a harder line against former employees who signed noncompete agreements -- and not always to prevent them from stealing their business away. In many cases, employment specialists say, they want to send a warning to their current employees that the contracts they signed have teeth.</p>
        <p>''Employees are companies' hottest commodities right now,'' said Michael B. Carlinsky, a lawyer with Orrick, Herrington &amp; Sutcliffe in Manhattan. ''More and more employers are using noncompetes, and similar tactics, to hold onto their workers.''</p>
        <p>Many noncompete agreements prohibit employees from working in a specific geographical area -- or for a specific competitor -- for a year or more after the end of their employment. Others restrict employees from taking clients with them when they resign or from revealing trade secrets.</p>
        <p>Such pacts are thriving in all industries, Mr. Carlinsky said, but particularly in high technology, where an extremely mobile work force and the high value of intellectual property have some companies drafting and trying to enforce strict noncompete clauses for employees at all levels.</p>
        <p>In certain cases, companies are suing to restrict employees from moving to competitors even when there is no noncompete agreement, citing the need to protect their trade secrets.</p>
        <p>Lucent Technologies recently filed a suit against 10 former employees in its optical manufacturing site in North Andover, Mass. The employees resigned earlier this year to join Cisco Systems, which was opening a competing optical networking plant in Salem, Mass. They ranged in experience from one of the top-tier managers at the Lucent plant to a 23-year-old employee. The suit asserts that the former employees -- none of whom signed noncompete agreements -- were making off with proprietary information and should be prevented by court order from working at Cisco.</p>
        <p>To the employees' relief, a federal district court in Massachusetts recently issued an order allowing them to continue working at Cisco pending the outcome of the suit. ''This case has put a lot of stress on my family,'' said Daniel Tymann, a former manufacturing director at Lucent who is named in the suit. Before the August court ruling, Mr. Tymann said, he had to sit down with his wife and 14-year-old daughter ''and discuss the possibility of us relocating; that was extremely upsetting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tymann said when he left Lucent, his superiors never said they might sue him. ''I was certainly aware of my obligations to keep any proprietary information of Lucent's proprietary,'' he said. ''I'm disappointed that they questioned my integrity.''</p>
        <p>The lawyer for the former Lucent employees, Gregory L. Lippetz, contends that Lucent filed the suit to send a message to other employees who might be thinking about jumping ship. ''There are some companies who use noncompetes as a retention tool to hang over employees' heads,'' Mr. Lippetz said.</p>
        <p>A Lucent spokeswoman, Mary Lou Ambrus, maintains that the 10 employees agreed to a noncompete clause that was included in a stock option grant. ''We feel the company has a right and an obligation to protect confidential information,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Although more companies are trying to enforce noncompete agreements, not all are victorious. In a recent lawsuit, Heartland Securities filed a claim against several employees for violating noncompete agreements. In one situation, an employee, Jared Gerstenblatt, signed an employment contract with Datek Online Brokerage Services (now owned by Heartland), promising to pay back up to $200,000 in ''training costs'' if he left the company before completing four years of employment. He left shortly before his four-year anniversary to become a day trader. A federal district court in New York ruled in March that the contract was overly restrictive. ''It was a clever attempt to create a disincentive for people to leave,'' Mr. Carlinsky said.</p>
        <p>Heartland's lawyer declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Experts say that unpopular as noncompete contracts are with workers, when used properly, they are a legitimate way for employers to protect their interests.</p>
        <p>''I encourage all my clients to have employees sign noncompetes, especially those who work in the tech arena,'' said Michael D. Golden, a partner at the Atlanta law firm, Arnall Goden &amp; Gregory. ''Why should you let somebody run off with your clients or your intellectual capital?''</p>
        <p>Kathleen Gadd, one of Mr. Golden's clients, and senior managing director of Office Innovation, an office products company based in Lawrenceville, Ga., agrees. Her company makes sales representatives agree in writing not to take accounts with them when they leave. In addition, senior executives are asked to sign a pact promising not to reveal portions of the company's business plan. ''I've spent the last four years building this business from scratch,'' Ms. Gadd said. ''I have a right and a responsibility to protect it.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 4, 2000, Saturday  An article on the Workplace page on Wednesday about ''noncompete'' agreements, in which workers accept restrictions on future employment after leaving a company, misspelled the name of a law firm in Atlanta at which one partner, Michael D. Golden, encourages employers to use the device. It is Arnall Golden &amp; Gregory, not Goden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 4, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on the Workplace page on Wednesday about ''noncompete'' agreements, in which workers accept restrictions on future employment after leaving a company, misspelled the name of a law firm in Atlanta at which one partner, Michael D. Golden, encourages employers to use the device. It is Arnall Golden &amp; Gregory, not Goden.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
