<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Race Is Neck and Neck at Finish</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920418T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED6143DF93AA35757C0A964958260" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Race Is Neck and Neck at Finish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain's hard-fought general election campaign ended today in a cliffhanger, with prospects uncertain that Prime Minister John Major's Conservative Government would be able to retain its majority in the 651-member Parliament that is to be elected on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The opposition Labor Party's leader, Neil Kinnock, tired and hoarse after 8,000 miles of crisscrossing the country, sounded and acted confident that he would displace Mr. Major from 10 Downing Street on Friday after the votes were counted. But the Prime Minister, campaigning in south London, said he was "stone cold certain" that he would win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Britain's hard-fought general election campaign ended today in a cliffhanger, with prospects uncertain that Prime Minister John Major's Conservative Government would be able to retain its majority in the 651-member Parliament that is to be elected on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The opposition Labor Party's leader, Neil Kinnock, tired and hoarse after 8,000 miles of crisscrossing the country, sounded and acted confident that he would displace Mr. Major from 10 Downing Street on Friday after the votes were counted. But the Prime Minister, campaigning in south London, said he was "stone cold certain" that he would win.</p>
        <p>The final public opinion polls today showed the two parties running so close that neither might emerge with a clear majority of 326 or more seats.</p>
        <p>This election, like other recent ones in France, Germany and Italy, seems likely to produce a strong but fragmented expression of discontent with the status quo, which has lasted nearly 13 years. Courting Liberal Democrats</p>
        <p>Even if the Conservatives somehow manage to hold onto a slim majority, the era that was marked by the personality and free-enterprise philosophy of Mr. Major's Conservative predecessor, Margaret Thatcher, seems over. He replaced her in November 1990, after a parliamentary revolt against her leadership, and she is not running in this election.</p>
        <p>Another likely consequence is a re-examination of central Government control from London over Scotland, Wales and even Northern Ireland. The Scottish National Party, a separatist group that seeks independence for Scotland within the European Community, is vying with Labor for the majority of Scotland's 72 seats in the House of Commons. The Conservatives do not expect to beat Labor overall north of the border.</p>
        <p>If the result is close, Mr. Major and Mr. Kinnock might have to spend days negotiating with the Liberal Democrats and other smaller parties to try to assemble a majority and form a government, or try to struggle along without one for awhile.</p>
        <p>The Liberal Democrats have insisted up to now on a change in the British electoral system, to give them a chance of winning the same proportion of seats in Parliament as the 20 percent of the vote they are likely to get on Thursday, as a precondition of any deal for a coalition. Major's Strategy Assailed</p>
        <p>The Mori polling organization, which has come within one percentage point of the actual results in pre-election polls in all three of the last general elections, surveyed 1,731 voters in 164 constituencies Tuesday and today and found 38 percent saying they would vote Conservative, 39 percent Labor, 20 percent Liberal Democrat and 3 percent for others.</p>
        <p>Such a result, said Robert M. Worcester, Mori's chairman, would give the Conservatives 296 seats, Labor 300, the Liberal Democrats 27 and others 28. But, he said, "It's too close to call," since the poll's margin of possible error was plus or minus 2 percent.  "We've never had such a close election," he said.</p>
        <p>In the last vote, in 1987, the Conservatives won 42.3 percent of the vote, and a 101-seat majority.</p>
        <p>Some Conservatives blame Mr. Major's bland personality and the defensive campaign that he and his team waged for their reduced prospects this time. The Prime Minister called the election in the middle of the longest recession since the 1930's, and waged his campaign battle against Mr. Kinnock's plans for higher taxes and higher Government spending on things like education and the National Health Service, rather than on their past performance, or their plans for the future.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinnock, 50 years old, a career politician who has transformed the Labor Party from the left-wing fringe to which Mrs. Thatcher had relegated it in the 1980's, made the most of the advantage handed to him by the economy.</p>
        <p>"Two recessions, millions unemployed, thousands of bankruptcies, thousands of repossessions, the oil wealth dissipated, the country divided and now seriously in debt," he said, his Welsh lilt by now hoarse from a month of campaigning, at a rally of thousands of cheering supporters in the constituency of Blackburn in northwest England on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate is now 9.4 percent and rising, as it has been since 1989, when Mrs. Thatcher's Government raised interest rates to double-digit levels to get soaring inflation under control. But at the last election, in June 1987, unemployment was even higher, though it was falling.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinnock's party frightened many voters away then by proposing to give up Britain's nuclear deterrent.  Now that the cold war is over and the Soviet Union is gone, Labor reassures voters since 1989 about its commitment to a British nuclear defense.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Mr. Kinnock finished his campaign in his South Wales constituency of Islywn, as Mr. Major, 49, prepared to go to his own district of Huntingdon, 60 miles north of London, to vote.</p>
        <p>Many politicians and poll takers predict a second election this year, perhaps in October, if Thursday's result is close.</p>
        <p>That would mirror the situation in 1974, when Labor narrowly edged ahead of the Conservatives in the vote in February, but did not win a majority until October.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinnock staked his campaign this year on a gamble: that people were willing to pay higher taxes -- or at least let the rich pay them -- in return for more spending on public services, particularly the National Health Service, which does not bill patients for most treatment but is financed from general tax revenues. The Conservatives are spending $:36 billion ($62.6 billion) on it this year, but have introduced a variety of small charges and market-oriented management methods that Labor denounced as "creeping privatization." Labor's Tax Plan</p>
        <p>"The National Health Service is now in mortal danger," Mr. Kinnock said the other night. "Its whole future rests upon the decision we take as a nation when we vote."</p>
        <p>Labor has promised to undo all the management changes the Government has introduced into the Health Service and to put an additional $1.74 billion, or $:1 billion, into it over the next two years if it wins.</p>
        <p>Mr. Major, given to wooden recitation of statistics rather than inspiring visions of broad philosophy, resorted to a wooden soapbox to liven up his campaign in the last week or so, but seemed to remain very much the polite, courteous bank clerk he had once been on the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>But today, commenting on Labor's plans to raise taxes to a maximum rate of 59 percent, including social security, on incomes of $:40,000 ($68,000) and above, from 40 percent now, Mr. Major said it would be "stark staring bonkers to increase tax on an economy coming out of recession."</p>
        <p>Seemingly driven almost bonkers by the prospect of a Labor victory, The Sun, the enthusiastically Conservative tabloid published by Rupert Murdoch, ran 10 pages of "Nightmare on Kinnock Street" gloom and doom coverage today.</p>
        <p>It included a report from a psychic that Mao Zedong, the deceased Chinese leader, and Stalin were backing Labor from the grave. Elvis Presley was reportedly for Mr. Major's party and Ghengis Khan believed that only Mrs. Thatcher had the stomach for a fight, and did not deign to choose from among the others.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 18, 1992, Saturday</p>
        <p>Charts on April 9 and 11 about the British Parliament misstated the number of seats in the old House of Commons. It was 650; it is now 651.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 18, 1992, Saturday</p>
        <p>Charts on April 9 and 11 about the British Parliament misstated the number of seats in the old House of Commons. It was 650; it is now 651.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
