<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2.5 Cheers for George Bush</title>
    <meta content="13FRUML" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Washington; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/13/books/review/13FRUML.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frum, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mead, Walter Russell</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Power, Terror, Peace, and War (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Council on Foreign Relations</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Mead, Walter Russell</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Power, Terror, Peace, and War: America's Grand Strategy in a World at Risk (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DE1331F930A25755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2.5 Cheers for George Bush</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Power, Terror, Peace, and War': 2.5 Cheers for George Bush</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Frum</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frum, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Frum reviews book Power, Terror, Peace, and War: America's Grand Strategy in a World at Risk by Walter Russell Mead (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POWER, TERROR,</p>
        <p>PEACE, AND WAR</p>
        <p>America's Grand Strategy in a World at Risk.</p>
        <p>By Walter Russell Mead.</p>
        <p>226 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walter Russell Mead, a senior foreign policy analyst, endorses many of the president's acts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POWER, TERROR,</p>
        <p>PEACE, AND WAR</p>
        <p>America's Grand Strategy in a World at Risk.</p>
        <p>By Walter Russell Mead.</p>
        <p>226 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $19.95.</p>
        <p>WALTER RUSSELL MEAD is the Henry A. Kissinger senior fellow in United States foreign policy at the Council on Foreign Relations. Despite the crushing respectability of that title, Mead has earned a deserved reputation as one of the country's liveliest thinkers about America's role in the world. And in ''Power, Terror, Peace, and War,'' his originality has led him dangerously -- but gratifyingly -- away from respectability.</p>
        <p>Mead says, ''A mix of incredulity, outrage, shock, anger and despair is running through the foreign policy establishment as many of its most cherished ideas and institutions are impatiently brushed aside.'' As one of the leading lights of that same establishment, Mead might have been expected to join in the keening and wailing. Instead, he has concluded that President Bush has been right on just about everything important in the war on terror.</p>
        <p>For those who support the president and his policies, ''Power, Terror, Peace, and War'' is interesting not only in itself but also as evidence of how dramatically Bush has transformed the American foreign policy debate. For those who do not support the president, this book is a sharp reminder that, in Mead's words, opponents have ''not yet managed to present a cogent and convincing alternative strategy.''</p>
        <p>In tandem with the eminent historian John Lewis Gaddis, the author of the equally arresting new book ''Surprise, Security, and the American Experience,'' Mead has done something that academic experts rarely do: defy their professional consensus and open their minds to new ideas. Yes, Mead can be critical of the White House. He writes, ''The Bush administration's conduct of affairs has been too choppy and uncertain, its ability to formulate and express its strategic direction too crude and unconvincing.'' But on the specifics, he is almost entirely approving.</p>
        <p>Employing overwhelming force against terrorist enemies? Check: ''Those who cannot stand us must learn at least to fear us.''</p>
        <p>Invading Iraq to rebuild the Middle East? Check: ''Taking Iraq's political weight out of the radical Sunni Arab camp would make a permanent and probably beneficial change in the political geometry of the Middle East.''</p>
        <p>Threatening pre-emption as a tool against nuclear proliferation? Check: ''The European nations . . . who engaged Iran in the process that led to the Iranian agreement to accept weapons inspectors would never have taken this issue so seriously if they had not feared that the alternative to European demands was an American invasion.''</p>
        <p>Grounding decisions in national values? Check: ''Foreign policy can't be conducted over the heads or against the basic instincts of the American people.''</p>
        <p>De-emphasizing the Israeli-Palestinian dispute? Check: ''The Palestinian peace party cannot reliably deliver Palestinian society unless peace offers concrete benefits for the overwhelming majority of displaced Palestinians, and since there is no peace party in Israel if the return of millions of Palestinians is the price of a deal, peace remains tantalizingly out of reach. In a situation where neither of the parties is willing to accept any of the feasible solutions, there is very little that an outside power can do to force an agreement.''</p>
        <p>Understanding the conflict with militant Islam as an ideological struggle? Check: '' 'Arabian Fascism' is a totalitarian ideology inspired by a mythologized vision of the past. . . . And it aims by force to restore this past not only in the world of Islam, but ultimately throughout the world.''</p>
        <p>If anything, Mead's basic views are even starker than those of the Bush administration. Europe is fading -- militarily, economically, demographically. America is rising. The Europeans sense that their positions will count for less and less in the world of the future, and so, while they still can, they seek to lock the United States into arrangements and institutions that will grant them an effective veto over American decision making.</p>
        <p>Mead is not quite ready to hammer a Bush/ Cheney sign into his front lawn. Despite his admiration for most of the administration's actions, he finds its personality and style ultimately off-putting and alien.</p>
        <p>Yet if Bush presents his ideas too bluntly for Mead's taste, some will find Mead's own presentation too circumlocutory. Short as this book is, it could have been shorter still, especially in its opening chapters -- as if Mead were cushioning his expected reader against the audacious thoughts contained in the second half.</p>
        <p>Thus he lingers over a lengthy discussion of the changes in the world economy since 1970, retelling the familiar story of how the shift from a mass-production economy has lifted America's position relative to that of Europe, Japan and Russia. However, Mead does not have a good deal to add about the question that obviously follows: why did America do so much better than the other industrial countries? The answer to that question is crucial to the next -- and even more important -- question: how long can the American advantage be expected to continue?</p>
        <p>But if Mead's opening drags, his ending dazzles. He closes with a fascinating prediction about how the war on terror will change the country. Just as the struggle against the Soviet Union prodded Americans to prove that capitalism ''could do better than Communism at improving the lives of working people and enhancing the lives of the poor,'' so, Mead suggests, the struggle against Islamic extremism will intensify the trend toward greater piety in American public life.</p>
        <p>The Islamic extremists, Mead says, have falsely accused the United States of having lost touch with its spiritual roots. ''As part of our grand strategy . . . we shall have to take steps to make these charges less plausible in the future. Inescapably, this will lead many Americans to renew their personal faith commitments and make the moral and social ideals of their religious roots more relevant in their daily conduct and in their assessments of politicians and of political ideas.''</p>
        <p>If Mead is right, then it is not only President Bush's foreign policies that begin to look visionary, even inescapable. So too does his religious style. It could be the future. Get ready.</p>
        <p>David Frum, who served as a speechwriter to President Bush, is the author, with Richard Perle, of ''An End to Evil: How to Win the War on Terror.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Frum, who served as a speechwriter to President Bush, is the author, with Richard Perle, of ''An End to Evil: How to Win the War on Terror.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
