<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Politics Of the Mideast Is Local</title>
    <meta content="03nyc" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/03/nyregion/03nyc.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1743869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Javits, Jacob K, Convention Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Silvercup Studios</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Architects and Planners for Justice in Palestine (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rogers, Richard (Lord Rogers)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Javits, Jacob K, Convention Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EEDF1431F930A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Politics Of the Mideast Is Local</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">All Politics of the Mideast Is Local</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman NYC column examines controversy surrounding architect Richard Rogers, lead architect on Jacob K Javits Convention Center and Silvercup Studios in New York; says Lord Rogers has been forced to distance himself from pro-Palestinian organization Architects and Planners for Justice in Palestine, which called for economic boycott of Israel's construction industry, if he is to do business in New York (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to politics, New York is a six-borough city. Borough No. 6 is what the rest of the world calls the Middle East, specifically Israel and the Palestinian territories. What happens there has a remarkable way of reverberating here.</p>
        <p>Just ask Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton. Her 2000 election campaign nearly ran off the rails when she gave Yasir Arafat's wife, Suha, a peck on the cheek after Mrs. Arafat made a virulent attack on Israel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to politics, New York is a six-borough city. Borough No. 6 is what the rest of the world calls the Middle East, specifically Israel and the Palestinian territories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to politics, New York is a six-borough city. Borough No. 6 is what the rest of the world calls the Middle East, specifically Israel and the Palestinian territories. What happens there has a remarkable way of reverberating here.</p>
        <p>Just ask Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton. Her 2000 election campaign nearly ran off the rails when she gave Yasir Arafat's wife, Suha, a peck on the cheek after Mrs. Arafat made a virulent attack on Israel.</p>
        <p>When Edward I. Koch was mayor, he had his own foreign policy for the Middle East; now and then, it came close to resembling United States government positions. Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani went so far as to make himself the city's Bouncer-in-Chief, tossing Mr. Arafat out of a city-sponsored concert for dignitaries gathered to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Over the years, little has changed. The sixth borough continues to roil New York politics.</p>
        <p>Middle Eastern shadows have fallen across two huge expansion projects: at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center in Manhattan and at the Silvercup Studios in Long Island City, Queens. In both cases, the lead architect is Richard Rogers, of Britain, formally known as Baron Rogers of Riverside (a fitting title, some might say, for a man hoping to work along the Hudson and East Rivers).</p>
        <p>Without a doubt, Lord Rogers is eminent in his field. But he is also not without controversy.</p>
        <p>Early last month, he was host in London to 60 members of Architects and Planners for Justice in Palestine, a group that, as its name suggests, does not take kindly to Israel. Indeed, it vehemently denounced the concrete barrier that the Israelis have built through the West Bank and along its periphery -- a barrier that Israel describes as essential to fight terrorism but that critics view as keeping some Palestinian towns in a virtual lockdown.</p>
        <p>To the architects in London, it is ''an apartheid system of control.'' Some said they were considering an economic boycott of Israel's construction industry and a possible call to expel Israeli architects from the International Union of Architects. The group met at Lord Rogers's London office not once but three times, The Independent of London has reported. As word of those meetings emerged this week, some New York officials reacted. The state comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi, was poised, a spokesman said, to send a letter to the governor and his lieutenants reminding them that taking part in an anti-Israel boycott is illegal under New York law.</p>
        <p>In short order, Lord Rogers backpedaled faster than a circus performer. ''My convictions on peace and justice have always been clear,'' he said in a statement on Wednesday. But given the boycott suggestions, he said, ''I am dissociating myself from this organization.''</p>
        <p>That he was worried became more obvious yesterday. He hired Howard J. Rubenstein, New York's preferred public-relations executive for those in hot water. Through Mr. Rubenstein, the baron issued a second statement. ''I abhor boycotts of any kind -- Israel or any other place,'' he said. ''It's not the way to achieve peace.''</p>
        <p>END of story?</p>
        <p>It would seem so, said the Empire State Development Corporation, the state agency that gave Lord Rogers the Javits contract. Indeed, said the baron's New York partner company, FXFowle. But perhaps the final chapter has not been written.</p>
        <p>Silvercup Studios issued its own statement yesterday, calling on Lord Rogers to go beyond what he has said thus far and to ''unequivocally renounce the group and its mission.'' Helen M. Marshall, the Queens borough president, agreed that the baron had to ''go further and disavow himself from that group.'' City Councilman David I. Weprin of Queens, said he, too, wanted to hear more.</p>
        <p>No one spoke more forcefully than Sheldon Silver, the Assembly speaker, who invoked the memory of the late Senator Javits, a firm supporter of Israel. Lord Rogers's involvement in the boycott discussions was hardly peripheral, Mr. Silver said. As for state officials, their ''lack of accountability for what his actions have already suggested is nothing short of shameful.''</p>
        <p>So who knows? If this dispute gets really hot, maybe the five boroughs will not become this Mr. Rogers's neighborhood. At issue, after all, is the sixth borough -- where anything can happen, and often does.</p>
        <p>NYC E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: haberman@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
