<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Wrangling, House Supports Extending Extra Jobless Benefits</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="641973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH-SPEAKING GROUPS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF1031F935A25753C1A965958260" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Wrangling, House Supports Extending Extra Jobless Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than two weeks of wrangling, the House voted today to extend the program of emergency unemployment benefits for workers who have been jobless for more than six months and have exhausted their state assistance.</p>
        <p>It is the fifth extension of emergency Federal unemployment benefits since November 1991 and is intended to continue helping the 60,000 unemployed workers who become eligible for such assistance every week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than two weeks of wrangling, the House voted today to extend the program of emergency unemployment benefits for workers who have been jobless for more than six months and have exhausted their state assistance.</p>
        <p>It is the fifth extension of emergency Federal unemployment benefits since November 1991 and is intended to continue helping the 60,000 unemployed workers who become eligible for such assistance every week.</p>
        <p>The one-sided 302-to-95 vote was deceptive. Less than 24 hours before, a coalition of Democrats and Republicans embarrassed the House Democratic leadership by rejecting a similar plan on a procedural vote of 274 to 149. An extension has been expected to receive full Congressional approval eventually, but the wrangling could have delayed the resumption of the benefits. The last extension expired on Oct. 2.</p>
        <p>The problem arose before the first vote on Thursday. At issue was a provision that would prevent immigrants who have been in this country less than five years from obtaining Supplemental Security Income, the welfare program for the blind, elderly and disabled. These benefits are now available to immigrants after three years.  Money-Saving Move</p>
        <p>Representative Dan Rostenkowski of Illinois, the Democratic chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, had proposed the change as a way of saving $331 million to pay for the extension in unemployment benefits. A Congressional budget rule requires that the cost of extending the unemployment assistance be offset by either tax increases or spending cuts.</p>
        <p>But the Democratic leadership dropped the Rostenkowski plan in the face of impassioned opposition by Hispanic members. The leaders instead proposed to save the same amount of money by extending the program for three months instead of four. But the concession to Hispanic members caused support among Democratic members to erode and led to the rejection on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The bill passed today after the Hispanic members accepted defeat and dropped their insistence on retaining the current welfare policy for immigrants.</p>
        <p>The legislation that passed today would extend the unemployment program for four months and includes the change in the the welfare program.  Having the Administration's strong support, it is expected to pass the Senate.</p>
        <p>"The caucus fought hard on this bill and will continue to battle against those who would make impoverished legal immigrants scapegoats for our problems," said Representative Jose E. Serrano, Democrat of the Bronx and chairman of the Hispanic caucus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rostenkowski praised the bill during the House debate. "The assistance we provide" for the unemployed, he said, "will in many cases mean the difference between scraping by or plunging into poverty."</p>
        <p>Currently, 2.5 million people are receiving state jobless assistance. Another 1.4 million were receiving the Federal emergency benefits before that program expired on Oct. 2. The emergency benefits program would provide extra jobless benefits for seven weeks, except for those in Alaska, California, Rhode Island, West Virginia and Puerto Rico. In those states, where the unemployment rate is above 9 percent, the extension would be 13 weeks.</p>
        <p>The average benefit is $179 a week.</p>
        <p>Of the 95 lawmakers who voted against the extension today, 80 were Republicans and 15 were Democrats. Conservative Republicans led the opposition to the measure, saying the Government could not afford it.</p>
        <p>"Unemployment is going down," said Representative David Dreier, Republican of California. "Nationwide, things are going better. Maybe it's time to consider these extended benefits may be contributing to the problem."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
