<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="19VIDB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DA113FF93AA25751C1A961958260" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sampling of some new video releases, including several foreign films; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pixote</p>
        <p>With his scruffy street comrades, the title character (roughly translated as Peewee and portrayed memorably by Fernando Ramos Da Silva, left) roves the slums of Sao Paulo, snatching purses, rolling drunks, dealing dope and otherwise working the back streets, whorehouses and gambling dens for all they can scrounge. Hector Babenco's film jumps right in among its vagrants, at once expressing outrage at the conditions and admiring the humanity and resilience of those who carry on without hope of relief or escape.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Babenco shows us rock-bottom,'' Vincent Canby wrote in The New York Times, ''and because he is an artist, he makes us believe it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pixote</p>
        <p>With his scruffy street comrades, the title character (roughly translated as Peewee and portrayed memorably by Fernando Ramos Da Silva, left) roves the slums of Sao Paulo, snatching purses, rolling drunks, dealing dope and otherwise working the back streets, whorehouses and gambling dens for all they can scrounge. Hector Babenco's film jumps right in among its vagrants, at once expressing outrage at the conditions and admiring the humanity and resilience of those who carry on without hope of relief or escape.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Babenco shows us rock-bottom,'' Vincent Canby wrote in The New York Times, ''and because he is an artist, he makes us believe it.''</p>
        <p>1981. New Yorker. $89.95. 127 minutes. Portuguese with English subtitles. No rating. Release date: Dec. 30.</p>
        <p>My Saison Preferee (''My Favorite Season'')</p>
        <p>A middle-aged sister and brother, Emilie (Catherine Deneuve) and Antoine (Daniel Auteuil), face family strains when their demanding 76-year-old mother (Marthe Villalonga) comes to live with Emilie, her husband (Jean-Pierre Bouvier) and their two grown children. A neurologist, Antoine reacts more with his brain than his heart, which, along with the mother's caustic manner, plays havoc with Emilie's marriage and household. With Ms. Denueuve, who is filmed in an unkind natural light, giving a performance of complexity and candor, Andre Techine's film plays the situation naturally, ''probing believable troubles with honesty, intelligence and tact'' (Janet Maslin).</p>
        <p>1996. Fox Lorber. $89.98. 122 minutes. French with English subtitles. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>187</p>
        <p>In the California state penal code, the numbers in the title stand for murder, an unsettling prospect for Trevor Garfield (Samuel L. Jackson), who has moved west in search of a more peaceful academic setting after being stabbed by a student back in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>But in Southern California the students are anarchic and the authorities are more concerned with lawsuits than teachers' safety. Though Kevin Reynolds's film can get a little carried away with its own earnestness, it is ''genuinely disturbing in its vision of fearless students and powerless teachers locked in struggle'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1997. Warner. $103.92. Laser disk, $34.98. 119 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Air Bud</p>
        <p>Left doleful by his father's death, 12-year-old Josh (Kevin Zegers) gets a lift when he seemingly inherits a stray golden retriever that plays basketball.</p>
        <p>But when the hound starts hitting three-pointers and attracting media attention, its abusive former owner (Michael Jeter) wants it back. Woof. It's just hard to generate much interest in an exercise that is so ''wan and by-the-numbers'' (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>1997. Disney. $19.99. Laser disk $39.99. 97 minutes. Closed captioned. PG. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
