<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="04LIGUID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1486258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5D6123CF937A35756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>With 17 performers from Long Island competing for scholarships, McDonald's Gospelfest 2003 pulls into the Westbury Music Fair on Saturday for two days. Local talent like Michael Davis of Central Islip; the Joshua Generation Choir of Bellport; Thedia Darnel, a poet from Roosevelt; Kim Castro of East Patchogue; and Jazmin McDaniel of Hempstead, will be joining the headliners Hezekiah Walker and the Love Fellowship Choir, Vickie Winana, Cissy Houston and the Rev. Timothy Wright at 7:30 p.m. on Saturday and 4:30 p.m. on Sunday. Information: (516)334-0800.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>With 17 performers from Long Island competing for scholarships, McDonald's Gospelfest 2003 pulls into the Westbury Music Fair on Saturday for two days. Local talent like Michael Davis of Central Islip; the Joshua Generation Choir of Bellport; Thedia Darnel, a poet from Roosevelt; Kim Castro of East Patchogue; and Jazmin McDaniel of Hempstead, will be joining the headliners Hezekiah Walker and the Love Fellowship Choir, Vickie Winana, Cissy Houston and the Rev. Timothy Wright at 7:30 p.m. on Saturday and 4:30 p.m. on Sunday. Information: (516)334-0800.</p>
        <p>Musical Memories</p>
        <p>During his long career, Salvatore Guaragna, better known as Harry Warren, has written more than 700 songs -- from ''Chattanooga Choo-Choo'' to ''Lullaby of Broadway.'' On Thursday at 8 p.m., in an original revue, ''That's Amore! A Musical Salute to Harry Warren,'' the composer's work will be performed at the Monroe Lecture Center Theater on Hofstra University's Hempstead campus. Information: (516)463-6644.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Midge Woolsey of Channel 13 and WQXR Radio will be host of an edition of the 92nd Street Y series, ''Lyrics &amp; Lyricists,'' directed by Barry Levitt, at the Landmark on Main Street in Port Washington. The program is ''Always: A Tribute to Irving Berlin,'' and begins at 8 p.m. Information: (516)767-6444.</p>
        <p>Moore Memories</p>
        <p>Mary Tyler Moore, a board member of the North Shore Child and Family Guidance Center, puts her performing talent where her philanthropic heart is on Saturday when she offers her one-woman show, ''Some Recollections With Mary Tyler Moore.'' Complete with reception before and dinner after, the benefit is at 6:30 p.m. at Adelphi University's University Center in Garden City. Information: (516)626-1971.</p>
        <p>Blue Tunes</p>
        <p>Last February, the Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center on Main Street held its first blues concert. It has booked more blues for Saturday: ''The Mother Lovin' Blues Show.'' Featuring the Kerry Kearney Band, Frank Latorre and the King Bees, Lucy Bonilla., Richie Cannata and Paul Kayen, the concert is at 7:30 p.m. Information: (631)288-15000.</p>
        <p>Theater on Film</p>
        <p>The American Film Theater series is back, 28 years after its run in movie houses. Featuring performances by Katherine Hepburn, Paul Scofield, Lee Marvin and Glenda Jackson in plays by major 20th-century playwrights, the series begins a monthly run at the Cinema Arts Center in Huntington today at 11 a.m.</p>
        <p>The first film is Harold Pinter's ''Homecoming'' starring Ian Holm, Vivien Merchant and Cyril Cusack. It will be shown again at 7 and 9:15 p.m. tomorrow. Future installments include Edward Albee's ''Delicate Balance'' in June, and Eugene O'Neill's ''Iceman Cometh'' in September. Information: (516)423-7611.</p>
        <p>Some Friends</p>
        <p>''Music at Hillwood,'' Tilles Center's series of music, poetry and commentary of the Romantic era, ends its season today with ''Musical Friendships.'' With Kate Burton narrating and Caroline Stoessinger, a pianist and the series' founder and host, heading the musical component, the concert in Brookville is at 3 p.m. and features music by Brahms, Dvorak and Mahler. Information: (516)299-3100.</p>
        <p>Tulips Blooming</p>
        <p>Hofstra's Dutch Festival is today, from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. The event showcases more than 100,000 tulips brightening the campus, and includes Dutch foods, crafts and entertainment. Information: (516)463-6582.</p>
        <p>There will be more tulips today, at the Tulip Festival in Heckscher Park from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. Information: (631)351-3014. Free buses will shuttle visitors to the ''Sheep to Shawl Festival'' from noon to 4 p.m. at Dr. Daniel W. Kissam House at 434 Park Avenue. Sponsored by the Huntington Historical Society, the event features demonstrations of sheep shearing and spinning. Information: (631)427-7045.</p>
        <p>Free Choice</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- The Massapequa Philharmonic Orchestra plays its last concert, all-Sibelius, at 8:30 p.m. at the Berner Middle School on Carmans Mill Road. Information: (516)795-4071.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
