<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making an Airport Just Calverton's Size</title>
    <meta content="04LICALV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1486248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Calverton (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grumman Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ain, Stewart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D6123CF937A35756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making an Airport Just Calverton's Size</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART AIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ain, Stewart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on concerns raised by some residents over proposed town rules and regulations that they fear could turn runways at former Grumman plant in Calverton into public rather than private airport; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEARLY two years ago, Riverhead Town voters rejected a proposal that would have permitted the use of town money to open both runways at the former Grumman plant in Calverton and turn the site into a public rather than a private airport. Now, some residents fear that is about to happen anyway.</p>
        <p>''We don't want an Islip or a Westhampton Airport here,'' said Rex Farr, president of the Greater Calverton Civic Association, representing about 500 families. ''We believe it would severely damage our quality of life.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEARLY two years ago, Riverhead Town voters rejected a proposal that would have permitted the use of town money to open both runways at the former Grumman plant in Calverton and turn the site into a public rather than a private airport. Now, some residents fear that is about to happen anyway.</p>
        <p>''We don't want an Islip or a Westhampton Airport here,'' said Rex Farr, president of the Greater Calverton Civic Association, representing about 500 families. ''We believe it would severely damage our quality of life.''</p>
        <p>He said recently proposed town rules and regulations for use of the 10,000-foot runway at the site have so many loopholes that in five years Delta Airlines could be operating regularly scheduled passenger service from there.</p>
        <p>A public hearing last month to discuss the proposed rules and regulations -- which do not call for use of the second, 7,000-foot runway -- attracted more than 100 residents, many of whom expressed similar concerns.</p>
        <p>Robert Kozakiewicz, the town supervisor, said that because so many people raised objections, the rules and regulations would be ''fine tuned and made more concise and clearer.'' Another public hearing would then be scheduled, he said.</p>
        <p>''The frenzy and the hype that got stirred up because of the rules are unfortunate because that is not where we are at,'' Mr. Kozakiewicz insisted. ''Nobody is looking to establish a public use airport or to use taxpayer money to improve or maintain the 10,000-foot runway.''</p>
        <p>''My vision,'' Mr. Kozakiewicz added, ''is to find a way to keep this asset viable without spending taxpayer money. It's like the need to keep your house in shape. If we let this runway go to waste and not have paint put on it, we will have dropped the ball.</p>
        <p>''Nobody has ever talked about having another Islip Airport or commercial airline passenger service. What has happened is that individuals who raise money by lobbying to get people worried and agitated are saying that this is an attempt to shove another Islip down our throats -- and we are not looking to do that.''</p>
        <p>But Sidney Bail, president of the Wading River Civic Association, which also has about 500 members, said he believes those rules and regulations open the airport ''to a whole field of general aviation activities.''</p>
        <p>This would be contrary to a reuse plan adopted by the town for the airport, he said, because it calls for the airport to be used only ''as an accessory to manufacturing activities'' by companies at the industrial park. The park is located in another part of the 2,900-acre former Grumman site.</p>
        <p>''It is clear that aviation is to be an accessory use, not a stand-alone activity,'' Mr. Bail said.</p>
        <p>He added that he was also concerned about a proposal to expand the industrial park from its current 700 acres to 1,600 acres, leaving the rest for recreational purposes.</p>
        <p>''Increasing the industrially zoned land could open the site to more extensive aviation,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Barbara A. Blass, a member of the town board, said she too is concerned about the future of the airport, especially because the proposed rules and regulations were drawn up based upon a design for a general aviation airport.</p>
        <p>''The community never embraced that and neither did the reuse plan, so these rules, if adopted, would go beyond the aviation envisioned and are inconsistent with our zoning,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Blass said that because the proposed expansion of the industrial park requires an environmental study, she has proposed rewriting the zoning for the area, which was adopted in the late 1990's after the site was handed over to the Town of Riverhead by its former owner, the United States Navy.</p>
        <p>''When the zoning was written, it was written somewhat vaguely and it says that general aviation use is a permitted use,'' she said. ''But the term 'aviation use' was never defined. Every board member now or in prior years said they are not sure what the zoning means. So while we are considering expanding the industrial district, let's clarify the level of aviation that was anticipated to make sure it is clear and unambiguous. And the terminology has always been that it is an accessory to the industrial core.''</p>
        <p>''When the supervisor questioned where I would had gotten that notion,'' Ms. Bass added, ''I reminded him that it is throughout the reuse plan and that I am trying to mirror what it said by cleaning up the zoning code. We would be irresponsible to consider expanding the industrial zone at Calverton without taking a very careful look at the permitted and accessory uses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kozakiewicz insisted, however, that the 10,000-foot runway has ''always been considered as part of the redevelopment scheme'' for the former Grumman site. He said he would like to see it redeveloped in a way that creates jobs and builds a tax base for the town.</p>
        <p>''I am not looking to bring in regularly scheduled commercial airlines or a jetport,'' he said. ''And I heard the taxpayers say, 'Don't raise our taxes to fix it.' But I am searching for a way to keep it viable so that businesses on the site have it as a tool to enhance their property.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
