<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alar's Gone, Little Thanks to the Government; Rush to Judgment</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALAR (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">POTTER, J CRAIG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1039F933A05754C0A967958260" item-length="310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alar's Gone, Little Thanks to the Government; Rush to Judgment</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a former Federal regulator, I felt a special appreciation for your July 9 front-page article on Alar. You clearly show the folly of Government's basing public health policy on weak or incomplete science and media hype. Unfortunately, Alar is not an isolated case.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a former Federal regulator, I felt a special appreciation for your July 9 front-page article on Alar. You clearly show the folly of Government's basing public health policy on weak or incomplete science and media hype. Unfortunately, Alar is not an isolated case.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government put the United States asbestos industry out of business, only to learn that most asbestos risks are very low. I remember very well discussions about the real risks of asbestos that were thrust aside in the rush to judgment largely driven by public perceptions, often based on poor or partial information.</p>
        <p>A further example is dioxin, where the Environmental Protection Agency has set such stringent limits on dioxin in the environment that they now threaten a number of industries. Yet the latest toxicology shows dioxin is far less dangerous to people than once suspected. There are many other examples.</p>
        <p>If we are not careful, we risk repeating the same mistake with electric and magnetic fields. A few epidemiological studies have suggested exposure to them may slightly increase the risk of certain rare cancers. Other studies have found no such relationship.</p>
        <p>But a number of grass-roots organizers are calling electric and magnetic fields a serious health risk requiring immediate Government attention. The news media have found this an appealing story.</p>
        <p>From 1985 to 1988, I was assistant administrator of the E.P.A. in charge of air and radiation programs. Our work raised early questions about electric and magnetic fields. Partly as a result of that work, a large scientific program is under way to answer those questions.</p>
        <p>For once, let's hold off on the hysteria by letting the researchers finish their work. This will let Government regulators base their decisions on solid science. J. CRAIG POTTER Washington, July 12, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
