<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Are Next Gibsons And Ashes?</title>
    <meta content="29VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Sports of The Times" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Tennis Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harmon, Rodney</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E5D81231F93AA1575BC0A961958260" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Are Next Gibsons And Ashes?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey, in Sports of The Times column, comments on work of Rodney Harmon, African-American who is director of multicultural development for United State Tennis Assn; USTA's grass-roots development program seeks to draw 800,000 new people to tennis, including inner-city youths; photo of Harmon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is not enough to go looking for the next Tiger Woods or the next Jackie Joyner-Kersee or the next Alex Rodriguez. You have to start with a talent pool.</p>
        <p>Rodney Harmon goes out looking for tennis players. He goes to Moore Park in Miami -- ''an inner-city neighborhood,'' he noted. The young people there see a tall, athletic African-American man with an open personality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is not enough to go looking for the next Tiger Woods or the next Jackie Joyner-Kersee or the next Alex Rodriguez. You have to start with a talent pool.</p>
        <p>Rodney Harmon goes out looking for tennis players. He goes to Moore Park in Miami -- ''an inner-city neighborhood,'' he noted. The young people there see a tall, athletic African-American man with an open personality.</p>
        <p>They might figure out that he has some education: Southern Methodist University, in fact. He doesn't hang a sign around his neck saying that he comes from the same town as the late Arthur Ashe, or that he was a quarterfinalist at the United States Open in 1982. He will play hoops or touch football, proving that tennis players too can be athletes.</p>
        <p>He recently ran into a young man who was 5 feet 7 inches tall and could dunk a basketball, two-handed, from a stationary start. Harmon felt like a tennis version of a recruiting officer for the military: Uncle Sam Wants You.</p>
        <p>''I tell them, 'Tennis can get you into college,' '' Harmon was saying yesterday, adding that tennis is a lifetime sport.</p>
        <p>Harmon is the director of multicultural development for the United States Tennis Association, based in Miami. His job is to make sure all cultures are represented in U.S.T.A. ventures, but his deeper mission is to proselytize for the sport he loves.</p>
        <p>The U.S.T.A. rolled out just about every suit and blazer in all of tennis yesterday to announce a five-year, grass-roots development program with an estimated $31 million price tag. The task force wants to establish 1,000 points of light, or 20 local programs, or whatever, to draw 800,000 new people to tennis. Later it  will announce a plan for the geniuses uncovered by the programs.</p>
        <p>The former Czechoslovakia knew how to bring out the calipers to measure the calf muscles of a wiry 9-year-old who turned out to be Martina Navratilova, but I'm a little dubious about programs in this huge and diverse nation.</p>
        <p>There are millions of little Codys and Hunters dribbling a soccer ball around a bunch of orange cones, but the American soccer establishment still has no clear path to develop the next Diego Armando Maradona, who developed his genius kicking a wadded-up sock in the barrio in Buenos Aires.</p>
        <p>The problem is that peer pressure and role models produce the next wave of geniuses more efficiently than programs do. Free advertisement is better than lucrative campaigns.</p>
        <p>''Basketball is big everywhere,'' Harmon admitted. ''And in Florida, where I live now, and in Texas, where I used to live, football is king.''</p>
        <p>Harmon thinks the role models are available for his favorite sport, too. He cites MaliVai Washington, the 1996 Wimbledon finalist, and Chanda Rubin, the young hopeful currently in a slump. There has been Zina Garrison and Lori McNeil from the same park in Houston. The Williams sisters, Venus and Serena, are products of the father's isolated vision. And before that there was Althea Gibson and Arthur Ashe.</p>
        <p>Rodney Harmon was 7 when Ashe won the United States Open in 1968, and at the age of 10 he attended a clinic given by Ashe and Charlie Pasarell. Harmon came along in the same park program in Richmond run by black groups or the white establishment, and then he was recruited to college in Dallas.</p>
        <p>No tennis player becomes an accomplished player in a schoolyard the way most basketball players do, even before the school programs and summer camps. In tennis, there are too many strokes to learn, too many details, too many age groups. Without massive programs, entire generations and population swaths will be lost.</p>
        <p>''Billie Jean King once told me that she never would have made it to Wimbledon without her local parks program,'' said Dean Tice, the executive director of the National Recreation and Parks Association, referring to the program in Long Beach, Calif., that produced King.</p>
        <p>Somehow, American champions manage to emerge from the pattern of country clubs and public parks and previous U.S.T.A. programs. But the superbly competitive Chris Evert did not produce 10 challengers, and the historically talented Pete Sampras does not strike the emotional cords that Michael Jordan does, and nobody should have expected it.</p>
        <p>Tennis needs some kind of artificial boost or else it will remain the province mostly of people who can afford the lessons and the clothes and the court time. Harmon says there is talent to go around. As a soccer buff, I say to Harmon, if you find any geniuses with thick thighs and a low center of gravity, share the wealth.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
