<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Girl, 2, Slain For Crying, Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="29CHIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pena, Brenda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loriano, Irene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coad, Donald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E3DC1331F93AA1575BC0A961958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Girl, 2, Slain For Crying, Officials Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City investigators say that Brenda Pena, two-year-old girl found battered, unconscious and hemorrhaging internally in her Brooklyn home, was beaten, apparently because she would not stop crying; child's mother, Irene Loriano, and her boyfriend, Donald Coad, are charged with her killing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 2-year-old girl found battered, unconscious and hemorrhaging internally in her Brooklyn home on Wednesday was beaten to death, apparently because she would not stop crying, investigators said yesterday as the child's mother and her boyfriend were charged with her killing.</p>
        <p>An autopsy showed that the victim, Brenda Pena, suffered fatal lacerations of the pancreas, liver, small intestine and other organs and bled internally, as a result of ''multiple blunt impacts to the torso,'' said Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the New York City Medical Examiner's office, which ruled the death a homicide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 2-year-old girl found battered, unconscious and hemorrhaging internally in her Brooklyn home on Wednesday was beaten to death, apparently because she would not stop crying, investigators said yesterday as the child's mother and her boyfriend were charged with her killing.</p>
        <p>An autopsy showed that the victim, Brenda Pena, suffered fatal lacerations of the pancreas, liver, small intestine and other organs and bled internally, as a result of ''multiple blunt impacts to the torso,'' said Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the New York City Medical Examiner's office, which ruled the death a homicide.</p>
        <p>After a day of questioning, the girl's mother, Irene Loriano, 21, of 563 Crescent Street in East New York, and her boyfriend, Donald Coad, 21, of 108 Avenue D in Manhattan, were taken to the 75th Precinct station in Brooklyn and booked on homicide and other charges.</p>
        <p>Investigators said both had made statements indicating that Mr. Coad had become enraged and beaten the girl Wednesday morning because she would not stop crying. When Brenda fell unconscious, the investigators said, someone in the household called the police, and the Emergency Medical Service took the child to Brookdale Hospital Medical Center, where she was pronounced dead on arrival.</p>
        <p>In the tragic lists of fatal child abuse in New York City, where the perils of growing up in households tormented by alcohol, drug abuse and other problems are legion, the most common evil may be the senseless battering of infants by mothers' boyfriends, often because of a child's crying, officials say.</p>
        <p>''It's fairly common,'' said one investigator, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''There's often a history of domestic violence, and it extends to a child. Men have this power.''</p>
        <p>It was unclear if drugs or alcohol had any role in Brenda Pena's death. And while some investigators said there were no signs of long-term abuse of the girl, other officials said that doctors at Brookdale had found bruises on her body in various stages of healing. These bruises did not necessarily indicate long-term abuse, but doubts remained.</p>
        <p>However, the family had not come to the notice of child-welfare officials. ''There was no prior report of abuse or neglect regarding the mother or this child,'' said Maggie Lear, a spokeswoman for the city's Administration for Children's Services, which began an inquiry. She said that Brenda's 4-year-old brother, who has been placed in foster care, showed no signs of abuse or neglect.</p>
        <p>Brenda Pena, who was born in February 1995, lived with her mother, brother and an aunt in a neighborhood of well-kept, two-story brick houses. Neighbors, stunned at news of her death, recalled a little girl who frequently played with other children in a yard behind the house on Crescent Street, or toddled along with her mother to the store.</p>
        <p>At 11:20 A.M. on Wednesday, a caller, described only as a member of the victim's household, brought the police and an Emergency Medical Service team to the family's first-floor apartment. They found Brenda unconscious; her torso, arms and back were streaked with dark bruises. ''She had been very badly beaten,'' said an official familiar with the investigation, who also insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>The medical team administered cardiopulmonary resuscitation at the apartment, investigators said. But efforts to save her life were unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>After making statements yesterday, investigators said, Mr. Coad was charged with three counts of homicide -- one of intentional killing, one of causing the girl's death by depraved indifference and one of causing the death of a person under 11 by depraved indifference. The charges carry varying penalties, up to 25 years to life in prison.</p>
        <p>Ms. Loriano was charged with criminally negligent homicide, an accusation that she failed to protect the child in a deadly situation, a Class E felony with a maximum penalty of four years in prison. Both suspects were charged with endangering the welfare the child, a misdemeanor.</p>
        <p>Little was known yesterday about the nature or duration of the mother's relationship with Mr. Coad. A woman who said she was a sister of Mr. Coad said in a brief telephone interview that he had never before been in trouble, though he was an unemployed school dropout.</p>
        <p>Asked if her brother had a temper or was subject to angry outbursts, the woman said: ''Only if somebody wears his pants.'' Asked what she meant, she said, 'You know, if you put on my shirt, I get angry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
