<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Studies Dispute View of Dyslexia, Finding Girls as Afflicted as Boys</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="378662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="EDUCATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DYSLEXIA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">READING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL EDUCATION (HANDICAPPED)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF CHILD HEALTH AND HUMAN DEVELOPMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, DAVID (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLATA, GINA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dyslexia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dyslexia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Education (Handicapped)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB113EF931A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Studies Dispute View of Dyslexia, Finding Girls as Afflicted as Boys</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINA KOLATA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLATA, GINA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Despite a widespread belief to the contrary, girls are just as likely as boys to have the reading impairment dyslexia, three studies say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Despite a widespread belief to the contrary, girls are just as likely as boys to have the reading impairment dyslexia, three studies say.</p>
        <p>Despite a widespread belief to the contrary, girls are just as likely as boys to have the reading impairment dyslexia, three studies say.</p>
        <p>But teachers are far more likely to diagnose the condition in boys, researchers said, to the point that too many boys are in special education classes and too many girls with reading problems are struggling in silence.</p>
        <p>Dyslexia afflicts 10 to 15 percent of the population.</p>
        <p>Experts on dyslexia said the findings would force school systems to re-examine methods of diagnosing the problem and referring children for help. Children with dyslexia can be taught to read when their disorder is recognized. One study is being published today in the Journal of the American Medical Association. Another is being prepared for publication, and the third has been published in part.</p>
        <p>'Very Important Papers'</p>
        <p>''These are very important papers,'' said Dr. David Gray, an educational psychologist and dyslexia specialist at the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development, which has paid for much of the research. He said the results had ''major social consequences and major research implications.''</p>
        <p>The research being published today is by Dr. Sally Shaywitz, the co-director of the Center for the Study of Learning and Attention Disorders at Yale University and other researchers. Their study involved 445 Connecticut children who were studied from the time they entered kindergarten until they reached third grade. The researchers found that the schools identified more than four times as many second-grade boys as girls as being dyslexic, and more than twice as many third-grade boys as girls were said to have reading problems.</p>
        <p>But when the researchers independently tested the students, they found equal numbers of boys and girls in both grades with reading difficulties. And, they found, fewer than half the children referred for reading problems actually had them.</p>
        <p>The tendency to reverse letters in words is thought of as typical of dyslexia but that image is untrue, said Dr. Shaywitz, who added that such reversals are ''made by all kinds of readers. She said, ''Children with dyslexia make more errors in general so they make more reversals too, but not proportionately more,'' she explained.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shaywitz said children who had trouble learning to read had trouble with language in general. ''When they see a word in print, they have difficulty pronouncing it and they have difficulties in writing sentences and paragraphs.''</p>
        <p>For the past century, educators and psychologists have assumed that dyslexia strikes mostly boys. Entire research programs have been set up to find the biological basis for the presumed gender difference in developing dyslexia. For example, researchers have proposed that something that occurs during fetal life can turn a male brain into that of a genius or, as a sort of opposite side, a dyslexic.</p>
        <p>The theory also held that dyslexia was possibly linked to being left-handed, possibly hinting at a scrambling of signals in the brain. But the three groups of researchers found no relationship between left handedness and reading disabilities.</p>
        <p>Unbiased Sample, for First Time</p>
        <p>Most earlier research on dyslexia worked with children identified by school systems as having dyslexia, but the three new studies worked with an unbiased group chosen from all students. Most school systems rely on the recommendations of teachers before testing students for the impairment, rather that testing all students for it.</p>
        <p>Male participants typically account for 80 percent of those treated at dyslexia clinics, said Dr. C. Wilson Anderson, who is president of the Orton Dyslexia Society and teacher trainer for the Menninger Clinic in Topeka, Kansas. But with the new evidence that dyslexia affects girls in equal numbers, school systems may improve their referral methods, Dr. Anderson said. ''Quite frankly, I'm excited by the studies,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Sheila B. Plank, national executive at the National Center for Learning Disabilities, in New York, said: ''This research encourages us to accelerate our replication efforts. This is a real breakthrough.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Reid Lyon, a neurology professor at the University of Vermont in Burlington and chairman of the scientific review committee for the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development in Bethesda, Md., said: ''These are significant findings. From a social standpoint, it is critical that we understand that equal numbers of boys as girls have difficulty learning to read.''</p>
        <p>Study in North Carolina</p>
        <p>A second study, by Dr. Frank Wood, a professor of neuropsychology and director of the dyslexia program at Bowman Gray University in Winston-Salem, N.C., involved 485 children in the Winston-Salem-Forsyth County schools. Dr. Wood, Dr. Rebecca Felton, associate director of the dyslexia program, and their colleagues, tested the children in the first grade and again in the third grade. They found no difference in the reading abilities of boys and girls.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wood, said he and his colleagues ''were shocked'' when their research project showed there was no difference. ''This contradicts decades of conventional wisdom,'' Dr. Wood said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard Olson and Dr. John De Fries of the University of Colorado in Boulder reached the same conclusion after studying over 400 pairs of twins, looking for an inherited component to dyslexia. The twins included over 100 pairs of identical twins in which at least one member of each pair had a reading disability and over 100 pairs of identical twins with no reading disabilities, for comparison. They also included more than 100 pairs of fraternal twins, with at least one member of each pair having a reading problem and more than 100 pairs of fraternal twins with no reading problems.</p>
        <p>Boys Are 'Being Penalized'</p>
        <p>Dr. Olson and Dr. De Freis also found essentially no differences by sex in the occurrence of dyslexia. ''We agree with Dr. Shaywitz,'' Dr. Olson said. He added that identical twins were more likley to both be dyslexic than fraternal twins, indicating that a tendency to have a reading disability is inherited.</p>
        <p>Dr. Shaywitz, said she hoped the findings would lead to a fundamental change in the way reading disabilities were viewed. ''Boys are really being penalized by being mislabeled and girls, who really need help, are failing to be noticed,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She and others said they suspect the frequent diagnosis of dsylexia in boys and the failure to diagnose it in girls is caused partly by teachers' and parents' expectations that boys, not girls, will have problems. ''It becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy,'' Dr. Shaywtiz said.</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
