<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Primaries; PEROT'S STRENGTH SHOWN IN OREGON</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OREGON</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (STATE)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLE, R W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, H ROSS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE123FF932A15756C0A964958260" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Primaries; PEROT'S STRENGTH SHOWN IN OREGON</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLE, R W JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a startling demonstration of electoral strength, Ross Perot captured a significant portion of Republican and Democratic votes in Tuesday's Oregon primary, according to interviews with voters leaving polling places, and he may have done the same thing in Washington State.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot's exact totals are not known because all his support was from write-in votes, which Oregon law does not require to be counted in primaries, except in special circumstances. And in Washington, where the primary was a popularity contest unrelated to convention delegates, write-ins need not be tallied for a week after an election day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a startling demonstration of electoral strength, Ross Perot captured a significant portion of Republican and Democratic votes in Tuesday's Oregon primary, according to interviews with voters leaving polling places, and he may have done the same thing in Washington State.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot's exact totals are not known because all his support was from write-in votes, which Oregon law does not require to be counted in primaries, except in special circumstances. And in Washington, where the primary was a popularity contest unrelated to convention delegates, write-ins need not be tallied for a week after an election day.</p>
        <p>But a survey of voters leaving the polls in Oregon by Voter Research and Surveys, a consortium of four television networks, indicated that Mr. Perot, a Texas billionaire who plans an independent Presidential candidacy, had won 13 percent of the vote in the Democratic primary and 15 percent in the Republican primary. In remote San Juan County, Wash., a group of islands in Puget Sound where the relatively few votes were tabulated quickly, Mr. Perot gathered enough write-in votes to lead both parties' primaries.</p>
        <p>"I've seen nothing like it since Vietnam," said Senator Bob Packwood, an Oregon Republican who easily won renomination. "Public alienation from politics as usual is just about complete. After the check-bouncing business, everyone said: 'That's it. No more.' And of course that feeds Perot's fire."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot has been shown leading President Bush and Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas, the likely Democratic nominee, in several state polls and, last weekend, in a national poll taken by Time magazine and CNN. But not until Tuesday had he attracted any number of actual votes from actual voters -- and it happened in Oregon and Washington without any campaigning by Mr. Perot, without appeals for votes from his backers and without advertising.</p>
        <p>Now that it has happened twice, similar or even larger protests may develop in the remaining primary contests. They conclude with contests in California and five other states on June 2. And while Mr. Bush and Mr. Clinton remain all but certain of nomination, every Perot vote erodes the credibility of their candidacies in the general election and increases that of his own. Results in 2 States</p>
        <p>The apparently spontaneous protest vote considerably tarnished easy victories for Mr. Bush and Mr. Clinton. Mr. Bush took 76 percent of the Oregon vote to 22 percent for Patrick J. Buchanan, his conservative challenger. In Washington, the count was 83 percent for the President and 13 percent for Mr. Buchanan.</p>
        <p>On the Democratic side, Mr. Clinton captured 50 percent of the Oregon vote. His only active rival, former Gov. Edmund G. Brown Jr. of California, took 35 percent -- a solid showing that could portend a strong run for Mr. Brown in his home state.</p>
        <p>The Arkansas Governor picked up 28 delegates in Oregon, pushing his total to 1,788, or 83 percent of the 2,145 he needs for nomination. Mr. Brown gained 19 delegates, giving him 374.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also won in Washington, with 51 percent to 29 percent for Mr. Brown. Delegates there are allocated in caucuses and conventions.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most surprising finding of the survey of voters leaving the polls in Oregon, even more than the large number of write-in votes for Mr. Perot, was that more Democratic primary voters said they thought well of the Texan (57 percent) than of Mr. Clinton (49 percent). Among Republican primary voters, the same number (59 percent) expressed favorable views of Mr. Perot as did so about President Bush.</p>
        <p>The voter survey also included hypothetical three-way races. Among Democratic primary voters, Mr. Perot did at least as well as Mr. Clinton, pulling 45 percent to 42 percent for Mr. Clinton, with a margin of sampling error of plus or minus 4 percentage points. Among Republicans, Mr. Bush pulled 51 percent to 40 percent for Mr. Perot.</p>
        <p>Among Oregon voters who turned out for the primary, in other words, Mr. Perot has greatly weakened partisan ties without announcing his candidacy. If Mr. Perot, a computer entrepreneur, can fight the two major-party candidates to a draw among their own fellow party members this fall, he will be very difficult to stop.</p>
        <p>In comments in Austin, Tex., Mr. Clinton seemed to be trying to link himself with the insurgency of Mr. Perot and thus to buttress his claim to be an agent of change.</p>
        <p>As far as voters' "positive feelings for Ross Perot, I can't blame them," Mr. Clinton said. "I agree with a lot of what he says," he added. "I think the system needs to be shaken up, and I'm willing to compete with anyone who wants to run for President. I have no negative feelings about what happened in Oregon."</p>
        <p>Election officials in Oregon said that casting write-in votes was difficult in that state because it used a punched-card system in most precincts. Voters must take other steps beyond merely writing in a name. In such cases, write-in campaigns usually distribute palm-sized instruction cards to be taken into the voting booths, but there apparently was no official or unofficial campaign on Mr. Perot's behalf in Oregon.</p>
        <p>Ted Thomas, the Texan's state coordinator, said he had told supporters to forget about the primaries and concentrate on collecting petitions to put his name on the general-election ballot. He added, "They didn't listen." Vote Termed Spontaneous</p>
        <p>"It was not organized at all, to my knowledge," said Carol Auger, executive director of the Oregon Democratic Party. "It's a very significant vote, not to be taken lightly. People are tired of Republicans blaming Congress and Democrats blaming the White House, so they find it appealing when Perot talks about using the best people of both parties."</p>
        <p>Next Tuesday, primaries will be held in Kentucky and Arkansas, which is Mr. Clinton's home state but also the state where Mr. Perot was born. On June 2, Alabama, Montana, New Jersey, New Mexico and Ohio will vote, along with California. A leading New Jersey Democrat said the Perot campaign had already set up tables, looking for volunteers, at every mall in his area.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
