<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Miracle on Market St. for Final Retail Holdout</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NEWARK JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MACY, R H, &amp; CO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRUM, CHARLES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED71539F932A15756C0A964958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Miracle on Market St. for Final Retail Holdout</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES STRUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRUM, CHARLES</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the end yesterday, a floorwalker could roll a bowling ball down almost any aisle at Macy's in Newark and not hit anyone.</p>
        <p>Sunday newspaper inserts announced specials or extended store hours at Herald Square and many branches, but not in Newark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the end yesterday, a floorwalker could roll a bowling ball down almost any aisle at Macy's in Newark and not hit anyone.</p>
        <p>Sunday newspaper inserts announced specials or extended store hours at Herald Square and many branches, but not in Newark.</p>
        <p>And the Cellar, Macy's famous Manhattan basement of exotic food and state-of-the-art pots and pans, was reduced to a small section of china, glassware and small appliances on the second floor here. The real basement in Newark was closed to shoppers, as were 12 of the 16 floors in the block-square building on Market Street.</p>
        <p>By lunchtime, customers had already begun to hear about the end of a store whose slogan, "We're a part of your life," mocked the announcement yesterday. With the closing, Newark has lost the last and perhaps most potent symbol of a once-glorious mercantile history and suffered another blow in its attempt to restore an economy that fled with its middle class two decades ago.</p>
        <p>While most shoppers expressed dismay, there was also a good deal of indignation that the only sizable chain stores left in downtown Newark would be two five-and-dime stalwarts, McCrory's and Woolworth's.</p>
        <p>"Where am I going to do my shopping now?," said Octavia Hutchins, who had just bought a pair of shoes.  "This is the last of the quality stores."</p>
        <p>Ms. Hutchins, who lives in East Orange and teaches first grade in the Newark public schools, said she shopped at Macy's because it was convenient. And while its noontime trade rarely registered brisk on the shopping meter, it was the busiest part of the selling day, which revolved around the schedules of office and courthouse staffs on their breaks.</p>
        <p>Mary Mahoney of Union Township, who works in state offices a few blocks away, said she shopped often, for cosmetics, clothes and housewares. "It saves us going to the mall at night," she said.</p>
        <p>Macy's managers refused to discuss the closing, and many on its sales staff followed instructions not to talk about it. Reporters were politely asked to leave. But Ms. Mahoney and other customers reported that some of the 340 employees were clearly distraught, after having been told at 9 yesterday morning that the store, the largest of seven Macy's outlets to be shut, would close by Aug. 1.</p>
        <p>Mayor Sharpe James expressed shock at the announcement but said through a spokeswoman, Pamela E. Goldstein, that he would not comment until after a meeting tomorrow morning that had been requested by a Macy's official earlier in the week.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued in New York, Macy's said the Newark building, which is owned by the company, would stay occupied, housing a computer operation and corporate offices employing several hundred people.</p>
        <p>In its heyday, the Macy's store, which began life in 1892 as L. Bamberger &amp; Company, was a jewel of Newark's carriage trade. Its founder, Louis Bamberger, arrived from Baltimore, acquired a bankrupt dry goods shop called Hill &amp; Cragg and turned it into a vast emporium of service and style. It made him rich, and he returned the favor, endowing the Newark Museum and the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton University.</p>
        <p>By 1929, with both of his partners dead, he sold to R. H. Macy &amp; Co., which kept the Bamberger name until 1986. Many customers still call the store by its old nickname, Bams, and the name L. Bamberger &amp; Co. remains on bronze plaques outside the building. 'A Kind of Filene's Basement'</p>
        <p>For years, Bamberger's shared Broad and Market streets with stores like Kresge, Hahne's, Hearn's, Ohrbach's, Jay's, Burt's, S. Klein on the Square and Sears Roebuck &amp; Company. All of them are gone.</p>
        <p>And with Newark's economy souring, Macy's began to use its store here to move merchandise that failed to sell elsewhere. "It became a kind of Filene's basement, I guess," said Richard G. Schoon, president of the Chamber of Commerce, adding that in his impression the store was probably just breaking even.</p>
        <p>Ultimately what happened to its predecessors happened to Macy's, just as it happened elsewhere: malls. But the character of Newark's neighborhoods and its central business district were contributing factors. Few people live downtown, so getting to Macy's meant driving or taking buses. There is little free parking, and if shoppers have to rely on buses, there are buses that go to the malls, which have more variety than the small, inexpensive shops that are all that remain on Market Street.  NEWARK JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
