<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bottle Collecting: Pieces of the Past Worth Digging Deep For</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="645952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLECTORS AND COLLECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PIKE, HELEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD1F3BF932A05753C1A965958260" item-length="1472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bottle Collecting: Pieces of the Past Worth Digging Deep For</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELEN PIKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PIKE, HELEN</byline>
      <dateline>SOUTH AMBOY</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMEWHERE under dense overgrowth in this industrial Raritan Bay town, Glenn Vogel and Glenn Harbour are digging through the ash, clay, sand and rusting metal of history.</p>
        <p>For more than six hours, the slow, rhythmic work is punctuated by odd bits of nursery rhymes and nonsense songs that float up from a 15-foot hole in the abandoned dump. Mr. Vogel and Mr. Harbour estimate they are digging down as far as 1895. Scattered around the opening are the remains of leather boots, wooden buckets, porcelain bowls and eight-inch-long oyster shells -- all of which they have dug up and none of which interest them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMEWHERE under dense overgrowth in this industrial Raritan Bay town, Glenn Vogel and Glenn Harbour are digging through the ash, clay, sand and rusting metal of history.</p>
        <p>For more than six hours, the slow, rhythmic work is punctuated by odd bits of nursery rhymes and nonsense songs that float up from a 15-foot hole in the abandoned dump. Mr. Vogel and Mr. Harbour estimate they are digging down as far as 1895. Scattered around the opening are the remains of leather boots, wooden buckets, porcelain bowls and eight-inch-long oyster shells -- all of which they have dug up and none of which interest them.</p>
        <p>Only when the clink of metal against glass occurs does the site erupt with whoops of glee as they gently unearth what they are searching for: turn-of-the-century hand blown bottles.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Vogel's and Mr. Harbour's passion for glass may seem obsessive, they are not alone in collecting the old-fashioned containers that used to hold any liquid from bromides to beer. Experiencing a Resurgence</p>
        <p>Every 10 years, often concurrent with a recession, bottle collecting experiences a resurgence, said Isabel Sherwood of Toms River, an officer of the national Federation of Historic Bottle Collectors and a one-time digger.</p>
        <p>The current interest has been building for about three years, she said. The Jersey Shore Bottle Club, to which she, Mr. Vogel and Mr. Harbour belong, counts its membership in terms of families. Recently, it added 20 new members to its longstanding core of 70.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sherwood further estimates that the region has about 475 individual collectors who regularly get together to trade, buy, exhibit and share historical information.  'Often a Family Affair'</p>
        <p>There are three clubs in the state affiliated with the federation: the North Jersey Bottle Collectors Association in Oakland, the Heritage Club in Vineland and the Jersey Shore Club, which meets monthly in Belmar. There is also a nonfederation bottle collectors' club in New Egypt.</p>
        <p>"Collecting, even digging for bottles, is often a family affair," said Mrs. Sherwood, who occasionally helps her husband, Stanley, with his collections of milk bottles and glass balls that were once used for target shooting.</p>
        <p>One reason for the passion of collecting bottles is that they are relatively inexpensive. Some sell for as little as a few cents at a yard sale while others are found. These discoveries often lead the would-be collector to library talks given by established collectors, bottle shows and club meetings.</p>
        <p>The most frequently asked questions are: What used to be in the bottles? Where were they made? Who made them? Why are they colored? How can I find more like this one?</p>
        <p>That is usually how a collection gets started, said Mrs. Sherwood, who began with fruit jars and now also collects pickle jars. Style, color, maker, location and former content, like perfume, medicine, poison, bitters, soda and even olive oil, become the framework on which to build a collection.</p>
        <p>Many collectors print handouts of the research that they have tirelessly gleaned from libraries, county historical archives and even courthouse records. Some collectors branch out, looking for vintage postcards and sepia-toned photographs in an effort to identify business locations and the faces of the entrepreneurs whose bottles they now own. Still others seek out advertising labels to match their bottles.</p>
        <p>"It brings me back in time," said Bob Randolph, a Manasquan auctioneer who was one of 150 exhibitors at the recent fall show of the Jersey Shore Club. Back in time also means when he was a youngster growing up in Neptune and ignorantly smashing blob-topped and hutch-topped bottles he uncovered in a Shark River creek bed.</p>
        <p>Today, those vintage bottles whose tops indicate how they were sealed fetch $45 and more, Mr. Randolph said with a shake of his head. He said bottles were once again setting records at auctions and private sales, as they did in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>"Color is king," he said. "It's dictating the price." A bottle in amber or light yellow or greenish blue can, even if its shape is plain, command 10 times the price of a more ordinary bottle, he said.</p>
        <p>After color comes age, Mr. Randolph added. Bottles made before 1870 are much sought after because few have survived and most were crudely made before manufacturing techniques evolved.</p>
        <p>The last criterion is category, and, Mr. Randolph said, flasks head collectors' wish lists. They are followed by soda bottles and then colored pontils, named for the indentation in the base that is made when the blow pipe is removed from the finished glass container.</p>
        <p>But even though prices at auction can climb as high as $42,000 for a single bottle, Mr. Randolph was quick to point out that fortunes are not made overnight.</p>
        <p>"People spend years developing an eye for detail and color gradations," he said. "They start with dollar bottles and work their way up. If a category gets out of range for them, they try to develop another one that hasn't been discovered. It's really a form of treasure hunting. But nobody should quit their day job."</p>
        <p>All of which is of little importance to Chris Tobin, 12, of Forked River.</p>
        <p>"I like the odd stuff," Chris said, "different shapes, different colors."</p>
        <p>Chris was one of the 500 individuals -- 100 more than last year -- who attended a bottle show at Toms River High School North. His purchase for the day was a 50-cent gum dish from Millville Art Glass, a cranberry-colored disk made by Ed Johnson, a retired glass-mold maker.</p>
        <p>Chris's biggest investment to date is a $5 cranberry bottle he found during an antique furniture foray with his mother, Connie, who regularly attends shows and yard sales. Chris said he has yet to dig for bottles but may do so eventually.</p>
        <p>Rita and Howard Morgan of Howell have stopped digging because they now have a 2 1/2-year-old son, Christopher. But they came to the bottle show looking for glass flasks, ice-cream soda bottles and mason jars. They have even begun a glass-train bottle collection for their son.</p>
        <p>When he gets older, the couple may dig again, taking the child with them, Mrs. Morgan said. But if they do, it will be with caution. One outing netted them each $60 fines for trespassing, she said.</p>
        <p>"I think it was a high amount to discourage us," Mrs. Morgan said. "But the farmer didn't even give us time to explain ourselves before he called the police." Taking Inventory</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, back at the dump, Mr. Vogel and Mr. Harbour were taking inventory. Whenever they find a large, promising site, they observe the buddy system to avoid cave-in related accidents. They also rarely dig in the summer when it is the height of tick and chigger season. And they usually confine their digs to open land or abandoned sites, like former dumps.</p>
        <p>"I'm looking for color to fill out my collection," said Mr. Harbour, a painting preservationist, who found a honey-amber shoe-polish bottle at the dig.</p>
        <p>On the open market, the bottle would go for about $10, he said, but for this amateur archeologist, the value lies in having found a bottle that will now be part of his private collection.</p>
        <p>Besides color, Mr. Harbour is also putting together a collection based on the Bayshore region from South Amboy to Highlands. To date, he has gathered a small -- 250-item -- but impressive variety of medicine, cider, milk, beer and soda bottles, along with broken stoneware crocks he has meticulously glued back together. He exhibits his findings at libraries and museums in the area. A Journey Into the Past</p>
        <p>"Americans used to live out of glass," said Mr. Harbour, a Middletown resident who actively promotes glass-related events at the Spy House, a Revolutionary-era museum on the Raritan Bay in the township's Port Monmouth section. "Their medicine, their food, even their advertising used to be on glass."</p>
        <p>Mr. Vogel, an Eatontown-area historian who works at Fort Monmouth, said, "Every bottle represents a little journey into the past."</p>
        <p>At the dig he found little of interest other than a pale lavender machine-made Eiffel Tower Fruit Juice bottle. "It's the first time I've ever seen one of these," he said.</p>
        <p>The bottle will probably go into his sale pile. Mr. Vogel, who owns more than 600 bottles, concentrates on handblown beers and sodas from the 1860's, even though he owns some machine-made bottles that first appeared in 1903.</p>
        <p>"It's all about owning a little piece of history," he said.</p>
        <p>His favorite part of his collection is the bottles of William A. French of Red Bank, a bottler who, Mr. Vogel discovered, was one of the five wealthiest men in New Jersey in 1900. His French collection features 47 different bottles so far.</p>
        <p>"We're local historians who use bottles to tell the stories of an area," Mr. Vogel said. "If we don't do it now, soon it will be lost forever."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
