<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Aristide Fails to Return, His Foes Celebrate in Haiti</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="646216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PORT-AU-PRINCE (HAITI)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D71630F932A05753C1A965958260" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Aristide Fails to Return, His Foes Celebrate in Haiti</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti, Oct. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting at sundown on Friday and lasting through the night, the streets of the capital echoed with gunfire as far-right groups and soldiers opposed to the return of the nation's exiled President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, celebrated their success in defying the international effort to bring about his return by today.</p>
        <p>By dawn, the desolate scene left by the revelry and spent gunpowder spoke volumes about the mood of this country, and of the price it has paid for the army coup 25 months ago that overthrew Haiti's first democratically elected Government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Starting at sundown on Friday and lasting through the night, the streets of the capital echoed with gunfire as far-right groups and soldiers opposed to the return of the nation's exiled President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, celebrated their success in defying the international effort to bring about his return by today.</p>
        <p>By dawn, the desolate scene left by the revelry and spent gunpowder spoke volumes about the mood of this country, and of the price it has paid for the army coup 25 months ago that overthrew Haiti's first democratically elected Government.</p>
        <p>Since July, Oct. 30 had been scheduled as the date for Father Aristide's return. Had he come back, the city would have been the stage of a popular celebration. Instead, this morning it was like a ghost town.</p>
        <p>When Father Aristide was elected nearly three years ago, jubilant crowds coursed through the streets. Today, blue-shirted policemen and stony-faced plainclothesmen grimly patrolled the downtown area with automatic weapons slung from their shoulders. Fear in the Streets</p>
        <p>Throughout the low-lying areas of Port-au-Prince, where the poor live in crowded slums, often without sewage or drinking water, supporters of Father Aristide expressed regret and skepticism at efforts by international diplomats to restore democracy here.</p>
        <p>"This was supposed to be like New Years Day," said Samuel Delva, 41, who stood with neighbors warily monitoring the streets for signs of the gunmen who have been regularly terrorizing his neighborhood. "We thought we would be delivered. Now we are shedding tears, and the worst thing is that they are provoking us."</p>
        <p>Haiti's military has tried in recent weeks to build popular enthusiasm for its defiance of the United Nations-brokered accord that was to have paved the way for Father Aristide's return. Hitting a time-honored theme among Haitian nationalists, the Army commander, Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras, told a radio interviewer on Thursday that he would "prefer to be defeated standing up rather than lying down."</p>
        <p>Rumors have been rife that far-right political parties, working in league with the army, would declare Father Aristide's presidency vacant this weekend and call for new elections. "They have already decided that they can shut the country down for a year and wait out the outside world," said a businessman with extensive army contacts. A New Dictatorship?</p>
        <p>Some diplomats have said that a recent increase in the terror campaign -- in which plainclothes gunmen known as attaches fire their guns into the air in crowded neighborhoods -- was meant to signal the coming of a new dictatorship.</p>
        <p>But with Haiti's economy slowly choking under the pressure of an international blockade on oil supplies, the prices for basic goods rising fast and the death toll mounting daily from political violence, there was little sign today that the nationalistic chord had any resonance.</p>
        <p>"We would like to do something, but we have no guns," said Jacques Joseph, an unemployed 43-year-old who was one of the few pedestrians near the downtown area early this morning. "Every day we see more bodies of their victims. They are killing people and doing nothing for us -- just look at all the rubbish."</p>
        <p>This deep disgust over the military is almost matched, however, by a growing cynicism toward the diplomats who have imposed embargoes and held what to many seems an interminable series of talks that have all failed to produce the desired result: Father Aristide's return to power and the removal of the army leaders who overthrew him. Little Faith in Diplomats</p>
        <p>"They keep asking us to believe, but it is just about impossible having any faith in them now," said a wealthy, American-educated businesswoman who has closely followed the United Nations-led diplomacy here. "It is getting to the point where we are asking ourselves if we wouldn't be better off on our own."</p>
        <p>A Haitian human rights worker who supports Father Aristide's return said: "Nothing has been solved because the international community is talking out of both sides of its mouth. The diplomats are playing with us. Meanwhile, Aristide, by sticking with these negotiations, has neutralized the only real weapon he has: the man in the street."</p>
        <p>But the diplomats, who have sought to play down the importance of Father Aristide returning by today, the date called for in the agreement he and General Cedras signed in New York, can do little but ask Father Aristide's supporters for more patience and faith.</p>
        <p>"We have absolutely no doubt that we will be successful," the new United States Ambassador, William L. Swing, said this morning. "We will not be cowed at all."</p>
        <p>There was scant enthusiasm today, however, from Robert Malval, the businessman whom Father Aristide appointed as Prime Minister on August 30. As a television crew set up its equipment on his roof in order, an aide said, to broadcast the "coup live," if one should come, Mr. Malval spoke bleakly about the situation here.</p>
        <p>Asked about a telephone conversation with President Clinton on Friday, Mr. Malval said: "He offered 100 percent support. There was no doubt about his commitment here."</p>
        <p>As Mr. Malval compared some of the diplomatic turns of the Haitian crisis to "theater of the absurd," his mood darkened.</p>
        <p>"I cannot blame the average man for losing hope right now," he said. "Sometimes I too feel that this is a truly meaningless situation. I am an existentialist myself, but even then there must be a limit."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
