<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Singer Who Is Also a Scholar</title>
    <meta content="13TOMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1175985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hampson, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mahler, Gustav (1860-1911)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5D7143EF930A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Singer Who Is Also a Scholar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with baritone Thomas Hampson, who is part of team of scholars doing important research into songs of Mahler; photo; Hampson will present Mahler's songs in recitals at Carnegie Hall (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE baritone Thomas Hampson would never call himself a musicologist. He lacks the academic training and has too much respect for the field to claim a place in it.</p>
        <p>Yet for more than 10 years he has been part of a small team of scholars doing important research into the songs of Gustav Mahler. The work has already produced authoritative critical scores of Mahler's complete songs in the versions for voice and piano, published by Universal Edition, the house that brought out Mahler's music in his lifetime. By the end of the year, this comprehensive project will also have produced critical editions of the complete songs in their versions for voice and orchestra, including transpositions to higher and lower keys, as well as orchestral study scores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE baritone Thomas Hampson would never call himself a musicologist. He lacks the academic training and has too much respect for the field to claim a place in it.</p>
        <p>Yet for more than 10 years he has been part of a small team of scholars doing important research into the songs of Gustav Mahler. The work has already produced authoritative critical scores of Mahler's complete songs in the versions for voice and piano, published by Universal Edition, the house that brought out Mahler's music in his lifetime. By the end of the year, this comprehensive project will also have produced critical editions of the complete songs in their versions for voice and orchestra, including transpositions to higher and lower keys, as well as orchestral study scores.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hampson, who will present recitals of Mahler's songs on Tuesday and Thursday evenings at Carnegie Hall with the pianist Wolfram Rieger, plays down his role in the project, which has primarily been supervised by an Austrian musicologist, Renate Stark-Voit, a Mahler scholar for more than 20 years.</p>
        <p>''I was a sort of mascot,'' Mr. Hampson said recently at a restaurant near Lincoln Center. ''I guess you could call me the 'Mitarbeiter,' '' or collaborator, he added. Still, in the Universal catalog the edition of the Mahler songs for voice and piano, published five years ago, is called the Hilmar-Hampson Edition (Hilmar having been Dr. Stark-Voit's surname in an earlier marriage).</p>
        <p>''That's kind of fun,'' Mr. Hampson said. Most musicologists would consider it much more than that. Having one's name on an important new edition of works by a major composer could clinch tenure for a teacher at a university.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Hampson would become so scholarly in midlife is not what his background and early career suggested. Born in Elkhart, Ind., he was raised in eastern Washington State. His father was a nuclear engineer; his mother, an accomplished organist, played at the family's Seventh-day Adventist church. When he emerged in the 1980's, he attracted immediate attention for his robust baritone voice and dashing stage presence. Then a client of the powerful manager Herbert Breslin, Mr. Hampson was promoted as a hunky, thick-maned, all-American opera star.</p>
        <p>''Mistakes were made by a lot of people at the time, including me,'' he said. ''I came on so quickly. I underestimated how in-your-face I can be sometimes, because of my own enthusiasm. But that enthusiasm is born out of abject curiosity and a lot of energy.''</p>
        <p>Though his work in opera has won him greater popularity, his devotion to the art song has earned him the gratitude of song devotees and the respect of critics. At 44, he is an inquisitive artist who champions songs by living composers, especially Americans, and neglected repertory. A recent project is typical: Mr. Hampson sings the title role in a new EMI Classics recording of ''King Roger,'' an ecstatic, late Romantic and nearly forgotten opera from 1926 by the Polish composer Karol Szymanowski. Set in the 12th century, it deals with the attractions and dangers of Dionysian sensuality. Mr. Hampson learned the role in the original Polish, a daunting task.</p>
        <p>His involvement with Mahler deepened in the late 1980's, when he performed and recorded several Mahler song cycles conducted by Leonard Bernstein. ''I knew at the time that scholars were marching through the works of Mahler, preparing critical editions for publication,'' he said. He calls the Universal volumes of the symphonies and other works the ''famous blue books.'' But, Mr. Hampson wanted to know, where were the blue books for the songs?</p>
        <p>In 1989, Dr. Stark-Voit heard Mr. Hampson perform in a Mahler festival in Kassel, Germany, she said recently. Coincidentally, at the very moment she recalled this -- while speaking by telephone from Germany, where she was vacationing -- Mr. Hampson's voice was coming over her radio, performing the role of Germont in the Metropolitan Opera's live broadcast of Verdi's ''Traviata.''</p>
        <p>''At that concert in Kassel, he interpreted the Mahler songs in a manner that impressed me so very much,'' Dr. Stark-Voit remarked. ''I said to myself, 'This is the man I want to work with on the critical edition.' '' She met him that evening and explained the scope of the project but also the problem.</p>
        <p>The Mahler Gesellschaft, the Austrian society formed in the 1960's to promote Mahler's music and support research and publication, was facing financial trouble, and Universal would publish the works only with outside financing. Mr. Hampson was eager to help, so Dr. Stark-Voit introduced him to Karl Heinz Fussl, a respected, elderly scholar then supervising the research, who has since died.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hampson offered to pay for an assistant to help Dr. Fussl and Dr. Stark-Voit. But they wanted him to have a role in the research as well. At first he was reluctant.</p>
        <p>''I told them that I wasn't a musicologist, that I did not deserve to sit at this table,'' Mr. Hampson said. But it proved eminently helpful to have a singer involved with the work, Dr. Stark-Voit said.</p>
        <p>''His point of view was different from that of actual scholars,'' she explained. As they examined manuscripts together, in places far and wide (including the Morgan Library in New York, which owns several manuscripts), Mr. Hampson noticed things that many scholars would have missed, Dr. Stark-Voit said. He was especially struck by recurring divergences in the songs between their piano and orchestral versions. Sometimes even notes in the vocal lines and words in the texts are different.</p>
        <p>This discovery fortified the case for the most important finding of the entire project, namely, that Mahler considered the versions of the songs with piano, which were almost always composed first, independent works, not just preliminary drafts of orchestral conceptions. ''It was a new idea,'' Dr. Stark-Voit said, ''and he was right.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hampson is quite convincing on the subject. Mahler was ''very chastising to anyone who presumed that the process he followed in composing his songs was one of filling in the piano parts with orchestration,'' he said. Moreover, Mahler was an immensely practical musician, attentive to performers' needs, flexible with regard to transpositions and seldom fixed in his mind about whether a particular song should be sung by a man or a woman.</p>
        <p>As evidence, Mr. Hampson cites a letter Mahler wrote to Johannes Messchaert, a Dutch singer and close colleague. Messchaert was preparing a recital that he was going to perform with Mahler at the piano.</p>
        <p>He wrote regarding two nettlesome problems, Mr. Hampson said. ''First, the key of the song 'Das Irdische Leben' from 'Des Knaben Wunderhorn,' which was E flat minor, was too high for him. Second, something troubled him about the vocal contour of the line 'Wie holen sie ein auf jenen Hoh'n! Im Sonnenschein!' from the fourth song of 'Kindertotenlieder.' The vowels necessary to sing the German were not right at those pitches, he felt.''</p>
        <p>Mahler wrote back posthaste, Mr. Hampson said, telling Messchaert not to worry about the key and offering to play ''Das Irdische Leben'' in any key the singer wanted once they rehearsed. As to the problematic vocal line, Mahler wrote that he would not change the melody but could provide a different scan of the words. In the letter he scribbled a staff and notes offering an alternative way of fitting the text to the melody in that phrase. To Mr. Hampson, this was not the act of a composer who thought of the piano versions of these songs as mere orchestral sketches.</p>
        <p>In his Carnegie Hall programs Mr. Hampson will sing the songs Messchaert inquired about as well as some 30 others. The programs include songs from ''Des Knaben Wunderhorn,'' the complete ''Kindertotenlieder'' and ''Lieder Eines Fahrenden Gesellen,'' and four of the Ruckert lieder.</p>
        <p>Although these works are best known in their orchestral embodiments, Mr. Hampson's fondness for the piano versions is easy to understand. While the orchestral versions bring Mahler's incomparable sense of instrumental color and lush beauty to the songs, the intricacies of the music arguably come through more clearly in the versions with piano. Moreover, the singer is laid bare, so the emotional content of the music can be even more wrenching, though in an intimate way.</p>
        <p>Mahler never expected people to choose between the two. Nor does Mr. Hampson. He simply wants to validate the versions for voice and piano. As a de facto musicologist, he has helped provide authoritative information about the music. The critical edition includes his English translations of Mahler's performance directions, as well as explanatory comments by Mr. Hampson in footnotes. To him, when Mahler writes that a phrase is to be sung, say, ''with a breaking voice'' (in English translation), it means something subtly different from when he writes ''with a broken voice.''</p>
        <p>''I don't want to tell anyone how to sing these songs,'' he said. ''I just want singers to have a proper basis to make their own decisions. Now they do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hampson's continuing involvement with Mahler research should be easier now that he lives with his family in Vienna, in a newly renovated apartment large enough to house his extensive collection of scores, books and recordings. He was recently named a Kammersanger of the Vienna State Opera, an honor infrequently bestowed on Americans. ''Especially baritones,'' Mr. Hampson added wryly. ''We take what we can get.''</p>
        <p>His career in opera proceeds excellently. He returns to the Met in March to sing the title role in Rossini's ''Barbiere di Siviglia.'' He feels that his voice has gotten stronger in recent years, enabling him to enter ''into a new kind of tormented, full-bodied lyric repertoire,'' as he put it: roles like Tchaikovsky's Eugene Onegin and, in Vienna in 2002, the weighty title role of Verdi's ''Simon Boccanegra.''</p>
        <p>He did his first Wagner role, Wolfram in ''Tannhauser,'' at the Zurich Opera last spring, and he feels that his lyrical vocal style is truer to the European tradition than the heave-ho approach that has been so common. ''I think we have taken the big sound idea in Wagner as far as humanly possible,'' he said. ''Maybe it's time to pull back.''</p>
        <p>His explorations of song still seem to claim him the most. He is rightly proud of ''To the Soul,'' a 1997 EMI album of 26 songs by 18 composers, all settings of poems by Walt Whitman, performed with Mr. Hampson's frequent collaborator the pianist Craig Rutenberg. Some of the composers are famous, like Ned Rorem; some are obscure, like the Brooklyn-born William H. Niedlinger, who died in 1924. The idea was to entice listeners to consider the different ways such wide-ranging composers treat Whitman's remarkable words.</p>
        <p>The glory of song is that it allows words and music to mingle: what Mr. Hampson calls the ''dialogue of the poetry'' and ''the musical comment.'' He knows that song recitals can be a hard sell for audiences and that many people may come to his because he is a famous opera singer.</p>
        <p>''That's fine,'' he said. ''I love cashing in whatever celebrity I have, if people will turn out for a song recital.'' With his Mahler recitals this week, audiences will get to hear the work of Thomas Hampson the scholar as well as Thomas Hampson the songster.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
