<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="13GUID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1176025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DA123EF930A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>After its usual cold weather break, the Westbury Music Fair reopens Friday with ''Smokey Joe's Cafe -- the Songs of Leiber and Stoller.'' This national touring version of the Grammy and Tony Award-winning celebration of rock 'n' roll will be offered at 8 p.m. Friday; 2 and 8 p.m. Saturday, and 3 p.m. next Sunday at the showcase on Brush Hollow Road. In future weeks, the lineup will include the Beach Boys, Feb. 26 and 27; ''If You Ever Leave Me . . . I'm Going with You'' with Renee Taylor and Joe Bologna, March 3; the Judds, March 24 and 25; and ''Grease'' April 28 through 30. (516) 334-0800.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>After its usual cold weather break, the Westbury Music Fair reopens Friday with ''Smokey Joe's Cafe -- the Songs of Leiber and Stoller.'' This national touring version of the Grammy and Tony Award-winning celebration of rock 'n' roll will be offered at 8 p.m. Friday; 2 and 8 p.m. Saturday, and 3 p.m. next Sunday at the showcase on Brush Hollow Road. In future weeks, the lineup will include the Beach Boys, Feb. 26 and 27; ''If You Ever Leave Me . . . I'm Going with You'' with Renee Taylor and Joe Bologna, March 3; the Judds, March 24 and 25; and ''Grease'' April 28 through 30. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>Love's Sweet Song</p>
        <p>This year, for their annual ''Songs of Love'' concert, via the Long Island Composers Alliance, Helene Williams, soprano, and Leonard Lehrman, pianist-composer, will spice up the traditional program of songs by Blitzstein, Coward, Porter, Rodgers, Schubert and Lehrman with a New York premiere. The duo will perform ''The Richest Man in Town,'' a song by Jerry Bock and Sheldon Harnick that was written for ''Fiddler on the Roof,'' but was cut to make way for ''Miracle of Miracles.'' The concert, at 2:30 p.m. at the Westbury Library on Jefferson Street, is just one of several programs today marking Valentine's Day.</p>
        <p>At Chelsea Center on Northern Boulevard in East Norwich, the first of a ''Sunday Afternoon Tea Series'' will be devoted to ''How to Make Your Home Romantic.'' Along with a cuppa, the how-to's will be dispensed at 12:30 p.m. (516) 571-8550. In ''A Celebration of Love,'' at the Wheatley Plaza in Greenvale, Scott Rella, an ice sculptor, will carve a love seat flanked by life-sized harps, cherubs, cupids and gargoyles, from noon to 4 p.m. (516) 627-2277. Also today, ''Valentine's Day Traditions,'' an exhibition of valentines sent to Sally Townsend, who lived in Raynham Hall during the Revolutionary War, will be featured from 1 to 5 p.m. at the museum on West Main Street in Oyster Bay (516) 922-6808.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow, Seena Edelman will perform ''Hollywood's Beautiful Love Songs'' at 1 p.m. at the Levittown Library on Bluegrass Lane (516) 731-5728. On Tuesday, the Island Poets will provide ''An Evening of Love Poems'' at 7:30 p.m. at Barnes and Noble on Jericho Turnpike in Commack. (631) 462-0896.</p>
        <p>All That Jazz</p>
        <p>With four concerts on tap this week, jazz reigns on the Island. Today ''Jazz Revelations,'' the series at St. John's Episcopal Church, South Franklin Street in Hempstead, has the schedule to itself. And Gwen Cleveland, vocalist, and Her Quartet, with Bubba Brooks on tenor sax, Bross Townsend on piano, John Dooley on bass and Tootsie Bean on drums, will perform at 3 p.m. (516) 538-4750. Come Friday, audiences will have to chose between Boney James, the jazz saxophonist, who appears at 8 and 10:30 p.m. at the Inter Media Art Center on New York Avenue in Huntington (631) 549-9666, and Ramsey Lewis, the pianist, who plays at 8 p.m. at Tilles Center on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville (516) 299-3100. On Saturday, the Jazz Alliance performs in a free concert at the Harborfields Library on Broadway on Greenlawn (631) 757-4200.</p>
        <p>Horne Coaches</p>
        <p>Marilyn Horne, the opera diva, has been devoting her retirement days to helping young opera singers perfect their art and craft. In her master classes, she tutors the singers in ''dos and don'ts'' and, with a mix of love, candor, humor and spontaneous inspiration, critiques their efforts. She brings her master class to Long Island for the first time on Tuesday, appearing with a group of advanced singers like Lee Poulis, a baritone from Huntington, at 8 p.m. at the Landmark on Main Street in Port Washington (516) 767-1384.</p>
        <p>'Dinosaurs 2000'</p>
        <p>For adults and children who never tire of dinosaurs, the place to be through Labor Day is the Sands Point Preserve. Yes, the robotic fellows are back in ''Dinosaurs 2000.'' Displayed in realistic diorama settings, the show stars such creatures as the Coelophysis from the Triassic Period, Apatosaurus (Brontosaurus), Stegosaurus and Archaepteryx from the Jurassic Period and Triceratops, Ankylosaurus and Pteranodon from the Cretaceous Period. The show can be seen from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tuesdays through Sundays at the preserve off Middle Neck Road (516) 571-7900.</p>
        <p>'Sundays at Seven'</p>
        <p>''Sundays at Seven,'' the series of ''art happenings'' the second and fourth Sundays of each month at the Northport Historical Museum that provide a venue for the various arts, begins its fifth season today with ''600 Pounds of Sound.'' In ''A Day in the Life of a Long Island Music Production Company,'' with Bob Westcott as host, James Yarsky, Mark Hubbard and Tom Griffith will tell about Coconut Grove, a recording studio in Huntington. And yes, on a scale together the three company men weigh 600 pounds. The program is at 7 p.m. at the museum on Main Street (631) 757-9859.</p>
        <p>Beethoven's 'Ode'</p>
        <p>Beethoven's Symphony No. 9 (''Ode to Joy'') gets a major treatment today in Rockville Centre when choir members from the village's churches and synagogues join forces with the South Shore Symphony and soloists like Carol Atmore, soprano; Patricia Steiner, alto; James R. Guthrie, tenor; and Steven Frederick, bass, to create the masterpiece. Under the batons of Scott Jackson Wiley, conductor, and Michael Bower, co-director of Music at St. Agnes, the concert is at 7:30 p.m. at St. Agnes Cathedral on Quealy Place (516) 764-1558.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- ''Baroque Sundays at Three'' returns with ''The Art of the Baroque Violin,'' a concert of virtuoso string music from France, Germany and Italy. Amie Roosevelt, an alumna of the State University at Stony Brook, and her chamber group will do the honors at Staller Center's Recital Hall on the Stony Brook campus (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>To mark Black History Month, the Long Island String Quartet plays light classics, including excerpts from ''Porgy and Bess'' sung by Albert Rhodes, at 3 p.m. at Salten Hall on the Old Westbury campus of the New York Institute of Technology (516) 686-7640.</p>
        <p>Joshua Ruff, the history curator at the Museums at Stony Brook, offers a slide-lecture on ''Lighthouses of Long Island'' at a meeting of the Nassau County Historical Society at 2:30 p.m. at the Community Church of East Williston on Roslyn Road (516) 538-7679.</p>
        <p>TOMORROW -- Singled out among 4,000 entries in a national student art contest sponsored by the United States Department of Energy, three Long Island youngsters will get their just rewards at 10 a.m. during a reception at Brookhaven National Laboratory. Debbie Goodman and Jessica Miller, fourth graders, and Elana Taubman (one of 30 finalists), fifth grader, of the Lindell School in Long Beach produced 3 of the top 100 entries in ''Energy Millennium: Honor the Past; Imagine the Future'' and their works will be shown with the 97 others through Feb. 29 at the lab's Berkner Hall on William Floyd Parkway in Upton (631) 344-8350.</p>
        <p>Under the auspices of the Museum of the Universe, which local astronomers hope to create one day, the Book Revue on New York Avenue in Huntington is offering a series of monthly ''Astronomy Roundtables'' dealing with new astronomy books. The first under discussion, during a waxing Gibbons moon, is ''The Moons of Jupiter: From Galileo to Galileo'' by Dr. Robert Pappalardo. Following the talk at 8 p.m. ''sidewalk astronomers'' from the museum will have telescopes set up for viewing (631) 582-6688.</p>
        <p>FRIDAY -- The ''Cinema Classics'' series at the Half Hollow Hills Library in Dix Hills turns to Alfred Hitchcock's ''To Catch a Thief'' at 7:30 p.m. at the library on Vanderbilt Parkway (631) 421-4530.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- The winners of the Sixth Annual Reading Rainbow Young Writers and Illustrators Awards Contest sponsored by WLIW21 will be announced during ''Reading Fun Day'' from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. at Roosevelt Field's fountain area. Celebrities like Darlene Love, singer; Chris Burke, actor; ''Magic'' Al Garber; and a member of the New York Liberty women's basketball team will be on hand to read from their favorite works, while characters from ''Dittydoodle Works'' and ''Zebby's Zoo'' entertain (516) 367-2100, extension 3032.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
