<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Banks Pledge $6 Billion To Aid Bid by A.T.&amp;T.</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="407657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NCR CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN TELEPHONE &amp; TELEGRAPH CO INC (AT&amp;T)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAPIRO, EBEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB103DF932A25751C1A966958260" item-length="554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Banks Pledge $6 Billion To Aid Bid by A.T.&amp;T.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EBEN SHAPIRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHAPIRO, EBEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A.T.&amp; T.'s hostile bid to acquire the NCR Corporation received the endorsement of the banking community yesterday, as more than 50 American and foreign banks agreed to provide financing.</p>
        <p>The American Telephone and Telegraph Company said its request for commitments for the $6 billion package that Chemical Bank is putting together was "substantially oversubscribed." Chemical, which is leading the financing syndicate, is providing $600 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A.T.&amp; T.'s hostile bid to acquire the NCR Corporation received the endorsement of the banking community yesterday, as more than 50 American and foreign banks agreed to provide financing.</p>
        <p>The American Telephone and Telegraph Company said its request for commitments for the $6 billion package that Chemical Bank is putting together was "substantially oversubscribed." Chemical, which is leading the financing syndicate, is providing $600 million.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp; T. officials were clearly delighted by the banks' response. The company's treasurer, S. Lawrence Prendergast, said, "It indicates their belief in the financial soundness of A.T.&amp; T.'s offer." He added that about half of the commitments were from foreign institutions.  NCR Shares Drop</p>
        <p>Despite the ease with which A.T.&amp; T. obtained financing, NCR's stock drifted lower for the second consecutive session, as traders said a prolonged takeover struggle now appeared more likely.</p>
        <p>On the New York Stock Exchange, NCR stock closed down 50 cents, at $91.25, after trading as low as $89.75. The stock rallied after the bank financing was announced. A.T.&amp; T closed unchanged at $29.875.</p>
        <p>NCR's chairman, Charles E. Exley Jr., has said the company is not for sale for less than $125 a share. "It almost seems like he is looking forward to a protracted battle," Kathy Rold, an arbitrager, said. "There is not going to be the instant gratification that everybody expected last week."</p>
        <p>But Jack Grubman, an analyst with Paine Webber, said NCR and A.T.&amp; T. would come to terms "in a matter of weeks rather than months."</p>
        <p>Under Federal securities law, the NCR board must formally respond to the phone company's $90-a-share cash offer by Dec. 19.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp; T. said that it was considering several options to raise the capital for the acquisition, including short-term borrowing in the form of promissory notes that would be backed by the bank group loan.</p>
        <p>"We will probably use the private placement market to some extent," Mr. Prendergast said. A.T.&amp; T. can also tap into the $6 billion directly.</p>
        <p>Some banks have a policy against financing hostile takeovers of big customers. In an attempt to overcome such objections, A.T.&amp; T. executives have told some bankers that the deal will eventually turn friendly.</p>
        <p>Citibank, which banking sources said declined to participate in the A.T.&amp; T. loan, has such a policy. "We will not actively particapte in a hostile takeover of a good customer," said Anne Luzzatto, a Citibank spokeswoman. Both NCR and A.T.&amp; T. are Citibank customers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prendergast said only a few banks had declined because of such conflicts. Bonus Offer</p>
        <p>In an inducement to get the financing in place quickly, Chemical and A.T.&amp; T. offered a bonus to banks that made commitments by noon yesterday. The deadline for commitments was Dec. 14. But because the credit facility was oversubscribed, the syndicate's books were closed yesterday.</p>
        <p>NCR won a legal victory yesterday when Federal District Judge Frederic N. Smalkin in Baltimore dismissed a suit filed by A.T.&amp; T. The action sought a declaratory judgment that if A.T.&amp; T. began a proxy fight, it would not activate a Maryland law that would prevent the companies from merging for five years if the takeover is successful. NCR is based in Dayton, Ohio, but is incorporated in Maryland.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
