<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Home Abroad; 'To Thine Own Self Be True'</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">POWELL, COLIN L (GEN) (RET)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D91130F930A15753C1A963958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Home Abroad; 'To Thine Own Self Be True'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Colin Powell craze has crossed the Atlantic. When he signed books in London, The Times had front-page stories on successive days, describing him as "the clear opinion poll favorite to be the next President." Joe Rogaly, the astute Financial Times columnist, writing of the general's significance for racial attitudes, said his election "would change humanity where change matters most, inside its head."</p>
        <p>General Powell himself, by all signs, wants to go for it. The question is how. And there he faces what could be a fatal temptation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Colin Powell craze has crossed the Atlantic. When he signed books in London, The Times had front-page stories on successive days, describing him as "the clear opinion poll favorite to be the next President." Joe Rogaly, the astute Financial Times columnist, writing of the general's significance for racial attitudes, said his election "would change humanity where change matters most, inside its head."</p>
        <p>General Powell himself, by all signs, wants to go for it. The question is how. And there he faces what could be a fatal temptation.</p>
        <p>"Powell Changes Tone to Appeal to Conservatives," a headline said the other day. That is the temptation for General Powell: to trim his beliefs, if he seeks the Republican nomination, in order to please the conservatives who dominate the party today.</p>
        <p>On "CBS This Morning" last week, General Powell said "the Republican route is easiest" if he decides to run. "I mean, there's a structure; there's a party; there's financing."</p>
        <p>His comments on issues in that broadcast sounded to some as if he were trying to please conservatives. He said: "The religious right has to be given credit for focusing our attention again on the fact that we are a nation under God, focusing attention on the family. . . . Many of the positions they take I fully support."</p>
        <p>He had said similar things before, and he added the caveat: "Where I've had some differences is how you translate that into actual public policy and amending the Constitution or the enactment of law." But his phraseology did seem more deferential to Pat Robertson's Christian Coalition.</p>
        <p>On abortion, he flatly disagreed with the Christian right: When a woman faces the choice, he said, "I think she has to have control over her own destiny, her own body."</p>
        <p>At this point, he said, he did not favor government funding of abortions. But he added that he "would want to think about that some more, because there are women in circumstances where they are forced to a choice because they can't afford any other choice."</p>
        <p>General Powell denied that his words were an attempt to cater to Republican conservatives. But they were seen as such by some people, and that points to a great danger for him if he does become a candidate.</p>
        <p>Colin Powell's fundamental attraction for American voters is that he is a straight arrow who says what he thinks regardless of the consequences -- "a plain blunt man," in Shakespeare's phrase. He is admired not for his particular views on issues but for his steadfast character.</p>
        <p>Americans have a profound distaste these days for politicians who trim in order to please everyone. We have just had two grotesque examples: President Clinton disavowing his own tax legislation and then saying he didn't mean the disavowal and Senator Bob Dole saying the return of a campaign contribution from gay Republicans was a mistake.</p>
        <p>If General Powell slips into that style, he will lose much of his appeal. He surely knows that. He knows that Dwight Eisenhower sullied himself by deferring to Joe McCarthy and cutting praise for Gen. George C. Marshall from a Wisconsin campaign speech. Eisenhower and Marshall are General Powell's heroes.</p>
        <p>But the pressures to trim will be severe if he goes for the Republican nomination. It will be odd, anyway, for someone who has called himself a "Rockefeller Republican" to be the nominee of Pat Robertson's Republican Party, or Newt Gingrich's. Some right-wing Republicans, seeking a sure winner, favor General Powell. Others are extremely unhappy at the prospect, and are saying so.</p>
        <p>The way to avoid the problem would be for General Powell to run as an independent. He said on CBS: "It's never been done as an independent, but I don't dismiss it yet."</p>
        <p>I think the political experts who say that he could not raise the necessary money as an independent, or get over the hurdle of state election laws, are wrong. One of the top advertising executives in the country said recently that he could put together a team, instantly, to do all the media work for an independent Powell candidacy and handle its legal problems.</p>
        <p>But as a Republican or an independent, Colin Powell will be a viable candidate only if he remains himself, if he says: Here I am; I am not going to change to get your vote.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
