<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parties Shift Budget Debate to How Proposals Affect Children</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D7153FF930A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parties Shift Budget Debate to How Proposals Affect Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After weeks of attacking the Republican budget in the name of the elderly, the Democrats are shifting tactics and arguing that the country's children will suffer unduly if all the spending cuts become law. Not to be outdone, the Republicans are countering that their programs would benefit the young in the long run.</p>
        <p>But in this argument, many economists side with the Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After weeks of attacking the Republican budget in the name of the elderly, the Democrats are shifting tactics and arguing that the country's children will suffer unduly if all the spending cuts become law. Not to be outdone, the Republicans are countering that their programs would benefit the young in the long run.</p>
        <p>But in this argument, many economists side with the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Speaker Newt Gingrich gave a preview of the Republican position in a speech on Thursday night, saying a vote to curb Medicare spending would halt the rise in the national debt, saving today's children from paying unbearable taxes in the future.</p>
        <p>But legislating for posterity by reducing the deficit and thereby reducing future taxes mostly helps children who grow up to become jobholders and taxpayers.</p>
        <p>Many economists do say that reducing the deficit now could lead to faster economic growth and, eventually, more jobs and a higher overall standard of living for today's children. But most of these economists also say the specific spending cuts in the Republican plans would fall very heavily on poor and lower-middle-class children today, leaving them less able to hold jobs in the years ahead. These poor and lower-middle-class children are the net losers even when the effects of higher long-term growth and more jobs are included.</p>
        <p>The Democrats will promote their children-first arguments in a campaign that is to begin with a visit by Hillary Rodham Clinton to a children's hospital in New York on Monday morning. That same day the White House will release an economic analysis of the effect of the Republican budget proposals on children. Throughout the week Cabinet officials will fan out across the country giving speeches portraying Republicans as politicians willing to steal children's school lunches and ignore their medical needs.</p>
        <p>One Administration official said the theme will be, "You can balance the budget for children without balancing the budget on the backs of the children."</p>
        <p>Republicans are not waiting for the Democratic assault. Mr. Gingrich has scheduled a visit on Monday to the Boys Town orphanage in Nebraska, which he praised last year as a model of private charity replacing Government in caring for the poor.</p>
        <p>The Republicans' planned cuts affecting low-income families with children would be substantial. At a time when a quarter of the nation's children live in poverty, the Republicans propose to cut projected spending on welfare, including the Aid to Families With Dependent Children program, turning that program into block grants to state governments. House Republicans are also calling for spending freezes or cuts for programs that maintain minimum health and nutrition standards for children and provide preschool education for young children in poor families.</p>
        <p>The White House recently calculated that the poorest fifth of American families with children would lose an average of $1,521 a year in income and $1,662 a year in health benefits under Republican plans. These are families with an average annual income of $13,325.</p>
        <p>To present themselves as defenders of children, Republicans have emphasized their $500-a-child tax credit. "It is real," said Senator Frank H. Murkowski, Republican of Alaska. "It will help families with children and be very, very meaningful."</p>
        <p>But the tax credit would do little to help children in low-income households. Families that have no Federal income tax liability after other exemptions and deductions would not be eligible for refunds.</p>
        <p>For example, a family of four with both parents working and both children in child care programs would not qualify for the credit if it earned less than $24,000 in 1996. The Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, a liberal Washington research group with a reputation for accurate statistics, has calculated that 23.7 million children, or 34 percent of the nation's children, live in families too poor to qualify for the credit. Another 7.1 million children, or 10 percent, would qualify only for a partial credit.</p>
        <p>The real winners from the Republican tax and budget plans are likely to be affluent children, who receive relatively little direct Federal spending but will have to pay much of the taxes for the national debt that today's adults leave behind. According to Congressional Budget Office figures, Federal budget deficits would total $1.35 trillion more over the next decade under President Clinton's plan to balance the budget in 10 years than they would under the Republican plan to balance it over 7 years.</p>
        <p>Braking growth in the debt will hold down net interest payments on the debt, which have already risen to 15.3 percent of the Federal budget from 8.9 percent in 1980.</p>
        <p>"It does seem pretty clear that those who will gain over the longer term will be those who would be paying the taxes," said Alan J. Auerbach, a professor of economics and law at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Economists differ sharply about whether the proposed spending cuts would foster or impede economic growth by the time today's children are adults. Clinton Administration officials make the case that the Republicans are eliminating so many educational and training programs that they will hurt future growth, and the Administration plans to distribute a list of academic articles on Monday supporting that position.</p>
        <p>"Those programs have a very high rate of return to the society and therefore are justified against other forms of investment," said Martin N. Baily, a member of President Clinton's Council of Economic Advisers.</p>
        <p>But most economists take the view that cutting the budget deficit will in general help future economic growth and children, by leaving money to be invested productively in the private sector instead of collecting it as taxes. "There would be a net benefit over the lifetime of young people, but not necessarily to everybody," said Robert D. Reischauer, the former director of the Congressional Budget Office. "What you're looking at is a situation in which, disproportionately, children in low-income homes would be contributing to the deficit reduction effort."</p>
        <p>While paying few of the costs of deficit reduction, affluent children would benefit at least as much as poor children from a bigger economy. To the extent that poor children are less educated or even less nourished during their formative years, they will prove less able to compete for good jobs with the children of affluent families.</p>
        <p>Advocates for children condemn that possibility as unacceptable, and some question the view of budget experts that the economy will grow more with the Republican budget plans. "It's very anti-family, anti-young family," said James D. Weill, the general counsel of the Children's Defense Fund, a liberal group in Washington. "If you cut the deficit by trashing the programs that you need to have children that are healthy and well nourished, the offsetting effects on the economy will hurt growth and in the long run hurt efforts to control Government spending and deficits."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
