<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kosar And Crew Are Kept In Check</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MIAMI DOLPHINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DE1E38F930A15753C1A963958260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kosar And Crew Are Kept In Check</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernie Kosar is not the best quarterback in the National Football League, not even the best on the Miami Dolphins when Dan Marino is healthy. But Kosar is certainly one of the most upbeat, so the pained look on his face was out of character.</p>
        <p>There was good reason. The Jets had just upset Kosar and the Dolphins, 17-16, today at Giants Stadium, and Kosar was trying to dress and leave the scene of a disillusioning game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bernie Kosar is not the best quarterback in the National Football League, not even the best on the Miami Dolphins when Dan Marino is healthy. But Kosar is certainly one of the most upbeat, so the pained look on his face was out of character.</p>
        <p>There was good reason. The Jets had just upset Kosar and the Dolphins, 17-16, today at Giants Stadium, and Kosar was trying to dress and leave the scene of a disillusioning game.</p>
        <p>"The team feels horrible and I feel horrible," he said. "I'm discouraged that we lost. I'm discouraged with myself."</p>
        <p>At the same time, Kosar praised the Jets' defensive scheme.</p>
        <p>"We couldn't get downfield," he said, "because they were playing a soft zone and dropping their linebackers deep. That requires the front four to put on a good rush, and they did that. I thought we would do a better job against it."</p>
        <p>So did Don Shula, the Dolphins' coach.</p>
        <p>"I'm disappointed that we haven't been able to make the plays in the fourth quarter when we've needed them," Shula said.</p>
        <p>Late in the fourth quarter, when the Dolphins trailed by a point but seemed to have the game in reach, they foiled themselves when Kosar was intercepted by Curtis Joseph and Victor Green. The first interception came with 2 minutes 24 seconds left, after Mike Williams of the Dolphins had run a 12-yard curl route.</p>
        <p>"We had man coverage," Kosar said. "It was a timing route, and Mike slipped."</p>
        <p>With Williams on the ground, the ball went right to Joseph, the Jets' rookie cornerback, on the Jets' 20-yard line. He returned it 39 yards and out of danger.</p>
        <p>"That was nice," Joseph said, "but I wasn't celebrating. There were still two minutes to go and anything could happen."</p>
        <p>Anything did. Only 35 seconds later, after a Jets punt, the Dolphins had the ball again, on their 20. And 42 seconds after that, the Dolphins were on the Jets' 37, almost in the comfort zone of their field-goal kicker, Pete Stoyanovich.</p>
        <p>On the sideline, Stoyanovich was kicking into a net, waiting for the moment he could win the game. The Jets defense did not let it happen. Kosar dropped back and was hounded by Hugh Douglas, the Jets' rookie defensive end. Kosar slipped away, but Douglas pursued and was about to level him when Kosar got off a pass to O. J. McDuffie.</p>
        <p>"The ball looked wobbly," said Green, a safety guarding McDuffie in the Jets' nickel defense. "It came right to me. Then, finally, I knew we had the game."</p>
        <p>And then, finally, the Dolphins knew they had real problems. They had won their first four games of the season, starting with a 52-14 rout of the Jets in Miami. Then they lost by 3 points in overtime to the Indianapolis Colts, 3 points to the then 0-5 New Orleans Saints and now by a point to the Jets.</p>
        <p>Marino has missed the last two games after arthroscopic knee surgery. The Dolphins expect him to play next Sunday against the resurgent Buffalo Bills.</p>
        <p>No Dolphin seemed to take the loss harder than Bryan Cox, the volatile middle linebacker.</p>
        <p>"You don't think how good you're supposed to be," he said. "You don't think about winning titles. We've got to start playing football. We've got to ask: 'What's happening to us? How can we change?'</p>
        <p>"Bernie did a good job today. We haven't helped him at all. Neither of the last two losses has fallen on him. It's us, the defense. Turnovers are what we get paid for. Things aren't bad, but they're not good."</p>
        <p>They are certainly not good when the Dolphins lose to the Jets, whose only previous victim was the expansion Jacksonville Jaguars. But Cox said the Jets, bad record and all, should not be dismissed.</p>
        <p>"I wouldn't call this loss embarrassing," he said, "because they are an N.F.L. team. There are no bad teams in this league."</p>
        <p>Maybe, wide receiver Irving Fryar said, the Dolphins can draw something positive from this loss. "This will stop everyone from talking about going to the Super Bowl now," he said. "We can start concentrating on one game at a time. Maybe our focus will be a little bit better now."  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
