<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BMW M5: It's Nice To Drive the King</title>
    <meta content="25SERG$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/25/automobiles/25SERG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">BMW</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFDE123AF936A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BMW M5: It's Nice To Drive the King</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">BMW M5: It's Nice To Drive the King</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serge Schmemann evaluates BMW M5 sedan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF everything seems under control,'' Mario Andretti once declared, ''you're just not going fast enough.'' That is a risky proposition to apply to the BMW M5. Most of the time I was in a gleaming black version of same, everything seemed so under control that I repeatedly ended up going far too fast.</p>
        <p>If I had to choose just one among the M5's many amenities, it would have to be the humble cruise control, to make sure that I kept my driver's license. This is a car so powerful, so sophisticated, so lithe, that it is otherwise almost impossible to keep it down to something as mundane as 75 miles an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is a car so powerful, so sophisticated, so lithe, that it is almost impossible to keep it down to something as mundane as 75 miles an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF everything seems under control,'' Mario Andretti once declared, ''you're just not going fast enough.'' That is a risky proposition to apply to the BMW M5. Most of the time I was in a gleaming black version of same, everything seemed so under control that I repeatedly ended up going far too fast.</p>
        <p>If I had to choose just one among the M5's many amenities, it would have to be the humble cruise control, to make sure that I kept my driver's license. This is a car so powerful, so sophisticated, so lithe, that it is otherwise almost impossible to keep it down to something as mundane as 75 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>Let's try a controversial assessment: the M5 may be the best sedan on the road. I can hear the protests -- what about the Bentley Arnage with its extraordinary comfort, or the Mercedes S600 with its extraordinary electronics or the Mercedes E55 AMG with its scalding power? In this rarified company, ''best'' needs to be carefully defined in terms of speed, power, comfort, utility or sophistication. I might agree, for one thing, that this much power and agility are simply too much for American roads.</p>
        <p>But how else would you classify a sedan that has every luxury small and large, weighs more than two tons, yet holds its own against a Corvette or a Porsche 911 Carrera? All right, it's not nearly as spacious as a Cadillac DeVille -- the E.P.A. actually classifies the M5 as a compact sedan -- or even its own 7-Series siblings. But there's simply nothing else out there that drives quite like this, yet still caters so richly to our decadence.</p>
        <p>I piloted my black beauty, with its saddle-brown upholstery, over close to 1,000 miles of Interstate highway, Canadian back roads and the Taconic Parkway of upstate New York. On one particularly sinewy northern stretch of the Taconic, two lesser Bimmers fell in and we snaked along in close formation for mile after beautiful mile at speeds double the posted limit, smiling like children let loose in Toys ''R'' Us, my trusty Valentine One radar detector sweeping the horizon for spoilsports.</p>
        <p>It caught one strong scent. We jabbed our brakes and watched with genuine sadness as a trooper turned on the 97 strobe lights on his roof and behind his grille -- why is a single flashing light enough everywhere else in the world? -- and pounced on a relatively innocent yellow Toyota.</p>
        <p>Oh, and those curvy, hilly Canadian back roads! Though the low-profile tires and sporty suspension let you know just how much damage the northern winter does to asphalt, the machine stayed unflappably level and willing. Steering, brakes, clutch and shifter blended in perfect harmony, so that the M5 seemed actually to enjoy the ride, egging me on to yet another, quicker downshift here, a deeper jab on the throttle there. And it rewarded particularly agile maneuvers with what sounded like a deep, virile purr.</p>
        <p>So what is the M5? Basically, it's the midsize 5-Series BMW four-door transformed by the zealots at Motorsport, the supertuner division of BMW (and the ''M'' in the M5) charged with turning ''ultimate driving machines'' into whatever lies beyond ultimate. They have been doing this since the 1980's, consistently adding more horsepower, torque and electronics. The current model was unchained for the 2000 model year, its heart a 4.9-liter V-8 with 32 variably timed valves, its brain an electronic marvel that, among many things, manages a state-of-the-art electronic throttle. The muscle is fed through a Getrag six-speed to wide 18-inch wheels hanging from an aluminum sport suspension and gas-pressure shocks.</p>
        <p>But to conclude that size is the key is to miss the point about what makes this car great. Perusing the literature about the M5 is a trip through the exotic edge of automotive technology -- German technology, to give credit where it is due. The oil system, for example, is linked to the Dynamic Stability Control computer to make sure that all eight pistons are bathed in cooling oil no matter how hard the car corners. Air reaching the cylinders doesn't get there through a single throttle body, as on common engines, but through eight separate, electronically controlled throttle butterflies. These and countless other electronic gizmos work seamlessly to direct the car precisely where the driver wants it, and sometimes to give the illusion that the machine anticipates the driver's intent.</p>
        <p>Inside, the M5 is everything a $70,000 chariot should be, and there are wonderful heated power seats. I had a few nits; the most frustrating was that the steering wheel, once adjusted comfortably, concealed the top of the instruments.</p>
        <p>From without, few bells or whistles announce the M5, so that it is hard to distinguish it from other 5-Series sedans. Such understatement is an indelible part of the German auto ethic. German cars are traditionally identified by a few letters and numbers -- S500, 325i, A8 and the like -- often determined partly by the engine displacement. But even that is too much for many Germans, who order their cars without the badges, as if to say that the money they are spending reflects solely a passion for the machinery and not the status (or, in a few Philistine instances, to conceal that they got the cheapest version).</p>
        <p>If truth be told, those who need to know, do know. Few German aficionados would miss the matched pairs of tailpipes, the beautiful wheels or the blue-and-red ''M' badges that identify the very best.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK:  The best sedan you can drive, until you lose your license.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
