<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Somber Notes From the Underground: A Folk Music Landmark Faces Uncertainty</title>
    <meta content="25POST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/25/nyregion/thecity/25POST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345811"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MORNINGSIDE HEIGHTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Folk Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Postcrypt Coffeehouse (Nyc)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brune, Adrian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coffeehouses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Folk Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffeehouses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Columbia</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Loeb, Lisa</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDF173AF936A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Somber Notes From the Underground: A Folk Music Landmark Faces Uncertainty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Somber Notes From the Underground: A Folk Music Landmark Faces Uncertainty</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADRIAN BRUNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brune, Adrian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Postcrypt Coffeehouse in basement of Columbia University's St Paul's Chapel, where folk musicians have been playing for tips for nearly 40 years, is found to be in violation of city codes and may have to close; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beneath the stained glass windows and mahogany pews of St. Paul's Chapel at  Columbia University, Rebecca Josephson and Adrienne Baranowicz filed into the basement crypt to practice their weekly ritual: devotion to the guitar-strumming patron saints of folk music.</p>
        <p>The two Columbia students are among the dozen followers of a tradition that has existed at the university for nearly 40 years. They help run Postcrypt Coffeehouse, where twice a week a folk show takes place in the chapel's candle-lighted, acoustically perfect brick crypt. An hour before the music starts -- the headliner this night is Edie Carey, a Barnard graduate -- they set up chairs and tables for an intimate audience of 25, stock the refrigerator with Rolling Rock and put up water for tea and instant coffee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beneath the stained glass windows and mahogany pews of St. Paul's Chapel at Columbia University, Rebecca Josephson and Adrienne Baranowicz filed into the basement crypt to practice their weekly ritual: devotion to the guitar-strumming patron saints of folk music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beneath the stained glass windows and mahogany pews of St. Paul's Chapel at  Columbia University, Rebecca Josephson and Adrienne Baranowicz filed into the basement crypt to practice their weekly ritual: devotion to the guitar-strumming patron saints of folk music.</p>
        <p>The two Columbia students are among the dozen followers of a tradition that has existed at the university for nearly 40 years. They help run Postcrypt Coffeehouse, where twice a week a folk show takes place in the chapel's candle-lighted, acoustically perfect brick crypt. An hour before the music starts -- the headliner this night is Edie Carey, a Barnard graduate -- they set up chairs and tables for an intimate audience of 25, stock the refrigerator with Rolling Rock and put up water for tea and instant coffee.</p>
        <p>''Upon visiting the Postcrypt, most alumni comment on how little it has changed over the years,'' said Andy Stevens, a student worker. The original stage survives, as does the mosaic bar, and the strange wooden box with the word ''Postcrypt'' hand-lettered in Gothic script above one door.</p>
        <p>But the space is facing difficult days. When a water main broke in the spring, firefighters discovered code violations, including candles in wine bottles instead of votive candles. In September the students were told they might have to find a new place to meet.</p>
        <p>The administration proposed moving performances to J. J.'s Place, an on-campus dining facility, or to a lounge in a residence hall. When the students refused to budge, the administration restricted seating at the Postcrypt to 25 people, including the performer and three snack-bar workers.</p>
        <p>The Columbia administration now monitors the space, even though no accidents have occurred in the coffeehouse. ''We know that if we cannot remain within the administration's parameters, we can get closed down,'' Ms. Baranowicz said.</p>
        <p>Because Postcrypt makes all its money on the sale of refreshments, the move could force the coffeehouse to close its doors or  charge admission. For now, Postcrypt just breaks even, with a typical audience of about 20.</p>
        <p>''We do not want to change Postcrypt's history as a free music venue,'' Ms. Baranowicz said. ''That would change the essence of Postcrypt, just as changing venues would.'' The only payment the musicians  receive is from a tip jar that is passed around.</p>
        <p>Most performers are happy to play for little money just to play the crypt. They consider the acoustics so good for guitar and  voice that they don't even need a microphone.</p>
        <p>The dozens of acoustic performers who have appeared at Postcrypt include Ani DiFranco, Lisa Loeb, Jeff Buckley, Martin Sexton and Suzanne Vega, a Barnard alumna. If Postcrypt abandoned its basement for the white walls and vending machines of a student lounge, its workers fear that it would lose many of the current artists, who come to partake of Postcrypt's tradition and intimacy.</p>
        <p>Ms. Carey said: ''In a place like Postcrypt, you feel like you are playing your songs for the first time again, because everyone listens so intently. The words suddenly seem to have new meaning. And the candles. I really like the candles.''</p>
        <p>ADRIAN BRUNE</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MORNINGSIDE HEIGHTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
