<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Question Box</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D61E39F935A35752C0A964958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Question Box</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ray Corio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yount Nears Milestone</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>How close is Robin Yount to reaching 3,000 hits in his major league career?</p>
        <p>A. Closer than any other active player, and close enough to count on baseball issuing a "Robin Yount Countdown" shortly before the outfielder's 37th birthday next Sept. 16. The Milwaukee Brewers' star will enter the 1992 season with 2,878 hits for his 18-year career, which means he needs just 122 to join a group of 16 players that embraced Rod Carew as its most recent member in 1985.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yount Nears Milestone</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>How close is Robin Yount to reaching 3,000 hits in his major league career?</p>
        <p>A. Closer than any other active player, and close enough to count on baseball issuing a "Robin Yount Countdown" shortly before the outfielder's 37th birthday next Sept. 16. The Milwaukee Brewers' star will enter the 1992 season with 2,878 hits for his 18-year career, which means he needs just 122 to join a group of 16 players that embraced Rod Carew as its most recent member in 1985.</p>
        <p>Right now, Yount stands 26th on the hit list, between Frankie Frisch and Mel Ott. Since he rapped out 131 hits in 130 games last season and has averaged 160 hits a season for his career, only a prolonged injury would prevent Yount from clearing the 3,000 barrier sometime late next season. Once there, the future is secure, for among those with 3,000 or more hits, no player other than the ineligible Pete Rose has failed to be voted into the Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Notre Dame Passers</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>How many quarterbacks at Notre Dame have been voted all-Americans?</p>
        <p>A. Almost an offensive team full, with 10 earning the consensus honors of several selection groups, ranging from Gus Dorais in 1913 to Terry Hanratty in 1968. In between, with the years selected, were, in order: Harry Stuhldreher (1924, along with two of the other Four Horsemen); Frank Carideo (1929 and 1930), Angelo Bertelli (1943), Johnny Lujack (1946 and 1947), Bob Williams (1949), Ralph Guglielmi (1954), Paul Hornung (1956) and John Huarte (1964).</p>
        <p>Four of these passers -- Bertelli, Lujack, Hornung and Huarte -- also were winners of the Heisman Trophy, awarded since 1935 to college football's outstanding player. Oddly, a couple of guys named Joe -- Theismann and Montana -- failed to draw much all-America support while calling the signals for the Irish, but reaped mounds of praise as Super Bowl winning pros with Washington and San Francisco, respectively.</p>
        <p>Year of the 2-Pointer</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>When did college football begin the 2-point conversion?</p>
        <p>A. Next fall will mark the 35th season a college coach has had the option of having his team run or pass for 2 points from the 3-yard line after a touchdown or of merely attempting a placekick for 1 point. Before the 1958 rule expansion, the National Collegiate Athletic Association had not changed the scoring in football since 1912, when the value of a touchdown was inflated from 5 points to 6 points (and the value of a forward pass was considered nil by most coaches).</p>
        <p>Year of the Face Mask</p>
        <p>Q. When did the face mask become part of college football?</p>
        <p>A. Last fall marked the 40th anniversary of the legalization of the face mask for college players. In 1957, a penalty was imposed for grabbing the face mask. Which means that for six years, players could yank at each other with an in-your-face style and pretty much get away with it.</p>
        <p>The Old Puck Game</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>In The New York Times Sunday Sports section on Dec. 29, a listing of 1991 winners included Sweden as the world champion in bandy. What's bandy?</p>
        <p>A. Think of ice hockey with a ball or field hockey on skates or soccer with sticks and you're in the ball park, or at least on the rink, which is the playing area for bandy. The game, with 11 players to a side including a goalkeeper with no stick, originated in the colder regions of England about 200 years ago, according to the International Dictionary of Sports and Games. But it has become more popularized during the winter months in such ice-laden areas as the Baltic States, the Netherlands, Russia, Mongolia and the Scandinavian countries (hence Sweden's reign in 1991).</p>
        <p>Bandy players skate on what amounts to an ice-covered soccer field with a border. There are two 45-minute halves, and the ball, sometimes as red as the players' cheeks, is somewhere between a field hockey ball and a golf ball in size. Players may stop it with their skates and even kick it, but only the goalkeeper can handle it as he defends a net almost identical to the one in hockey.</p>
        <p>Like hockey, there are penalties and face-offs and offsides and even ejections. The sticks also are similar to those in hockey and are curved inwards. Like bandy legs, which is how the sport got its name.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions concerning any aspect of sport: statistics or strategies, rules or records. The address is Question Box, SportsMonday, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions not published cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
