<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rules Forcing Towns to Pick Big New Dumps or Big Costs</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANDFILL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARBAGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF123DF935A35752C0A964958260" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rules Forcing Towns to Pick Big New Dumps or Big Costs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>LUVERNE, Ala.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Federal and state rules are forcing the closing of hundreds of old community garbage dumps and prompting the development of many fewer, but much larger landfills that only the biggest cities and the largest garbage companies can afford to build and operate.</p>
        <p>And residents of thousands of small communities, like this one south of Montgomery, will be forced to choose the revenue and heavy truck traffic of a new nearby landfill or the huge increase in costs of transporting their garbage far away. What is definite, though, is that the new regulations are proving to be a bonanza to the nation's largest garbage companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Federal and state rules are forcing the closing of hundreds of old community garbage dumps and prompting the development of many fewer, but much larger landfills that only the biggest cities and the largest garbage companies can afford to build and operate.</p>
        <p>And residents of thousands of small communities, like this one south of Montgomery, will be forced to choose the revenue and heavy truck traffic of a new nearby landfill or the huge increase in costs of transporting their garbage far away. What is definite, though, is that the new regulations are proving to be a bonanza to the nation's largest garbage companies.</p>
        <p>"A little county like ours can't afford to build a new dump," said Dwight Faulk, the probate judge and chairman of the Crenshaw County Commission. "So we have to have a company do it for us. These laws were set up for big business to monopolize an industry." Boon to Large Companies</p>
        <p>Industry executives agree. "There are only a handful of companies that will have the capabilities to provide the type of environmentally sound facilities that the public is demanding," said John C. Shirvinsky, vice president of public affairs for the Chambers Development Company, a Pittsburgh-based garbage company that operates 14 huge landfills around the country.</p>
        <p>Rarely have environmental regulations produced as many political distractions for the communities they are written to protect, or meant as much to the bottom lines of the industry they are intended to regulate. Upgrade or Close</p>
        <p>The intent of new Federal regulations, which were issued in October, was to eliminate toxic waste problems caused by community-owned dumps that leaked. The Government now requires new landfills to be built with plastic and clay liners, liquid collection and treatment systems, and other expensive environmental equipment that has raised the cost of opening a landfill to $10 million or more. Old town dumps that fail to meet the new requirements must close by 1993.</p>
        <p>The new Federal rules, and a few older state laws including those established by New York and New Jersey, mean most of the 6,500 community dumps across the country will be forced to close within the next few years, the Environmental Protection Agency has said. In their place will be 1,000 or so immense modern landfills owned primarily by a dozen or so companies and intended to serve entire regions.</p>
        <p>In effect, the Government may be helping to establish regional monopolies, and that worries some officials.</p>
        <p>"It's not difficult to project a situation in the future where very few firms could have regional or statewide control on the management of public wastes," said Thomas C. Jorling, the Commissioner of Environmental Conservation in New York, which will have fewer than 100 landfills by 1995, down from 518 in 1983. "If that occurs, it might be necessary for some kind of public utility regulations so that the public is not ripped off."</p>
        <p>Garbage industry executives insist, though, that there is enough competition to protect homeowners and businesses. "There will not be so few landfills that a city has only one option for disposal," said Philip S. Angell, the special assistant to the chairman of Browning-Ferris Industries, the nation's second-largest disposal company, in Houston. "There also will be a broader range of disposal options -- recycling, composting, incineration."</p>
        <p>The big money in garbage, nevertheless, still remains in dumping it. Despite recycling and new incinerators that turn trash into steam, electricity and ash, the amount of garbage headed for landfills amounts to 130 million tons a year, according to the National Solid Wastes Management Association, the industry's trade group. Battle in Alabama</p>
        <p>The nation's big garbage companies now earn $30 to more than $100 a ton to haul and dispose of the refuse. Managing garbage has grown into a $30-billion-a-year industry, and revenues are expected to double within five years, industry analysts say.</p>
        <p>Industry executives warn potential investors that the path to a new landfill is strewn with political obstacles, and only 1 of 10 proposed landfills is actually built. But they also acknowledge that companies nimble enough to overcome local opponents and beat their competitors in building a new landfill can realize profits of 25 to 50 percent on revenues of more than $100,000 a day.</p>
        <p>Thus, garbage companies are now battling for control of a region's garbage. And in few places is the fight more aggressive than in Alabama.</p>
        <p>Only 10 or 12 of the state's 102 community and county landfills meet the new requirements of the Federal law and the rest will close by the end of 1993, according to state officials.</p>
        <p>Garbage companies, led by Waste Management of Oak Brook, Ill., the nation's largest, and Browning-Ferris, are battling for their share of the nearly 13,000 tons of garbage dumped in landfills by Alabama every day. The two companies, and several smaller companies, have proposed replacing the state's community dumps with 15 large regional landfills.</p>
        <p>The proposals have angered some residents who say they believe such large landfills are unnecessary to replace the unobtrusive small dumps. In Blount and Walker Counties, north of Birmingham, county leaders have been threatened with death for inviting Browning-Ferris to propose new regional landfills, residents and state officials said.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups warned that the new dumps provide far more capacity than Alabama needs and aresituated to take advantage of Alabama's superior network of railways, waterways and highways to accept garbage from other states.</p>
        <p>"We're being set up to become the garbage dumping ground of the nation," said Linda Guy, the president of the Alabama Environmental Coalition, a state environmental group. "If all these new dumps are built, we'll have capacity for 30,000 or 40,000 tons per day, three times what we produce." Protecting Counties</p>
        <p>Executives from Waste Management and Browning-Ferris objected to Mrs. Guy's assertion. State law, they said, protects counties by requiring companies and communities to negotiate a contract that specifies the dozen or so counties that a new regional landfill would serve.</p>
        <p>"It would be political and economic suicide for Waste Management or any other company here to import garbage from New York or New Jersey or any other state," said Steve Bradley, a Waste Management spokesman in Birmingham. "Alabama just won't tolerate it."</p>
        <p>But Alabama is seeing garbage companies fiercely trying to derail another company's proposal for a new landfill. For decades, Crenshaw County's 14,000 residents used the garbage dump just north of Luverne. It cost Crenshaw County $80,000 a year to haul residents' garbage and operate the landfill, and families paid an average garbage fee of $10 a month, said Mr. Faulk, the probate judge.</p>
        <p>About two years ago, Mr. Faulk said, county leaders recognized that the new Federal and state rules would require the county to either spend millions of dollars modernizing the old dump or build a new one at an even higher cost. Late in 1990, Crenshaw County's five commissioners signed a contract with a Florida company to close the old county dump at a cost of $100,000, and build a $10 million 200-acre landfill on the same land four miles north of town to serve residents from Crenshaw and nine neighboring counties.</p>
        <p>The company, Three Rivers Construction of Marianna, Fla., was eager to gain a contract and promised benefits that have become common in Alabama and other states. Crenshaw County residents could dump their garbage free in the landfill and Three Rivers would pay the county $1.50 a ton for other garbage disposed there, a potential source of income to the county that eventually could be worth $300 to $800 a day. For the fiscal year 1991, the county's entire budget was $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>The proposed landfill, which is awaiting state approval, stirred protests from residents who worried it was too big and would cause dangerous levels of truck traffic.  'People Wouldn't Stand for It'</p>
        <p>"If we just closed the dump and didn't build a new one, that meant we'd have to take our garbage out of the county to another dump where tip fees are going to be $20, $25, or $30 a ton," Mr. Faulk said. "Add the trucking costs and you can see that the cost of garbage disposal would go to $300,000 or $400,000 a year. People wouldn't stand for it."</p>
        <p>But the project's biggest opponent has been Waste Away, a Montgomery-based garbage company and a business partner of Waste Management. Waste Away has a competing proposal to build its own $12 million landfill 35 miles east of here and wants the garbage from Crenshaw and surrounding counties to be dumped there to make the project more profitable. Crenshaw County would pay at least $24 a ton, plus hauling costs, to dump there.</p>
        <p>At a public hearing last month in the Crenshaw County courthouse, Waste Away sent a team of lawyers and engineers to attack the Crenshaw landfill. One of Waste Away's engineers said the proposed Crenshaw County landfill site was unsuitable and could become a threat to the environment and public health. Charles Patterson, a lawyer for Waste Away, said a second landfill in the region would generate such competition for garbage that waste would come into the area from out of state. "We don't need another regional landfill," Mr. Patterson said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Faulk and other commissioners were livid after the hearing. "What you are seeing here is raw power and greed," he said.</p>
        <p>Sarah Clark, another commissioner, added: "The commissioners of Crenshaw County did what was best for Crenshaw County. If the people of Crenshaw County want to pay $30 a month for garbage pickup, it's up to them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
