<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bojana Journal; What's There to Pardon? Bulgaria's Old Boss Asks</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="751954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENTENCES (CRIMINAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BULGARIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZHIVKOV, TODOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D7123CF933A05750C0A963958260" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bojana Journal; What's There to Pardon? Bulgaria's Old Boss Asks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>BOJANA, Bulgaria</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inside a whitewashed villa surrounded by a wire fence and protected by police guards, Bulgaria's longtime Communist leader, Todor Zhivkov, is living out his last years under house arrest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhivkov, now 82, was among the Communist leaders in Eastern Europe who were ousted in late 1989. He was sentenced in 1992 to seven years in prison after being convicted of illegally spending the equivalent of $24 million on cars, entertainment and apartments for favored aides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inside a whitewashed villa surrounded by a wire fence and protected by police guards, Bulgaria's longtime Communist leader, Todor Zhivkov, is living out his last years under house arrest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhivkov, now 82, was among the Communist leaders in Eastern Europe who were ousted in late 1989. He was sentenced in 1992 to seven years in prison after being convicted of illegally spending the equivalent of $24 million on cars, entertainment and apartments for favored aides.</p>
        <p>His doctors say he suffers from heart and circulatory ailments, and a judge has ruled that he may serve his sentence at his granddaughter's villa in this elegant suburb of Sofia, the capital.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Zhivkov's friends have urged him to seek a pardon, but he refuses.</p>
        <p>"A pardon is extended if a crime has been committed," he wrote in a letter to President Zhelyu Zhelev last year. "I, Todor Zhivkov, have committed no crime against the Bulgarian people. Let the people of Bulgaria judge me. Let history rule."</p>
        <p>In his 33 years in power, Mr. Zhivkov was widely despised. But in Bulgaria today, the emergence of a new generation and the serious problems of post-Communist life have combined to soften many people's memories of his rule.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhivkov's villa commands a scenic view of Sofia. Senior officials of the current Government are among his neighbors on a shaded dead-end street.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors did not respond to requests that a reporter be allowed to meet Mr. Zhivkov, and guards outside his house routinely block outsiders from entering. But Bulgarians speak about him freely.</p>
        <p>"These days you hear a lot of Bulgarians saying they would like to have Zhivkov back," said Alexander Dimitrov, 31, a business executive.  "In those days we had everything.  Well, maybe not everything, but we had a lot. Life was much easier then."</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhivkov has few family members to whom he can now turn for solace. He is a widower and his only daughter, Ludmila, died in 1981, apparently a suicide. His only son is living in troubled obscurity, reportedly suffering from drug problems. A 23-year-old grandson was extradited from Switzerland in February and is in a Sofia prison awaiting trial for his part in a reported rape in 1988.</p>
        <p>For a time, particularly in the 1960's and 70's, Mr. Zhivkov seemed to enjoy considerable popularity at home. He moved to industrialize Bulgaria, educate its population and break down rigid class barriers.</p>
        <p>But toward the end of his rule, his repressive bent and refusal to abandon Marxist economics led to growing disenchantment. By the time he was ousted in 1989, he was probably the most hated man in Bulgaria.</p>
        <p>Many Bulgarians now say Mr. Zhivkov's enthusiasm for collective farming was a disaster because it cut the peasants' link to the land and thus devastated the agrarian economy. His harshest policy, however, may have been his campaign in the 1980's to force members of the country's Turkish minority to change their names and abandon their ethnic heritage.</p>
        <p>"That was an unbelievably cruel thing to do," said Vera Djambazova, a Bulgarian journalist. "In those days I hated Zhivkov physically, with a tremendous passion. I was ashamed that such a dull, stupid peasant was ruling our country. But I don't hate him anymore. I think of him as a funny old man."</p>
        <p>In the Zhivkov era, many dissidents were offered bribes to remain silent instead of being imprisoned.  Those who refused to curb their criticism sometimes found themselves in mortal danger.</p>
        <p>Among them was Georgi Markov, a prominent author who defected to the West and began broadcasting anti-Communist messages into Bulgaria. His books were banned, and in 1978, in one of the most bizarre assassinations of the cold war, he was killed on Waterloo Bridge in London by an agent who used a specially rigged umbrella to shoot poison into his leg.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most interesting period of Mr. Zhivkov's long rule was the late 1970's, when his daughter, Ludmila, was a powerful figure. As Culture Minister, Ludmila Zhivkova sought to open Bulgaria to Western ideas, encouraging modern art and publishing works by authors like Allen Ginsberg and Arthur C. Clarke.  Some suspected that her death in a bathtub at her father's official residence was engineered by political enemies, but no proof of foul play has surfaced.</p>
        <p>"All the changes that we associate with Gorbachev and perestroika, we knew in Bulgaria in the 1970's," said Alexander Fol, one of Bulgaria leading historians, who was close to Ludmila Zhivkova and became Education Minister with her support. "At the beginning of the Zhivkov period, the regime was very repressive. But later things became looser."</p>
        <p>"Todor Zhivkov was at the top for 33 years, which is not so easy in the Balkans," Mr. Fol said. "He was not a Stalinist, not nearly as brutal as some other Communist leaders. His role was to stand between the Soviet Union and Bulgaria. We still know very little about what really went on in that relationship, but it seems that he played the game very well from the Bulgarian perspective.</p>
        <p>"In the geopolitical situation Bulgaria found itself in, I'm not sure that an intellectual like me could have been a successful statesman. Perhaps a man like Zhivkov was more appropriate for that game."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
