<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>400 Honor Seegers' Folk Protests</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER PEOPLE'S ACTION COALITION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEEGER, PETE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEEGER, TOSHI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DC1531F93AA25750C0A966958260" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>400 Honor Seegers' Folk Protests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES FERON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FERON, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, March 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The songs of a half century of political protest punctuated the stillness here today as folk singers and friends of Pete and Toshi Seeger gathered in a downtown neighborhood center to mark a special occasion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The songs of a half century of political protest punctuated the stillness here today as folk singers and friends of Pete and Toshi Seeger gathered in a downtown neighborhood center to mark a special occasion.</p>
        <p>The songs of a half century of political protest punctuated the stillness here today as folk singers and friends of Pete and Toshi Seeger gathered in a downtown neighborhood center to mark a special occasion.</p>
        <p>It was the presentation by a regional political action group, the Westchester People's Action Coalition, of its annual Peace and Justice award to the Seegers, who live near Beacon, 30 miles north of here.</p>
        <p>More than 400 guests attended, including former members of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War and some who had fought for civil rights and against the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>Corliss Lamont, the 88-year-old author and educator, praised the folk singer for ''using his music as a social weapon'' and said the Seegers ''should be remembered in our history'' because ''they lived their lives so that the world's children can see a new day.''</p>
        <p>Partners in a Celebrated Contempt</p>
        <p>Mr. Seeger and Mr. Lamont had been cited for contempt of Congress in refusing to cooperate with the House Committee on Un-American Activities in the 1950's when it was investigating Communist associations, but both were later acquitted on appeal.</p>
        <p>Fred Hellerman, a member of the Weavers, the singing group that included Mr. Seeger and was blacklisted for its left-wing associations, recalled the ''gratifying times'' of their earlier years together.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seeger began playing his 5-string banjo at union halls, in migrant labor camps and at concerts and rallies in the 1930's. Speakers recalled his concern for the environment. He is identified with an educational campaign using the sloop ''Clearwater'' to try to halt pollution of the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Connie Hogarth, director of the Westchester coalition, referred to the Seegers as ''two rare birds'' who she hoped would not ''become an endangered species.'' She referred to the singer as the ''Pied Piper of our times, seeking simple justice,'' and lauded his partner of 47 years as ''a visionary with her feet firmly planted on earth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seeger, who has said his only real talent is getting people to sing with him, ended the tribute just that way. Joined on the podium by some of his grandchildren, he led the packed hall with the stirring message and rising melody of ''If I Had a Hammer,'' which Mr. Seeger wrote with Lee Hays in the 1940's: ''It's the hammer of justice, it's the bell of freedom, it's the song between my brothers and my sisters, all over this land.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
