<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Yankee Robinson Returns as a Winner</title>
    <meta content="20XVEC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/20/sports/baseball/20VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1528814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Sports of The Times"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Marlins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Marlins</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E4DE113EF933A15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Yankee Robinson Returns as a Winner</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ex-Yank Comes Home Winner in Every Sense</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses Florida Marlins hitting coach Bill Robinson, who played three seasons with New York Yankees, and is seeking his fourth World Series title; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Florida Marlins arrived at Yankee Stadium for the World Series on Friday, they could see all the retired numbers out behind the left-field fence. A few even made a pilgrimage to the monuments to absorb the history of the place.</p>
        <p>Most of the Marlins do not know that their hitting coach, Bill Robinson, was once a teammate of some of those legendary players -- Elston Howard (No. 32), Whitey Ford (No. 16), Thurman Munson (No. 15) and Mickey Mantle (No. 7).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now, at age 60, Marlins hitting coach Bill Robinson is looking for his fourth World Series ring in four organizations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Florida Marlins arrived at Yankee Stadium for the World Series on Friday, they could see all the retired numbers out behind the left-field fence. A few even made a pilgrimage to the monuments to absorb the history of the place.</p>
        <p>Most of the Marlins do not know that their hitting coach, Bill Robinson, was once a teammate of some of those legendary players -- Elston Howard (No. 32), Whitey Ford (No. 16), Thurman Munson (No. 15) and Mickey Mantle (No. 7).</p>
        <p>''Bill played with Mantle?'' asked Derrek Lee, the Marlins' thoughtful first baseman. ''Bill doesn't talk much about himself. He never mentioned that.''</p>
        <p>The Marlins have other things on their minds, like trying to bounce back from their 6-1 loss last night at the Stadium that evened the Series at 1-1. They are living in the present, as well they should.</p>
        <p>Whether they know it or not, their paternal hitting coach is an inspiration for athletes -- or anybody else who has a bad day or a bad couple of years. You can come back. You can go from failure to the World Series.</p>
        <p>If they thumb through the Marlins' guide, the players will note that Robinson batted .196, .240 and .171 in three seasons with the Yankees -- then slipped back to the minor leagues. They know failure when they see it in the stark figures.</p>
        <p>Now, at age 60, Robinson is looking for his fourth World Series ring in four organizations.</p>
        <p>It is not the rings that make him a contented man. He takes pride in his wife, Mary, and their two children, and he also takes pride in coming back from failure.</p>
        <p>On Friday before the Marlins' workout, Robinson was standing in the Stadium, which is even more majestic in its blue-seated vastness without the tawdry blare of the public-address system. Old friends came up and hugged him and welcomed him ''home.'' Robinson could look out to right field, the position he was virtually handed in 1967, after the Yankees traded Clete Boyer to the Braves for him.</p>
        <p>The president of the Yankees, Michael Burke, a warm and decent man, called Robinson the next Roger Maris, a heavy burden.</p>
        <p>''I was ready to be Reggie Jackson and Reggie Smith,'' Robinson said, mentioning two contemporaries who made it big.</p>
        <p>''But I made a mistake on opening day,'' Robinson continued. ''I hit a home run in the Presidential opener in Washington, and everybody noticed it. Then I tried to hit a home run every time up.'' He hit six more all season.</p>
        <p>''Mickey used to tell me, 'You can't hit like me; you have to hit like yourself,' '' Robinson said. ''He told me to relax, but I don't think I listened.''</p>
        <p>It was a compliment that Mantle, who was in all kinds of physical and psychic pain, offered any advice at all. Perhaps Mantle, who had suffered anxiety and a return to the minor leagues in his rookie season, could see a bit of himself in the intense new man, who squeezed the bat tightly and wound up in Syracuse in 1970.</p>
        <p>''I did my crawling,'' Robinson said the other day. ''It was a negative, but I tried to turn it into a positive.''</p>
        <p>Somewhere along the line, Robinson had heard a comment from Willie Davis, the Dodgers' center fielder, that made sense to him.</p>
        <p>''It's not my life, and it's not my wife, so why worry,'' Robinson recited the other day. ''I say it to myself all the time. I live by it.''</p>
        <p>He relaxed enough in the minors to make it back to the majors in 1972, first with the Phillies, then with the Pirates. He hit more than 20 home runs in four different seasons, over .300 twice, and in 1979 he earned his first World Series ring.</p>
        <p>Later, he became a hitting coach with the Mets and earned his second ring in 1986. By 1999, he was in the Yankees' organization and received his third World Series ring.</p>
        <p>''The only thing that eluded me was managing,'' he said. ''I managed in Venezuela one winter, but not in the majors. That's not going to happen. But I've gone from a bum to an average player to a star for a while. I am fulfilled and happy.</p>
        <p>''I have been with my loving wife for 40 years. The good Lord has blessed me 50 times over.''</p>
        <p>He doesn't brag, but if you ask, he will tell you that their son, Billy, a graduate of North Carolina, works for MTV, and their daughter, Kelley, a graduate of Fashion Institute of Technology, works as a fashion designer.</p>
        <p>He has done well. And he does not look back. He did not escort the younger Marlins around the big ballpark in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''I'm not really a nostalgic person,'' Robinson said. ''I played here three years, but now I work for the Marlins.''</p>
        <p>He does not trade in on his Mantle connection. ''The only thing Bill told me,'' Lee said, ''was that he was in two World Series and that his two teams came from behind both times.''</p>
        <p>This is correct. The 1979 Pirates were behind, three games to one, and won the Series. The 1986 Mets were behind, 2-0 and 3-2, and won the Series.</p>
        <p>Bill Robinson is an expert on coming back.</p>
        <p>Sports of The Times</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
