<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Stop Now</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749326"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED8103EF934A25750C0A963958260" item-length="428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Stop Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists say that human evolution may be at an end. Natural selection is stopping, no doubt as a result of natural selection. Homo sapiens, always the finest proof of the survival of the fittest, appears to have concluded that it is fit enough.</p>
        <p>Evolutionary theorists have their own explanation. There are no more isolated ecosystems where mutations can evolve, which is a nice way of saying that when people spend a lot of time by themselves they turn very weird.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists say that human evolution may be at an end. Natural selection is stopping, no doubt as a result of natural selection. Homo sapiens, always the finest proof of the survival of the fittest, appears to have concluded that it is fit enough.</p>
        <p>Evolutionary theorists have their own explanation. There are no more isolated ecosystems where mutations can evolve, which is a nice way of saying that when people spend a lot of time by themselves they turn very weird.</p>
        <p>But what is the ontological import? Have we stalled in a fit of complacency, so happy with the product that any further tinkering is unnecessary? Or after eons of working at it, have we decided we cannot handle one more rewrite? Perhaps the entire species has come down with the first known case of chronic evolutionary fatigue syndrome.</p>
        <p>While intellectuals on the left and right argue about the proper genetic explanation for America's social problems, "the human line," as the experts call it, has decided to cash in its chips. As William K. Stevens noted in Science Times this week, lions and leopards and saber-toothed cats no longer carry off the unfit. So couch potatoes are just as safe as aerobics instructors.</p>
        <p>On the positive side, this means we can relax. We do not need to read Deborah Tannen anymore because we are never going to improve communication between the sexes. We do not need to listen to Martha Stewart anymore because we are never going to cut up those doilies for cake decorations. We do not need to fret over our children's eating habits and manners; they will not be any thinner or more sensitive than we are.</p>
        <p>But are we sure that this is the right moment to freeze the frame? We might try to adapt a little beyond stuffy sinuses, the baseball strike, platform shoes, Jerry Springer, Robert James Waller and the Brady Brunch. And what if some ambitious insect race sneaks past us while we are glued to F. Lee Bailey spatting with Marcia Clark?</p>
        <p>The scientists predict that we will eventually take our future into our own hands through genetic engineering. Given how well attempts to change society on the basis of science have gone in the past, it will not be pretty. It is bad enough when your 11- year-old comes to you and wants her navel pierced; imagine when she announces her intention to be re-engineered as Courtney Love.</p>
        <p>The prospect conjures up a "Star Trek" moral fable: Captain Kirk, standing at the deck of the Enterprise, looking sadly back at Earth. "They were a fine species," he says, "until they tried to better themselves genetically."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
