<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awad Closes Fast at Gulfstream Park</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GULFSTREAM PARK (RACE TRACK) (FLA)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAILEY, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSERO, FRANK A JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOTT, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DC163CF934A25750C0A963958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awad Closes Fast at Gulfstream Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
      <dateline>HALLANDALE, Fla., March 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gulfstream Park ended its two-and-a-half-month racing season today with a slight drop in attendance but a strong gain in its favorite export, simulcasting. It also declared Jerry Bailey its leading jockey, Bill Mott and Frank A. Passero Jr. its leading trainers and the 5-year-old Awad the surprise winner of its closing feature, the $300,000 Pan American Handicap.</p>
        <p>Awad ran fifth behind several of the same horses three weeks ago in the Gulfstream Park Breeders' Cup Handicap. He likes to run late, and he did it with success today, shooting from ninth and last place to first as they turned for home. At the wire, he had 1 3/4 lengths on Misil, who had three lengths on Frenchpark. The favorite, Yokohoma, finished eighth with Bailey riding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gulfstream Park ended its two-and-a-half-month racing season today with a slight drop in attendance but a strong gain in its favorite export, simulcasting. It also declared Jerry Bailey its leading jockey, Bill Mott and Frank A. Passero Jr. its leading trainers and the 5-year-old Awad the surprise winner of its closing feature, the $300,000 Pan American Handicap.</p>
        <p>Awad ran fifth behind several of the same horses three weeks ago in the Gulfstream Park Breeders' Cup Handicap. He likes to run late, and he did it with success today, shooting from ninth and last place to first as they turned for home. At the wire, he had 1 3/4 lengths on Misil, who had three lengths on Frenchpark. The favorite, Yokohoma, finished eighth with Bailey riding.</p>
        <p>The winner, owned by Ryehill Farm and trained by David Donk, ran the mile and a half on the turf in 2:292/5 with Eddie Maple aboard and paid $17.20 for $2 to win.</p>
        <p>Douglas Donn, the president of Gulfstream, noted that rainy weather had caused on-track attendance and betting handle to be "virtually static." Attendance was down eight-tenths of a percentage point to 662,499 and on-track betting slipped 1.8 percent to $120 million. But total handle, including simulcast, soared by 9.1 percent to a record total of $622 million for 62 days. Bailey Tops With 82 Winners</p>
        <p>Mike Smith rode Holy Bull, Sky Beauty and Devil His Due. He won the Eclipse Award as the nation's best jockey the last two years, and won the most stakes races the last two years. He was the leading rider at Gulfstream Park last year.</p>
        <p>Jerry Bailey won the Kentucky Derby aboard Sea Hero two years ago. He won the Breeders' Cup Classic in 1993 aboard the 133-1 long shot, the French horse Arcangues, and in 1994 aboard Concern. Last Saturday at Gulfstream Park, he rode seven winners.</p>
        <p>And on the strength of that record-setting performance, Bailey defeated Smith for the riding title at Gulfstream with 82 winners, 7 more than Smith. And Passero and Mott, the leading trainer for the last two years, tied for this year's title with 23 winners apiece. Different Forms of Artistry</p>
        <p>The most dramatic moment of Gulfstream's season came Feb. 11 when the formidable career of Holy Bull ended on the backstretch during the running of the Donn Handicap.</p>
        <p>The Horse of the Year and 3-year-old champion of 1994 strained the tendons and ligaments in his left foreleg. Holy Bull was retired to stud duty at Jonabell Farm in Lexington, Ky. He won 13 of his 16 races and $2.4 million.</p>
        <p>At the other end of the artistic scale, a horse named McKenzie's Reef made history, too. He ran fourth in the fourth race on Wednesday, and probably set a record when 25 claims were entered for him. The lucky bidder, determined by lot: Robin Frank, acting for his father, Eric Frank.</p>
        <p>Nobody was certain why McKenzie's Reef elicited so many claims. He is a 3-year-old gelding who had won 2 of 9 career starts and earned $23,355. He was trained by the red-hot Passero. It's Virtually a Match Race</p>
        <p>It won't exactly be a match race, but the San Felipe on Sunday at Santa Anita may be close. The race will star the two top contenders for the Kentucky Derby, the undefeated Afternoon Deelites and the juvenile champion of last year, Timber Country. They may face three other horses, but will have eyes only for each other.</p>
        <p>"In a virtual match race," said D. Wayne Lukas, the trainer of Timber Country, "speed and turn of foot are everything. It puts us at a tremendous disadvantage. With no pressure, Afternoon Deelites is virtually home free."</p>
        <p>But before weeping for Lukas, remember: He is never more dangerous than when he starts conceding races.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
