<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Well-Tempered Collection</title>
    <meta content="22CTMUSIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1DA1739F931A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Well-Tempered Collection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIAN WISE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR about 10 years, Lakeville was home to Wanda Landowska, a 20th-century harpsichordist famous for bringing the Baroque instrument out of the museum and onto the concert stage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Landowska died in 1959, but her companion of many years, Denise Restout, continued to live in their rambling six-bedroom Victorian house in Lakeville until her death in March last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR about 10 years, Lakeville was home to Wanda Landowska, a 20th-century harpsichordist famous for bringing the Baroque instrument out of the museum and onto the concert stage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Landowska died in 1959, but her companion of many years, Denise Restout, continued to live in their rambling six-bedroom Victorian house in Lakeville until her death in March last year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Restout bequeathed thousands of personal items from Ms. Landowska's life and career to the Library of Congress. The items have been transported to Washington, offering a fresh opportunity to examine her musical legacy. The papers, which the library moved from Connecticut last October, include Ms. Landowska's musical scores, recordings, photographs, correspondence, original manuscripts and other items. Also included is a pair of harpsichords that she played throughout her career.</p>
        <p>''It's a major acquisition,'' said Jan Lauridsen, assistant chief of the library's music division. ''Landowska was so important in reviving the harpsichord and its repertory in the 20th century. It had been considered an obsolete instrument until then.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Landowska's years in Lakeville were a relatively peaceful coda to an often turbulent life. She was born in Warsaw in 1879, and began playing piano at age 4. In her early years, composers like Chopin, Liszt and Brahms had made the concert grand piano the king of keyboard instruments. Harpsichords mainly gathered dust in the furniture collections of museums. But early on, Ms. Landowska was fascinated by the instrument. She taught herself how to play it, and how to recreate a forgotten style of performance. She gave her first public performance in 1903, and soon became well known in Europe and Russia for her pioneering work to bring the harpsichord back into the musical mainstream.</p>
        <p>In 1913, she left Poland and studied in Berlin, before moving to Paris. There she met her husband, the Polish ethnologist Henry Lew. Teaching in Germany at the outbreak of World War I, she and her husband were interned there until the Armistice. He died in a car accident only days before they were to return to Paris.</p>
        <p>She rebuilt her life in Paris, but two decades later had to escape the Nazi advance on the city, abandoning many harpsichords and a library of 10,000 books and scores. Eventually, she reached the French Pyrenees, and in 1941, obtained passage to New York. Again starting from scratch, she and Ms. Restout, who had been a harpsichord student of Ms. Landowska's, settled in Lakeville in 1949. Ms. Landowska made several recordings there, including celebrated versions of Bach's ''Well-Tempered Clavier'' at age 70.</p>
        <p>The Lakeville home was musical salon for friends and colleagues, even long after Ms. Landowska's death. Ms. Restout devoted her energies to Ms. Landowska's legacy, teaching harpsichord in Ms. Landowska's style, and editing and translating her writings on music.</p>
        <p>The library's acquisition will give scholars and enthusiasts of Baroque music a closer look at Ms. Landowska's complex legacy, said Raymond White, senior music specialist at the library. While she is credited with reviving 17th-and 18th-century music, she preferred a vigorous, richly colored sound that runs counter to today's tastes, and often revised compositions to reflect her preferences.</p>
        <p>''In some cases, she edited extremely heavily, adding more notes to increase the sound,'' Mr. White said. ''When she started, she was competing with a romantic aesthetic. She felt that in order to compete she needed a bigger sound.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Landowska also took liberties with instrument design. In 1912, she hired the French manufacturer Pleyel to create a harpsichord to her specifications. With a big tone and double keyboard, it resembled a piano, and was not particularly historic, according to today's understanding.</p>
        <p>Historians say Ms. Landowska preferred the bulky Pleyel models not so much for their sound as for their durability; she hauled as many as four instruments with her on trains and coaches for performances in Europe and in the United States, and once famously dragged one on a sled through a blizzard to play for Leo Tolstoy in Russia. The library is in the process of refurbishing two of her World War I-era harpsichords, along with a clavichord and a Steinway piano.</p>
        <p>Elaine Camperone, founder of Harpsichord Unlimited, an early-music organization in New York, said Mr. Landowska was important to many harpsichordists today.</p>
        <p>''People who know about her have always thought she was the greatest,'' she said. ''The strength of her rhythmic playing, her technique and her curiosity were unparalleled.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White said some of the collection's most prized items were photographs that document Ms. Landowska's distinctive playing technique. ''We have a series of photos of her playing, and you can see her hands on the two different manuals, with her long, spindly fingers stretching across the keys,'' he said. ''Her hand positions were very unique, and the photos tell you a lot about how she came up with her style.''</p>
        <p>Once it is cataloged, the entire Landowska collection will be made available to the public. It is one of the most significant musical additions to the library, Mr. White said, which has the papers of American composers and performers including Leonard Bernstein, Aaron Copland, George Gershwin, Richard Rodgers and John Philip Sousa.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
