<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenberg, in Exile, Plots His Next Move</title>
    <meta content="22INSU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/22/business/yourmoney/22insure.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">American International Group</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenberg, Maurice R</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4D81439F931A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="3015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenberg, in Exile, Plots His Next Move</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Greenberg, in Exile, Plots His Next Move</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY L. O' BRIEN and JENNY ANDERSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAURICE R. GREENBERG has come late to a love of lacrosse. Cut off from managing American International Group, the insurance juggernaut he cherished and fiercely controlled, the strong-willed Mr. Greenberg now spends part of his time cheering his grandchildren at their prep school sporting events.</p>
        <p>Subjected to the uncertainties and indignities of a sprawling insurance investigation that is engulfing him, Mr. Greenberg also shuttles between various lawyers' offices and his own temporary command center at 299 Park Avenue in New York. Ousted as A.I.G.'s chairman and chief executive in March, he is tightly focused on mounting his legal defense and is mulling how best to wield his remaining levers of power to recapture his lost glory at the top of corporate America's food chain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ousted chairman and chief executive of the American International Group is mulling how to recapture his lost glory at the top of corporate America's food chain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAURICE R. GREENBERG has come late to a love of lacrosse. Cut off from managing American International Group, the insurance juggernaut he cherished and fiercely controlled, the strong-willed Mr. Greenberg now spends part of his time cheering his grandchildren at their prep school sporting events.</p>
        <p>Subjected to the uncertainties and indignities of a sprawling insurance investigation that is engulfing him, Mr. Greenberg also shuttles between various lawyers' offices and his own temporary command center at 299 Park Avenue in New York. Ousted as A.I.G.'s chairman and chief executive in March, he is tightly focused on mounting his legal defense and is mulling how best to wield his remaining levers of power to recapture his lost glory at the top of corporate America's food chain.</p>
        <p>Even in exile, Mr. Greenberg, who is 80, entertains visiting Asian and Russian emissaries seeking to tap his expertise and business connections. He also exercises influence over a large block of A.I.G. stock while harboring intense resentment toward those still inside the company who forced him out. But his status as a mover and shaker going forward is bound up in a little understood A.I.G. offshoot that owns some $16 billion of its parent company's stock.</p>
        <p>Despite his newfound life as a part-time homebody, no one expects Mr. Greenberg to relinquish his role at the company that controls that stock -- the Starr International Company, a privately held Dublin enterprise commonly known as SICO. The company provides him with vast resources for a possible second act as a financier -- assuming, of course, that he emerges unscathed by the myriad civil and criminal investigations.</p>
        <p>But SICO's billions, its relationship to A.I.G. and its future are now in play, setting in motion an unwieldy, unpredictable sideshow in a mushrooming insurance industry inquiry that includes Mr. Spitzer, the Securities and Exchange Commission, the Justice Department and the New York State Insurance Department.</p>
        <p>The possibility of criminal charges against individuals associated with A.I.G. heightened last week when it emerged that the New York attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, convened a grand jury to weigh such charges, according to a person briefed on the investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg's fate, and his endgame for SICO's vast trove of A.I.G. stock, has Wall Street atwitter.</p>
        <p>''My guess is that they won't give up the assets,'' said David Schiff, an insurance analyst who publishes a newsletter, Schiff's Insurance Observer, referring to Mr. Greenberg and his SICO colleagues. ''They could just give it up, but why would they? It gives them control of a huge block of A.I.G. stock. The question is, what happens to that?''</p>
        <p>LIKE many long, fruitful and complicated corporate unions, A.I.G.'s relationship with SICO ended badly.</p>
        <p>On March 22, A.I.G., scrambling to manage the fallout from the mounting regulatory investigation, notified SICO that it wanted access to reams of SICO's records housed in shared Bermuda offices. Two days later, A.I.G. sent a lawyer and a pair of computer technicians into SICO's Dublin headquarters and locked down the office of a senior executive there, according to several people briefed on the events.</p>
        <p>SICO countered A.I.G.'s moves the next day, securing its records under armed guard at a new facility in Bermuda. Since then, the legal and financial tug of war between the two companies has abated.</p>
        <p>Among the small group of executives orchestrating SICO's affairs is Mr. Greenberg, who is known as Hank. For years, SICO's relationship to A.I.G. and its existence as a compensation vehicle for A.I.G.'s most elite employees have been topics of speculation and occasional criticism on Wall Street. Mr. Greenberg's supporters say that SICO has been unfairly characterized as shrouded in mystery and that his role there has been unfairly maligned.</p>
        <p>One of two companies of what eventually became the modern incarnation of A.I.G. as a publicly traded company, SICO, which was incorporated in Panama in the late 1940's and had its headquarters until last fall in Bermuda, once controlled a profitable fleet of overseas insurance agencies.</p>
        <p>Named after A.I.G.'s founder, Cornelius Vander Starr, SICO also owned The Lookout, a Hong Kong estate where Mr. Starr vacationed and a perch giving A.I.G. a lucrative foothold in China and the Asian insurance market. According to corporate records, later holdings included real estate in Japan, art and two yachts, the Serendipity and the Serendipity 2, which Mr. Greenberg docked at his retreat in the exclusive Florida enclave of Ocean Reef. In addition, SICO owned Morefar, a golf course on Mr. Starr's estate in Brewster, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Before going public in 1969, A.I.G., under Mr. Greenberg's direction, bought SICO's agency businesses for about $110 million in stock. He orchestrated the deal because he was concerned that A.I.G.'s operations would be in conflict with SICO's businesses after the public offering, and he wanted to rationalize A.I.G.'s corporate structure, according to Edward E. Matthews, a former senior vice chairman at A.I.G. and one of SICO's 12 voting shareholders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matthews noted that while Mr. Greenberg and several others at SICO who were recipients of that initial A.I.G. stock could have cashed in, they chose to use the windfall as seed money for a long-term compensation plan designed to motivate top employees who helped A.I.G. expand its insurance operations. From then on, SICO existed primarily as a repository for A.I.G. stock, and little else, Mr. Matthews said.</p>
        <p>Starting in the mid-1970's, SICO's directors met every two years to decide which A.I.G. employees would receive SICO's highly prized stock grants. The rules of the grants were strict. The awards remained in SICO's coffers until an employee retired at age 65, after which he or she vested shares often valued at tens of millions of dollars. If an employee left A.I.G. for a rival, they forfeited their stock. Over the decades, as A.I.G. expanded into the world's largest insurance company, the SICO kitty ballooned.</p>
        <p>''In the early days it was not a lot of money, and auditors initially deemed it immaterial and outside of A.I.G.,'' said Mr. Matthews. ''But over the years, A.I.G. became a very large company, so this $110 million became 311 million A.I.G. shares. At one time it became worth about $30 billion.''</p>
        <p>Today, with A.I.G.'s shares depressed, SICO's stock pool is worth about $16 billion. SICO's supporters said its program encouraged loyalty to the company, a rarity on Wall Street, and ensured that rewards were tied to long-term performance -- a crucial issue in an industry where hastily written policies can bring cash in the door quickly but derail a company years later when unforeseen disasters (hurricanes, for example) spark a rash of expensive claims.</p>
        <p>SICO's proponents also say the company allowed A.I.G. to keep costs low because it didn't have to fund an expensive deferred compensation plan internally. But just seven directors and 12 shareholders oversee SICO's treasure chest. Mr. Greenberg is a member of both groups, although he does not occupy any of SICO's six officer slots, according to corporate records.</p>
        <p>Critics complained that during Mr. Greenberg's long tenure at A.I.G.'s helm, SICO became one of the many financial cudgels the steely and authoritarian executive wielded to keep senior management of A.I.G. firmly under his sway. About 700 of A.I.G.'s 92,000 employees participate in SICO's compensation program.</p>
        <p>''People are not wedded to A.I.G. to receive their SICO payouts -- they are enslaved to Hank Greenberg, who controls what SICO doles out,'' claims an amended lawsuit that a Louisiana pension fund filed against A.I.G. on Tuesday in Delaware Chancery Court. The suit, originally filed in December 2002, seek damages for alleged financial misdealings by A.I.G. that hurt the pension fund's investment in A.I.G.</p>
        <p>''We take great issue with the idea that anything we've done is to take advantage of A.I.G. shareholders,'' said Mr. Matthews. ''We all remain major A.I.G. shareholders and I, for one, have never diversified.''</p>
        <p>People close to Mr. Greenberg said that he, too, takes exception to the idea that SICO, or any entity he was involved with, attempted to take advantage of A.I.G., a company he built into a financial powerhouse.</p>
        <p>A.I.G.'s board, alarmed by warnings from Mr. Spitzer that he planned to file criminal charges against the company for suspected document destruction, ousted Mr. Greenberg in March. Mr. Spitzer's office, the S.E.C. and the Justice Department are investigating ways in which A.I.G. used questionable accounting tactics to enhance its financial statements.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg declined to comment, but people close to him say he believes A.I.G.'s weakened stock price is due to his absence from the company and a law enforcement investigation that has run out of control.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they said, he feels betrayed by his former board. ''He's public enemy No.1 now,'' said Bernard Marcus, a former chairman of Home Depot and an acquaintance of Mr. Greenberg's. ''I thought you were innocent until proven guilty. That's not the case here.'' Mr. Greenberg, he added, should have been allowed to participate in the company's internal investigation into misleading accounting practices.</p>
        <p>In response to those comments, an A.I.G. board member said, ''Should we have circled the wagons and told Eliot Spitzer we wouldn't cooperate?''</p>
        <p>Still, other allies criticize Mr. Spitzer's tactics in the investigation, including a recent appearance on George Stephanopoulos's television news program. When Mr. Stephanopoulos showed a clip of Mr. Greenberg's attorney, David Boies, asserting that his client had not been involved in fraudulent activities, Mr. Spitzer said that he believed that fraud had in fact occurred.</p>
        <p>''If Eliot Spitzer has a case, he should make it in the appropriate fashion,'' said Bob Kerrey, a former senator from Nebraska and now president of the New School in New York. ''You should not try someone publicly.'' (One of Mr. Greenberg's charitable foundations donated $10 million to a New School program.)</p>
        <p>''The A.G. was not commenting on Mr. Greenberg specifically,'' said Darren Dopp, a spokesman for Mr. Spitzer. ''Instead, he was commenting on the improper conduct that had already been acknowledged by the company.''</p>
        <p>Still, there were ample reasons for regulators like Mr. Spitzer to become curious about the nature of A.I.G.'s far-flung and often impenetrable operations. The company, and Mr. Greenberg in particular, spent years using hardball tactics to cow analysts, regulators and anyone else who dared to criticize or closely examine A.I.G.'s dealings -- a tradition Mr. Spitzer's investigation upended. Moreover, A.I.G.'s organizational chart, made up of scores of off-shore entities and interlocking companies, looks like nothing so much as a vast and indecipherable circuit board.</p>
        <p>Atop that chart are a handful of enterprises, including SICO. The company collects tens of millions of dollars in annual dividends that it says have always been distributed to employees. Nonetheless, SICO's cash horde has prompted analysts and others to wonder how the funds are spent. Although Morefar and The Lookout have been characterized in news media accounts as expensive perks maintained under the SICO umbrella, corporate records indicate that A.I.G. paid SICO only about $4 million to $5 million a year for use of the properties -- a drop in the bucket for A.I.G.</p>
        <p>Although SICO was nominally constituted as a compensation vehicle, records indicate it has engaged in insurance activities. At one time, it controlled and operated a company called Astral Reinsurance that, until being dissolved in 2002, absorbed insurance risks underwritten by another A.I.G. concern, Union Excess.</p>
        <p>Astral's vice president was L. Michael Murphy, a confidant of Mr. Greenberg who lives in Bermuda and is SICO's president and managing director. Mr. Murphy worked at A.I.G. as its chief legal counsel in Bermuda. A.I.G. fired him in March, saying he refused to cooperate with Mr. Spitzer's investigation. His lawyer declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Although an internal A.I.G. report written in 2003 described SICO's 12 voting shareholders as its owners, others with direct knowledge of SICO's operations said the company's ultimate owner is a nonprofit based in Dublin, called Starr International Charities. Should SICO be dissolved, the proceeds from the sale of its A.I.G. stock are supposed to go to that entity.</p>
        <p>The charity, which relocated to Dublin from Bermuda last fall, has three trustees: Mr. Murphy, a SICO executive named Margaret Barnes and the British banking giant HSBC Group, according to Mr. Matthews. He said that Ireland taxes stock dividends at a 5 percent to 10 percent rate, compared with 30 percent in Bermuda, and that prompted the move to Dublin. Other than a contribution last year to Dublin's Abbey Theater, the charity has yet to make substantial local contributions, but SICO representatives said it plans to do more this year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Barnes is SICO's controller and it was her Dublin office that A.I.G representatives locked down in late March, prompting SICO to secure its documents in Bermuda. Irish insurance regulators say they have no records pertaining to SICO's operations in Dublin. Nor does Ireland regulate charities that are based there, leaving SICO free to operate there with little oversight.</p>
        <p>Dublin, which has promoted itself in recent years as a friendly locale for insurers, has emerged as a hornet's nest in the insurance investigations in the United States. A Dublin unit of General Re, an insurer controlled by Warren E. Buffett's Berkshire Hathaway, helped handle one of the improper A.I.G. transactions that Mr. Spitzer and the S.E.C. are scrutinizing; the Justice Department recently notified the former head of General Re's Dublin office that he is a target of a criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>SICO representatives insist that the company's insurance operations, and any other business dealings, were always very minimal and that it served foremost as a compensation vehicle -- nothing more. Still, some observers contend that SICO served other purposes for Mr. Greenberg and his compatriots at the company.</p>
        <p>''I think they always wanted it as an antitakeover device,'' said Mr. Schiff. ''And they keep referring to this 'act of generosity' when they originally contributed their stock. I don't think it's generous to compensate employees. I think it's fair. The people who've gotten the most from this are already wealthy people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Matthews pooh-poohs the notion that SICO was an antitakeover tool.</p>
        <p>''If people want to ask what is the antitakeover device at A.I.G., we say success and size,'' he said. ''When you get very large, that is what protects you, not SICO.''</p>
        <p>Besides running SICO, Mr. Greenberg is one of three executives who exercise control over C.V. Starr, another A.I.G. affiliate that retained insurance brokerages he did not want A.I.G. to have on its books when it went public. C.V. Starr now owns about 2 percent of A.I.G.'s shares. It has cozy business relations with A.I.G., while also operating as another compensation vehicle for a group dubbed ''The Billionaires Club'' by A.I.G. employees, according to the Delaware court case. Starr has 80 shareholders, including current A.I.G. officers and directors. Among that group are Martin Sullivan, A.I.G.'s new chief executive, and Donald P. Kanak, the company's chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>Regulators are concerned about conflicts between both Starr entities and A.I.G. The Delaware lawsuit contends that $495.2 million in commissions A.I.G. paid Starr between 1999 and 2003 were ''completely unnecessary and were simply a means of lining the pockets of Starr's owners.'' The suit also asserts that many of the businesses run within Starr are simply mirror operations for identical businesses in A.I.G. -- doing the same things and run by the same people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boies, who represents C.V. Starr and SICO as well as Mr. Greenberg, disputed that the commissions were excessive or unnecessary, saying that A.I.G.'s examination of the payments two years ago reached the same conclusion. Mr. Boies is overseeing an effort to fully separate Starr from A.I.G. He estimates that the Starr brokerages may fetch $450 to $500 million in a sale. A.I.G. has first rights to buy the brokerages, but Starr can sell them to a third party.</p>
        <p>As the machinery Mr. Greenberg built at A.I.G. is gradually unwound, the days when he roamed the company's halls reminding executives that they should be prepared for his 3 a.m. phone calls are over. So, too, are the sessions in his office when he relentlessly peppered executives with incisive questions about their budgets or strategies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg's insistence on tight budgets created a streamlined and bare-boned culture with A.I.G. While those at the top of the company may have benefited over the years from access to SICO and Starr's riches, most of the tens of thousands of people who worked for the company never did. A.I.G. has acknowledged that most of its employees were paid about a fifth less than counterparts at competing concerns.</p>
        <p>AND Mr. Greenberg, as one of SICO and Starr's chief custodians, has a handsome kitty at his disposal to plan a next move -- for as long as he is free to do so. As A.I.G. seeks to distance itself from him and dismantle relations with SICO and Starr, Mr. Greenberg is said to be determined to put his resources to use. He is mulling reconstituting the Starr companies as a venture capital firm and inviting executives to join him in investing adventures.</p>
        <p>Wherever Mr. Greenberg lands, observers say that he, like A.I.G. itself during his reign, remains respected, feared, and still, even now, naggingly opaque.</p>
        <p>''He was the giant of the industry,'' said A.J.C. Smith, who retired as the chairman of Marsh &amp; McLennan in 2000. ''Everyone has an opinion of him, but that's like having an opinion of the president of the United States. Not too many people actually know him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
