<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advanced Screenwriting According to Me</title>
    <meta content="22BAKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/22/movies/22bake.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050529T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Dahl, Roald</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Burton, Tim</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Depp, Johnny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DD1639F931A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advanced Screenwriting According to Me</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Advanced Screenwriting According to Me</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB BAKER</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN AUGUST, one of Hollywood's most in-demand script polishers, could have been working on any number of projects on a recent spring morning. There was the script he is writing and hoping to direct. There was the musical adaptation of a novel. There was a movie based on the video game ''Prince of Persia,'' on which he is serving as an executive producer for Jerry Bruckheimer. And looming over all was July 15, the day his adaptation of ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,'' directed by Tim Burton and starring Johnny Depp, opens in theaters.</p>
        <p>But instead, as Mr. August sat down at the computer in his spacious Hancock Park house, he logged on, as he does most every day, to www.johnaugust.com, where aspiring writers pelt him with questions. Should I take a job rewriting a bad movie? How much guidance should my script give the actors? Does ''based on a true story'' have any legal meaning? What kind of printer do you use?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The teacher in John August has a gift for explaining. The geek in him built a Web site to offer his advice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN AUGUST, one of Hollywood's most in-demand script polishers, could have been working on any number of projects on a recent spring morning. There was the script he is writing and hoping to direct. There was the musical adaptation of a novel. There was a movie based on the video game ''Prince of Persia,'' on which he is serving as an executive producer for Jerry Bruckheimer. And looming over all was July 15, the day his adaptation of ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,'' directed by Tim Burton and starring Johnny Depp, opens in theaters.</p>
        <p>But instead, as Mr. August sat down at the computer in his spacious Hancock Park house, he logged on, as he does most every day, to www.johnaugust.com, where aspiring writers pelt him with questions. Should I take a job rewriting a bad movie? How much guidance should my script give the actors? Does ''based on a true story'' have any legal meaning? What kind of printer do you use?</p>
        <p>On this morning, Mr. August selected a query from a hopeful screenwriter asking about legal issues involved in adapting a friend's discarded memoir -- unbeknownst to the friend. Mr. August told the correspondent she was on shaky ground legally, then added that he found her appropriation of her friend's memoir a little -- well, unfriendly. He said he told her: ''My advice: tell him what you did, and show him the script. Maybe he'll love it. Maybe he'll hate it and stop being your friend. I can't say I'd blame him.''</p>
        <p>There are scores of Web sites run by screenwriters, most of them with limited credentials, and a few others run by pros and geared to working writers. By contrast, Mr. August's site -- free, like most of the others -- draws an audience reminiscent of the University of Southern California's film school, where he earned a graduate degree a little more than a decade ago. The site reflects not only Mr. August's talent for explanation but also his enthusiasm for it. It reveals him to be, in his words, a ''big techno-geeky nerd'': he built and administers it himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. August, 34, has won a reputation for versatility with scripts like ''Go'' (1999), the cool and chaotic look at disaffected young people directed by Doug Liman (''Swingers''), and ''Big Fish'' (2003), the fanciful family tale directed by Mr. Burton. In between, Mr. August has earned enough as a script doctor to buy that expensive house, which he shares with his partner of five years, Mike Douglass.</p>
        <p>For all the success, www.johnaugust.com has a decidedly humble, nuts-and-bolts sensibility. To cheer the struggling masses, Mr. August posts a list of the 11 full-length scripts he has sold or written on spec that have never been shot. He jokes that operating the site ''is an excuse not to work,'' and that it's ''more fun than video games.'' But he also calls it ''one of those pay it back, pay it forward things.''</p>
        <p>Mr. August is 6 feet tall and 170 pounds with a shaved head. But he retains a boyish earnestness, which Hollywood usually strips from people before swallowing them.</p>
        <p>To describe his feelings at getting the ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory'' job, for example, he unselfconsciously invokes a cliché: it was ''a dream come true,'' he says. And then he retrieves a 28-year-old postcard. His third-grade teacher, in Boulder, Colo., had asked everyone in the class to write to someone famous. Most kids went for President Jimmy Carter. Young John, having read ''Charlie,'' wrote to its author, Roald Dahl. The postcard that arrived shortly thereafter seemed like a treasured reward: a personal note from the man himself. Eventually, someone broke the news that it was no more than a form letter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton wanted his film to follow Dahl's text more faithfully than had the 1971 version, ''Willy Wonka and the Chocolate Factory,'' starring Gene Wilder. However, the book offered no guidance about Willy's boyhood. So Mr. August playfully made him the son of a renowned, candy-hating dentist.</p>
        <p>In one of the script's flashbacks, Willy's father throws his son's Halloween candy into the fireplace; in another, Willy finds one piece spared from the flames and bites in. Then, the script says, the opening chords of Jimi Hendrix's version of ''All Along the Watchtower'' begin to play, and ''we begin a spinning perspective shot that would leave Hitchcock jealous. In little Willy's eyes we see a reaction. He's like Isaac Newton getting beaned by the apple.''</p>
        <p>Mr. August said he discovered his craft-to-be at 10, while watching a rented tape of a black comedy, ''The War of the Roses.'' It occurred to him that ''everything the actors were saying and doing was written someplace. So I tried to write down the dialogue and find out what that was like.''</p>
        <p>He studied advertising and journalism at Drake University in Iowa, attended a summer film program at Stanford and was accepted at U.S.C.'s prestigious two-year graduate program in film production. After graduation, in the late 90's, three breaks fell his way in about a year and a half: he sold ''Go''; his agent sent him ''Big Fish,'' a Southern novel by Daniel Wallace; and Columbia asked him to join the dozen or so writers who were trying to salvage a film version of the 1970's television series ''Charlie's Angels.'' Mr. August said yes with an exclamation point. He set out to write an affectionate ''giant hug'' to the show he'd grown up with, celebrating the Angels' duality: three women (Drew Barrymore, Cameron Diaz and Lucy Lu) who were ''incredibly proficient on their jobs, and giant dorks when they were off the job.''</p>
        <p>''Because comedy isn't about cool people,'' he said. ''Comedy is about dorks and idiots.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. August had fallen in love with ''Big Fish,'' which tells the story of a larger-than-life father through his son's eyes. The narrator is about the same age that Mr. August was when his own father died. Mr. Burton was brought on to ''Big Fish'' and developed a fondness for Mr. August's ability to write sweetly without falling into the ditch of sentimentality.</p>
        <p>''That was the tricky thing he did very well,'' Mr. Burton said. ''With families, you can go through years of therapy and not know what it's about. His great gift is capturing those things that are quite difficult to discuss.''</p>
        <p>Mr. August said his sexual orientation has helped him notice things others miss, because for the first 20 years of his life, he said, he was ''observing the world and trying to model my behavior to look as straight as possible. It's sort of this psychological 'CSI' you're doing on a daily basis. You're always looking for motivation.''</p>
        <p>But he's not especially eager to write a gay-themed picture. ''I suspect every gay screenwriter has a big gay-catharsis movie inside them,'' he said. ''But then you go to a gay film festival and you see everyone else has done their movie, and there's not a pressing need for you to do yours.''</p>
        <p>Some fans of Mr. August's work pine for more of his unconventional ''Go'' sensibility and less of his fascination with pop culture icons. They took some satisfaction last year when he was nominated in the best-adapted-screenplay category by the British Academy of Film and Television Arts for ''Big Fish'' and nominated in the worst-screenplay category for the ''Charlie's Angels'' sequel by a Hollywood group that honors ''raspberries.''</p>
        <p>Mr. August regards this dichotomy with a smile. He can afford it. On his side are not just the film executives who keep giving him work but also the acolytes on his Web site, who get to listen in as he finds writing lessons everywhere. A few weeks ago, he was picking up dinner at a fast-food place when he saw a man holding tight to the roof rack of an S.U.V. while the woman driving it tried to pull out of the parking lot.</p>
        <p>''Here's my thought process,'' he typed the next morning. First, he recalled, he wondered if the man and woman even knew each other. Was he harassing her? Was she skipping out on the parking charge?</p>
        <p>Then, ''John August Concerned Citizen slowly reverted into John August Screenwriter,'' he wrote, ''as I tried to construct scenarios to explain what had just happened.'' He thought through a Parking Lot Attendant scene, a Furious Boyfriend scene, an Eerily Calm Stalker, a Random Psycho.</p>
        <p>Then he tried to decide what genre it was: ''If you put Will Ferrell in the guy's role, clinging to the side of an S.U.V., then it's a comedy,'' he wrote. ''Hugh Grant, and it's a romantic comedy. Sean Penn, and it's a thriller.''</p>
        <p>And if you put John August in the observation deck, it's yet another learning opportunity.</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 29, 2005, Sunday  A picture caption last Sunday with an article about the screenwriter John August referred incorrectly to the opening of ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,'' which he adapted from the Roald Dahl novel. It is scheduled for July 15, as the article said, not next month.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 5, 2005, Sunday  An article on May 22 about the screenwriter John August misstated his age at the time he watched a videotape of the 1989 film ''The War of the Roses,'' an experience that he says inspired his career choice. He was 18, not 10.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 29, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Sunday with an article about the screenwriter John August referred incorrectly to the opening of ''Charlie and the Chocolate Factory,'' which he adapted from the Roald Dahl novel. It is scheduled for July 15, as the article said, not next month.</p>
        <p>Correction: June 5, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on May 22 about the screenwriter John August misstated his age at the time he watched a videotape of the 1989 film ''The War of the Roses,'' an experience that he says inspired his career choice. He was 18, not 10.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
