<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dead Merchant of Venice</title>
    <meta content="22CRIMEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/22/books/review/22CRIMEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRIME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7D91030F931A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dead Merchant of Venice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dead Merchant of Venice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Christmas lights are up and shoppers are thronging the busy outdoor market at Campo Santo Stefano in Donna Leon's BLOOD FROM A STONE (Atlantic Monthly, $23). But there is nothing festive about the wintry views of Venice in Leon's bleakly beautiful story, which opens with the brazen murder of an African street peddler and closes with a cynical shrug at the hopelessly corrupt state of Italian government.</p>
        <p>Commissario Guido Brunetti, the philosophical police detective in Leon's politically topical series, doesn't know where to begin when he is assigned to investigate the professional assassination of a vu cumprà, one among hundreds of illegal African aliens who stand outside fashionable shops after business hours to sell knockoff designer handbags to tourists. Although an annoyance to merchants, these undocumented clandestini are generally tolerated by the Venetians, who take a live-and-let-live attitude toward them, and are ignored by local police authorities, who assume they are under the control and protection of organized crime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The detective becomes as pragmatic as any wily shopkeeper on the Rialto about working outside the system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Christmas lights are up and shoppers are thronging the busy outdoor market at Campo Santo Stefano in Donna Leon's BLOOD FROM A STONE (Atlantic Monthly, $23). But there is nothing festive about the wintry views of Venice in Leon's bleakly beautiful story, which opens with the brazen murder of an African street peddler and closes with a cynical shrug at the hopelessly corrupt state of Italian government.</p>
        <p>Commissario Guido Brunetti, the philosophical police detective in Leon's politically topical series, doesn't know where to begin when he is assigned to investigate the professional assassination of a vu cumprà, one among hundreds of illegal African aliens who stand outside fashionable shops after business hours to sell knockoff designer handbags to tourists. Although an annoyance to merchants, these undocumented clandestini are generally tolerated by the Venetians, who take a live-and-let-live attitude toward them, and are ignored by local police authorities, who assume they are under the control and protection of organized crime.</p>
        <p>Once the investigation is under way, Brunetti becomes aware of the complex role the vu cumprà play in Italy's underground economy -- from the tax-free income they generate for local landlords to the leather factories they keep humming in Puglia. Because the commissario is a compassionate soul, he is also stirred by the hardship of their lives and dismayed by the casual prejudice against them that he detects in a younger generation that includes his own adolescent daughter. And, because he is an intelligent man, he is struck by the injustice of it all. ''How arrogant we were,'' he says of the early Western world's plundering of the African continent, ''and how arrogant we remain.''</p>
        <p>But Brunetti is still, after all, a Venetian; and once he realizes the murdered man was not what he seemed, the detective becomes as pragmatic as any wily shopkeeper on the Rialto about working outside the system. Told that the Foreign Ministry has taken an interest in the case and warned by his superior that ''we have to leave this alone,'' he employs his native skills at subterfuge, trickery and deceit to carry on his inquiries, lest the homicide turn into another example of insabbiatura, which translates as ''the burying of an inconvenient case in the sand.''</p>
        <p>Although Brunetti takes neither pride nor pleasure in his cloak-and-dagger activities, readers will enjoy the paradoxical way in which justice is served in Venice -- by ignoring the law and doing the right thing the wrong way. Everyone in Brunetti's circle of confederates resorts to these stealth tactics, from his loyal secretary, Signorina Elettra, whose illegal hacking skills are legendary, to the kindly priest on San Zan Degolà, who robs the parish treasury to minister to his flock of needy immigrants. ''At times,'' Leon tells us, ''Brunetti asked himself why he bothered with official police channels at all.'' In this subtle and sophisticated mystery, that is not a rhetorical question.</p>
        <p>The spare, emotionally eloquent style of Chris Knopf's first novel, THE LAST REFUGE (Permanent Press, $26), gives shapely form to the confessional story narrated by Sam Acquillo, a 52-year-old systems engineer who has opted out of his fast-track life and gone to seed at his parents' summer cottage -- more of a shack, actually -- on Little Peconic Bay in the Long Island resort town of Southampton. ''It bothered me that people considered lightheartedness and optimism the norm,'' says this reclusive hero, who has spent the past four years drinking alone, tinkering with his father's '67 Pontiac Grand Prix and brooding on ''the desperate hopelessness of human existence.'' Sam is drawn out of his self-pitying gloom when the crabby old lady in the next cottage drowns in her bathtub, and he lets a local cop talk him into serving as the administrator of her estate. Not that he's looking for trouble, but the death looks fishy to Sam, who has a suspicious mind and knows a thing or two about waterfront property values. While his low-key investigation is only minimally suspenseful, the characters he chats up are such original oddballs and their conversation so bracing that you want to kick off your shoes and spend some time on the porch with them, just taking in the view and enjoying the talk.</p>
        <p>Poverty, starvation, disease and the vicious abuse of the weak and helpless -- William Murdoch, the sympathetic Toronto police officer in Maureen Jennings's late-Victorian mysteries, has seen the suffering and wept for it all. In NIGHT'S CHILD (McClelland &amp; Stewart, paper, $18.95), the fifth novel in this remarkably unsentimental series, the humane detective is shaken by yet another social abomination: the exploitation of children in the underground pornography trade. Murdoch is made aware of the matter by Amy Slade, a teacher at an elementary school where children show up, if they show up at all, tired, hungry, sick and covered with bruises. A so-called New Woman, who dresses in ''odd but practical trousers,'' Miss Slade has discovered salacious photos of one of her pupils, the 13-year-old Agnes Fisher, who is now missing. While well-observed characters like Miss Slade lend humanity to the melodramatic events, realistic scenes set in private homes (where grieving families lay out their dead for portrait artists) and public places (like the Mechanics Institute, where Murdoch's current lady friend competes in a World Typewriting Competition) bring to life a violent but vital society of astonishing contradictions.</p>
        <p>From the Department of Pretentious Prologues: Authors who insist on opening their narratives with portentous (and laboriously written) introductions have only themselves to blame when we bail out before getting to Chapter 1. Take Harlan Coben: ''You never meant to kill him. Your name is Matt Hunter. You are 20 years old. You grew up in an upper-middle-class suburb in northern New Jersey, not far from Manhattan. You live on the poorer side of town, but it's a pretty wealthy town. Your parents work hard and love you unconditionally. You are a middle child.'' Top that!</p>
        <p>CRIME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
