<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="20FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DA1E31F933A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Macedonia Talks Stalled; Mediators May Be Called In  Political leaders from various factions remained deadlocked after four days of intensive negotiations over the conflict with ethnic Albanian rebels, raising the possibility, foreign diplomats said, that international mediators might be summoned to break the impasse. The government has called a cease-fire until June 25, and the rebels have announced their own until June 27, but clashes have continued and shooting could be heard on the outskirts of the capital, Skopje.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Belgrade May Balk on Hague  A top Yugoslav official said the government might withdraw a bill on cooperating with the United Nations war crimes court, after the junior coalition partner, the Socialist People's Party of Montenegro, said it would vote against it.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Macedonia Talks Stalled; Mediators May Be Called In  Political leaders from various factions remained deadlocked after four days of intensive negotiations over the conflict with ethnic Albanian rebels, raising the possibility, foreign diplomats said, that international mediators might be summoned to break the impasse. The government has called a cease-fire until June 25, and the rebels have announced their own until June 27, but clashes have continued and shooting could be heard on the outskirts of the capital, Skopje.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Belgrade May Balk on Hague  A top Yugoslav official said the government might withdraw a bill on cooperating with the United Nations war crimes court, after the junior coalition partner, the Socialist People's Party of Montenegro, said it would vote against it.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Compensation for Nazi Slaves  Thousands of Nazi-era slave laborers were sent $4,400 checks as the first payments from a $4.5 billion German compensation fund, more than half a century after the fact and following years of legal wrangling and delay. Victims are eligible to receive up to $6,600 each, depending on their wartime circumstances.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Sharon Welcome, Arafat Not  Prime Minister Ariel Sharon of Israel will meet with President Bush at the White House next week for their second face-to-face discussions since Mr. Sharon's election. Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, has not been invited to Washington by the administration, and officials made clear they had no pending plans to do so.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Syria Finishes Beirut Pullout  Syria has withdrawn 6,000 troops from the Beirut area, Lebanese officials said, ending decades of a military presence despised by Lebanese Christians. But Syrian troops remain elsewhere in Lebanon.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Yemen Acknowledges Arrests  Officials confirmed that they had arrested eight people suspected in a plot to bomb the American Embassy. Two others are being sought.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-20</p>
        <p>U.S. Explores Settlement Of Tobacco Industry Suit  The Bush administration took the first step toward seeking settlement of the multibillion-dollar civil lawsuit against the tobacco industry. Attorney General John Ashcroft notified lawmakers that he had named a team of lawyers to explore the possibility of a settlement.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Patients' Rights Bill Debate  The Senate began debate on a far-reaching bill to define patients' rights, but Republicans resisted swift action, saying they needed more time to study it. The legislation, sponsored by two Democrats, Edward M. Kennedy and John Edwards, and a Republican, John McCain, has triggered a large-scale political and lobbying war.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The new majority leader, Tom Daschle, seeking to break an impasse over Senate organization, said he would hold votes this week on two Republican proposals concerning the treatment of judicial nominees.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Agency Seeks Adviser on Gays  The Agriculture Department is advertising for a ''gay and lesbian program specialist'' to help improve working conditions for its gay employees. Gay rights advocates say they believed it is the first time that an administration has sought to hire someone to handle gay and lesbian issues in the federal workplace.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Federal Inmate Put to Death  Juan Raul Garza, 44, was executed by injection at the federal penitentiary in Terre Haute, Ind., for three murders, becoming the second federal inmate put to death in a week, after a hiatus of 38 years.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>'Road Rage' Pet Killing  Andrew Douglas Burnett, 27, was convicted of felony animal cruelty for throwing a small dog to its death in traffic during a dispute with its owner last year in San Jose, Calif. He faces up to three years in prison.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Online Propositions to Children  One in five children who go online regularly is approached by strangers for sex, a study said. Yet most of the young people say they are not bothered by the messages and ignore or block them, another study said.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Astoria Fire Is Traced To 2 Boys' Playful Accident  City fire investigators believe that the hardware store fire that killed three firefighters and seriously injured a fourth was the result of roughhousing by two teenage boys, who knocked over a can of gasoline, starting a deadly chain of events. No charges were filed, though officials did not rule out the possibility.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Guardian for Mayor's Children  A judge appointed a law guardian to give the two children of Mayor Giuliani and Donna Hanover a voice in the couple's increasingly rancorous and protracted divorce. The guardian will help devise a plan for a meeting between the children, Andrew, 15, and Caroline, 11, and the mayor's friend, Judith Nathan.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Councilman Defends Actions  City Councilman Thomas V. Ognibene acknowledged that he made calls on behalf of a building industry consultant at the center of a corruption inquiry, but he said his efforts were not out of the ordinary and that he never took any valuable gifts.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Uproar Over Murals' Removal  An international dispute has erupted in a Ukrainian city near Poland where workers from Yad Vashem, Israel's main Holocaust museum, chiseled fragments from a newly discovered series of wall paintings by Bruno Schulz, a Polish-Jewish writer, artist and Holocaust victim.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Ripken Calling It Quits  Cal Ripken, 40, the Baltimore Orioles icon who did not miss a game for more than 16 seasons, will retire.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Big Fine for Accounting Firm  The S.E.C. brought civil fraud charges against Arthur Andersen for flawed audits of Waste Management in the early and mid-1990's, and Andersen agreed to pay a $7 million penalty, the largest ever assessed against an accounting firm.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart Accused of Sex Bias  Six female employees of the nation's largest private employer filed a federal lawsuit accusing it of discriminating against women. The suit seeks class-action status.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Assessing Technology Stocks  A Merrill Lynch study of 37 technology stock favorites found that even at their current depressed levels, technology shares remained expensive. The findings suggest that the investor optimism that has lifted the Nasdaq 23 percent above its April lows may be premature.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq ended 4.03 points higher, at 1,992.66, after rising 68 points.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: At last, action on California; invitation to an arms race; the Boy Scout amendment; another iron man retires.</p>
        <p>Column: Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
