<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Buick, Synergy Is Spelled Woods</title>
    <meta content="20TOUR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/20/sports/20TOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1303128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buick Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Westchester Country Club</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3DC1E31F933A15755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Buick, Synergy Is Spelled Woods</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses preparations for Buick Classic golf tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no better recipe for a golf tournament's success than the presence of Tiger Woods, who is playing at the Buick Classic in Harrison, N.Y., for the first time since 1997, when he finished in a tie for 43rd place.</p>
        <p>Woods causes tickets sales to accelerate, ratings to soar and hearts to leap -- all that would seem to matter to tournament economics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no better recipe for a golf tournament's success than the presence of Tiger Woods, who is playing at the Buick Classic in Harrison, N.Y., for the first time since 1997, when he finished in a tie for 43rd place.</p>
        <p>Woods causes tickets sales to accelerate, ratings to soar and hearts to leap -- all that would seem to matter to tournament economics.</p>
        <p>The sellout of 22,000 tickets for Friday's second round represents a first for the 34-year-old event. And there are not many tickets left for the remaining days.</p>
        <p>Robert Dale Morgan, the vice president of championship golf for the PGA Tour, said that although the Tiger effect has not been measured, Woods's decision to play, as well as the presence of four of the other eight top players in the world, and a weeks-long local advertising campaign, contributed to the sales.</p>
        <p>So if marketing Woods works so well, why is the PGA Tour trying to expand the appeal of the tournament, the biggest sports event in Westchester, into New York City?</p>
        <p>In part, to guard against the years when he does not appear at the Westchester Country Club. Like any other tournament, the Buick needs to prove itself to golf fans every year, and one way to do that is to expand its appeal southward.</p>
        <p>And, Peter Mele, the tournament director, said additional parking, more shuttle buses from train stations and parking lots, and extra security were in the works before Woods agreed to play.</p>
        <p>''It's a simple goal,'' Morgan said. ''To build a model where a television network and league can focus on an event, and have an impact on a particular market. The Buick is in New York. So are ABC and ESPN. Hopefully, what people will see is a bigger, better Buick Classic.''</p>
        <p>The Tour's planning began late last year -- months before Woods confirmed that he would play in the Buick Classic -- in meetings with ABC and ESPN officials.</p>
        <p>''The notion was how do we take the assets of the Walt Disney Company and make them go to work for the Buick Classic,'' Ed Erhardt, the president of ESPN-ABC Sports Sales said. ESPN is carrying the tournament tomorrow and Friday, followed by ABC's coverage Saturday and Sunday.</p>
        <p>This tournament represents Woods's broad appeal. He is a spokesman for Disney, whose networks are televising the tournament, and Buick, which sponsors it.</p>
        <p>Among the elements of the PGA Tour-Disney campaign are: a 30-minute highlight show on Channel 7 Thursday and Friday nights; segments on ABC's ''Good Morning America'' (the program's Jack Ford will play in today's pro-am with Woods) and ''The View,'' with Star Jones; on-site reports by ESPN's ''SportsCenter'' and forecasts by a Channel 7 weatherman; promotional events at the ESPN Zone in Times Square; the use of promotional e-mail messages from ESPN.com; and advertising on WABC-AM, Radio Disney, ABC Radio and WPLJ-FM.</p>
        <p>''New York has a significant amount of sports,'' Erhardt said, ''and this is a way for ABC, ESPN and the PGA Tour to puncture the collective consciousness of the New York sports fan.''</p>
        <p>The campaign is designed to elevate the tournament's suburban image and raise the tournament's moderate profile to advertisers, fans and viewers. The Buick is not a major, like the Masters or the United States Open, so it not only has to break out of the clutter of New York sports and entertainment options, but out of the weekly golf mix.</p>
        <p>And in an attempt to, at least temporarily, expand its political presence outside Harrison, the PGA Tour will hold a reception tonight, 26 miles away, at Gracie Mansion, its host Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who was to play with Woods today in the pro-am.</p>
        <p>Giuliani is closely identified with attending Yankee games, but Morgan said that Giuliani made Gracie Mansion available because the PGA Tour and Buick Classic sponsored the Mayor's Fleet Week golf tournament last month in Queens. And even though the Buick Classic is not in one of the five boroughs, the mayor is nonetheless looking to attract golf tournaments to the city and to lure more tourists.</p>
        <p>Still, the effort to expand the Buick Classic's appeal would not likely be as effective without Woods's appearance.</p>
        <p>Yet the tournament cannot expect him in Harrison any time after this year's tournament.</p>
        <p>Mele, the tournament director, said: ''This year, we'll have people who haven't been here for a long time, or have never been here, largely because of Tiger. Hopefully, once they're here, they'll think it's a great place to come in the future, Tiger or not.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
