<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>13 Years Later, an Arrest in a Manhattan Doctor's Slaying</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="703154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLUMBIA-PRESBYTERIAN MEDICAL CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCDOWELL, PATRICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOOD, JOHN CHASE JR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIORGIO, JERRY (DETECTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7DC1439F932A05754C0A962958260" item-length="1554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>13 Years Later, an Arrest in a Manhattan Doctor's Slaying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly 13 years ago, Dr. John Chase Wood Jr., a 31-year-old resident in surgery at Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center, was accosted by three young men as he strode back to the hospital from dinner at home nearby with his pregnant wife.</p>
        <p>One brandished a gun, and they demanded his money. Dr. Wood, a tall, husky man who played spirited rugby and elegant classics and jazz on the French horn,  apparently resisted, and there was a brief scuffle. One shot was fired, and Dr.  Wood, struck in the heart, died an hour later in the hospital where he worked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly 13 years ago, Dr. John Chase Wood Jr., a 31-year-old resident in surgery at Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center, was accosted by three young men as he strode back to the hospital from dinner at home nearby with his pregnant wife.</p>
        <p>One brandished a gun, and they demanded his money. Dr. Wood, a tall, husky man who played spirited rugby and elegant classics and jazz on the French horn,  apparently resisted, and there was a brief scuffle. One shot was fired, and Dr.  Wood, struck in the heart, died an hour later in the hospital where he worked.</p>
        <p>The assailants took his wallet -- a few credit cards and $5 in cash -- and fled from a moment of madness that destroyed a promising life, shattered a family, stunned colleagues and friends and stirred outrage in a city that had seen too much senseless killing.</p>
        <p>Scores of detectives joined an investigation that went on for months. In the  meantime, the doctor's widow, Diana Newton Wood, gave birth to a boy in March 1982. But gradually the leads and headlines faded, and hopes for tracing the suspects dwindled. Even so, Detective Jerry Giorgio never gave up.</p>
        <p>And yesterday, after years of checking hundreds of sources and leads, 30-year-old Patrick McDowell, an unemployed Washington Heights janitor who spent 10 of the last 13 years in prison for another killing, was charged with the murder of Dr. Wood.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDowell, married and the father of three children, was seized by the police after a foot chase Friday morning and was found in possession of a gun and two bags of marijuana, the police said. After long questioning in which he may have tripped himself up, the police hinted, he was charged early yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Crucial Link</p>
        <p>"I've often described this case as a big jigsaw puzzle," Detective Giorgio said at a news conference at the 34th Precinct station house. "It came down to talking to neighborhood people -- friends and associates of the suspect -- and hoping at some point that a person might just walk in wishing to discuss the case."</p>
        <p>But in the end, it was apparently the suspect himself who provided the police with the crucial missing piece. "McDowell made a statement -- it was not a confession," Detective Giorgio said. He declined to give details, but the suspect apparently said something that the police felt no one but the killer might have known.</p>
        <p>Relatives of Mr. McDowell expressed doubt yesterday that he had killed Dr. Wood. They acknowledged that his past had been troubled, but said he had become a Jehovah's Witness since his release from prison in April 1992 and had held various jobs, including one as a cleaner at Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center -- an assertion that was denied by the hospital and was not confirmed by  the police.</p>
        <p>Mr. McDowell had long been a suspect in the case. Detective Giorgio said he came to his attention early in 1982, when he questioned him in another killing,  and had since closely tracked his movements, in and out of prison. He also said  investigators believed that Mr. McDowell fired the shot that killed the doctor,  and that they had identified the two other suspects, who are still being sought.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wood's widow, now an anesthesiologist at a Boston hospital, was told of the arrest, as were his parents, who live in Yardley, Pa. Diana Wood yesterday recalled days of trauma in the aftermath of her husband's killing and years of struggle to raise a child and rebuild her life with the help of relatives and friends of the slain doctor, whose life and career at the time of his death appeared to hold outstanding promise.</p>
        <p>Wife Was a Nurse</p>
        <p>A graduate of Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons, he had been a pediatric resident at Presbyterian Hospital for three years and a resident in surgery for two years, and planned to specialize in pediatric surgery. His wife, a nurse at the hospital, was five months pregnant with their  first child.</p>
        <p>At 8:45 P.M. on Nov. 2, 1981, clad in his physician's white jacket and trousers and a green surgical shirt, he was returning to work at the hospital at 168th Street and Broadway from dinner at his apartment nearby when the thugs approached him on Riverside Drive at 165th Street, one drew a .22-caliber pistol and the robbery and fatal shooting occurred.</p>
        <p>While the killers escaped, a half-dozen witnesses to the shooting were found  by police officers canvassing the neighborhood. They were unable to identify possible suspects from police photo files, however, and within months the trail  seemed to grow cold.</p>
        <p>In February 1982, Detective Giorgio, then a member of the Manhattan homicide  squad, arrested Mr. McDowell, then 18, for killing Gina Martin, a Playboy bunny, in a robbery in the lobby of her apartment building on East 55th Street on Dec.  10, 1981. Mr. McDowell admitted shooting the woman but called it an accident, pleaded guilty to manslaughter and drew a 10-year prison term.</p>
        <p>The sentence was served in various state prisons, including the Fishkill Correctional Facility, where relatives said Mr. McDowell took college courses and in 1990 received a certificate in juvenile justice from Marist College in Poughkeepsie. His brother-in-law, David Williams, said Mr. McDowell made the dean's list in 1989.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of Interviews</p>
        <p>While Mr. McDowell gave his address as 800 Riverside Drive, where some of his relatives live, Mr. Williams said he actually lives elsewhere in the area with his wife, Carmella, and three children, a 13-year-old girl and 2-year-old and 4-month-old boys.</p>
        <p>Detective Giorgio, 60, a 35-year police veteran who joined the 34th Precinct  eight years ago and worked on Dr. Wood's murder with Detective Robert Small, gave few details yesterday of the effort to track Mr. McDowell, beyond saying that the investigation involved hundreds of interviews with potential witnesses, countless hours of surveillance and cooperation by state parole authorities and  other police agencies.</p>
        <p>The arrest appeared to mark the end of an obsession. "I didn't think about it every day," the detective said, but he added, "I certainly thought about it every week." Many times, he said, he took his thick file on the case to prosecutors for review, only to be told to get more evidence.</p>
        <p>Detective Giorgio said the break came unexpectedly Friday morning after two 34th Precinct police officers, William Mendez and James Hosey, were told by a group of people on a corner in Washington Heights that a man in a gray suit and  red tie had just threatened them with a 9-millimeter pistol.</p>
        <p>Several blocks away, they saw a suspect, who fled at their approach. They jumped out of their car, gave chase and captured Mr. McDowell in front of 504 West 157th Street. Nearby, they said, they found a discarded 9-millimeter pistol and in the suspect's pocket two bags of marijuana.</p>
        <p>Detective Giorgio soon learned that the man he suspected in Dr. Wood's murder had been picked up, and joined in interviewing the suspect throughout the day at the 34th Precinct station house. Shortly after midnight Mr. McDowell was taken to central booking at One Police Plaza in lower Manhattan.</p>
        <p>There he was charged with second-degree murder and robbery in Dr. Wood's death, and with possession of a weapon and marijuana.</p>
        <p>The police said they had roughly known Mr. McDowell's whereabouts and had made enough progress in their investigation that they would have arrested him within weeks. But proceeding with the gun charge first might have complicated a  murder case, they said, so they charged him with murder right away. "There was no way I wanted to lose him in the court system," Detective Giorgio said.</p>
        <p>Relatives, including Mr. McDowell's brother-in-law, Mr. Williams, expressed skepticism over the allegations. They said he had not been in trouble since his  release from prison, insisted he had nothing to do with drugs or guns, and said  that his troubled life had been lifted by commitments to education and religion.</p>
        <p>'Mountain Out of a Molehill'</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams said Mr. McDowell hoped to help troubled youths and recently registered for September classes at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice. His arrest, Mr. Williams said, had stunned the family. "We're in shock," he said. "We don't want nothing to happen to him. Because of what he's been through in the past they can take little things that happen and make a mountain out of a molehill."</p>
        <p>But to Detective Giorgio, the arrest was the end of a long quest. "I think it's a rhetorical question," he said when asked about his feelings. Then, beaming, he added: "Just look at me and you can tell."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
