<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="621499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D91231F937A25754C0A965958260" item-length="889" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ron Alexander</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OVERHEARD by R. Chester Redhead in an outdoor cafe on upper Madison Avenue. Mother to boy, about 6: "Hurry and finish your soup before it gets dirty."</p>
        <p>Overheard by Elizabeth Hunter in the cafe at the recently renovated Jewish Museum. Gray-haired woman, almost certainly a tourist, to gray-haired man: "Ellis Island was nice, but the Statue of Liberty I could have done without."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OVERHEARD by R. Chester Redhead in an outdoor cafe on upper Madison Avenue. Mother to boy, about 6: "Hurry and finish your soup before it gets dirty."</p>
        <p>Overheard by Elizabeth Hunter in the cafe at the recently renovated Jewish Museum. Gray-haired woman, almost certainly a tourist, to gray-haired man: "Ellis Island was nice, but the Statue of Liberty I could have done without."</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Last week I was in Katz's, the delicatessen on the Lower East Side, and as I ordered a couple of sandwiches at the counter, I instinctively took out a dollar bill to tip the counter man.</p>
        <p>I had learned this time-honored technique from my father, who started taking me to Katz's when I was a kid. He would order a sandwich and then tap a quarter on the counter, indicating to the gruff-looking fellow on the other side that there was a little something extra in it for him if he piled on a few more slices of corned beef.</p>
        <p>Some 30 years and much inflation later, the going rate for a Katz's tip is about a buck or two for two sandwiches. The amount may have changed, but the effect is still the same.</p>
        <p>As I found a table and cracked open a bottle of Dr. Brown's cream soda, I thought about this valuable piece of New York City information and the person I had learned it from.</p>
        <p>Other kids' dads taught them how to play second base or how to figure out higher mathematics. My dad taught me how to order a decent corned beef sandwich. WARREN SHOULBERG</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>HOME MOVIES AND ME Charlie Chan and No. 1 Son were always on some case; the Whistler stalked a dark street though you never saw his face. There was Veronica Lake and Alan Ladd  and William Bendix being bad; and somewhere outside was World War II and rationing and meatless stew and terrible problems across the sea but you couldn't prove it from my movies and me. ED ROSSMANN</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>A busy corner on Wall Street. Jack Grubel stops to make a phone call. There on top of the phone is a small camera. Expecting a frantic owner to rush by, Mr. Grubel waits for someone in distress. But he waits in vain. His windfall: a 35-millimeter point-and-shoot camera with a German name. Only a few shots remain on the film. What has caught the eyes of what is probably a foreign family visiting New York? A few days later Mr. Grubel has his answer in 27 photos.</p>
        <p>Start the odyssey with a Park Avenue street scene and then proceed in this order: surrey near the Plaza; the entrance of the Gainsborough Studios on Central Park South; woman posing by a Jackie Mason poster; the entrance of The New York Times; Empire State Building; outlandishly garbed store mannequins; Central Park jogging path; youngster basking in F.A.O. Schwarz teddy bear corner (three shots); Statue of Liberty ferry excursion; woman in green Liberty headdress; Trinity Church; Stock Exchange entrance.</p>
        <p>Then, apparently, a stop to make a phone call.  Then: "Honey, you left it where?" Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>The time has come to tell about my latest telephone reservations call.</p>
        <p>When I made a dinner reservation at Montrachet, the restaurant in TriBeCa, the young woman who took the call asked if we preferred smoking or nonsmoking. "Oh, definitely nonsmoking," I said. "One of our party has asthma and a second person has breathing problems of her own."</p>
        <p>With warm and sincere sympathy, our reservation-taker said: "I know how it is. I have asthma myself. I'll put you in severe Nonsmoking." And so she did. ALICE LIPTON ECKSTEIN</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Sign, spotted by Lola Troy Fiur, near the up escalator on the fourth floor of Bloomingdale's: GIORGIO ARMANI  IS TEMPORARILY  LOCATED  BEHIND  CALVIN KLEIN  Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>It is one of the more uncomfortable of recent afternoons. Wearing a tan poplin suit on a downtown E train, I am trying my best to remain natty despite the soaring thermometer. Barely penetrating my consciousness is the huckstering of a subway merchant selling a radio. After a few seconds I realize that he has picked me as his target market.</p>
        <p>"Hey you! You want to buy a radio?"</p>
        <p>"No thank you," I reply. There is the briefest of pauses and then the unique selling point. "It plays Beethoven!" DENNIS P. McGUIRE</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>After hearing so many voice-mail instructions in the last few years, I tend to become discouraged at the long lists of instructions that never seem to apply to my situation. But the other day I heard one that confirmed my faith in the people behind the machines.</p>
        <p>I was phoning a publishing company, and the message started in the usual fashion with a voice droning "Press 1 if you would like to order a specific publication, press 2 if you have a question about an invoice." I was listening halfheartedly when the last option caught my attention with "Press 6 if you would like to speak with a sales representative, if you are thoroughly confused or if you would like to speak with a thoroughly confused representative.</p>
        <p>Sometimes there's hope. EMMY WYATT Metropolitan Diary welcomes contributions of short anecdotes, observations and light verse about life in the New York region. Unused material cannot be returned unless accompanied by a stamped, self-addressed envelope.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
