<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Within a Florida Civics Lesson, Rich Stories</title>
    <meta content="641316SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1402178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sunshine State (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DB1339F932A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Within a Florida Civics Lesson, Rich Stories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gazing across an immaculate Florida golf course that used to be a swamp, Murray Silver (Alan King), a multimillionaire developer, conjures the Florida dream of sunshine, orange groves and balmy breezes wafting through palm trees. Wearing the sly, imperious grin of a successful snake-oil peddler and waving his arms like a maestro, he proudly announces to his golfing partners, ''We created this nature on a leash.''</p>
        <p>This pungent little scene is a perfect prelude to John Sayles's ''Sunshine State,'' a spacious American epic that examines the world of Delrona Beach, a fictional Florida seacoast town in the throes of development. But as the movie widens its scope, it evokes the ugly flip side of nature on a leash: strip malls, fast-food outlets, environmental destruction, the uprooting of stable communities and the Disneyfication of history. The deeper the movie delves into the forces that threaten to tear apart this nondescript town somewhere south of Jacksonville, the more Delrona Beach looms as a microcosm of not only Florida but also the United States wherever greedy developers stake their claims in the name of progress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gazing across an immaculate Florida golf course that used to be a swamp, Murray Silver (Alan King), a multimillionaire developer, conjures the Florida dream of sunshine, orange groves and balmy breezes wafting through palm trees. Wearing the sly, imperious grin of a successful snake-oil peddler and waving his arms like a maestro, he proudly announces to his golfing partners, ''We created this nature on a leash.''</p>
        <p>This pungent little scene is a perfect prelude to John Sayles's ''Sunshine State,'' a spacious American epic that examines the world of Delrona Beach, a fictional Florida seacoast town in the throes of development. But as the movie widens its scope, it evokes the ugly flip side of nature on a leash: strip malls, fast-food outlets, environmental destruction, the uprooting of stable communities and the Disneyfication of history. The deeper the movie delves into the forces that threaten to tear apart this nondescript town somewhere south of Jacksonville, the more Delrona Beach looms as a microcosm of not only Florida but also the United States wherever greedy developers stake their claims in the name of progress.</p>
        <p>''Sunshine State,'' which opens today in Manhattan and Los Angeles, may be the most far-reaching civics lesson ever crammed into a 2-hour-21-minute film. But more important, it creates a cinematic mosaic of American lives unprecedented in its range, balance, subtlety and even-handedness. More than a dozen indelible characters are woven into Mr. Sayles's multigenerational, multicultural tapestry. By the end of the film you feel you've not only touched the soul of each one but also tasted some salty essence of our national life. A crucial ingredient of that essence, the movie suggests, is a nagging, unappeasable restlessness that may be the emotional engine driving American capitalism.</p>
        <p>Several of the performances in this beautifully written and acted film are small revelations. The closest thing to a central character is Marly Temple (Edie Falco), a sardonic, quick-witted young woman who runs her family business, the Sea-Vue Motel, a slightly shabby but strategically located hostelry that rival developers are itching to purchase and tear down. From her tired Florida twang to her slumped posture to her slightly sour squint, Ms. Falco's Marly is so fully realized that not a drop of her signature role on ''The Sopranos'' is allowed to leak into her performance.</p>
        <p>A former mermaid in a local aqua show, Marly is divorced from Steve (Richard Edson), the oafish leader of a defunct rock band named Skeeter Meter (a kind of Lynyrd Skynrd manqu). Steve now ekes out a living impersonating a Union soldier at a local historical attraction and dreams of owning and operating a water slide.</p>
        <p>When Marly's younger boyfriend, Scotty (Marc Blucas), announces he's about to leave town to pursue his dream of becoming a golf pro, she falls into an aimless romance with Jack Meadows (Timothy Hutton), a lonely, peripatetic landscape architect who transforms swampland into upscale suburban environments.</p>
        <p>The movie is organized around the histories of two families: one white (the Temples), the other black (the Stokeses). Marly's grandly histrionic mother, Delia Temple (Jane Alexander), known as ''the Sarah Bernhardt of Delrona Beach,'' runs the community theater and is a devout environmentalist. Delia's husband, Furman (Ralph Waite), who founded the motel, is a genial, partially blind curmudgeon whose rants about how the world is going to hell attest to his still-vigorous fighting spirit.</p>
        <p>The Stokeses are headed by Eunice (Mary Alice), the proud, stiff-backed widow of a revered pillar of Lincoln Beach, a black-owned middle-class enclave that the developers are scheming to obliterate. When Eunice's daughter Desiree (Angela Bassett), exiled in disgrace 25 years earlier, shows up with her husband, Reggie Perry (James McDaniel), an anesthesiologist, the scars of old family wounds are ripped open.</p>
        <p>The film's most wrenching encounters are Eunice and Desiree's embittered, walking-on-eggshells dialogues that reveal how the mother's strait-laced morality and obsession with respectability drove her beautiful, rebellious daughter to become pregnant at 15. After being hastened out of town to stay with an aunt in Georgia, Desiree went north and built a career doing infomercials.</p>
        <p>The kind of mother-daughter strife that seems so cutely contrived in ''Divine Secrets of the Ya-Ya Sisterhood'' here feels achingly real. The flashes of resentment, sorrow and lingering affection exchanged by these two great actresses perfectly cast in their roles makes one of the most compelling emotional duels to be seen in a movie in quite a while.</p>
        <p>As the story begins, Eunice has taken Terrell Bernard (Alexander Lewis), a 13-year-old distant relative, under her wing. Traumatized by a family tragedy, this listless teenager has tendencies toward vandalism and pyromania, and he latches on to Reggie as a surrogate father.</p>
        <p>A third family, the Pickneys, is more sketchily drawn. Earl (Gordon Clapp), a suicidal county commissioner, is battling a gambling addiction that has left him susceptible to bribery. His fussy, high-strung wife, Francine (Mary Steenburgen), runs Buccaneer Days, a bogus local festival that involves a parade, make-believe pirates and a treasure hunt. Francine, who lends the film its brightest notes of comic relief, whines about how hard it is to ''invent a tradition'' and navely refers to her unstable husband as ''my rock.''</p>
        <p>Without forcing the connections, ''Sunshine State'' has most of its characters cross paths at one time or another, and their remarks constitute an informal community dialogue. If the movie has a moral center, it is Dr. Lloyd (Bill Cobbs), an African-American resident of Eunice's generation who has been around since the civil rights era and who tries with little success to goad the apathetic residents of Lincoln Beach into organizing against the developers.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lloyd's idealism is balanced by the pragmatism of Flash Phillips (Tom Wright), a college football legend, also African-American, who has been hired as a front man by a group of developers to buy property under his name. It is Flash who, when confronted with his own duplicity, delivers some of the film's saddest and most resonant lines: ''There's a handful of people who run the whole deal, and the rest of us who do what they say and get paid for it.''</p>
        <p>''Sunshine State'' isn't the first film by Mr. Sayles to imply a larger social view by focusing on a microcosm. ''Lone Star'' examined Texas, and ''Limbo'' explored Alaska. But ''Sunshine State'' has an authority and a breadth of vision that those worthy earlier films lack. In telling overlapping stories, it is Mr. Sayles's first film to convey the sweep of a top-drawer Robert Altman movie.</p>
        <p>There are huge differences of course between the two directors. Mr. Altman is an entertainer with a satirist's wink and a fondness for high drama, while Mr. Sayles is a social realist whose films have an essayistic weight. His scrupulous insistence on seeing every side of a political issue will make ''Sunshine State'' seem a little dry for those who expect the roller-coaster dips that an Altman film promises. And when ''Sunshine State'' reaches a crucial turning point, the fate of Delrona Beach is determined not by the characters' passions but by an act of God in which the past almost literally rises up from below. The lack of a human tragedy produces a slight letdown.</p>
        <p>But make no mistake. ''Sunshine State'' is a great film on its own sober, unflashy terms. As its conflicts unfold, you can only marvel at Mr. Sayles's skill at fashioning dialogue that is charged with competing ideas yet still sounds utterly natural coming out of its characters' mouths.</p>
        <p>For all its measured cool, ''Sunshine State'' isn't entirely detached. Here, as in all his films, Mr. Sayles shows himself a humanist who believes in the ability of ordinary people to change their lives for the better, if they will only rouse themselves. Except for the story's most rapacious developers, all his characters exhibit a strain of decency.</p>
        <p>At the same time ''Sunshine State'' is shot through with a profound sense of disappointment at the suffocating banality and shortsightedness of American popular culture. Is a tacky pageant like Buccaneer Days, in which clich pirates walk the plank into a plastic pool, really the best we can come up with when struggling to tell our history? Given the facts of that history, the movie suggests, it may be the only reality we are able to face.</p>
        <p>As two characters chat about the portrayal of Florida's discovery and settlement, the choice comes down to a Disney-style pageant of ''Indians, pirates and Spanish gold'' or ''mass murder, rape and slavery.'' As shallow and phony as the Disney version might be, how many people would willingly embrace the more truthful alternative?</p>
        <p>''Sunshine State'' is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned) for strong language and adult situations.</p>
        <p>SUNSHINE STATE</p>
        <p>Written, directed and edited by John Sayles; director of photography, Patrick Cady; music by Mason Daring; production designer, Mark Ricker; produced by Maggie Renzi; released by Sony Pictures Classics. Running time: 141 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Edie Falco (Marly Temple), Jane Alexander (Delia Temple), Ralph Waite (Furman Temple), Angela Bassett (Desiree Perry), James McDaniel (Reggie Perry), Mary Alice (Eunice Stokes), Bill Cobbs (Dr. Lloyd), Gordon Clapp (Earl Pickney), Mary Steenburgen (Francine Pickney), Timothy Hutton (Jack Meadows), Tom Wright (Flash Phillips), Marc Blucas (Scotty Duval), Miguel Ferrer (Lester), Charlayne Woodard (Loretta), Alan King (Murray Silver), Richard Edson (Steve Tregaskis) and Alexander Lewis (Terrell Bernard).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
