<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is It Sharpton to the Rescue? India-Pakistan Trip Is Set</title>
    <meta content="21SHAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/21/nyregion/21SHAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1402301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India/Kashmir and Jammu</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">India</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Kashmir and Jammu (India)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharpton, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7D7123FF932A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="429" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is It Sharpton to the Rescue? India-Pakistan Trip Is Set</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Is It Sharpton to the Rescue? India-Pakistan Trip Is Set</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a delicate situation. A six-decade-long border dispute with religious roots that reach back centuries. A million heavily armed troops massed along Himalayan mountain passes. Two third world powers tapping their fingers on nuclear buttons.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton is ready to go.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton will head to India and Pakistan next month to try to talk leaders of the two nations out of going to all-out war over Kashmir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a delicate situation. A six-decade-long border dispute with religious roots that reach back centuries. A million heavily armed troops massed along Himalayan mountain passes. Two third world powers tapping their fingers on nuclear buttons.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton is ready to go.</p>
        <p>If all goes as planned, Mr. Sharpton, the spotlight-loving civil rights advocate who is gearing up for a 2004 presidential run, will head to India and Pakistan next month to try to talk leaders of the two nations out of going to all-out war over Kashmir.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton said that as a follower of Mahatma Gandhi, who was, after all, from India, he felt morally bound to offer help.</p>
        <p>''The thought that the land where Gandhi lived and taught the world nonviolence could be the site of the first nuclear confrontation requires anyone who embraces his principles to make an appeal,'' Mr. Sharpton said yesterday.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the world, they are not so sure that a visit from Mr. Sharpton would have much effect on Indo-Pakistani relations.</p>
        <p>''I can tell you that in India he's going to have a tough time finding an appointment,'' Shekhar Gupta, editor in chief of The Indian Express, a national newspaper, said by phone from Punjab after a reporter explained to him who Mr. Sharpton was. ''I'm not sure that what the subcontinent needs is foreign moral authorities to tell them what's good and what's not good for them.''</p>
        <p>Besides, Mr. Gupta said: ''We in India claim to be a nation of one billion followers of Mahatma Gandhi, and I'm not sure we followed his teachings most of the time. One more disciple of Mahatma Gandhi is not going to be very much more reassuring a thought.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton claimed no particular insight into the tangled regional conflict. But, pointing to his three-month prison stint last year for protesting the United States Navy's bombing exercises in Puerto Rico, he defied anyone to challenge his credentials as a pacifist.</p>
        <p>''There's no expert on Southeast Asia that can match me on Gandhian philosophy and activism,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
