<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boxing;   Douglas Fills an Empty Plate</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB173DF931A25751C0A966958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boxing;   Douglas Fills an Empty Plate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT McG. THOMAS Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: He was a high school basketball player who played a year in junior college before following his father's footsteps into a professional ring career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: He was a high school basketball player who played a year in junior college before following his father's footsteps into a professional ring career.</p>
        <p>He was a high school basketball player who played a year in junior college before following his father's footsteps into a professional ring career.</p>
        <p>That was in 1981, but for James (Buster) Douglas, the road to boxing glory did not begin until three years later, and when it did, it began with an empty paper plate.</p>
        <p>The man who held it was John Johnson, the 45-year-old manager who is widely credited with turning Douglas from a talented but lackadaisical club fighter with an aversion to training into the determined professional who knocked out Mike Tyson in the 10th round of their heavyweight title bout in Tokyo yesterday.</p>
        <p>Johnson, who took over the fighter's career in 1984 after Douglas had run up an 18-2-1 record with 14 knockouts, mostly against lackluster opponents, recalled not long ago that it was Douglas's 24th birthday, April 7, when the fighter called him to ask if the manager would take him on.</p>
        <p>Loose-Knit Associates</p>
        <p>The two had known each other slightly since Douglas was a 10-year-old growing up in Columbus, Ohio, and Johnson, a native of West Virginia who had moved to Columbus when he was 12, was beginning to get a reputation in athletics there, first as a high school football coach and later as trainer and manager of fighters.</p>
        <p>Douglas's father had been a middleweight contender known as Billy (Dynamite) Douglas, who had done well enough in the ring to raise his family of four sons in comfortable circumstances and to inspire James, the oldest, to try his own hand at the sport.</p>
        <p>But after fighting from the age of 10 to 15, he quit to concentrate on basketball.</p>
        <p>Douglas, who is known for his decided gentleness, said he simply wasn't mean enough at the time.</p>
        <p>''My mom had to make me fight,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He lasted a year at Mercyhurst College in Erie, Pa., before returning to Columbus, where he resumed boxing and turned pro at the age of 21.</p>
        <p>''I'd seen him on the amateur level,'' Johnson said, ''and I definitely thought he was a great talent.'' But when the manager checked with friends about Douglas's professional career, he did not like what he heard: Douglas was known as a fighter who lacked passion for his profession and would not train.</p>
        <p>Even so, Johnson set up a meeting with the fighter at the manager's home. It was then, Johnson recalled, that he held up the paper plate.</p>
        <p>Million-Dollar Proposition</p>
        <p>''I told him that it was empty,'' he said, ''but if he paid the price, someday there'd be a million on it.''</p>
        <p>No one who saw Douglas yesterday could doubt that he had paid the price of rigorous training and conditioning, but for all Johnson's admonitions there were enough lapses along the way to keep many fans from giving Douglas a serious chance to defeat Tyson.</p>
        <p>Douglas's first fight under Johnson, a scheduled eight-rounder against Dave Starkey at a Columbus nightclub on July 9, 1984, turned into a fiasco. After Douglas landed the first blows, Starkey went down on one knee, then picked Douglas up and tried to throw him out of the ring. Both fighters were suspended and the bout was declared a one-round no contest.</p>
        <p>For his next fight, Douglas showed better form. Fighting on five days' notice he scored a 10-round decision over Randall Cobb in Las Vegas in November 1984, and then a first-round knockout of Dion Simpson in Atlantic City the following March.</p>
        <p>He was back to his old habits two months later, however, when he huffed his way to a loss to Jesse Ferguson during an ESPN tournament in Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>After upsetting a former champion, Greg Page, and taking decisions over David Jaco and Denovrell Collier during 1986, Douglas won a chance at the International Boxing Federation title. But in a fight against Tony Tucker for the championship that had been abandoned by Michael Spinks, Douglas was again out of shape. After dominating Tucker for most of the bout he tired noticeably in the 10th round and was knocked out.</p>
        <p>Coming that close to a title may have been the very lesson Douglas needed.</p>
        <p>Beginning with a second-round knockout of Donny Long in Columbus in November 1987, he won his next six fights decisively enough to qualify for a shot against Tyson, but not so desively that many fans gave him much of a chance at winning.</p>
        <p>Outside the ring, Douglas has been beset by a series of tragedies, including the loss of a brother, who died in an accidental shooting., Douglas, who has been separated from his wife since last September, has an 11-year-old son, Lamar, by another woman, who is terminally ill, and in Tokyo the boxer has seldom been seen without Lamar.</p>
        <p>Before the fight Douglas said he was dedicating the bout to his mother, who died on Jan. 18, three weeks before her son finally filled the empty paper plate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
