<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Results Plus</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mayotte</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD173DF931A25751C0A966958260" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Results Plus</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Skiing</p>
        <p>Two in a Row: Carole Merle showed yesterday that she was back in top form after a knee injury last season by winning her second super giant slalom in two days, in Meribel France. Merle was timed in 1 minute 7.51 seconds.(AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L.</p>
        <p>Blues 4, Sabres 2: Brett Hull's goal for St.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Skiing</p>
        <p>Two in a Row: Carole Merle showed yesterday that she was back in top form after a knee injury last season by winning her second super giant slalom in two days, in Meribel France. Merle was timed in 1 minute 7.51 seconds.(AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L.</p>
        <p>Blues 4, Sabres 2: Brett Hull's goal for St.</p>
        <p>Skiing</p>
        <p>Two in a Row: Carole Merle showed yesterday that she was back in top form after a knee injury last season by winning her second super giant slalom in two days, in Meribel France. Merle was timed in 1 minute 7.51 seconds.(AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L.</p>
        <p>Blues 4, Sabres 2: Brett Hull's goal for St. Louis extended his scoring streak to a team-record 20 games. The previous record, 19, was set by Blake Dunlop in the 1980-81 season. (AP)</p>
        <p>Penguins 4, Flyers 1: Mario Lemieux extended his near-record point-scoring streak to 46 games with a second-period goal as Pittsburgh won at the Spectrum in Philadelphia for only the 8th time in 70 games.(AP)</p>
        <p>Canucks 4, Bruins 2: Petri Skriko and Paul Reinhart scored goals 56 seconds apart midway through the second period yesterday as Vancouver got its first victory in Boston since Dec. 13, 1980.(AP)</p>
        <p>Capitals 5, North Stars 3: Dino Ciccarelli and Dale Hunter each scored a goal and an assist for Washington, which was playing at home. Washington's rookie goaltender, Jim Hrivnak, lost his shutout when Shawn Chambers scored in the third period. (AP)</p>
        <p>Oilers 7, Jets 4: Petr Klima and Esa Tikkanen each scored twice as Edmonton overcame a 3-0 deficit for a home-ice victory. Klima scored his goals in a four-goal outburst in the final period.(AP)</p>
        <p>Horse Racing</p>
        <p>A Stakes-Record Sprint: Appealing Guy smashed the stakes record yesterday as he cruised to a seven-length victory in the $87,300 Hollie Hughes Handicap at Aqueduct. Carrying 118 pounds with Jacinto Vasquez up, the 4-year-old covered six furlongs on the fast inner dirt oval in 1:08 4/5, bettering by one and two-fifths seconds the record set by Columbia Holme in 1984. The clocking was only one-fifth of a second off the track record for Aqueduct's inner oval posted by Once Wild on Feb. 3. Vigorous Reply was second, a head in front of his entrymate, Argyle Lake. Appealing Guy earned $52,380.(AP)</p>
        <p>Golf</p>
        <p>Hawaiian Wins by a Stroke: David Ishii needed only a round of par 72 for a one-stroke victory yesterday in the Hawaiian Open at Honolulu. Ishii, a slender 34-year-old native of Honolulu who plays mostly on the Japanese tour, is only the second Hawaiian to win in the 25-year history of this event. His task was eased by the misfortunes, some self-inflicted, that befell his rivals. Hubert Green took himself out of contention with a late triple-bogey. Craig Stadler missed six consecutive short putts. Jodie Mudd chopped up the 18th hole.(AP)</p>
        <p>Suncoast Title for Hill: Mike Hill shot a two-under-par 70 and held off a challenge by Lee Trevino to win the G.T.E. Suncoast Classic tournament in Tampa, Fla., yesterday, for his first Senior PGA Tour victory. Hill earned $67,500.(AP)</p>
        <p>Tennis</p>
        <p>Agassi Wins: Andre Agassi inaugurated the new A.T.P. tour with characteristic flair, hammering out a 6-1, 6-3 victory over Todd Witsken in the finals of the $250,000 Volvo tournament at San Francisco. It was the ninth professional title of Agassi's four-year pro career, but just the second since he rose to No. 3 in the world at age 18 in November 1988. He has since slipped to eighth.</p>
        <p>Coming off an intensive two-month weight-training program, Agassi ripped repeated winners on both his forehand and backhand. He also showed great speed against the overmatched Witsken of Carmel, Ind., who failed to hold serve in the 65-minute match and won only 11 points in eight service games.(AP)</p>
        <p>85th Title for Lendl: Top-seeded Ivan Lendl defeated fifth-seeded Tim Mayotte, 6-3, 6-2, yesterday in the final of an indoor tournament in Milan, Italy, for his 85th title and third Milan championship.(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
