<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridge</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="852907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGE (CARD GAME)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6DF1139F936A15756C0A960958260" item-length="359" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The usual rewards for success in American tournaments are prestige and masterpoints, but not cash. May in New York City offers three rare exceptions. The Cavendish Teams and Pairs, during the Mother's Day weekend, use a Calcutta format, with players and nonplayers buying shares in the contestants.</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, the Eastern Regional Championships open with the Greenpoint  Pairs, with an entry fee of $250 a pair, four-fifths of which is returned in prize money. This high-quality event, with table screens, is popular with experts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The usual rewards for success in American tournaments are prestige and masterpoints, but not cash. May in New York City offers three rare exceptions. The Cavendish Teams and Pairs, during the Mother's Day weekend, use a Calcutta format, with players and nonplayers buying shares in the contestants.</p>
        <p>Two weeks later, the Eastern Regional Championships open with the Greenpoint  Pairs, with an entry fee of $250 a pair, four-fifths of which is returned in prize money. This high-quality event, with table screens, is popular with experts.</p>
        <p>The winners on Thursday, collecting first prize of $1,600, were Jim Rosenbloom and Roy Welland of Manhattan. They ended with 1,076.67 imps, far ahead of the runners-up, Robert Sartorius of Lake Hiawatha, N.J., and Robert Heitzman Jr. of Alpine, N.J., who scored 755.08.</p>
        <p>In the diagramed deal, the most striking of the day, most East-West pairs played in spades at the four or five level, making 10 tricks. The winners were doubled in five clubs, after the auction shown.</p>
        <p>West should no doubt have persevered to five spades on the general principle  that with freak hands, one should bid one more for luck. He was right in thinking that he could not make five spades, but wrong that he could beat five clubs.</p>
        <p>Two rounds of spades were led, and Rosenbloom as South ruffed in dummy and finessed the club jack. He then ran diamonds, discarding his heart loser, and made his contract easily, eventually losing a trump trick. Some quick analysts thought that West should have cashed the heart ace at the second trick and then led a second spade. This forces dummy to ruff, and apparently gives East a  trump trick.</p>
        <p>But South survives with careful play. He takes two trump finesses, winning with the ten and nine, and ruffs a heart. He then crosses to dummy with a diamond and ruffs another heart. He runs diamonds, finishing with the lead in dummy after the 11th trick, and West's guarded club king is trapped under the declarer's ace-queen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
