<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharon of Israel: Hawkish Talons as Sharp as Ever</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="852939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHARON, ARIEL ARIEL SHARON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2DF1139F936A15756C0A960958260" item-length="1424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharon of Israel: Hawkish Talons as Sharp as Ever</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE;</byline>
      <dateline>SEDEROT, Israel, May 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A scarred veteran of many wars, military and political, Ariel Sharon is not for mincing words or chasing after the undecided vote with dovish posturing.</p>
        <p>"Our people are not used to this kind of election," he said, referring to the new system under which Israelis vote directly for a Prime Minister rather than only for a party. "People used to back the party that expressed what they believed was the main issue. It was very easy for them to struggle for an idea,  or for a party, or for a movement. But they're not used to go out in the streets and advocate for an individual. These people are the hard core of the Likud."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A scarred veteran of many wars, military and political, Ariel Sharon is not for mincing words or chasing after the undecided vote with dovish posturing.</p>
        <p>"Our people are not used to this kind of election," he said, referring to the new system under which Israelis vote directly for a Prime Minister rather than only for a party. "People used to back the party that expressed what they believed was the main issue. It was very easy for them to struggle for an idea,  or for a party, or for a movement. But they're not used to go out in the streets and advocate for an individual. These people are the hard core of the Likud."</p>
        <p>All the chasing after the "floating vote," Mr. Sharon continued, uttering the term with obvious disdain, was threatening to lose this loyal core.</p>
        <p>His impressive bulk ensconced in an easy chair in the lounge of his spacious  farmhouse in the rolling hills of southern Israel, Mr. Sharon was explaining why he had decided to publish an unadorned exposition of the Likud's hard-line views at a time when the party's standard-bearer, Benjamin Netanyahu, was bending over backward to soften the Likud's pugnacious image in the election next week.</p>
        <p>In a striking article printed in The Jerusalem Post and several other papers  last week, Mr. Sharon declared, "The time has come to dispel the confusion and explain the national camp's position in simple language, without verbal preening."</p>
        <p>"The Likud cannot accept the Oslo accords," he wrote, referring to the Labor  Government's agreements with the Palestinians, which Mr. Sharon branded "terrible and dangerous." Instead, Israeli security forces should be free to operate in any Palestinian area, he wrote. All Palestinian Authority offices in  Jerusalem should be closed. The search for peace with Syria should be suspended  until President Hafez al-Assad is gone. And in any case, Israel should keep the  Golan Heights. And so on.</p>
        <p>There was no indication whether the article was approved by Mr. Netanyahu, and it was unlikely Mr. Sharon would have felt bound to seek anyone's approval.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Sharon's claim that the article was intended for the Likud hard core,  many Israelis might counter that Mr. Sharon is that hard core.</p>
        <p>A retired general who fought in the toughest battles of every Israeli war, and a politician who has been at the heart of every right-wing cause from Jewish settlements in the West Bank to the maximum use of force against militant Arabs, Mr. Sharon, 68, figures in this campaign as probably the strongest power behind  Mr. Netanyahu.</p>
        <p>"Next Wednesday the real choice will not be between Shimon Peres and Benjamin Netanyahu, but rather between Shimon Peres and Ariel Sharon," wrote Yoel Marcus, a commentator for the daily Haaretz. "This is for the simple reason that Sharon, who is now ensconced in a bunker, will be the strongest and most influential person in a government headed by Netanyahu."</p>
        <p>Mr. Marcus listed several reasons: Mr. Sharon was among the first of the Likud veterans to come to Mr. Netanyahu's side. It was he who forged Likud's alliances with two competing right-wing parties, those of David Levy and Rafael  Eitan. And, though not observant himself, the champion of building Jewish settlements across the entire "Land of Israel" -- a concept that includes the West Bank -- enjoys a strong credibility among Orthodox Jews.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon purports not to understand why President Clinton does not see things as clearly as he does, why he supports Prime Minister Peres.</p>
        <p>"Since that infamous handshake in Washington, 217 people have been killed and about 1,000 wounded in terrorist attacks," he said, referring to the handshake on Sept. 13, 1993, between Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, and Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin that formally began the process toward peace. "I don't think any American President would recommend to his own people to run these risks."</p>
        <p>"I and my wife, we sleep with a gun under our bed," Mr. Sharon declared. "I say with a full heart that the American President does not sleep with a gun under his bed."</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Sharon seems to need that gun about as little as Mr. Clinton might, given the tall fence around his land and the soldiers deployed to guard his house.</p>
        <p>"I know President Clinton is the most friendly President we've ever had," he  continued. "I would have expected that his support would be to strengthen democracy in this country. One can much easier understand the position of the King of Morocco, the President of France, the President of Egypt, the King of Jordan, all calling in the most open way to vote for Peres. Arafat does, and many people regard him according to every criteria a war criminal. He is a war criminal."</p>
        <p>To Mr. Sharon, Mr. Arafat is anathema. The two major mistakes of the Israeli-Palestinian agreements, he declared, were that it was signed with Mr. Arafat -- "I don't know anyone who has so much civilian Jewish blood on his hands since Hitler" -- and that it handed responsibility for the struggle with terrorism "into the hands of a terrorist."</p>
        <p>That raised the question Mr. Peres has been asking in his campaign: Whom would a Likud Government negotiate with?</p>
        <p>Another question is whether any Palestinian would negotiate with Mr. Sharon,  who is the Israeli most responsible for planting Jewish settlements in the West  Bank and Gaza Strip, and who bought a house in the heart of the Arab section of  Jerusalem from which he drapes a huge Israeli flag. The house is permanently guarded by Israeli soldiers and is the focus of frequent incidents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon insists he would not try to take away what the Israeli Government  has already given the Palestinians, though he lists conditions that would at the least put a new interpretation on the accords.</p>
        <p>"They can run their life without interference," he said, but Israel would retain responsibility for everything that affects its security -- a concept that to Mr. Sharon ranges from terrorism to veterinary supervision. Since the nearby  Gaza Strip came under Palestinian control, he noted, "we had to slaughter 3,000  sheep."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharon also leaves no doubt that he would push for a renewed expansion of the Jewish settlements in the West Bank, whose growth has been frozen by the Labor Government. It was Mr. Sharon, as Housing Minister, who was responsible for the settlements, and he fought hard in the last years of the Likud Government to build as many as possible, despite strong pressure against them from the United States.</p>
        <p>For all that, the old warrior insists that he is every bit as much for peace  as Mr. Peres. "I don't think for one minute that Mr. Peres is more for peace than myself," he said.</p>
        <p>But as he talks, it becomes evident that Mr. Sharon's idea of peace is still  based on a vision of Israel surrounded by potential foes, relying only on itself to survive. He described the many battles he had waged, the wounds he suffered,  the friends he saw killed. Most of the wars, he said, started with "Arab terrorism."</p>
        <p>He talked of the 1982 invasion of Lebanon that he led as Defense Minister, a  war that became hugely unpopular in Israel and led to the fall of his Likud Government.</p>
        <p>"The war in Lebanon was a war of salvation," he insisted defiantly. "There was an independent kingdom of terrorism in Lebanon. My only mistake was not to understand that the Labor Party and Peace Now would take advantage of the war in order to overthrow the Government.</p>
        <p>"When we take steps toward peace, we have to take these things into consideration. We live here, with a gun under our bed, not in Washington. I understand war and peace. But for me peace means security. If it doesn't provide security for the state of Israel now and in the future, I don't regard it as peace."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
