<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fans Let Lopez Know She Makes Their Cut</title>
    <meta content="06LINK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/06/sports/golf/06LINK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1406096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Women's Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lopez, Nancy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Webb, Karrie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eathorne, A J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ochoa, Lorena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richard, Deb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Halls of Fame</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Halls of Fame</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Wykagyl Country Club</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lopez, Nancy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DD1E31F935A35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fans Let Lopez Know She Makes Their Cut</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fans Let Lopez Know She Makes Their Cut</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>HUTCHINSON, Kan., July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Golf Notebook discusses fan reaction to Nancy Lopez, who does not make cut after second round at US Women's Open, but gets warm reception from fans who appreciate golf; Lopez plans to retire; two-time defending champion Karrie Webb does not make cut; A J Eathorne, Lorena Ochoa and Deb Richard withdraw with injuries before second round of tournament (M),</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Nancy Lopez made a tearful departure from the United States Women's Open, the gallery showered her with affection and appreciation.</p>
        <p>By all indications, Lopez competed in her final Open today, missing the cut with a nine-over-par 79 that left her 20 over for the tournament. It is unlikely that Lopez will receive another special exemption from the United States Golf Association, and at age 45, she has already announced that she will not play another full season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By all indications, Nancy Lopez competed in her final Open on Friday, missing the cut with a nine-over-par 79.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Nancy Lopez made a tearful departure from the United States Women's Open, the gallery showered her with affection and appreciation.</p>
        <p>By all indications, Lopez competed in her final Open today, missing the cut with a nine-over-par 79 that left her 20 over for the tournament. It is unlikely that Lopez will receive another special exemption from the United States Golf Association, and at age 45, she has already announced that she will not play another full season.</p>
        <p>So as Lopez walked up the 18th fairway, the gallery at Prairie Dunes Country Club gave her one last standing ovation, while another Hall of Fame player, Juli Inkster, who was standing on the adjacent 10th tee, tipped her visor toward Lopez out of respect.</p>
        <p>''I'm just grateful to the fans,'' said Lopez, who won 48 tournaments and 3 majors, but never won the Open. ''It's a thrill to walk up 18 and feel the love that people have not just for me, but for the L.P.G.A.</p>
        <p>''I would have liked to have played much better this week, but my game is just not there. I'd like to finish strong this year. I'm going to keep working on it.''</p>
        <p>No L.P.G.A. player has ever been more popular than Lopez, who connected with fans because of her magnetic personality. Lopez said she had simply followed the example set by her father, Domingo, who died in April.</p>
        <p>''My dad was such a great inspiration because he always told me to keep trying and never quit, to enjoy what I was doing and always smile,'' Lopez said. ''He was always positive, and that's what I have always been taught. When I'm out here, if I can make somebody feel good by smiling at them or saying hi to them, then I'm doing my job, at least for my dad.''</p>
        <p>Lopez finished second at the Open four times, most recently in 1997, when she lost by one stroke to Alison Nicholas, despite becoming the only player in Open history to shoot all four rounds in the 60's.</p>
        <p>Asked how she felt about never winning the Open, Lopez smiled and said, ''I think four seconds should equal a first.''</p>
        <p>Webb Misses Cut</p>
        <p>The two-time defending champion Karrie Webb also missed the cut, never recovering from an opening-round 79. Webb was trying to become the first player to win three consecutive women's Opens, but she made only one birdie in two days, shooting a second-round 73 to finish at 12 over par. Webb had made 56 consecutive cuts, dating to September 1999.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday took a big chunk of my confidence,'' Webb said today. ''I didn't swing as freely as I was in the practice rounds. It has been almost three years since I missed the cut. Obviously, it's not the best time to miss one, but hopefully it's another three years before I miss one.''</p>
        <p>Webb said her performance had little to do with any pressure to defend her title.</p>
        <p>''My swing disappeared overnight,'' said Webb, who will play in the Big Apple Classic beginning July 25 at Wykagyl Country Club in New Rochelle, N.Y. ''It sounds stupid to think that I really felt like I was swinging well. It just vanished yesterday on the 11th tee. Hopefully it's just one week, and next week it will be back to swinging good again.</p>
        <p>''I've always done well under pressure,'' Webb said. ''I think that was the biggest shock for me, that I normally thrive on that, and it went the opposite way.''</p>
        <p>Three Withdraw</p>
        <p>Three players withdrew before today's round: A. J. Eathorne (wrist injury), Lorena Ochoa (neck injury) and Deb Richard (pulled stomach muscle).</p>
        <p>Pak Struggles to Make Cut</p>
        <p>Se Ri Pak, who has won two of the last three women's majors, barely made the cut, shooting a 75 today to finish the second round at nine over.</p>
        <p>GOLF: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
