<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sanity on Adultery</title>
    <meta content="10TUE1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="936057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adultery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ralston, Joseph W (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adultery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7D8133CF933A25755C0A961958260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sanity on Adultery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says decision by Gen Joseph Ralston to withdraw as candidate to become next Chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff was only sensible and responsible course of action given public outrage over recent handling of adultery cases in military; says anguish over derailing of his candidacy will serve useful purpose if it forces both military and Congress to reform policy on sexual offenses that is veering dangerously out of control (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gen. Joseph Ralston's decision to withdraw from contention to become the next Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff was the only sensible and responsible course of action given public outrage over the recent handling of adultery cases in the military. His candidacy was doomed once it became known that he, too, had committed adultery earlier in his career. Neither Congress nor the American people could ignore a sexual infraction by one of its  top generals, however innocuous that conduct might seem to his supporters, when lesser officers have been drummed out of the service for similar offenses. But the anguish over the derailing of the Ralston candidacy will serve a useful purpose if it forces both the military and Congress to reform a policy on sexual offenses that is veering dangerously out of control.</p>
        <p>The madness in current policy can be measured by the recent loss or punishment of three talented officers, all for reasons stemming from consensual but adulterous affairs with civilians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gen. Joseph Ralston's decision to withdraw from contention to become the next Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff was the only sensible and responsible course of action given public outrage over the recent handling of adultery cases in the military. His candidacy was doomed once it became known that he, too, had committed adultery earlier in his career. Neither Congress nor the American people could ignore a sexual infraction by one of its  top generals, however innocuous that conduct might seem to his supporters, when lesser officers have been drummed out of the service for similar offenses. But the anguish over the derailing of the Ralston candidacy will serve a useful purpose if it forces both the military and Congress to reform a policy on sexual offenses that is veering dangerously out of control.</p>
        <p>The madness in current policy can be measured by the recent loss or punishment of three talented officers, all for reasons stemming from consensual but adulterous affairs with civilians.</p>
        <p>First came Lieut. Kelly Flinn, the first woman to pilot a B-52, whose affair with a married civilian was reported to authorities by a serviceman facing sexual offense charges himself. She was forced to resign after she lied about the affair to investigators and disobeyed an order to break it off. Then came Maj. Gen. John Longhouser, a much-decorated soldier who headed the Aberdeen Proving Ground, who was forced to retire after a tipster revealed his affair with a civilian while he was separated from his wife five years ago. Now General Ralston has dropped out of the running for Chairman of the Joint Chiefs because a war college classmate revealed his consensual affair with a civilian C.I.A. analyst that started some 14 years ago when he, too, was separated from his wife.</p>
        <p>One need not condone adultery to recognize that it occurs frequently in civilian and military life and is tacitly tolerated so long as it does no harm to others in the community. The consternation many citizens feel about the military cases stems from a belief that the affairs are too slight a basis for destroying careers or promotion prospects.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary William Cohen should not have tried to push the candidacy of General Ralston, a friend of his, when to do so raised the issue of a double standard for top-ranking officers. But he was clearly right to call for drawing brighter lines between what is acceptable and what is not. With luck, the panels he has just appointed to review sexual misconduct and gender issues will inject some sanity into the process.</p>
        <p>The governing philosophy should surely be that the military has no business investigating consensual sexual affairs unless they have a direct bearing on job performance or the maintenance of military discipline. That would rule out almost any investigation or punishment of private consensual affairs between military personnel and civilians who are not part of the same command. In theory, the military only prosecutes adultery now when it is deemed to undermine good order and discipline or bring discredit upon the armed forces. But once a witch hunt is started, it seems increasingly hard to make rational distinctions.</p>
        <p>The military should without question crack down on superiors who use their power to coerce sex from subordinates, as has happened with drill sergeants demanding sex of trainees at Aberdeen. It should also set rules governing sex that has potential to disrupt command structure and morale. Examples would be affairs between officers and enlisted personnel or between senior and junior officers in the same chain of command. Sexual abuse of any kind cannot be tolerated.</p>
        <p>But what needs to stop is the incessant prying into sexual relationships that have no bearing on military matters. The bar needs to be raised higher before a complaint, anonymous or otherwise, triggers an investigation. Commanders should rely more on administrative penalties than on career-ending prosecutions. The ''hot lines'' designed to let women report sexual abuse and harassment anonymously may need to be revised to eliminate vindictive charges about consensual sex between adults. The goal should be to prevent sexual misconduct that harms individual soldiers or military missions while ignoring sexual affairs that are no business of the military.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
