<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Virtually A-Wake</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="51" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="858009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKEND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONICMAIL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOYCE, JAMES (1882-1941)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E7DE1439F935A25755C0A960958260" item-length="1579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Virtually A-Wake</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Sullivan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STATELY, plump Joyceans everywhere are probably descending from the stairhead right this minute, dressing gowns ungirdled, and tucking with relish into big Bloomsday breakfasts consisting of the tangy inner organs of beasts and fowls. My own celebratory plan is to log on, as I do almost every day, to my Internet server and receive the mail brought to me courtesy of J-Joyce and F-Wake, the mailing lists that collectively make up Joyce on line. Thanks to the two of them -- J-Joyce for discussion of Joyce generally and F-Wake for discussion of matters specifically regarding what the members often refer to simply as the "Wake" -- my computer screen has begun to bloom, so to speak, with almost daily  epiphanies. If I had not been a subscriber to the Joyce list, for example, I wouldn't have known about the latest "Ulysses" references in Tank Girl, the Generation X comic book ("Stately, plump Booga descends the stairhead of Chateau Tank Girl," goes a line in one story), or about the one in Woody Allen's "Take the Money and Run." (A recent J-Joyce posting read, "In the bank robbing scene . . . the date is prominently displayed: it's June 16th. Coincidence?") Nor would  I have had any idea that James Joyce has contributed in a crucial way to the work of Rodney Dangerfield. (In the movie "Back to School," check out Sally Kellerman's orgasmic reading of Molly Bloom's soliloquy, which Dangerfield, bursting from his classroom seat, punctuates by shouting "Yes! Yes!")</p>
        <p>One day on J-Joyce someone is posting a newly discovered Homeric trait in Leopold Bloom; the next, there is a discussion of Freud and footwear as both relate to "The Dead." "I've just finished an essay called 'Scribbledehobbles: Writing Irish-Jewish Feet in Freud, Joyce and Beckett,' " a Joyce scholar from somewhere in Britain writes. "Anyway, in it I find myself going on at some length not only about Gretta's galoshes, but also what seem to be other instances of significant foot-fixation in Joyce's work." Once in a while, college kids plug in to look for help with term papers, and sometimes find more  help than they're looking for. If I were in college and had to write a couple of pages by Monday, I'm not sure I'd want to hear from a Middle English scholar who minors in Joyce and has a lot to say about "textual genetics."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STATELY, plump Joyceans everywhere are probably descending from the stairhead right this minute, dressing gowns ungirdled, and tucking with relish into big Bloomsday breakfasts consisting of the tangy inner organs of beasts and fowls. My own celebratory plan is to log on, as I do almost every day, to my Internet server and receive the mail brought to me courtesy of J-Joyce and F-Wake, the mailing lists that collectively make up Joyce on line. Thanks to the two of them -- J-Joyce for discussion of Joyce generally and F-Wake for discussion of matters specifically regarding what the members often refer to simply as the "Wake" -- my computer screen has begun to bloom, so to speak, with almost daily  epiphanies. If I had not been a subscriber to the Joyce list, for example, I wouldn't have known about the latest "Ulysses" references in Tank Girl, the Generation X comic book ("Stately, plump Booga descends the stairhead of Chateau Tank Girl," goes a line in one story), or about the one in Woody Allen's "Take the Money and Run." (A recent J-Joyce posting read, "In the bank robbing scene . . . the date is prominently displayed: it's June 16th. Coincidence?") Nor would  I have had any idea that James Joyce has contributed in a crucial way to the work of Rodney Dangerfield. (In the movie "Back to School," check out Sally Kellerman's orgasmic reading of Molly Bloom's soliloquy, which Dangerfield, bursting from his classroom seat, punctuates by shouting "Yes! Yes!")</p>
        <p>One day on J-Joyce someone is posting a newly discovered Homeric trait in Leopold Bloom; the next, there is a discussion of Freud and footwear as both relate to "The Dead." "I've just finished an essay called 'Scribbledehobbles: Writing Irish-Jewish Feet in Freud, Joyce and Beckett,' " a Joyce scholar from somewhere in Britain writes. "Anyway, in it I find myself going on at some length not only about Gretta's galoshes, but also what seem to be other instances of significant foot-fixation in Joyce's work." Once in a while, college kids plug in to look for help with term papers, and sometimes find more  help than they're looking for. If I were in college and had to write a couple of pages by Monday, I'm not sure I'd want to hear from a Middle English scholar who minors in Joyce and has a lot to say about "textual genetics."</p>
        <p>A few of the really serious Joyceans get upset when people start trading Joyce posters, T-shirts and the like -- a list member recently derided a burst of such swapping with the phrase "Joyce Shopping Channel," apparently forgetting that "Ulysses" is, among other things, the great catalogue of middle-class life. Mostly, however, the scholarly and the not-so-scholarly chat together peacefully, as was the case in a recent three-day discussion of flatulence in Joyce's work, which was prompted by a graduate student's apparently serious need to compare Joyce's take on the matter with Dante's in "Paradise Lost." A sample: "The reference to Dante that you are referring to seems quite applicable to what I have been discussing in my thesis. The Dantean stance on flatulence is placed  in Stephen's recitation of a couple of lines of 'Paradise Lost' in Scylla and Charybdis, where he talks of . . . making the sound of a trombone. I am sorry that I cannot cite . . . directly." (It was during this discussion that an actual Joyce scholar noted parenthetically that Michael J. Fox, in a celebrity interview, confessed to coveting the role of Le Petomane, the famous French flatulist.) The best thing about the Joyce mailing list is that unlike on-line discussion groups devoted to other authors, it is stylistically appropriate. Replies to postings build on each other day after day, like so many Joycean references, or like Stephen Dedalus's overactive brain in the walk-on-the-beach  chapter of "Ulysses." If, as an essay in Wired magazine argued a while back, Thomas Paine is the father of the Internet, because he so acutely embraced the technology of the moment in his quest to disseminate his revolutionary ideas, then Joyce is the Internet's proto-stylist: the author who anticipated the Web's stream of consciousness. A message posted a few weeks ago addressed this issue:</p>
        <p>"I am a Dubliner, a software engineer and a Joyce enthusiast. As a teen-ager I approached Joyce thinking he was just an Irish Dickens or a Myles Na gCopaleen without the jokes. I emerged in awe. That awe remains. As a software engineer I  have tremendous affinity with Joyce for reasons that perhaps only a few software engineers will understand. At one level 'Ulysses' is a wonderful piece of software engineering along with all the other more traditional artistic accolades."</p>
        <p>Not being one of those engineers, I'm not sure I understand -- if I did, I'd probably be doing something more constructive with my morning E-mail time, like  taking over the computers at the Federal Reserve. But I like to think that Joyce, the man who attempted to open Ireland's first cinema, and the first significant mentioner of television in a work of fiction (from "Finnegans Wake": "Television kills telephony in brothers' broil"), would today have his own Web site -- perhaps featuring Molly Bloom Yes!-ing in such a fashion as to raise the ire of a Congressman trolling late at night for constitutional improprieties.</p>
        <p>The way that Joyce anticipated the computer age is even more apparent on F-Wake, whose participants go live every Wednesday at 5 P.M. Pacific standard time in a virtual study room located somewhere among the modems at the University of California, Berkeley. The other day, in order to participate in a  virtual Wakeian discussion, I took my copy of "Finnegans Wake" over to habitat@.com, my local espresso bar/Internet access site. Sipping sparkling cider, I was surrounded, in the physical realm, by three women in their 20's who were discussing their poetry and their E-mail sex lives; at one point when I looked up, they apologized for interrupting my "studying." ("You mean you just read it for fun?" one of them asked me. "Cool!") The "Wake" group was examining  a page-and-a-half-long sentence in the middle of Chapter 4 that begins: "This wastohavebeen underground heaven, or mole's paradise."</p>
        <p>As far as the advancement of any greater understanding of Joyce's work went  that afternoon, I'm afraid that I was of little help; those already discussing the sentence were seeing relevant Scandinavian roots, while I kept losing my place. In fact, my most significant contribution was dumb Joycean luck: I had entered the virtual discussion room at the moment the other "Wake" fans were discussing a reference to Gilbert and Sullivan. Noticing the coincidence of my surname, a participant typed, "Interesting."</p>
        <p>The amazing thing was that the discussion of the text elucidating itself before me on my latte-stained terminal screen was itself resembling a page from  the "Wake," complete with typos to be explored, clarified and wondered over by generations of Joyce scholars to come. In another session, for instance, "the Devil himself" was the phrase that kicked things off. That sent the group to "and a Dublin sylph" and then to "Dublin sulpher," which brought everyone to the ancient word for Dublin, the proper noun, we were reminded, that translates to "black pool." It was as if the "Wake" were some kind of self-replicating virus.  Scrolling back through past discussions on my screen, I saw the participants all blurting out little convoluted excerpts of Joycespeak, and, jolted by caffeine,  I recalled that Joyce himself originally referred to "Finnegans Wake" only as "Work in Progress."</p>
        <p>A few months ago a potentially devastating query was posted to the general Joyce discussion group. A college student who claimed to be speaking on behalf of "a friend" asked what was the point of reading "Ulysses" over and over and analyzing it all the time? This was like asking the chairman of Exxon about the  necessity of revenue growth or the Pope about the point of Scripture and prayer. In minutes, a flurry of responses arrived in my E-mail in-box, and the faithful  rallied around a passage from Richard Ellmann's biography in which Joyce talks about "my idea of the significance of trivial things." Then someone added a sound byte from Joyce making reference to Ibsen: "Still, I think out of the dreary sameness of existence, a measure of dramatic life may be drawn."</p>
        <p>For a couple of days, I kept waiting for a big resolution of "What does it all mean?" as the topic had been billed in all the E-mail replies. But after a small controversy regarding the authenticity of the "trivial things" quotation,  the whole discussion tapered off like the faintly falling snow at the end of "The Dead," and soon we were back to discussions about things like Joyce and TV, and about a posting from a graduate student in British Columbia who says he is working on a hypertext version of the Sirens chapter from "Ulysses" that will allow the browser to hear whatever Dublin songs might have been running through  Bloom's head at that point in the book. I quick-saved that particular piece of information, and I thought, Nothing trivial here.</p>
        <p>BOOKEND Robert Sullivan is a contributing editor at Vogue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert Sullivan is a contributing editor at Vogue.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
