<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bronfman Heir Plotting His Comeback, in Music</title>
    <meta content="24BRON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/24/business/media/24BRON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1538040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lee, Thomas H, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warner Music Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Computer Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirkpatrick, David D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronfman, Edgar Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Universal Studios</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bronfman, Edgar Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6D9113BF937A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bronfman Heir Plotting His Comeback, in Music</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bronfman Heir Plotting His Comeback, in Music</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID D. KIRKPATRICK and ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kirkpatrick, David D; Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Success of Edgar Bronfman Jr's deal to buy Warner Music from Time Warner for $2.6 billion hinges in large part on his conviction that embattled music industry can tame online piracy and reverse three-year sales slump; Bronfman is betting on untested new Internet business, sale of music online; unlike his earlier deal, when he sold his family's Seagram liquor empire for shares of Vivendi, this time he has assembled well-healed cadre of investors that shore his vision, including group led by Thomas H Lee Partners; Bronfman himself is expected to contribute $250 million to deal; in wooing investors, he argued that online music piracy is already abating thanks to lawsuits by music industry and legal online music sales by companies like Apple Computer and Wal-Mart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last three years, Edgar Bronfman Jr. has lived in the shadow of a monumentally bad decision. He sold his family's Seagram liquor empire for shares of Vivendi, a French utility-turned-media company, only to watch it nearly collapse and take with it his family's fortune.</p>
        <p>But today, Mr. Bronfman and a group of investors led by Thomas H. Lee Partners are expected to announce an agreement to buy Warner Music, home to Madonna and R.E.M. among many others, from Time Warner for $2.6 billion, people involved in the deal said yesterday. Mr. Bronfman, a onetime songwriter for Celine Dion and others, will become the company's top executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edgar Bronfman Jr. and a group of investors are expected to announce an agreement with Time Warner to buy Warner Music for $2.6 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last three years, Edgar Bronfman Jr. has lived in the shadow of a monumentally bad decision. He sold his family's Seagram liquor empire for shares of Vivendi, a French utility-turned-media company, only to watch it nearly collapse and take with it his family's fortune.</p>
        <p>But today, Mr. Bronfman and a group of investors led by Thomas H. Lee Partners are expected to announce an agreement to buy Warner Music, home to Madonna and R.E.M. among many others, from Time Warner for $2.6 billion, people involved in the deal said yesterday. Mr. Bronfman, a onetime songwriter for Celine Dion and others, will become the company's top executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman is expected to contribute about $250 million to the deal, buying himself a chance to repair his damaged reputation.</p>
        <p>But the deal's success hinges in large part on Mr. Bronfman's contrarian conviction that the embattled music industry can tame online piracy and reverse a three-year sales slump. Like Mr. Bronfman's deal with Vivendi, the acquisition of Warner Music is in part another bet on an untested new Internet business, the sale of music online. This time, however, he has assembled a well-healed cadre of investors that share his vision.</p>
        <p>Through a spokeswoman, Mr. Bronfman declined to comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>Despite the disastrous results of the Vivendi deal, Mr. Bronfman has told friends he thinks he has nothing to prove.</p>
        <p>''The only time I hear Edgar get upset is when he reads that this is about redemption,'' said Richard D. Snyder, former chief executive of Simon &amp; Schuster and a Bronfman friend and adviser. ''He feels: 'This is my next stage. I am 48. This is what I am going to do with the rest of my life. I don't want to sit home and have a yacht and do the things that wealthy people do. I want to work.' '' Mr. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>Yet other friends and some of his backers said that Mr. Bronfman's drive in pursuit of the deal -- and his pledging an additional $50 million of his own money during a frenzied final weekend of negotiations -- was hard to understand as anything but a quest for vindication. ''He is not working around the clock because he needs the money,'' a member of the investor consortium said. ''This is about him.''</p>
        <p>In wooing the investors, Mr. Bronfman argued that online music piracy was already abating thanks to lawsuits by the music industry and legal online music sales by companies like Apple Computer and Wal-Mart.</p>
        <p>But some investors were not as sanguine about the industry's prospects, particularly at a cost of $2.6 billion. Yesterday afternoon, at least one investor who was expected to participate in the consortium, the media entrepreneur Haim Saban, backed out, people involved in the bid said. But by the end of the night the investor group had lured Mr.Saban back for a much lower stake.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman, who last week doubled his original $100 million commitment, added $50 million yesterday.</p>
        <p>Others involved in the bid defended the deal, saying that cost cutting alone would increase profits at Warner Music. But some executives of the music unit wonder how much fat remains in its operations. Warner Music has laid off more than 2,000 of its 6,500 employees over the last three years.</p>
        <p>The entertainment business has always been Mr. Bronfman's passion. Taking a cue from his father, Edgar Sr., who once made a run at control of MGM over his own father's objections, Edgar Jr. skipped college to make movies. He produced films including ''The Bunker,'' a war film, and ''The Border,'' starring Jack Nicholson. He wrote songs including ''To Love You More,'' recorded by Ms. Dion, and ''Whisper in the Dark'' sung by Dionne Warwick.</p>
        <p>He tried his hand at producing for Broadway, too, and recently returned to it. He is currently producing a musical, ''Never Gonna Dance,'' a stage version of the Fred Astaire and Ginger Rogers film ''Swingtime,'' that is scheduled to open on Dec. 4.</p>
        <p>His earlier career as a producer never paid off and after a few years in Hollywood he took a job with his father at Seagram in 1982.</p>
        <p>In 1993, Edgar Jr. encouraged his father to began buying shares in Time Warner as a possible acquisition target.</p>
        <p>In 1995, a year after becoming chief executive of Seagram, he overruled the objections of his uncle Charles to sell Seagram's stake in the chemical giant DuPont and instead acquired control of the entertainment businesses of MCA, the parent company of Universal Studios, for $5.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman's tenure drew mixed reviews from investors. In the six years after his appointment as chief executive, Seagram's shares consistently lagged the performance of Time Warner and other major entertainment stocks. But they doubled, outperforming DuPont.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bronfman endeared himself to executives who worked for him. ''He did a sensational job with Universal and the success we have today is due to his leadership,'' said Ron Meyer, the president and chief operating officer Mr. Bronfman hired to run Universal's film and television studios. ''If he winds up with Warner Music, I have no doubt that he will do a superb job with it.''</p>
        <p>Executives at Universal Music say Mr. Bronfman astutely overruled opposition within his family and backed them in the acquisition of the rap label Interscope, which became a steady source of hits. ''He is a tough guy, and I am glad he got this,'' Doug Morris, chief executive of Universal Music, said.</p>
        <p>Executives credit Mr. Bronfman with helping to engineer the acquisition of Polygram for $10.4 billion in 1998, making Universal by far the largest of the five major music companies.</p>
        <p>But the purchase came near the top of the market. The music industry soon found itself troubled by the free downloading of music from the Internet, and what was a $40-billion-a-year global business is expected to fall to about $30 billion this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman blundered in 2000, when, again over the opposition of his uncle, he agreed to sell Seagram to the French executive Jean-Marie Messier for $34 billion in Vivendi stock. Mr. Messier was bent on transforming Vivendi into a multimedia powerhouse that would transmit songs, movies and video games over mobile phones and other devices.</p>
        <p>His vision of the future proved wildly premature, and the debts from his acquisitions brought the company to the brink of bankruptcy. The Bronfmans' stake in Seagram was worth $6.8 billion at the time of the sale, but the value of Vivendi shares has fallen by more than 60 percent since then. It is impossible to know how much Edgar Bronfman Jr. lost.</p>
        <p>Early in 2002, Mr. Bronfman, realizing too late that Mr. Messier's spending spree had mired the company in debt, tried to oust Mr. Messier. The first attempt failed, and Mr. Bronfman later blamed French anti-Americanism and anti-Semitism for the resistance. After Vivendi's close brush with bankruptcy and Mr. Messier's departure in 2002, Mr. Bronfman was roundly derided on Wall Street and in the press. ''He took a beating -- some of it he deserved, some of it he didn't,'' Mr. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman began plotting his return to the business soon after his departure, taking a leave from Vivendi's board to court backers for a bid in the auction of its Universal entertainment businesses.</p>
        <p>Several investors -- familiar with his reputation as a wealthy dilettante -- said they had been surprised by his hard work and determination. He traveled around the country to seek investors, sometimes working 14-hour days and often on weekends. Thomas H. Lee Partners and several others signed on.</p>
        <p>In September, Mr. Bronfman's group ultimately lost the auction to a bid from General Electric's NBC division. But friends of Mr. Bronfman said that, aware of his dismal reputation from the Vivendi deal, he considered even second place a victory, proving that he could assemble a $12 billion bid and compete against G.E.</p>
        <p>''The most important part of it was that Edgar gained his credibility back on Wall Street and with the private equity groups,'' Mr. Snyder said. ''It was not easy.''</p>
        <p>About three months ago, Time Warner ended a period of exclusive talks about merging its music division with Bertelsmann's in favor of a sale to EMI. Mr. Bronfman called Richard D. Parsons, the Time Warner chief executive, and with Thomas H. Lee Partners began to reassemble many of the same investors to bid for Warner Music.</p>
        <p>People involved in the bid said Thomas H. Lee Partners had put up more than $600 million, the largest contribution. Bain Capital is investing $350 million, and Providence Equity Partners $150 million. The rest of the money will be borrowed.</p>
        <p>Along with Mr. Bronfman, Scott M. Sperling, an executive at the Lee fund, negotiated the deal with Time Warner and its bankers, Morgan Stanley, these people said. Mr. Sperling and other partners would dominate the Warner Music board, the people involved in the bidding said, overseeing Mr. Bronfman as the top executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bronfman's luck turned two weeks ago, when Bertelsmann announced talks with Sony's music division. The two sets of music-industry merger talks -- Time Warner with EMI, Bertelsmann with Sony -- promised months of gridlock on the way to regulatory approval. Mr. Bronfman's investment group needed no such approval, tipping Time Warner's decision in its favor.</p>
        <p>As the Time Warner board met to consider the bids last Thursday, Mr. Bronfman was having lunch with Roger Ames, chairman of Warner Music, at the Four Seasons restaurant in Manhattan, a gathering spot for media executives where their display of camaraderie would not be missed. Mr. Ames will stay on with Mr. Bronfman after the deal.</p>
        <p>When it closes, Mr. Bronfman will have another chance to make good on a pledge he made when he became chief executive of Seagram in 1994: ''I am not going to go down in history as the one Bronfman'' who lost the family fortune.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
