<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: On the Trail</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D6103CF933A15756C0A964958260" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: On the Trail</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brown Urges Input but Misses Chance</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND, May 19 (AP) -- Edmund G. Brown Jr. says the Democratic Party's platform committee should hold public hearings on the policies it will support. But Mr. Brown skipped the public hearing the committee did hold.</p>
        <p>The Presidential candidate held a news conference today to make the appeal for public hearings in the same hotel here where the party held its only national platform hearing a day earlier. More than 90 people testified at the 14-hour hearing, but Mr. Brown did not ask to speak, party officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brown Urges Input but Misses Chance</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND, May 19 (AP) -- Edmund G. Brown Jr. says the Democratic Party's platform committee should hold public hearings on the policies it will support. But Mr. Brown skipped the public hearing the committee did hold.</p>
        <p>The Presidential candidate held a news conference today to make the appeal for public hearings in the same hotel here where the party held its only national platform hearing a day earlier. More than 90 people testified at the 14-hour hearing, but Mr. Brown did not ask to speak, party officials said.</p>
        <p>"To hold an all-day and all-night session in a room down the hall here in one city in America is not enough to engage the American people at the level required to win the Presidency in 1992," Mr. Brown said. "This has to be a major program of the Democratic Party between now and the convention."</p>
        <p>Ginny Terzano, a party spokeswoman, said that the party heard from "a broad spectrum of American voters" at the hearing and that the public could submit written testimony as well.</p>
        <p>A drafting committee is to begin writing the platform in mid-June and the final platform will be decided at the Democratic National Convention in New York City in July. Signatures Runneth Over</p>
        <p>TALLAHASSEE, Fla., May 19 (AP) -- Supporters of Ross Perot today submitted more than 230,000 signatures, nearly four times the number needed, to put him on Florida's Presidential ballot.</p>
        <p>Perot supporters submitted petitions in all 67 counties, where elections supervisors will count them using a random sampling method. Mr. Perot needs 60,312 signatures to appear on the November ballot.</p>
        <p>"I don't recall anything statewide that has been as widespread as this," said the state's Supervisor of Elections, Dot Joyce. "It's really catching on."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot has been certified for the ballot in four states so far: Tennessee, Utah, Maine and Delaware. A Promise to Avoid Club</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA, May 19 (AP) -- Lynn H. Yeakel, the Democratic Senate candidate in Pennsylvania, said today that she would not dine at her husband's country club if its lack of black members becomes an issue.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yeakel's husband, Paul, pays the dues and is a voting member at the Waynesborough Country Club in Paoli, a Philadelphia suburb. Ms. Yeakel said that the club, where she sometimes dines, has Jewish, Asian and female members, and that blacks had been invited but that none had joined. Ms. Yeakel said she had taken black friends to the club.</p>
        <p>Her daughter's wedding reception is to be held there this weekend, but she said "if it's a perception problem, I guess I won't go out there to eat."</p>
        <p>Ms. Yeakel is challenging the incumbent Republican Senator, Arlen Specter.</p>
        <p>"I have actively worked against discrimination my entire life," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
