<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Experts Now Say Baghdad Was Far From Making an A-Bomb Before Gulf War</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA163EF933A15756C0A964958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Experts Now Say Baghdad Was Far From Making an A-Bomb Before Gulf War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>VIENNA, May 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An extraordinary secret gathering of nuclear-weapon designers from the United States, Britain, France and Russia has concluded that on the eve of the Persian Gulf war, Iraq was further from producing a nuclear weapon than had been estimated, United Nations officials say.</p>
        <p>The designers were sent by their countries at the request of the International Atomic Energy Agency to review evidence brought back from Iraq by inspectors who went there to destroy Baghdad's nuclear program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An extraordinary secret gathering of nuclear-weapon designers from the United States, Britain, France and Russia has concluded that on the eve of the Persian Gulf war, Iraq was further from producing a nuclear weapon than had been estimated, United Nations officials say.</p>
        <p>The designers were sent by their countries at the request of the International Atomic Energy Agency to review evidence brought back from Iraq by inspectors who went there to destroy Baghdad's nuclear program.</p>
        <p>At a meeting here in early April, the designers concluded that the Iraqi program faced such significant bottlenecks that President Saddam Hussein was at least three years and possibly more from acquiring his first crude atomic weapon.</p>
        <p>Before the war, United States intelligence estimated that Iraq's nuclear program would be incapable of producing a bomb for at least five years.</p>
        <p>But in November 1990, as he sought to build support for a possible war with Iraq, President Bush said Baghdad might be able to build a bomb in as little as six months, and in speeches after the war he listed the nuclear program as one reason for going to war rather than waiting for a trade embargo to compel Iraq to end its occupation of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>And David Kay, the American who led many of the early inspections in Iraq, said on several occasions just after the war that the evidence suggested that Iraq would have had a bomb in 12 to 18 months.</p>
        <p>"We now think it would have been at least twice as long as that," a senior agency official familiar with the designers' findings said in a recent interview here. "There were several important bottlenecks."</p>
        <p>The International Atomic Energy Agency, an autonomous group in the United Nations system, was charged with finding and destroying Iraq's nuclear-weapons facilities under the Security Council's terms for ending the gulf war.</p>
        <p>The agency, which has monitored Iraq's civilian nuclear program for years, has been criticized for failing to uncover the extent of the military operation.  What the Problems Were</p>
        <p>The meeting in April to review Iraq's program on the eve of the war brought together bomb designers from the four countries that have joined the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, which the agency administers.</p>
        <p>The gathering is believed to have been the first in which experts from the NATO nuclear powers met to discuss the design of atomic weapons with their counterparts from what used to be the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>A summary of their conclusions said Iraq had run into significant troubles in several areas: enriching uranium, building a device to squeeze the nuclear charge until it explodes and understanding how materials react under very high pressures.</p>
        <p>Iraq was taking up to a month to assemble each of the machines, called calutrons, with which it planned to make enriched uranium by electromagnetic separation. Eight calutrons were operational when the war started and the plant was destroyed, and Iraq would have needed several years to install the 80 or so necessary to produce enough explosives for a single bomb, officials here said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the more modern centrifuge-enrichment plant that Iraq planned had run into difficulties, the officials said: Experts from Urenco, the Anglo-Dutch-German centrifuge-enrichment plant in the Netherlands, have concluded that Iraq's design was fundamentally flawed.  Help From Abroad</p>
        <p>Iraqi officials have told the international agency that they received some assistance with centrifuge enrichment from unnamed foreign experts. Agency experts suspect this help may have come from Germany, but others suggest Pakistan, which has a centrifuge-enrichment program for uranium.</p>
        <p>Iraqi officials have said parts for their centrifuge program came from a German company called C. Plath, two Swiss companies identified as Schaublin and SMB Schmiedemeccanica and a British company called Matrix Churchill, which is partly owned by the Iraqi Government. Germany is investigating Plath; it is unclear what happened in the Swiss and British cases.</p>
        <p>The next inspection team is due in Baghdad next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Officials are particularly eager to track down the companies that provided special steel-and-carbon rotor blades for centrifuges. The suppliers could throw important light on whether Iraq has now acknowledged all its uranium-enrichment capacity or whether it is still concealing machines capable of producing nuclear explosives.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Possible Inquiry in U.S.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON, May 19 (Special to The New York Times) -- The House Judiciary Committee announced today that it would consider whether to request the appointment of an independent counsel to investigate the Bush Administration's conciliatory policy toward Baghdad before the 1990 invasion of Kuwait by Iraq and whether it involved violations of Federal law.</p>
        <p>Consideration of whether to appoint a counsel stems from a two-year investigation by Representative Henry B. Gonzalez, Democrat of Texas and chairman of the House Banking Committee, into the Administration's decision to approve $1 billion in credits for Iraq despite evidence that Iraq had misused millions in earlier credits.</p>
        <p>For more than two years the Government has had evidence that Iraq diverted food purchased under the credit program, which is administered by the Agriculture Department, exchanging the food for money and arms from the Soviet bloc and other countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
