<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Stands To Benefit As Military Expands</title>
    <meta content="10INSI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/10/business/yourmoney/10INSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1366578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET INSIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman Sachs Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubel, Howard A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Insight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Afghanistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DE153CF933A25751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Stands To Benefit As Military Expands</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Who Stands to Benefit as Military Expands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with Goldman Sachs aerospace and defense analyst Howard A Rubel on US military industry and which companies are best positioned to benefit from $48 billion military budget proposed by Pres Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH'S 2003 budget calls for a $48 billion, or 14 percent, jump in military spending, the biggest increase in two decades. While a sizable chunk is for pay raises, health care and the impact of inflation on programs, weapons procurement would rise 12 percent, reversing a general decline through most of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Assuming that Congress approves the bulk of the plan amid patriotic fervor, this implies good times for companies that produce equipment, some of which recently  proved itself in the war in Afghanistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Howard A. Rubel, aerospace and defense analyst at Goldman Sachs, took time to discuss the industry and which companies were best positioned to benefit if President Bush's budget is approved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRESIDENT BUSH'S 2003 budget calls for a $48 billion, or 14 percent, jump in military spending, the biggest increase in two decades. While a sizable chunk is for pay raises, health care and the impact of inflation on programs, weapons procurement would rise 12 percent, reversing a general decline through most of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Assuming that Congress approves the bulk of the plan amid patriotic fervor, this implies good times for companies that produce equipment, some of which recently  proved itself in the war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Howard A. Rubel, aerospace and defense analyst at Goldman Sachs, took time last week to discuss the industry and which companies were best positioned to benefit. Following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is this military buildup seen as a pretty big deal on Wall Street?</p>
        <p>A.  You bet. Many weapons systems and platforms of the 1980's are becoming obsolete. Sept. 11 shined a bright light on a host of needs. For example, the average age of the Air Force fleet is somewhere around 23 years, compared with around 16 years then. If current trends continued, we could be looking at a fleet averaging very close to 30 years, an extreme situation for a country that prides itself on being technologically advanced. We had thought there would be a 4 to 7 percent increase, to about $350 billion; twice that is quite striking.</p>
        <p>Q.  I suppose it's telling that none of the older systems are to be eliminated. Didn't we expect at least one of the three new jet fighter programs to be canceled or cut?</p>
        <p>A.  We're using 40-year-old B-52's to bomb the Taliban, but it is the precision weapons they carried that made the substantial difference. The force multiplier of technology really worked. And look what happened: we got all three fighter programs.</p>
        <p>Q.  What surprised  you in the budget?</p>
        <p>A.  It's hard to have a lot of surprises in a $379 billion budget; it requires a lot of planning. The surprise was the overall size and also dividing it into two elements, the core and an additional $10 billion for discretionary items.</p>
        <p>Q.  Most of the stocks, with the exception of Boeing, are trading near 52-week highs. How do you appraise the group now?</p>
        <p>A.  There's opportunity for the stocks to deliver very good returns, but it's not a straight line. They are affected by political perceptions, technological innovations and the performance of individual companies. We're at a point where all three are favorable, and this will continue for a while. This industry is much more tightly run, more efficient than the way it used to be.</p>
        <p>My call is that we'll see share prices move up in line with earnings growth of  from low single digits to midteens, versus probably 7 percent for the market as a whole. But most of the expansion of price-earnings multiples is behind us. We have the group overweighted and have for some time.</p>
        <p>Q.  Which are your favorites among the military contractors?</p>
        <p>A.  What I am recommending is a mix of names. One is Boeing. All the civil aviation stocks took a tremendous pounding the first week the market reopened after Sept. 11. To walk away then would have been selling at the bottom, and since then they've provided pretty good returns. While you're going to see declining output at Boeing, its price reflects the essential market risk.</p>
        <p>Their space and defense business alone is worth in the low $30's, and with the stock at about $40 you have a call on the global economy when it turns. You don't pay much for a very powerful commercial franchise. Some of its space and defense programs, such as missile defense, are at important crossroads, and they are in the heart of the market as a key supplier of satellite systems such as Wide Band Gap Filler. The company should generate $2.5 billion-plus in free cash this year and possibly more than $3 billion next year, a 9 percent free cash flow yield. The stock should be trading today in the mid-to upper $40's.</p>
        <p>Q.  What are your other favorite military companies?</p>
        <p>A.  Last month we added Rockwell Collins, a leading supplier of avionics, to our recommended list. The stock got pounded because investors associated it almost exclusively with Boeing, but the reality is that only about 8 percent of Collins's sales are to Boeing directly. It should earn $1.20 a share this fiscal year and $1.40 in 2003. It has a unique franchise, with many of their commercial applications also serving the military, and a spectacular balance sheet.</p>
        <p>Of course, we also like a couple of the big guys that are pure plays, like Lockheed Martin and General Dynamics. All the major companies have evolved to meet changing needs.</p>
        <p>Q.  Which companies' stocks would you avoid?</p>
        <p>A.  We have Northrop Grumman and Raytheon as market performers. We're not recommending them.</p>
        <p>MARKET INSIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
