<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stony Brook Student Held in Obscene Letters</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTI-SEMITISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORNOGRAPHY AND OBSCENITY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK AT STONY BROOK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KUO, JASON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D7113BF935A25755C0A963958260" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stony Brook Student Held in Obscene Letters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>YAPHANK, L.I., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 26-year-old graduate student has been charged with mailing scores of anti-Semitic, anti-Japanese and obscene letters to professors and students at the State University of New York at Stony Brook over six years, the Suffolk County police said today.</p>
        <p>The student, Jason Kuo, a naturalized American citizen of Chinese descent, who lives in student housing, was charged with aggravated harassment after a document expert matched his handwriting with the handwriting in the letters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 26-year-old graduate student has been charged with mailing scores of anti-Semitic, anti-Japanese and obscene letters to professors and students at the State University of New York at Stony Brook over six years, the Suffolk County police said today.</p>
        <p>The student, Jason Kuo, a naturalized American citizen of Chinese descent, who lives in student housing, was charged with aggravated harassment after a document expert matched his handwriting with the handwriting in the letters.</p>
        <p>"His motive was initially to get even with a person or persons he felt had offended him in some way," said Detective Sgt. Joseph C. Zito, the commanding officer of the Suffolk County Police Bias Crimes Bureau. "But at some point in time it just became something to do."</p>
        <p>Sergeant Zito said that Mr. Kuo was "a rather shy, demure young person," who readily admitted he wrote the letters, in some case to people he didn't know. The police arrested him on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Many of the recipients were on the faculty of the university's School of Dental Medicine, where Mr. Kuo was a student until he was suspended for low grades. University officials said Mr. Kuo was still enrolled as a graduate student, but declined to provide details. They said officials would meet soon to decide whether to suspend or expel Mr. Kuo.</p>
        <p>Suzanne M. Benedetto, an investigator for the university police, said that Mr. Kuo sometimes slipped letters under the doors of campus rooms. She estimated he had sent or hand-delivered at least 100 letters over six years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuo's name appeared on long lists of possible letter writers the police gathered from victims.</p>
        <p>In at least one instance, Mr. Kuo signed the name of another student to letters addressed to the student's professors. The police said obscene letters Mr. Kuo sent to women were sometimes accompanied by pornographic magazines.</p>
        <p>A dental school faculty member who spoke on condition of anonymity said he and his wife had received more than 30 unsolicited pornographic magazines at their home, followed by a stream of obscene and anti-Semitic letters.</p>
        <p>"At first I thought it was a joke, but then several months ago we began to get totally obscene mail," said the faculty member, who said he knew little about Mr. Kuo.</p>
        <p>"He was just a kid who was there," he said. "Zero happened with him. I have no idea why he would do this."</p>
        <p>A second-year student who also spoke on the condition of anonymity said that she received sexually explicit pamphlets and an obscene letter. She said that she did not know Mr. Kuo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuo was released on $225 bail. He faces up to two years in jail if convicted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
