<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row; At Samsonite, Neil Barrett has found a niche by designing travel wear of such gadgety inventiveness that 007 would love it.</title>
    <meta content="18FRON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1169519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Samsonite Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrett, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EEDC1F3AF93BA25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row; At Samsonite, Neil Barrett has found a niche by designing travel wear of such gadgety inventiveness that 007 would love it.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Front Row: At Samsonite, Neil Barrett has found a niche by designing travel wear of such gadgety inventiveness that 007 would love it. **Front Row column on designer Neil Barrett refurbishing design of Samsonite travel wear; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last March, when six Libyan officials were tried in Paris for ordering the bombing of a French plane a decade earlier, the evidence against them included a Samsonite suitcase armed with explosives. A year earlier, a sworn deposition taken in Mexico described a scene in which cocaine traffickers transported $60 million in bribe money in Samsonite luggage. In fact, until just a few months ago, the name Samsonite, the favorite suitcase for much of the world, was more likely to turn up in court documents regarding international miscreants than in the pages of international fashion magazines.</p>
        <p>But the arrival of the British designer Neil Barrett, 34, at the company about a year ago has done much to refurbish Samsonite's image as something other than a maker of drab luggage for Floridians over 63, along with the occasional felon. The suitcase purveyor has gained such cachet that last week Francois Pinault, the French financier bent on assembling a luxury-goods empire, became Samsonite's largest shareholder, acquiring 30 percent through a holding company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last March, when six Libyan officials were tried in Paris for ordering the bombing of a French plane a decade earlier, the evidence against them included a Samsonite suitcase armed with explosives. A year earlier, a sworn deposition taken in Mexico described a scene in which cocaine traffickers transported $60 million in bribe money in Samsonite luggage. In fact, until just a few months ago, the name Samsonite, the favorite suitcase for much of the world, was more likely to turn up in court documents regarding international miscreants than in the pages of international fashion magazines.</p>
        <p>But the arrival of the British designer Neil Barrett, 34, at the company about a year ago has done much to refurbish Samsonite's image as something other than a maker of drab luggage for Floridians over 63, along with the occasional felon. The suitcase purveyor has gained such cachet that last week Francois Pinault, the French financier bent on assembling a luxury-goods empire, became Samsonite's largest shareholder, acquiring 30 percent through a holding company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett introduced his first travel wear for the company early last year. It has brought Samsonite $10 million in sales, said Beppi Fremder, president of Samsonite in Italy, the division of the company responsible for fashion.</p>
        <p>The clothes, for men, women and children, are meant to perform sleight of hand. One jacket adjusts to the wearer's body temperature, so that the wearer would theoretically be as comfortable in it in Cleveland as in Phoenix. Other jackets have travel pillows or reading lamps that pop out of the collars. In one instance, a hiking coat comes with a walking stick incongruously attached (in case the hiker falls down and is injured), along with a flask inside a pocket (in case he wants to numb the pain with some Maker's Mark). Some pants have zip-off legs to turn them into shorts.</p>
        <p>The clothes pretty much perform every subsidiary function short of turning into cappuccino makers, and the style seems to be influencing others. When Naoki Takizawa showed his Issey Miyake men's wear collection in Milan this month, he showed sweaters that had hoods and capes stealthily tucked into them and jackets with all sorts of gadget holders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett's first collection, for fall 1999, was picked up by Louis Boston, Saks Fifth Avenue and Jeffrey in New York. Jeffrey Kalinsky, owner of Jeffrey, says that Samsonite clothes have sold better than anything else in his store. ''We didn't have a piece to mark down,'' he said. Retailers like Fred Segal in Los Angles, Neiman Marcus and Bergdorf Goodman are carrying the line for spring. ''It's kind of gimmicky,'' James Aguiar, Bergdorf's fashion director, acknowledged. ''But it's gimmicky without being stupid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrett's pedigree as a designer is akin to a banker who has hurdled Harvard, Stanford Business School and Goldman Sachs. He studied at Central St. Martin's College of Art and Design in London and then earned a master's degree at the Royal College of Art before landing jobs at Gucci and Prada. In the early 1990's, he wrote Prada's chief executive, Patrizio Bertelli, suggesting the company start a men's wear division and offering his services. Months went by, but Mr. Barrett was eventually granted a brief meeting with Mr. Bertelli (''he flips through your work so quickly,'' Mr. Barrett said) and was unexpectedly offered the job of overseeing men's wear design, which he held until 1998.</p>
        <p>His training at Gucci and Prada gave him, he said, ''a vision of reality.'' He designs his Samsonite line aboard planes and trains between London, Milan and Florence. The idea for his jacket cum reading lamp was born when he was in the passenger seat of a car and trying to do some work. The interior light didn't work. ''In the car is when you want to make your phone calls,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Samsonite line, Mr. Barrett is making a name for himself with his own men's wear, also functional. He started, he said, because, ''I particularly dislike feminine clothes for men,'' a style that has dominated on the runways. When he offered his first collection last year, 100 stores worldwide chose to carry it. Last week in Florence, he showed his first signature line on a runway, with unfussy looks for women, too, including conservative leather skirts and jackets. There were 1,000 people in the audience. After a few days of watching men parade down some Milan runways in skirts, they no doubt were relieved to be there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
