<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Tracked The Family Of a Boy Later Killed</title>
    <meta content="01ABUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Laquan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bethel, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DD1F3AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Tracked The Family Of a Boy Later Killed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials say that just three days before 14-month-old Laquan Harris died of brain hemorrhage, allegedly at hands of his mother's live-in boyfriend, child welfare workers had ordered a caseworker to provide intensive counseling to family; photo of Anthony Bethel, 33, who is charged with second-degree murder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just three days before a 14-month-old boy died of a brain hemorrhage, allegedly at the hands of his mother's live-in boyfriend, child welfare workers had ordered a caseworker to provide intensive counseling to the family, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Administration for Children's Services assigned the family of the boy, Laquan Harris, to its ''intensive preventive services program,'' Nicholas Scoppetta, Commissioner of the agency, said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just three days before a 14-month-old boy died of a brain hemorrhage, allegedly at the hands of his mother's live-in boyfriend, child welfare workers had ordered a caseworker to provide intensive counseling to the family, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Administration for Children's Services assigned the family of the boy, Laquan Harris, to its ''intensive preventive services program,'' Nicholas Scoppetta, Commissioner of the agency, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Under such a program, which typically lasts six to eight weeks, a caseworker with responsibility for only two families can arrange counseling  and parenting classes and be available to help around the clock.</p>
        <p>Mr. Scoppetta said that caseworkers had last had contact with the boy's mother on Nov. 25. At the time, he said, there was no evidence of abuse.</p>
        <p>But the next day, the family was assigned to intensive case management as a procedural safeguard, he said.</p>
        <p>''A preliminary examination shows no indication of improper case practice,'' Mr. Scoppetta said yesterday. ''However, our investigation has just begun.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, help did not come soon enough for the boy. Police received a 911 call early Saturday morning reporting that the boy was unconscious at his family's Boynton Avenue apartment in the Soundview section of the Bronx.</p>
        <p>By the time city Emergency Medical Service workers arrived on the scene, the child was in cardiac arrest, a spokesman for the agency, Firefighter Bob Crowe, said.</p>
        <p>The boy was rushed to Jacobi Medical Center in the Bronx, where he was pronounced dead about six and a half hours later.</p>
        <p>An autopsy found that the boy had died of blunt impact injury to the head, which caused a brain hemorrhage, said Ellen Borakove, a spokeswoman for the City Medical Examiner.</p>
        <p>On Saturday evening, the police arrested Anthony Bethel, 33, who was living with the boy's mother. He was charged with second-degree murder and manslaughter.</p>
        <p>The mother, Lakeisha Briggs, 22,  was not in custody yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bethel did not have a criminal record, a Police Department spokeswoman, Officer Valerie St. Rose, said.</p>
        <p>Child welfare workers, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said yesterday that the family had first come to the agency's attention on Nov. 3, when the boy's mother went to Jacobi Medical Center seeking medical attention for herself. The child was with her.</p>
        <p>Doctors at the hospital notified the state child abuse telephone line, the workers said, but the allegations were not substantiated by caseworkers, who made a visit later that day.</p>
        <p>Over the following three weeks, caseworkers, concerned in part about the presence of the boyfriend, visited the household numerous times, although they did not uncover evidence of abuse.</p>
        <p>But on Nov. 26, determining that Laquan's family needed help, the agency offered counseling, parenting tips, and a caseworker on call 24 hours a day.</p>
        <p>Three days later, the boy was dead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
