<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reebok Ends 'Dan and Dave' Olympic Ads</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="549122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECATHLON</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REEBOK INTERNATIONAL LTD</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920810T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D7123AF933A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reebok Ends 'Dan and Dave' Olympic Ads</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with yet another unforeseen twist in the saga of "Dan and Dave," Reebok International Ltd. has decided to end its costly and controversial advertising campaign.</p>
        <p>"The 'Dan and Dave' campaign, as we know it, has been settled in Barcelona," a Reebok spokeswoman, Bernadette Mansur, said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with yet another unforeseen twist in the saga of "Dan and Dave," Reebok International Ltd. has decided to end its costly and controversial advertising campaign.</p>
        <p>"The 'Dan and Dave' campaign, as we know it, has been settled in Barcelona," a Reebok spokeswoman, Bernadette Mansur, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>"We got everything we needed to," she said.</p>
        <p>"You've got to know when to fold 'em," she added.</p>
        <p>The decision follows the end of the decathlon at the 1992 Summer Olympics in Barcelona, Spain, in which both of Reebok's advertising stars fell far short of their lofty promise. Eight Months of Ads</p>
        <p>For the last eight months, Chiat/ Day/Mojo Inc. in New York, Reebok's advertising agency, has been running a series of commercials centering on Dan O'Brien and Dave Johnson. Initially, the spots urged viewers to anticipate a competition between the two handsome young Americans for the gold medal in the decathlon at the Summer Games, which would decide who was "the world's greatest athlete."</p>
        <p>But when Mr. O'Brien unexpectedly failed to qualify for the American Olympic team, the Stoughton, Mass., footwear maker scrambled to revamp the campaign, which has been estimated to cost $30 million. One commercial hailed Mr. O'Brien's efforts, though they fell short; additional spots treated the pair's relationship in humorous fashion, as Mr. O'Brien cheered on Mr. Johnson from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>But Mr. O'Brien's support was clearly not sufficient to encourage Mr. Johnson to win a gold medal. When the decathlon ended Thursday, Mr. Johnson had won only a bronze -- hardly the kind of medal that wins medals along Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, Ms. Mansur said, "We knew it was a risk, and it is in our nature to take risks."</p>
        <p>She added that the cross-training shoes promoted by Mr. O'Brien and Mr. Johnson were selling extremely well.</p>
        <p>"Consumers asked for the 'Dan and Dave shoes,' " she said.</p>
        <p>Intriguingly, the gold medal in the decathlon was won by Robert Zmelik, a Czech athlete who has also been a Reebok endorser. Alas, Reebok never mentioned him in its campaign in this country. Like NBC, which covered the Games through a red, white and blue camera lens, Reebok's ads emphasized the all-American O'Brien-Johnson rivalry.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mansur said that in ending the campaign, Reebok had decided not to run ads saluting Mr. Zmelik's victory or featuring him with Mr. O'Brien and Mr. Johnson. She added that Reebok "will continue to support Dan and Dave," both of whom remain under contract, "and will work with both of them."</p>
        <p>"How they may fit into the marketing mix or turn up in the future is to be determined," she said.  'International Home Run'</p>
        <p>Despite the actual outcome of the decathlon, which turned the Reebok campaign's rhetoric hollow, Ms. Mansur said the company thought the advertising was a success. The reason, she added, was its ability to connect with the public.</p>
        <p>"We believe we hit an international home run in the terms of our marketing efforts," she said.</p>
        <p>Hmmmmm. Baseball. Maybe that, unlike the decathlon, is a sport Mr. O'Brien and Mr. Johnson can excel in.  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
