<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public TV And Ads: Rescue, At a Price</title>
    <meta content="09GOOD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="935850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6D8153CF93AA35755C0A961958260" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public TV And Ads: Rescue, At a Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman column says arguments against advertisements on public television outweigh those for it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Are commercials on public television, alas, an idea whose time has come? But, wait, didn't that time come several years ago? What about those plugs that open ''The Newshour'': Archer Daniels Midland (''supermarket to the world''); the C.I.T. group (''helped thousands of companies and individuals reach their goals''); New York Life (''wise investment philosophy''). Oh, I remember, they are only ''announcements,'' and the companies that pay for them are ''underwriters.''</p>
        <p>There we have one of the dilemmas that commercials pose for public television. The nation's best nightly news program is, as they say, made possible by companies whose blurbs mock the straight talking and respect for viewers that is supposed to inform both ''The Newshour'' and public broadcasting. It's enough to call up a muddle of metaphors: the camel's snout is under the tent; the dominoes are toppling; give them an inch and they take your arm; the lady proposes to be just a little bit pregnant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Are commercials on public television, alas, an idea whose time has come? But, wait, didn't that time come several years ago? What about those plugs that open ''The Newshour'': Archer Daniels Midland (''supermarket to the world''); the C.I.T. group (''helped thousands of companies and individuals reach their goals''); New York Life (''wise investment philosophy''). Oh, I remember, they are only ''announcements,'' and the companies that pay for them are ''underwriters.''</p>
        <p>There we have one of the dilemmas that commercials pose for public television. The nation's best nightly news program is, as they say, made possible by companies whose blurbs mock the straight talking and respect for viewers that is supposed to inform both ''The Newshour'' and public broadcasting. It's enough to call up a muddle of metaphors: the camel's snout is under the tent; the dominoes are toppling; give them an inch and they take your arm; the lady proposes to be just a little bit pregnant.</p>
        <p>Coming from Lawrence K. Grossman, once head of PBS and always a smart advocate for public television, the notion of soliciting advertising in a bigger way must be taken seriously. Mr. Grossman says rightly that the system needs money to generate high-quality programs. Opponents say rightly that advertisers will put their money where their interests are. That means imported hits like ''Mystery'' and ''Masterpiece Theater,'' or, to be up to date, ''Mobil Masterpiece Theater.'' It means more nature shows and travel shows, no doubt with network personalities playing host. Don't expect Mobil to go in for tough documentaries about lobbying in Washington or politics in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>All the arguments of both sides in what could be a long debate have weight:</p>
        <p>*An unwillingness to compromise, even on a matter of principle, can be self-defeating. Isn't it better to have a mildly contaminated version of public broadcasting than a purer system with fewer resources? After all, the ''announcements'' are innocuous, and everybody likes ''Mystery.'' Granted, but isn't there a point at which a nuisance becomes a threat, an intrusion becomes a takeover?</p>
        <p>*Perhaps a generous market response would permit the stations to do away with those excruciating fund-raisers. Or would it only mean that viewers would be afflicted by both fund-raisers and commercials on the principle that stations cannot ever get enough of that wonderful stuff? Will viewers continue to be as generous?</p>
        <p>*If advertisers flock to the call, public television may be able to do new and more daring programs. But won't public television's enemies in Congress cite the injection of private money as a reason for cutting back further on public money, making the system even more dependent on corporation largess? And won't needy or greedy stations be tempted to lure ever more advertisers with ever more crowd pleasers? The Three Tenors every three hours?</p>
        <p>Mr. Grossman's proposal to permit commercials two nights a week (will they be known as ''enhanced announcements'' or ''enriched baloney''?) seems to be a sign of desperation. In quest of more edifying programs, he agrees to a further retreat from the ideal of an institution created to hold out against the commercialization that suffuses the entire culture.</p>
        <p>Despite his good intentions, it's a bad idea. Advertisers have a record of inspiring acquiescence, not liberation, in their beneficiaries, and given the pressures on public stations, it is hard to rouse much confidence in the mere humans who run them to resist the power of the advertising dollar once it is available.</p>
        <p>And even aside from the invitation to more pop programs, the commercials themselves (except possibly for the self-kidding ones) are inherently insulting to the audience that public television is supposed to be serving and nurturing.</p>
        <p>Public television was created in recognition of what commercial television can do and, pointedly, what it is incapable of doing. Every new bow to commercialization undermines the basic mission of what used to be called noncommercial broadcasting and makes it harder even for its champions to support it.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
