<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Catching Up: Boots, Booze and Blues</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NIGHTCLUBS AND CABARETS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DA1F31F93AA35757C0A963958260" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Catching Up: Boots, Booze and Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BLUES in the night? "Not in my backyard," I sing to all who will listen, predicting noise, cars, milling drunkards in the dark and empty bottles in the morning.</p>
        <p>Carl Jensen listens. From his stall at the Union Square Park Greenmarket, he can see the grand old American Savings Bank building on East 15th Street, soon to become a fast-fun franchise, a 1,500-seat restaurant-nightclub called the House of Blues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BLUES in the night? "Not in my backyard," I sing to all who will listen, predicting noise, cars, milling drunkards in the dark and empty bottles in the morning.</p>
        <p>Carl Jensen listens. From his stall at the Union Square Park Greenmarket, he can see the grand old American Savings Bank building on East 15th Street, soon to become a fast-fun franchise, a 1,500-seat restaurant-nightclub called the House of Blues.</p>
        <p>"Blues sounds O.K. at first," said Mr. Jensen, a bearded political philosopher who trucks down from Burdett, N.Y., each weekend with his wife, Ginny, and his dog to sell mustards and jellies. "But to make money, club owners have to get their patrons hammered. To do that, you have to crank up the volume. All the studies say that loud music increases drinking. I wouldn't trust them to keep the place bluesy and upscale."</p>
        <p>Mr. Jensen remembers when patrons of the late, unlamented Underground, which was diagonally across the park, would pour out at dawn, hammered, and beat up farmers setting up in the market.</p>
        <p>He didn't have much time to talk, however, because customers were asking for Boots, the homeless city dog the Jensens took in last summer. Last month, Boots's left foreleg was amputated when a 12-pound malignant tumor was removed.</p>
        <p>He was doing fine, dozing under the truck, wrapped in dressings. The Jensens have spent $1,200 so far on the 8-year-old dog's surgery. About half has come back in donations and from sales of cookies shaped like Boots. Mrs. Jensen says she's not even thinking about the heartworm treatments he'll soon need, much less about a blues club part owned by the actors Dan Ackroyd and Jim Belushi and brought to us by the same sensibility (and some of the same management) that created the Hard Rock Cafe.</p>
        <p>*  This business of noise and absentee owners is on my mind these days because of the Pit, on weeknights the amiable Cheers of 15th Street, on weekends a boom box. The amped noise of its bar bands has been blasting through a plate-glass window, across a courtyard and into my bedroom. But recently, the noise seemed muffled: still annoying, but not loud enough to preclude sleep.</p>
        <p>When I stopped by early one afternoon, Cindy Hawkins, actress, agent, building super, was tending an empty bar and working on her book, "Maniac in the Kitchen: Stop Me Before I Cook Again," which features her Sweet Jack Taters, a sweet potato casserole soaked in Jack Daniel's.</p>
        <p>She sent me upstairs to the bandstand. The plate-glass window had been entirely boxed in with plasterboard. Good for me, but not much help for the houses on either side. They share party walls.</p>
        <p>"People come into a neighborhood promising jobs, never promising drugs, noise, parking problems," said Ms. Hawkins after she heard my House of Blues rap. "Ever play Pick Up Sticks? It's very hard to move one stick without disturbing a few others. When Zeckendorf Towers went up, our water pressure dropped. It's never really come back. On the other hand, empty buildings aren't good, either."</p>
        <p>The Pit's owners, Vinny, Tony and Billy, all work in the nabe but live elsewhere; they are never around when the bands play. Of course, now I've got to thank them for insulating that window. Do you think Ackroyd and Belushi are going to move into Zeckendorf Towers to supervise their new outlet?</p>
        <p>I called Arthur Z. Schwartz, who is running with Aubrey Lees for Democratic Party Leaders in a gerrymandered district that cleverly avoids both the Pit and my house, but includes the bank building.</p>
        <p>If they were already elected, campaigned Mr. Schwartz, they would help all the opposed community groups sing their blues to the appropriate agencies, like the community board, the Police, Sanitation and Health Departments, the State Liquor Authority, Consumer Affairs, City Council, etc. Mr. Schwartz cited the campaign that ousted the Lone Star Cafe from the Village.</p>
        <p>"The resurgence of the Union Square area is based on businesses supporting residences, not vice versa," Mr. Schwartz said. "I would probably be against the club."</p>
        <p>*  But Daphne Mahoney would like the club in her backyard. Her Jamaican restaurant, Daphne's Hibiscus, squeaked through the winter only because catering and takeout sales rose. There were nights when only one table was served. Marketing is the problem, said Ms. Mahoney: there were weddings at the Hibiscus the past two Sundays, and most of the guests had never heard of the place.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mahoney, who lives nearby, was a beloved sales and service manager at the late, lamented Citibank branch on 15th Street and Irving Place (another possible nightclub site), but hasn't been able to relocate her popularity to her restaurant on 14th Street and Second Avenue. The nabe, alas, looks west.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mahoney credits the 14th Street Business Improvement District with improved sanitation, security and lighting that have changed the look of the block at night from one of a horror show to that of a deserted movie set. But there are still too many empty storefronts and no major attractions to bring in customers. Ms. Mahoney wants the House of Blues to move in next door.  COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
