<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>De Gaulle Is Thrown A 1-2 Punch</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="140029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKHAM, JAMES M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LE PEN, JEAN-MARIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITTERRAND, FRANCOIS (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHIRAC, JACQUES (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880428T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DB1738F93BA15757C0A96E948260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>De Gaulle Is Thrown A 1-2 Punch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES M. MARKHAM, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKHAM, JAMES M</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, April 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: One clear loser in the first round of France's presidential election Sunday was Charles de Gaulle. The founder of the Fifth Republic died in 1970, but two of his surviving foes are having posthumous revenge on his legacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: One clear loser in the first round of France's presidential election Sunday was Charles de Gaulle. The founder of the Fifth Republic died in 1970, but two of his surviving foes are having posthumous revenge on his legacy.</p>
        <p>One clear loser in the first round of France's presidential election Sunday was Charles de Gaulle. The founder of the Fifth Republic died in 1970, but two of his surviving foes are having posthumous revenge on his legacy.</p>
        <p>One of them is Jean-Marie Le Pen, the leader of the National Front, which has divisively painted third-world immigrants as the scapegoats for France's ills. Mr. Le Pen's surprising showing made him a possible arbiter of the runoff vote between President Francois Mitterrand and Prime Minister Jacques Chirac on May 8. The other surviving foe is the Socialist President himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Le Pen appeals to a disaffected electorate that is troubled by unemployment and by immigrants in France. But as a former paratrooper in colonial Algeria, he has tapped a vein of anti-Gaullist resentment and a lurking sympathy for Marshal Henri Philippe Petain, who headed the collaborationist Vichy Government during World War II. Ex-Colonists at the Forefront</p>
        <p>It is not by accident that some of Mr. Le Pen's most fervent supporters are former colonists from Algeria who still loathe de Gaulle for allowing the North African nation to become independent in 1962. The National Front counts in its ranks a number of former officers who plotted against de Gaulle in a violent, last-gasp effort to keep Algeria French.</p>
        <p>One of the most conspicuous is Pierre Sergeant, a National Front legislator and a former Foreign Legion officer who was condemned to death for his role in the 1961 anti-Gaullist putsch in Algeria but later granted amnesty. In that failed army coup, four generals opposed to Algerian independence plotted the seizure of Algiers, but most regular officers remained loyal to de Gaulle.</p>
        <p>Suggestively, at Mr. Le Pen's most recent electoral rally, the crowd wildly cheered in memory of Gen. Raoul Salan, the leader of the 1961 putsch and the instigator of last-ditch efforts in 1962 to block Algerian independence through terrorist strikes.</p>
        <p>''It is the revenge of Vichy and the war of Algeria,'' said Jean Lacouture, the author of a three-volume biography of de Gaulle, speaking of the upsurge of support for Mr. Le Pen. ''There are still 10 percent of Frenchmen who remain attached to Petain and another 10 percent who have not forgiven the loss of Algeria.'' A Sense of Mission Awry</p>
        <p>Mr. Lacouture said that de Gaulle had tried to give France a ''noble and melancholy'' sense of mission after its defeat in war and the loss of its colonies. Mr. Le Pen, the historian argued, represented another response to ''the post-grandeur'' phase of the nation's history.</p>
        <p>''Le Pen is the nasty, horrible and dirty face of the Gaullist experience, the face that de Gaulle tried to endow with a certain pride,'' he said. ''Gaullism was a positive response, but Le Penism is a vengeance, the inversion of Gaullism.''</p>
        <p>Another posthumous blow to de Gaulle has been landed by Mr. Mitterrand, who fiercely opposed the general and who three decades ago denounced the Fifth Republic constitution as ''a permanent coup d'etat.'' In fact, the de Gaulle-Mitterrand animosity had its origins in their first meeting in Algiers during World War II, a demonstration of the longevity of political feuds in France. Revival of Factions</p>
        <p>At 71 years old, Mr. Mitterrand is within reach of something no leader of the Fifth Republic ever attained: his second election as President by universal suffrage. But many Gaullists are convinced that if Mr. Mitterrand is re-elected to a seven-year term he intends to transform the nature of the Fifth Republic, reviving the primacy of political parties and factions that the general so detested.</p>
        <p>''One of the constants of Mitterrand's career is that he wants to destroy the Fifth Republic and justify his opposition to the Constitution in 1958,'' said Olivier Guichard, a former Gaullist minister who is a member of the National Assembly.</p>
        <p>''His objective,'' continued Baron Guichard, seated in a small office off the Place du Palais Bourbon, ''is to create an Assembly where there is no majority and where he can have the kind of success he did under the Fourth Republic. After all, this is a man who was a minister 11 times with a parliamentary group of 12 people. Not bad.''</p>
        <p>At the stately Senate building, overlooking the Jardins du Luxembourg, Maurice Couve de Murville, the veteran former Gaullist Foreign Minister, was asked what the general would think of France's murky political situation in 1988. The white-haired senator answered softly: ''He would not be proud.'' Savoring the Prerogative</p>
        <p>Whatever historic hostility Mr. Mitterrand may harbor toward the Fifth Republic Constitution, he has savored, and jealously guarded, the prerogatives of the Gaullist presidency. But he has said that he favors an end to the ''monarch-presidency'' and would be a referee, not a commanding officer, in a second term.</p>
        <p>As far as Gaullists are concerned, the vote on Sunday was ignominious for a final reason. The standard-bearer of the latter-day Gaullist movement, Prime Minister Chirac, won only 19.9 percent of 30.8 million votes cast, only 5.5 percentage points more than Mr. Le Pen, the fourth-place finisher. Raymond Barre, a conservative former Prime Minister, finished third. Opinion polls before the ballot had put Mr. Chirac's percentage in the middle 20's.</p>
        <p>A good Gaullist, explained Pierre Sudreau, a politician who helped write the Fifth Republic Constitution, should rally the broadest coalition possible. Alas, Mr. Sudreau remarked, President Mitterrand was doing a far better job than Mr. Chirac in this regard.</p>
        <p>''If Mitterrand had not harassed him so much, well, I cannot say that de Gaulle would have actually voted for Mitterrand,'' Mr. Sudreau said. ''But he would not have voted for Chirac. He would have abstained.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
