<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Climbing His Way Back, With Help From Neediest</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="575995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK TIMES NEEDIEST CASES FUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC1230F931A25751C1A964958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Climbing His Way Back, With Help From Neediest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One day Larry K. was wearing expensive suits, hatching deals for a prominent brokerage firm and dating a woman he loved. The next day he woke up in a mental hospital and his life began a seven-year plunge that left him an angry and confused man cut off from family and friends.</p>
        <p>After that first breakdown, he wandered the country for years, working at menial jobs as a series of doctors tried to treat him. "It was a tough time," he recalled the other day. "I fought with everybody and I was always wrapped up in my head. I was a total basket case."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One day Larry K. was wearing expensive suits, hatching deals for a prominent brokerage firm and dating a woman he loved. The next day he woke up in a mental hospital and his life began a seven-year plunge that left him an angry and confused man cut off from family and friends.</p>
        <p>After that first breakdown, he wandered the country for years, working at menial jobs as a series of doctors tried to treat him. "It was a tough time," he recalled the other day. "I fought with everybody and I was always wrapped up in my head. I was a total basket case."</p>
        <p>Doctors finally diagnosed manic-depression in 1988 and he began taking lithium, which cured him of the worst symptoms. Now, at the age of 43, he is struggling to start over with help from Metro-House, a shelter financed in part by United Jewish Appeal-Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York, a charity aided by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund. 'I Don't Have to Worry'</p>
        <p>Metro-House, which opened earlier this year, assists mentally ill people who are trying to fit back into society after leaving hospitals. About 40 men and women live at the transitional shelter at 117 West 70th Street in Manhattan, which is run by the Metropolitan New York Coordinating Council on Jewish Poverty.</p>
        <p>Metro-House provides Larry K. with a room and meals while he searches for his first stable job in more than a decade. When he feels nervous about his return to the workaday world, he can seek out counselors there for advice and support.</p>
        <p>"I'm constantly getting better now," he said. "This place has been very helpful. It gives me a place to stay, so I don't have to worry."</p>
        <p>This year's Neediest appeal, the 81st, comes during a relentless recession in New York City that has heaped added burdens on charities like U.J.A.-Federation. Many are trying to aid growing numbers of the newly unemployed while also caring for people like Larry K.</p>
        <p>The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund was born in 1911, when Adolph S. Ochs, the publisher of The Times, decided that his readers would be eager to improve their city if they only knew about the poverty around them. The 1992-93 campaign ends on Feb. 28.</p>
        <p>The Times pays for the fund's overhead, so all contributions are given directly to the seven charities, which must rely more and more on private donations because of strained budgets and reduced government help.</p>
        <p>Now that his illness is under control, Larry K. wants to find a job at a brokerage, even though he would have to start slowly and could not put in the long hours he was accustomed to before his first breakdown.</p>
        <p>"I loved that work and I was good at it," he said. "I feel like I have the chance to pick up with the rest of my life. This has been a very difficult and trying period. But now I feel good. I get along with people. My head is clear. I feel like I've gotten a new lease on life." Previously recorded . . . $1,529,636.68 Recorded yesterday . . . $30,824.00 Total . . .  $1,560,460.68</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
