<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 700 Students, French Cuisine 101</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="450521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGER, JOSEPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAUSMAN, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC1E3DF936A35755C0A967958260" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 700 Students, French Cuisine 101</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERGER, JOSEPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST of the 11 New York City high school students dining at L'Ecole restaurant yesterday had never eaten in a French restaurant before, and until three months ago, they had certainly never cooked a French meal.</p>
        <p>But since February, they have been part of a new program that has initiated 700 home economics students into the mysteries and near-surgical skills of French cooking. And they were reaping their rewards, only partly in the form of escalopes of codfish and pommes dauphine prepared for them by a kitchen supervised by a former chef to Charles de Gaulle and a former chef at Le Cirque.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST of the 11 New York City high school students dining at L'Ecole restaurant yesterday had never eaten in a French restaurant before, and until three months ago, they had certainly never cooked a French meal.</p>
        <p>But since February, they have been part of a new program that has initiated 700 home economics students into the mysteries and near-surgical skills of French cooking. And they were reaping their rewards, only partly in the form of escalopes of codfish and pommes dauphine prepared for them by a kitchen supervised by a former chef to Charles de Gaulle and a former chef at Le Cirque.</p>
        <p>Under a Board of Education program organized by Richard Grausman, a cookbook author, at 12 high schools, students who have never prepared anything more elaborate than hamburgers and rice and beans were taught to cook poached salmon, crepes, chicken piccata, profiteroles and tricolor pasta made from scratch.</p>
        <p>They have been trained in the proper handling of the knife and the omelet pan and in measurement, cleanliness and order. They can talk about presentation and garnishing, frontiers that are new for some home economics classes.</p>
        <p>"You curl your fingers when you chop," said Egbert Gibbs, an 18-year-old senior at Prospect Heights High School in Brooklyn who said he until the program began, he had been most comfortable helping his Trinidadian mother make curried goat. "That way the knife can't cut you."</p>
        <p>The students have also learned that there are different worlds and different tastes beyond the mean streets where many of them grew up, though a visitor probably could not have detected that, observing the poise with which the six girls and five boys handled L'Ecole.</p>
        <p>"I never tried French cooking," said Aisha Sanjurjo, an 18-year-old senior at Adlai Stevenson High School in the Bronx. "I'm Puerto Rican and I eat Puerto Rican food -- rice and beans, chicken and a lot of pork. French food is a lighter meal for me."</p>
        <p>Miss Sanjurjo and Mr. Gibbs were the top winners in a competition that was the icing on the program, a contest in which they were judged on their ability to chop, slice and dice, make an omelet and prepare dishes like crepes sucrees filled with creme patissiere and topped with sauce au chocolat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibbs, whom one cook described as having particulartly deft hands, won a full $12,750 scholarship for a six-month course at the French Culinary Institute on lower Broadway which operates L'Ecole. And Miss Sanjurjo, along with her teacher, Christina Lyles, won an all-expenses-paid weeklong trip to Le Cordon Bleu Cooking School in Paris.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grausman said he conceived the program as a reaction to a food-industry convention at which manufacturers were envisioning microwave ovens for the car and cookless kitchens. He wondered if home economics classes might be willing "to upgrade their instruction" and challenge students. He disregarded warnings from friends that he ought to try his program in more affluent areas with more sophisticated palates.</p>
        <p>"I figured if I could do it here I could it anywhere," he said. "People said, 'These New York kids won't know the difference between one dish and another.' But instead of an apple pie, they made an apple tart and just the appearance of that makes them feel they've been able to accomplish something their friends never have."</p>
        <p>Remarking on the skill of the students, Dorothy Cann, the institute's president, said: "What we saw in the kitchen was discipline, maturity, purpose and seriousness. Cuisine is a very civilizing thing."</p>
        <p>Still, Alair Sailhac, a former chef at Le Cirque and one of the judges, said the students had a long way to go to develop the speed, organization, economy of motion and grace under pressure that distinguishes a restaurant chef from a fine home cook.</p>
        <p>"If you are too slow, you cannot be a chef," he said.</p>
        <p>To start the program, Mr. Grausman held a one-day training session for home economics teachers to lessen the intimidation some of them felt about haute cuisine. They used his book "At Home With French Classics" (Workman, 1989) as their textbook, but he conceded that in the coming school year the teachers would need regular Saturday classes.</p>
        <p>The program's teachers said that even if their students never became chefs, they have learned how to meet deadlines, to handle delicate equipment and to understand a foreign menu. The students agreed.</p>
        <p>"They taught us the basic knowledge," said Harrison Okine, a 20-year-old junior at Stevenson who finished third in the competition. "So when you step out, you step out with confidence."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
