<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Penguins Keep Pressure on the Devils</title>
    <meta content="17devils" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1826818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L. ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EED7143EF934A25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Penguins Keep Pressure on the Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Feb. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Madden, the Devils' defensive ace, took the ice Friday night with a full face mask on his black helmet. Pittsburgh's Sidney Crosby was already at the other end of the ice, skating in lazy circles.</p>
        <p>Five days after Madden was hit in the face with a puck, his eye was still bloody and his cheek was stitched. He wanted to shadow Crosby, the N.H.L.'s leading scorer, but the Penguins showed in their 5-4 victory that they were more than a one-man team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Madden, the Devils' defensive ace, took the ice Friday night with a full face mask on his black helmet. Pittsburgh's Sidney Crosby was already at the other end of the ice, skating in lazy circles.</p>
        <p>Five days after Madden was hit in the face with a puck, his eye was still bloody and his cheek was stitched. He wanted to shadow Crosby, the N.H.L.'s leading scorer, but the Penguins showed in their 5-4 victory that they were more than a one-man team.</p>
        <p>''We kept driving and we worked hard for our chances,'' Crosby said.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh (31-17-9) scored three first-period goals and held off the Devils during a frantic finish to roll to its fifth consecutive victory and 13th in its past 15 games. The Penguins have crept to 5 points behind the first-place Devils (35-17-6) in the Atlantic Division.</p>
        <p>''They've come a long way since the beginning of the year,'' Madden said. ''They're not giving up the leads they used to get. They're a more mature hockey club.''</p>
        <p>Crosby, the Penguins' 19-year-old center, opened a power play at 10 minutes 27 seconds of the second period by winning a face-off against Madden, collecting the puck and firing in his 26th goal of the season. He had gone eight games without a goal.</p>
        <p>''Nice to get the monkey off my back,'' Crosby said.</p>
        <p>The Devils, who defeated the Penguins in three of their first four games this season, have hardly been slumping; they are 16-4-3 since Dec. 26. But the Penguins are gobbling up ground. They were 13 points behind the Devils three weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''As good of a run as we've had, Pittsburgh's had a better one,'' Devils center Scott Gomez said.</p>
        <p>The Devils trailed entering the third period, 5-2, but they scored twice in the first nine minutes. Zach Parise scored his 23rd goal, on a power play, and Travis Zajac scored his 11th goal on a long slap shot. But the Penguins held on.</p>
        <p>A season ago, Crosby's first in the N.H.L., the Penguins finished with 22 victories and 58 points, the second fewest in the league. Coach Michel Therrien said after Friday's game that he considered his team, although very talented, to still be very young.</p>
        <p>''One thing we compensate with is hungry play,'' Therrien said. ''We have no fear to play.''</p>
        <p>The Penguins scored on two of their first three shots against goaltender Martin Brodeur. Penguins defenseman Josef Melichar flipped a shot from the point, and Jarkko Ruutu tipped it past Brodeur just 3:02 into the game.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh scored again on its next shot, and Crosby got his 64th assist. Crosby shoveled a pass to the point, and Melichar and defenseman Robert Scuderi pitched it back and forth until Scuderi scored his first goal of the season at 5:19.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the best,'' Crosby said of Brodeur. ''You want to gain confidence as early as you can and keep rolling.''</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh scored a third goal at 17:54 after Devils defenseman Paul Martin failed to clear the puck. Penguins right wing Michel Ouellet collected the puck to Brodeur's right, then slipped a pass to the rookie center Jordan Staal, who scored his 24th goal.</p>
        <p>The Devils, who got second-period goals from Brian Rafalski and Patrik Elias, nearly caught up in the third period. But the Penguins locked down late in the game and prevented the Devils from mounting a final threat.</p>
        <p>''I'm very pleased with the way our players are able to compose themselves,'' Therrien said.</p>
        <p>CANUCKS 2, BLACKHAWKS 1 -- Trevor Linden and Brendan Morrison scored in the shootout, and Roberto Luongo made 34 saves to lead visiting Vancouver to its third consecutive victory.</p>
        <p>Vancouver's Matt Cooke scored midway through the third to tie the score at 1-1. The victory moved the Canucks into first place in the Northwest Division. (AP)</p>
        <p>BLUE JACKETS 3, SHARKS 0 -- Gilbert Brule, Fredrik Modin and Sergei Fedorov each had a goal and an assist and Fredrik Norrena stopped 29 shots to give Columbus a home victory.</p>
        <p>San Jose was shut out for the second consecutive game, running its scoreless streak to 148 minutes 30 seconds. (AP)</p>
        <p>BLUES 1, PREDATORS 0 -- Bill Guerin scored late in the second period, Manny Legace stopped 19 shots and host St. Louis defeated Nashville for the first time in 15 games.</p>
        <p>It was the Predators' first game since they acquired center Peter Forsberg from Philadelphia on Thursday night. (AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L. ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
