<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Moves To Ease Harm From Enron</title>
    <meta content="Y04ENR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/04/business/04ENRO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1381244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ENRON'S MANY STRANDS: THE EMPLOYEES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Street Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse First Boston</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, Chase &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, Arthur J (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scalia, Eugene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Enron Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDC1E3AF937A35757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Moves To Ease Harm From Enron</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Moves to Ease Harm From Enron</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BARBOZA and RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David; Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal government moves on two fronts to protect interests of Enron investors and retirement-plan participants, as parties in company's bankruptcy proceedings maneuver to lay claim to company's dwindling assets; Labor Department officials accuse Enron of backing out of agreement to pay independent investment firm State Street Corp to oversee its three employee pension plans, move that angry officials with agency describe as 'repudiation' of deal signed less than month ago; Enron denies backing out of deal, but Labor Department officials say dispute is sure to delay transfer of control of pension plans out of hands of Enron executives who have been criticized for not protecting interests of employees and retirees as Enron's stock plunged last fall; Securities and Exchange Commission also says it will ask that US Bankruptcy Judge Arthur J Gonzalez appoint independent examiner with expanded powers to investigate Enron's collapse and potential conflicts of interest in bankruptcy case; SEC is supporting move by group of creditors, including various pension and retirement funds, because of widespread accusations of conflicts of interest involving companies with longstanding ties to Enron, including Citigroup, Credit Suisse First Boston and J P Morgan Chase; Labor Department solicitor Eugene Scalia says Enron should abide by agreement to pay State Street Corp to oversee its pension plans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal government moved on two fronts yesterday to protect the interests of Enron investors and retirement-plan participants, as parties in the company's bankruptcy proceedings maneuvered to lay claim to the company's dwindling assets.</p>
        <p>Labor Department officials accused Enron yesterday of backing out of an agreement to pay an independent investment firm to oversee its three employee pension plans, a move that angry officials with the agency described as a ''repudiation'' of a deal signed less than a month ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal government moved to protect the interests of investors and retirement-plan participants as parties maneuvered to lay claim to Enron's dwindling assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal government moved on two fronts yesterday to protect the interests of Enron investors and retirement-plan participants, as parties in the company's bankruptcy proceedings maneuvered to lay claim to the company's dwindling assets.</p>
        <p>Labor Department officials accused Enron yesterday of backing out of an agreement to pay an independent investment firm to oversee its three employee pension plans, a move that angry officials with the agency described as a ''repudiation'' of a deal signed less than a month ago.</p>
        <p>Enron denied backing out of the deal, but Labor Department officials said the dispute was sure to delay, for at least some time, transfer of control of the pension plans out of the hands of Enron executives who have been criticized for not protecting the interests of employees and retirees as Enron's stock plunged last fall.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission also said that it would ask today that Judge Arthur J. Gonzalez of United States Bankruptcy Court in New York appoint an independent examiner with expanded powers to investigate Enron's collapse and potential conflicts of interest in the bankruptcy case.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. said that it was supporting a move by a group of creditors, including various pension and retirement funds, because of widespread accusations of conflicts of interest involving companies with longstanding ties to Enron. Among those with possible conflicts are Wall Street banks like Citigroup, Credit Suisse First Boston and J. P. Morgan Chase.</p>
        <p>''We support the appointment of an examiner because an independent person with no relation to the transactions could investigate and report back to the court on whether there is money available to pay investors and other estate creditors,'' said Alistaire Bambach, an enforcement official at the S.E.C.</p>
        <p>The government is also stepping in to protect the interests of Enron employees who lost out when the stock tumbled ahead of the company's Chapter 11 bankruptcy filing in December.</p>
        <p>Last year, more than 60 percent of the 401(k) assets of Enron employees had been invested in company stock that quickly became worthless as Enron collapsed. In Congressional hearings in February, lawmakers were outraged to learn that one executive who serves as a trustee overseeing the plan knew last summer of warnings about the company's severe accounting problems but did nothing to protect participants in the plan. The trustees were also criticized for other aspects of their handling of the retirement plans.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from Congress and Labor Department officials, who had threatened to go to court to oust the trustees, Enron agreed in March to turn over control to the State Street Corporation, which was to be paid up to $2.7 million a year out of Enron's assets. The three retirement plans have combined assets of more than $2 billion, according to government and company officials.</p>
        <p>But during a hearing Tuesday afternoon before Judge Gonzalez, lawyers for Enron backed out of the agreement, the Labor Department said, and the judge said he would not approve the payments to State Street out of the company's assets. Enron's creditors also opposed the deal, contending that any payments should come from the assets of the retirement plans, not the company.</p>
        <p>But Labor Department officials say that is unacceptable and that Enron should stick to its deal. ''The representations made by Enron's attorneys in federal court yesterday were a contradiction and repudiation of the agreement Enron signed with the federal government,'' Eugene Scalia, the Labor Department solicitor, said in an interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I called Enron's general counsel at 9 a.m. this morning and made crystal clear to him that we expect them to abide by the agreement they signed, and if I were in Enron's shoes, this isn't the way I'd be dealing with the government right now,'' Mr. Scalia said.</p>
        <p>Labor Department officials declined to say what steps they might take next, but legal experts said they had three choices: to ask the judge to reconsider or agree to have State Street paid on an interim basis; to use the retirement plan assets to pay the fees for a short time while another arrangement is worked out; or to sue Enron.</p>
        <p>Daniel Weiss, the spokesman for Representative George Miller of California, the senior Democrat on the House Committe on Education and the Workforce, accused Enron of ''hoodwinking'' the government and urged the Labor Department to take action. ''The same pension administrators are in place who were there during the downfall of Enron, when they said not one word to employees in the retirement plan about the declining financial condition of Enron,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But late yesterday, Enron took issue with the Labor Department's characterization of the company's actions, saying that the company's lawyers had told the judge it ''did not oppose'' paying State Street's fees out of the estate. But according to an Enron spokesman, the judge then asked whether the payments to State Street might be considered ''prepetition'' claims, and thus might make them ineligible to be paid from the estate, because the events that prompted the change in pension trustees occurred before Enron sought bankruptcy court protection.</p>
        <p>In response to that question, Enron's lawyer told the judge that the change arose ''as a result of events before the bankruptcy, not after,'' said the spokesman, Mark Palmer.</p>
        <p>The Securities and Exchange Commission said it had stepped into the Enron bankruptcy case because the agency was interested in ensuring that public investors who lost money in the case were treated fairly.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C. joined a group of creditors who have long been pushing for an independent trustee to take charge of the bankruptcy case because of all the potential conflicts of interest involving Enron and its major creditors.</p>
        <p>Judge Gonzalez asked the creditors and others involved in the case to resolve their dispute, and many have agreed to do that by asking for the appointment of an independent examiner to investigate Enron's collapse, and possibly even determine whether some major creditors are liable for their dealing with Enron.</p>
        <p>Some of the largest Enron creditors are thought to have played a role in creating and investing in some of the off-balance-sheet partnerships that helped bring down the company.</p>
        <p>Several major law firms in the Enron bankruptcy case also had longstanding ties to Enron and could also be involved in potential conflicts of interest, some creditors say.</p>
        <p>''The creditors are led by entities that were aiders and abettors of the fraud,'' said Andrew Entwistle, a lawyer who represents the Florida state pension fund. ''We want an examiner with subpoena power to come in and investigate the special- purpose entities, the accounting fraud, the insiders, the lawyers and the accountants, among others.''</p>
        <p>The creditors' committee has also agreed to the appointment of an independent examiner, but the group has fought the idea of giving an independent examiner expanded powers, arguing that it would not want the examiner to duplicate its work.</p>
        <p>''This is all a tempest in a teapot,'' said Stephen Blauner, a spokesman for Milbank, Tweed, Hadley &amp; McCloy, the law firm that represents the creditors committee. ''The committee has endorsed the concept of an examiner. The only issue is the scope. The committee is desirous of avoiding duplication of efforts. It should be in everyone's interest to avoid excessive expenditure of the estate's precious assets.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Entwistle said the real issue was who had control. ''What they're really saying is we want the creditors' committee to control the process and the examiner to be limited,'' he said. ''But we want an examiner who is only accountable to the court.''</p>
        <p>ENRON'S MANY STRANDS: THE EMPLOYEES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
