<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Annual Appraisal of the Urge to Innovate</title>
    <meta content="19ZIMM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montclair Art Museum (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DF1430F93AA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Annual Appraisal of the Urge to Innovate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <dateline>MONTCLAIR</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews works on view at 1998 New Jersey Arts Annual at Montclair Art Museum; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS year's edition of the New Jersey Arts Annual at the Montclair Art Museum doesn't just stand (or hang) there decorously. Some of the work is sharp and direct, while other pieces challenge through subtlety and indirection. Although the work mostly stays within traditional, recognizable genres and media, the 47 artists share an urge to innovate.</p>
        <p>The exhibition comprises selections agreed upon by a diverse group of judges: Maurice Sanchez, a master printmaker from Montclair; Grace Stanislaus, the former director of the Museum for African Art in Manhattan, and Gail Stavitsky, curator of collections and special exhibitions at the Montclair Art Museum. Any artist who lives or works in New Jersey, or was born in the state, was eligible to submit slides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS year's edition of the New Jersey Arts Annual at the Montclair Art Museum doesn't just stand (or hang) there decorously. Some of the work is sharp and direct, while other pieces challenge through subtlety and indirection. Although the work mostly stays within traditional, recognizable genres and media, the 47 artists share an urge to innovate.</p>
        <p>The exhibition comprises selections agreed upon by a diverse group of judges: Maurice Sanchez, a master printmaker from Montclair; Grace Stanislaus, the former director of the Museum for African Art in Manhattan, and Gail Stavitsky, curator of collections and special exhibitions at the Montclair Art Museum. Any artist who lives or works in New Jersey, or was born in the state, was eligible to submit slides.</p>
        <p>New Jersey art has long been closely identified with the industrial landscape, which is still a ripe subject. In the gauzily painted ''Landscapes With Tanks and Chopper,'' by Robert Kogge of Hoboken, a helicopter hovers almost invisibly over twin oil storage tanks. In ''Heading Up River,'' by David Ahlsted of Egg Harbor, factory smokestacks are in the distance, but the viewer's vantage point is a small boat tethered to a freighter.</p>
        <p>''Warehouse,'' by Tom Birkner of Lambertville, presents a empty space, all bricks and wood floors, arranged in a series of similar rooms that might continue to infinity; the bare warehouse speaks to a changed economic climate. ''Warehouse'' has a country cousin in ''Farm,'' by Paul Weingarten of Montclair. This tilled field, in the style of van Gogh, careers vertiginously, a sensation exaggerated by Mr. Weingarten's canvas, which is not a true rectangle but a lopsided parallelogram.</p>
        <p>Figurative work here comes wrapped in psychological overtones. Sited so that they can be pondered at the same time are ''Path of Least Resistance,'' by Nancy Depew of Kingston, and ''One Can Be Trapped Without Realizing It,'' by Jean Kawecki of Upper Montclair. In Ms. Depew's startlingly clear canvas, a figure, reminiscent of one of Ingres's, curls into a difficult, abject position. Ms. Kawecki has fitted a generic figure, fashioned from slate and copper, between the viselike arms of a forked tree branch.</p>
        <p>On the surface, ''Watch Me,'' a large color photograph by Rosemarie Gelber of Summit, is two winsome little girls, near look-alikes, in party dresses. But one child's hair is slicked back, suggesting the possibility of androgyny. Two figures, one menacing, the other resigned, also fill the canvas of the blunt ''Death Knows Me,'' by Miriam Beerman of Upper Montclair.</p>
        <p>Artists today have abandoned the old battle in which a choice had to be made between abstraction and realism; they can use either tradition as needed. ''Wounded,'' a hanging sculpture by Elaine Lorenz of Cliffside Park, is a spiraling form made of aluminum mesh covered with beeswax and painted like flesh. It is suspended from a vine, but its trunk seems to have been savagely hacked away. Near this disturbing piece is its seductive opposite: ''Trisect,'' by Estella Lackey of Hoboken, who has simply stretched black lace on a triangular metal frame.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey poet William Carlos Williams once wrote, ''No ideas but in things,'' and the category of common objects includes, among other work, the stunning film noirish photographs ''Evidence No. 3'' and ''Evidence No. 4,'' by Klaus Schnitzer of Upper Montclair. In one picture is a cigar in a half-empty whisky glass; the other shows spent bullets. At the other extreme, ''Childhoods Passing,'' by Rolla Herman of Montclair, is a mobile whose elements are items of children's clothing made of brown paper.</p>
        <p>But the ideas in things can be ineffable. The face of a perplexed child, scissored from a painting and collaged onto a surface of various reds by Gloria Rodriguez of Jersey City, is haunting, and the title, ''Picture of Inner Clarity,'' isn't altogether reassuring. ''Sac,'' an amber-colored container made of latex by Marion Held of Montclair, eludes a literal reading; it might be a purse, but the sculpture also might evoke the sacrum, the wide bone forming the pelvis, since what looks like a partial spinal column made of stoneware is emerging from it. ''Breath,'' by Nancy Cohen of Jersey City, is a nearly impalpable sculpture of various materials, including glass, cement and wax. Facing a poster-size photograph of what looks like an atomic blast in ''Waiting for Convection,'' by Jeannette Louie of West Orange, is a chair in the sleek 1950's modern style that flourished alongside nuclear-age anxiety.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH a grounding in New Jersey is required, many artists have incorporated motifs from their countries of origin into their Jersey-made work. Tony Khawam, who was born in Syria but now lives in Budd Lake, was inspired by carpets for his busy painting ''Interchange,'' whose title refers to a system of highways. For her sculpture ''Watch Out America,'' Ela Shah, a native of India who now lives in Upper Montclair, has placed a teetering tower inspired by Hindu temples atop a toy mail truck. Zhiyuan Cong, who was born in China and now lives in Pompton Lakes, has etched the Great Wall in the jade and amber tones associated with Chinese painting and has included half-hidden images of venerable sages.</p>
        <p>Artists also borrow from cultures not their own. In her drawing ''Buddha,'' Batya Halpern of Montclair has prominently rendered the head of the eponymous enlightened personage. ''Journey,'' by Robert Forman of Hoboken, is almost a tour de force: a seven-foot-tall painting in yarn. It features, as a wide border, a meticulous and detailed parade of the world's people. Mr. Forman learned the yarn technique in Mexico, but this ancient method is balanced by the computer-generated center of the work, in which figures are indistinct. This work is an emblem of the spirit of innovation that rules the exhibition.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY ARTS ANNUAL</p>
        <p>Montclair Art Museum  3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair</p>
        <p>Through Aug. 16. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sundays and Thursdays, 1 to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>(973) 746-5555</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
