<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Who Made Time Their Ally</title>
    <meta content="19WITT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wittnauer Interational</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coleman, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watkins, Charles D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Watches and Clocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DB1630F93AA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Who Made Time Their Ally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By F. ROMALL SMALLS</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Wittnauer International, timepiece manufacterer based in New Rochelle, NY, which, under new leadership of Robert L Coleman and Charles D Watkins, two black entrepreneurs, is gaining national recognition; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the competitive world of timepiece manufacturing, the name of Wittnauer has stood as a symbol of quality for more than 118 years. And under the leadership of its new owners, Wittnauer has continued that tradition while finding new  market growth. As a result, the company and the team of executives who now head it have gained national recognition.</p>
        <p>Just a few years before the current barrage of billion-dollar mergers, Wittnauer International, based here, managed to make its own mark in business history. Although the price tag of $28 million was not ground breaking, the 1996 acquisition of the watchmaker by Robert L. Coleman and Charles D. Watkins, two black entrepreneurs from St. Louis, heralded a new era in the industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the competitive world of timepiece manufacturing, the name of Wittnauer has stood as a symbol of quality for more than 118 years. And under the leadership of its new owners, Wittnauer has continued that tradition while finding new  market growth. As a result, the company and the team of executives who now head it have gained national recognition.</p>
        <p>Just a few years before the current barrage of billion-dollar mergers, Wittnauer International, based here, managed to make its own mark in business history. Although the price tag of $28 million was not ground breaking, the 1996 acquisition of the watchmaker by Robert L. Coleman and Charles D. Watkins, two black entrepreneurs from St. Louis, heralded a new era in the industry.</p>
        <p>With sales of more than $40 million last year, Wittnauer was recently ranked No. 48 in the top 100 black-owned companies in the United States in the June issue of Black Enterprise, a national business news magazine devoted to issues and trends of black-owned businesses.</p>
        <p>Wittnauer was among several new entries on the list, and the company tied with a Maryland-based telecommunications distributor. This year's survey highlighted 270 black-owned companies.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview in their corporate offices here, Mr. Coleman, chief executive officer of Wittnauer, and Mr. Watkins, its president, reflected on the combined years of experience that prepared them for their acquisition of Wittnauer, which produces more than 300,000 timepieces a year. Mr. Watkins has 20 years of executive experience with groups like Southwestern Bell and the Boy Scouts of America. He earned a master's degree in public affairs from Washington University in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coleman earned an M.B.A. from Stanford University in Palo Alto, Calif., and has more than 24 years of corporate experience. He served as the president of several companies, including a 7-Up bottling franchise in St. Louis. Mr. Coleman and Mr. Watkins have been childhood friends for more than 40 years and business partners for more than a decade.</p>
        <p>After an 18-month bidding battle with some of the largest watchmakers, including Movado and Bulova, Mr. Coleman and Mr. Watkins achieved what few believed they could do when they successfully outbid their competitors in 1996 for the Wittnauer Watch Company, then a  division of Westinghouse Electric Company.</p>
        <p>Three years after founding Composite Holdings, L.L.C., Mr. Coleman and Mr. Watkins made their bid for Wittnauer. Composite Holdings is now the principal holding company of Wittnauer, which has 176 employees in the United States, Canada and Puerto Rico.</p>
        <p>Originally, Composite Holdings petitioned Westinghouse for its Micarta division, a maker of laminates like Formica.</p>
        <p>''Micarta was at that time a $95 million division with over 500 employees,'' Mr. Coleman said. ''We lost on that acquisition attempt to International Paper, and Westinghouse felt bad enough about that loss that they offered us an opportunity to bid on the Wittnauer Watch Company.'' Mr. Watkins said, ''Initially, it was a clean offer, but after we got into the process it turned into a bidding war.''</p>
        <p>Both men have a penchant for wearing a watch from the Swiss-designed Wittnauer collection on each wrist. They recalled that they were turned down by 30 financial investment agencies when they first tried to acquire Wittnauer.</p>
        <p>''It is real clear in our hearts and our minds that if we hadn't gotten together and got on our knees and prayed for doors to be opened -- and they were opened beyond what you would normally expect to be open,'' Mr. Coleman said -- the deal would not have gone through. Wittnauer International is also the largest black employer in Westchester, and Mr. Coleman and Mr. Watkins said they believed it was the only black-owned watch manufacturer in the world.</p>
        <p>The management responsibilities for running the company, which has been in its current downtown location for the last 26 years, are divided between the two Missouri natives. Mr. Coleman handles the overall financial operations of Wittnauer and Mr. Watkins oversees the daily operations like human resources, product development and marketing.</p>
        <p>''Wittnauer is a better quality watch,'' said Mark Reyman, manager of Reyman Jewelers in Mount Vernon, which has been selling fine watches and jewelry for more than a century. ''We have had Wittnauer watches for a long time. They are moderately priced fine watches in the $175 to over $1,200 range.'' Mr. Reyman said Wittnauer watches are the type of timepiece often passed down from generation to generation as a family heirloom.</p>
        <p>For most of Wittnauer's 118-year history, it has been inextricably connected with Longines watches. Longines watches were long considered as the high end of the Wittnauer Watch Company product line. The Wittnauer brand of watches were thought of as ''good value'' timepieces.</p>
        <p>According to an International Wristwatch Magazine article, ''Wittnauer watches played 'second fiddle' to Longines watches -- ironic, perhaps, given that Wittnauer was the parent company and Longines the 'child.' '' In 1872, the Swiss-born and trained watchmaker, Albert Charles Wittnauer, immigrated to New York. In 1880 Albert along with his brother and a Swiss watch importer founded A. Wittnauer Watches Company, which specialized in American-made, medium-priced timepieces with Swiss-made movement parts.</p>
        <p>For more than a century Wittnauer was the exclusive seller of Longines watches, and for 58 years the company was named the Longines-Wittnauer Company -- until 1994 -- when the two watch manufacturers ended their long relationship. In 1994 Longines joined the SMH Watch Companies, a cartel of watch companies. In 1928 Wittnauer become the first watchmaker in the world to make a waterproof, shockproof, antimagnetic watch called the All-Proof.</p>
        <p>Wittnauer represents what Alfred A. Edmond Jr., vice president and executive editor of Black Enterprise, said he sees as the latest trend in black business developments. ''The most important thing about Wittnauer is that, like many new growth companies on the Black Enterprise 100, they got to the Black Enterprise 100 by acquisition,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also said that more blacks are acquiring companies like Wittnauer, which appeal to a mass market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coleman and Mr. Watkins divide their time between homes in Connecticut and St. Louis. They both serve on various advisory boards and take part in a number of organizations in the county.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins has been working with Westchester Community College in developing its long-term financial planning, and Mr. Coleman is the chairman of the Westchester and Rockland African-American Chamber of Commerce, which was organized to assist black-owned businesses.</p>
        <p>As for the company's ranking in Black Enterprise's Top 100, Mr. Watkins said: ''We were somewhat reluctant because we didn't want to seem as if we were bragging about our stature in the business community. But we are excited and honored to be associated with such distinguished black-owned companies.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Edmond of Black Enterprise said: ''It is amazing in the past 30 years to see what African-Americans have accomplished. As old as the brand name of Wittnauer is, it would have been inconceivable in my mother's generation that black men would own Wittnauer. It is a testament that African-Americans now own a brand of that quality.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
