<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Pimpernel' Again, Because Everybody Knows His Name</title>
    <meta content="19PERL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Richard E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgovern, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaw, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Scarlet Pimpernel, The (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF1E31F93AA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Pimpernel' Again, Because Everybody Knows His Name</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>PRAGUE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on joint A&amp;E and BBC three-part television mini-series The Scarlet Pimpernel, which is being filmed in Prague, Czechoslovakia, and stars Richard E Grant, Elizabeth McGovern and Martin Shaw; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE gilt and crystal chandeliers sparkle, the marble walls shimmer, and the elegant china on the dining table is straight out of the 18th century. This is a set for ''The Scarlet Pimpernel,'' the ever-popular story of love and double lives, action and derring-do, in the aftermath of the French Revolution.</p>
        <p>Apparently there can never be too many versions of the story, which was immortalized by Leslie Howard and Merle Oberon on film in 1935 and has been produced on stage and screen many times since. There is even a musical version currently on Broadway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE gilt and crystal chandeliers sparkle, the marble walls shimmer, and the elegant china on the dining table is straight out of the 18th century. This is a set for ''The Scarlet Pimpernel,'' the ever-popular story of love and double lives, action and derring-do, in the aftermath of the French Revolution.</p>
        <p>Apparently there can never be too many versions of the story, which was immortalized by Leslie Howard and Merle Oberon on film in 1935 and has been produced on stage and screen many times since. There is even a musical version currently on Broadway.</p>
        <p>Now A&amp;E, which brought ''Pride and Prejudice,''  ''Emma'' and ''Tom Jones'' to American cable television, is producing ''The Scarlet Pimpernel'' with the BBC. The three-part, six-hour mini-series, replete with 1,200 costumes and visually rich locales in the Czech Republic, promises to be  lush in the current literary-adaptation style. One of the main attractions of filming the Pimpernel's tale yet again, at a cost of $9.1 million, a princely sum for television, is the opportunity for a high-class adventure story.</p>
        <p>''With all his disguises and rescues, the Pimpernel was really like the first crusader, the first Superman,'' explained Delia Fine, A&amp;E's vice president for film, drama and the performing arts. ''When you put the combination of adventure and romance against the horrors of the French Revolution, it stands the test of time.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, while not everyone may remember the story line, the recognition level of the name Scarlet Pimpernel in many parts of the world is extraordinarily high.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the story, set in 1792, is Sir Percy Blakeney, a foppish English aristocrat who is in reality the elusive Scarlet Pimpernel, rescuer of innocent French aristocrats from the guillotine. He is a master of disguise, whisking counts and countesses from under the nose of Chauvelin, the French Government's most hard-headed zealot.</p>
        <p>Blakeney's wife is the intelligent and beautiful Marguerite, a French actress who quotes Rousseau and once had an affair with Chauvelin. The strained marriage that we initially see between Percy and Marguerite is transformed into one of love and trust as they work together under life-threatening conditions.</p>
        <p>The stars of this new version are Richard E. Grant, whose most recent film role was as the Spice Girls' manager in ''Spice World''; Elizabeth McGovern, the American actress who while still a teen-ager rushed to fame in Robert Redford's ''Ordinary People'' and most recently appeared in the 1997 film ''The Wings of the Dove,'' and the English actor Martin Shaw, who was on Broadway in 1996 in ''An Ideal Husband.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. McGovern, now married, a mother and living in London -- ''Not many go from Hollywood to Hammersmith,'' she says with a laugh -- the role of Marguerite is a chance to get inside the head of a woman in a mature relationship. ''It's about people who have passions and go for it; it's not about people who sit around and think,'' she said during a break from the 90-day shooting schedule in the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>''They're always fighting,'' she said of Marguerite and Percy. ''But they love each other passionately. This is a portrait of a marriage, not a love affair.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McGovern, 35, said she was relieved to be able to be an ''actress and not the cutest, most idealized woman'' that most Hollywood scripts demanded.</p>
        <p>''For a woman not in her 20's, the stories on television often are more actor-friendly and often give the chance to play a real part,'' Ms. McGovern said. ''This is a well-written relationship. She's a grown-up. Not many parts are written for grown-up women. And she's in the center of the action, which is something all actresses are looking for.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Shaw, playing Chauvelin represents the challenge of turning a character that has traditionally been played as an unremittingly dark villain without any redemptive qualities into something more nuanced. Mr. Shaw says he tries to make the character a bit more believable and to highlight his motives.</p>
        <p>''He is the main baddie, the head of the secret police of Robespierre, a cynical opportunist who was once a revolutionary,'' Mr. Shaw said. But even as such a malevolent zealot, Chauvelin retains one ideal: his love for Marguerite, about whom he is obsessive.</p>
        <p>To give more currency to Chauvelin to contemporary audiences, Mr. Shaw said, he plays the character as a 34-year-old, much younger than in past productions. ''He's much more interesting viewed as a 1950's Maoist.''</p>
        <p>The producers of ''The Scarlet Pimpernel'' promise plenty of gorgeous scenery and staging. The Czech Republic was chosen for most of the shooting because its castles and Prague itself are much closer to the look of Paris in the 1790's than present-day France. Paris, like Prague today, still had a medieval feel to it, said the mini-series' BBC producer, Julian Murphy. Many of the castle interiors are still in good condition -- like the Clam Gallas Palace in Prague, where the crew spent a day shooting -- and many of the palaces in the countryside are derelict enough to suggest post-revolutionary France. The producers have avoided the tourist-laden town squares that the Czech authorities have recently redecorated in pastel pinks, blues and yellow and instead have chosen more dilapidated areas or have filmed at night.</p>
        <p>The costume designers have had a whole new look to translate. By the 1790's, all the corseting and restricted fashion of French dress had given way to easier, almost punklike looks. Everybody's hair is flowing or in loose ponytails. As for the dialogue, don't expect anything too specific to the period or the book, which was written in 1900 in London by Baroness Orczy, a Hungarian emigre. The story always fascinated, but the writing was never considered great literature.</p>
        <p>''Because Jane Austen wrote great dialogue, people felt obliged to put that in and be faithful to it,'' said Ms. McGovern. ''With this we can be freer.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
