<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agents' Testimony Shows Power of Starr's Office</title>
    <meta content="Y19STAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1033004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Secret Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cockell, Larry L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E0DB1330F93AA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agents' Testimony Shows Power of Starr's Office</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>LITTLE ROCK, Ark., July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Subpoenas issued to Larry L Cockell and seven other Secret Service agents assigned to Pres Clinton attest to authority of Whitewater independent counsel, Kenneth W Starr (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton is in his native state of Arkansas this weekend, but the man who for months stood at his shoulder, charged with protecting his life, is not.</p>
        <p>Larry L. Cockell, the Secret Service agent who heads the President's protective detail, was forced to remain in Washington awaiting a summons to appear before a grand jury investigating whether Mr. Clinton carried on a sexual affair with Monica S. Lewinsky, a former White House intern, and then lied about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton is in his native state of Arkansas this weekend, but the man who for months stood at his shoulder, charged with protecting his life, is not.</p>
        <p>Larry L. Cockell, the Secret Service agent who heads the President's protective detail, was forced to remain in Washington awaiting a summons to appear before a grand jury investigating whether Mr. Clinton carried on a sexual affair with Monica S. Lewinsky, a former White House intern, and then lied about it.</p>
        <p>By bringing Mr. Cockell and seven other Secret Service agents to the Federal courthouse in Washington, the Whitewater independent counsel, Kenneth W. Starr, made a powerful legal and visual statement about the authority of his office. And while it is hazardous to predict the course of any investigation, it appears that Mr. Starr is entering a decisive phase of the inquiry.</p>
        <p>Much of the legal underbrush that has hindered the independent counsel's investigation for most of this year has been removed, clearing the way for Mr. Starr to move quickly to complete the inquiry.</p>
        <p>Although questions remain on lawyer-client privilege and the assertion of a broad new privilege governing Secret Service testimony, prosecutors now have an opportunity to question officials and agents of the Secret Service about what they may have seen or heard regarding Mr. Clinton and Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Still unresolved is the question of whether -- and under what terms -- Mr. Clinton himself might answer prosecutors' questions about his relationship with Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>After a week of legal maneuvering, Mr. Starr on Friday won the right to call Mr. Cockell and seven other Secret Service agents before a grand jury to testify in the Lewinsky matter when Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist rejected a plea by the Justice Department to shield the agents from questioning. But the Chief Justice said the Supreme Court might yet decide to hear the department's appeal of lower court rulings that denied an Administration claim that Secret Service personnel are protected from having to testify regarding the President by an untested ''protective function privilege.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr's inquiry has disrupted life at the White House in ways large and small over the past four years. This week, Mr. Starr struck at the innermost circle of those around the President, the Secret Service agents who provide a 24-hour, flesh-and-bone shield against potential harm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cockell, who in February won the most prestigious job in the Secret Service as head of the Presidential detail, has been reassigned to unspecified administrative duties until his testimony has ended. Special Agent Brian Stafford, who preceded Mr. Cockell as chief of Presidential security, led the Secret Service squad accompanying Mr. Clinton to Little Rock this weekend.</p>
        <p>While the Secret Service and the White House said that Mr. Cockell and the other agents would comply with the subpoenas, there was little disguising the resentment felt at the interruption of what has been Mr. Cockell's unblemished 17-year career, which included duty guarding Presidents Ronald Reagan and George Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said on Friday that it would be inappropriate for him to comment on the Secret Service subpoenas and the reassignment of his hand-picked chief bodyguard, Mr. Cockell. But aides said that the President is seething at what he considers a violation of the intimate and confidential relationship he must have with those assigned to guard him.</p>
        <p>One Democratic ally of the President said that Mr. Clinton believes the subpoenas were a vindictive act by Mr. Starr designed to embarrass the President and humiliate the Secret Service, and he predicted a strong public backlash against Mr. Starr. Mr. Starr has denied any political motives, saying he seeks only ''the truth.''</p>
        <p>With the testimony of the agents secured, Mr. Starr is moving to complete the questioning of the inquiry's central witnesses.</p>
        <p>Linda R. Tripp, who secretly tape-recorded hours of confessional conversations with Ms. Lewinsky, has spent much of the past three weeks before the grand jury and is expected to return next week. Mr. Clinton's closest friends and advisers already have given testimony and, except for Ms. Lewinsky, few major figures remain to be called.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit is expected to rule soon on whether Mr. Clinton can invoke lawyer-client privilege to prevent the testimony of Bruce R. Lindsey, the deputy White House counsel and Mr. Clinton's closest confidant. When that issue is settled, the major remaining witnesses are Ms. Lewinsky and the President.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has resisted numerous entreaties from Mr. Starr to voluntarily provide testimony, and it is unclear whether the prosecutor can compel his compliance with a criminal subpoena.</p>
        <p>And negotiations with Ms. Lewinsky's lawyers over an immunity deal have stalled, with no indication when the talks might bear fruit. If the negotiations fail, Mr. Starr must decide whether he will indict her on charges of perjury and obstruction of justice.</p>
        <p>Lawrence G. Barcella, an experienced white-collar defense lawyer and former Federal prosecutor in Washington, said that he believed that Mr. Starr's most likely course in the near term is to call Ms. Lewinsky before the grand jury under a limited grant of immunity. Mr. Starr, he added, should benefit from the fact that Ms. Lewinsky is now represented by a pair of respected defense lawyers, Plato Cacheris and Jacob A. Stein.</p>
        <p>''You have to believe that Plato and Jake have explained to her the consequences of lying if and when she goes before a grand jury,'' Mr. Barcella said. ''They will tell her that the prosecutor has set up a situation in which the only way she can lose is by lying. That's a tremendous incentive to get her to tell the truth.''</p>
        <p>Indicting her would be costly to Mr. Starr, both legally and in public relations terms, Mr. Barcella added.</p>
        <p>''It is a one-witness case and she is the witness,'' he said. ''The prosecutor can develop tangential evidence but in the end he needs her.''</p>
        <p>Investigators still appear to be many weeks away from completing the fact-finding phase of their inquiry. They indicated that they intend to continue questioning Ms. Tripp and will bring back to the grand jury other central witnesses, including Mr. Clinton's confidential secretary, Betty Currie.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr's chief spokesman, Charles G. Bakaly 3d, has indicated that the independent counsel will not file an interim report to Congress. As a practical matter, this means that if Mr. Starr concludes he has found evidence of an impeachable offense, no report will be sent to Congress until after the November election. That is because even when the question of witnesses is complete, it will take many weeks to write a detailed report of the inquiry's findings.</p>
        <p>Republicans in Congress seem grateful not to be facing an impeachment inquiry as the fall election season opens. Earlier this year, Speaker Newt Gingrich, Republican of Georgia, harshly criticized the President almost daily and encouraged other Republicans to speak of the ''crimes'' being committed in the White House.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gingrich and other Republicans have softened their oratory in recent weeks, saying that Republicans will campaign on their legislative record this fall, not on Mr. Clinton's morals.</p>
        <p>''We have a powerful positive message to run on,'' said Christina Martin, Mr. Gingrich's press secretary. ''The Speaker in the fall will be talking about our accomplishments.''</p>
        <p>Attacking the President's private behavior as a campaign tactic, one Republican House member said this week, ''is a dead horse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
