<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Begins Into Georgia Plane Crash</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRUNSWICK (GA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL TRANSPORTATION SAFETY BOARD</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC SOUTHEAST AIRLINES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COUGHLIN, SUSAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF163FF934A35757C0A967958260" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Begins Into Georgia Plane Crash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>BRUNSWICK, Ga., April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board today began piecing together the causes of a commuter airliner crash that killed former Senator John G. Tower and 22 others, Elaine Gwin quietly grieved by the side of Touchstone Parkway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board today began piecing together the causes of a commuter airliner crash that killed former Senator John G. Tower and 22 others, Elaine Gwin quietly grieved by the side of Touchstone Parkway.</p>
        <p>For months, Mrs. Gwin had feared that a tragedy would occur in her family.</p>
        <p>Her son by a previous marriage, 21-year-old Charles Gillian 3d, is a private in the First Cavalry, a mechanized unit from Fort Hood, Tex., that is still in the Persian Gulf war zone. But it wasn't Charles that Mrs. Gwin wept for today. The tears were for her husband, Tom, a 45-year-old vice president with a manufacturing company. He was confirmed today as being among the 23 people killed in the crash, about 150 yards north of the parkway. As Mrs. Gwin waited, rescue workers were beginning to remove the bodies from the wreckage.  'I Knew Tom Was on It'</p>
        <p>"My assistant called around 3 yesterday and said there had been a crash of a plane taking off. She said I might be needed at the hospital to help the families," said Mrs. Gwin, 49, the manager of social services at the Glynn-Brunswick Hospital here. "I looked at the clock and I told her it couldn't be taking off. That has to be the plane coming in. I knew Tom was on it."</p>
        <p>The commuter airliner, a Brazilian-made Embraer 120 operated by Atlantic Southeast Airlines, crashed into the woods two miles from the Glynco Jetport runway on Friday afternoon. All on board, including 20 passengers and three crew members, were killed, the National Transportation Safety Board confirmed today.</p>
        <p>Susan M. Coughlin, the vice chairwoman of the safety board, who is leading the investigation, said at a news conference today that there was no evidence that weather had been a factor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coughlin said the flight, Atlantic Southeast Airlines No. 2311, had been cleared for landing by the F.A.A. Air Traffic Control Center in Jacksonville, Fla., 60 miles south. She noted that the Glynco Jetport does not have a control tower.  Nine-Month Investigation</p>
        <p>Tapes of communications between the cockpit and the controllers in Jacksonville were normal, she said, and did not indicate that the plane was experiencing any problems. The Safety Board today said the plane was new when delivered to the airline in December 1990.</p>
        <p>The plane's captain had more than 13,000 hours of flying experience and was the first commercial pilot to be certified by the Federal Aviation Administration to fly this model of Embraer plane, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Coughlin said it could take nine months for investigators to reach any conclusion about the accident.</p>
        <p>The shattered wreckage was lying in thick woods on ground matted with ferns and pine needles, leaves and bark. The site was bisected by a shallow creek and was swarming with mosquitoes. The tops of four or five trees were sheared off 50 feet above the spot where the wreckage lay.</p>
        <p>The plane's tail fin lay askew on the ground. The aluminum fuselage, charred, but still shiny in places, was clearly marked with red, orange and yellow stripes and the airlines's initials, ASA, though workers, apparently from the airline company, were beginning to use cans of spray paint to cover the markings. About a dozen investigators were picking through the wreckage and were photographing it.</p>
        <p>All of the victims' bodies were removed from the scene.</p>
        <p>Along with Mr. Tower, the dead included his 35-year-old daughter, Marian; Manley Lanier Carter Jr., an astronaut from Houston, and Dr. Nicholas E. Davies, an Atlanta internist who was to assume office as the president of the American College of Physicians later this week.  [ Obituary, page 32. ]</p>
        <p>As carloads of rescue workers, police and Federal investigators swept past her this morning, Mrs. Gwin waited for her husband's body to be recovered.  'You Don't Fool Yourself'</p>
        <p>Mrs. Gwin, who, at first, spoke with composure about the crash, said her training as a mental health counselor has helped to make her own grief bearable. "I think about what I say to patients and their families," she said. "You have to be a good listener. You don't fool yourself and tell yourself false things, like everything's going to be all right. Everything isn't all right. You let yourself cry and express what you're feeling."</p>
        <p>Then Mrs. Gwin's eyes reddened and she wept quietly as a friend gently led her away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
