<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Back in Business; Iraq Is Left to the Mercy of Saddam Hussein</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="435907"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDEPENDENCE MOVEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DE1130F934A35757C0A967958260" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Back in Business; Iraq Is Left to the Mercy of Saddam Hussein</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY the time the United Nations Security Council agreed last week on the conditions for a permanent cease-fire in Iraq, the countries that fought Saddam Hussein had already, in effect, made their peace with him. After more than a month of civil war, the Council also finally condemned the Iraqi President for his bloody repression of the insurrections within his country, and some nations were planning to air-drop humanitarian aid to masses of Kurdish refugees fleeing his tanks and helicopter gunships.  But these steps only underscored the political morass that President Bush, as the leader of the anti-Iraq coalition, found himself in when he decided to stand aside as Iraqi troops broke the back of the rebellions and the spirit of his people.</p>
        <p>The unsettling fact was that Mr. Bush -- and the world -- had refused to get involved in Iraq's civil war because of a bizarre convergence of interests with Saddam Hussein himself: the coalition that pushed the Iraqis out of Kuwait fears the disintegration of the Iraqi state, and its leaders believe that only a strong central Government in Baghdad can prevent such a breakup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY the time the United Nations Security Council agreed last week on the conditions for a permanent cease-fire in Iraq, the countries that fought Saddam Hussein had already, in effect, made their peace with him. After more than a month of civil war, the Council also finally condemned the Iraqi President for his bloody repression of the insurrections within his country, and some nations were planning to air-drop humanitarian aid to masses of Kurdish refugees fleeing his tanks and helicopter gunships.  But these steps only underscored the political morass that President Bush, as the leader of the anti-Iraq coalition, found himself in when he decided to stand aside as Iraqi troops broke the back of the rebellions and the spirit of his people.</p>
        <p>The unsettling fact was that Mr. Bush -- and the world -- had refused to get involved in Iraq's civil war because of a bizarre convergence of interests with Saddam Hussein himself: the coalition that pushed the Iraqis out of Kuwait fears the disintegration of the Iraqi state, and its leaders believe that only a strong central Government in Baghdad can prevent such a breakup.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the United States and Iraq's neighbors would have embraced a revolt in which the Iraqi Army and people joined hands, overthrew the dictator and replaced him with another ruler. But none of the allies were prepared to support a messy civil war with an unclear outcome. "Everyone was counting on a palace coup and when that didn't materialize, we were abandoned," said Talib Shibib, an Iraqi opposition leader who was foreign minister of Iraq when the Baath Party took over briefly in 1963. "No one was prepared to support a popular revolt."</p>
        <p>In Washington, supporters of the President's decisions raised the prospect of "Lebanonization" -- central authority in Iraq might totally break down, leaving Iraq shattered along sectarian and ethnic lines as foreign powers carved it into spheres of influence. Fear that Iraq would fall apart partly explains why democratizing Iraq was never on the agenda -- not for Mr. Bush, not for the coalition and not for Mr. Hussein. The Iraqi leader could have been speaking in the name of the coalition that had mauled his troops when he asked in a March 16 speech: "Is it democracy and patriotism to break Iraq into sects and ethnic communities fighting among themselves? Is it patriotism and democracy for a single Iraq to be turned into factions and clans, as happened in Lebanon?" No, he answered himself, such a fragmentation would be "a betrayal of the homeland and the people."</p>
        <p>What, then, did President Bush have in mind when he called for the Iraqi military and the Iraqi people "to take matters into their own hands" and force the Iraqi President "to step aside"? There are indications that one model he had in mind was that of Romania, where in late 1989 the people and the army together overthrew their longtime dictator, Nicolai Ceascescu, in a frenzied but brief popular upheaval that ended with his brutal execution. Couldn't that happen in Iraq, he asked aides and visitors shortly after the gulf war began, knowing there was no clear answer.</p>
        <p>Once the coalition routed Mr. Hussein's forces, the Kurds and Shiites did revolt -- but the military stuck with Mr. Hussein. It was then that Mr. Bush insisted that he had never misled the Iraqi people and that the United States had no intention of imposing a solution on Iraq.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Hussein were overthrown, the replacement envisioned by a number of senior Administration officials was a leader modeled after another Arab strongman, President Hafez al-Assad of Syria. One senior State Department official recently told a visiting European envoy that "an Iraqi Assad" would be the best the United States could hope for -- "a reliable and predictable enemy." By those standards, it would not matter that Mr. Assad had slaughtered 10,000 to 25,000 of his own people when they rose up against him in 1982. He had proven by joining and fighting in the international coalition against Mr. Hussein that he could function in the outside world with prudence and realism.</p>
        <p>The Turks took a similarly jaundiced view once they had glimpsed the possibility of a chaotic postwar Iraq. In late February, President Turgut Ozal said, "We would like to see a democratic Iraq" -- not necessarily a "Western standard democracy," but a somewhat more open society. But a few weeks later, in a news conference with President Bush in Washington, Mr. Ozal said: "I think it would be better if everybody stayed out and let the Iraqi people decide what they want to do."</p>
        <p>Initially, King Fahd of Saudi Arabia predicted that a government "would emerge in Baghdad with a national and Islamic stature" that would have good relations with Riyadh. The Saudis assembled a group of Iraqi exiles whom they hoped would form a government-in-exile. But as President Hussein held on, the Saudis seemed to lose their appetite for revolution. Last week, the Saudi Ministry of Information quietly ordered newspaper editors to stop criticizing Mr. Hussein and to limit coverage of the Iraqi civil war to news agency dispatches. Egypt's View</p>
        <p>Even Egypt seemed to favor some accommodation with Iraq. Boutros Ghali, the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs, said just before the war began that Egypt could coexist, even cooperate with Mr. Hussein, a declaration that was not challenged by other Egyptian officials. And when the Arab League was convened in Cairo at the end of March, the first time all 21 members attended since the invasion of Kuwait, the meeting broke up after only 90 minutes, although the Iraqi delegate was allowed to take his seat as if it were business as usual.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir of Israel said last week that he was outraged by the plight of the Kurds, but even Israeli leaders have stopped predicting that Mr. Hussein will be overthrown soon.</p>
        <p>Of all the countries of the region, Iran has been perhaps the most ambivalent about how to deal with the civil war. It allowed weapons, food, medicine and even armed men to move across the long border with Iraq in support of the insurgents, and it has offered to accept large numbers of Kurdish refugees. But the mullahs would not welcome the installation of a rump Islamic republic in the Shiite south, for example, if it provoked Turkey to reassert its control over the north.  Even when the Iraqis attacked the holy Shiite cities of Najaf and Karbala, the Iranians were remarkably subdued in their response. In January, Iran's Foreign Minister told the French Foreign Minister that Iran's only priorities were that Iraq not be dismembered and that Mr. Hussein not be replaced by a pro-American puppet.</p>
        <p>As the regional players moved to heal the wounds of war and the outlines of a postwar era began to emerge, what was remarkable was how little had changed. Granted, the military machine that Iraq had built was broken as a threat to his neighbors. But the region last week was beginning to look much as it had before Mr. Hussein invaded Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
