<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="08FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1495320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DE1539F93BA35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>Inspectors Survey Security At Iraqi Nuclear Site  Inspectors from the International Atomic Energy Agency arrived in Iraq to survey the loss of control over the country's nuclear program during the allied forces' drive on Baghdad. They will look into reports of lax security at the nuclear research complex in Tuwaitha, and the discovery that villagers had been using contaminated barrels for daily water use.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Shift in Heroin Trade  Colombia and Mexico have become the dominant suppliers of heroin to the United States, supplanting Asia, in a trend that experts and the authorities fear could offset American-backed successes in a war on drugs that has focused mostly on cocaine.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-21</p>
        <p>Inspectors Survey Security At Iraqi Nuclear Site  Inspectors from the International Atomic Energy Agency arrived in Iraq to survey the loss of control over the country's nuclear program during the allied forces' drive on Baghdad. They will look into reports of lax security at the nuclear research complex in Tuwaitha, and the discovery that villagers had been using contaminated barrels for daily water use.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Shift in Heroin Trade  Colombia and Mexico have become the dominant suppliers of heroin to the United States, supplanting Asia, in a trend that experts and the authorities fear could offset American-backed successes in a war on drugs that has focused mostly on cocaine.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Israeli Checkpoint Attacked  Three Palestinian gunmen opened fire at an army checkpoint on the Gaza-Israel border, causing multiple Israeli casualties before being shot dead, Israeli officials said. The attack came two days after the militant group Hamas rejected a halt to violence against Israelis.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Deadly Bombing in Afghanistan  A suspected suicide car bomber hit a military bus carrying German troops in Kabul, killing at least 4 soldiers and wounding 29 in the most deadly attack on the international security force since its work began 18 months ago, military officials said.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Thailand Quietly Fights Terror  Although Prime Minister Thaksin Shinawatra of Thailand insists publicly that his county is safely on the sidelines in the campaign against terrorism, he has secretly been helping the United States in significant ways, American officials say.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>30-42</p>
        <p>Lobbying Starts as Groups Foresee Vacancy on Court  Interest groups on the left and the right are beginning full-scale political campaigns -- including fund-raising, advertising and major research -- to prepare for what many expect to be a Supreme Court vacancy in the next several weeks.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Failings Seen at NASA  NASA is working to fix the hardware problems that contributed to the space shuttle Columbia's break-up. But the independent board that is investigating the accident has made it clear that the space agency itself also needs fixing.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Music Industry Woos Listeners  Record executives have started to address music fans directly to persuade people to buy their product again. How well they succeed is likely to determine the way music is produced for years to come.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Episcopalians Elect Gay Bishop  New Hampshire Episcopalians elected the first openly gay bishop anywhere in the worldwide Anglican Communion, a step likely to roil the church in America and England.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>An I.R.S. Reversal  The Internal Revenue Service has restored the tax-exempt status of a charitable organization that helped pay for lectures by former House Speaker Newt Gingrich, a step that some experts say is unusual.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Oakland Chief Is Ousted  Dennis K. Chaconas, the school superintendent in Oakland, Calif., was ousted after three years in control of the financially troubled system.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>45-52</p>
        <p>Nursing Home Workers Vent Frustration in Report  Nursing home workers in New York feel overwhelmed and ill-treated, and fear for the care of residents, largely because staffing is inadequate, according to a new study.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Science on the Sound  About 160 scientists converged on Long Island Sound armed with microscopes and butterfly nets to count and classify plant and wildlife, in what they called a BioBlitz.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Fresh Air Fund</p>
        <p>52</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Freddie Blassie  The professional wrestler known as the Vampire who became a cult figure to fans by playing the villain inside the ring during the 1950's and 1960's, he was 85.</p>
        <p>43</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>51  Weather</p>
        <p>53  Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>51</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
