<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Stage, and Off</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="676541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CITICORP CENTER (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN JEWISH THEATER</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST PETER'S CHURCH (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MINETTA LANE THEATER</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">THEATER DEVELOPMENT FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, MICHAEL HENRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SONDHEIM, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBER, BRUCE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DAY THE BRONX DIED, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MERRILY WE ROLL ALONG (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Theater Development Fund</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Stephen Sondheim</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDB113CF936A15750C0A962958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Stage, and Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bruce Weber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEBER, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Black and White</p>
        <p>It was early evening, two weeks ago Sunday, a rehearsal day at the American Jewish Theater for Michael Henry Brown's drama "The Day the Bronx Died," the first play by a black playwright ever presented by the 20-year-old theater. The actors had just gone home, leaving the director, Gordon Edelstein, and the theater's artistic director, Stanley Brechner, in the cellarlike space on West 26th Street in Chelsea.</p>
        <p>At about 6:30 P.M., four young black boys, not even teen-agers, walked in from the street and downstairs into the theater lobby. They started shouting, making a disturbance, and then they left. "We just figured, 'Kids,' " Mr. Brechner said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Black and White</p>
        <p>It was early evening, two weeks ago Sunday, a rehearsal day at the American Jewish Theater for Michael Henry Brown's drama "The Day the Bronx Died," the first play by a black playwright ever presented by the 20-year-old theater. The actors had just gone home, leaving the director, Gordon Edelstein, and the theater's artistic director, Stanley Brechner, in the cellarlike space on West 26th Street in Chelsea.</p>
        <p>At about 6:30 P.M., four young black boys, not even teen-agers, walked in from the street and downstairs into the theater lobby. They started shouting, making a disturbance, and then they left. "We just figured, 'Kids,' " Mr. Brechner said.</p>
        <p>But moments later, when the incident was repeated, Mr. Brechner followed the four outside and caught up to them in a nearby supermarket.</p>
        <p>"I said: 'Don't come down again. It's private property,' " Mr. Brechner said, adding that when he asked them what the problem was, why they were bothering the theater, the answer, from one, was: "I understand you don't like blacks."</p>
        <p>Unpleasant though it was, that, Mr. Brechner thought, was the end of it. "But then I went back to the theater," he said, "and the next thing we heard was a smash."</p>
        <p>The boys had thrown a beer bottle through the theater's front window.</p>
        <p>The incident -- troubling, of course, in itself -- was an eerie reflection of the themes being presented onstage at the theater, whose 2,000 subscribers are predominantly Jewish and where there has never been so frank a work about relations between blacks and Jews.</p>
        <p>"The Day the Bronx Died," which opened on Tuesday, has a cast of 10 black and 2 white actors. It takes place in 1968, just before and after the assassination of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., and it exposes, often in blunt fashion, profane language and at high volume, the racial biases that operate, inevitably it seems, even among friends.</p>
        <p>It's the kind of production that leaves an audience -- this particular audience, anyway -- with a sense of "We have met the enemy and he is us." People leave the theater largely silent, Mr. Brechner said. And so it was at one recent performance, with most people unable to summon up much more than a repetitive mutter: "Very powerful. Very powerful."</p>
        <p>For the actors, too, the confrontational dynamic is palpable. Mr. Brechner said he noticed that the audience had been responding appropriately to the humor of the Jewish characters, but when the black characters were joking around, the audience was less at ease. One of the play's leading actors, Akili Prince, agreed.</p>
        <p>"When I give Billy the finger, nobody laughs," he said of a scene in which his character, a black teen-ager, jocularly argues with a white friend. "When he makes remarks at me, I hear the chuckles."</p>
        <p>Referring to seminars with the cast and audience, which the theater has been holding after Sunday matinees, Kelly Neal, a black actor who plays a gang leader, said: "A lot of the 60-year-old Jewish folks have been honest. They've come clean. There's a lot of guilt. They say, 'This isn't my responsibility.' One woman said: 'Why are you doing this piece? Don't you have a moral responsibility to show something more positive?' "</p>
        <p>"It is important that black voices get heard by whites," Mr. Neal continued. "It isn't important for us to gear our voices that way, but we get value from hearing what the other 'camp' has to say. We're doing an unsafe play in an unsafe environment, and we're making magic."</p>
        <p>The boys who broke the window, all of whom are 12 years old, were quickly caught. As part of making amends, three of them are now working at the theater as ushers. One of them, it turns out, writes plays and wants to be an actor. Another, who corroborated Mr. Brechner's account of the events, played Officer Krupke in a school production of "West Side Story." His critique of "The Day the Bronx Died": "I like the acting. But I can't really judge. The whole thing was good." He likes the ushering job so much he has enlisted a friend. 'Merrily' Rolling Back</p>
        <p>Last week's announcement that the York Theater Company revival of Stephen Sondheim's "Merrily We Roll Along" would open at the Minetta Lane Theater instead of at St. Peter's Church, in the Citicorp Center, the York's usual home, was premature.</p>
        <p>The deal, which would have moved the show to a 399-seat house from a 160-seat one and would have allowed the Minetta Lane's owners, Mitchell Maxwell and Alan Schuster, to produce the show commercially themselves after four weeks, fell through late last Friday, long after the York sent out a press release and Mr. Maxwell confirmed the details. But John Breglio, Mr. Sondheim's lawyer, who said he was stunned to read that the transfer arrangement was completed, said his client had never agreed to terms. He wouldn't say what the deal-breaker was, but an obviously distressed Mr. Maxwell said it concerned the play's potential ancillary earnings -- recordings, road companies and the like -- the producers ordinarily share with the author on the basis of the length of the run.</p>
        <p>"The subsidiary interests being offered to us were not acceptable," Mr. Maxwell said.</p>
        <p>The snag will delay the show's opening by two weeks. Performances begin on May 26 at St. Peter's Church. "It's no real hardship," said the director, Susan H. Schulman. "Both spaces are problematic." Homage to Hal Prince</p>
        <p>The Theater Development Fund, subsidizer of plays, administrator of TKTS and, in general, supporter of the performing arts, turns 25 this year, an occasion to be noted May 22 with a gala celebration, including a black-tie dinner in Shubert Alley and an hourlong show at the Broadhurst Theater, which will be an homage to Hal Prince. (Tickets are $500; information: 212-221-0885.)</p>
        <p>The show is to be directed by Lonny Price, an actor and director in his own right, who first met Mr. Prince in 1975, when, as a high school student, he went to work for the director as a gofer. Six years later, Mr. Prince cast him in "Merrily We Roll Along."</p>
        <p>"I used to invest my bar mitzvah money in Hal's shows," said Mr. Price, who is now 35. "I had $1,000 in 'Pacific Overtures,' and $1,000 in 'On the 20th Century' and 'Side by Side by Sondheim.' 'Pacific' was a bust, '20th Century' I don't remember. But with 'Side by Side' a check for, like, $4 comes in every couple of years."</p>
        <p>For this you pay homage? Well, maybe there's something else.</p>
        <p>"After 'Merrily' opened, Hal came to my dressing room," Mr. Price recalled. "He said: 'I'm sorry I didn't give you a hit. I think I gave you a good show, but I'm sorry I didn't give you a hit.' That's why you want to give back."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
