<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expectations Still Soar a Mile High</title>
    <meta content="01SMIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All-Star Games</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Denver (Colo)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Claire</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Denver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DB113FF932A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expectations Still Soar a Mile High</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Claire Smith</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Claire</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses soaring expectations in Denver, Colo, for festivities surrounding, and including, baseball's All-Star Game (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For most players, the All-Star Game provides a respite from the longest regular season among professional team sports. That should be the case for everyone heading to the midseason festivities in Denver next week. Except for Mark McGwire.</p>
        <p>McGwire, the most-watched player in the land, may have his chase of Roger Maris's season home run record of 61 put delayed come the midseason break Monday through Wednesday. But that is not so of the demands that he continue to be Herculean. Not when McGwire, the brightest star in the constellation of players shooting toward Maris-like heights, will be on display at Coors Field, that home run haven that sits a mile above sea level.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For most players, the All-Star Game provides a respite from the longest regular season among professional team sports. That should be the case for everyone heading to the midseason festivities in Denver next week. Except for Mark McGwire.</p>
        <p>McGwire, the most-watched player in the land, may have his chase of Roger Maris's season home run record of 61 put delayed come the midseason break Monday through Wednesday. But that is not so of the demands that he continue to be Herculean. Not when McGwire, the brightest star in the constellation of players shooting toward Maris-like heights, will be on display at Coors Field, that home run haven that sits a mile above sea level.</p>
        <p>To all of baseball the collision of power, appeal, a player and a ball park is viewed as a gift from on high. One can only hope that it is as nice for McGwire, who has shown signs of chafing of late because of the constant attention.</p>
        <p>McGwire may be able to blast the ball deeper and more often than any of his competitors, making him the odds-on favorite to catch Maris. What McGwire didn't want to catch was the debilitating waves of attention, the sort that caused Maris anything but joy in 1961, when that Yankee great eclipsed Babe Ruth's record of 60.</p>
        <p>Maris almost succumbed to the pressures and the unfair vilification by those who thought anything Ruthian should remain sacrosanct. McGwire, however, is enjoying nothing but waves of adulation from the fans and positive attention from the news media. But sometimes waves of any sort can overwhelm, and McGwire, who hit his 37th homer last night, is showing signs that the waves are close to knocking him off his feet. The Cardinals had hoped that McGwire would be spared the more negative aspects of the chase.</p>
        <p>Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa said: ''Our thought here is that we hope the fans have a lot of fun with the chance. And the more people having big years the better the chance any of them will have, including Mark, because the pressure will be a lot less.''</p>
        <p>There are others gamely chasing both McGwire and Maris. Seattle's Ken Griffey Jr. leads the American League with 32 homers. Sammy Sosa of the Cubs also has 32.</p>
        <p>Griffey, arguably the most recognizable and popular player in the game, is enjoying relative anonymity when it comes to home runs, comfortably riding the jet stream of attention being heaped on McGwire. And Sosa? He will likely remain a delicious appetizer and McGwire the main meal. McGwire's impact is that great. And unfortunately that is swinging both ways. McGwire is showing signs of being a bit overwhelmed by the home-run hysteria that so far is only threatening to consume him everywhere he travels.</p>
        <p>Cardinal batting practice is suddenly a hot ticket, whether at home or away. More than 18,000 fans turned out when McGwire made his first appearance in Houston's Astrodome on June 16. He popped nine homers at practice, then said, ''I felt like a caged lion, and I didn't like it.''</p>
        <p>The happening isn't limited to fans. Ball clubs are happily opening gates early. Every television station, newspaper and magazine wanting to record a segment of a potentially historic season is flocking to the parks, so much so that the Cardinals have had to regiment interviews and deny most every television request. One station even broadcast play-by-play of McGwire's batting practice in Arizona. ''Ridiculous,'' the big first baseman told reporters.</p>
        <p>Now, individual interviews are a thing of the past. The Cardinals have stepped in to help their star, organizing group sessions. Yesterday in St. Louis, McGwire was greeted by about 35 journalists. He spoke good-naturedly, but he only spoke for eight minutes, down from the average of 30 minutes he allowed on a just-completed road trip. It's called self-preservation and it is perhaps the biggest lesson handed down by Maris.</p>
        <p>What is intriguing is that McGwire once thought his shoulders were broad enough to carry whatever the season could bring. ''I use a lot of common sense,'' McGwire said in early spring. ''I'm too tough mentally for letting anything mess up or let anything affect why I am here or the fact of why I am here.''</p>
        <p>But as the Cardinals struggle, as McGwire tries to hold dear the real mission, he is being inundated by the peripheral issue. That 9 of his last 13 homers have come in Cardinal losses just makes the Maris talk all the more awkward.</p>
        <p>Now comes the All-Star Game break. McGwire's mere presence may cause the home run hitting contest next Monday to overshadow the All-Star Game on Tuesday. Yes, Sosa, Andres Galarraga and Juan Gonzalez will also be on hand. But which one could ever hope to outshine McGwire.</p>
        <p>Griffey alone might have been nominated to share the glory as well as the glare. But Griffey, fearful of fatigue because the Mariners will play a night game Sunday, long ago announced that he would not participate in the home run contest.</p>
        <p>Griffey's decision not only waters down the competition, but it also guarantees the focus will increase on McGwire. Life in the fish bowl goes on. And until McGwire proves otherwise, both Roger Maris's burden as well as his record remain immense.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
