<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blurb Wars: The Critic Strikes Back</title>
    <meta content="18ishe" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/18/theater/18ishe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1769857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isherwood, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Isherwood, Charles</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0D81331F93BA25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blurb Wars: The Critic Strikes Back</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blurb Wars: The Critic Strikes Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES ISHERWOOD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Isherwood, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Isherwood article humorously explores technique of creating positive blurbs for poorly reviewed play; discusses tactics such as Flagrant Elision of Ellipses and Recontextualized Sneer; examples; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAW the show. Hated it, I'm afraid. Said as much, in 800 meticulously chosen words.</p>
        <p>But lo! Open the paper a few mornings later, and there, for the world to see, is an artful distillation of my review, all those paragraphs pared down to their essence. Well, their essence according to the advertising and marketing specialists hired by the producers. In big type liberally laced with exclamation points, readers would learn that, in fact, ''I loved this play!!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ticket buyer beware! The art of selective quoting is one of the oldest games in the hype business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAW the show. Hated it, I'm afraid. Said as much, in 800 meticulously chosen words.</p>
        <p>But lo! Open the paper a few mornings later, and there, for the world to see, is an artful distillation of my review, all those paragraphs pared down to their essence. Well, their essence according to the advertising and marketing specialists hired by the producers. In big type liberally laced with exclamation points, readers would learn that, in fact, ''I loved this play!!''</p>
        <p>Shocking, I know!</p>
        <p>Yes, the art of selective quoting is one of the oldest games in the hype business, and readers are generally wise to it. Ellipses are not a good sign, and if an advertisement features quotes from critics pruned to just one word (''Brilliant!'' -- Joe Schmo; ''Powerful!'' -- Betty Burns), chances are good the foliage surrounding them is less fragrant with affection.</p>
        <p>The above are fictional examples, but since the subject today is fictionalized truths, it seems acceptable. Still, there are plenty of actual examples to suggest that advertising copywriters are becoming bolder, more inventive, more inspired -- which is perhaps to say more desperate -- in their revisions of critical history.</p>
        <p>A new tactic seemingly on the rise is the Flagrant Elision of Ellipses.</p>
        <p>Last spring I reviewed a new play about Peggy Guggenheim called ''Woman Before a Glass.'' The notice was markedly tepid. I called the show, among other things, ''a big chunk of theatrical costume jewelry.'' Undaunted by my faintest of praise, the ad mavens scoured the review for positive -- or even neutral -- wording and strung together the following: ''A trip to the Promenade Theater introduces us to the sensational history of Peggy Guggenheim, performed vigorously and meticulously by the formidable Mercedes Ruehl. Smoking, drinking, name-dropping, art, men and the men who make art. Some shindig, no? A trip to Venice!'' (Italics, and most punctuation, theirs.)</p>
        <p>Now, I have written some regrettable paragraphs in my day, but this increasingly free-associative string of phrases seemed to suggest I'd channeled Diana Vreeland at her most deliciously madcap.</p>
        <p>Another popular trend is what you might call the Recontextualized Sneer. The prize winner for the hotly contested title of most critically scorned new musical of the season just past was probably ''In My Life,'' a loony tale of love and song and Tourette's syndrome written and directed by Joseph Brooks. The reviews were almost universally terrible.</p>
        <p>In The New York Times, Ben Brantley dismissed it as ''a sea of singing syrup.'' For starters. But someone found some gems of praise glittering in the gloom. The line that appeared in the advertisement? ''It's true that 'In My Life' does have jaw-dropping moments of whimsy run amok, but beneath the swirling, madcap flourishes lies a small, pink candy heart, the kind schoolchildren exchange on Valentine's Day.''</p>
        <p>Alas it seems there was not much of a market for jaw-dropping whimsy run amok, or even candy hearts. The show closed quickly anyway. (Perhaps there are not enough Diana Vreelands in this dark world; whimsy run amok was sort of her thing.)</p>
        <p>Equal ingenuity was shown by the folks behind the feeble comedy ''Jewtopia,'' which I dismissed as so much tasteless matzoh ball soup when it opened in the fall of 2004. In a best-and-worst-of-the-season article that followed, I singled the show out for more opprobrium, calling it ''schlocky but apparently unstoppable.'' But read the fine print in the ABC advertisements in The New York Times and you'll find, on occasion, the following: ''Unstoppable'' -- Charles Isherwood, New York Times.</p>
        <p>Talk about chutzpah. (The show continues to be unstoppable, by the way, but don't quote me -- please.)</p>
        <p>Still, I wrote the word, and must stand by it. But David Rooney, the chief theater critic at Variety, recently had the surreal experience of seeing his name attached to words he was certain he had never written. In an ad in his own publication, he saw that in assessing ''The Color Purple'' he'd written that ''Elisabeth Withers-Mendes is PERFECT and irresistible.'' Only problem was, far from describing her as PERFECT, he had hardly mentioned her. An investigation revealed that a slight mix-up had occurred. It wasn't Mr. Rooney but Roma Torre of New York 1 who had been so taken with Ms. Withers-Mendes. Oops.</p>
        <p>This inadvertent error recalls one of the great quote-ad scams of all time. That was perpetrated by -- who else? -- the master huckster David Merrick, a producer who took particular pleasure in needling the critics. Expecting pans for 1961's ''Subways Are For Sleeping,'' Merrick scoured the Eastern seaboard for fellows with the same names as New York's leading theater critics. The namesakes, with wee photos, appeared alongside bigger blurbs in an ad that screamed, ''7 Out of 7 Are Unanimously Ecstatic About 'Subways Are For Sleeping.' '' (The New York Times caught the ad and stopped it before it ran, but it appeared in The Herald-Tribune.)</p>
        <p>Something vaguely similar, if rather more flattering, once happened to me. I reviewed, reasonably favorably, a new play by Kenneth Lonergan, and wasn't surprised to see a few words from my notice posted in an ad.</p>
        <p>Anyway, the words I recognized, but the name wasn't quite right. They'd attributed my prose to some guy named Christopher Isherwood. Who he?</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
