<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chechen Separatist Leader Reported Killed by Russians</title>
    <meta content="18chechnya" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/18/world/europe/18chechnya.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1770105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beslan (Russia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saidullayev, Abdul Khalim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Basayev, Shamil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Chechnya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chechnya (Russia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D81131F93BA25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chechen Separatist Leader Reported Killed by Russians</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Russian Troops Kill Leader of Chechen Separatists</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian special forces kill Chechen separatist leader Abdul Khalim Saidullayev in raid in Chechen village in which two Russian officers were also killed; Saidullayev was little-known fighter, religious figure and Islamic judge appointed in March 2005 to lead rebels; was far less prominent than Shamil Basayev, who claimed responsibility for Beslan terrorist attack (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russian special forces killed the leader of Chechnya's separatists on Saturday, officials said, reveling in a new blow to a rebel movement with a long history of terrorist attacks that has recently appeared seriously weakened.</p>
        <p>The leader, Abdul Khalim Saidullayev, died in a raid in a Chechen village in which two Russian officers were also killed, the director of the Federal Security Service, Nikolai P. Patrushev, said at an international security conference, Russian news agencies reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russian special forces killed the leader of Chechnya's separatists, dealing a blow to a rebel movement that has carried out terrorist attacks but recently has appeared to be seriously weakened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Russian special forces killed the leader of Chechnya's separatists on Saturday, officials said, reveling in a new blow to a rebel movement with a long history of terrorist attacks that has recently appeared seriously weakened.</p>
        <p>The leader, Abdul Khalim Saidullayev, died in a raid in a Chechen village in which two Russian officers were also killed, the director of the Federal Security Service, Nikolai P. Patrushev, said at an international security conference, Russian news agencies reported.</p>
        <p>Officials said they would conduct tests to confirm that the body was Mr. Saidullayev's, but they displayed little doubt that they had succeeded in finding and killing the movement's leader. Russian television channels showed gruesome images of a body that appeared to be his, and a Web site linked to the Chechen rebels confirmed his death and declared him a martyr.</p>
        <p>''The terrorists have been virtually decapitated,'' Prime Minister Ramzan A. Kadyrov, the leader of Chechnya's pro-Moscow government, told the Interfax news agency in the regional capital, Grozny. ''They have sustained a severe blow, and they are never going to recover from it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Saidullayev, who was believed to be in his 30's, was a little-known fighter, religious figure and Islamic judge when he was appointed in March 2005 to replace Aslan Maskhadov, the rebel leader and elected president of Chechnya during its brief period of independence in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maskhadov, who led the separatists after Russian forces invaded the republic in 1999 to reassert federal control for the second time, was killed that month in a similar raid in the village of Tolstoy-Yurt, only 12 miles from Grozny.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saidullayev led a movement that continues to wage a partisan war against Russian forces in Chechnya and other largely Muslim republics in the Northern Caucasus, but he remained a shadowy figure who was far less prominent than Russia's most wanted man, Shamil Basayev.</p>
        <p>Mr. Basayev, nominally the movement's second in command, has claimed responsibility for the worst terrorist attacks in Russia, including the hostage siege of a school in Beslan in 2004 that ended with the deaths of 331 people.</p>
        <p>In remarks posted on a separatist Web site last week, Mr. Saidullayev offered to negotiate peace but vowed to continue struggling for independence, a goal that seems farther away than ever. He said that as long as Russian forces killed women and children in Chechnya, he could not order a halt to attacks like that at Beslan. ''Was it not this callous indifference to the killing of our children that made Beslan and things that happened before it possible?'' he said, in remarks published in a Bulgarian news weekly, Politika, as transcribed by the BBC.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saidullayev died in Argun, a village that is also close to Grozny and is believed to have been his hometown. Officials provided few details of the raid, but it appeared that some of his associates might have escaped, since Mr. Patrushev said a hunt was under way.</p>
        <p>The fact that he was able to enter a town under federal control underscored the republic's instability, but officials portrayed his death as evidence of the separatists' growing weakness and marginalization. The separatists move in small groups and have not recently been able to attack in large numbers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kadyrov, in remarks shown on the Russian television station NTV, said Mr. Saidullayev had been betrayed by an informer bought for the price of a dose of heroin. Mr. Kadyrov said the rebel leader died even as he was planning new attacks in Chechnya and possibly beyond.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Kadyrov and other pro-Moscow forces have asserted greater control over the republic -- and have been accused of committing human-rights violations in the process -- attacks recur with disturbing regularity, especially during the spring and summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Basayev and another prominent rebel commander, Doku Umarov, remain at large. This week the two men appeared in a video posted on a rebel Web site.</p>
        <p>In it, Mr. Basayev taunted Mr. Kadyrov, claiming to have killed his father, Akhmad, in a bombing in Grozny in 2004, and to have put a price on the son's head.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
