<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Doing in Geneva</title>
    <meta content="GENEVA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/24/travel/GENEVA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Geneva (Switzerland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labalme, Corinne</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">What's Doing In...(times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Geneva</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DD1239F937A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Doing in Geneva</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORINNE LaBALME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labalme, Corinne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corinne LaBalme article on travel attractions of Geneva; photos; map (What's Doing in...article) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the winter season in high gear, legions of skiers and snowboarders are landing in Geneva -- and immediately taking off for the mountains. It's easy to understand: any city so closely associated with banking and bureaucracy looks dull at first glance. But Geneva's reality has always been livelier than its Calvinist reputation, and unexpected treasure lurks in the cracks of its formal facade.</p>
        <p>How do you get to it? Take a good, long look at the tourist track -- the glittery boutiques, the stately five-star hotels, the Red Cross Museum and the United Nations compound -- and then head off trail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the winter season in high gear, legions of skiers and snowboarders are landing in Geneva -- and immediately taking off for the mountains. It's easy to understand: any city so closely associated with banking and bureaucracy looks dull at first glance. But Geneva's reality has always been livelier than its Calvinist reputation, and unexpected treasure lurks in the cracks of its formal facade.</p>
        <p>How do you get to it? Take a good, long look at the tourist track -- the glittery boutiques, the stately five-star hotels, the Red Cross Museum and the United Nations compound -- and then head off trail.</p>
        <p>Go no farther than the crazy-quilt Schtroumph (or Smurf) buildings, named for the blue comic book elves, to prove that the Swiss have a whimsical sense of humor. The Gaudi-style apartment complex at 23-29, rue Louis Favre, built by the city from 1982 to 1984 in a district behind the train station, is a curvilinear riot of chopped-off turrets, mosaics and polychrome moldings.</p>
        <p>Or head downstream from the Coulouvreniere Bridge, where the Forces Motrices power station, built in 1886, straddles the Rhone like a Beaux-Arts edition of the chateau of Chenonceau. Geneva converted this industrial landmark into an alternative stage for lyric theater in 1997, but kept some of the brightly painted machinery in the lobby.</p>
        <p>On the Left Bank near Plainpalais Park, an abandoned factory provides loft space for the lively Museum of Modern and Contemporary Art. With its hard-to-find doorway and genial air of artistic anarchy, it harks back to the early days of TriBeCa.</p>
        <p>The glorious St.-Pierre Cathedral in the Old City, an amazingly elegant building that manages to integrate the Romanesque, Gothic and neo-Classical, forms only a small part of Geneva's religious heritage. For example, the glistening Byzantine domes of the Russian Orthodox Church on the Rue de Toepffer, admission 60 cents, crown the building where Dostoyevsky's daughter was baptized.</p>
        <p>The Petit Palais Art Museum, known for its Impressionist collection, will be closed for renovation until spring. For those spending New Year's Eve in Geneva, the mezzo-soprano Sara Fulgoni will sing ''Carmen'' at the Grand Theatre.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>You might spot the next Denise Biellmann at the Swiss National Figure Skating Championships, which take place Jan. 11 to 13 at the Patinoire des Vernets, 4-6, rue Hans Wildorf, (41-22) 418-4000, on the southern edge of town. Admission to the training sessions and competitions, from 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m, is free.</p>
        <p>In 1923, Fernand Leger designed the vibrant decor and costumes for ''The Creation of the World,'' a jazz-age ballet created by Darius Milhaud, Blaise Cendrars and Jean Borlin. Until March 4, a colorful scale model of the set fills an entire room of ''Fernand Leger and African Art,'' showcasing the importance of African motifs in post-World War I European art, at the Musee d'Art et d'Histoire, 2, rue Charles-Galland; (41-22) 418-2600; Web site, mah.ville-ge.ch. Closed Monday. Admission: $3 (at 1.7 Swiss francs to the dollar).</p>
        <p>Jean-Philippe Rameau's lighthearted opera-ballet ''Platee,'' one of the first 18th-century burlesque compositions in France, gets an exuberant staging at the Grand Theatre from Jan. 28 to Feb. 4, except Feb. 2. The plight of the child-bride and her elderly suitor provides the comic story line that propels Rameau's witty pastiche of the Baroque lyric tradition. Place Neuve; www.geneve opera.ch; (41-22) 418-3130. Tickets: $14 to $73.</p>
        <p>The London-based artist Gavin Turk uses pastiche to make visual points by recycling a variety of pop icons -- everything from Che Guevara and Sid Vicious to plastic trash bags. Through Jan. 21, a retrospective of his provocative paintings, sculpture and photographs is on view at Mamco, the Contemporary Arts Center, 10, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers; (41-22) 329-1842. Closed Monday. Admission: $2.35. Web site: mamco-ge.tripod.com.</p>
        <p>Visitors in town on Valentine's Day can celebrate with a medley of French love songs sung by the super-crooner Charles Aznavour. The concert takes place Feb. 14 at the 5,000-seat Geneva Arena, near the airport and the Palexpo Convention Center.  Tickets: $29 to $65 from (41-22) 710-9090 or www.ticketcorner.ch.</p>
        <p>Through Jan. 7, the Musee Rath, 1, Place Neuve, (41-22) 418-3340, honors the Swiss-born modernist painter Cuno Amiet (1868-1961) with an exhibition of 150 of his paintings. Connected to Gauguin's Pont-Aven group in Brittany and the German Brucke movement, Amiet juxtaposes dazzling color contrasts in his work, considered a vital link between symbolism, naturalism and abstraction. Admission: $5.90. Closed Monday. Web site: mah.ville-ge.ch.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>To explore the Old City, start out in the Place du Bourg-de-Four, a popular meeting place on the site of the ancient Roman forum and market. The narrow side streets leading from the plaza, lined with 16th-  to 18th-century buildings, shelter some of the best bistros and prettiest home-decoration boutiques in town.</p>
        <p>Take the children for a ride on the merry-go-round on the Place de la Madeleine, and be sure to see Calvin's Chair in the St.-Pierre Cathedral, which also houses an impressive archaeological site. The noontime bells are justly famous.</p>
        <p>For a scenic aside, head south -- but not very far -- to Carouge, Geneva's Greenwich Village, a mini-Mediterranean enclave just beyond the city limits. This area, treated as an arty suburb by most Genevans, was ceded to the Kingdom of Sardinia in 1754 and developed into an Italian-style village. The houses have little balconies, built over a ground floor arcade of columns, all of which turn inside toward the garden courtyards. Unless somebody leaves a door open, you don't see these balconies or gardens from the street.</p>
        <p>A five-minute, $1.30 ride on the No. 12 tram from central Geneva takes visitors to this unexpected small-town oasis replete with outdoor cafes, art galleries and craft shops. The open-air market takes place on Wednesday and Saturday mornings.</p>
        <p>From 1803 until 1933, local artisans produced distinctive, yellow-tinted Carouge creamware ceramics. Examples are on display at the Carouge Museum, 2, Place de Sardaigne, (41-22) 342-3383, in an 18th-century, pastel-tinted stucco house. The museum is closed from Jan. 1 to March 15, but with notice, visits can be arranged on weekdays.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Geneva's fanciest Right Bank hotels are clustered on the same stretch of waterfront as the midpriced Hotel Ambassador, 21, Quai des Bergues, (41-22) 908-0530, fax (41 22) 738-9080; hotel-ambassador.ch on the Web. Roughly one third of the 86 rooms, which are decorated in fresh pastel shades, have lake views. There is a ground-floor restaurant, but renovations are scheduled for the lobby in January and February. Doubles: $135 to $203.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Hermitage, 8, rue de la Tour Maitresse, (41-22) 310-3024, fax (41-22) 310-3015, hotelhermitage.ch, near the lake and the best Right Bank shopping, offers 25 uncluttered but cozy rooms in primary colors and with jaunty rustic touches like carved wooden doors. Rooms on the top floor, under the eaves, have pine-paneled walls. Doubles: $107.</p>
        <p>Budget: The reception area for the cheerfully bohemian, family-run Hotel Rio, 1, Place Isaac-Mercier, (41-22) 732-3264, fax (41-22) 732-8264, www.hotel-rio-geneve.ch, is on the second floor and is reached by a loft-style elevator. Most of the 27 rooms in this centrally situated hotel, 10 minutes from the train station, have private bathrooms, and six have kitchenettes. The two-bedroom suite with kitchen that sleeps six is a prime value at $106. Doubles: $46 to $76.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The director collects antiques, which explains why each of the 50 rooms looks different at the eccentric, turn-of-the-century Hotel de la Cigogne, 17, Place Longemalle, (41-22) 818-4040, fax (41-22) 818-4050, www.relaischateaux.ch/cigogne, in the Right Bank business and shopping center. No. 34 has curved, Gaudi-style walls and hammered-lead closets; No. 38 is adorned with Chinese lacquer, and No. 68 has an ornate 18th-century carved canopy bed and a cathedral ceiling. Many rooms have working fireplaces. Doubles: $247 to $312.</p>
        <p>Colette vacationed at Hotel Le Richemond, Brunswick Garden, (41-22) 715-7000, fax (41-22) 715-7001, and her favorite suite, priced at $2,764, features framed memorabilia, extravagant inlaid furniture and a bathtub dwarfed by black marble pillars. The Richemond's lavish decor blends Art Deco charm with Victorian excess, but all 98 rooms have Internet access. Some have lake views. Doubles: $318 to $435.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Across from the courthouse in the heart of the Old Town, a lively, legal crowd gathers at the Palais de Justice, 8, Place du Bourg-de-Four, (41-22) 318-3737, fax (41-22) 818-6101, for generous lunch specials ($8 to $10.50) like lamb stew, artichoke-roquefort salad or a Swiss menu based on fondue and cold cuts. The cozy cellar tavern schedules Friday jazz concerts. Dinner for two with wine: $40.</p>
        <p>Cannons from Geneva's ancient arsenal are displayed across the street from Les Armures, 1, rue du Puits-St.-Pierre, (41-22) 310-3442, fax (41-22) 818-7113, a bustling restaurant that takes its period decor so seriously that the basement dining room is called Les Oubliettes. Cosmopolitan entrees range from salade nicoise to spaghetti, but hearty Swiss specialties like perch fillets in butter sauce or grilled schubling sausage with rosti (hash-brown potatoes) are the major attractions. Dinner for two with wine: $60.</p>
        <p>Off the tourist track, local residents enjoy cheese fondue and Swiss white wine at the casual Cafe St. Gervais, 4, rue des Corps Saints, (41-22) 732-5898, on a Right Bank side street behind the St.-Gervais Temple. The wood-paneled walls are adorned with colorful ski scenes. The cafe's Swiss spin on croque-monsieur -- open-face toasted ''croute'' sandwiches topped with cheese, ham or mushrooms -- makes a full meal. Dinner for two with wine: $35.</p>
        <p>On a clear day, lakefront tables in the romantic rose-and-white dining room of the Cafe de la Paix, 11, Quai du Mont-Blanc, (41-22) 909-6000, offer a stunning view of snowcapped mountains. The three-course $19 business lunch, with daily choices that vary from Thai calamari to preserved duck, is one of the best bargains in town. The brasserie-style dinner menu features steak with herb polenta and turbot with cepes. Dinner for two with wine: $132.</p>
        <p>Across from the Cathedral, the Creperie St.-Pierre, 6, Place de la Taconnerie, (41-22) 310-0976, stays open for lunch and dinner seven days a week. The simple cheese-caraway pancake served in the informal dining room costs $4.40; the goat cheese, tomato and walnut version is $8. A copious dinner salad, $8, includes mixed vegetables and meat pate.</p>
        <p>Jean-Paul Goddard, the only two-star Michelin chef in downtown Geneva, has set the city's gastronomic gold standard for 21 years at Le Bearn, 4, Quai de la Poste, (41-22) 321-0028, fax (41-22) 781-3115, decorated with understated formality. The $35 lunch menu provides a fine introduction to his classic haute cuisine, but the winter tasting menu, $123 including wine, is a stylish ode to foie gras, scallops vinaigrette, sea bass and roast duckling with endives. Dinner for two with wine: $294.</p>
        <p>CORINNE LaBALME writes about cultural events in Europe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">CORINNE LaBALME writes about cultural events in Europe.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
