<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wyoming Rivers Produce Trophies</title>
    <meta content="24OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/24/sports/24OUTD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trout</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wyoming</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wind River Reservation (Wyoming)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Greg</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Outdoors (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DF1538F937A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wyoming Rivers Produce Trophies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Greg Thomas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Greg</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outdoors column on fishing for golden trout in Wyoming's Wind River Mountain Range; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you want to catch wild trout without burning a pile of calories, Wyoming's Wind River Mountain Range, where granite peaks thrust 13,000 feet into the sky and its fish grow to massive proportions, is not the place to be.</p>
        <p>The Wind River Range, which stretches 100 miles across western Wyoming's sage-covered expanse, is considered some of the most remote and beautiful terrain in North America. Pine trees and aspens cover the foothills until those granite monoliths take over. But most of its trout lakes rest in designated wilderness areas, five or more miles away from roads, attainable only via foot power or horsepower, the kind that doesn't come with a set of reins and spurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you want to catch wild trout without burning a pile of calories, Wyoming's Wind River Mountain Range, where granite peaks thrust 13,000 feet into the sky and its fish grow to massive proportions, is not the place to be.</p>
        <p>The Wind River Range, which stretches 100 miles across western Wyoming's sage-covered expanse, is considered some of the most remote and beautiful terrain in North America. Pine trees and aspens cover the foothills until those granite monoliths take over. But most of its trout lakes rest in designated wilderness areas, five or more miles away from roads, attainable only via foot power or horsepower, the kind that doesn't come with a set of reins and spurs.</p>
        <p>As I recently found, the Winds require a measure of dedication and a healthy dose of lung power to appreciate.</p>
        <p>During a trek into any of the Wind River's 200 or so lakes, anglers may be required to negotiate several thousand feet of elevation gain, accompanied by a 40-pound backpack and maybe a blister or two. Those who prefer their angling with a bottle of wine and a plate of cheese and crackers resting on the tailgate need not apply. But do keep in mind, remote lakes don't see much, if any, angling pressure and the trout contained within them grow to large size. The Winds hold rainbow, brook, cutthroat and golden trout, and all achieve or even exceed the magical 20-inch mark, a length that separates a nice western trout from a true hog.</p>
        <p>And the Wind Rivers remain one of the last bastions for golden trout, a fish so painted in pastel, a combination of subtle gold and orange, highlighted by a penetrating red slash, that they become almost impossible to describe accurately. Most people simply call goldens the most gorgeous of trout species. The largest goldens in the world swim in the Wind Rivers.</p>
        <p>Golden trout originated in the Sierra Nevada Mountains of California, but they seldom exceed a pound in their native waters. Goldens were first introduced to the Wind River's barren lakes in the 1940's, carried in crates on the backs of horses and released in select waters. Those fish immediately took hold. Wyoming's current state record golden, which was taken in the Wind Rivers at Cook Lake in 1948, weighed 11 pounds!</p>
        <p>I was looking for the world-record golden -- a fish weighing 12 to 15 pounds -- during my two-week, 100-mile trek through the Winds. I was armed with three flyrods, an assortment of sinking and floating flylines, several hundred fly patterns, enough pasta to satisfy the most staunch Italian and a professional photographer to record the historic catch.</p>
        <p>We began our quest at the northern edge of the mountain range, covering nine miles of nasty trail to reach a lake high above timberline. I felt as if I were on top of the world, but my legs were incredibly shaky, my muscles twitching uncontrollably. Unfortunately, the lake held no goldens, although I did catch and release several nice cutthroats, including a 17-inch slab.</p>
        <p>The following day we climbed four grueling miles to a lake once known to contain big goldens. I fished that lake, which rested at 11,200 feet, for several hours without sighting a fish, let alone garnering a strike. It was as if the Wind River lakes were barren once again and I was casting on a sea of futility. I fished several lakes in the area with the same result.</p>
        <p>The following day, now on the eastern side of the range, we hiked 11 miles to a lake that a biologist had circled on my map. Along the trail we encountered two full-grown bull moose. We played a game of hide and seek with the largest bull, an 800-pound animal, as it wandered around a giant boulder, peeking at us as we peeked back.</p>
        <p>When we reached our destination, exhausted and dripping in perspiration, I was exalted. I could tell, just by looking at that gorgeous lake, with its deep center and shallow, fertile flats, that it contained big goldens. I held that notion through the first 50 strikeless casts. By 100 casts I was discouraged and returned to our camp, which consisted of a tiny tent and a minuscule propane stove. That's when the lightning set in. Karen, the photographer, and I crouched under low vegetation for an hour or more as rain pelted our bodies and electric darts drilled the surrounding country.</p>
        <p>The next day, having thrown at least 500 casts, I gave up, declared the lake deserted and told Karen to pack her bag.</p>
        <p>As we exited the area I spied a small lake tucked in a beautiful mountain bowl. We climbed down to the water and I immediately spotted a large trout finning near shore. I cast a beetle imitation near its position and the fish charged the fly, then struck, as if it hadn't eaten in a week. I played the fish gingerly and finally landed the brute. It measured 22 inches long! Unfortunately, the fish was a cutthroat, not a golden.</p>
        <p>It was the kind of fishing that every fly angler dreams of -- large trout that hold little regard for their safety contained in a beautiful setting, separated from the maddening pace of society by long miles of trail and a fresh mind-set.</p>
        <p>Those anglers who know golden trout best are not surprised by my lack of success. They regard goldens as one of the most discerning, difficult trout species. They say goldens often feed solely on plankton, refusing flies as if they represented a plague.</p>
        <p>Golden trout addicts say that late spring (which means late June and early July in the Wind Rivers), just as ice frees its grip on those mountain lakes, is the time to catch big goldens. Given good health and the will to carry backpacks through those rugged mountains, Karen and I will return to the Winds next year, determined to catch the world-record golden. We've contracted golden trout fever.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
