<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Prospects of a Dire Winter, Check for Energy Efficiency</title>
    <meta content="CNCLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DB1139F937A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Prospects of a Dire Winter, Check for Energy Efficiency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ACCORDING to the National Weather Service we are in for a cold winter, and the energy companies report that because of fuel shortages, energy costs will be high this year. For these reasons, it is a good idea to inspect your home to see where you can conserve energy.</p>
        <p>One basic and easy way to cut fuel bills is by turning your thermostat to 68 degrees during the winter months. At the same time try to increase the humidity in the air. Moist air holds and conducts heat better than dry air, and you will experience a greater degree of comfort because your skin and nasal passages are less likely to dry out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ACCORDING to the National Weather Service we are in for a cold winter, and the energy companies report that because of fuel shortages, energy costs will be high this year. For these reasons, it is a good idea to inspect your home to see where you can conserve energy.</p>
        <p>One basic and easy way to cut fuel bills is by turning your thermostat to 68 degrees during the winter months. At the same time try to increase the humidity in the air. Moist air holds and conducts heat better than dry air, and you will experience a greater degree of comfort because your skin and nasal passages are less likely to dry out.</p>
        <p>The simplest way to put moisture into the air is by setting up a humidifier. Admittedly a humidifier runs on electricity and that can add a little to your bill, but there are other ways to moisturize the home. Place shallow pans of water on, or near, radiators or heat registers. Mist your houseplants regularly. Leave the bathroom door open after taking a shower and don't vent your stove when boiling soup or steaming vegetables.</p>
        <p>Next, inspect your heating system for possible leaks. This is not a problem with either hot water or steam systems, but it can be a significant problem with forced-air systems. Studies have shown that air leaks can account for one-third of an average home's energy losses.</p>
        <p>Inspect all seams in the air ducts for leaks. Most duct leaks occur in the uninsulated areas of the home; areas like the attic, crawlspace, or in an unheated basement. Do not use the familiar gray duct tape to seal leaking seams, because the heat from the ducts will cause the tape to deteriorate. Instead use special duct sealant or silicone caulk to seal narrow cracks. Both products are available in cartridges that fit into caulking guns. Patch wider gaps with fiberglass mesh tape (this is also used to cover the joints in drywall) and duct sealant.</p>
        <p>When you inspect the attic ducts, take the time to look around the chimney. Usually, there is a wide space between the chimney and the framing. This is an intentional gap that keeps the hot chimney from setting the wooden joists on fire, but it provides an open passage for air leaks. The best, and safest, way to seal this gap is by installing strips of metal flashing around the chimney. Nail them to the surrounding joists and caulk the edges near the chimney with high-temperature-resistant silicone.</p>
        <p>Make sure your furnace is energy efficient by having the firebox cleaned and the burner element tuned. This should be done by a professional. If you have a forced-air furnace, inspect the air filter and change it whenever it gets dirty, but at least every three months. You should have spare filters on hand so you can change them as needed during the winter.</p>
        <p>A dirty air filter restricts the air flow from the furnace and can seriously damage the furnace and blower parts. Do not operate the furnace without a filter; otherwise the blower will spew dust and dirt throughout the house.</p>
        <p>What kind of filter should you buy? The most common furnace filter is the flat, one-inch-thick fiberglass filter. It is relatively inexpensive -- usually less than $1 -- and is designed to capture the larger dust particles in the system.</p>
        <p>The pleated fabric filter is a little better than the flat fiberglass filter. The filter element is pleated to expand the total surface area so it can trap a higher percentage of particles, including dust, pollen, mold, animal dander and some bacteria. The increased filtration can make the air cleaner and offer some relief for allergy suffers. These filters cost about $4.50 each.</p>
        <p>Another type of pleated filter has an internal wire element that carries an electrostatic charge. This charge of static electricity makes the filter more effective in capturing smoke particles and bacteria. It costs between $6 and $14.</p>
        <p>All of these filters should be replaced when they get dirty, but one type of filter can be washed and reused. It is an electrostatic reusable filter. It looks more like a window screen than a furnace filter because it doesn't have either a cloth or fiberglass filter element. Instead, it has an electrostatically charged wire screen. Electrostatic reusable filters are not as effective as pleated filters for capturing dust particles and they are expensive, costing between $20 and $40. However, they can be washed and reused whenever they get dirty; and with care they can last as long as five years. Electrostatic reusable filters should be washed every month, and it is a good idea to have a second filter on hand to insert in furnace while you are cleaning the primary one.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
