<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fed Survey Shows Marked Pickup in the Economy</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES ANDSALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DC1539F93AA35756C0A960958260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fed Survey Shows Marked Pickup in the Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A survey by the Federal Reserve pointed today to a marked pickup in the economy during March and April, more evidence that expansion is solid again in most parts of the country.</p>
        <p>"Activity advanced at a moderate pace," the Fed's survey found, while price increases remained mostly subdued and there was "only scattered" upward pressure on wages despite a tight job market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A survey by the Federal Reserve pointed today to a marked pickup in the economy during March and April, more evidence that expansion is solid again in most parts of the country.</p>
        <p>"Activity advanced at a moderate pace," the Fed's survey found, while price increases remained mostly subdued and there was "only scattered" upward pressure on wages despite a tight job market.</p>
        <p>One exception, however, was the New York district, which the Fed singled out as having "weakened somewhat" in the last two months. Among the poor performers  were factories in the Buffalo area and the housing market in Albany, the latter  continuing to suffer from state job cuts.</p>
        <p>Job creation picked up in both New York and New Jersey but the unemployment rate still climbed in New York because of a sharp increase in the number of people seeking work. A clear bright spot, however, was tourism, which the survey found "continues to boom," with the hotel occupancy rate in New York City reaching a 16-year high in the first quarter of the year.</p>
        <p>The Fed's survey of its 12 districts was part of the preparation for the May  21 meeting of the interest rate-setting group, the Federal Open Market Committee. Today's report seemed to increase only slightly the chance that the Fed would soon raise short-term rates to prevent inflation from accelerating.</p>
        <p>The Fed's latest anecdotal survey, which was issued at noon, had little effect on the financial markets today. While bond prices surged, the rally was largely attributed to unexpectedly strong demand for 10-year bonds at a Treasury auction.</p>
        <p>In a separate report, the Conference Board said its index of economic indicators, which tend to move at the same time as the economy as a whole, edged up one-tenth of 1 percent in March, less than the eight-tenths of 1 percent gain posted in February.</p>
        <p>Last week, the business-sponsored research group reported that its index of predictive indicators, formerly compiled by the Commerce Department, also moved  up for the second straight month.</p>
        <p>The Fed's survey, titled "Current Economic Conditions" but widely referred to as the beige book after the color of its cover, said in its summary that all 11  districts other than New York showed expansion and that several of them reported that the pace had "quickened" recently. It noted a pickup in both retail sales and in manufacturing and suggested that factory inventories were no longer higher than desired.</p>
        <p>"Activity also picked up in nonfinancial services, commercial and consumer lending and real estate," declared the summary, written this time at the Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond. On the other hand, "mortgage loan activity slowed, as</p>
        <p>did tourism in several districts and agriculture suffered from adverse weather."</p>
        <p>The survey found minimal the effect of a 17-day strike in March against General Motors. Even in Buffalo, where 6,000 were idled, the deterioration of manufacturing was "not directly related" to the strike, the Fed stated. And the  Cleveland district reported that the strike seems to have had "only a small effect" on sales.</p>
        <p>Despite a low unemployment rate, averaging 5.5 percent during March and April, most districts saw "little upward pressure" on prices other than for energy and grains, the Fed also found. And wage pressures were "only modest" over all despite several industries in the St. Louis district reporting higher costs and Minneapolis reporting pay increases of 4 to 5 percent.</p>
        <p>One striking example of how tight labor markets have become in the upper Midwest, especially for blue-collar workers, was the decision by the Minneapolis-St. Paul transit system to reduce the minimum age for bus drivers to 19. A restaurant in the St. Louis district was reported to have delayed its opening for two months for lack of help, while a Tennessee hotel was forced to recruit workers from overseas. Atlanta reported that filling entry-level positions "has become a challenge."</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the Dallas district reported fewer wage pressures or labor shortages than earlier in the year while Kansas City said "employers report few  wage increases" despite a continuing tight job market.</p>
        <p>The word from Chicago was that the area economy "remained at relatively high  levels" despite pockets of slowing or actual decline. "Labor market shortages continued to be the main concern of businesses despite softening demand for workers from the manufacturing sector," the Fed survey found.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
