<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frohnmayer Says Grants Are Being Spread Thinner</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FROHNMAYER, JOHN (CHMN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB123DF931A15751C0A967958260" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frohnmayer Says Grants Are Being Spread Thinner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA GAMAREKIAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John E. Frohnmayer, the chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts, told a House subcommittee today how the agency was trying to make do these days with less money. New legislation has cut the amount of money the endowment dispenses while reallocating more money for state arts agencies.</p>
        <p>"We are trying to stretch money by giving smaller grants and keeping the same number of applicants in the pool to compensate for the $12 million that has been taken from the disciplines into state programs," Mr. Frohnmayer said during a daylong hearing before the Interior Subcommittee of the Appropriations Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John E. Frohnmayer, the chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts, told a House subcommittee today how the agency was trying to make do these days with less money. New legislation has cut the amount of money the endowment dispenses while reallocating more money for state arts agencies.</p>
        <p>"We are trying to stretch money by giving smaller grants and keeping the same number of applicants in the pool to compensate for the $12 million that has been taken from the disciplines into state programs," Mr. Frohnmayer said during a daylong hearing before the Interior Subcommittee of the Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>Congress told the endowment last year to increase the amount of money it distributes directly to states to 27.5 percent, from 20, decreasing its own grants by $12 million. The percentage will rise to 32 next year.</p>
        <p>In response to a question from Representative Les AuCoin, Democrat of Oregon, Mr. Frohnmayer said that because of this requirement and others it would take a budget increase of $57 million to restore the endowment's grants to their previous level. Congress has required that in addition to the state money, half of any money appropriated in excess of $175 million go to arts education. The Size of the Budget</p>
        <p>The arts endowment is the only cultural agency that did not receive an increase in spending from the Bush Administration this year. Its proposed budget for Fiscal Year 1992 remains $174 million, the present level. Its sister agency, the National Endowment for the Humanities, has traditionally received less money than the arts endowment. But the Bush Administration has requested $178.2 million for the humanities, an increase of nearly 5 percent, leading many people in Washington to surmise that the arts endowment is on probation at the White House. Mr. Frohnmayer had requested $212 million.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the subcommittee, Sidney R. Yates, an Illinois Democrat and longtime arts supporter, is expected to try to increase the appropriation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yates also heard testimony from more than a dozen of the agency's program directors, querying them about the mood at the agency, whether they felt browbeaten and weakened as a result of last year's Congressional debate over the endowment's grant-making policy.</p>
        <p>"I personally will tell you that a few months ago it was difficult to function, not because of any internal problems," D. Antoinette Handy, the director of the music program, said "but because of the constant telephone calls, the confusion, the misinformation that we read in the newspapers. But I feel that the quality of the grants has remained high."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
