<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q and A</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="867646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PIORKO, JANET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4D91739F93BA15754C0A960958260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q and A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET PIORKO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PIORKO, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buses in Mexico</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buses in Mexico</p>
        <p>Q.  I have heard that Mexico has very good air-conditioned buses with toilet  facilities. True? Some friends and I are thinking of taking a bus trip through the country. -- Ethel Ruymaker, Oakland, Calif.</p>
        <p>A.  Buses are one of the best ways to get around central Mexico in particular, and new highways have recently cut travel times from Mexico City to  provincial capitals like Guadalajara, Morelia and Oaxaca, and to smaller cities  such as Acapulco and San Miguel de Allende. There is also adequate service between provincial cities, although the roads aren't always as good.</p>
        <p>A number of companies offer first-class service that includes air-conditioning, bathrooms, movies, a box lunch and sometimes even free coffee  and soft drinks. The wide seats recline and the buses themselves, mostly Mercedes-Benz equipment, provide a comfortable ride.</p>
        <p>Mexican bus stations tend to be at least as clean and comfortable, if not a bit more so, than their United States counterparts. However, travelers should keep a grip on their luggage and beware of pickpockets.</p>
        <p>Mexico City has four stations -- the Central del Norte for northern and western routes; the Central del Sur for southern destinations; the TAPO for eastern and southeastern lines; and the Central Poniente, also known as Observatorio, for points west.</p>
        <p>A one-way trip -- or viaje sencillo in Spanish -- to Guadalajara takes seven  hours and costs between $22 and $30, while the four-and-a-half-hour ride to San  Miguel de Allende is about $14. The trip to Acapulco takes five hours and costs  $18 to $24. (Rates calculated at 7.5 pesos to the dollar.) Round-trip fares are  double.</p>
        <p>Most companies offer first-class service and a more expensive service with the same amenities but bigger seats. Each company's names for these services vary, so be sure to ask which amenities you are getting.</p>
        <p>Here are some of the major companies: (The country code is 52, the city code  5.)</p>
        <p>NORTH AND WEST: Primera Plus: 587-5200, 587-5222, 567-8033, 587-5311.</p>
        <p>E.T.N.: Central del Norte, 567-9466, 567-9654; Observatorio, 273-0251, 277-6529, 277-0889.</p>
        <p>Elite: Central del Norte, 729-0762, 729-0763; Observatorio, 271-3692, 271-0578.</p>
        <p>Futura Estrella Blanca and Ejecutivo Turistar: 628-5738, 628-5739, 628-5740.</p>
        <p>EAST, SOUTHEAST: A.D.O. G.L. and Linea Uno: 785-9659, 522-1111.</p>
        <p>Cristobal Colon and Servicio Plus: 756-9926, 763-8433.</p>
        <p>SOUTH: Estrella de Oro: 689-3955.</p>
        <p>Futura Estrella Blanca and Ejecutivo Turistar: 628-5738, 628-5739, 628-5740.</p>
        <p>Operators for bus lines rarely speak English, so making reservations can be difficult if you don't speak Spanish. Two travel agencies can make reservations  and have employees who speak English:</p>
        <p>Agencia Del Sur, 19A Mar de Copernico, Fraccionamiento Los Olivos, Mexico City; 678-1901; fax 677-7187. About 20 minutes' drive from downtown.</p>
        <p>Agencia B'Gal, 5 Circuito Centro Comercial, Ciudad Satelite, Mexico City; 393-0389; fax 562-8063. About 40 minutes from downtown.</p>
        <p>To Malta and More</p>
        <p>Q.  Through a recent public-television broadcast, I became interested in the  country of Malta. Unfortunately, there is only one direct flight on Air Malta to and from the island at this time. To take advantage of the best air fare I would have to spend two weeks there, which is more than I would like. Are there any cruises to Athens or parts of Italy that I could take until my return flight? -- Rhea Albert, Amityville, L.I. A.  You are partly right: Only one airline has direct service between New York and Malta but it is Balkan-Bulgarian Airlines, not Air Malta. (Air Malta does take reservations and sell tickets for the flight.) Balkan-Bulgarian flies a Boeing 767 each Monday from New York nonstop to Malta and returns on Friday.</p>
        <p>So, theoretically, you could stay as little as three days; according to an Air Malta official, there is no minimum-stay requirement for the least expensive published fare, which is $1,338 in the summer high season. If you wanted to stay more than three days, however, and you wanted a direct flight on your return, you would have to stay at least 10 days because of the schedule. Air Malta: (212) 245-7768.</p>
        <p>You can spend a lot less than $1,338, however, by using a ticket purchased through a consolidator, or ticket wholesaler. One travel agent that handles a lot of Malta business, R.A.L. Travel in West New York, N.J., (201) 861-8448, said a round-trip consolidator ticket on Balkan-Bulgarian Airlines would cost about $790 in high season; in September, that price will come down to about $730.</p>
        <p>Up and Away Travel, a consolidator that deals directly with the public, cited slightly lower fares, for example, a round-trip ticket on Balkan-Bulgarian Airlines for $750 until the end of August. You can also route your trip via another destination, flying nonstop on Balkan-Bulgarian to Malta and returning on Air Malta to London, for example, then taking Virgin Atlantic to New York for roughly $75 more. With these fares, there is a minimum stay of seven days, the company said. Up and Away, 347 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10016; (212) 889-2345, fax (212) 889-2350.</p>
        <p>As for side trips from Malta, there are a number of ferries, mostly to Sicily. For example, Virtu Ferries has high-speed catamaran service to Pozzallo  (90 minutes) and Catania (three and a half or four hours) several times a week from April 1 to early October. (There is a limited schedule in winter.) The company also offers a one-day excursion to Pozzallo, Mount Etna and Taormina four days a week in season. The price is 32 Maltese lira, or about $90, including catamaran and air-conditioned bus; lunch is extra. Virtu Ferries in Malta: telephone (356) 318854; fax (356) 345221.</p>
        <p>There is a Malta National Tourist Office at 350 Fifth Avenue, Suite 4412, New York, N.Y. 10118; telephone (212) 695-9520, fax (212) 695-8229.</p>
        <p>Fall in Italy</p>
        <p>Q.  We will be in Rome, Venice and Florence at the end of September and early October. What kind of weather can we expect? -- Valerie Applebaum, Brooklyn, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A.  Not too warm for serious sightseeing and not too cool for cafe-sitting, if you are lucky. In Rome at that time of year, temperatures should reach the 70's during the day and drop down to the 50's or 60's at night. Florence is roughly similar, and Venice typically a bit cooler. You might encounter some rain, so be sure to pack (or wear) a raincoat.</p>
        <p>JANET PIORKO</p>
        <p>Travel on Line Computer users will find a searchable collection of the What's Doing, Frugal Traveler, Practical Traveler and Q. &amp; A. columns in The New York Times on the Web, at http://www.nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
