<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 8 Years, Coliseum May Be More Than Issue</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="623969"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK COLISEUM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION AUTHORITY (MTA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PINDER, JEANNE B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZUCKERMAN, MORTIMER B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF1E3EF936A15754C0A965958260" item-length="1178" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 8 Years, Coliseum May Be More Than Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEANNE B. PINDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PINDER, JEANNE B</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been eight years since Mortimer B. Zuckerman won the right to demolish the New York Coliseum and build something else on its site. But finally, the next few days or weeks may reveal the shape of the building that will be built -- if anything is to be built there at all.</p>
        <p>The coming week is likely to see a flurry of negotiations over the fate of the Coliseum site, at 59th Street and Columbus Circle, a prime location that makes it probably the best development site left in the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been eight years since Mortimer B. Zuckerman won the right to demolish the New York Coliseum and build something else on its site. But finally, the next few days or weeks may reveal the shape of the building that will be built -- if anything is to be built there at all.</p>
        <p>The coming week is likely to see a flurry of negotiations over the fate of the Coliseum site, at 59th Street and Columbus Circle, a prime location that makes it probably the best development site left in the city.</p>
        <p>The fresh impetus to the negotiations came about a week ago when Mayor David N. Dinkins, in response to a request from the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, which owns the Coliseum, indicated his willingness to force a mid-August deadline on Mr. Zuckerman to negotiate a deal.</p>
        <p>Previously, Mr. Dinkins avoided taking a stand on the M.T.A.'s dealings with Mr. Zuckerman, who wants to cut the negotiated price of the land and reduce the scale of the planned development. Best Thing, Worst Thing</p>
        <p>The talks over the Coliseum, one of the longest-running public policy soap operas in New York, feature the tug and pull of elected and appointed officials from the city and the M.T.A., as well as Mr. Zuckerman and an array of civic groups. All say they are doing the best thing for New York, but the deadlock resulting from their actions has done exactly what all agree is the wrong thing: left the Coliseum exhibition hall and office building under-used and deteriorating.</p>
        <p>"This is one of the premiere sites in the city of New York," said Borough President Ruth W. Messinger of Manhattan. "It is an embarrassment to all of us that Columbus Circle, the gateway entrance to the park, the Theater District and a major residential neighborhood, has been allowed to lie fallow and become a center for drug-dealing, street-sleeping and shoddiness."</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman's original 1985 plan to build a 2.1-million-square-foot project on the 3.4-acre site was scaled back twice after widespread criticism, court challenges and the pullout of the main tenant, Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Now, with court challenges over project's size and other issues exhausted and the city's office-space market suffering from the biggest glut in memory, Mr. Zuckerman has sought to cut his offering price from its market-peak 1985 level to something more like what the land would bring in today's depressed market.  He also wants to reduce his building plans again, to a project that would be built in stages, people close to the talks say. 'Major Law Firm' Lined Up</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman said in a telephone interview that he planned to make a formal proposal to the M.T.A. and to the city soon. The proposal would probably involve building 150,000 square feet of retail space and 700,000 square feet of office space, he said. He added that most of it would be occupied by a "major New York law firm" that he declined to name but is said by people close to the talks to be Weil, Gotshal &amp; Manges.</p>
        <p>"You can't build these things on spec any more," Mr. Zuckerman said. "We have great confidence that we can put together a tenancy if given the time for complex legal and financing arrangements."</p>
        <p>That would create new jobs in the construction industry, Mr. Zuckerman said, and leave room for more development on the Coliseum site.</p>
        <p>The current price tag on the site is $338.6 million. People familiar with the talks said Mr. Zuckerman now hoped to buy an unspecified amount of land for the first building for $62 million, and leave the price of the rest of the land to be negotiated later.</p>
        <p>The perennially cash-strapped transportation authority, which owns the Coliseum and other buildings on the site through a subsidiary, has been trying to close the Zuckerman sale or get money from the property through other, interim uses since the last lawsuit over Mr. Zuckerman's development plan was settled last autumn. The M.T.A. has been reluctant to cut the price of the land or to sign on to a staged development plan. 'Doesn't Sound Like a Sale'</p>
        <p>Robert Bergen, general counsel for the M.T.A., declined to comment on the current negotiations but said: "We have said we're not interested in phased developments, where we have to continue to hold the property for him at our expense while he's getting ready to develop it. That doesn't sound like a sale to me."</p>
        <p>City officials including Barry F. Sullivan, Deputy Mayor for Finance and Economic Development, and Carl Weisbrod, president of the city's Economic Development Corporation, are also known to be taking an active role in the talks with Mr. Zuckerman. Mr. Dinkins, in his response to the M.T.A., called for Mr. Zuckerman to negotiate an acceptable deal for the sale by Aug. 16 and to close the sale by Nov. 15.</p>
        <p>Because of the complicated sales agreement for the site, the city and the M.T.A. -- which is not a city agency -- both must sign on to any plan, and their interests do not necessarily coincide.</p>
        <p>While city officials declined to comment publicly on the talks, a senior city official who spoke on condition of anonymity said the city believed that it and the M.T.A. should look hard at Mr. Zuckerman's new offer when it is made formal. Further, the official said, the city wants to make sure that issues other than immediate cash rewards are considered in any decision.</p>
        <p>Looking at Larger Impact</p>
        <p>The official said: "The city has an interest in the larger economic impact of the project. There might be a use that brings in more direct revenue to the city but has a very limited secondary economic impact, or there might be one that would bring in a limited amount of direct revenue but have a much more significant economic impact."</p>
        <p>A retail user, for example, might bring a high rent, but another proposal -- like studio or exhibition space -- could pack a punch with secondary income from hotel and restaurant traffic. In any case, the official said, "We would be wary of encouraging speculative office space."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, people close to the talks said tempers were wearing thin. These people said that Mr. Zuckerman thought that the M.T.A. was trying to force his hand in a weak market and get a 1985 price for the land, and that it seems clear he could benefit from continuing delay that would grant time for talks with Weil, Gotshal or for a stronger market.</p>
        <p>These people also said that city officials were miffed that the M.T.A. gave no warning this month when it sent Mayor Dinkins its letter calling for the city to join the agency in setting a closing date and that M.T.A. officials suspect that Mr. Zuckerman is negotiating in the hopes of a delay.</p>
        <p>Finally, despite the apparent deadline Mr. Dinkins set in his letter to Peter E. Stangl, the authority's chairman, careful readers noted that further delay was not impossible. Mr. Dinkins wrote that "should the parties, acting reasonably and responsibly, be unable to reach an agreement by Aug. 16, 1993, I would be prepared on that date to concur" if the M.T.A. issued a closing notice -- suggesting that this deadline, too, is an elastic one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
