<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC Gives Martha Stewart an After-Prison Show</title>
    <meta content="09MART$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/09/business/media/09martha.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1633385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Martha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burnett, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Burnett, Mark</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4DF1031F93AA35751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC Gives Martha Stewart an After-Prison Show</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Martha Stewart Gets an After-Prison Show</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC and Mark Burnett announce they have reached deal with Martha Stewart's company Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia to bring her back to morning television in 2005, after she is released from prison; Burnett says he and Stewart will create more ambitious version of her syndicated cooking and style show; new hourlong program will be taped beginning in September in front of live audience and will feature more celebrities and humor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NBC and Mark Burnett, the reality-television mogul behind ''The Apprentice'' and ''Survivor,'' announced yesterday that they had reached a deal with Martha Stewart's company to bring her back to morning television next year, after she is released from prison in West Virginia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnett said that he and Ms. Stewart would create a more ambitious version of her syndicated cooking and style show, which was dropped by many stations after her conviction in March on charges of lying to federal investigators about a stock sale. The new hourlong program would be taped beginning in September in front of a live audience and would feature more celebrities and humor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Martha Stewart will host an hourlong, daily syndicated show with a live audience when she gets out of prison, her company said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NBC and Mark Burnett, the reality-television mogul behind ''The Apprentice'' and ''Survivor,'' announced yesterday that they had reached a deal with Martha Stewart's company to bring her back to morning television next year, after she is released from prison in West Virginia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnett said that he and Ms. Stewart would create a more ambitious version of her syndicated cooking and style show, which was dropped by many stations after her conviction in March on charges of lying to federal investigators about a stock sale. The new hourlong program would be taped beginning in September in front of a live audience and would feature more celebrities and humor.</p>
        <p>In September, Mr. Burnett announced that he and Ms. Stewart were working to create a prime-time reality television series. He did not comment directly on the status of that project.</p>
        <p>''She's actually very funny,'' said Mr. Burnett, who has visited Ms. Stewart in prison and said he would do so again next week, although he stressed that they had not discussed the television deal or business matters, which would have been a violation of prison rules. He said the agreement for the morning show was worked out before Ms. Stewart went to prison.</p>
        <p>Shares of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia rose $1.55 yesterday, or 7 percent, to close at $24.43.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stewart began serving her five-month prison sentence in October, and after she is released she must serve five months in home confinement. Mr. Burnett and Susan Lyne, the new chief executive of Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia, said they had no hesitation about announcing the television plans while Ms. Stewart was still serving her sentence. They added that they believed that her potential for drawing a large television audience could be much larger after her prison stint.</p>
        <p>''This is a forgiving country,'' said Ms. Lyne, at the company's headquarters in Manhattan, standing in front of a poster-size picture of Ms. Stewart pouring batter into a bowl. ''People love redemption stories.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether Ms. Stewart would refer to her prison experience (one of her lawyers has said that she is cooking often, using the communal microwave), Ms. Lyne said, ''I think she won't avoid it.''</p>
        <p>While there has been speculation that Ms. Stewart's program could replace Jane Pauley's morning talk show, which has struggled to find an audience, the network's executives said that no decision had been made about Ms. Pauley's show.</p>
        <p>''One show has nothing to do with the other show,'' said Barry Wallach, president of NBC Universal Domestic Sales and Distribution, which syndicates Ms. Pauley's show and will also handle Ms. Stewart's. He added, of Ms. Pauley's program, ''Jane has shown some growth recently.''</p>
        <p>At the news conference to announce the television deal, Ms. Stewart's presence could be felt everywhere at her headquarters, from the cheerful Christmas music to the hot cider and cookies with silver sugar buttons served to guests.</p>
        <p>In her remarks, Ms. Lyne rigorously avoided using the words ''jail'' and ''prison,'' instead referring to West Virginia or Alderson, the town where the prison is..</p>
        <p>But Mr. Burnett, whose flamboyant personality is reflected in his reality shows, repeatedly referred to Ms. Stewart's incarceration and tried to make light of it. ''Millions of people feel like Martha got a raw deal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added that before Ms. Stewart went to prison, he and she had filmed some test video for the new show and during the filming, Ms. Stewart gave him a fruit peeler.</p>
        <p>''And I really thought she was giving me a file to bake into a cake,'' he said, joking, and adding, ''Of course, Martha didn't think it was funny.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
