<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keep in Mind</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA143CF936A15751C1A964958260" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keep in Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"THE SNOW QUEEN," a movie adaptation of the Hans Christian Andersen fairy tale in which the Queen abducts a young boy and his friend tries to find him. Tomorrow and Sunday at 2 P.M., at the Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $7; $4 for children. Information: (212) 875-5600.</p>
        <p>"THE NUTCRACKER," a one-hour production by the New York Theater Ballet, for toddlers and preschoolers in an intimate setting. Tomorrow through Thursday at Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan, daily at 1 and 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $17.50; $12.50 for children. Information: (212) 307-7171.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"THE SNOW QUEEN," a movie adaptation of the Hans Christian Andersen fairy tale in which the Queen abducts a young boy and his friend tries to find him. Tomorrow and Sunday at 2 P.M., at the Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $7; $4 for children. Information: (212) 875-5600.</p>
        <p>"THE NUTCRACKER," a one-hour production by the New York Theater Ballet, for toddlers and preschoolers in an intimate setting. Tomorrow through Thursday at Gould Hall, 55 East 59th Street, Manhattan, daily at 1 and 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $17.50; $12.50 for children. Information: (212) 307-7171.</p>
        <p>"BABES IN TOYLAND" and "PAPER BAG PLAYERS AND YOU" Two separate shows, the first by Theaterworks/USA and the second a new show by the Paper Bag Players. "Babes," tomorrow at 11 A.M., 1 and 3:30 P.M. "Paper Bag Players and You," Sunday through Thursday at 11:30 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. At the Emelin Theater, Library Lane, Mamaroneck, N.Y. Tickets: $10 a show. Information: (914) 698-0098.</p>
        <p>"CHRISTMAS CAROUSEL," with Santa, Christmas trees, holly plants and ornate decorations. At the Lever House lobby, 390 Park Avenue, at 53d Street, Manhattan. Hours: Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 P.M. (Display is visible through street windows at all times; the building is closed on Christmas and New Year's Day.) Free. Information: (212) 906-4695.</p>
        <p>"ALDO AND THE MAGIC LAMP," a new family musical based on the Aladdin story, set in an urban community garden. Produced in collaboration with Operation Greenthumb, a nonprofit group that oversees New York City neighborhood gardens. Tomorrow through Thursday at the Vineyard Theater, 309 East 26th Street, Manhattan. Performances: daily at 1 and 3 P.M. Tickets: $10; $6 for children. Information: (212) 353-3874.</p>
        <p>"LA CANTATA DEI PASTORI" ("The Shepherd's Cantata"), a 17th-century story about the journey of Mary and Joseph to Bethlehem, featuring commedia dell'arte characters. Presented by I Guillari di Piazza (the Jesters of the Square), a company specializing in southern Italian music and plays. Performed in Italian, with period costumes and instruments. Tomorrow at 7 P.M. and Sunday at 2 P.M. at the Synod House, Cathedral of St. John the Divine, Amsterdam Avenue at 111th Street, Morningside Heights. Tickets: $15; $8 for children. Information: (212) 924-0077.</p>
        <p>KWANZAA CELEBRATION, at the American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 79th Street. Featuring an African marketplace, Sunday from 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.; poetry and folktales, on Monday at 1 and 3 P.M.; a workshop on the principles of Kwanzaa, on Monday at 1, 2 and 3 P.M.; contemporary African music, African games and rites of passage, on Monday from 1 to 4 P.M.; African dance demonstration, Tuesday at 2 and 4 P.M.; African cloth-design workshops, Tuesday at noon, 1:30 and 3 P.M.; African poetry, Tuesday at 1 and 3 P.M., and Puerto Rican music and dance, Tuesday at 1:30, 2:30 and 3:30 P.M. The program is sponsored by the New York Urban Coalition and the Cultural Institutions Group, an organization that promotes New York City arts and science institutions. Free, first come first served, , with museum admission: $5; $2.50 for children. Information: (212) 769-5315.</p>
        <p>"CELEBRATE! SEPHARDIC HANUKKAH," a party showing how the holiday is celebrated in the Middle Eastern tradition, with an art workshop. Monday from 1:30 to 4:30 P.M., at the Staten Island Children's Museum, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston. Admission: $3, plus a $1 workshop fee. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>"THE RANSOM OF RED CHIEF," a musical by On Stage Productions, based on the O. Henry story about hapless kidnappers and an unruly child. Hartley House Theater, 413 West 46th Street, Clinton. Holiday schedule: Monday through Wednesday at 3 P.M.; Jan. 2 at 3 and 7 P.M., and Jan. 3 at 3 P.M.; performances continue through Jan. 17. Tickets: $8; $6 for children. Information: (212) 666-1716.</p>
        <p>"ART ON SITE," a family holiday workshop at the Queens Museum of Art, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park. Participants will view the exhibition "Fragile Ecologies: Artists' Interpretations and Solutions" and make art related to the show. Tuesday and Wednesday at 1 P.M. A $2 fee, in addition to museum admission: $3; $1.50 for children over the age of 5. Information: (718) 592-9700.</p>
        <p>"ST. NICHOLAS CELEBRATION," a narration of the coming of St. Nicholas to New Amsterdam, performed by the Bronx Arts Ensemble and Singers, with Dutch carols. Part of the Lincoln Center Community Holiday Festival. Tuesday at 7:30 P.M., Alice Tully Hall. Free. Information: (212) 960-4602 or (212) 960-4602.</p>
        <p>"KWANZAA: AN AFRO-AMERICAN CELEBRATION," with music, crafts and fish stories. Tuesday from 10:30 A.M. to noon (for 5 to 7 year olds) and from 1:30 to 3 P.M. (for 8 to 12 year olds). At the New York Aquarium, West Eighth Street and Surf Avenue, Coney Island, Brooklyn. Fee: $11. Reservations: (718) 265-3474.</p>
        <p>"KWANZAA: FROM UMOJA TO IMANA," a family workshop meant to teach African culture and the holiday Kwanzaa. At the Bronx Museum of the Arts, 1040 Grand Concourse, at East 165th Street, Morrisania. Wednesday and Thursday, 11 A.M. Free with museum admission: $3; $2 for children over age 12. Information: (212) 681-6000.</p>
        <p>PETTING ZOO AND HORSE RIDES, Bryant Park, Avenue of the Americas at 40th Street. Part of the First Night New York '93 events; sponsored by the North Wind Museum on City Island, the Bronx. Thursday from noon to 5:30 P.M. Free with button pass, which covers all First Night events: $15; $7 for children 6 to 12. Information: (212) 745-8360.</p>
        <p>PUPPET SHOW, featuring the Speaking Shield Puppet Theater and a giant mermaid puppet. Part of First Night New York '93. Grand Central Terminal, Park Avenue and 42d Street. Thursday at 3:30 P.M. Free with button pass, which covers all First Night events: $15; $7 for children 6 to 12. Information: (212) 745-8360.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S CONCERT AND STORYTELLING, with Meg Lowenthal, a pianist, who will play short pieces by Chopin, Mendelssohn and Debussy at 2:30 and 3 P.M., and Gretchen Argetsinger, a storyteller, performing at 1:30 and 2:30 P.M. Part of First Night New York '93. Thursday at the Pierpont Morgan Library, 29 East 36th Street, Murray Hill. Free with button pass, which covers all First Night events: $15; $7 for children 6 to 12. Information: (212) 745-8360.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
