<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Labor Day Getaways, a Few Deals</title>
    <meta content="13praclabor" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/13/travel/13praclabor.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060827T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1782441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER: HOLIDAY TRAVEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7D91E3FF930A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Labor Day Getaways, a Few Deals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">For Labor Day Getaways, a Few Deals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE HIGGINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STILL looking for a cheap Labor Day getaway? You may have your work cut out for you. Packed planes and high prices are expected through the first weekend in September, with few bargains for procrastinators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you’re scrambling to get away, late-summer discounts can still be found. But you may have your work cut out for you to find them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STILL looking for a cheap Labor Day getaway? You may have your work cut out for you. Packed planes and high prices are expected through the first weekend in September, with few bargains for procrastinators.</p>
        <p>Late-summer air fares, for instance, are more expensive than last year. For the first week in September, fares to Florida, Hawaii, Las Vegas and Europe were up between 9 and 17 percent through the end of June, compared with a year ago, according to Sabre Airline Solutions. And many hotels that have been seeing record occupancies and double-digit rate increases see no reason to start discounting. Demand for Labor Day ''is stronger than last year,'' said Amy Ziff, editor at large of Travelocity. ''I wouldn't be surprised if this year is a record breaker.'' Still, some deals remain. Here is a roundup of some of the better offerings.</p>
        <p>ACCOMMODATIONS -- While there is still availability at some traditional Labor Day beach resorts like the Jersey Shore or Cape Cod, finding a bargain is more of a challenge. One place to look is the Web site for the New England Inns and Resorts Association, NewEnglandInnsandResorts.com, which says some members have been fully booked since 2005, but others are offering Labor Day promotions. The deals listed on the site are mostly gas credits or value-added packages that throw in breakfast or a bottle of wine. Only a few are offering cut rates; the Catania Hospitality Group, for example, is discounting its three hotels in Massachusetts by 20 percent. In New Jersey, forget bargains at the beach. ''I think you'll see more discounting inland, along the Delaware,'' which has seen soft bookings after flooding earlier this summer, said Terry Anderson, president of the Preferred Inns of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>For deeper discounts, head to a city, where hotels typically aren't as full and may be offering better bargains. In many cases, you won't even have to give up your tan. Many properties in cities like New York and Washington are offering rooftop pools and sun decks. In New York, Hotel Gansevoort is offering a two-night ''Who Needs the Hamptons?'' package through Sept. 4, starting at $570 a night. It includes breakfast, spa treatments for two, reserved chairs at the rooftop pool during the week, and a bag full of sunscreen, water misters and magazines -- for a saving of more than $200. The newly redesigned Park Hyatt Washington, which boasts bathrooms with deep soaking tubs and an indoor pool, has a $405 two-night package with breakfast, free parking and two tickets for the Old Town Trolley -- a saving of 27 percent. Hotel Palomar, also in Washington, has a lap pool and sun deck with cabanas, and is offering a $119 a night Labor Day rate for Aug. 31 to Sept. 4 including breakfast -- about a 30 percent savings.</p>
        <p>AMUSEMENT PARKS -- For families, some of the best deals are at theme parks. Cedar Point in Sandusky, Ohio, and Knott's Berry Farm in Buena Park, Calif., both rolled back prices on everything from admission (now $39.95 for adults from about $45 last year) to cotton candy (now just 25 cents a stick from $3). This year, Universal Orlando Resort in Florida began allowing children 9 years old and under in free when their parent buys a $99.95 two-day multipark pass online. Not to be outdone, SeaWorld recently announced a children-free promotion for families staying at participating Orlando Marriott hotels.</p>
        <p>Families that book four or more nights at one of the Loews Hotels at Universal Orlando Resort get free tickets for two adults and two children good for seven days to Universal Studios and Islands of Adventure. Hotel rates start at $199 at Loews' Royal Pacific Resort, $299 at the Hard Rock Hotel and $259 at Portofino Bay Hotel. Downtown Disney Resort Area Hotels, a group of seven hotels on Disney property in the Orlando area, are also offering deals. The newly renovated Royal Plaza, for example, is renting rooms for as low as $89 a night through Sept. 30. Guests booking directly with the hotel at (800) 248-7890 can get a $10 gas card if they ask for it when making their reservation.</p>
        <p>CANADA -- Canadian provinces are trying to lure more American visitors across the border. From January to May, visits by Americans were down 5 percent from the same period in 2005, according to the Canadian Tourism Commission. One of the reasons for the downturn is a stronger Canadian dollar. The United States dollar bought 1.33 Canadian dollars in July two years ago compared to about 1.13 this year, according to Avery Shenfeld, a senior economist at CIBC World Markets in Toronto.</p>
        <p>But in many cases, the exchange rate is being offset by lower rates. In Quebec City, the Loews Le Concorde is offering rates as low as 149 Canadian dollars ($134 at the current rate of 1.11 Canadian dollars to $1) -- a saving of 45 percent. And Fairmont Hotels and Resorts, which has 21 properties in Canada, is offering ''Only One Way'' summer rates of up to 40 percent off at most of its Canadian hotels.</p>
        <p>Through October, travelers can book discounted two-night hotel packages in Montreal at www.sweetdealmontreal.com that include late check-out, buffet breakfast or an upgrade. Rates at the InterContinental Montreal begin at 219 Canadian dollars. For bargains in Calgary, Alberta, check www.greatcalgaryescapes.com. One listing: The Calgary Marriott is offering a Cars Eat Free package with promotion code TRS that includes free parking and a gas card worth 25 Canadian dollars, from 159 Canadian dollars a night.</p>
        <p>HURRICANE HOLIDAYS -- The best savings are to be found in off-peak destinations like Mexico, the Caribbean and parts of Florida, where typical off-season incentives have been stepped up a bit to try to lure wary travelers back after last year's hurricanes.</p>
        <p>In the Florida Keys, hard hit by Hurricane Wilma last year, prices are an average 25 percent lower during the off-season, according to the Cheaptickets.com Off-season Deals Report. Prices in New Orleans are 22 percent less in the off-season, while those in the Bahamas are 14 percent lower.</p>
        <p>Through July, air fare to Cancún over the Labor Day weekend was down 16 percent from last year according to Travelocity. And most resorts that were damaged by Hurricane Wilma last October have reopened with improved facilities. Some are offering perks. For instance, starting Aug. 16, the recently reopened JW Marriott Cancún Resort and Spa will offer guests staying at least four nights discounts and gifts ranging from a free bottle of champagne to 15 percent discounts on back massages.</p>
        <p>Aruba, which hasn't had a direct hit by a major hurricane in more than 100 years, is also offering deals. The Radisson Aruba Resort and Casino, for example, is offering savings of 10 percent, with rates starting at $209 a room a night including a $100 food and beverage credit for stays of five nights or longer.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER: HOLIDAY TRAVEL</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 27, 2006, Sunday  The Practical Traveler column on Aug. 13, about Labor Day deals, included incorrect information provided by the Park Hyatt Washington about a $405 package with breakfast, free parking and two tickets for the Old Town Trolley. The price is per night, not for two nights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 27, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Practical Traveler column on Aug. 13, about Labor Day deals, included incorrect information provided by the Park Hyatt Washington about a $405 package with breakfast, free parking and two tickets for the Old Town Trolley. The price is per night, not for two nights.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
