<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Art' Is No Luxury</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="641267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PORT AUTHORITY OF NY AND NJ</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61F30F937A25753C1A965958260" item-length="452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Art' Is No Luxury</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City is a difficult place to find an apartment, a cheap hotel room, a seat on the subway or, all too often, a moment's peace. But finding a theater, a museum, an art gallery, a dance group or a concert is a cinch. The city is up to its ears in the arts.</p>
        <p>Last week the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey released a report that tells just what that extraordinary cultural concentration means to the metropolitan economy. It means jobs, lots of them, for New Yorkers -- and tax revenues for the city and state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City is a difficult place to find an apartment, a cheap hotel room, a seat on the subway or, all too often, a moment's peace. But finding a theater, a museum, an art gallery, a dance group or a concert is a cinch. The city is up to its ears in the arts.</p>
        <p>Last week the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey released a report that tells just what that extraordinary cultural concentration means to the metropolitan economy. It means jobs, lots of them, for New Yorkers -- and tax revenues for the city and state.</p>
        <p>In 1992 the arts and other cultural activities in the metropolitan region generated almost $3.5 billion in wages, salaries and royalties, a 10 percent increase over the last decade. They were responsible for 107,000 jobs, ranging from starring on stage to making ballet slippers to catering for movie crews. And their total economic impact, counting expenditures by arts institutions, their suppliers, wage earners and visitors, generated 9.8 billion sorely needed bucks in the metropolitan area. Nearly 25 percent of that money came from tourists who said they had come to New York, or lengthened their stays there, to go to museums, galleries, theaters and concerts.</p>
        <p>Some of what the arts bring to New York is impossible to quantify. The film makers who shot, in whole or part, more than 100 features there last year spent $168 million. But the public relations value of, say, the opening of Woody Allen's "Manhattan Murder Mystery" -- a magical nighttime city seen from above while Bobby Short sings "I Happen to Like New York" on the soundtrack -- are incalculable.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority report makes no recommendations for subsidizing the arts at any particular level. But it contains more than enough hard figures to convince readers that the arts in New York feed a whole lot more than the soul. The arts are clearly a major economic sector, more so in New York than anywhere else in the country; their health should be treated with care.</p>
        <p>But while Mayor David Dinkins has seen the wisdom of keeping the city's Cultural Affairs budget, which mostly supports nonprofit organizations, close to its 1990 high, Gov. Mario Cuomo has seen only the short-term gain of Draconian cuts. Three years ago, the New York State Arts Council's budget -- much of which comes to the metropolitan area -- was $54 million. Today it's $25 million -- and would be even less had the Legislature not restored $3 million that the Governor wanted out.</p>
        <p>The state needs to take a second look at the adequacy of its arts funding. Would that the baseball fan who governs and who suggested spending $500 million on a new stadium in Manhattan were half as interested in keeping the arts in town.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
