<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Way to Treat a Lady</title>
    <meta content="31MERKINT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/31/books/review/31MERKINT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1379968"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Merkin, Daphne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Templeton, Edith</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Darts of Cupid, The: And Other Stories (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Templeton, Edith</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DA1138F932A05750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Way to Treat a Lady</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Darts of Cupid': The Romance of Prey and Predator</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Daphne Merkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Merkin, Daphne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daphne Merkin reviews book The Darts of Cupid: And Other Stories by Edith Templeton; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DARTS OF CUPID</p>
        <p>AND OTHER STORIES.</p>
        <p>By Edith Templeton.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A collection of short stories by Edith Templeton, a writer in her 80's, trains a dark lens on the hidden components of desire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DARTS OF CUPID</p>
        <p>AND OTHER STORIES.</p>
        <p>By Edith Templeton.</p>
        <p>312 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Pantheon Books. $23.</p>
        <p>There are certain women writers -- Jean Rhys is the most obvious example, but it is also true of Katherine Mansfield and Marguerite Duras -- whose work is fragrant with melancholy, possessed of a secret knowledge. Whatever the nominal subject of their attention, these women seem always to be writing about the same thing: the unpredictability of desire and the inevitable passing of their own desirability. Impressionistic perceptions -- what they make of a world that constantly impinges on their apprehensions of their own moods and wishes -- are the key to their narratives, much more than characters or plot lines; one senses a memoirist's self-reflecting impulse rather than a novelist's colonizing approach to the material at hand. And the only reliable verities in the limited but compelling universes that come under their scrutiny are that men will be untrustworthy, passion will be unrequited and life will always let you down.</p>
        <p>Edith Templeton, who is 85, comes late to this group. She has been writing for decades, having published stories in The New Yorker since the 1950's, as well as several novels and a travel book. Yet she is sufficiently unknown to qualify as a discovery for all but a few readers. Five of the seven stories in ''The Darts of Cupid'' originally appeared in The New Yorker, and there are certain ways in which they might be said to exemplify that magazine's polished (and often parodied) literary sensibility, composed as they are of discriminating aperçus and minutely observed social transactions. But Templeton's fiction resists pigeonholing, in large part because of an emotional undertow -- a subtle, almost subliminal engagement with a kind of sexual longing that hinges on a perceived discrepancy in power -- which pulls it in a different, more audacious direction.</p>
        <p>The version of erotic attraction that afflicts Templeton's protagonists (all of whom seem to be closely modeled on the author) has little to do with ordinary affection or socially accepted codes of behavior. It is about the desire that dare not speak its name, at least not in polite print -- the unladylike desire to be treated as anything but a lady by a man who is clearly not a gentleman. The klutzy, clinical term for it, I suppose, would be sadomasochism. What this form of heterosexual bonding addresses head on that more genteel variations on the theme do not is, among other things, the inherently illogical nature of sexual desire. It acknowledges the core disconnection between love and lust that Freud kept stubbing his toe on.</p>
        <p>Although this is a quandary that women have to deal with every bit as much as men, its treatment in explicit but nonpornographic fiction has been almost exclusively the province of male writers like Henry Miller, Norman Mailer and Philip Roth. Serious female writers have tended to slight the darker side of the paradox of desire as a suitable subject for exploration. This collective avoidance comes about, I think, because women writers feel under greater pressure to bring the vagaries of the heart into alignment with the dictates of the mind, as befits the kinder, gentler (or, at any rate, more domesticated) sex. Which leaves the field to a select few who, like Pauline Reage and Anne Rice, tend to overplay the gothic elements and underplay the psychological tensions. For this reason alone Templeton's writing would be worth looking at, but happily for the reader there are other reasons as well.</p>
        <p>This daringly unconventional aspect of her work is perhaps best reflected in the long title story; along with stories like ''A Coffeehouse Acquaintance'' and ''Nymph &amp; Faun,'' it demonstrates the author's gift for understated but uneasy-making revelations of character. ''The Darts of Cupid'' created a stir at the time of its publication, in 1968, because of the cynical and erotically charged subtext that beat its tom-tom under a casual, almost airheadish exterior. Set against the wartime backdrop of the fictional English town of Bathdale, in the American branch of the office of the chief surgeon (Templeton herself worked in very similar circumstances), this tale of a severed romance is narrated in a brittle, no-nonsense fashion by Eve, a recently separated woman in her 20's who has already breezed through two affairs. (''In each case, I had been bored.'') The hothouse atmosphere created by a gaggle of cooped-up women -- devoted maternal secretaries, hard-bitten young typists and gossips starved for office intrigue -- is heightened by the fact that the few men who grace the premises are unavailable officers who are higher up on the totem pole. (A snobby, even brutal class consciousness much like that of Ivy Compton-Burnett informs Templeton's sensibility, dividing the world into inexorable pairings of the empowered -- those who come from ''a ruling-class background'' and are ''genuinely well bred'' -- and the powerless ''underlings,'' who are ''common as dirt.'') Comic relief is provided by a letchy twosome, nicknamed the Big Bad Wolves, who ''offer the incense of flattery'' in search of a bit of hanky-panky.</p>
        <p>The two-night love affair between Eve and a man known only as the Major that is at the heart of the story is as far from ''good, clean English fun'' as one can get. The couple trade in a kind of repartee -- You are so exquisitely made,'' the Major tells her right after they have a tumble, ''I could break every bone in your body'' -- that seems to be a code for his menacingly amorous intentions and her show of indignant resistance ('' 'Go to hell,' I said''). Theirs is a romance of prey and predator -- the narrator compares her lover to ''a keeper in the zoo'' -- and Templeton is untimorous about the sexual dynamics behind this sort of interaction: ''He turned me on my flank and pulled my nightgown up under my armpits. He placed my head against his chest and slid his arms about me and entwined his legs in a bewildering, complicated grip with mine, till my body was entirely enwrapped and enclosed and imprisoned in his.'' In the midst of lovemaking, Eve remembers an image that she had once seen in a Japanese print, in which a woman's nude corpse afloat in the sea is gripped by a large octopus who is ''penetrating her with his many arms.'' She goes on to explain the self-extinguishing lure of sexual surrender in the most matter-of-fact fashion, rather as though she were describing the ordinary evolution of romantic attachment: ''I knew,'' Templeton writes, ''that this was the rendering of love as it should be: trapped inescapably, secure and fastened, drowned in bed and water, both cradle and grave. I gave a sigh of contentment and fell asleep.''</p>
        <p>Several of the stories are set in the early 30's, in the upper-crust Prague of Templeton's youth. Here the flimsy veil of fiction is dispensed with entirely: the narrator is called Edith and the tone is clearly autobiographical. The atmosphere is Chekhovian with an edge, allowing for a cleareyed view of the decadent currents that run under the grand, well-mannered surfaces, where villas have both ''good'' and ''everyday'' dining rooms. Edith's disdainful and easily irritated mother, whose voice is ''bleached with boredom,'' has been ''twice divorced before the age of 30.'' The two of them spend the holidays with Edith's grandmother, who lives in a Bohemian castle where the parlor maid is unceasingly deferential and the desultory talk is of evening dresses, the French Revolution and assorted visitors who may or may not prove interesting. As in ''The Darts of Cupid,'' the story begins small and artfully opens out to embrace inarticulate longings and unspoken impasses.</p>
        <p>Interestingly, in spite of its bold articulations, the collection as a whole has a period feel; even when they are set closer to contemporary time, the stories seem steeped in nostalgia, haunted by the spirit of a cosmopolitan, black-tie milieu that has gone the way of rotary telephones. Perhaps this accounts for the strange feeling I had as I was reading, as though there were another tale -- a kind of ghost limb -- behind each story that had been lost in the translation onto the page. Or maybe it has something to do with an informing elusiveness that contradicts the directness of Templeton's style and her deft evocation of a bygone time and place. ''Come and catch me,'' this wily temptress of a writer seems to be saying. ''Catch me if you can.'' But we know we can't, if only because she has gone and given her heart to the man who will break it, and she won't admit to the pain. What we are left with are these stories, sparkling with untold hazard, like pieces of cut glass.</p>
        <p>Daphne Merkin is the author of the novel ''Enchantment'' and ''Dreaming of Hitler,'' a collection of essays.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daphne Merkin is the author of the novel ''Enchantment'' and ''Dreaming of Hitler,'' a collection of essays.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
