<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Best Friends, Till Marriage Do Us Part</title>
    <meta content="31HASK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/31/movies/31HASK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1380043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckay, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macdowell, Andie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chancellor, Anna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staunton,Imelda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haskell, Molly</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Crush (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">MacDowell, Andie</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Holofcener, Nicole</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DA133BF932A05750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Best Friends, Till Marriage Do Us Part</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Best Friends, Till Marriage Do Us Part</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOLLY HASKELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haskell, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on on movie Crush, directed by John McKay and starring Andie MacDowell, Anna Chancellor and Imelda Staunton, latest in group of films that focus on how relationships change when one friend becomes engaged; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOUR best friend tells you she's engaged. Do you (1) hug her, bring out the champagne and throw yourself enthusiastically into the wedding plans, or (2) let your true feelings emerge? That is to say, widen your eyes in horror, shriek ''Are you kidding?'' (while making plans to eliminate the unwelcome intruder) and -- a more polite form of murder -- make fun of her engagement ring?</p>
        <p>Strikingly, this viperish tactic has appeared not once but twice on the screen in recent years: first in Nicole Holofcener's 1996 film ''Walking and Talking,'' when Catherine Keener guffaws over her best friend Anne Heche's hand-crafted token of betrothal, and again in a very funny episode of HBO's ''Sex and the City,'' when Samantha almost faints from fashion shock at the pear-shaped diamond that Aidan has given to Carrie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John McKay's "Crush" is the rare movie that penetrates the surface of women's camaraderie and looks unblinkingly at its darker side.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOUR best friend tells you she's engaged. Do you (1) hug her, bring out the champagne and throw yourself enthusiastically into the wedding plans, or (2) let your true feelings emerge? That is to say, widen your eyes in horror, shriek ''Are you kidding?'' (while making plans to eliminate the unwelcome intruder) and -- a more polite form of murder -- make fun of her engagement ring?</p>
        <p>Strikingly, this viperish tactic has appeared not once but twice on the screen in recent years: first in Nicole Holofcener's 1996 film ''Walking and Talking,'' when Catherine Keener guffaws over her best friend Anne Heche's hand-crafted token of betrothal, and again in a very funny episode of HBO's ''Sex and the City,'' when Samantha almost faints from fashion shock at the pear-shaped diamond that Aidan has given to Carrie.</p>
        <p>I can't divulge the lengths to which another best friend goes in ''Crush,'' the witty new British film about a trio of single women in their 40's. But it's enough to say that when the prim headmistress played by Andie MacDowell falls head over knickers for a former student, her doctor pal (Anna Chancellor) goes lethal trying to sabotage the relationship. Indeed, this female buddy comedy, written and directed by John McKay, ceases to be a comedy and almost doesn't recover from the consequences of the friend's machinations.</p>
        <p>But -- miraculously -- it does, and before the last-minute redemption and reconciliation, the film brings to the surface the dirty little secret of female solidarity that is rarely touched upon, not just in movies but in life. That is the rivalry, the jealousy, the ferocious fear of abandonment that underlie our support of one another. The fact that as we sit around giggling and gossiping and talking about men, urging each other into or out of this or that affair, on some level the last thing we really want is for one of us to find true bliss, ''forsaking all others'' in the cruel and terrifying words of the marriage ceremony.</p>
        <p>But with that glimpse of the down-and-dirty side of female relationships comes an awareness of its opposite, an intimacy so special that it requires all the resources and propaganda of romance to wean us from the feeling of irreplaceable loss that marriage represents.</p>
        <p>Female buddy pictures are not exactly a staple of movies, contemporary or otherwise. From the beginning of cinematic time, we've had male bonding films in every wrinkle and permutation. There was Howard Hawks's prototypical ''A Girl in Every Port'' of 1928, in which the sailor played by Robert Armstrong says about his fellow seaman, Victor McLaglen, ''That big ox means more to me than any woman'' (this referring to the gorgeous and decidedly non-oxlike Louise Brooks).</p>
        <p>We've had cowboy buddies like Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, the rash of interracial cop duos of the last two decades, the mutually adoring mobster fraternities of Coppola and Scorsese, men at war taking the bullet for their fellow soldiers, and coming-of-age pictures that generally focus on how two high school wise guys joke and fumble their way into their sexual initiation, the sex being secondary to the conspiracy of yuks.</p>
        <p>But the female version has been restricted to a few oddities: the runaway avengers in ''Thelma and Louise,'' the comically angry ex-spouses of ''The First Wives Club,'' the teenage meanies of ''Heathers'' and some road movies that all seemed to feature Drew Barrymore. The amusing lesbian courtship of ''Kissing Jessica Stein,'' now in theaters, suggests that younger women may have a more relaxed perspective on the fluidity of female relationships. At the moment, if there is one girlie group that is flailing and wisecracking its way into the spotlight, it's the thirtyish ''singletons'' in the Bridget Jones mode.</p>
        <p>Rare indeed is a movie that portrays the anxieties and the joys of single women in their 40's as John McKay's ''Crush'' does. The film sees them both truthfully and romantically, as ever so slightly ravaged, a little more desperate than their younger counterparts, but still beautiful, still in the game. Even rarer is the movie that penetrates the surface of that camaraderie and looks unblinkingly at its darker side.</p>
        <p>''Crush,'' which opens on Wednesday in New York and Los Angeles, takes Andie MacDowell, who is 43, back to Britain in another rural setting. (Remember when she abandoned Hugh Grant in ''Four Weddings and a Funeral'' to marry the Scotsman amid baronial splendor?) Here she plays a sort of Jekyll-and-Hyde role that finally captures her peculiar daffy-chic appeal. You have to go back to ''Sex, Lies and Videotape'' (1989) to find that teasingly contradictory mix in her: the shy, well-brought-up Southern girl, ladylike to a fault, but with a saucy look in her eye and a passionate nature waiting to be unleashed.</p>
        <p>As Kate, the spinsterish head of a proper British prep school, Ms. MacDowell wears unflattering clothes and thick stockings but lets her hair down each week with the vixenish, thrice-married Molly (Ms. Chancellor) and the relentlessly peppy Janine (Imelda Staunton, playing a divorced, small-town cop). These are dames who make up for the hole in their love lives with weekly jam sessions of smoking, drinking and getting high on the British equivalent of Twinkies. Who would give up, without a fight or a bout of depression, such joyous commingling -- the pigging out, the bad jokes, the good jokes, the let-it-all-hang-out camaraderie of women who in each other's company still think of one another as ''girls.''</p>
        <p>Given the libidinous girl talk, there's something out of character and out of date in the outrage they express over Kate's affair with a much younger man, a sexy organist. Her lover, Jed, is deemed unsuitable by the cultured middle-class standards of her friends, but the tension his social awkwardness produces is overplayed. How come no one seems to notice that this supposedly boobish swain, portrayed by a newcomer, Kenny Doughty, is drop-dead desirable on any turf? Mr. Doughty's Jed doesn't seem to know yet just how attractive he is. His Jed is the unspoiled Adonis, the latterday Lawrentian ideal -- passionate and he can fix things! -- that every woman yearns for. The real problem, of course, is that Kate and Jed fall for each other in a love so unbridled that it excludes the friends in a way a tamer marriage to their preferred suitor, a sweet vicar played by Bill Paterson, would never do.</p>
        <p>Beneath the friends' vendetta lies a sense of bereavement, that hollow in the pit of the stomach that comes from seeing your best friend in a wedding dress, a rapt smile on her face, forgetting your existence. The two sisters in Anita Brookner's 1999 novel, ''Falling Slowly,'' simply stop going to weddings because of the ''disappearance of confidantes.'' At least they have each other. But what about the childhood friends, the surrogate siblings, played by Ms. Keener and Ms. Heche in that seriously underrated gem ''Walking and Talking''?</p>
        <p>We first see them as pre-teenagers, lying on a bed, poring and gagging over X-rated pictures. They then become adults who share not only an apartment but every aspect of their lives. Similarly, the quartet of young women in HBO's ''Sex and the City'' are each other's family, a chorus of enthusiasm, support and occasional scolding. When Carrie (Sarah Jessica Parker) tells her friends that she's engaged, Samantha (Kim Cattrall) comes out with an unprintable expletive, then says, ''If you're going to ruin our lives, at least . . .'' The implication is, choose a man who can choose the right ring.</p>
        <p>For all the griping and bemoaning in the single-woman genre about the dearth and elusiveness of men, of affairs gone south, one has to wonder if the commitment-phobes and Mr. Wrongs that women gravitate to aren't, at least unconsciously, a way of postponing the moment of decision, both dreaded and longed for, which will bring with it a whole host of other decisions and lifelong responsibilities. Do I want to have a child? How much of myself do I allocate for this, for that? How dedicated will I be to my career? All of this, knowing that whatever the choices, something that is enmeshed in the friendships of women will be lost forever: an easy confidence, a relaxation of the vigil of looking our best, a different and freer way of measuring time.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in an era of divorce, with the demystification of romance, in a world where the term ''love everlasting'' has no place, the dreams of a Perfect Soulmate are harder to sustain. Carrie ponders: ''How do you know when it's not right . . . perhaps there are no right guys, right moments, right answers.''</p>
        <p>When Ms. Keener's Amelia and Ms. Heche's Laura finally have it out, Amelia says: ''You're only concerned with your own happiness. You don't want to know what it's like for me.''</p>
        <p>Laura replies, ''What is it like for you?''</p>
        <p>Amelia, pausing: ''Hard.''</p>
        <p>Laura: ''Me, too.''</p>
        <p>The characters and the films that address that knowledge don't deserve to be dismissed as ''chick flicks.'' These pictures carry a darker and more subversive message that belies the idea of boy-girl romance as the pot of gold and marriage as the fulfillment of every woman's destiny.</p>
        <p>INTIMACY among women may get no respect, but that in itself could be a testament to the power of that most primal and complicated of all relationships. Even in that venerable genre, the ''woman's film'' of the 30's and 40's, where love and sacrifice, grief and lamentation were the order of the day (hence the term ''weepers'') and women's friendships took precedence (and star power) over the men who stoked their rivalry, the mourning was over the deaths or departures of men and children, never each other.</p>
        <p>We may abandon our female friends when a ''better'' (i.e., male) offer comes along, as once we spurned our too-familiar mothers for our more glamorous fathers, but in the end, these friendships abide. And how many and varied they are! You walk into any tea room or cafe and you see women in a huddle, talking intensely. They might be old college friends, godmother and goddaughter, mentor and acolyte, lesbians, single women, one married and the other not, and any of a hundred other combinations. Of women and the ties that bind them there are a million stories, but who tells them? A few quirky independent or European films. The Hollywood mainstream, the guys in the game of pitching and financing movies, aren't interested.</p>
        <p>Molly Haskell is a New York film critic. Her most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the worst best-picture Oscar winners.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Molly Haskell is a New York film critic. Her most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the worst best-picture Oscar winners.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
