<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hurricane Leaves Trail Of Damage Along Gulf</title>
    <meta content="18STOR$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/18/national/18storm.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040922T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1612228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ivan (Storm)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Caribbean Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Red Cross</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crampton, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tornadoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alabama</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Georgia</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mississippi</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD61739F93BA2575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hurricane Leaves Trail Of Damage Along Gulf</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ivan Leaves Long Trail of Damage Along Gulf</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS CRAMPTON; Reporting for this article was contributed by Terry Aguayo from Miami, Perry Athanason and Duwayne Escobedo from Pensacola, Fla., Felicity Barringer from Mobile, Ala., and Ariel Hart from Atlanta.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crampton, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>GULF SHORES, Ala., Sept. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hurricane Ivan leaves 75 people dead in Caribbean and at least 40 dead in United States; storm has been down-graded to tropical depression but spent record 10 days as major hurricane; destruction is concentrated along Gulf coast; storm spawned tornadoes in several states, left hundreds of thousands of people without power, damaged homes and caused flash floods; Red Cross shelters take in as many as 40,000 people; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The calm blue skies above this Alabama town on Friday made it seem like any other beach resort on a sunny afternoon.</p>
        <p>A cursory inspection of the thin strip of land along the Gulf of Mexico, however, quickly revealed the destruction wrought by Hurricane Ivan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although downgraded to a tropical storm, Ivan is still churning a deadly path north.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The calm blue skies above this Alabama town on Friday made it seem like any other beach resort on a sunny afternoon.</p>
        <p>A cursory inspection of the thin strip of land along the Gulf of Mexico, however, quickly revealed the destruction wrought by Hurricane Ivan.</p>
        <p>The sand was peppered with tire-puncturing debris that included a mushy mixture of building materials and personal belongings. A wooden house twisted on its stilts leaned sideways, while another had lost its roof and perhaps an upper floor. It was hard to tell.</p>
        <p>A concrete condominium lay crumpled like tissue paper; another leaned precariously toward the water. Long tongues of tile flooring dripped toward the waves from one building, sole remnants of sought-after sea-view rooms that were sheared off by the storm.</p>
        <p>Of the houses on the upscale gated community of Ono Island that still had roofs, many appeared blinded by the shattering of their large panoramic windows.</p>
        <p>Although the hurricane has been downgraded to a tropical depression, it continues to churn north, leaving a death toll of 75 in the Caribbean and, The Associated Press said, at least 40 in the United States, and hundreds of thousands without power in Alabama and Florida.</p>
        <p>The hurricane, which spawned at least 48 tornadoes in Florida, Georgia, the Carolinas, Virginia, West Virginia and Maryland, set the record of 10 days for the amount of time spent as a major hurricane.</p>
        <p>Moving through Georgia and the Carolinas, the storm killed 11 people as it tossed trees onto cars, homes and power lines while unleashing mudslides and floods.</p>
        <p>Most of those deaths occurred in mountainous Appalachia, where strong rains washed flash floods across roads.</p>
        <p>In White County, Ga., a 6-year-old girl was swept into a culvert from her trailer park by a flooding creek, an emergency management spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Heavy rain stranded about 150 students and employees at an elementary school in southeastern Ohio, The Associated Press reported, although emergency officials said the building was on high ground and out of danger.</p>
        <p>''We're probably here for the duration of the night,'' the school librarian, Patti McKibben, told the wire service. ''The Red Cross is bringing in blankets by boat.''</p>
        <p>About 100 children in the West Virginia panhandle also were forced to spend the night at their schools because of flooding, The Associated Press said.</p>
        <p>In Virginia, Gov. Mark R. Warner declared a state of emergency, the wire service reported, and in western North Carolina, the Department of Transportation said nearly 200 roads were impassable, including Interstate 40 west of Asheville.</p>
        <p>Here in Gulf Shores, armed National Guard personnel turned back all island residents as the authorities waited for the tidal surge to recede enough for damage assessments.</p>
        <p>Officials in Florida, where the third hurricane in five weeks has left virtually the entire state a federal disaster area, pleaded for extra time before residents come back.</p>
        <p>''We're asking people to not return to their homes,'' said Cragin Mosteller, spokeswoman for the Florida Emergency Operations Center in Tallahassee. ''Today is critical for search and rescue.''</p>
        <p>Large swaths in the hurricane's path through Florida and Alabama remained without electricity, with some officials warning that full restoration of power could take weeks.</p>
        <p>Peter Teahen, a Red Cross spokesman, said Friday that 32,000 people were in Red Cross shelters on Thursday night, down from 40,000 on Wednesday night. Most of those, Mr. Teahen said, were in Florida, where the charity was still providing shelter for 510 evacuees from Hurricane Frances, which struck less than two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>In Alabama, incidents of looting and price gouging were reported by officials at the Baldwin County emergency management agency, including the arrest of two men found scavenging at a school.</p>
        <p>Emergency food distribution points were set up by the authorities in Baldwin County, but several restaurants began to reopen, including a Burger King with its front sign gone.</p>
        <p>''This is our first meal since eating in a church on Wednesday in Mississippi,'' said Tracy Hubbard, as she waited in line at the Burger King. ''I can't wait to eat something other than a sandwich.''</p>
        <p>Some people said they enjoyed aspects of being thrown back to the pre-electricity era.</p>
        <p>''I feel like an old-time innkeeper when working by candlelight and using paper,'' said Clennie Thead, duty manager at a Holiday Inn Express near the Alabama shoreline that was booked solid with people weathering the hurricane.Two policemen helped shoppers at a darkened Walgreen's in Pensacola, Fla., fetching items as employees worked the registers.</p>
        <p>Gasoline became a valued commodity as residents returned with empty tanks from safe havens.</p>
        <p>''We prayed over the top of this car and really only got here on fumes,'' said Richard Proctor of Foley, Ala., who had taken refuge in Mobile.</p>
        <p>A hospital in one of the hardest-hit Alabama counties reported a sharp increase in hurricane-related accidents.</p>
        <p>''There was nothing to do during the storm,'' said Dr. John Meade of South Baldwin Regional Medical Center. ''Now things are really starting to get busy.''</p>
        <p>Among the more high profile businesses wrecked by the hurricane was Floribama, a vast beachfront complex of bars along the Florida-Alabama state line.</p>
        <p>''I can tell you that Floribama is no more,'' said Jim Jeter, who flew an ultralight airplane along the coast on Friday morning. ''I would not call this a cultural disaster because I am sure they will rise again.''</p>
        <p>Many who heard news of the devastation returned with relief to find their homes mainly intact.</p>
        <p>''I can tell you that I will be thanking the Lord for what happened to our place,'' said Greg Ingle of Foley who had retreated to Birmingham before the storm. ''There's damage on every building around ours, including one that was opened up like a can of sardines.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ingle, who sells spas, said he expects to be out of work for quite some time.</p>
        <p>''There's certainly a lot of people who could use a therapeutic spa,'' he said. ''But I don't reckon it's the first thing on anyone's mind right now.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Tropical Storm Jeanne Weakens</p>
        <p>SAMANA, Dominican Republic, Sept. 17 (AP) -- Tropical Storm Jeanne lashed Puerto Rico and the Dominican Republic on Friday before it weakened to a tropical depression and headed toward the Bahamas. Eight were killed across the Caribbean.</p>
        <p>In Puerto Rico, a severe thunderstorm in the south brought up to two feet of rain and produced lightning and gusty winds that caused the authorities to urge residents to stay inside sturdy buildings. Officials urged residents to boil their water, prompting angry comments because half the four million residents were without running water for a third day and 70 percent had no electricity.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 22, 2004, Wednesday  An article on Saturday about the aftermath of Hurricane Ivan misspelled the name of a beachfront complex of bars along the Florida-Alabama border that was damaged by the storm. It is Flora-Bama, not Floribama.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 22, 2004, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the aftermath of Hurricane Ivan misspelled the name of a beachfront complex of bars along the Florida-Alabama border that was damaged by the storm. It is Flora-Bama, not Floribama.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
