<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earning Some Extra Frequent Flier Miles Without Actually Getting on a Plane</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Your Money Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="608971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA103CF936A25756C0A965958260" item-length="442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earning Some Extra Frequent Flier Miles Without Actually Getting on a Plane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andree Brooks</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You've managed to accumulate, say, 18,000 miles on Continental Airlines' frequent flier program. That puts you only 2,000 miles short of the 20,000 miles needed to qualify for a round-trip coach fare anywhere in the continental United States -- an agonizingly close call.</p>
        <p>But don't assume you must take another flight to qualify for the free trip. "If you're just a few miles short of your goal there are several ways to make up the difference," said Randy Petersen, editor of Insider Flyer magazine, a monthly consumer publication based in Colorado Springs for members of frequent flier programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You've managed to accumulate, say, 18,000 miles on Continental Airlines' frequent flier program. That puts you only 2,000 miles short of the 20,000 miles needed to qualify for a round-trip coach fare anywhere in the continental United States -- an agonizingly close call.</p>
        <p>But don't assume you must take another flight to qualify for the free trip. "If you're just a few miles short of your goal there are several ways to make up the difference," said Randy Petersen, editor of Insider Flyer magazine, a monthly consumer publication based in Colorado Springs for members of frequent flier programs.</p>
        <p>One solution is to "buy" the remaining miles. Right now, three carriers allow this option. Air Canada has a program that permits the purchase of a maximum of 10 percent of the needed miles at a cost of $26 for each 1,000 miles credited.</p>
        <p>Continental permits up to 20 percent of the miles to be purchased at $25 for 1,000 miles.</p>
        <p>British Airways requires at least 35,000 miles to be in the account before allowing participation in its "booster" program -- a package of 5,000 miles at a cost of $100. Lower amounts are not permitted. But any excess will be credited toward a future trip. British Airways also allows others in the same household to pool their miles to accumulate an award level.</p>
        <p>If you intend to fly United, Delta, American or Northwest, or any other airline that does not currently allow you to "buy" the remaining miles, you must use a different strategy.</p>
        <p>Tie-ins with the long-distance telephone companies is one. Calls made on MCI, for example, allow you to accumulate miles on Northwest and American. You also receive a bonus of 2,000 miles on American or 500 miles on Northwest just for transferring to MCI service.</p>
        <p>Eating your way through the numbers is another option. Northwest has a tie-in with some 60 restaurants, mostly in the Midwest, that credit two miles for every dollar spent at their establishments.</p>
        <p>Sending packages is another. T.W.A. credits 500 bonus miles for shipping packages within the country through its air freight service and 1,000 miles for an overseas shipment.</p>
        <p>Affinity credit cards is yet another. For instance, Diners Club offers one frequent mile on any major domestic airline for every dollar charged. American Express has a similar but more limited program.</p>
        <p>The experts warn that these special arrangements are as unpredictable as an on-time arrival at the gate. Some could be suddenly curtailed, others extended.</p>
        <p>Whenever you're just a few miles shy of a goal, it pays to call the frequent flier desk of the airline in question for details of its current offerings or tie-ins.</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
