<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="751388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DD173AF934A15750C0A963958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHORT CUTS SUSPECTED ON PIPELINE</p>
        <p>The $695 million Iroquois pipeline is the Northeast's most bountiful source of energy in decades, winding 375 miles from the Canadian border across the heart of New York through western Connecticut and into central Long Island, delivering fuel to heat 2.7 million homes. But four years after the project was completed, Federal prosecutors, landowners and several of the very contractors who built the pipeline are questioning whether a rushed job took short cuts with safety, creating a time bomb somewhere along the pipeline. A1. POLICE ARREST 296 AT A COCKFIGHT</p>
        <p>Heavily armed police officers and agents of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals crashed into an old movie theater in the Bronx, seized 296 people and scores of caged and bloody roosters and shut down what had been billed as a national championship cockfight. The raid -- the largest in the 129-year history of the A.S.P.C.A. -- followed two months of undercover investigations that tracked preparations for an event that had kicked off the 1995 cockfighting season in New York City and brought hundreds of spectators and fighting cocks from all over New York State, as well as New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Puerto Rico. A1. NEW YORK CITY  QUESTIONS ARISE IN A YOUTH'S DEATH</p>
        <p>The police said 16-year-old Yong Xin Huang was shot and killed during a struggle with an officer on Friday when the officer's gun accidently discharged. But a friend of Mr. Huang said that the teen-ager did not resist and that the shooting was not accidental. The two starkly different versions emerged as the police and the family struggled to find out what really happened Friday morning in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn. One thing both agreed on was that Mr. Huang was carrying a carbon dioxide-powered Grossman Air Pistol, which resembles a real weapon, outside a friend's house. B3. BOY, 7, IS STRUCK AND KILLED IN CAR CRASH</p>
        <p>Seven white candles burned at the front stoop of 192 Nagle Avenue in the Inwood section of Manhattan. They marked the spot where Varness Vargas, 7, died when an Oldsmobile station wagon smashed into two parked cars, jumped a curb and struck the boy early Saturday night. The police still have an incomplete picture of the events that ended with the boy's death. B4. REGION  A SHOWDOWN ON LOBBYING BILL</p>
        <p>A two-year campaign by business and construction trade groups to undercut the lobbying activities of a student-based advocacy organization is heading for a showdown. A bill to change the way Rutgers University students contribute to the organization, the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group, is in position for a vote in the Senate. Its sponsor predicts that the vote there will be as close as the one in the State Assembly, which recently approved the measure. B5. CASTING NETS FOR SURPLUS FUNDS</p>
        <p>New Jersey's boarding house rental assistance fund has $20 million in its account but few applicants for the boarding house improvements it supports, so Governor Whitman will divert half the money to her new urban housing program. She has also grabbed $50 million from the state's unemployment insurance fund that had been destined for a health insurance program that still has not been put into place. And the Governor is looking hungrily at the $125 million reserve that the Hackensack Meadowlands Development Commission draws on to maintain the giant, inactive landfill there. B5. CHEMICAL FIRE ERUPTS IN WAREHOUSE</p>
        <p>A chemical fire spewing hazardous fumes in a warehouse in Hackensack, N.J., forced several dozen people from their homes Saturday night and burned for more than 24 hours before firefighters extinguished it, officials said. The fire began around 7 P.M. in a one-story warehouse at the CWD Transport Company, a trucking concern at 55 Devoe Street. More than 60 firefighters battled the blaze, and 16 suffered minor injuries and smoke inhalation. B4. BODY MAY BE LINKED TO PAROLED KILLER</p>
        <p>A badly decomposed body discovered yesterday in Rockland County is believed to be another victim of a paroled murderer who has been charged with killing one woman and raping another since his release. B5. Chronicle B4</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHORT CUTS SUSPECTED ON PIPELINE</p>
        <p>The $695 million Iroquois pipeline is the Northeast's most bountiful source of energy in decades, winding 375 miles from the Canadian border across the heart of New York through western Connecticut and into central Long Island, delivering fuel to heat 2.7 million homes. But four years after the project was completed, Federal prosecutors, landowners and several of the very contractors who built the pipeline are questioning whether a rushed job took short cuts with safety, creating a time bomb somewhere along the pipeline. A1. POLICE ARREST 296 AT A COCKFIGHT</p>
        <p>Heavily armed police officers and agents of the American Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals crashed into an old movie theater in the Bronx, seized 296 people and scores of caged and bloody roosters and shut down what had been billed as a national championship cockfight. The raid -- the largest in the 129-year history of the A.S.P.C.A. -- followed two months of undercover investigations that tracked preparations for an event that had kicked off the 1995 cockfighting season in New York City and brought hundreds of spectators and fighting cocks from all over New York State, as well as New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Puerto Rico. A1. NEW YORK CITY  QUESTIONS ARISE IN A YOUTH'S DEATH</p>
        <p>The police said 16-year-old Yong Xin Huang was shot and killed during a struggle with an officer on Friday when the officer's gun accidently discharged. But a friend of Mr. Huang said that the teen-ager did not resist and that the shooting was not accidental. The two starkly different versions emerged as the police and the family struggled to find out what really happened Friday morning in Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn. One thing both agreed on was that Mr. Huang was carrying a carbon dioxide-powered Grossman Air Pistol, which resembles a real weapon, outside a friend's house. B3. BOY, 7, IS STRUCK AND KILLED IN CAR CRASH</p>
        <p>Seven white candles burned at the front stoop of 192 Nagle Avenue in the Inwood section of Manhattan. They marked the spot where Varness Vargas, 7, died when an Oldsmobile station wagon smashed into two parked cars, jumped a curb and struck the boy early Saturday night. The police still have an incomplete picture of the events that ended with the boy's death. B4. REGION  A SHOWDOWN ON LOBBYING BILL</p>
        <p>A two-year campaign by business and construction trade groups to undercut the lobbying activities of a student-based advocacy organization is heading for a showdown. A bill to change the way Rutgers University students contribute to the organization, the New Jersey Public Interest Research Group, is in position for a vote in the Senate. Its sponsor predicts that the vote there will be as close as the one in the State Assembly, which recently approved the measure. B5. CASTING NETS FOR SURPLUS FUNDS</p>
        <p>New Jersey's boarding house rental assistance fund has $20 million in its account but few applicants for the boarding house improvements it supports, so Governor Whitman will divert half the money to her new urban housing program. She has also grabbed $50 million from the state's unemployment insurance fund that had been destined for a health insurance program that still has not been put into place. And the Governor is looking hungrily at the $125 million reserve that the Hackensack Meadowlands Development Commission draws on to maintain the giant, inactive landfill there. B5. CHEMICAL FIRE ERUPTS IN WAREHOUSE</p>
        <p>A chemical fire spewing hazardous fumes in a warehouse in Hackensack, N.J., forced several dozen people from their homes Saturday night and burned for more than 24 hours before firefighters extinguished it, officials said. The fire began around 7 P.M. in a one-story warehouse at the CWD Transport Company, a trucking concern at 55 Devoe Street. More than 60 firefighters battled the blaze, and 16 suffered minor injuries and smoke inhalation. B4. BODY MAY BE LINKED TO PAROLED KILLER</p>
        <p>A badly decomposed body discovered yesterday in Rockland County is believed to be another victim of a paroled murderer who has been charged with killing one woman and raping another since his release. B5. Chronicle B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
