<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE FIFTH DOWN</title>
    <meta content="01fifth" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E2DE133FF932A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE FIFTH DOWN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Das, Benjamin Hoffman, Naila-Jean Meyers, Toni Monkovic and John Woods</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Questions at Quarterback</p>
        <p>Chiefs Coach HermAN Edwards is a firm believer that a player does not lose his starting job to injury, but in the case of quarterback Trent Green he may want to make an exception.</p>
        <p>In Green's stead, Damon Huard, above, has not only performed well -- a quarterback rating of 97.0 or above in five of seven games and seven touchdowns in his past five starts -- but he has improved as the season has progressed. He has reeled off consecutive wins with strong performances against the formidable Chargers and Seahawks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Questions at Quarterback</p>
        <p>Chiefs Coach HermAN Edwards is a firm believer that a player does not lose his starting job to injury, but in the case of quarterback Trent Green he may want to make an exception.</p>
        <p>In Green's stead, Damon Huard, above, has not only performed well -- a quarterback rating of 97.0 or above in five of seven games and seven touchdowns in his past five starts -- but he has improved as the season has progressed. He has reeled off consecutive wins with strong performances against the formidable Chargers and Seahawks.</p>
        <p>A 20-13 loss at Oakland on Sunday left the Super Bowl champion Steelers and the moribund Raiders with identical 2-5 records and similar problems at quarterback.</p>
        <p>Ben Roethlisberger of the Steelers sounded disgusted with himself -- ''In my wildest dreams, I didn't think I'd be playing this bad'' -- after 4 interceptions pushed his total to 11 in five and a half games. But Andrew Walter of the Raiders was worse.</p>
        <p>Walter completed 5 of his 14 attempts, meaning Raiders receivers had only one more catch than Raiders defenders. ''Personally, it was ridiculous,'' said Walter, whose passer rating (17.3) matched his team's net passing yardage (17).</p>
        <p>Dear Old I.S.U.</p>
        <p>Quarterbacks Seneca Wallace and Sage Rosenfels were calling the shots Sunday, the first time that two Iowa State graduates have done that at the same time in N.F.L. history. Both had solid games, but not enough to win. In his first start, the fourth-year veteran Wallace had 198 passing yards and 3 touchdowns in the Seahawks' 35-28 loss to the Chiefs. And Rosenfels, who has started only twice in his six seasons, replaced the Texans' David Carr in the second half of a 28-22 loss to the Titans and passed for 186 yards and 3 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Jangled in Jacksonville</p>
        <p>Is there a more puzzling team at the midpoint of the season than the Jacksonville Jaguars?</p>
        <p>After opening the season with impressive victories against the Cowboys and the Steelers and a close loss to the still-undefeated Colts, the Jaguars have been like Jekyll and Hyde. They lost at Washington, now 2-5, in overtime in Week 4, then overwhelmed the Jets at home by 41-0. After their bye, the Jaguars had a confounding loss to the Texans, also 2-5. They followed that with a road victory over the Eagles, who were then 4-2.</p>
        <p>A rash of injuries on defense have contributed to the inconsistency. With two losses already to teams that are 2-5, the Jaguars next play the 2-5 Titans, who have a modest two-game winning streak. Which Jaguars will show up?</p>
        <p>Seattle Not Gaining</p>
        <p>The Seahawks were missing five offensive starters against the Chiefs on Sunday -- quarterback, running back, receiver, guard and tackle -- but gamely rallied to take the lead in the fourth quarter before losing, 35-28.</p>
        <p>Some saw that as a moral victory, coming a week after a knee injury put quarterback Matt Hasselbeck on the bench beside Shaun Alexander (foot). Coach Mike Holmgren, below, was not among them. The Seahawks are 1-3 since Alexander broke a bone in his foot in September, and with two regulars missing from the offensive line Sunday, Seattle rushed for a paltry 47 yards. ''Right now, we can't run worth a darn,'' Holmgren said.</p>
        <p>But optimism for a return to the Super Bowl is not lost. Seattle (4-3) is tied for first place with St. Louis (4-3) in the National Football Conference West, and Alexander is expected back for a Nov. 12 game against the Rams.</p>
        <p>Boom and Bust</p>
        <p>Fantasy football drafts allow fans to experience the agony of a Bobby Beathard (chose Ryan Leaf No. 2 over all) and the satisfaction of a Bill Walsh (chose Joe Montana in the third round).</p>
        <p>But it's the failures that tend to linger, and running backs have generally been disappointing this season.</p>
        <p>Biggest Busts</p>
        <p>LaMont Jordan, Raiders running back: Caught in Oakland's downward spiral, Jordan, who is now nursing a back injury, has rushed for only 335 yards and a touchdown.</p>
        <p>Edgerrin James, Cardinals running back: Has received plenty of carries (185), but has not done much with them -- 3 touchdowns and 516 yards rushing -- behind Arizona's soft offensive line.</p>
        <p>Carnell Williams, Buccaneers running back: Built his reputation on his opening three-game total of 434 yards as a rookie last year, but has been barely above average since.</p>
        <p>Shaun Alexander, Seahawks running back: After slow starts, LaDainian Tomlinson and Larry Johnson have justified their high selections. Alexander, the other member of the Big Three, has been hurt. But even before his foot injury, he was held to 187 yards rushing in three games.</p>
        <p>Best Picks</p>
        <p>Donovan McNabb, Eagles quarterback: The runaway scoring leader in almost any fantasy format. His average position in ESPN live drafts was No. 36, partly because it was thought he lacked elite wide receivers after Terrell Owens's departure.</p>
        <p>Michael Vick, above, Falcons quarterback: His average draft position was 86th in ESPN live drafts, yet he ranks fifth among ESPN scoring leaders. In the past two games, he has seven touchdown passes.</p>
        <p>Brian Westbrook, Eagles running back, and Reggie Brown, Eagles wide receiver: The two have been beneficiaries of Philadelphia's resurgence under McNabb.</p>
        <p>Marques Colston, Saints wide receiver: When he arrived as a rookie, it was not clear whether he would be a tight end or a wideout, but he has been an off-the-charts success. He was not listed in the USA Today Sports Weekly preseason fantasy football guide but now he ranks 21st among ESPN scoring leaders.</p>
        <p>Extra Points</p>
        <p>Penalties may not be as good an indicator of performance as some coaches suggest. Arizona has committed the most this season (60); Cleveland has the fewest (24). The Cardinals are 1-7, the Browns 2-5.  The only kickers in the N.F.L. who have not missed a field goal also play for the only undefeated teams. They are Robbie Gould (20 of 20) of the Bears and Adam Vinatieri (14 of 14) of the Colts.  For the third consecutive week, a team won without scoring a touchdown on offense. The Raiders defeated the Steelers, 20-13, on the strength of two field goals and two interceptions returned for touchdowns. Last week, the Buccaneers (three field goals and two picks) upset the Eagles, 23-21, and the Bears (two fumbles and a punt) defeated the Cardinals, 24-23, two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL The Fifth Down's contributors are Andrew Das, Benjamin Hoffman, Naila-Jean Meyers, Toni Monkovic and John Woods.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">The Fifth Down's contributors are Andrew Das, Benjamin Hoffman, Naila-Jean Meyers, Toni Monkovic and John Woods.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
