<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Cracks Down As Fish Stocks Decline</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="655743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD133AF930A25751C1A965958260" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Cracks Down As Fish Stocks Decline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been 17 years since Congress passed the Magnuson Fishery Conservation and Management Act, regulations intended to reverse the steep decline in the catches of the nation's fishing industry. But the slide continues.</p>
        <p>Although the law imposed strict catch limits and shortened fishing seasons and all but banished foreign trawlers from American waters, fish stocks off every coast are under more pressure than ever from bigger and more efficient boats and nets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been 17 years since Congress passed the Magnuson Fishery Conservation and Management Act, regulations intended to reverse the steep decline in the catches of the nation's fishing industry. But the slide continues.</p>
        <p>Although the law imposed strict catch limits and shortened fishing seasons and all but banished foreign trawlers from American waters, fish stocks off every coast are under more pressure than ever from bigger and more efficient boats and nets.</p>
        <p>Fisheries regulators, whipsawed by economic, environmental and political interests, are constantly struggling to minimize overfishing and, at the same time, maximize returns for boats and crews.</p>
        <p>Worried about the outcome of this struggle, Congress has again stepped in and mandated still more fishing restrictions. In a last-minute vote before Thanksgiving adjournment, the lawmakers ordered a new set of rules imposing stricter limits and shorter seasons.  Focus on Atlantic</p>
        <p>An important difference in the new legislation is that it focuses not on the deep offshore waters regulated by the Magnuson Act but instead on shallow inshore waters, specifically the shoreline waters of the Atlantic coast that once teemed with fish. Many of the details of the new regulations will be decided by a compact of representatives of the Atlantic Coast states from Maine to Florida.</p>
        <p>For the short term, as the new rules take effect, the fishing situation for many recreational and commercial fishermen will probably get worse before it gets better. The tighter limits and shorter seasons will mean even less opportunity for weekend anglers and even less money for already hard-pressed trawler owners and their crews. But if stocks rebound, the fun and the good times will return.</p>
        <p>Can they rebound?</p>
        <p>"The statistics are alarming," says Representative Gerry E. Studds of Massachusetts, chairman of the House Merchant Marine and Fisheries Committee.</p>
        <p>Along the Atlantic Coast, the weakfish catch has fallen 85 percent since 1980, the summer flounder catch has fallen 70 percent since 1989, and the decline in landings of cod and haddock has left the New England fishing fleet foundering in economic woe.</p>
        <p>In the Gulf, red snapper flourishes only in areas where wrecks prevent trawling.</p>
        <p>On the Pacific Coast, there are still salmon, perch and bass to be had. But in many cases, particularly outside Alaska, now the nation's most productive fishing region, stocks exist only because hatcheries are producing fingerlings. Widespread Overfishing</p>
        <p>"The nation's fisheries are at a crossroads," Diana H. Josephson, a top fisheries official in the National Ocean and Atmospheric Administration, recently told Congress.</p>
        <p>Ms. Josephson said that 67 of the 236 species tracked by Federal scientists were being overfished and that 61 other species were being harvested to capacity. Some species have become so scarce, she noted, that the fishing season for them opens and closes on the same day.</p>
        <p>"We can do better," Ms. Josephson asserted.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic's shoreline, where the new Congressional action was focused, was once home to great schools of weakfish, sea trout, black sea bass, flounder, blues, spot, croaker, shad and herring. But in recent years, many species have become extremely scarce, partly because of pollution and unfavorable weather, but mainly because of overfishing.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, East Coast recreational anglers have found themselves returning to dock with only a small fish or two in the cooler. And, just as many offshore Atlantic fishermen did in earlier years, many inshore commercial fishermen are now looking for jobs on land or have started trawling for sharks and other fish that previously were considered inedible nuisances.</p>
        <p>"The stock of virtually every fish species on the East Coast is in terrible condition," said John H. Dunnigan, the executive director of the Atlantic States Marine Fisheries Commission, an interstate compact that Congress authorized a half-century ago to draw up and administer rules for Atlantic coastal fishing. Stronger Enforcement</p>
        <p>While the aim of the new inshore regulations will be much the same as the older offshore regulations -- to halt overfishing and give fish stocks time to rebuild -- there is more.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, it has been the states, rather than the Federal Government, that have regulated fishing in waters extending up to three miles from their coastlines. They have consulted and cooperated with each other, but some states have nevertheless been more lax than others in regulating.</p>
        <p>Given that many Atlantic fish migrate, the disparity in enforcement takes on added importance.</p>
        <p>The new Congressional mandate calls for the states to continue to consult with each other and to define common limits and seasons on various fish species. But to insure that enforcement is uniform, if a state refuses to go along with a particular restriction, the Federal Government will step in and declare a moratorium on the affected fish in that state.</p>
        <p>"This provision gives the law real teeth and that will make all the difference in the world," said William J. Goldsborough, a fisheries expert for the Chesapeake Bay Foundation, a nonprofit conservation organization. "The only other time we've had that was with the striped bass law, and it's one of the great fish-recovery stories."</p>
        <p>Striped bass had all but disappeared from the Chesapeake Bay and the Atlantic when, in the early 1980's, Congress pressured the East Coast states to impose strict fishing limits and, in some cases, fishing moratoriums. Federal agencies were authorized to step in and impose controls on states that refused to act.</p>
        <p>There was almost universal compliance, and today striped bass are back in the bay and the Atlantic in large numbers and recreational and commercial fishermen are once more enjoying good -- though strictly regulated -- catches.</p>
        <p>"There's no reason now why the same thing can't happen to shad and weakfish and blues and all the other depleted Atlantic coast species," Mr. Goldsborough said. Voicing Doubts</p>
        <p>Robert West, a commercial fisherman from Buxton, on North Carolina's Outer Banks, has his doubts. So does his wife, Susan, who recently sent a letter to Congress warning that "devastating" consequences might result from tighter limits on coastal fishing.</p>
        <p>"When it comes to fish," Mr. West said recently between forays into the wintry Atlantic, "our experience has been that government, especially the Federal Government, usually ends up doing more harm than good.</p>
        <p>"First they said they were going to rebuild all the fish stocks way out to sea," he said. "It hasn't happened. Now they say they're going to rebuild all the inshore stocks. Any reasonable person knows that something has to be done to conserve fish. But this time, with all these new rules, I fear they're going to break us all."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
