<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sadly Loping Along, With Brief Snatches of Euphoria</title>
    <meta content="03GREE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1006920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0D8173AF930A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sadly Loping Along, With Brief Snatches of Euphoria</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Neil Greenberg and his four 'impressively acute' dancers; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neil Greenberg has claimed a spot for himself in American modern dance of the 1990's by imaginatively addressing the vast subject of time. His odd vocabulary of movement -- loping, galumphing, looping and sequences of steps called triplets -- has become a personal style. But there was a distracting lack of clarity to the trilogy, the first of two programs, that Mr. Greenberg presented on Tuesday night at Playhouse 91.</p>
        <p>In the 1997 ''Part Three (My Fair Lady),'' Mr. Greenberg and his four impressively acute dancers move to snatches of music from ''My Fair Lady'' and even briefer bursts of Judy Garland, interspersed with silence. The dancers' happily unfurling upper bodies and Michael Stiller's sudden floods of light hint at an approximation of big-blast Broadway fantasy and the pleasure of dancing to that music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Neil Greenberg has claimed a spot for himself in American modern dance of the 1990's by imaginatively addressing the vast subject of time. His odd vocabulary of movement -- loping, galumphing, looping and sequences of steps called triplets -- has become a personal style. But there was a distracting lack of clarity to the trilogy, the first of two programs, that Mr. Greenberg presented on Tuesday night at Playhouse 91.</p>
        <p>In the 1997 ''Part Three (My Fair Lady),'' Mr. Greenberg and his four impressively acute dancers move to snatches of music from ''My Fair Lady'' and even briefer bursts of Judy Garland, interspersed with silence. The dancers' happily unfurling upper bodies and Michael Stiller's sudden floods of light hint at an approximation of big-blast Broadway fantasy and the pleasure of dancing to that music.</p>
        <p>The mood turns darker and the choreography more mainstream, filled with calligraphically angling bodies and a much heavier use of weight, in the 1997 ''Part Three (Judy Garland),'' set to snatches of Garland. Suzanne Gallo's black shirts and tights wittily recall Garland's look. But what does Mr. Greenberg mean to communicate beside vague sadness?</p>
        <p>His new ''Part Three (Luck)'' updates the audience on his own and the company's life after his signature 1994 ''Not-About-AIDS Dance.''</p>
        <p>We learn, through his trademark projected phrases, that Mr. Greenberg, who is HIV-positive, is doing better and that Ellen Barnaby, a dancer of special delicacy and steely strength, is leaving the group. Here and throughout the evening, the dancers sit staring out into the audience, an attempt, presumably, to bring viewers even more into the piece.</p>
        <p>The movement is subtler here, with handsome juxtapositions of bodies. But the point is still blurred. Mr. Greenberg may be aiming at a kind of faux-naif quality or deconstruction. But the extra-dance information does not ''help the pure dance read more strongly,'' as Mr. Greenberg described his intentions in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, one tends to come away from dances by the supposedly impenetrable Merce Cunningham, with whom Mr. Greenberg once performed, with a much stronger sense of whom one has been watching.</p>
        <p>The company, which also includes Christopher Batenhorst, Justine Lynch and Paige Martin, will perform through Sunday at Playhouse 91, at 316 East 91st Street in Manhattan, as the closing event in the 92d Street Y Harkness Dance Project festival.  DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
