<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Governor Finds Himself In a Struggle for Survival</title>
    <meta content="Y28MAR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: MARYLAND"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glendening, Parris N (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sauerbrey, Ellen R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Molotsky, Irvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDF113CF93BA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Governor Finds Himself In a Struggle for Survival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRVIN MOLOTSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Molotsky, Irvin</byline>
      <dateline>BETHESDA, Md., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maryland Gov Parris N Glendening, moderate-to-liberal Democrat in one of nation's most reliably Democratic states, is struggling for political survival against Republican candidate, Ellen R Sauerbrey, who he defeated by less than 6,000 votes in 1994, even though he has presided over state that has prospered more than most in strong national economy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By most ordinary reckoning, Parris N. Glendening should be a shoo-in as he seeks re-election as Governor of Maryland.</p>
        <p>He is a moderate-to-liberal Democrat in one of the nation's most reliably Democratic states. He has presided over a state that has prospered more than most in the strong national economy. And he has been endorsed by the leading newspapers in the state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By most ordinary reckoning, Parris N. Glendening should be a shoo-in as he seeks re-election as Governor of Maryland.</p>
        <p>He is a moderate-to-liberal Democrat in one of the nation's most reliably Democratic states. He has presided over a state that has prospered more than most in the strong national economy. And he has been endorsed by the leading newspapers in the state.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Glendening is in the race of his life, an election that seems even closer than the one in 1994, when he won by fewer than 6,000 votes, or four-tenths of 1 percent, over the Republican candidate, Ellen R. Sauerbrey, who is his opponent again this year.</p>
        <p>With a week to go before the Nov. 3 election, Mr. Glendening is at a loss to explain why the race is so close, although some analysts suggest the reasons include a subtle shift in the state's once staunchly liberal leaning and the Governor's indecision over whether to embrace or shun President Clinton during the height of the Monica Lewinsky scandal.</p>
        <p>A Washington Post poll found that among people who say they are certain to vote, 50 percent favor Mrs. Sauerbrey and 49 percent Mr. Glendening, a statistical dead heat.</p>
        <p>''We had the most bitter primary,'' the Governor said at a campaign stop here in vote-rich Montgomery County, just outside Washington, as he searched for an explanation for the closeness of the race. ''We've taken on the tobacco lobby, the National Rifle Association, the casino and slot industry. Your enemies remember more than your friends do.''</p>
        <p>But the issues he offered as reasons for his poor poll showing have been used successfully by candidates in states considered less liberal and less Democratic than Maryland.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sauerbrey, on the other hand, has several possible explanations as to why she, a conservative Republican, is doing so well in the polls and has an excellent chance of being elected Maryland's first Republican governor in 32 years.</p>
        <p>''The 1994 election showed that Maryland is not as liberal as everybody thought,'' Mrs. Sauerbrey said as she also campaigned in Montgomery County, which she does not expect to carry but where she hopes to reduce Mr. Glendening's majority. ''There has been a net gain for the Republican Party.''</p>
        <p>Statistics at the Maryland Board of Elections confirm that. From August 1994 to last August, the Democrats increased their enrollment in the state to 1,459,760, a gain of 25,854. But the Republicans, starting with a smaller base, did better, rising to 767,391, an increase of 92,331. So the Republicans had a net gain of more than 66,000 over the Democrats.</p>
        <p>Eric M. Uslaner, a professor of government and politics at the University of Maryland, said Mr. Glendening had failed to build on his popularity because of some early decisions that were not popular throughout the state.</p>
        <p>One was state support for the construction of a new football stadium for the transplanted Cleveland Browns, now the Baltimore Ravens. It was partly financed by the state lottery and, Mr. Uslaner said: ''People thought that some of that money should have gone into education. It was especially opposed in Montgomery County.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Uslaner was asked in an interview whether Mr. Glendening's seeming aloofness, verging on dullness, had contributed to his lack of a strengthened base. In its editorial endorsing the Governor for re-election, The Baltimore Sun said politely, ''He is not charismatic.'' The Washington Post, which also endorsed him, said Mr. Glendening had a ''plodding personality.''</p>
        <p>''It's more than just dull,'' Mr. Uslaner said. ''He doesn't connect well with the voters. He was a professor. Some of us just don't make great political candidates, and being from a one-party area, he cut his teeth in an old-fashioned machine, where loyalty to a party can be more important than establishing a rapport with a large number of voters.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glendening, 56, taught political science at the University of Maryland for 27 years before he was elected Governor. He was previously on the Prince George's County Council and served as the County Executive, working his way up through the ranks until being elected Governor.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Sauerbrey, 61, lives in Baltimore County, the suburb outside the city, and taught biology in high school before being elected to the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>In the 1994 election, Mr. Glendening carried only the three most populous areas in the state: Montgomery and Prince George's Counties, both Washington suburbs, and Baltimore. Mrs. Sauerbrey carried all other voting districts, but they did not provide enough votes to overcome Mr. Glendening's big margins in the areas he carried.</p>
        <p>The Governor's campaign has not been a smooth one.</p>
        <p>For a long time, the two leading elected black officials in the state -- the Prince George's County Executive, Wayne K. Curry, and the Mayor of Baltimore, Kurt L. Schmoke, both Democrats -- put off endorsing the Governor.</p>
        <p>When they did, on Oct. 8, less than a month before the election, they did it without much enthusiasm and without even notifying Mr. Glendening that they were doing it. Mr. Glendening badly needs the black vote to carry the state, and both Prince George's and Baltimore are predominantly black.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glendening's biggest problem involved President Clinton. Mr. Glendening sought in September to distance himself from the President over the Lewinsky scandal by canceling a fund-raising event with him and then did not show up at a visit by Mr. Clinton to a school in Montgomery County. But later Mr. Clinton campaigned for the Governor -- again in Montgomery County -- and the two were reconciled.</p>
        <p>Asked about his reversal in an interview, Mr. Glendening said: ''We did what we believed to be right. The President has done a great job. However, his actions were wrong and he should have apologized. Then he did apologize. He asked for forgiveness. Not one of us has not made mistakes.''</p>
        <p>Had he made a mistake as great as the President?</p>
        <p>''No,'' Mr. Glendening said. ''Not a doozy of a mistake.''  THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: MARYLAND</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
