<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Parade, Immigrants Bask in El Duque's Glory</title>
    <meta content="28DUQU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Union City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Maria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Orlando</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cuban-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E7D6103CF93BA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Parade, Immigrants Bask in El Duque's Glory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIA NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Maria</byline>
      <dateline>UNION CITY, N.J., Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Parade held, Union City, NJ, to honor New York Yankees pitcher Orlando Hernandez; large Cuban community revels in Hernandez's success following his escape from Cuba; city's Latin American officials comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a day for pride, more than for politics, when Orlando (El Duque) Hernandez, the Yankee pitcher, paraded down Bergenline Avenue here today, in the heart of Cuban and Hispanic New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But for many of those lining the bustling commercial strip, waving Yankee banners and Cuban flags, El Duque's story, his escape from Cuba on a raft and his success as a World Series pitcher 10 months later, represented a bigger-than-life version of their own immigrant experiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a day for pride, more than for politics, when Orlando (El Duque) Hernandez, the Yankee pitcher, paraded down Bergenline Avenue here today, in the heart of Cuban and Hispanic New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But for many of those lining the bustling commercial strip, waving Yankee banners and Cuban flags, El Duque's story, his escape from Cuba on a raft and his success as a World Series pitcher 10 months later, represented a bigger-than-life version of their own immigrant experiences.</p>
        <p>''The Yankees play in the House That Ruth Built,'' said Rudy Garcia, Union City's Mayor, who is also a Cuban immigrant. ''But today he is coming to the Street That Immigrants Built, Bergenline Avenue.''</p>
        <p>Union City and the surrounding towns across the Hudson River from New York City have the largest concentration of Cubans outside of Miami, as the Mayor likes to point out, and they have become a magnet for immigrants from other Latin American countries like Mexico, Ecuador, El Salvador and Nicaragua. An estimated 70 percent of the population of Union City and West New York is Hispanic, and along Bergenline Avenue, businesses with names like Gonzalez H.S. Fabrics and Mi Bandera Restaurant, owned by Hispanic immigrants, have produced an economic boom in the area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia said he was originally going to offer Mr. Hernandez the keys to the city, but somehow that didn't seem enough in an area where people felt he was one of their own.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we feel a great deal of pride in El Duque,'' Mr. Garcia said. So he and Mayor Albio Sires of West New York, also from Cuba, decided to give Mr. Hernandez a parade.</p>
        <p>''He exemplifies two virtues important to the Cuban community,'' Mr. Garcia said. ''One is his love of freedom. He risked his life to get out of Cuba on a raft. Two is his love of family. A lot of Cubans are separated from their families and it is a result of Fidel Castro's tyranny.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia was referring to El Duque's two daughters, his mother and his former wife, who were allowed to leave Cuba by Mr. Castro after the intercession of John Cardinal O'Connor and others. The family has a 30-day visa, but officials are working to extend their stay.</p>
        <p>Some who lined the 30-block route along Bergenline Avenue -- the police estimated that the crowd, which was packed several deep at some points, grew to 5,000 -- waited more than two hours in the gray afternoon. When Mr. Hernandez finally came by, in a float decorated in white with Yankee blue trim that practically flew down the street, they barely caught a glimpse of him and his family. But no matter. They beamed and cheered nonetheless.</p>
        <p>''He's a Hispanic who is trying to move the community forward,'' said Lorena Fuentes, who is from Guatemala. ''It's nice to have someone represent us. He's a man everyone admires because he brought his family here.'' As Mr. Hernandez's float passed, followed by limousines full of dignitaries, cheering people crowded around and ran after it.</p>
        <p>The parade drew teen-agers, grade-school children and older people. Many knew that El Duque's half-brother, Livan Hernandez, also defected from Cuba and joined the Florida Marlins in time to help them win the World Series last year.</p>
        <p>But like many heroes, El Duque has already been mythologized to the point where some versions of his story were not backed by facts.</p>
        <p>''He came here to play for the Yankees to get enough money to get his brother out of jail,'' said Mrs. Fuentes's son, Carlos, 10, who wore a Yankee hat and shirt.</p>
        <p>Yasser Warrad, 14, pedaled several blocks on his Dino racing bicycle from his home to Bergenline Avenue, carrying his half-brother, Carlos Pico, 12. Both of them are from Puerto Rico, they said.</p>
        <p>''It's illegal to go on a boat from Cuba,'' said Carlos, awed by El Duque's story. ''I'm glad they let his family come.''</p>
        <p>A sign atop a blue Chevrolet station wagon spoke for many in the crowd. It said, in English and in Spanish, ''To El Duque: God Bless You, Your Family, the Yankees, and God Bless America.''</p>
        <p>''I am a grand fanatic when it comes to the Yankees,'' said Leonardo Gutierrez, 53, from Puerto Rico, a Hudson County employee who made the sign. ''I am a fan of El Duque because he brought his family over. That is a beautiful thing.''</p>
        <p>Aymara Watson, who came to North Bergen from Cuba in 1995, said she remembered seeing Mr. Hernandez pitch at Latin American Stadium in Havana before she left the country.</p>
        <p>''He was a real loss to Cuba,'' she said. ''But for us it is such a thing of pride, and in such a short time.''</p>
        <p>In Cuba, she said, everyone suffered economically, even champion athletes like Mr. Hernandez. ''He probably earned enough to buy his girls one pair of nice shoes each, but he probably still had to stand in line for the bodegas like everyone else.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Hernandez flew by on his float, Enio Martinez, 67, watched quietly, a Yankee cap on his head and his hands in his pockets. Mr. Martinez said that when he was a restaurant owner in Cuba in the 50's, he traveled to New York just to watch a Yankees game. After Mr. Castro took over, Mr. Martinez became disillusioned ''with the new regime,'' as he called it, and worked in the sugar cane fields for two years to earn permission to leave the country.</p>
        <p>''I lost everything in Cuba,'' he said. The government had taken over his business and expropriated his home. He was allowed to leave with his wife and two children. But he never saw his mother again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martinez reflected on Mr. Hernandez's quick success in the United States, and he and his daughter, Mercedes Blanco, laughed when they could not remember whether the Yankee pitcher made $6 million or $9 million.</p>
        <p>''By coming here, he won something even bigger,'' Mr. Martinez said. ''His liberty.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
