<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gay Church Sues TV Station For Rejecting an Infomercial</title>
    <meta content="Y28GAY$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cathedral of Hope</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WGN-TV (Chicago)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D8103CF93BA15753C1A96E958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gay Church Sues TV Station For Rejecting an Infomercial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cathedral of Hope, nation's largest gay and lesbian church, suesWGN-TV, Chicago television station for allegedly breaking agreement to broadcast infomercial produced by church because it considered advertisement, aimed at reaching out to lesbian and gay teenagers, too controversial (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation's largest gay and lesbian church filed suit today against a Chicago television station, accusing the station of breaking its agreement to broadcast an infomercial produced by the church because the station considered the advertisement too controversial.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the church, the Cathedral of Hope in Dallas, believe the station, WGN-TV, which is seen nationally when it is fed by satellite to cable systems around the country, rejected the infomercial ''based on their views that this is not appropriate content for those stations,'' said a lawyer for the church, Christopher Wolf. ''I think those are code words for homophobia and for antigay discrimination.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nation's largest gay and lesbian church filed suit today against a Chicago television station, accusing the station of breaking its agreement to broadcast an infomercial produced by the church because the station considered the advertisement too controversial.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the church, the Cathedral of Hope in Dallas, believe the station, WGN-TV, which is seen nationally when it is fed by satellite to cable systems around the country, rejected the infomercial ''based on their views that this is not appropriate content for those stations,'' said a lawyer for the church, Christopher Wolf. ''I think those are code words for homophobia and for antigay discrimination.''</p>
        <p>The church, with 2,300 members, spent two years producing the infomercial and tried to market it to national cable stations over the summer. Church officials saw it in part as a counterweight to advertising by conservative Christian groups, including recent full-page newspaper advertisements with people who say they are former homosexuals who ''overcame'' their sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>''We just wanted to make our voice heard against the overwhelming onslaught of people using the media to say how bad gay people are,'' said the pastor, the Rev. Michael Piazza. ''We wanted mostly to reach out to lesbian and gay teen-agers but also people living in rural areas, to tell them there is this possibility that you can be gay and Christian, there is this possibility that you are a child of God.''</p>
        <p>Most of the cable companies the church contacted said no. WGN-TV agreed to broadcast the advertisement, scheduled five showings and accepted a check for the first payment in July, church officials say. Then, church officials said, a week later, WGN canceled the agreement and returned the check.</p>
        <p>Charles J. Sennet, senior counsel for the Tribune Company, which owns WGN-TV, declined to comment on the lawsuit or to explain the network's version of events, saying the company would respond in court. Mr. Sennet suggested the church might not know exactly what happened because church officials did not communicate directly with the station, but used a media buyer, Phil Rozansky, president of Tower Media Advertising, in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rozansky's version of events differs markedly from the church's.</p>
        <p>''I think what they're trying to do is make this a political issue and a slam against gay rights,'' Mr. Rozansky said. ''They are jumping to conclusions and making accusations that are not appropriate and do not logically follow the facts.''</p>
        <p>The 30-minute infomercial begins with a montage of antigay demonstrators and speeches by televangelists. The bulk of the advertisement is devoted to happy church members, both gay and straight, children playing and the church's inclusive philosophy. At the end, Mr. Piazza talks about a gay minister who was so distraught he committed suicide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf, who considers the WGN agreement binding, said that at WGN's suggestion, the church agreed to change the title of the infomercial from ''Holy Homosexuals'' to ''A Cathedral of Hope'' and agreed to blur the image of Pat Robertson, the evangelist, to make his face unrecognizable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rozansky, who said he had mistakenly believed top executives at WGN had signed off on the deal, said there were other ''specific issues within the show that make it inappropriate for airing.''</p>
        <p>''I was working with the ministry to make those adjustments and they told me they were willing to make some of those changes,'' Mr. Rozansky said, ''but then they brought in the lawyers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rozansky said that infomercials that touch on sensitive subjects are routinely turned down by television stations. He said WGN had  turned down paid programming that had ''gay-bashing'' themes.</p>
        <p>He said the other stations, including the Discovery Channel, Black Entertainment Television and Odyssey, had turned the commercial down for varying reasons, including length, religious content and controversial subject matter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
