<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daphne Arnstein; Arts Group Founder In Harlem Was 78</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Obituary" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330870"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARNSTEIN, DAPHNE BARRITT-VANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DE1E31F932A35750C0A966958260" item-length="239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daphne Arnstein; Arts Group Founder In Harlem Was 78</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Daphne Barritt-Vane Arnstein, an arts patron who founded the Harlem Cultural Council and was a co-founder of the Jazzmobile, died of heart disease Saturday in Mount Sinai Hospital. She was 78 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Daphne Barritt-Vane Arnstein, an arts patron who founded the Harlem Cultural Council and was a co-founder of the Jazzmobile, died of heart disease Saturday in Mount Sinai Hospital. She was 78 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Daphne Barritt-Vane Arnstein, an arts patron who founded the Harlem Cultural Council and was a co-founder of the Jazzmobile, died of heart disease Saturday in Mount Sinai Hospital. She was 78 years old and lived in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Arnstein and the pianist and composer Billy Taylor founded the Jazzmobile 25 years ago to bring summer programs of free live music performed by prominent musicians to various New York neighborhoods. She served on the board of Jazzmobile, which also conducts year-round workshops, lectures and demonstrations. For her role in Jazzmobile's creation, Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller presented Mrs. Arnstein with the New York State Council on the Arts Award.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Arnstein also founded Bands of Steel, a music training program; Festival on the River, and Speakeasy, a dialogue between grade school children and the elderly. She served on the jazz council of Local 802 of the American Federation of Musicians and took part in the breakfast feeding program of St. Peter's Lutheran Church.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Arnstein, a native of Tonbridge, England, came to the United States in 1941. She worked for Russian War Relief, became director of the Westchester Chapter of the National Conference of Christians and Jews and president of the Utopia Day Care Center in Harlem.</p>
        <p>Surviving are two sons, Simon, of Baltimore, and Nelson B., of Santa Monica, Calif.; a daughter, Gemma Rettman of Eugene, Ore., and two grandchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
