<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gorbachev and Yeltsin, Tense Allies, Push Union Plan</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SOVIET TURMOIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF1F38F937A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="1758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gorbachev and Yeltsin, Tense Allies, Push Union Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Sept. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and President Boris N. Yeltsin of the Russian federated republic acknowledged differences today but joined together in urging the adoption of a new governing structure for the Soviet Union, based on the resurgent power of its constituent republics.</p>
        <p>Speaking before the national Congress, the two leaders demonstrated once again that their old bitter rivalry has given way to a tense alliance that could be the key to the new shape and composition of the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and President Boris N. Yeltsin of the Russian federated republic acknowledged differences today but joined together in urging the adoption of a new governing structure for the Soviet Union, based on the resurgent power of its constituent republics.</p>
        <p>Speaking before the national Congress, the two leaders demonstrated once again that their old bitter rivalry has given way to a tense alliance that could be the key to the new shape and composition of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>In a speech that blamed Mr. Gorbachev for ceding ground last winter to right-wing forces, Mr. Yeltsin paid the Soviet President a back-handed compliment by saying he had emerged from his three-day ordeal during last month's coup "a different man," who could now be trusted to help lead the country out of its crisis.  [ Excerpts from parliamentary session, pages A14 and A15. ] Fate of the Union</p>
        <p>Both men pinned the fate of the future union on a vote, due Wednesday, on an emergency package that both preserves some form of central government -- with responsibility for the military, foreign affairs and certain undefined economic functions -- while transferring the bulk of the power once held by the Kremlin to the republics.</p>
        <p>Yielding to criticism, Mr. Gorbachev and the republic leaders today amended their plan for a drastic overhaul of the Soviet Government, offering to keep the old Soviet Parliament alive, as a symbol of the continuity between the old Soviet Union and the confederated structure now emerging.</p>
        <p>In an emotional and personal speech, Mr. Gorbachev today urged the 2,000-odd members of the Congress of People's Deputies to act quickly on the emergency package before the political disintregration of the Soviet Union spreads to the economy, disrupting the vital links that still tie its 15 republics together. 'We Are All One'</p>
        <p>Referring to criticism of his position, Mr. Gorbachev said: "Today you have a President. Tomorrow you may have another president. In any case, we are all one, side by side, and we shouldn't spit on one another. This is just my reaction to all of these doubts that have been cast upon my conduct."</p>
        <p>"There are urgent food problems,"he said, "urgent problems connected to the preparation for winter, problems of law enforcement, the financial situation -- all these demand coordinated action."</p>
        <p>"Let me tell you," he said, "the West is watching. If we are able to coordinate, unite within the new forms, find new structures, new people, the West will support us."</p>
        <p>The revised plan, released on the eve of the vote, seemed intended to win support from delegates who had criticized Mr. Gorbachev for usurping their constitutional authority by handing it over to a new Council of Representatives, drawn equally from all Soviet republics. The new formula would preserve the Parliament, and replace one of its chambers with the republic-dominated council. The Congress, the parliament's parent body, is expected either to dissolve itself, or wither away as the last remnant of a dying system. Outcome Believed Uncertain</p>
        <p>A two-thirds majority of the Congress is required for adoption of the emergency package. After the debates on the floor today, some observers were reluctant to predict the outcome of the vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin appealed to the deputies to cede their role, and accept the situation created over the last two weeks when in the aftermath of the failed coup, republic after republic voted to declare independence.</p>
        <p>"We have to agree that, yes, there can be independent republics which insist on confederation, or on a federation, or on associate members, or on an economic union," he said, "but whatever, they should be part of a unified system."</p>
        <p>"It is precisely the republics today which represent the main source for stabilization, " he said, "and a desire to trample or block them will only push the country toward disaster." Russian Assures Neighbors</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin also sought to reassure his critics that the Russian republic, which emerged triumphant after the failed coup, is not bent on imposing its will on its neighbors.</p>
        <p>"The Russian state, having chosen democracy and freedom, will never be an empire, nor an elder brother, or a younger brother," said Mr. Yeltsin. "It will be an equal among equals."</p>
        <p>On the sensitive question of the Soviet Union's nuclear arsenal, more than 80 percent of which is located on Russian territory, Mr. Yeltsin said he would seek a greater voice for his republic on the control of nuclear weapons, but acknowledged that the union's armed forces should be preserved, "with the U.S.S.R.'s nuclear arsenal without fail remaining under the control of the center."</p>
        <p>"For its part, Russia guarantees preservation of the integrity of the armed forces' nuclear potential," he said. "This will not fall either to hawks or to extremists. Special structures are now being devised for this." Nuclear Disarmament Favored</p>
        <p>In an interview with CNN later today, he said he favors a total elimination of nuclear weapons in Russia. "But," he said, "there are other factors involved, i.e. reasonable security. We need parity with other nations, and we need to promote the idea of non-proliferation and extend it to other countries."</p>
        <p>Some delegates today were predicting that the Congress would avoid a scheduled vote on the recognition of the independence of the three Baltic republics, and perhaps other republics that have lately voted to break away from the Soviet Union. They speculated that Mr. Gorbachev might recognize Baltic independence by presidential decree, although a report that he had told this to a delegation from Latvia was denied today by Latvia's representation in Moscow.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Soviet press agency Tass reported today from New York that the Soviet delegation at the United Nations has indicated it will support the membership of all Soviet republics to the United Nations, including Latvia, Estonia and Lithuania. Dispute in Azerbaijan</p>
        <p>But already, the republics' drive for independence has sparked new trouble, as ethnic minorities within some republics began their own secessionist movements. Azerbaijan today angrily denounced the leadership of Nagorno-Karabakh, a mountainous region with an Armenian majority, for trying to secede, declaring the move as "unconstitutional."</p>
        <p>In the Georgian capital, Tbilisi, troops of that republic today fired on demonstrators who were demanding the resignation of President Zviad Gamsakhurdia. Four demonstrators and 21 policemen were wounded in the melee, according to the Georgian president's press service.</p>
        <p>In an interview on Soviet television tonight, Mr. Gamsakhurdia defended the police crackdown. "Not a single democratic government would permit an armed opposition," he said. "They were armed, they shot at policemen. These armed excesses were organized by provacatuers and the enemies of Georgia." Soviet television also reported that warrants for the arrests of three opposition leaders had been issued.</p>
        <p>Tass reported that television broadcasts in the republic had been suspended, as "a tide of rallies" swept Georgia.</p>
        <p>In the desperate serach for a formula that will satisfy the Soviet Union's myriad parts, the authors of the plan now before the Congress quickly adjusted to concerns heard from the floor. Among other complaints were those from representatives of the autonomous republics, ethnic enclaves within the larger Soviet republics, who said they feared their own autonomy would be swallowed up by the jealous republics.</p>
        <p>In the Ukraine, a republic considered critical to the success of new negotiations on the shape of the union, the chairman of the republic's Parliament, Leonid Kravchuk, said he disagreed with some points of the agreement negotiated Sunday night between Mr. Gorbachev and 10 republic leaders, and presented to the national Congress Monday.</p>
        <p>"We disagree, for example, with the idea of some abstract separate center," he said, adding that he would insist that all central bodies be inter-republican. "Otherwise," he said, in remarks clearly aimed at the Russian government, "We shall have what we have now: the closer you are to the center, the more you get."</p>
        <p>In an interview with the news agency Interfax, Levon Ter-Petrosyan, the Armenian president, said a major issue had been removed today when the Soviet Defense Ministry said it would allow each republic to become a single military region, with local military commands answerable both to the republics and to the center. This, he said, represented a "big step forward."</p>
        <p>At the Congress today, Aleksandr Zhuravlyov, a Communist deputy from the republic of Byelorussia, warned against the agreement, which he said would leave the Soivet Union as neither a country, nor a state.</p>
        <p>By voting for the agreement, he told his fellow delegates, "you will cease to be deputies. One cannot be a deputy of a nonexistent state."</p>
        <p>The draft bill distributed today cast some light on the nature of the new governning structures envisioned under the agreement. It proposes the creation of a new State Council, made up of the Soviet president and the leaders of the republics, which in effect would serve as the country's ruling body.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Soviet would continue its existence, but its lawmaking authority would be put in the hands of a newly formed Council of the Republics, made up of 20 representatives from each republic. The Council of the Republics would set procedures for the federal government, approve the appointment of federal ministers and consider inter-republican agreements.</p>
        <p>The second chamber, the Council of the Union, would consider only issues concerning civic rights and freedoms and other issues, which do not fall under th jurisdiction of the upper chamber. Its decisions would have to reviewed by the Council of the Republics.</p>
        <p>Most of those who rose to speak today urged acceptance of the structure, warning that the alternative would be "suicidal," as the Mayor of Leningrad, Anatoly A. Sobchak, said at the end of the day's session.</p>
        <p>Eduard Kozin, a college teacher, from Sumy in the Ukraine, said; "The resignation of the president is the most horrible thing that might happen at the congress."</p>
        <p>"The president of the Soviet Union is extremely necessary today as a coordinator of activities inside the union and as a connecting link to the world community," he said.</p>
        <p>"Besides, this president has the button," said Mr. Kozin. "Giving the button to somebody else might lead to world catastrophe."  SOVIET TURMOIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
