<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Religion and Natural History Clash Among the Ultra-Orthodox</title>
    <meta content="22RABB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/22/science/22rabbi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1658930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yeshivat Lev HaTorah (Israel)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mindlin, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slifkin, Nosson (Rabbi)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mysterious Creature (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Science of Torah, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Camel, the Hare and the Hyrax, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D61E3CF931A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Religion and Natural History Clash Among the Ultra-Orthodox</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Religion and Natural History Clash Among the Ultra-Orthodox</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX MINDLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mindlin, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rabbi Nosson Slifkin, 29-year-old biblical zoology instructor at Yeshivat Lev HaTorah and author, recently had three books banned by group of 23 ultra-Orthodox rabbis because they hold that books take position against literal reading of scripture; books Mysterious Creature, The Science of Torah and The Camel, the Hare and the Hyrax were all banned and subsequently dropped by Slifkin's publisher and distributor; seek to reconcile sacred texts with current scientific knowledge; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was early January when the posters went up in Mea Shearim, Jerusalem's largest ultra-Orthodox neighborhood, and they signaled the start of a bad year for Rabbi Nosson Slifkin.</p>
        <p>Twenty-three ultra-Orthodox rabbis had signed an open letter denouncing the books of Rabbi Slifkin, an ultra-Orthodox Israeli scholar and science writer. The letter read, in part: ''He believes that the world is millions of years old -- all nonsense! -- and many other things that should not be heard and certainly not believed. His books must be kept at a distance and may not be possessed or distributed.'' Rabbi Slifkin, the letter-writers continued, should ''burn all his writings.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is a rhinoceros kosher? Trying to reconcile Jewish Scripture and natural history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was early January when the posters went up in Mea Shearim, Jerusalem's largest ultra-Orthodox neighborhood, and they signaled the start of a bad year for Rabbi Nosson Slifkin.</p>
        <p>Twenty-three ultra-Orthodox rabbis had signed an open letter denouncing the books of Rabbi Slifkin, an ultra-Orthodox Israeli scholar and science writer. The letter read, in part: ''He believes that the world is millions of years old -- all nonsense! -- and many other things that should not be heard and certainly not believed. His books must be kept at a distance and may not be possessed or distributed.'' Rabbi Slifkin, the letter-writers continued, should ''burn all his writings.''</p>
        <p>Fundamentalist Christians have long championed a literal reading of the Bible that suggests the planet is thousands of years old, rather than millions. But the denunciation of Rabbi Slifkin has publicized a parallel strain of thought among ultra-Orthodox Jews, a subset of the Orthodox Jewish community that is deeply skeptical of modern culture, avoiding television and the Web and often disdaining college education.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Slifkin has made a career of reconciling Jewish Scripture with modern natural history. He teaches a course in biblical and talmudic zoology at Yeshivat Lev HaTorah, near Jerusalem, and gives frequent lectures, sometimes wearing a boa constrictor along with his black hat and jacket. With nine books to his name at age 29, he is a young up-and-comer in the sober world of Jewish scholarship.</p>
        <p>The controversy surrounding him has pitted Jews who are skeptical of science against their more cosmopolitan brethren, who may follow ultra-Orthodox traditions but hold jobs as doctors or teachers. ''My sense is there are literally tens of thousands of people who are upset about the ban,'' said Dr. Andrew Klafter, an assistant professor of clinical psychiatry at the University of Cincinnati School of Medicine, who is ultra-Orthodox. ''I'm very, very puzzled by it.''</p>
        <p>In the days after the ban, Rabbi Slifkin's publisher and distributor dropped the three books mentioned in the open letter. He himself lost several speaking engagements and saw his own rabbi pressured to expel him from his synagogue. ''He was crushed,'' said a friend, Rabbi Yitzchok Adlerstein, a professor of Jewish law and ethics at Loyola Law School in Los Angeles. ''Do you know what it's like to walk through the street and see posters branding you a heretic?''</p>
        <p>Three of Rabbi Slifkin's books, published from 2001 to 2004, were singled out in the letter or in related materials: ''Mysterious Creatures,'' ''The Science of Torah'' and ''The Camel, the Hare and the Hyrax.''</p>
        <p>Predictably, the banned books have become hits. A copy of ''Science of Torah'' recently sold on eBay for $125, or five times its cover price. And Rabbi Gil Student, whose company, Yashar Books, has taken over the distribution of the other two books, said he had done a year's business in a month selling them.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Slifkin's books seek to reconcile, rather than to contrast, sacred texts with modern knowledge of the natural world.</p>
        <p>But in the process, he has sometimes cast a critical eye on those texts. In ''Mysterious Creatures,'' Rabbi Slifkin discussed fantastic animals mentioned in the Torah and the Talmud -- among them, the unicorn and the phoenix -- and suggested that, in reporting their existence, Jewish sages might have relied on the erroneous writings of ancient naturalists.</p>
        <p>He gently debunked the claim, found in a medieval text, that geese grow on trees, explaining that it was ''based on the peculiar anatomy of a certain seashell.'' And he examined the Talmudic doctrine that lice, alone of all animals, may be killed on the Sabbath because they do not sexually reproduce -- a premise now known to be false.</p>
        <p>In ''The Camel, the Hare and the Hyrax,'' Rabbi Slifkin examined the difficult separation of animals into kosher and nonkosher, and discussed apparent exceptions and contradictions to the claims of Jewish law. (The aardvark and the rhinoceros, for example, meet one test for being kosher but not another.)</p>
        <p>And in ''The Science of Torah,'' he took a scientist's eye to the Torah. Evolution, he wrote, did not disprove God's existence and was consistent with Jewish thought. He suggested that the Big Bang theory paralleled the account of the universe's creation given by the medieval Spanish-Jewish sage Ramban. And Rabbi Slifkin wrote, to quote his own later paraphrase, that ''tree-ring chronology, ice layers and sediment layers in riverbeds all show clear proof to the naked eye that the world is much more than 5,765 years old.''</p>
        <p>The latter statement was particularly galling to the rabbi's critics, who support a literal reading of Genesis that they say puts the earth's age at 5,765.</p>
        <p>The rabbis who signed the letter denouncing Rabbi Slifkin are widely respected Torah authorities; one of them, Yosef Shalom Elyashiv, 91, is a leader of Israel's United Torah Judaism Party and one of the most respected scholars in Orthodox Ashkenazi Judaism. As a result, the letter has had repercussions far beyond the congregations of those who signed it. Rabbi Slifkin's publisher, Targum Press, and his distributor, Feldheim Publishers, have stopped carrying the books. Aish HaTorah, an Orthodox outreach organization, has removed most of his articles from its Web site.</p>
        <p>Revered though they are, however, most of the rabbis signing the letter are not known as community leaders or public voices; only one of the Americans, for example, sits on the eight-member Council of Torah Sages at the head of Agudath Israel of America, an influential national Orthodox organization. Rather, they represent the most unworldly segment of the ultra-Orthodox community, in which learning is prized and contact with the secular world, including secular education, is shunned.</p>
        <p>The letter against Rabbi Slifkin is not the only recent outburst against science among the ultra-Orthodox. Last November, during the annual conference of Agudath Israel, Rabbi Uren Reich, the dean of Yeshiva of Woodlake Village in New Jersey, said, ''These same scientists who tell you with such clarity what happened 65 million years ago -- ask them what the weather will be like in New York in two weeks' time.''</p>
        <p>Many science-minded ultra-Orthodox Jews say it is spiritually wrenching to see leaders they revere endorsing views they oppose.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Adlerstein of Loyola said: ''I know rabbis, I know teens in yeshivas who were on the verge of quitting'' when the letter first came out. ''They look at themselves in the mirror and they say, 'What have I been representing?'''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
