<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serbian President Supports U.N. Troops for Yugoslavia</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CROATIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILOSEVIC, SLOBODAN (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DA1F31F93BA15751C0A964958260" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serbian President Supports U.N. Troops for Yugoslavia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with widespread discontent among Serbs over the civil war with Croatia and the resulting damage to Yugoslavia's economy, President Slobodan Milosevic of Serbia said today that he regarded the impending deployment of United Nations troops in Serbian-held areas of Croatia as "the beginning of a peaceful solution to the Yugoslav crisis."</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic's hard-line posture toward Croatia, especially after the republic declared independence in June, was a major factor in setting off the civil war. And before a United Nations-brokered cease-fire took hold on Jan. 3, the Serb-led Yugoslav Army had seized one-third of Croatia. But in his first speech since then, delivered in a televised address today, Mr. Milosevic appeared eager to present himself as conciliatory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with widespread discontent among Serbs over the civil war with Croatia and the resulting damage to Yugoslavia's economy, President Slobodan Milosevic of Serbia said today that he regarded the impending deployment of United Nations troops in Serbian-held areas of Croatia as "the beginning of a peaceful solution to the Yugoslav crisis."</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic's hard-line posture toward Croatia, especially after the republic declared independence in June, was a major factor in setting off the civil war. And before a United Nations-brokered cease-fire took hold on Jan. 3, the Serb-led Yugoslav Army had seized one-third of Croatia. But in his first speech since then, delivered in a televised address today, Mr. Milosevic appeared eager to present himself as conciliatory.</p>
        <p>In Serbia, public opinion has been divided between those who celebrate what the government calls the "liberation" of Serbian-inhabited enclaves in Croatia and those who believe that Serbia should have sought a peaceful solution. Between 6,000 and 10,000 people are believed to have died in the fighting, including many Serbian civilians. The fighting destroyed dozens of towns and villages in Croatia and disrupted an economy that once made Yugoslavia the most prosperous country in Eastern Europe.  Addressing Serbian Parliament</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic, a 48-year-old veteran of Yugoslavia's Communist Party, used his 40-minute speech to the Serbian parliament to strike an uneasy balance. By invoking a peaceful solution and heralding the plan to send more than 14,000 United Nations peacekeepers, he reached out to opponents who bitterly criticized him last year when he rejected the presence foreign soldiers on Yugoslav territory. He relented only after Yugoslav troops and Serbian militias had seized Croatian areas where nearly 600,000 Serbs lived before the fighting started.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Milosevic demanded that opposition groups in Serbia behave with what he called "responsibility," and he warned that failure to do so could threaten the multiparty system that has succeeded Communism here. Diplomats said this appeared to be a warning to the opposition groups that are planning a mass demonstration against his government in central Belgrade on March 9. The protest will mark the first anniversary of a mass protest in a central Belgrade square last year that drew government gunfire, killing two demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic insisted that Serbia would continue to press for a new federal state in Yugoslavia, to be formed by Serbia, its ally Montenegro and any other territory that wished to join. But in making the assertion, he did not repeat his insistence that all Serbs had the right to live in a single Yugoslav state. This, too, had a possible conciliatory connotation, since it came on the eve of the weekend referendum in Bosnia and Herzogovina, a republic where Serbs, who form 40 percent of the population, have pressed for annexation of their enclaves by Serbia.</p>
        <p>With the main Serbian political groups in Bosnia urging a boycott, the referendum is expected to bring a strong endorsement for independence, leaving only Serbia and Montenegro, among the six republics of what was Yugoslavia, committed to maintaining a federal state. Results of the vote are expected early next week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
