<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sell-Off of Media Property Sets Off a Frenzy in Turkey</title>
    <meta content="21TURK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/21/international/europe/21turkey.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1651823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Turkey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFD71E3AF932A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sell-Off of Media Property Sets Off a Frenzy in Turkey</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Sell-Off of Media Property Sets Off a Frenzy in Turkey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL, Feb. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turkish government plan to sell newspaper and television stations seized to settle debts sets off fierce battle over who owns country's media; mighty political and financial fortunes are in balance, because owning big newspapers and popular television channels brings politicial influence; in Turkey,1 that political weight is magnified because so much of media is concentrated in hands of few family-controlled companies (M))</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Media barons in Turkey are a versatile group. One has an organic farm and a nationwide string of gas stations. Another is a mining tycoon who runs power plants.</p>
        <p>It also used to be the fashion here for bankers to have a media outlet or two, and for some media companies to own banks. But many banks went bust four years ago, and to settle their debts, Turkish regulatory authorities seized their newspapers and television stations. Now the government, controlling some of the biggest papers and stations, says it wants to sell them, starting in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Turkish government, controlling some of the biggest newspapers and television stations, says it wants to sell them, starting in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Media barons in Turkey are a versatile group. One has an organic farm and a nationwide string of gas stations. Another is a mining tycoon who runs power plants.</p>
        <p>It also used to be the fashion here for bankers to have a media outlet or two, and for some media companies to own banks. But many banks went bust four years ago, and to settle their debts, Turkish regulatory authorities seized their newspapers and television stations. Now the government, controlling some of the biggest papers and stations, says it wants to sell them, starting in March.</p>
        <p>The auction has set the stage for a fierce battle over who owns Turkey's media, with mighty political and financial fortunes in the balance.</p>
        <p>The industrial Goliaths that already control the lion's share of the media market hope to buy more. But some government officials see the sell-off as an opportunity to take on those media barons and break down their dominating positions.</p>
        <p>''It's a disgraceful situation now,'' said Ahmet Tezcan, a senior adviser to Prime Minister Recip Tayyip Erdogan. ''It's all because the media owners jumped into the financial markets, and because there was an unhealthy relationship between the media and politics.''</p>
        <p>Owning big newspapers and popular television channels brings political influence, as in many other countries. In Turkey, that political weight is magnified because so much of the media is concentrated in the hands of a few family-controlled companies.</p>
        <p>Over the years, especially during horse-trading over cabinet posts in coalition governments, the media magnates have campaigned openly for their favorites. But journalists say political interference is less a problem than the owners' outside commercial interests.</p>
        <p>''You can't write about anything that damages the economic interests of the owner,'' said Yavuz Baydar, the ombudsman for the daily Sabah and a veteran journalist who has worked for several of the big media companies as a reporter and editor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baydar used to be the ombudsman at the newspaper Milliyet until his sharp critique of an incorrect front-page article soured his relations with the paper's owner, Aydin Dogan, who has interests in television stations, gas stations, banks, tourism, insurance and organic farming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dogan's newspapers account for nearly 45 percent of all daily newspaper sales in the country. He has expressed interest in buying some of the state's media properties to add to his market share. So have some of his rivals in the publishing and broadcasting business.</p>
        <p>''Expectations are quite high for a wild and dirty war,'' Mr. Baydar said. ''Diversification should be the goal, but it seems very difficult.''</p>
        <p>A convergence of several deadlines has brought the issue of media ownership here to the forefront.</p>
        <p>Not only television and radio stations, newspapers and magazines are to be auctioned off. Regulators are also preparing to reallocate broadcasting frequencies, which could bring new attention to who owns what and shake up the distribution of television licenses.</p>
        <p>Even now, no person or family is supposed to own more than 20 percent of the shares of any radio or television station, although the rule has rarely been enforced. ''We're going to take care of that when we revise the laws,'' Mr. Tezcan said. ''And maybe the TV station owners will not be able to own a TV station any longer.''</p>
        <p>Before selling off its media outlets, Turkey has to set ground rules that will determine how regulated the media companies will be, through limits on who may bid, how many stations a single owner may have, whether foreigners may own a television station and if a media owner may own nonrelated businesses.</p>
        <p>Past efforts to settle such issues were fiercely contested. Three years ago, over the veto of President Ahmet Necdet Sezer, the Parliament eased regulations on media owners. The president warned that the law would ''open the door for big capital to establish their monopoly on TV and radio broadcasting'' and put ''individual commercial interests'' ahead of the public's right to an independent press.'' Turkey's Supreme Court later ruled parts of the new law unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Mr. Erdogan will have great influence but has yet to make a public commitment either to regulate or deregulate further. But Mr. Tezcan, his adviser, said, ''The prime minister believes that media, government and business need to be separated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dogan favors lifting restrictions on media ownership, which he said would make the business more transparent and give the public more choice. ''Right now the media situation is a disgrace because they are either tied to the state ideologically or financially,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''If you split them, they're not going to be economically viable,'' he added. ''If media groups don't have financial freedom, you can't have press freedom. If you don't have financial independence, you lean toward power groups or politicians, and in the end you are ruled by them.''</p>
        <p>The ranks of press barons and television tycoons thinned considerably in 2001, when some 20 Turkish banks collapsed under the weight of bad loans and risky currency transactions. Many had print and television holdings as well.</p>
        <p>In the fallout from the financial crisis, the Savings Deposit Insurance Fund took many media outlets, as well as mobile phone operators, factories and a host of other companies, into receivership. They are slowly being packaged and put up for bid.</p>
        <p>According to fund regulators, the first sale of media properties will include the pay television channel Cine 5, one of the holdings of Erol Aksoy, whose Iktisat Bank failed in 2001, and the Star group of newspapers, magazines and television stations.</p>
        <p>The Star group was taken over by the state last year when members of the Uzan family, its owners, were charged with bank fraud that the government says cost the state $6 billion. One of the biggest properties in government hands, the group includes two daily newspapers with a combined circulation of about 200,000 and Star TV, a news and entertainment channel with a 7 percent share of the broadcast advertising market.</p>
        <p>The fate of the daily Sabah and its sister television channel, ATV, also rests with Turkish authorities. They were part of the holdings of another banker turned press baron, Dinc Bilgin, who has been charged with defrauding his bank.</p>
        <p>After seizing the Bilgin media outlets, the state leased them to yet another media conglomerate, the Ciner Group, which has three other national daily newspapers with a combined circulation of 950,000, as well as electrical plants, mines and tourism companies.</p>
        <p>Neither Sabah nor ATV has officially been put up for sale yet. But competition among the media barons has already started.</p>
        <p>Turgay Ciner, the president of Ciner Group, has offered $200 million, according to Sabah's editor, Ergun Babahan. His rival, Mr. Dogan, said he had offered $525 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
