<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mindful of His Legacy, Hopkins Mulls the Future</title>
    <meta content="21BOXI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/21/sports/othersports/21boxing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1651825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hopkins, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eastman, Howard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hopkins, Bernard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71E3AF932A15751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mindful of His Legacy, Hopkins Mulls the Future</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mindful of His Legacy, Hopkins Mulls the Future</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Hopkins says he is looking to next challenge after defeating Howard Eastman in 12-round unanimous decision; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bernard Hopkins was not electrifying, but he was efficient.</p>
        <p>With his 12-round unanimous decision over Howard Eastman on Saturday night, Hopkins continued one of the longest championship reigns in boxing history and said he looked forward to his next challenge. Hopkins, the undisputed middleweight champion, has won 26 consecutive bouts. He has not lost since 1993, and his most recent victory was his 20th consecutive title defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his 12-round unanimous decision over Howard Eastman on Saturday night, Bernard Hopkins continued one of the longest championship reigns in boxing history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bernard Hopkins was not electrifying, but he was efficient.</p>
        <p>With his 12-round unanimous decision over Howard Eastman on Saturday night, Hopkins continued one of the longest championship reigns in boxing history and said he looked forward to his next challenge. Hopkins, the undisputed middleweight champion, has won 26 consecutive bouts. He has not lost since 1993, and his most recent victory was his 20th consecutive title defense.</p>
        <p>Those gaudy credentials leave Hopkins (46-2-1) with little to prove, so he shrugged off his inability to dominate Eastman (40-2) and looked ahead to larger goals. At 40, Hopkins can sense the end of his career coming. His remaining time in boxing is precious, he said, and he is determined not to waste it.</p>
        <p>''It's about history, along with the m-o-n-e-y,'' Hopkins said when asked what motivated him. ''This 20th defense was very special and personal to Bernard Hopkins. It's something that will be documented in boxing history. It was a hard 20. I don't think I looked 40 years old, but when you're in there with guys who are hungry, guys who are trying to get to the top, I understand their mentality. I was glad I was willing and able to take the challenge.''</p>
        <p>There were no knockdowns, and neither fighter was seriously hurt. But Hopkins took control after the fifth round; Eastman had predicted he would knock out Hopkins in the fifth. Hopkins was most effective in Rounds 8 through 10, snapping Eastman's head back with crisp counterpunches, particularly several hard left hooks.</p>
        <p>The action came in flurries, but there were lengthy stretches when neither fighter did much, and the Staples Center crowd of 12,828 booed on several occasions, looking for more action. But Hopkins saw little reason to take chances during the final two rounds, knowing he was comfortably ahead. The judges recorded scores of 118-110, 117-111 and 116-112, and Hopkins offered no apology for his conservative approach.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to bore anybody, but I have to fight the fight that's best for me,'' he said. ''I'm not a guy who comes in and tries to blast you out of there. I'm not a one-punch knockout artist. I'm more of technician. I eventually dissect you or beat you up. I give myself a B-minus. I'm my own worst critic. I will look at the tape and look at everything I should have done properly.''</p>
        <p>The victory left Hopkins with multiple options, including one that was directly in front of him. In the bout that preceded Hopkins-Eastman, the unbeaten middleweight Jermain Taylor (23-0) scored a third-round technical knockout over Daniel Edouard (16-1-2). Taylor hurt Edouard in the second round and finished him off with a blistering combination, followed by multiple unanswered blows to the head that persuaded the referee to move in and stop the fight.</p>
        <p>At 26, Taylor has been labeled the heir apparent to Hopkins. But Taylor is tired of waiting and wants to fight Hopkins next.</p>
        <p>''This is exactly the kind of performance I wanted,'' he said. ''I look up to Bernard Hopkins. I felt like this was an audition, and I could feel the pressure. I am willing to fight anyone. It makes me nervous when they say I am the heir apparent. He is not my king. Being a prince is O.K., but I want to be the king.''</p>
        <p>But Hopkins has not determined his next move. He has talked about a rematch against Felix Trinidad, whom he defeated in a brilliant 12th-round technical knockout in 2001. He may also move up to light heavyweight to challenge the ruler of that division, Glen Johnson.</p>
        <p>Hopkins's negotiating team is expected to meet with representatives of Johnson, Trinidad and Taylor in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>Hopkins was not at his best Saturday night. But he was good enough to extend his championship reign.</p>
        <p>''My goal was simple, to get my 20th defense,'' he said. ''I wanted to fight my fight, not Eastman's. The smart man lives to see another day.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
