<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COLLEGE FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</title>
    <meta content="03COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, William N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2D7143DF930A35753C1A961958260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COLLEGE FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wallace, William N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William N Wallace reports on college football scene (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yale</p>
        <p>There has been no heavy ticket demand for tonight's game matching the Bulldogs from the Ivy League against Valparaiso in Chicago's Soldier Field, which has 66,944 seats. This contest was scheduled as a rally for Midwest alumni, but Yale (0-2) has little to be positive about this season apart from the indefatigable enthusiasm of its new coach, Jack Siedlecki. His defense has allowed 80 points to date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yale</p>
        <p>There has been no heavy ticket demand for tonight's game matching the Bulldogs from the Ivy League against Valparaiso in Chicago's Soldier Field, which has 66,944 seats. This contest was scheduled as a rally for Midwest alumni, but Yale (0-2) has little to be positive about this season apart from the indefatigable enthusiasm of its new coach, Jack Siedlecki. His defense has allowed 80 points to date.</p>
        <p>Still, this may have been fortuitous scheduling for the Bulldogs. Valparaiso (1-3), an Indiana school, is a lesser member of the Pioneer League, a six-team Division I-AA conference dominated by Dayton.</p>
        <p>Its victory was by 1 point in overtime, 35-34, against Hope, a Division III team. Then came losses to Alma, also of Division III, 45-28; Morehead State, 56-24, and Drake, 27-7.</p>
        <p>This is not the first visit by a Yale team to the Windy City. The Bulldogs defeated the University of Chicago there, 27-0, in 1931 when Albie Booth was the captain and Amos Alonzo Stagg, Yale '88, coached the Maroon.</p>
        <p>Dartmouth</p>
        <p>The Green's 19-game winning streak, the longest in the nation, will be tested by Cornell (1-1) tomorrow in a key Ivy League match.</p>
        <p>Dartmouth (2-0), the unbeaten Ivy champion a year ago, has managed to replace such graduated offensive luminaries as quarterback Jon Aljancic (with Pete Sellers) and running back Greg Smith (with both Eric Davis and Jeff Link). In the 35-6 victory over Holy Cross, Sellers had a career afternoon when he completed 21 of his 34 passes for 234 yards and 3 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>The Big Red scored 38 points against Colgate, but it was not enough as Colgate had 45, the last 7 in overtime.</p>
        <p>The senior receiver Eric Krawczyk set a Cornell yardage record when he caught 14 of quarterback Scott Carroll's passes for 171 yards and 2 touchdowns. Carroll, like Sellers, is a senior playing as a regular after three seasons on the sideline.</p>
        <p>This could be the decisive Ivy League game of the season.</p>
        <p>Wagner</p>
        <p>Similarly, the Northeast Conference championship might well be decided when the two best teams in this Division I-AA nonscholarship league meet tomorrow. They are Wagner (3-0) and Robert Morris (3-1), and the game is at Moon Township, Pa.</p>
        <p>The Seahawks' veteran coach, Walt Hameline, always has a good running back, and the current one, Rick Sarille, was in the end zone with touchdowns four times against St. Francis in a 42-6 victory.</p>
        <p>Hameline sat him in the second half after he had rushed for 140 yards (8.2 yards per carry) in the first half.</p>
        <p>Sarille is from Key Biscayne, Fla., and Gulliver Prep, a new stop for Hameline on the recruiting trail.</p>
        <p>Catholic</p>
        <p>The Catholic University of America, in Washington, has been fielding teams for half a century, and the current one might be the best of all because of its quarterback, Kevin Ricca, and receiver Jeff Clay. Ricca is the Division III leader in total offense with an average of 349 yards per game, and Clay is No. 1 in receptions, 51 in four games and 9 for touchdowns, as well as in average yards per game, 174.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals have won all four this season under Coach Tom Clark, who has an overall record there of 25-6-1. The school's goal is selection for the 16-team Division III tournament for the first time and tomorrow's home game against Franklin &amp; Marshall (3-1), the Centennial League leader, will be a pivotal one.</p>
        <p>New Haven</p>
        <p>The Chargers, who have had only one losing season since 1983, are undefeated again and ranked No. 3 in Division II behind Carson-Newman of Tennessee and Pittsburg State of Kansas in an N.C.A.A. poll.</p>
        <p>New Haven trounced Indiana of Pennsylvania last Saturday, 43-14, signaling the diminishing stature of the teams from the Keystone State that have been so prominent in Division II.</p>
        <p>The leaders for the Chargers have been Don Highsmith, the senior running back from Middletown, Conn., and Lidz Eugene, the linebacker who has scored two touchdowns this season on turnovers.</p>
        <p>Coming up next Friday night is the traditional match with crosstown rival Southern Connecticut, also 4-0, at the latter's Jesse Dow Field.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The top teams in the coaches' preseason poll, Colgate (2-1) and Lehigh (1-2), meet tomorrow at Hamilton, N.Y., and the outcome could resolve the Patriot League title. Lehigh quarterback Phil Stambaugh had four touchdown passes in the fourth period in the 35-30 loss to Harvard. . . . The Crimson (2-0), meanwhile, will be host to Bucknell (3-0). . . . The New Jersey Conference title is most likely to be decided in the Rowan-College of New Jersey matchup at Rowan tomorrow. Both are 3-0. . . . The key match in the New England small college league will be Middlebury (2-0) at Amherst (2-0). Williams's 19-15 victory over Trinity was critical in this group. . . . Who has a better running back than Siena's Reggie Green? He has gained 100 yards or more in 20 of his last 21 games -- 225 yards in the last, a victory over Canisius. . . . Delaware has won six straight in Boston and is expected to make it seven, against Boston University.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM N. WALLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
