<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suspect in New Jersey Strangling Was Reportedly Sex-Case Victim</title>
    <meta content="03SLAY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jackson Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcfadden, Robert D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Werner, Edward P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simmons, Stephen P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manzie, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D8143DF930A35753C1A961958260" item-length="1772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suspect in New Jersey Strangling Was Reportedly Sex-Case Victim</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcfadden, Robert D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prosecutors say that Jackson Township, NJ, teen-ager charged with sexually assaulting and strangling 11-year-old Edward P Werner was sexually abused last year by Stephen P Simmons, convicted pedophile who lured him from on-line chat room to his home on Long Island and to motel rooms in Ocean and Monmouth Counties; murder suspect's name has not been disclosed by authorities, but lead investigator has identified him as Sam Manzie; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Jersey teen-ager charged with sexually assaulting and strangling an 11-year-old neighbor boy was himself sexually abused last year by a convicted pedophile who lured him from an on-line chat room to his home on Long Island and to motel rooms in Ocean and Monmouth Counties, prosecutors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The pedophile, who left a trail of credit-card receipts and was arrested last week, and the 15-year-old Jackson Township murder suspect had at least four sexual encounters between August and December of 1996, some lasting two days and one involving a man with whom the older man lived, officials said. The activities of at least one assault were photographed, they said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Jersey teen-ager charged with sexually assaulting and strangling an 11-year-old neighbor boy was himself sexually abused last year by a convicted pedophile who lured him from an on-line chat room to his home on Long Island and to motel rooms in Ocean and Monmouth Counties, prosecutors said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The pedophile, who left a trail of credit-card receipts and was arrested last week, and the 15-year-old Jackson Township murder suspect had at least four sexual encounters between August and December of 1996, some lasting two days and one involving a man with whom the older man lived, officials said. The activities of at least one assault were photographed, they said.</p>
        <p>Five weeks ago, the youth's parents discovered the relationship and took him to a therapist, who called prosecutors. The youth aided an investigation of the pedophile until last week. Then he smashed electronic equipment that had been installed in his home to monitor the contacts. The officials said he also refused further cooperation and rejected hospitalization and counseling.</p>
        <p>Four days later, on Saturday, Edward P. Werner, 11, was killed as he sold candy door to door for a P.T.A. fund-raiser in Jackson Township. His body was found on Monday in woods near the home of the suspect, who was arrested the next day after Ocean County officials learned of his meetings with an older man. Yesterday, what began as a missing person case last weekend widened to charges of pedophilia in New Jersey and in Suffolk County on Long Island. And just as the slaying raised concerns about the safety of children venturing to the doors of strangers, the latest revelations raised new worries about dangerous encounters by children roaming the Internet.</p>
        <p>The Internet, said the Suffolk District Attorney, James M. Catterson, ''can be a force for good, but in the hands of the immature it can be an engine of destruction.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Catterson said at a news conference that Stephen P. Simmons, 43, of Holbrook, N.Y., was being held in jail at Riverhead, N.Y., and had waived extradition to New Jersey. Mr. Catterson said Mr. Simmons was convicted of sodomizing a child in Brooklyn in 1984 and of lewd and lascivious conduct with a child in Florida in 1986 and went to prison for both crimes.</p>
        <p>The Monmouth County Prosecutor, John Kaye, said at another news conference that Mr. Simmons had been charged with nine offenses involving the young murder suspect -- two of sexual assault, three of criminal sexual contact and four of endangering the welfare of a juvenile.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaye said it did not appear that Mr. Simmons had forced the youth to have sex. But he said the acts were criminal because they involved a juvenile, who was 14 at the time they purportedly occurred.</p>
        <p>Because of the murder suspect's status as a juvenile, his name has not been disclosed by authorities in Ocean County, where the case is to be prosecuted.</p>
        <p>But a lead investigator in the case identified the suspect this week as Sam Manzie, who neighbors described as an intelligent loner who was fascinated with computers, who spent much of his time at a home computer and who even maintained a personal World Wide Web site.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaye said that it was over the computer that the youth first encountered Mr. Simmons last year. ''The boy was hanging around a homosexual chat line,'' the prosecutor said. As a result of the contacts, he said, the youth and Mr. Simmons arranged a face-to-face meeting.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor said the first encounter took place on Aug. 10, 1996, at the Freehold Raceway Mall in Freehold, N.J., and that the youth's father, unaware of the situation, drove him to the mall.</p>
        <p>Emily Constant, the chief of the Suffolk County District Attorney's family crimes bureau, said that Mr. Simmons drove the youth to his home in Holbrook, where he lived at that time with a 59-year-old man. The ranch home has a landscaped, fenced back yard with trees.</p>
        <p>''Our understanding is there was a weekend that they spent at this home in Holbrook and that there were numerous incidents over that weekend, but that was the only time this boy came to Long Island with Mr. Simmons,'' Ms. Constant said. Asked if others were present, she said, ''Our information is that it was this victim and Mr. Simmons.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kaye said that on that occasion the youth had engaged in sexual activities with Mr. Simmons and his housemate.</p>
        <p>When the youth did not return home on the night of Aug. 10, his parents called the police to report him missing, Mr. Kaye said. But no action was taken and the youth returned home the next day, he said.</p>
        <p>Other meetings between the youth and Mr. Simmons occurred on Sept. 29, Oct. 1 and Dec. 15, at motels in Freehold and in Howell Township and Jackson Township, where Mr. Simmons left a trail of credit card payments as well as the license plate number of his car on motel registration cards.</p>
        <p>On some occasions, Mr. Kaye said, Mr. Simmons picked up the youth at his home. While the youth sometimes stayed out overnight, his parents apparently knew nothing of the activities.</p>
        <p>''This youngster was very clever and quite sly in the way he got out from under his parents' control,'' Mr. Kaye said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear whether Mr. Simmons and the youth continued to meet this year, though the youth made frequent calls to Long Island and was absent from home from time to time, officials said. By late August, however, the youth's parents  had become suspicious.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaye said the father called and confronted Mr. Simmons. They also placed their son into therapy with a psychological counselor who,  after hearing the youth's story, called the Monmouth Prosecutor's office. Mr. Kaye said the information was nonprivileged and said the decision to pass it on to the authorities was ethically appropriate.</p>
        <p>Based on that tip, Mr. Kaye's office began its investigation of Mr. Simmons on Aug. 28. At first, he said, the youth cooperated, and detectives installed electronic devices at his home on Iowa Court to monitor and  record telephone and computer contacts between the youth and Mr. Simmons.</p>
        <p>But on Sept. 23, without explanation, ''this changed abruptly,'' Mr. Kaye said. ''The boy changed on us. The equipment was smashed with a hammer.'' Tapes also were destroyed by the youth, the prosecutor said. He said investigators were concerned about the suddenly angry, apparently disturbed youth.</p>
        <p>''They were of the belief that he needed some professional assistance,'' the Prosecutor said. ''We were trying to have him treated, or at least analyzed. We took him to a hospital and he refused to enter. He refused counseling.'' Asked if more could have been done, Mr. Kaye said, ''I can't conceive of anything we could have done more in a democratic society to restrain this boy.''</p>
        <p>In the belief that the youth, besides smashing the equipment, may have alerted Mr. Simmons and thus compromised the inquiry, the Prosecutor's office filed charges against Mr. Simmons and he was arrested by the Suffolk County authorities the next day, on Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>While the youth refused to testify  against Mr. Simmons before a grand jury -- exhibiting what Mr. Catterson called a reluctance ''not uncommon with teen-aged victims of sex crimes'' -- Mr. Simmons was held pending extradition proceedings by New Jersey authorities.</p>
        <p>Four days after the angry outburst of the youth in the murder case, the 11-year-old boy, Edward P. Werner, a sixth grader at Christa McAuliffe Middle School, was out selling candy and wrapping paper last Saturday. There have been unconfirmed reports that he was carrying as much as $200 that he had collected. No money has been found, but an additional charge of robbery was filed against the suspect yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Ocean County Prosecutor, E. David Millard, said the boy was taken inside the suspect's home late in the afternoon and was strangled after being sexually attacked. His body was then placed in a suitcase and may have been kept in or near the house as hundreds of police officers and volunteers searched the neighborhood over the weekend for the missing boy.</p>
        <p>Investigators said that the youth  watched the searchers from his porch on Sunday, and that he may have carried the suitcase with the 4-foot-11-inch, 60-pound body into the woods during a heavy rain Sunday night. The body was found Monday morning in an area that had been searched over the weekend.</p>
        <p>Acting on what he called intuition, Mr. Kaye's investigators called the Ocean County officials on Tuesday to say the body had been found near the home of a troubled youth involved in a pedophilia case. Ocean County investigators then questioned the youth, searched his home and charged him with the murder.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons, described by his neighbors as a short, moody man who sometimes took roles in local theatrical productions and who had a T-shirt shop in Bayport, N.Y., until it burned some time ago, could face up to 46 years in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>It is unclear if the murder suspect will be tried as an adult or a juvenile; authorities have a month to decide. If convicted as an adult, he would face 30 years to life in prison. Penalties for juveniles are much lower.</p>
        <p>More than 1,200 people attended a prayer service for the slain boy last night at Jackson Memorial High School in Jackson Township. Across the community of 36,000 people, green ribbons and bows have appeared in recent days on fences, trees, light poles and the lapels of hundreds of residents, as a remembrance of Edward Werner, whose favorite color was green.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
