<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate Aside, Fund-Raising Doesn't Stop</title>
    <meta content="03BUCK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fertitta, Tilman J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3D8143DF930A35753C1A961958260" item-length="2106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate Aside, Fund-Raising Doesn't Stop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton raised about $700,000 at Sept 26 dinner at Houston home of restaurant magnate Tilman J Fertitta that was attended by wealthiest Democrats in Texas; Clinton is stepping up his appearances at such events as inquiries deepen into his fund-raising practices; he has called for legislation that would prohibit dinners like Fertitta's; event demonstrates how hunt for money is almost preoccupation for Clinton, and shows way in which fund-raising zeal and skill of White House and Democratic Party combine to carry out mission; it also shows how sensitivities over fund-raising have forced some changes, like more careful scrutiny of guest lists; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly after 9 P.M., as the 70 or so guests picked over the last crumbs of their almond tuile with peaches, plums, pears and seasonal berries, President Clinton scanned the candlelit room of eight round tables filled with the wealthiest Democrats in Texas.</p>
        <p>''When you go home tonight,'' Mr. Clinton told his dinner companions in the elaborately decorated 10-car garage at a sprawling Houston mansion, ''I hope you will think about it and be glad you came.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly after 9 P.M., as the 70 or so guests picked over the last crumbs of their almond tuile with peaches, plums, pears and seasonal berries, President Clinton scanned the candlelit room of eight round tables filled with the wealthiest Democrats in Texas.</p>
        <p>''When you go home tonight,'' Mr. Clinton told his dinner companions in the elaborately decorated 10-car garage at a sprawling Houston mansion, ''I hope you will think about it and be glad you came.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the financially struggling Democratic National Committee were certainly glad they came to the dinner, held Sept. 26 at the home of a restaurant magnate, Tilman J. Fertitta. In a process that took only two and a half hours, Mr. Clinton and his entourage converged on Mr. Fertitta's home; the President posed for photographs, gave a speech, departed on schedule (before many guests had sipped their second cup of hazelnut coffee), and won about $700,000 in mostly unregulated ''soft money'' donations.</p>
        <p>It was another successful evening for the Democratic Party's premier, and most proficient, fund-raiser: Bill Clinton. As inquiries deepen into his fund-raising practices in the 1996 campaign, and as the President himself calls for legislation that would prohibit dinners like Mr. Fertitta's, Mr. Clinton is stepping up his appearances on the money circuit.</p>
        <p>(In this, Mr. Clinton is not alone: from Speaker Newt Gingrich on down, Republicans are even more skilled at staging big-money events, but they do not have a President to help attract guests.)</p>
        <p>As lavish as the Fertitta party was -- with an entry fee of at least $10,000 per person, a 900-pound ice sculpture of the White House by the pool and chairs covered with yellow silk and  and yellow and white roses -- the event was fairly typical. It demonstrates how the hunt for money is almost a preoccupation for Mr. Clinton, and shows the way in which the fund-raising zeal and skill of the White House and the Democratic Party combine to carry out the mission. It also shows how sensitivities over fund-raising have forced some changes, like more careful scrutiny of guest lists.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Clinton, Vice President Al Gore and Hillary Rodham Clinton have been the star attractions at dozens of fund-raising events this year. Because the fund-raising occasions have become so routine and because they usually occur at night -- long after most reporters' deadlines -- Mr. Clinton's appearances are not widely publicized. Yet, they often drive his entire schedule on any given day and, as happened in Houston, determine why he travels to a particular state.</p>
        <p>Despite the climate of concern in the capital about fund-raising practices, neither Mr. Clinton nor Mr. Fertitta had any apologies. Asked whether it was unfair for the wealthy to get such access to the President, Mr. Fertitta said in an interview: ''That's like saying someone who could afford front-row seats at a fight shouldn't go to it. That's the way the world is.''</p>
        <p>Everyone from the President on down pronounced the event a success. It, like so many others, took months of planning and strategizing and hundreds of decisions large and small.</p>
        <p>Host and Guests Chosen Carefully</p>
        <p>The selection of Mr. Fertitta as the host of the event arose out of a master plan for raising money late last year. Although the White House eagerly approved the idea, outlined in an ''event scenario'' by the Democratic National Committee, there was a snag when Representative Martin Frost of Texas, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, complained that the fund-raising event might interfere with his own ability to hit up donors for candidates for Congress and the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>A compromise was reached: White House officials agreed to dispatch Mr. Gore to Dallas in November to raise money for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee.</p>
        <p>Once the date was approved, most of the preparations went to officials at the Democratic National Committee. As one White House official put it: ''This is their event. I just provide the body.''</p>
        <p>Although White House officials had initially planned to hold the event at a Westin Hotel here, they relented to the wishes of the 40-year-old host, Mr. Fertitta, the multimillionaire president and chief executive of Landry's Seafood Restaurants. Mr. Fertitta said he was proud of his home and wanted a more intimate approach. ''We're not fake people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fertitta had been selected by party officials because he was a generous giver who had put on a dinner at his home for Mr. Clinton a year ago, when he transformed his front yard into an Old West town. He also picked up $75,000 in costs from this year's event, from the food to the catering staff to the string quartet to the tent over his carport.</p>
        <p>Trolling for guests, the party sent a feeler letter to reliable big donors in Texas asking if they would attend a dinner for the President. Then Mr. Fertitta and others made calls on their own to add to the list. In early September, Alan D. Solomont, the party's finance chairman, said he spent a day in Houston and a day in Dallas meeting with donors and reminding them ''why it was so important to the party'' that they help retire its debt of more than $15 million. Gov. Roy Romer of Colorado, the party's general chairman, made a follow-up trip. Not everyone had to pony up $10,000. A handful of politicians were given complimentary tickets, including former Gov. Ann Richards and Representative Sheila Jackson Lee.</p>
        <p>Just days before the event, White House aides found an official reason for Mr. Clinton to travel to Houston: they scheduled a speech at San Jacinto College. That way, some of the cost would be paid through the White House travel budget.</p>
        <p>As the date grew closer, party officials examined the guest list to make sure that none of those invited had been in prison or had other embarrassing information in their files. Officials said that with all the inquiries into the party's lax procedures in the 1996 campaign, they have become more vigilant in screening guests. Two people were disinvited from Mr. Fertitta's dinner because of concerns about their histories, officials said, but they would not give the reasons.</p>
        <p>Party officials put together a seating chart, making sure each table had the right mix of people. The party's finance chairman, Mr. Solomont, chose a prized spot for himself: he sat next to Carl Lewis, the Olympic sprinter who lives down the street. Mr. Lewis was the only African-American spotted among the guests.</p>
        <p>''I did say the person I want to sit beside is Carl Lewis,'' Mr. Solomont said. ''He's a very substantive guy. And I'm a little bit of a track-and-field devotee.''</p>
        <p>Chefs Prepare A Seafood Feast</p>
        <p>As officials of the party and the White House were reviewing the seating, the two executive chefs -- Kathy Ruiz of Landry's Seafood Restaurants and Lindell Mendoza of the San Luis Resort in Galveston, Tex., which is also owned by Mr. Fertitta -- were putting final touches on the menu.</p>
        <p>Though she sought advice from stewards at the White House, Ms. Ruiz said the menu fell into place easily. ''I know the President likes mangoes,'' she said, ''so that was kind of a no-brainer.'' She also said she wanted to take advantage of the fresh seafood from her restaurant. So the main course was ''Texas Gulf Red Snapper topped with Galveston Bay Jumbo Lump Crab Meat and Mango-Roasted Pepper Vinaigrette.''</p>
        <p>While the chefs were torn over whether to serve an appetizer of duck tamales with mole sauce or a seafood ceviche, they went with the seafood because even though several convection ovens were installed for the event, they did not think Mr. Fertitta's kitchen was large enough for a hot appetizer and entree. Each ceviche appetizer was served in an individual ice sculpture designed as a big scallop shell. For dessert, Ms. Ruiz wanted something light. She knew that the President did not like chocolate. Thus, the almond tuile with fruit. For a personal touch, every plate had a cookie shaped like a saxophone. (The press, police and support staff were served barbecue in a tent across the street.)</p>
        <p>Villa Mount Eden vineyards of Central California donated five cases of its 1995 Special Grand Reserve Chardonnay.</p>
        <p>A couple of days before the dinner, the chefs met with the Secret Service to discuss the menu. ''They made sure everything was fine,'' Ms. Ruiz said. ''They didn't change anything.''</p>
        <p>There was no ''taster'' to make sure the President's food was not poisoned. But for security reasons, the White House designated that just one of the tuxedo-wearing, white-gloved waiters would serve Mr. Clinton. Every time that waiter returned to the kitchen, Ms. Ruiz checked to see whether the President cleaned his plate.</p>
        <p>''He ate very well,'' she said. ''That I can tell you.''</p>
        <p>Rubbing Shoulders With the President</p>
        <p>When they arrived at the event around 6:30, some White House aides were worried about a sculpture in the window of Mr. Fertitta's house. It was a life-size bronze of an African-American man in a white tuxedo playing the piano. Some officials and reporters traveling with the President remarked that the sculpture was offensive to them.</p>
        <p>''While I thought it was a little unusual,'' said Douglas Sosnik, who was the President's traveling chief-of-staff on the trip, ''you can't go into a place and be the interior decorator police and say you don't like the color scheme or something.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fertitta said of the piano sculpture, ''It's art, it's just for fun.''</p>
        <p>The evening seemed to go without a hitch. A few hours after assailing the way campaigns are financed, in a speech at the community college, the President arrived at the Fertittas' white brick estate in the fashionable Memorial neighborhood (less than a quarter-mile from where former President George Bush built a more modest house.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was greeted by Mr. Fertitta and his wife, Paige, and their two young sons. He then mingled briefly out back, where guests were admiring the giant carving of the White House.</p>
        <p>A few minutes later, Mr. Clinton, clutching a diet Coke, stood in a photo line. It was a way for him to meet every guest personally, and for the donors to get photographs of themselves with the President.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton then joined the guests in the carport, which was converted for the night into an classy dining room, with candles in rose-decorated chandeliers. The President sat next to Mrs. Fertitta at a table in front of the room, though he wandered to another table for dessert.</p>
        <p>''We talked about family things and some issues,'' Mr. Fertitta said. ''Just normal conversation.''</p>
        <p>At the end of the meal, Mr. Solomont stood in front of an imposing Presidential seal and said, ''There are no better friends in this country to the Democratic Party and President Clinton than all of you.'' Then Mr. Fertitta introduced the President. ''All Americans are doing better today,'' he said, ''because Bill Clinton has been President.''</p>
        <p>Joking about how Mr. Fertitta had a dinner for him last year, Mr. Clinton took to the lectern and said, ''I think we ought to make this an annual thing!'' He went on for 20 minutes about the accomplishments of his Administration and the challenges ahead.</p>
        <p>Occasionally referring to index cards, Mr. Clinton also restated his belief in overhauling the way campaigns are financed. But, he assured the guests, ''I think it's a good thing you're here tonight, not a bad thing. And I'm proud of you for doing it.'' (Several of his aides said that while financial details of the event were in his briefing book, Mr. Clinton does not usually pay attention to such specifics.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton quickly departed after his remarks. Guests were given laminated copies of the menu and, on their way out, silver-plated picture frames with the White House seal in which they could put their photographs with the President.</p>
        <p>By the next morning, the dining room was transformed back into a carport. At the same table where Mr. Clinton was wined and dined, Mr. Fertitta's 5-year-old son, Michael, was feted for his birthday. The executive chefs who concocted the Clinton dinner catered the birthday party. The main course: hot dogs and hamburgers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
