<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Croatia Protects a General Charged With War Crimes</title>
    <meta content="Y03CRO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/03/international/europe/03CROA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1445500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Croatia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simpson, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bobetko, Janko (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Racan, Ivica (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Croatia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D91F38F930A35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Croatia Protects a General Charged With War Crimes</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Croatia Protects a General Charged With War Crimes</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL SIMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simpson, Daniel</byline>
      <dateline>LICKI CITLUK, Croatia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations war crimes tribunal has charged Croatia's wartime chief of staff, Gen Janko Bobetko, with crimes against humanity and demanded he be extradited to stand trial in The Hague; Croatia is refusing to hand him over, setting off dispute that highlights its problems in coming to terms with acts committed from 1991 to 1995, when it fought for independence against rebel Croatian Serbs backed by Serbia and Yugoslav Army; Prime Min Ivica Racan fears nationalist backlash that could bring down his reformist government if he hands Bobetko over; photo of Croatian Serb outside his burned-out house in village that was totally destroyed by Croatian forces in 1993; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nine years after Croatian tanks and artillery chased Djuro Pjevac and his neighbors out of this remote village, it remains a ghost town, reminiscent of countless others across the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pjevac, a 78-year-old Croatian Serb, has since returned to the rubble of a homestead he spent 50 years building, camping out in a makeshift hut the size of a small automobile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Croatia is refusing to hand over Gen. Janko Bobetko, setting off a dispute that highlights its problems in coming to terms with acts committed from 1991 to 1995.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nine years after Croatian tanks and artillery chased Djuro Pjevac and his neighbors out of this remote village, it remains a ghost town, reminiscent of countless others across the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pjevac, a 78-year-old Croatian Serb, has since returned to the rubble of a homestead he spent 50 years building, camping out in a makeshift hut the size of a small automobile.</p>
        <p>But the community he used to live in has been wiped out. In September 1993, Croatian forces set fire to every one of Licki Citluk's few dozen houses. Their former occupants, members of a Serb minority that was persecuted during World War II as well in the fighting that tore apart Yugoslavia in the 1990's, have no plans to return.</p>
        <p>''Only a nostalgic person would come back,'' Mr. Pjevac said. ''Look at the mess. A lot of people were killed here, some of them in their beds.''</p>
        <p>After the military action here, United Nations peacekeepers accused the Croatian Army of killing Serbian civilians in cold blood. But almost a decade passed without anyone being held accountable.</p>
        <p>The United Nations war crimes tribunal has now charged Croatia's wartime chief of staff, Gen. Janko Bobetko, with crimes against humanity and demanded he be extradited to stand trial in The Hague, where a genocide case against the former Serbian leader Slobodan Milosevic is already being heard.</p>
        <p>But Croatia is refusing to hand over General Bobetko, setting off a dispute that highlights its problems in coming to terms with acts committed from 1991 to 1995, when it fought for independence against rebel Croatian Serbs backed by Serbia and the Yugoslav Army.</p>
        <p>''The Croats thought The Hague was a tribunal for Serbs, and they're shocked to find that's not the case,'' said Zarko Puhovski, president of a human rights committee. ''The right-wing radicals here are sadly right in saying that no general from a winning army has ever been indicted for war crimes.''</p>
        <p>The country has reappraised the last decade since the death in 1999 of President Franjo Tudjman, the onetime Communist general who secured its independence. Nonetheless, the indictment of General Bobetko, an 83-year-old diabetic with serious heart problems who is said by doctors to be critically ill, has touched a raw nerve.</p>
        <p>Despite warnings that Croatia's hopes of eventually joining the European Union will be dashed unless it hands the general over, Prime Minister Ivica Racan has so far refused, fearing a nationalist backlash that could bring down his reformist government.</p>
        <p>The diplomatic quarrel has also raised questions about the tribunal's insensitivity to how it is perceived in the Balkans, where its actions stir fierce passions and most people close their ears to evidence against members of their ethnic group.</p>
        <p>The wording of the indictment against General Bobetko has angered many Croats, who believe it questions the legitimacy of an operation to stop Serbian artillery in an area known as the Medak Pocket from shelling nearby Croatian towns.</p>
        <p>''Janko Bobetko, acting individually and/or in concert with others, planned, instigated, ordered, committed or otherwise aided and abetted in the planning, preparation or execution of persecutions of Serb civilians of the Medak Pocket on racial, political or religious grounds,'' the indictment says.</p>
        <p>Such language, a standard formulation applied to similar cases, troubles Croats. It implies that their leaders actually planned the same sort of ''ethnic cleansing'' operations that Mr. Milosevic is accused of sanctioning. Although it remains unclear whether this was true in Licki Citluk, there is little doubt that something terrible happened.</p>
        <p>''Approximately 164 homes and 148 barns and outbuildings, being a majority of buildings in the villages within the Medak Pocket, were destroyed, mostly by fire and explosives, after the Croatian forces had taken effective control,'' the indictment adds. ''At least 100 Serbs including 29 local Serb civilians were unlawfully killed.''</p>
        <p>Any indictment would be challenged here, but one that casts doubt on the legitimacy of the Croats' fight against the Serbs, and points the finger at an ailing old man, is particularly inflammatory.</p>
        <p>A week after General Bobetko was indicted, he was made an honorary citizen of Gospic, a town known for its strong Croatian nationalism. Gospic was under Serbian artillery fire during the Croatian war, but local Serbs were also killed by Croats.</p>
        <p>Such evidence of the general's popularity has worried Mr. Racan, whose government has a narrow majority in Parliament over a resurgent nationalist-led opposition.</p>
        <p>Many political experts here worry that the sudden pressure from outside to face up to the past is backfiring.</p>
        <p>''The international community needs a normal and stable Croatia,'' said Slaven Letica, the author of several books on Croatian nationalism. ''Indictments such as this, with the terrible public relations from The Hague that accompanies it, just make the Croatian situation worse and the West more unpopular.''</p>
        <p>That said, diplomats credit The Hague's influence with bringing about two war-crimes trials here. In one, Gen. Mirko Norac is accused of crimes committed in Gospic in 1991. In the other, eight men are accused of atrocities in a military prison in Split in 1992.</p>
        <p>Although a majority of Croats surveyed by pollsters acknowledge that some soldiers committed war crimes in the fight for independence, they seem to be struggling to understand the principle of ''command responsibility'' under which General Bobetko is indicted.</p>
        <p>As commander of the armed forces, his failure to prosecute any subordinates who may have committed crimes in the Medak Pocket means he could be found guilty.</p>
        <p>Many experts believe that General Bobetko has fallen victim to the need to bring a high-ranking Croat to The Hague after Ante Gotovina, the last general to be indicted, went into hiding.</p>
        <p>But such protests do not impress the tribunal, whose chief prosecutor, Carla Del Ponte, says there are no grounds for Mr. Racan to appeal against the indictment. Hoping to stave off international sanctions, Croatia is trying to delay a decision without actually refusing to fulfill its obligation to cooperate.</p>
        <p>General Bobetko, who says he would rather die than go to The Hague, may yet be able to use his fading health to avoid a trial. ''The government is not stupid; they know they cannot challenge the indictment,'' said Mr. Letica, the author of books on Croatian nationalism. ''Their only hope is to drag this dispute out until Bobetko dies.''</p>
        <p>As winter approaches in Licki Citluk, Djuro Pjevac is unimpressed. ''Someone ordered this,'' he said, stoking the wood stove that heats his musty one-room shack and doubles as a bread oven. ''They should get what they deserve.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
