<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Today's Big-Name Playwrights Are Busy Translating the Past's</title>
    <meta content="03GOLD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THEATER" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="947990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gold, Sylviane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friel, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mamet, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frayn, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Lanford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stoppard, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chekhov, Anton (1860-1904)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibsen, Henrik (1828-1906)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGuinness, Frank</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doll's House, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Anton Chekhov</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/David Mamet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Tom Stoppard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Lanford Wilson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Michael Frayn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Henrik Ibsen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8103AF930A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="2096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Today's Big-Name Playwrights Are Busy Translating the Past's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIANE GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gold, Sylviane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big-name dramatists like Brian Friel, David Mamet, Michael Frayn, Lanford Wilson and Tom Stoppard have come to dominate rendering of great European plays into English; they are sharing billing with Chekhov, Ibsen and other masters; Frank McGuinness's version of A Doll's House, which is currently on Broadway, discussed; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REHEARSALS WERE NOT GOING WELL.  Tony Kushner's adaptation of a 17th-century French comedy by Pierre Corneille was being dogged by technical glitches. Convinced that professional jealousy from beyond the grave was at work, Mr. Kushner and the play's director, Mark Lamos, reprinted the program. They changed the title page from '' 'The Illusion' by Tony Kushner, based on a play by Pierre Corneille'' to '' 'The Illusion' by Pierre Corneille, freely adapted by Tony Kushner.''</p>
        <p>''The minute we did that,'' Mr. Kushner said, recalling the 1989 Hartford Stage production, ''all the technical problems stopped. Except the night before the opening, someone came by and pulled half the letters of my name off the marquee.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REHEARSALS WERE NOT GOING WELL.  Tony Kushner's adaptation of a 17th-century French comedy by Pierre Corneille was being dogged by technical glitches. Convinced that professional jealousy from beyond the grave was at work, Mr. Kushner and the play's director, Mark Lamos, reprinted the program. They changed the title page from '' 'The Illusion' by Tony Kushner, based on a play by Pierre Corneille'' to '' 'The Illusion' by Pierre Corneille, freely adapted by Tony Kushner.''</p>
        <p>''The minute we did that,'' Mr. Kushner said, recalling the 1989 Hartford Stage production, ''all the technical problems stopped. Except the night before the opening, someone came by and pulled half the letters of my name off the marquee.''</p>
        <p>If the ghosts of playwrights past are rattling their chains these days, it's not without reason. Big-name dramatists like Brian Friel, David Mamet, Michael Frayn, Lanford Wilson and Tom Stoppard, to name a few, have come to dominate the rendering of the great European plays into English. They are sharing billing with Chekhov, Ibsen and, yes, Corneille, and shaking up the theater's approach to the classics in the process.</p>
        <p>The most recent example on Broadway, Frank McGuinness's current vivid version of ''A Doll's House,'' which has been extended to Aug. 31, bowled over some critics with its bright language and contemporary tone. And, like most of his colleagues in the play-translation game, Mr. McGuinness accomplished his makeover without actually knowing the language of the original.</p>
        <p>Playwrights have been adapting -- and sometimes simply appropriating -- the work of foreign dramatists for centuries. Shakespeare reworked European plays, and Goethe ''translated'' Shakespeare. But the great modern translators like Constance Garnett, who brought Chekhov to the English-speaking world in the early part of this century, have been scholars, not playwrights.</p>
        <p>To Todd Haimes, whose Roundabout Theater Company regularly revives European classics for Broadway audiences, it is no surprise that ''more and more adaptations and translations are done by playwrights.''</p>
        <p>''In addition to keeping the story intact,'' he said, ''a play translation must be theatrical. And playwrights are used to writing not just good literature but plays, actable by actors and directable by directors.''</p>
        <p>In England, hiring playwrights to do new translations has become ''almost a fetish,'' said David Hare, who had a hit play, ''Skylight,'' on Broadway and a hit translation, Chekhov's ''Ivanov,'' in London last season. (A separate production, starring Kevin Kline as Ivanov, comes to Lincoln Center in October.)</p>
        <p>''You can pick a version of 'The Seagull,' '' Mr. Hare said, ''by most prominent British playwrights. It's slightly ludicrous that every time someone does a new production, they feel compelled to get a new translation.''</p>
        <p>The urge to reinvent the wheel isn't confined to England. Indeed, the British translations have prompted a similar surge in the United States. ''I'm a great believer in European plays having an American translation,'' said Robert Falls, the artistic director of the Goodman Theater in Chicago, who commissioned the American playwright Richard Nelson to translate ''The Cherry Orchard.'' ''The majority of the great classics that we've inherited were translated anywhere from 100 years ago to 40 years ago, usually by British writers. And there's a great difference between their language and American as a language.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Falls said, if he wanted to do ''A Doll's House,'' he wouldn't think of using the McGuinness version. ''I have great respect for it,'' he said. ''But it has English and Irish rhythms. Why would anyone want American actors doing a Scandinavian play with British accents?''</p>
        <p>Michael Feingold, a drama critic for The Village Voice and a professional translator of plays, said that both academics and playwrights can undermine the originals they translate. While most playwrights would shy away from rendering, as one academic did, the French command ''Kneel!'' as ''Genuflect!,'' Mr. Feingold said, he added that he had seen ''great plays ruined by both English and American playwrights because they did not understand what the original was about.''</p>
        <p>Translators who work the old-fashioned way, with a thorough grounding in the language they are translating, stress the importance of understanding the nuances of the text as well as the text itself. Still, the poet Richard Wilbur, widely regarded as the pre-eminent translator of Moliere, maintains that word-for-word translation never works. ''The kind of fidelity I've always aimed at,'' he said, ''is a thought-for-thought fidelity.''</p>
        <p>Fidelity tends to be in the eye of the beholder, however. Speaking of the recent vogue for the wry romances of the 18th-century French playwright Pierre de Marivaux, Mr. Feingold pointed out that in some translations, ''Marivaux looks very elegant and pretty, like a Fragonard painting. And then other people do him and it looks and sounds like the Three Stooges. So which one is Marivaux?''</p>
        <p>To Mr. McGuinness, there is no way to do plays of the past so that they are true to their own time. ''What was true to the time?'' he asked. ''I don't have a time machine. All I can do is an honest reading of what I see there, and to respect the central truths of the play.''</p>
        <p>The trick, of course, is figuring out what those central truths are, without being able to read the original. Before Lanford Wilson began his version of ''The Three Sisters,'' which was used last season in Scott Elliott's production at the Roundabout, he commissioned two literal translations, one from a native English speaker fluent in Russian, the other from a native Russian speaker fluent in English. He got a tape of a Moscow Art Theater production of the play, as well as the Russian text. And then he went to Berlitz, taking more than 100 hours of Russian lessons so he could use both the tape and the text in addition to the word-for-word translations.</p>
        <p>Few of his colleagues go to such lengths. They simply work from word-for-word translations provided by scholars. Stephen Wadsworth, a French-speaking opera director who has become a Marivaux specialist, tried that when he was first asked to translate and direct a Marivaux play. When he got the translation, he recalled, ''I immediately realized that it wasn't literal. There's no way that a translation can ever be literal.''</p>
        <p>The British playwright Pam Gems, whose play ''Stanley'' was presented at Circle in the Square last season, made the same discovery when working with academic translators. ''You are very often presented with the linguist's dramatic interpretation,'' she said. ''Having made my requests clear, I did manage to get an absolutely literal translation of 'Lady From the Sea,' '' by Ibsen. ''The problem is that it's often impenetrable. Languages don't cohere.''</p>
        <p>For ''Ivanov,'' Mr. Hare, who asked his translator to give him maximal rather than minimal interpretation, said he received ''all sorts of different interpretations of every line -- a wonderful sort of thesaurus of what different words could mean.''</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Gems, Mr. McGuinness demands ''a completely neutral transcription,'' he said. He tells collaborators: ''If there are stage directions which indicate how a speech is to be done, simply give me that stage direction. Don't attempt to recreate it. And be as ungrammatical as you like, be as apparently unintelligible as you like. Just give me what is coldly there, and then I can go to work on it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McGuinness, whose play ''Someone Who'll Watch Over Me,'' ran on Broadway in 1992, said he tries in his translations ''to get back to the excitement of what it must have been like to see them first; and that means getting back to the passion.''</p>
        <p>TO ALLOW A 20TH-CENTURY AUDIENCE  at ''A Doll's House'' to see what Nora loved about her overbearing, 19th-century husband, Mr. McGuinness felt he had to reshape the character of Torvald by cutting some of his more bullying lines. ''There are monstrous elements in him,'' the writer said, ''but there are good things in him as well. I didn't want to load the dice incredibly heavily against him.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gems faced the same problem in her ''Doll's House.''  ''If he's just an ogre,'' she said, ''who wouldn't leave him? He's a perfect Victorian husband -- he's honest, he's hard-working, he's obviously sexy. But I didn't cut his lines; instead, we cast an extremely handsome young Nordic actor. So when he said those lines, you simply felt maternal.'' Still, she understood, she said, what impelled Mr. McGuinness to cut the text. ''It is a problem when you're dealing with mores that have changed so much,'' she noted.</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees that the public needs help when confronting works of the past. Mr. Wilbur, for example, said he does not ''try to adjust Moliere to the contemporary audience except by using plain, clear language.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. McGuinness defended his fiddling with Ibsen's portrayal of Torvald. ''If I had set out to do a strictly scholarly exercise,'' he said, ''then what I have done I would judge as being wrong. But I'm not out to teach people about Ibsen; I'm out to entertain -- and to make an exciting play that conveys some of the shock it must have had when it first opened.''</p>
        <p>Although all involved say the practice of enlisting playwrights to refresh the classics is meant to serve theatergoers, the writers get more from the exercise than their royalties. Mr. Wilson said he found translating helpful in getting through dry spells in his own work. For Mr. Hare, it has provided a substitute for directing, allowing him to conceive productions in his head. For Mr. Kushner, it is ''an opportunity to examine a dramatic problem purely on the level of form.''</p>
        <p>However you look at it, Ms. Gems said, ''It's like practicing your Chopin: you can only be enriched by it.'' Sometimes, she said, the enrichment is not entirely welcome. She recalled that when her play ''Aunt Mary'' was in rehearsal, a well-known Japanese director asked if he could sit in. After watching the play, about a pair of transvestites whose lives are turned topsy-turvy by the arrival of a young woman in their lives, the director said to Ms. Gems, ''This is 'Vanya,' no?''</p>
        <p>''I was shattered,'' the playwright said. ''Totally shattered. Because I had just finished working on my version of 'Uncle Vanya.' And I hadn't realized it, but despite the totally different milieu, the theme I'd used was very similar.''</p>
        <p>If traces of Chekhov turn up in the works of playwrights translating them, the reverse can happen as well. When Chekhov wrote ''Ivanov,'' Mr. Hare said, ''he was a young playwright, and technically immature.'' He left one of the play's subplots unresolved, Mr. Hare said, ''so I wrote an end to that plot.''</p>
        <p>''Given the fact that Chekhov redrafted Act IV many times, and it's the act of the play that he was least satisfied with, I didn't have a bad conscience about it,'' Mr. Hare said. ''I felt that Anton would be perfectly happy that I had solved a problem which had somehow eluded him.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kushner felt equally justified in restructuring S. Ansky's ''Dybbuk,'' which was done at Hartford Stage in 1995 and will be produced this season at the Joseph Papp Public Theater beginning in October. ''It's immensely effective,'' he said, ''but most people remember it as this astounding love story, and it's probably the only love story in all of Western literature in which the lovers have, I think, three lines together on the stage. It's really clumsily constructed, because Ansky was an ethnographer and not really a dramatist.''</p>
        <p>To Mr. Haimes at the Roundabout, tinkering is justified if it can bring a classic to life. ''Any time an adapter takes a 200-year-old play and manages to thrill a contemporary audience, that playwright is getting his due,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The playwright-adapters agree, and don't flinch from the implications for their own work. ''In 10 or 15 years,'' Mr. McGuinness said of his ''Doll's House,'' ''my version will have dated. But Ibsen will never date. And somebody else will come along and they will do him in the language of their time. Because our language is constantly changing.''</p>
        <p>After he is dead, said Mr. Kushner, adapters and translators can do to him what he did to Corneille. ''Then, it's fair game,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
