<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing Against the Urge to Be Instantly Lovable</title>
    <meta content="03WINT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FILM" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="947992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Popular Entertainers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Katrin Cartlidge</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cartlidge, Katrin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winters, Laura</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Career Girls (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Naked (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Before the Rain (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Breaking the Waves (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D8103AF930A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="1482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing Against the Urge to Be Instantly Lovable</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA WINTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winters, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on films of British actress Katrin Cartlidge, including her latest movie, Career Girls; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BRITISH ACTRESS Katrin Cartlidge made her debut in feature films only four years ago, but her resume already reads like a list of contemporary classics. In that brief time, she has been featured in three of the most acclaimed European films of the 1990's: Mike Leigh's ''Naked,'' Milcho Manchevski's ''Before the Rain'' and Lars von Trier's ''Breaking the Waves.''</p>
        <p>As those titles would indicate, the 36-year-old actress, who worked in theater before turning to film, is known in the United States primarily to art-house audiences. But because of the international scope of her roles -- the fact that she has worked with Mr. Manchevski, who is from Macedonia, and Mr. von Trier, who is Danish -- she is much more familiar across Europe. In fact, she is generally thought of as a European actress rather than simply a British one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BRITISH ACTRESS Katrin Cartlidge made her debut in feature films only four years ago, but her resume already reads like a list of contemporary classics. In that brief time, she has been featured in three of the most acclaimed European films of the 1990's: Mike Leigh's ''Naked,'' Milcho Manchevski's ''Before the Rain'' and Lars von Trier's ''Breaking the Waves.''</p>
        <p>As those titles would indicate, the 36-year-old actress, who worked in theater before turning to film, is known in the United States primarily to art-house audiences. But because of the international scope of her roles -- the fact that she has worked with Mr. Manchevski, who is from Macedonia, and Mr. von Trier, who is Danish -- she is much more familiar across Europe. In fact, she is generally thought of as a European actress rather than simply a British one.</p>
        <p>''There's a sort of paradox about Katrin,'' said Simon Perry, the chief executive of British Screen, a company that helped finance ''Naked'' and ''Before the Rain.''  ''She is very English, with her quiet seriousness and self-deprecating humor, but the range of her look allows her to play characters of almost any European nationality or period.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cartlidge, who is slim and coltish, with large soulful eyes, is likely to be better known everywhere after ''Career Girls,'' Mr. Leigh's new film, opens on Friday. For one thing, moviegoers will find out what Ms. Cartlidge's friends have long known: she is very funny. Previously, she has been noted for playing dark, haunted women. In ''Career Girls,'' a bittersweet tale about two friends from college who spend a weekend together years later, she gets to add a bit of comedy to the mix -- though, this being a Mike Leigh film, the darkness is there, too.</p>
        <p>''Katrin is in a class by herself,'' said Mr. Leigh. ''She's extremely intelligent, and has an individual and anarchic attitude toward life and society in general. But at the same time she has this huge sense of humor.''</p>
        <p>Sitting in a West Broadway cafe the other day, Ms. Cartlidge looked appropriately eclectic, dressed in a white brocade vest and flowing beige trousers, carrying a small pink gingham knapsack. She spoke about Hannah, her character in ''Career Girls,'' as if she were a wayward friend who might stroll through the door at any moment. ''She's so cheeky,'' Ms. Cartlidge said with a laugh. ''She's a really naughty woman.''</p>
        <p>At one point in the film, Hannah, a woman who has adapted to the corporate world but is still an articulate hell raiser, walks into a luxury apartment and says nonchalantly, ''I suppose on a clear day you can see the class struggle from here.'' One wouldn't put it past Ms. Cartlidge, who has a rambunctious wit, to say that kind of thing in real life.</p>
        <p>In ''Career Girls,'' Hannah and the quieter Annie (Lynda Steadman) renew their friendship over a couple of days in contemporary London, but the film also includes flashbacks to their college days, when they were odd-couple roommates. This structure required Ms. Cartlidge to portray Hannah both as a maladjusted, verbally brutal student and as a polished but lonely career woman. ''You always wonder about a character's past when you play her,'' she said. ''I loved thinking about where Hannah's anger went as she got older and started wearing those pin-striped jackets. It's almost as if the anger becomes incisive and linear instead of volcanic.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cartlidge is, of course, experienced at untangling deeply snarled inner lives. In ''Naked,'' she was the druggie temptress Sophie, the role for which she won a prize as most promising European actress at the 1993 Geneva Film Festival. In ''Before the Rain,'' which shared the top award at the 1994 Venice Film Festival and was nominated for an Academy Award, she played Anne, a married British photography editor who falls in love with a maverick photojournalist. In ''Breaking the Waves,'' which won the Grand Prix at the 1996 Cannes festival, she played Dodo, the repressed sister-in-law of Emily Watson's passionate Bess.</p>
        <p>Dodo was a real departure for Ms. Cartlidge. ''It was like being put in a straitjacket,'' she said. ''But I wanted to explore this 'sensible' character and uncover her many layers: altruism, selfishness, sadness.''</p>
        <p>IMAGE DOES NOT FIGURE  high in Ms. Cartlidge's concerns. ''Katrin doesn't run away from a character's quirks or try to be instantly cute or likable, as some actresses do,'' said Mr. Manchevski.</p>
        <p>Instead, she zeroes in on a character's foibles. ''I think it's wonderful that women can start playing characters with more than a couple of sides, some of them not pleasant,'' she said. ''Audiences are not used to seeing characters like Hannah or Sophie, who are not trying to get us to fall in love with them. But why do we always have to fall in love with our leading ladies? Why can't we be just intrigued, or puzzled, or horrified, or amused?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cartlidge's interest in exploring vulnerability stems in part from her family history. Her mother is a German-Jewish refugee who fled Berlin as a girl in 1938; as a baby, her father was a foundling, literally left on the steps of an orphanage. Ms. Cartlidge grew up in London, where her father owned a small moving company. Her mother is a jewelry designer.</p>
        <p>Though her family is a close and happy one, Ms. Cartlidge has been influenced in a visceral way by the difficulties of her parents' early lives. When she told about her first visit to Berlin, a few weeks before, and seeing a house where her mother had lived, her eyes filled with tears. ''Seeing Berlin made me realize that the Second World War was just five minutes ago, literally,'' she said. ''I think because of that background I can never forget that human behavior can produce both enormous acts of heroism or enormous acts of cruelty. I suppose I am driven to projects, like 'Before the Rain' and 'Breaking the Waves,' which actually plumb the facade of society and show it to be just that: a facade.''</p>
        <p>As a child, Ms. Cartlidge was dyslexic, though this went undiscovered until she was in her teens. By then, she was disenchanted with school. She joined the Royal Court Youth Theater and concentrated on acting.</p>
        <p>In her early 20's, Ms. Cartlidge began to develop her taste for offbeat projects. She recalled touring suburban Manchester schools in a five-person production of ''Don Quixote,'' which was put on ''in the dinner halls, amid the mashed potatoes.'' But she also started to work in mainstream theater in London, acting at the Royal Court and at the Royal National Theater.</p>
        <p>One night in 1985, performing in London in a new play, she caught the eye of Mr. Leigh, but the right collaboration didn't come along until 1992, when he asked her to be in ''Naked.'' Overnight, she shifted from theater to film. She is still, however, someone who chooses jobs according to what they offer her creatively. ''I don't like doing work for the money,'' she said. ''If I did, I would have been able to buy my flat by now.'' (She lives in London, near Hampstead Heath, with her boyfriend of several years, a drama student from South Africa.)</p>
        <p>When asked if she would like to work in Hollywood, Ms. Cartlidge smiled and said, ''For me, Hollywood's just a place.''</p>
        <p>Such a professional attitude may well be unusual, but what clearly matters most to Ms. Cartlidge is the rock-bottom joy of acting itself. ''More than any other actor I know, Katrin will celebrate the whole process,'' Mr. Leigh said. ''When she was working on Hannah, she would constantly say: 'God, she's so great. Isn't she fun?' It's exhilarating to come upon someone who makes it fresh yet another time.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cartlidge does indeed seem to know how she wants to live her life. And she doesn't seem afraid of the passage of time, which distinguishes her from many other actresses. '' 'Career Girls' is about a couple of women who get older,'' she said. ''I actually love getting older. I hated my 20's; I couldn't wait to be 30. I'm really looking forward to turning 40, if I get there. And not just because things are more successful now, but because I think the older you get, the more you find life interesting apart from your own problems.''</p>
        <p>She laughed and made a gesture as if ushering in time. ''So roll on,'' she said. ''I can't wait.''</p>
        <p>FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
