<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hero Rides Into the Sunset. So Let Him Go.</title>
    <meta content="03LIPS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BACKTALK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="948269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BACKTALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vancouver Canucks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Messier, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Vancouver Canucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D9123DF930A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hero Rides Into the Sunset. So Let Him Go.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Robert Lipsyte welcomes New Rangers' captain Mark Messier's decision to go to Vancouver Canucks; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like Shane, he came out of the great glowing heart of the West and after he saved us he moved on. This is the only way to think about Mark Messier. This is not about money, it is about myth. I am glad he has gone to Vancouver, which is about as far away as he could go. I did not want to see Mess grow old on our ice.</p>
        <p>It also gives me pleasure to believe that Messier, wounded and past his prime -- like Shane after he beat the cattle baron's gunslingers and made the land safe for sodbusters -- wanted to spare us seeing him iced by young blades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like Shane, he came out of the great glowing heart of the West and after he saved us he moved on. This is the only way to think about Mark Messier. This is not about money, it is about myth. I am glad he has gone to Vancouver, which is about as far away as he could go. I did not want to see Mess grow old on our ice.</p>
        <p>It also gives me pleasure to believe that Messier, wounded and past his prime -- like Shane after he beat the cattle baron's gunslingers and made the land safe for sodbusters -- wanted to spare us seeing him iced by young blades.</p>
        <p>This is strictly fandom from Hallmark, I know, but we do owe this man, even if Madison Square Garden doesn't think that it does. Messier delivered. (Did Pat Riley? Patrick Ewing? Will Bill Parcells again?) It was the only Stanley Cup in most of our lifetimes. So cut me some slack for buying the sentimental notion that Messier went to the Far West rather than to the Caps to reduce the number of confrontations with his old teammates.</p>
        <p>Mess was always a mean and sneaky stick; as he grew older, the sly moves made up for his loss of speed. As a Canuck, he will rarely have to trip Brian Leetch, drive an elbow into Adam Graves or even, melt the thought, put a stick into Wayne Gretzky's wise-child face.</p>
        <p>I think I have reached my personal Pain Cap with Mess's leaving. This has not been a good month for local heroes. First, our home-grown Kid Dynamite imploded. Mike Tyson turned out not to be as tough as his Brooklyn neighborhood, although he showed that he hadn't forgotten how to survive. Faced with certain defeat to Evander Holyfield (who is so boring that Mills Lane, the referee, was the most bankable star who came out of that fight), Tyson managed to inflict damage and disqualify himself from humiliation.</p>
        <p>He also displayed the kind of wildness that will intimidate opponents in and out of the ring for years to come. The ear jokes are no joke; this troubled man is being set up to destruct before our eyes, probably on pay-per-view with Don King getting a piece. That is, if Tyson doesn't declare emotional bankruptcy by racking up on a motorcycle first.</p>
        <p>Our alien hero, Hideki Irabu, the savior from the East, was sent to the minor leagues to learn control and humility. He should have taken George Steinbrenner with him. During the hiatus, the Boss might check his wishful radar gun (a how-many-miles-an-hour fastball?) and his intelligence service. How could he shell out $12.8 million without a thorough background report?</p>
        <p>So, was Irabu's biological father really an American soldier? Does it matter, even in as racially polarized a society as Japan? Should we local media start taking cues from the Japanese media (''the locusts,'' according to Irabu) who have backed off asking him any questions he does not want to answer?</p>
        <p>Irabu had hardly gone (sayonara before the Cy Young) when one of my faves, Joe Namath, showed at the Jets' camp. That blast from the past allowed reporters to goad him into chiding Keyshawn Johnson for speaking too freely about team politics in his autobiography. Did Broadway Joe do it to jack the sales of Johnson's forgotten book, to sell Jets tickets, to promote his own TV sportscasting ratings? Does Joe want to take over some of Marv Albert's now-jeopardized gigs?</p>
        <p>Albert was a local hero, too, and a major talent, although a little soft on Patrick Ewing for my taste. How could the Garden's budget guards keep the Knicks' mediocre center but let the Rangers' great center go? If they were going to dump Mess, they should have done it before they bought his old playmate Gretzky.</p>
        <p>They should have concentrated on young players instead of trying to recondition a secondhand team. But, hey, Neil Smith was as critical to that Stanley Cup as Messier or Coach Mike Keenan.</p>
        <p>This is the Samurai Age in sports, and if Roger Clemens can leave Boston and Shaq can turn his back on Orlando, then we should have the good grace to wish Messier well. I will not root for the Canucks but I will root for Captain Dad, New York's most complete, dedicated, interesting and honorable 90's superstar.</p>
        <p>Even though the western is coming back (the proposed CBS series ''The Magnificent Seven'' is not based on the 1969-70 Knicks), it would have been a shame to watch another season of Wayne and Mess, the Young Guns of Edmonton, struggle to act out the Return of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid. The melting of those two legends into one another would have produced not the welcome replay of those early years but a weary continuation of their overtime. It would have been Butch and Sundance gunned down in Bolivia and bleeding out on the Garden ice in agonizingly slow motion.</p>
        <p>BACKTALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
