<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. O'Neal, Take Note: 6-8, 248-Pound Comer</title>
    <meta content="10BRAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASKETBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peekskill (NY)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Elton Brand</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markowitz, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brand, Elton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4D81638F933A25752C0A961958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. O'Neal, Take Note: 6-8, 248-Pound Comer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN MARKOWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markowitz, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>PEEKSKILL, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Elton Brand, Peekskill (NY) High School's star basketball player, who is six feet, eight inches tall and weighs 248 pounds; Brand is headed for Duke University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the first play of the first home game of this, his senior season, the hometown fans called out for one of Elton Brand's signature slams. Brand, who is 6 feet 8 inches and weighs 248 pounds, received an alley-oop pass and slammed it over the rim and through the twine. The packed gymnasium at Peekskill High School went wild.</p>
        <p>''I heard a lot of them yelling for me to dunk it on them hard,'' Brand said later. ''I feel I owe it to them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the first play of the first home game of this, his senior season, the hometown fans called out for one of Elton Brand's signature slams. Brand, who is 6 feet 8 inches and weighs 248 pounds, received an alley-oop pass and slammed it over the rim and through the twine. The packed gymnasium at Peekskill High School went wild.</p>
        <p>''I heard a lot of them yelling for me to dunk it on them hard,'' Brand said later. ''I feel I owe it to them.''</p>
        <p>Unnoticed by many of those same fans was the sight of Brand tucking in his jersey at the request of his coach, Lou Panzanaro, as Brand ran upcourt.</p>
        <p>''Little kids are impressionable,'' said the 17-year-old Brand. ''Coach doesn't want me to wear my shirt out. He thought all the little kids would start doing that. We don't want them to be sloppy.''</p>
        <p>Brand will bring his fierce but clean game to Madison Square Garden tomorrow when he will square off against Marist High School's 6-10 James Felton, who has given a commitment to St. John's, in what is being billed as the Elton vs. Felton Show. The game is part of the second Sprite Super 6 high school tripleheader. St. Patrick's will play St. Raymond's at 11 A.M., followed by St. Anthony-Christ the King at 1 P.M. and Marist-Peekskill at 3 P.M.</p>
        <p>Brand is so massive, strong and relentless that once he receives the ball inside, he is virtually unstoppable. With the possible exception of Rodney McCray when he played for Mount Vernon High School in the 1970's, Brand is the best big man to come out of Westchester County. Rick Pitino of Kentucky and Steve Lappas of Villanova coveted him, but Brand gave his oral commitment to Mike Krzyzewski and Duke.</p>
        <p>Before last summer, scouts rated Brand among the nation's top 50 players. But after he manhandled California's 6-10 golden boy, Chris Burgess, for a week at the Nike summer camp, Brand was rated the third-best player at the camp, and the scouts called him a warrior. A warrior, yes, but a peaceful one.</p>
        <p>''I try to keep my temper,'' Brand said. ''Other guys curse at the ref and their coaches. I won't be seen doing anything like that.''</p>
        <p>He has maintained an 88.4 grade average in high school while taking a number of honors classes and is ranked 16th in a class of 160 students.</p>
        <p>''I feel very fortunate to be involved with Elton and everything he has brought to our program,'' said Panzanaro, who is in his 22d season coaching the varsity squad. ''He created an attitude, an atmosphere.''</p>
        <p>Since Brand played on the varsity when he was in ninth grade, Peekskill has been a winner. In the first quarter of the Section I (Westchester, Rockland, Dutchess and Putnam Counties) championship game that season, Brand told Panzanaro: ''I've got to see a dentist. I can't find my tooth.'' Brand left the court and Panzanaro said he told his assistant coach, ''We're in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Less than a minute later, Panzanaro felt a tap on his shoulder. It was Brand. ''Coach, I can play,'' Panzanaro recalled Brand's telling him. ''I found my tooth. It was stuck in the roof of my mouth. I put it back in place.''</p>
        <p>Brand scored 21 points and grabbed 15 rebounds, but Peekskill lost. The last two seasons have ended differently as the Red Devils won State Class C and B titles, respectively. Since Brand's freshman season, Peekskill has had a record of 73-13 and Brand has scored 1,675 points as he closes in on the former Peekskill star Todd Scott's Westchester scoring record of 2,057. The team is off to a rough 5-4 start this season, all four losses coming against elite teams during holiday tournaments in Florida and Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Daisy Brand raised Elton and his half-brother, Artie, who is nine years older than Elton, as a single parent and has stressed the importance of religion.</p>
        <p>''Going to church has had a peaceful effect on me,'' Brand said. ''I just don't seem to get upset. When I do, I usually keep it inside of me and use it when I'm playing.</p>
        <p>''But I tell my mom: 'Right now, I'm just a teen-ager. I know you want me to live for the Lord. But just like you found out your own way that was what you wanted to do, let me find out that way, too.' ''</p>
        <p>Opposing players are finding it dangerous to get caught under the hoop during a signature Brand slam. But at least they won't have to worry about listening to a mouthful of trash talk from him while running back up the court. He won't be seen doing anything like that.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
