<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Low-Maintenance' Ward Is Happy to Step In When Needed</title>
    <meta content="10KNIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASKETBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Childs, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E3D71638F933A25752C0A961958260" item-length="449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Low-Maintenance' Ward Is Happy to Step In When Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., Jan. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charlie Ward will relinquish his role as starting point guard for New York Knicks when Chris Childs returns to action (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The view from the top of the key is very different than the view from the bench, as Charlie Ward may soon find out.</p>
        <p>He will again relinquish the role as the New York starting point guard if Chris Childs returns to action, as expected, when the Knicks play the Celtics in Boston on Friday night. This, however, is not something that Ward is unaccustomed to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The view from the top of the key is very different than the view from the bench, as Charlie Ward may soon find out.</p>
        <p>He will again relinquish the role as the New York starting point guard if Chris Childs returns to action, as expected, when the Knicks play the Celtics in Boston on Friday night. This, however, is not something that Ward is unaccustomed to.</p>
        <p>Ward, in his third season with the Knicks, started 13 games at the beginning of the season when Childs was sidelined with a fractured leg he sustained in the preseason. And when Childs left last week's game against Atlanta with back spasms, Ward was again called upon to fill in.</p>
        <p>He started both of the Knicks' home victories this week -- against Milwaukee Sunday and Dallas Tuesday. In 41 minutes against the Bucks, he scored  10 points and also notched 9 assists. Against the Mavericks, he played 26 minutes, scoring 5 points and adding 7 assists. All in all, not too bad.</p>
        <p>''I think that any time you go from starting to the bench it is difficult,'' Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy said. ''But Charlie has handled it well. Charlie is not the kind of guy who causes you problems. There are so many high-maintenance players in today's N.B.A. who would have a tough time with that. Charlie is one of the low-maintenance guys; he's easy to deal with.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks have a 24-9 record this season and are 11-4 with Ward as their starting point guard. Childs, in his first season with the Knicks, is shooting 48.3 percent from the floor and is averaging 10.6 points and 6 assists a game. But more important, he has already emerged as a player the team can depend on in clutch moments.</p>
        <p>And that leaves Ward to sit and watch as Childs runs the show, provided Childs is healthy.</p>
        <p>''I'm enjoying playing when I have the chance,'' Ward said. ''I have been given the chance to play and I'm learning. I'm O.K. with it.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>LARRY JOHNSON pulled his hamstring against the Bucks Sunday night and is not expected to play in the Knicks' games Friday and Saturday against the Celtics.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
