<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="670224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E0D9133BF931A15751C0A962958260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. is preparing to order a further reduction in cable television rates of 6 to 10 percent, a high-ranking agency official said. Last April, the agency adopoted rules intended to cut rates by 10 percent across the board, but angry customers have protested that their bills went up rather than down.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>The F.C.C. is preparing to order a further reduction in cable television rates of 6 to 10 percent, a high-ranking agency official said. Last April, the agency adopoted rules intended to cut rates by 10 percent across the board, but angry customers have protested that their bills went up rather than down.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Alan Greenspan reports to Congress today at an awkward time: bond traders are pushing up long-term interest rates while the Federal Reserve is trying to avoid another rate increase.  [ D1. ] International</p>
        <p>Rover's transformation from a state-owned money loser to a prize for BMW is an example of how many British companies have emerged from privatization in the 1980's stronger and more nimble.</p>
        <p>[ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Honda Motor plans to cut its ties to Rover, eventually selling its 20 percent stake, in response to BWM's purchase of the controlling interest in its European partner.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Mexico's economy grew only four-tenths of 1 percent last year, the weakest performance in the five years of President Carlos Salinas de Gortari's administration. The Government had projected an increase of 1.1. percent.  [ D9. ]</p>
        <p>Japan has decided to postpone, for as long as 20 years, a series of multibillion-dollar nuclear power projects.  [ A2. ] Companies</p>
        <p>After a setback last year, Dell Computer is returning to the notebook market with five new models. The product introduction is the company's first step in an effort to become a power in the portable computer business.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Acura NSX owners are suing Honda, and the U.S. is investigating why rear tires on some NSX sports cars wear out so quickly. In some cases, tires on the $65,000 model have been found bald of tread after a few thousand miles. Honda says the specially designed Yokohama tires are the best it can put on the car.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>U.S. Surgical's troubles may be a case of an upstart company that grew too big for its niche. The medical products company, which is dangerously strapped for cash, is negotiating with creditors and seeking equity investors.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A court document shows that Deloitte &amp; Touche auditors who read prospectuses for a series of energy partnerships sold by Prudential Securities never learned about significant details of an accounting tactic that Prudential said it had disclosed but that some investors called a secret fraud.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The Japanese company at the center of the trade dispute between the United States and Japan denied there was an effort to keep Motorola out of the Japanese market. The president of the company known as IDO criticized Motorola and Washington for precipitating the crisis over cellular telephone service.  [ D2. ]  Canada is allowing Paramount Communications to acquire two educational publishers. The decision by the Liberal Government has provoked protests about American control of the media.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Walt Disney's plans to build an American history theme park in northern Virginia have stirred a debate in the state.  [ A17. ] Markets</p>
        <p>In foreign markets, the dollar rose against the yen, while prices of United States Treasury bonds and other securities continued to drop. Markets in the United States were closed in observance of Washington's Birthday.  [ D6. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Enthusiasm for skating has been fueled by the Winter Olympics and the National Hockey League's growth. That is good news for companies that manufacture ice skates, including two giants whose shares are publicly traded. Market Place.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Is there truth in advertising? Twenty new questions on that age-old conundrum. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D8. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
