<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="670301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DE103BF931A15751C0A962958260" item-length="646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CUNY TOURNAMENT Baruch Faces Staten Island Point guard Jimmy Resvanis scored 19 points, including the 1,000th of his career, and a backcourt mate, Gerald Thomas, added 17 points and 7 assists as Baruch (9-14) beat Medgar Evers (8-15) and advanced to the semifinals of the 29th annual CUNY/Con Edison tournament at Lehman College in Manhattan yesterday. Baruch, which tomorrow night will oppose Staten Island (13-10), a 75-64 victor over City College, led by 34-30 at the half and then hit four 3-pointers for a 46-36 advantage that was never squandered. In its game, Staten Island led throughout, although it was close. Kirk Staine led the Dolphins with 21 points and Rommel Santos added 15. City's Earl Hernandez led all scorers with 26 points. The Beavers finished 7-17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CUNY TOURNAMENT Baruch Faces Staten Island Point guard Jimmy Resvanis scored 19 points, including the 1,000th of his career, and a backcourt mate, Gerald Thomas, added 17 points and 7 assists as Baruch (9-14) beat Medgar Evers (8-15) and advanced to the semifinals of the 29th annual CUNY/Con Edison tournament at Lehman College in Manhattan yesterday. Baruch, which tomorrow night will oppose Staten Island (13-10), a 75-64 victor over City College, led by 34-30 at the half and then hit four 3-pointers for a 46-36 advantage that was never squandered. In its game, Staten Island led throughout, although it was close. Kirk Staine led the Dolphins with 21 points and Rommel Santos added 15. City's Earl Hernandez led all scorers with 26 points. The Beavers finished 7-17.</p>
        <p>Shawn McCartney scored 25 points and Brian Palacio added 21 points and 10 rebounds as Hunter (23-2), ranked No. 8 in the nation by The Division III News, crushed John Jay (12-11), 120-77. The Hawks, who led by as many as 49 points, had five players in double figures. In tommorow's second semifinal, Hunter will face York (15-10), which defeated Lehman, 93-86. Hunter was paced by Antoine Morris's career-high 31 points. The Cardinals, who had seven players in double figures, led by as many as 17 points in the second half, only to see Lehman (16-8) cut the deficit to 87-83 late in the game. HORSE RACING Koluctoo Jimmy Al Wins Koluctoo Jimmy Al took the lead on the far turn and scored a four-length victory over Michelle Can Pass in the Stymie Handicap yesterday at Aqueduct. With Jorge Chavez aboard, Koluctoo Jimmy Al covered the mile and an eighth in 1:504/5 and returned $9.60, $4 and $3.20 for $2 across the board. Michelle Can Pass, the favorite in the 11-horse field and ridden by John Velazquez, overcame a bumping incident at the start to finish second. Federal Funds, coupled in the wagering with Jacksonport and ridden by Rafael Mojica Jr., was third. (AP) N.H.L. A Shootout in Philadelphia Rod Brind'Amour, Brent Fedyk and Eric Lindros each scored twice in Philadelphia as the Flyers beat the Montreal Canadiens, 8-7, last night. Montreal goaltender Patrick Roy was benched after the first 30:05, with Philadelphia ahead 6-4 on five power-play goals and one at even strength. The Flyers quickly responded with a power-play goal against Ron Tugnutt. The Canadiens closed within 7-6 at 6:01 of the third on Patrice Brisebois's unassisted goal before Lindros scored his second of the night 1:56 later. (AP) Maple Leafs 6, Kings 4: Doug Gilmour scored twice in the final 5:17, highlighting a five-goal third period that rallied visiting Toronto over Los Angeles. Wayne Gretzky scored two goals 97 seconds apart in the second period to give Los Angeles a 3-1 lead before the Kings fell apart and lost their fifth straight. Before the game, the National Hockey League suspended Kings defenseman Marty McSorley for his role in an eye-gouging incident against San Jose's Bob Errey on Saturday. (AP) Sabres 2, Nordiques 1: Yuri Khmylev scored the game-winning goal in the second period as Buffalo extended its unbeaten streak to four games with a victory over visiting Quebec. Sabres goalie Dominik Hasek, who kicked aside 33 shots, made several high-quality saves in the third period to secure the victory. (AP)</p>
        <p>Dallas 6, San Jose 3: Mike Modano scored three goals, including a tie-breaking goal in the third period, to spark visiting Dallas over San Jose. The Stars extended their winning streak to seven games, a franchise record. (AP) TENNIS Volkov, Novacek Gain Andrei Volkov of Russia, the sixth seed, beat Italy's Diego Nargiso, 3-6, 6-4, 6-4, yesterday to advance to the second round of the Rotterdam indoor tennis tournament. Seventh-seeded Karel Novacek defeated the qualifier Alex Antonitsch of Austria, 6-4, 7-5. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
