<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goutweed Proves a Hardy Foe for Gardeners</title>
    <meta content="12CUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DB123FF931A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goutweed Proves a Hardy Foe for Gardeners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I HAVE been battling a mysterious weed for more than 10 years now. It first showed up in my garden in St. James on Long Island when it crept up from the marshy banks of the Nissequogue River toward my shrub roses.</p>
        <p>I ignored it. The locals called it water locust, and talked vaguely of it being poisonous. But it was rather pretty, its serrated compound leaves arranged in threes around a 10-inch stem, with a flower much like Queen Anne's lace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I HAVE been battling a mysterious weed for more than 10 years now. It first showed up in my garden in St. James on Long Island when it crept up from the marshy banks of the Nissequogue River toward my shrub roses.</p>
        <p>I ignored it. The locals called it water locust, and talked vaguely of it being poisonous. But it was rather pretty, its serrated compound leaves arranged in threes around a 10-inch stem, with a flower much like Queen Anne's lace.</p>
        <p>Little did I know that this scourge would follow me, in bits and pieces of root that clung to my roses and lilies, when I moved a few favorite plants to my family's farm in Maryland.</p>
        <p>Though you may not have this particular weed, you may do battle with one quite similar, so here are my lessons learned. First, because I failed to go after every new shoot with a sharp-bladed hand weeder, its vigorous rhizomes quickly spread through my roses and butterfly bushes, my irises and coneflowers. It strangled my columbine and bleeding hearts. It made lemon balm -- the most aggressive mint I've ever met -- appear meek by comparison.</p>
        <p>Finally, I dug up this monster, which was not yet in bloom, and went off to my local extension agent.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to identify without the flower, but it looks like it's in the umbelliferae, or carrot family,'' said the agent, Bryan Butler. No wonder its flower looks like a wild carrot blossom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Butler suggested using Roundup, or glyphosate, a weed-killer that breaks down fairly quickly. ''I put on a latex glove, with a cloth glove over that,'' he said. ''Dip my hand in the Roundup, and draw it across the leaf.''</p>
        <p>I've killed poison ivy this way, because I'm so allergic to that vine, but I prefer to use organic methods wherever possible.</p>
        <p>''Well, then you'll have to dig it up,'' Mr. Butler said. ''If you keep at it, finally the roots will die.'' He also suggested plowing the soil over and exposing the roots to the sun; then repeating this exercise every two weeks. I could see Mr. Butler was used to advising farmers.</p>
        <p>''But this is a perennial bed,'' I explained. ''And chopping it up seems to encourage it.''</p>
        <p>Even more determined to find out its identity, I took it over to the National Arboretum in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Looks like angelica,'' said Kevin Conrad, a horticulturist there. ''I don't think so,'' I said, thinking of that graceful plant that can tower over your head. ''This plant is about a foot tall. And it proliferates by runners, underground.''</p>
        <p>''Hmmm,'' he said. ''We'll have to wait until it flowers.''</p>
        <p>I took him the entire plant, flowers and all, and then sent some seeds for good measure.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later, I got a letter from Dr. Alan Whittemore, neatly typed on United States Department of Agriculture stationery.</p>
        <p>''Your mysterious weed is goutweed, Aegopodium podagraria,'' Dr. Whittemore, a botanist, wrote. ''Also known as bishop-weed and ground elder.''</p>
        <p>Once very common in gardens, with a variegated form with white-bordered leaflets called snow-on-the-mountain, aegopodium is ''still used in the trade as a ground cover for difficult areas,'' he wrote. ''It's said to be tolerant of heavy clays and damp, shady conditions.''</p>
        <p>No kidding. It is also ''hard to contain and very difficult to eradicate once it's established,'' he wrote. A native of western Europe, the tender leaves were once eaten as salad, or cooked like spinach. In the Middle Ages, he continued, ''an infusion was made to treat arthritis, rheumatism, intestinal or bladder ailments, and used externally on burns, stings and hemorrhoids.''</p>
        <p>I began to look at this hideous takeover as the beginning of my farm for the healing arts. However, Dr. Whittemore added, ''I doubt if it is really effective for any of these; medieval medicine was notoriously poor.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, I got some practical advice on a visit to several gardeners in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''The only solution is to move,'' said one, Liz Blum.</p>
        <p>Another, Henry Homeyer, shook his head at the grim job ahead of me. His own battle with goutweed began when a friend gave him some irises. He tried weeding out every root and leaf. But the next year, it would be back again, as strong as ever. ''But I did beat it finally. It's been two years, and I'm still goutweed free.'' Here's how he did it. Ruthlessly, he threw out most of his iris.</p>
        <p>''The roots of the goutweed are so insidious,'' he said. The ones he could clean, he planted in big plastic pots for a whole year. If the goutweed didn't come back, he replanted them.</p>
        <p>But that first excavation day, he dug a foot of soil out of the entire 20- by 10-foot bed, and carted it 100 yards away behind his apple tree. ''I dumped it on four-mil plastic -- dirt, roots and plants -- and wrapped it up like a Christmas present,'' he said.  ''Then I weighed it down with clean dirt, so there was no escaping.'' It sits there still, ''in perpetuity, like a toxic waste dump.''</p>
        <p>Back at the iris bed, he laid down black landscape fabric, extending it about five feet beyond the original boundaries, hauling that dirt away as well. The fabric is permeable, allowing water, but no goutweed, to pass through. He then filled the enlarged bed with fresh soil and started all over again. Some experts suggest that simply hosing off an ornamental's roots, and inspecting it closely for any weed fragments, is enough for replanting. But Mr. Homeyer puts his ornamentals in quarantine for a year.</p>
        <p>''This spring, two years after this operation, I found a goutweed leaf on the far corner of this bed, just beyond the fabric. I dug it all out -- and haven't seen any signs of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Homeyer admitted to feeling a bit smug. ''Everyone says you can't beat the darn thing and you can,'' he said. ''You just have to be a bit of a fanatic.'' I'd say the same thing applies for any invasive weed: mint, Jerusalem artichokes, pigweed. Name your nemesis.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
