<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The National Pastime Falls Behind in the Count</title>
    <meta content="12BALL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/12/business/12BALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dusenberry, Phil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodwin, Doris Kearns</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Viertel, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kissinger, Henry A (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Veeck, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hawkins, Trip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenbaum, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bouton, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reichheld, Frederick F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Count</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Major League Baseball</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Selig, Bud</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD6123FF931A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="3393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The National Pastime Falls Behind in the Count</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">How to Re-energize Baseball and Win New Fans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Business of Major League Baseball is in a slump, with stadium attendance and television ratings down; ideas for re-energizing sport and winning new fans are proposed by luminaries Rudolph Giuliani, Phil Dusenberry, Doris Kearns Goodwin, Dan Rather, Tom Viertel, Henry Kissinger, Michael Veeck, Trip Hawkins, Stuart Greenbaum, Ken Burns, Jim Bouton and Frederick Reichheld; photos; charts (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are places where baseball games last just two and a half hours, where batters spend most of their time at home plate trying to hit the ball rather than fidgeting with their equipment. There are also places where the fans of every team legitimately dream of a championship. There are even places where the teams that do fall to last place continue to inspire passion until the final weeks of the season.</p>
        <p>And then there is Major League Baseball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With stadiums empty and televisions turned to other channels, it is a strange time for the $3.3 billion business also known as the national pastime. Here are four possible remedies</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are places where baseball games last just two and a half hours, where batters spend most of their time at home plate trying to hit the ball rather than fidgeting with their equipment. There are also places where the fans of every team legitimately dream of a championship. There are even places where the teams that do fall to last place continue to inspire passion until the final weeks of the season.</p>
        <p>And then there is Major League Baseball.</p>
        <p>In its world, games stretch beyond midnight, past the school-night bedtimes of the people who should be its most fervent fans. Only the richest of the sport's teams win even a single World Series game. Every September, when many also-ran teams have long since given up hope, their stadiums are empty and at-home fans turn their televisions to other channels.</p>
        <p>It is a strange time for the $3.3 billion business also known as the national pastime. Overall revenue has almost doubled since 1996, and ballparks like Yankee Stadium and Fenway Park are fuller today than they have ever been.</p>
        <p>But average attendance for the league still has not recovered to the levels it reached before the 1994 labor dispute -- despite a long economic boom, the construction of 10 stadiums, a doubling of the number of playoff teams and the addition of interleague games pitting, say, the Mets against the Yankees. Meanwhile, the fall of television ratings for games makes the National Football League look good, and the number of children playing organized baseball is plummeting.</p>
        <p>All in all, it is enough to make the sport's commissioner sound as if he is living in a Lewis Carroll story. ''Baseball is in the midst of an incredible renaissance,'' said Bud Selig, the sport's top executive -- later acknowledging, ''the economic problems are so pervasive that all options should be on the table.''</p>
        <p>At times like this, companies often seek outside help. So Money &amp; Business has turned not to the usual experts for inspiration, but to the world beyond Major League Baseball -- from the sport's own minor leagues all the way to baseball-agnostic Europe. These are the places where well-paced games are the norm or where even miserable teams can keep fans interested.</p>
        <p>Now is the time to be creative. In less than three months, after the World Series, the current labor agreement between major-league owners and players will expire. Each time the deal has come up for renewal in the last 30 years, there has been either a strike or a lockout. If baseball is going to flirt with that pain yet again, it might as well see what can be gained.</p>
        <p>Here are four ideas:</p>
        <p>Remedy One  Copy Bush Leagues, Bring Back the Fun</p>
        <p>Name one of the nation's largest metropolitan areas, and it probably has a thriving baseball team. It may even have three or four.</p>
        <p>The BlueClaws in Lakewood, N.J., playing 60 miles from Philadelphia, have already broken the all-time attendance record for the Class A South Atlantic League, and their inaugural season still has a few weeks left. The Brooklyn Cyclones have sold almost every seat -- about 7,500 a game -- in their first season. In the outer suburbs of Chicago, the Kane County Cougars built a new deck of seats last winter to accommodate their ever-growing crowds.</p>
        <p>Every night, thousands of people who could see Cal Ripken Jr. or Sammy Sosa instead choose to watch error-prone 21-year-olds.</p>
        <p>''We kind of got laughed at when we started,'' said Jeff Sedivy, the general manager of the Cougars, who opened for business in 1991. ''People were saying, 'Why would anyone be interested in minor-league baseball with two major-league teams in the market?' '' But attendance for the Cougars -- four notches below the majors -- has more than doubled in the last 10 years, to 7,500 fans a game.</p>
        <p>Of course, that is far less than the average crowd of 30,000 at a big-league game. On a typical midsummer night, 500,000 people are at major-league parks, compared to the 350,000 watching minor-league games.</p>
        <p>But the gap is narrowing. Between 1993 and last year, when per-game attendance fell 4 percent for the major leagues, it rose 19 percent in the minors. At the minors' lowest levels, where the stadiums are smallest, tickets cheapest and players youngest, attendance has risen the most.</p>
        <p>''It's accessible and easy, and it's all fun,'' said Steve Rogers, who was watching the Cougars beat an Ohio team, the Dayton Dragons, 11 to 2 on a recent Wednesday with his wife and three children. ''There's an excitement in the air here. The kids can really see the players.'' Mr. Rogers said he stopped attending Cubs games after the 1994 lockout.</p>
        <p>The majors have copied a few gimmicks from the minors, like having entertainment on the field between innings. On the whole, though, the big leagues have become less like the bush leagues.</p>
        <p>Major-league games now last an average of almost 3 hours, about 10 minutes longer than they did in the early 1990's and about 15 minutes longer than a minor-league game does. In the playoffs, they often drag on even longer.</p>
        <p>''You can't have the most important games of the year end at midnight on a school night and not have that come back to bite you,'' said Bob Costas, the NBC broadcaster and author of ''Fair Ball: A Fan's Case for Baseball'' (Broadway Books). Watching highlights on ESPN, he added, ''can't replace the drama of seeing it as it unfolds and remembering where you were the instant the balls hits the bat.''</p>
        <p>Shortening games need not involve the one move baseball has made -- its controversial attempts to expand the strike zone -- or the dream fans have about the eliminating the designated hitter. Baseball could, for instance, simply order batters and pitchers to stop wasting time.</p>
        <p>''After every pitch, Chuck Knoblauch'' -- the Yankees' left fielder -- ''steps out of the box, straightens his helmet, fixes his batting gloves, takes three or four swings,'' said Geoff Brown, the general manager of Lakewood's BlueClaws, whose home games are averaging 2 hours and 32 minutes. ''You don't have guys doing that in the minors.''</p>
        <p>Guys weren't doing it 30 years ago in the majors. Just watch an old baseball video.</p>
        <p>In a typical minor-league park, fans can also carry on one of baseball's most cherished rituals: a conversation. They don't have to out-shout the music and commercials that dominate so many big-league parks.</p>
        <p>At least one major-league team has seen the virtue in this. The San Francisco Giants recently canceled a team-sponsored ''scream off'' between fans on opposite sides of the ballpark and turned down the volume on songs played during the game. ''It gave everybody a headache,'' Larry Baer, the team's chief operating officer, said. ''We found that by dialing it down a little bit, we have not lost the casual fan.''</p>
        <p>Two other big differences between the majors and the minors are more complicated. Since 1993, the average ticket price in the big leagues has increased 61 percent on an inflation-adjusted basis to $19, according to Team Marketing Report, a newsletter in Chicago. A typical minor-league ticket costs $6.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the growing number of luxury skyboxes, which have the best views, has pushed the location of many major-league seats nearly into the clouds. That has stopped John Forni, a Cougars fan, from attending Chicago White Sox games. ''Last time I went down there, do you want to know how far up I was? I was so far up, I got seasick,'' he said. ''I'm not kidding.''</p>
        <p>Roger G. Noll, a Stanford economist who has studied sports business, says there is good reason to reconsider the emphasis on selling to the top end. ''The real problem with baseball is that it is increasingly marketing itself to the top 25 percent of the income distribution,'' he said. That has helped baseball sell more $100 jackets, but he added, ''over the long run, it probably undermines building a fan base.''</p>
        <p>Remedy Two  The Worst Teams Go to the Minors</p>
        <p>It was the final day of the soccer season in Huddersfield, England, where the local team was mired near the bottom of the standings. But odd things -- to American eyes -- were happening all around. Not only was the stadium almost full, but some of the fans had brought radios to keep tabs on a rival.</p>
        <p>Far from being unusual, though, similar scenes happen every spring all over Europe. To stoke interest, soccer leagues there ''relegate'' the worst teams at the end of each season to the minor leagues. They are replaced the following year by the most successful minor-league teams. The demoted teams -- usually three or four, depending on the country -- can return to the top-ranked league only by finishing at the top of the lower league during the next season.</p>
        <p>The battle to avoid relegation unfailingly captures attention. ''It keeps the season alive,'' said Russell Thomas, a sports editor at The Guardian in London. ''There's sort of a gruesome interest in the grimness of their plight.''</p>
        <p>Compare this to the grimness that will take place in Kansas City, Tampa Bay and other downtrodden baseball cities at the end of this season.</p>
        <p>''The thing people are really keen to avoid in Europe is meaningless games between two teams who really don't have anything to play for,'' said Dan Jones, a consultant with Deloitte &amp; Touche Sport in Manchester, England. ''You tend to get a lot of those in baseball.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the perpetual weakness of some franchises has led Mr. Selig, the commissioner, to say that Major League Baseball should consider disbanding a few teams. ''There are many owners who strongly believe we have too many teams,'' he said. The relocation of one or two teams, to wealthy areas without one, however, is a more likely outcome.</p>
        <p>But suppose baseball let the free market solve the problem, as Europe's soccer leagues do. It would be more exciting than contraction or relocation, and maybe more efficient. Baseball would start by deciding how many teams to have in the majors -- say 26, four fewer than currently, to reverse the dilution of talent caused by recent expansion. Baseball would then relegate the two worst teams to the minors -- and, for the first two years, not replace them.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, a dreary September game in Montreal between the Pirates and Expos, which now draws maybe 5,000 fans, would bring a Coliseum-like excitement: the loser would be facing the baseball equivalent of death.</p>
        <p>At the same time, baseball could award four new franchises to cities that want a major-league team: Charlotte, N.C., Portland, Ore., San Jose, Calif., and Washington come to mind. These teams would join the relegated teams in a new minor league that would soon promote its top two teams to the majors at the end of each season.</p>
        <p>In the new league, ''everybody who was playing above .500 would have promotion as part of their marketing in the second half of the season,'' said Mr. Noll, the economist, who has studied English soccer teams.</p>
        <p>The markets with the biggest fan bases and television audiences would generate enough money to remain in the majors consistently. Others would find a comfortable place in the lower league or would bounce up and down between the two. Owners who seek profit but not wins would have to the face the consequences of the terrible teams they put on the field. In future years, those teams would no longer be able to play against the game's stars.</p>
        <p>This plan may be radical, but it has another advantage over contraction: If baseball had decided to eliminate some teams in the 1980's, Atlanta and Seattle, two of the worst, might have gone. Today, both are in first place, and among baseball's richer teams. If they had been disbanded, they never could have staged their resurrection.</p>
        <p>Remedy Three  Find New Customers In Other Countries</p>
        <p>When American companies absolutely, positively need to increase profits, they often go overseas for new consumers and cheap labor. Major League Baseball has figured out the second tack. Rosters are filled with Latin-American players, who command small signing bonuses, and proven Asian stars, like Seattle's Ichiro Suzuki, are becoming more common, too.</p>
        <p>Now baseball is trying exports. It has sold broadcast rights to more foreign television stations, pushing international revenue to $60 million last year, from $2 million in the early 90's. But the strategy is hardly aggressive. When McDonald's moves into a new market, it doesn't sell frozen Big Macs in supermarkets; it opens restaurants. Baseball, though, sells only a derivative of its product -- broadcasts of the games.</p>
        <p>The sport has not always been so tame in its exports. In 1954, Cincinnati moved its top minor-league team to Havana. The team was called the Cuban Sugar Kings, and their slogan was, ''One more step, and we'll get there.'' It referred to the major-league ambitions of both the players and the city itself, according to Roberto González Echevarría, the author of ''The Pride of Havana: A History of Cuban Baseball'' (Oxford University Press).</p>
        <p>The team's high point came in 1959, when it won the Triple A championship. The final games in Havana drew 30,000 fans, including Che Guevara in a box behind home plate and Fidel Castro, who threw the ceremonial first pitch. The following season, as tensions between the United States and Cuba rose, the league moved the team to Jersey City.</p>
        <p>These days, several cities within a short flight of the United States are again intriguing possibilities for new minor-league teams. When Major League Baseball played its opening game of the 1999 regular season in Monterrey, Mexico, tickets sold out within hours. The same happened in San Juan, Puerto Rico, in April, when the Texas Rangers played the Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>Monterrey has three million people, and President Vicente Fox has called it a model of economic development. San Juan is a typically baseball-loving Caribbean city and has already had one brush with the minors.</p>
        <p>In the mid-1990's, David Hersh was planning to move the team he ran in Nashville, Tenn., to San Juan, which he considered to be the largest untapped market in the United States. But the Seattle Mariners, whose up-and-coming players were on the team's roster, blocked the move, saying they wanted the team within the continental United States, Mr. Hersh said.</p>
        <p>Yes, Monterrey and San Juan are quite poor by American standards.  ''There are the sponsorship dollars for a Triple A franchise'' in San Juan, Mr. Hersh said. ''There are not the ticket-buying dollars,'' because the island has a small middle class.</p>
        <p>Yet both cities are within reasonable flying distance of the double-A Texas League. Just as most companies enter new markets without expecting immediate profitability, baseball would probably need to view new foreign franchises as an investment in their initial years.</p>
        <p>But it would be an investment almost certain to create new fans of American baseball. The teams might even become part of the big leagues one day, as the Sugar Kings hoped to.</p>
        <p>Remedy Four  Can't Beat 'Em? Share the Wealth</p>
        <p>The Oakland A's seem to be the perfect rejoinder to those who think baseball's richest teams dominate the sport. Playing a short drive from the more popular Giants, the A's generate relatively little revenue and have a small payroll. Yet, with talented young players, they won their division last year and could make the playoffs this year as a wild card.</p>
        <p>Oddly, though, their fans don't seem particularly moved. Only 25,100, on average, go to a game -- leaving the A's 20th, among 30 teams, in attendance and well below the pace they set in the late 1980's, when they were last up-and-comers.</p>
        <p>It's hard to blame the fans. When the A's were stumbling at the beginning of this season, its executives began talking about trading Jason Giambi -- last year's American League most valuable player -- because he was expensive. Giambi remains in Oakland, but no clear-thinking A's fan can expect the core of the current team to stay together for the next few years. And this version of the A's still has not won a single playoff series.</p>
        <p>''What matters to a fan,'' Mr. Costas said, ''is the perception of a team's ability to contend.''</p>
        <p>By every measure, fewer teams have that ability today than just a decade ago. The gap between the richest team's local revenue and the poorest has grown to almost 20 to 1, from 4 to 1 a decade ago, driven by the big differences in television rights fees across the country.</p>
        <p>''The disparity is so large,'' said Paul Volcker, the former Federal Reserve Chairman, who served on league-appointed committee to study the game, ''that it leads fairly directly to a chronic inability on the playing field of a considerable number of clubs ever to get on the winning side of things.''</p>
        <p>''Presumably, that weakens interest in baseball,'' he added.</p>
        <p>True, wealthy teams, like the Yankees, dominated the sport in earlier eras, but the problem has not always afflicted the sport. In the 1980's and even the early 1990's, when the difference between a small and large payroll was much less, more frugal teams -- like the 1990 Cincinnati Reds or 1985 Kansas City Royals -- regularly played in and even won the World Series. Since 1995, no team with a payroll ranked lower than 7th has won a single Series game.</p>
        <p>The National Football League offers an alternative. In the 1960's, on the eve of their first big television contract, football's large-market owners agreed with their colleagues  and Pete Rozelle, the commissioner,  to split revenue almost evenly.</p>
        <p>Football is now the most-watched sport on television, and in the last five years, New York, St. Louis, Nashville and even Green Bay, Wis., have all had teams appear in the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>Baseball and football may seem to be opposite in many respects. George Carlin even wrote a stand-up routine about their differences. (''Baseball begins in the spring, the season of new life. Football begins in the fall, when everything's dying.'')</p>
        <p>But changing its financial structural would hardly threaten baseball's romance. ''We have not served our long-term problems well,'' Mr. Selig said. ''It's one thing I'll give Pete Rozelle and the owners of the N.F.L. a lot of credit for.''</p>
        <p>Like almost everything else in baseball, this issue is tied up in the rocky labor situation. The owners are using the revenue gap to try to force a salary cap on players. The players scoff at the owners' complaints that many teams are no longer profitable.</p>
        <p>Few people question that the issue is the biggest one now facing baseball, however. In the upcoming negotiations, ''we expect it likely that the most signigicant topic will be revenue sharing,'' said Don Fehr, the head of the players' union.</p>
        <p>Whatever specific form a new system takes -- a salary cap or a steep tax on rich teams, perhaps phased in gradually -- many fans just want a return to the days when anything seemed possible. After all, what is the point of watching a sport if a good part of the outcome is already clear?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
