<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Dispossessed</title>
    <meta content="15nicholson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/15/books/review/15nicholson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1732380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="'The White Earth,' by Andrew McGahan"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholson, Geoff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGahan, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">White Earth, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">McGahan, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">White Earth, The (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7DE1E30F936A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Dispossessed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Dispossessed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEOFF NICHOLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nicholson, Geoff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoff Nicholson reviews book The White Earth by Andrew McGahan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WHITE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Andrew McGahan.</p>
        <p>376 pp. Soho Press. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This Australian novel focuses on the struggle over aboriginal property rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WHITE EARTH</p>
        <p>By Andrew McGahan.</p>
        <p>376 pp. Soho Press. $25.</p>
        <p>When Cole Porter wrote, ''Give me land, lots of land,'' he was echoing sentiments that occur throughout the literary canon, from the Bible to Shakespeare to Chekhov and now ''The White Earth,'' by Andrew McGahan. Porter wasn't much concerned with who was the rightful owner of the land, or who had the right to do the giving; but these issues are what concern McGahan. This is his fourth novel, and it comes garlanded with praise from his native Australia. The subject matter is not parochial, but it takes on a highly localized form here. The action is set in the Darling Downs, some way inland from Brisbane. It isn't the Outback, but it's a long way from civilization.</p>
        <p>William is 8 when his father blows himself up in a harvester accident on the family farm. William and his mother are then forced to live with John McIvor, William's great-uncle, who owns Kuran Station, a stretch of land crowned with a ruined mansion -- a piece of crumbling Australian gothic. In the opening chapters it seems that's what this novel is trying to be too, with its menacing housekeeper, mysterious locked rooms, a sinisterly incompetent doctor and a secret society. One is a little surprised to find the year is 1993.</p>
        <p>Interspersed with William's story is the earlier narrative of his great-uncle, how he lusted after Kuran Station for so many decades, how he obtained it and how he lost everything else in the process, not least the love of his estranged daughter, Ruth. He's an old man, and there's a possibility he'll leave everything to William, but the boy must prove that his passion for the land coincides with his great-uncle's. John is given to saying things like: ''The truth is, land has to belong to someone to really come alive. It needs a human being to hear it and see it and to understand everything about it -- where it came from, where it's going. Otherwise it's just a piece of ground.''</p>
        <p>Such thoughts were on the minds of many Australians in 1993. That was the year the government was engaged in the tricky business of passing land legislation that would placate and empower the aborigines, without alienating the rest of the population. The novel contains a good deal of discussion of Native Title, perpetual and pastoral leases, definitions of ''ongoing aboriginal presence'' and the notion of terra nullius. Characters explain and debate these terms for William's benefit, and the uninitiated reader will be grateful for this beginner's guide. We see that these are burning issues, but since the people who oppose the legislation are a bunch of cranks, racists and cross-burners, the debate isn't exactly evenhanded.</p>
        <p>Legislative matters aside, this is essentially young William's story, and it's a tragic one. The rights and wrongs of owning land aside, he does have a profound attachment to the land, but this does him very little good. He is buffeted by the forces of history, and horribly manipulated by his mother and great-uncle, who both think land is far more important than love. Terror and pity are duly evoked. Australian reviewers found something Dickensian in all this, but young William struck me as tougher than most of the children in Dickens, and the world he inhabits is more thoroughly malevolent than anything Dickens invented. And although we're on William's side, he isn't especially likable.</p>
        <p>William ultimately goes into the wilderness and has some conveniently plot-related visions of burning men, ancestral inhabitants of the land and the mythical Australian creature, the bunyip. The prose in this section is purple and heavy-handed, and the subsequent discovery that these visions may have been caused by a nasty ear infection suggest McGahan wants to eat his cake and have it. It made me reluctant to take the whole enterprise quite as seriously as its author evidently does. But I wonder if he would even recognize this as criticism. His fictional universe is devoid of a great many things; lightness of touch, irony and the slightest hint of humor being among them. Cole Porter, it ain't.</p>
        <p>'The White Earth,' by Andrew McGahan Geoff Nicholson's most recent novel is ''The Hollywood Dodo.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoff Nicholson's most recent novel is ''The Hollywood Dodo.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
