<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Likes Challenges. But Time Warner?</title>
    <meta content="15bruce" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/15/business/yourmoney/15bruce.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1732180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wasserstein, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Icahn, Carl C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lazard Llc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wasserstein, Bruce</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E5D9173FF936A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="3101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Likes Challenges. But Time Warner?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">He Likes Challenges. But Time Warner?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Bruce Wasserstein, veteran deal maker and chairman of Lazard; he comments on criticism against his new effort to break up Time Warner, his former client, by supporting Carl Icahn's campaign against it; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''DO you want some pineapple juice?'' Bruce Wasserstein asked, as he poured himself a glass one morning last month in his enormous office on the 62nd floor of 30 Rockefeller Center, with a view of Central Park.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein, the veteran deal maker and chairman of the storied investment bank Lazard, sat on an antique red leather couch. He wanted to talk. As perhaps Wall Street's most inscrutable and zealously tracked figure, he feels misunderstood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Wasserstein, the veteran deal maker and perhaps Wall Street's most inscrutable and zealously tracked figure, feels misunderstood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''DO you want some pineapple juice?'' Bruce Wasserstein asked, as he poured himself a glass one morning last month in his enormous office on the 62nd floor of 30 Rockefeller Center, with a view of Central Park.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein, the veteran deal maker and chairman of the storied investment bank Lazard, sat on an antique red leather couch. He wanted to talk. As perhaps Wall Street's most inscrutable and zealously tracked figure, he feels misunderstood.</p>
        <p>''People just have no idea what they're talking about,'' he said of his critics, who most recently have lit into his new effort to break up Time Warner. ''No idea at all. I mean, most of these people I've never met.''</p>
        <p>Over the past three decades, as he worked on a string of headline-grabbing takeovers, including Texaco's acquisition of Getty Oil and the battle for Paramount Communications, Mr. Wasserstein, 58, has become one of the biggest names in finance. Is he a polarizing figure? To some, he is an arrogant publicity seeker; to others, he is self-effacing. The critics, and there are lots of them, contend that he is more out for himself than he is for his clients or colleagues, but none will say so on the record because of his enormous power in the industry. His moves and motivations are obsessively scrutinized in the business press with the same vigor that the tabloids apply to Jessica Simpson's love life.</p>
        <p>And it should come as no surprise: his career has been a Sophoclean drama. He recently won a bitter battle for control of Lazard from its patriarch, Michel David-Weill, and successfully took this famously secretive investment bank public despite a chorus of naysayers. Two years ago, he mounted a surprise bid to buy New York magazine, the publication that fostered the careers of writers like Tom Wolfe and Jimmy Breslin, and snatched it away at the 11th hour from a consortium of some of the city's biggest billionaires. And just last month, he announced that he would jump into the fight over Time Warner, his former client, by supporting Carl C. Icahn's campaign against it. Mr. Wasserstein's decision was fraught with so much controversy that one of Lazard's directors, Robert C. Clark, resigned because he also serves on Time Warner's board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein seems to relish being in the thick of the action -- the more complicated and contentious, the better: ''Naturally, people say, 'Well, he likes messy things.' It's because, well, what do people turn to us for? It's complicated things where it matters that you can actually think,'' he said, ticking off a list of projects in which the firm is involved, including reorganizations, bankruptcies and what he calls destructurings.</p>
        <p>''It's things like that, where being good at the business makes a difference,'' he continued. ''If it doesn't make a difference, if it's commodity business, you can go to Big Bank Corp.,'' he said, derisively referring to the giant financial supermarkets like Citigroup and J. P. Morgan Chase. ''This is a relationship firm, for 150 years, not the check-writing business. If we did that, we'd be out of business because we don't have any money. So, therefore, the only thing we do here is think a little bit.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Wasserstein is good at anything, it is thinking, overthinking, doubting his own thinking and thinking some more. He is a classic New Yorker in the Woody Allen mold. While he may be a card-carrying master of the universe, he is more brainy wonk than banker jock. Slouching on his couch, he is dressed in a somewhat wrinkled navy suit with a plain burgundy tie; the laces on both his shoes are untied.</p>
        <p>''He gets along by dint of his intellect,'' said Martin Lipton, the takeover lawyer who is a founder of Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz, a firm that has long done work for Mr. Wasserstein. ''There's no smoke and mirrors there. Bruce is Bruce. He doesn't pretend. I don't think he's driven by money or fame. I think what drives him is the intellectual challenge. He has one of the most inventive minds I've ever run across.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein, who grew up in Brooklyn with three sisters, including Wendy Wasserstein, the playwright, has been doing mental gymnastics, turning around a multitude of permutations in his mind, plotting his designs on the world, since he was a small child. ''Bruce was a genius, conveniently born on Christmas Eve with, according to my mother, Messiah potential,'' Wendy Wasserstein told New York magazine in 2002 (a year before her brother bought it).</p>
        <p>She also described how, as children, they would go on hiking adventures in the Catskills. Perhaps tellingly, she said: ''At the end of the trail, Bruce planted a stick, proclaiming it Bruceania. It never occurred to me to claim the new world as Wendyania.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein loves to question the conventional wisdom, what he calls ''questioning the premises.'' It was something he picked up at Harvard Law School and while working for the consumer activist Ralph Nader in the early 1970's. Mr. Wasserstein participated in several projects as one of ''Nader's Raiders'' with his classmate and friend, Mark Green, the Democratic politician who would become public advocate of New York City. The work with Mr. Nader included writing a book calling for stronger antitrust laws.</p>
        <p>''You can't just assume things are the way they are and that they have to be the way they are,'' he said about his obsession with questioning everything, as he quickly segued the conversation to the subject of his decision to join Mr. Icahn and take on Time Warner. ''The key thing most people miss in Time Warner is to ask, 'What's really going on here?' Forget all the personalities and all the screaming and the noise. Why is Time Warner set up the way it's set up? Well, it goes back in history. It was a historical accident.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein's choice to work with Mr. Icahn, however, was no accident. But it was a decision that sent Wall Street into a tizzy because Lazard, a white-shoe firm, had done the unspeakable: it had signed up with a corporate raider to take aim at Mr. Wasserstein's former client.</p>
        <p>''It's not that we're saying we're going to be in this business as a generic thing,'' he said, referring to the business of regularly advising raiders, who prefer to be known as shareholder activists. ''There's a specific situation that we saw a good opportunity, partly because we've been historical advocates of the separation of Time Warner,'' he said, adding that the firm recently was an adviser on the split-up of Viacom. ''Why shouldn't we do it?'' he added. ''What's evil about that? Why is that threatening to corporate America? It isn't.''</p>
        <p>He says his interests are aligned with those of Time Warner's shareholders because the bulk of his payment from Mr. Icahn's group will come only if Time Warner's stock goes up. (Lazard will be paid more than $5 million for every dollar Time Warner's stock rises above $18 a share. Time Warner's shares closed on Friday at $17.27.) ''Let's get the stock up together. It's very simple: with a modicum of effort these people can have a much higher stock,'' he added, referring to Time Warner's chief executive, Richard D. Parsons, and other corporate officers. ''That's good for everybody. And if Dick Parsons has a magic formula to get that stock up, you know, hurray.''</p>
        <p>AND critics find his sympathy for Time Warner shareholders to be amusing, since Mr. Wasserstein claimed credit -- and was paid -- for advising Time Warner on its merger with AOL in 2000, when he was still at Wasserstein Perella, the boutique investment bank he founded with Joseph R. Perella before the two had a falling-out.</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Wasserstein now plays down his role in the merger. ''We did a study for them of the Internet,'' he said of the work he did for Time Warner. ''We recommended them doing Yahoo. At the time there was a debate about it one way or the other. And they went off on their own and did AOL, which we had some questions about, mostly related to the management. But we didn't execute the deal. We didn't negotiate the deal. We didn't do the due diligence.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''It is true that we did three years of work on the Internet. And so what they said was, 'Yes, you were a strategic adviser on the Internet so we'll pay you a fee.' And that's what that was about.''</p>
        <p>So far, despite all the publicity, Mr. Icahn's campaign to oust Time Warner's board has met a tepid response by shareholders. Mr. Icahn is hoping that his campaign will be reignited when Lazard issues a report in the next several weeks detailing its plan for the company, but analysts say its chances are long.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein has been recovering from pneumonia and having coughing fits. ''Excuse me,'' he said repeatedly, as he put his hand up to signal another cough after pouring himself another glass of pineapple juice.</p>
        <p>Despite feeling ill, Mr. Wasserstein has every reason to feel good about his business. Since joining Lazard in 2002, he has rebuilt the storied firm; last year he solidified that progress by winning a long-simmering tussle with the firm's former partners to take the company public. Mr. Wasserstein persuaded Mr. David-Weill, the former chairman who had run Lazard for a quarter-century, to pursue an initial public offering and to use the proceeds to buy out the firm's former partners. But the agreement came with a huge caveat: If Mr. Wasserstein did not pull off the I.P.O. by last fall, he would have been forced to resign. He pulled it off.</p>
        <p>While the initial public offering originally appeared to be somewhat of a disappointment -- Lazard's shares quickly traded below the I.P.O. price -- the stock has been on a tear recently, as Lazard has reported better-than-expected earnings. Last quarter, the firm reported that earnings had doubled over the previous quarter. And just last week, its shares traded at their highest point yet, breaking through $35 a share before closing on Friday at $34.95. That is up from a price of $25 a share at the public offering.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Wasserstein refused to gloat. ''I don't need to be vindicated,'' he said. And he did not want to talk too much about his battle with Mr. David-Weill. ''I like Michel -- I mean in some sympathetic way. And he likes me in some sort of way. You know, things are more subtle than people's view of it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The I.P.O. proved to be a personal boon for Mr. Wasserstein's wallet. His investment in the company of about $30 million in 2002 turned into more than $300 million in paper profits. And while his inner circle was also rewarded handsomely, not everyone at the firm received a payday. Indeed, some executives were forced to take pay cuts, leading to grumbling among some of Lazard's senior staff that he had enriched himself at the expense of others at the firm. Mr. Wasserstein counters that the firm's bankers are now all incentivized as owners.</p>
        <p>When he joined Lazard, Mr. Wasserstein had a to-do list that included fixing the firm's fractious, secretive and gossipy structure. He also had to restock its talent pool, which had been badly drained with the high-profile departures of bankers like Felix G. Rohatyn, who led the financial rescue of New York City in the 1970's and served as ambassador to France in the Clinton administration; Gerald Rosenfeld, who is now the chief executive of the investment bank Rothschild North America; Kendrick R. Wilson III, who is now a vice chairman of Goldman Sachs; and Steven Rattner, who started the Quadrangle Group, a private equity firm.</p>
        <p>To address the talent shortage, Mr. Wasserstein first went on a hiring spree, using big pay packages to attract some of his top colleagues from his days at First Boston, including Gary W. Parr, Charles G. Ward III, Michael J. Biondi and Jeffrey A. Rosen.</p>
        <p>Then he turned his attention to the firm's processes. ''This place was like a basketball team where people were good at taking shots but they never passed the ball,'' he said. ''It was no way to run a team.'' The compensation program had a lot to do with it. ''If you were in Paris in the old days here and you worked with someone in New York, there would be a fee split,'' he said. ''So why work with the guy in New York? You could keep it all yourself if you never talked to the guy. So people didn't talk to the guy. I mean, that was the way it was done. So I got rid of all that.''</p>
        <p>He says that the firm is better for it. But he still thinks that the firm is underappreciated and misunderstood. ''I see these articles where people try to compare us to -- they really don't understand the firm because they try to compare us to people we're not,'' he said. ''We're not Goldman Sachs because we're not a diversified full-service whatever it is. We're certainly not Citibank or someplace like that. But we have little in common with the people at Greenhill or Evercore. We have 2,000 people here.'' Greenhill and Evercore are boutique investment banks.</p>
        <p>Still, some analysts question whether the bank's growth rate is sustainable and how much higher the stock can go.</p>
        <p>What will Mr. Wasserstein do for an encore? There are the persistent questions on Wall Street about whether he is trying to dress up Lazard for a sale, repeating the type of deal he made when he sold Wasserstein Perella to Dresdner Bank for $1.37 billion in 2000 -- a deal that proved a flop for Dresdner when many bankers left. But, he said, it was through no fault of his own. When he is asked the about the possibility of selling Lazard, a look comes over his face as if a crazy person has just asked a question in a foreign language. ''Why would I do that?'' he asked. ''I think there's a lot of opportunity to build the company. Whenever you cap it, you're often saying, 'O.K., I don't have the opportunity to further build it,' '' he added, waiving his hand as he explained that Lazard is not just any old company. ''I feel like a trustee for the future.''</p>
        <p>DESPITE all of Mr. Wasserstein's management work, he says he doesn't particularly enjoy dealing with the dowdy details of running his company: ''What I do is I find people who are gifted at administrating. I'm not -- or don't claim to be anyway. I just figure out what the system is.''</p>
        <p>He talks incessantly about his disdain for bureaucracy and the ceremonial responsibilities of the title he holds. He proudly tells the story of how he devised a system at First Boston in the 1980's to keep him from having to meet with visiting dignitaries. ''We created a subsidiary,'' he said. ''We called it something grand: First Boston International, something or another. And we made the guy who was our general counsel -- or was he was the deputy general counsel? -- we made him the chairman of that. And he sat and had tea and was perfectly pleasant. And everyone was delighted to meet this charming guy. And it saved an enormous amount of time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wasserstein likes to spend his time on the front lines doing deals for clients or for his own private equity firm, Wasserstein &amp; Company, which owns The American Lawyer and The Deal, the trade magazines, and has owned Maybelline, the cosmetics company, and Collins &amp; Aikman, a car parts maker, among others.</p>
        <p>On a table in his office is an enormous gift basket from Harry &amp; David, a business that his private equity fund owns. The basket is filled with several of its supernaturally beautiful pears. In the middle of the interview, amid some small talk about those pears, Mr. Wasserstein starts conducting an impromptu customer survey: ''Now let me ask you a question: When you order a gift, you get a label on the box that saysit's a gift from you, right? But there isn't a card inside. They charge $2.50 for the card. Are you outraged or not bothered?''</p>
        <p>Those types of details matter to Mr. Wasserstein. To him, they are important not just for his own investment, but also for what he can learn from them that he can apply to his clients. ''You learn that even if you're right on your theory of an investment, something for us always generally goes wrong,'' he said. ''And so it's nice to have the experience so you can anticipate. It's just that you have to think about the execution of projects, so instead of being ideological it's really what people are comfortable managing.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Wasserstein, the art of the deal is his life. He explains that when he is in the zone of working on a deal, he has reached Zen. ''It's inexplicable,'' he said. ''You see all this noise around you so the reaction is just to, hmm, and be very calm,'' he said. ''I don't know what's going on, but I find that much more relaxing than dealing with my kid who's just bumped into the wall or something. That's tension, but the deal stuff's very relaxing for me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
