<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will the Islanders Miss Something Down the Road?</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD91538F932A25752C0A965958260" item-length="637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will the Islanders Miss Something Down the Road?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINN, ROBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like men left to ponder the exhaust fumes of a bus they've just missed, so the forlorn Islanders are starting to worry that the playoffs are about to pull out of sight.</p>
        <p>Three straight losses, all of them by a single goal and all of them in games they had led, have marooned the team seven points in back of the Devils and the Rangers, who are tied in third place in the Patrick Division.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like men left to ponder the exhaust fumes of a bus they've just missed, so the forlorn Islanders are starting to worry that the playoffs are about to pull out of sight.</p>
        <p>Three straight losses, all of them by a single goal and all of them in games they had led, have marooned the team seven points in back of the Devils and the Rangers, who are tied in third place in the Patrick Division.</p>
        <p>Morale is a word best left unsaid around the Islanders' hushed locker room, where even the sound system has had its plug pulled.</p>
        <p>But after being snubbed by the Vancouver Canucks, 5-4, at Nassau Coliseum on Saturday night, Brian Mullen was angry enough to critique what's left of his team's backbone.</p>
        <p>"There's no excuse for the way we've played," he said, staring across the room at occasional linemate Steve Thomas, who stared morosely back. "We're playing just well enough to lose. We've got to get ourselves out of this or we're going to find ourselves out of the race."</p>
        <p>The lost weekend began early -- last Tuesday -- with a 2-1 home loss to Quebec that mortified the entire administrative staff of the Islanders.</p>
        <p>Coach Al Arbour, who several seasons ago accused a similarly listless platoon of Islanders of playing as if they wore tutus, or ought to, accused this year's bunch of playing a gritless, gutless brand of hockey.</p>
        <p>With the exception of goalie Glenn Healy, who was wounded in action last Friday and is sidelined with tendinitis, Arbour berated his boys with the ultimate insult: He called them soft.</p>
        <p>General Manager Don Maloney, who commiserated with and came to the same conclusion as Arbour, found the drive home to Rye particularly painful that Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>"I had too much to think about," said Maloney, who, like Arbour, is thinking that only a trade of significant -- and possibly risky -- proportion will jumpstart this franchise.</p>
        <p>"We are a middle-of-the-pack team," Maloney sighed. "Mediocrity, we've got that down pat. Some changes will inevitably be made."</p>
        <p>The Islanders (17-21-4), as their spotty record attests, are capable of occasional sessions of overachievement. They have beaten divisional front-runners like the Penguins and Rangers in the last month. Unbeatable to Beatable</p>
        <p>"On any given night, we can beat any team in the league," Maloney said. "The trouble is, any team can beat us on any given night."</p>
        <p>The games Friday and Saturday, when the Islanders stormed out to first period leads only to turn comatose in the second period, were unnecessary reminders of Maloney's assessment.</p>
        <p>The Islanders hustled into Buffalo for Friday's game brimming with good intentions. Pierre Turgeon wanted to show Pat LaFontaine that the Islanders, who exported LaFontaine to import Turgeon, had no regrets about last season's trade. Healy, making his eighth straight start in goal, was looking for a 14th victory to offset his 13 losses.</p>
        <p>The team took a 2-0 lead, mostly because of Buffalo's lack of organization in the opening period. But in the second period, the Sabres stung Healy with five goals on 18 shots and he was replaced by Danny Lorenz for the final period.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, it was eerie instead of invigorating when the Islanders, again benefiting from an effervescent first period, amassed what could have been a commanding 3-1 lead. Once again, they wavered in the second period and allowed the opponent to take a lead into the final period, a familiar, forbidden scenario.</p>
        <p>"We even talked about exactly that, about not doing it, and there it was again, a carbon copy," said Mullen, whose team has made no third-period comebacks this season and is 0-17-2 when it trails after two periods.</p>
        <p>"It seems like this team waits for something bad to happen for the work ethic to come back, and you can't have that happen and expect to win many games. Not at this time of year."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
