<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bed and Pirogi in Eastern Europe</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="459779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BED-AND-BREAKFAST LODGINGS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ERLICK, JUNE CAROLYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Bed and Breakfasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DE123CF937A25754C0A967958260" item-length="2592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bed and Pirogi in Eastern Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUNE CAROLYN ERLICK;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ERLICK, JUNE CAROLYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY Polish hostess, Helena Ditrych, showed me the tidy guest room of her Warsaw apartment with its blue curtains and oversized fan, and then whisked me into her kitchen for an ample meal of pirogis and cold cuts. It was only after my second glass of oversweetened fruit juice to stave off the unusual Warsaw heat that I realized she knew just a word or two of English and German. I speak absolutely no Polish.</p>
        <p>I was immediately taken aback, but then I thought of the fan, and decided to brave it. Helena, who must have been in her early 60's, was clearly not intimidated. After heaping more delicious pirogis on my plate, she fetched a heavy book that I thought for a moment was a Bible, but which turned out to be a Polish-English dictionary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY Polish hostess, Helena Ditrych, showed me the tidy guest room of her Warsaw apartment with its blue curtains and oversized fan, and then whisked me into her kitchen for an ample meal of pirogis and cold cuts. It was only after my second glass of oversweetened fruit juice to stave off the unusual Warsaw heat that I realized she knew just a word or two of English and German. I speak absolutely no Polish.</p>
        <p>I was immediately taken aback, but then I thought of the fan, and decided to brave it. Helena, who must have been in her early 60's, was clearly not intimidated. After heaping more delicious pirogis on my plate, she fetched a heavy book that I thought for a moment was a Bible, but which turned out to be a Polish-English dictionary.</p>
        <p>My memory of my stay as a paying house guest with Mrs. Ditrych last summer was that I spoke fluent Polish, which, of course, is an absurdity. But we did manage to talk about her fondness for Lech Walesa and her bus trip to Rome and what she thought of food prices and about her children and her grandchildren. It was all done with pictures, gestures, the dictionary and even a bit of church Latin.</p>
        <p>The five-day visit gave me an intriguing look into a simple Polish apartment in a dreary look-alike high-rise block of socialist housing. But I had not chosen to "stay private" -- as it is called in Eastern Europe -- out of curiosity. I had moved out of a non-air-conditioned luxury hotel when the management couldn't provide me with a fan. It had been the last straw: the hotel switchboard was so overloaded I couldn't call out, and a quick meal could not be had anywhere in the hotel. A taxi driver used frequently by journalistic colleagues helped direct me to an independent private-room network that furnished Mrs. Ditrych's address.</p>
        <p>The guest bedroom was at the front of the apartment, not far from the telephone, a luxury in Poland. The small room with its large bed and comfortable mattress and reading light also had a closet and a small writing desk. Blue polyester curtains matched a bedspread, and magazine cutouts of rock stars decorated the closet door. I shared the family bathroom, and was pleasantly surprised to find it had both a tub and shower with hot and cold running water.</p>
        <p>It was not my first home stay in Eastern Europe. In the last two years, I have stayed in more than 30 private homes in Poland, Czechoslavakia, Hungary and the former East Germany. I have found my hosts through government tourist agencies, private networks and occasionally by word-of-mouth. My accommodations were in small suburban houses surrounded by fruit trees, massive high-rise apartment buildings, charming half-timbered houses and even in a hilltop villa.</p>
        <p>I began staying private in September 1989, two months before the Berlin Wall was breached, to glimpse the then off-limits life of East Germany. It did not take many stays to convince me that staying private is much better value for the money than most Eastern European hotels; the most I've paid for a single room is $18.</p>
        <p>As the region moves into a market economy, many of its sterile, poor-service hotels are being upgraded, and Western-style hotels are being built. But the improvements can't keep pace with the influx of tourists, and it is increasingly difficult to make any hotel reservations at all.</p>
        <p>The newly liberated countries of Eastern Europe now make it easier to find private rooms. Bureaucratic restrictions have been lifted, and room placements aren't limited to government agencies. Soaring prices of consumer goods also mean hosts are eager for hard currency; but they have consistently been more motivated by curiosity about the Western world than by money.</p>
        <p>In the private homes I've stayed in, there has never been substandard plumbing or heating, although bathrooms are generally shared with hosts or other guests. Mattresses have been more comfortable than those found in Eastern European hotels, and such amenities as fans, reading lamps and radios are common. An unusually high percentage of the homes have had telephones, and they worked far better than overloaded telephone switchboards (although in Poland and the eastern part of Germany, it is still extremely difficult to call internationally or even between cities).</p>
        <p>A few hosts have put a television set in the guest room, but I've never had CNN or other English-language channels. English-language newspapers are as close as the nearest major hotel.</p>
        <p>The rooms I've stayed in have always been immaculately clean, and hosts have even offered to do laundry.</p>
        <p>Many of these private-stay homes count on return business or referrals, so it is in their interest to maintain standards. In addition, most hosts receive hard currency, which means that access to fans, radios, televisions and even telephones is a bit easier than for the average person.</p>
        <p>As a single woman, I also find that many of the inconveniences of hotels are avoided by staying with a family. It is an easy way to meet people without having simple friendliness misunderstood.</p>
        <p>The structure of state tourist agencies in eastern Germany, Czechoslavakia, Hungary and Poland has been kept to provide private room services, and one can often book ahead.  Hosts often pride themselves on being guides, taking me on walking tours or to the theater. I've been treated to elaborate home-cooked meals, and become privy to off-the-beaten-track restaurants that escaped socialist sameness.</p>
        <p>It is prestigious to have a Western guest, just as jeans and McDonald's are prestigious, and hospitality often reflects that attitude. Staying private has long been an open secret among Western executives traveling in Eastern Europe. Arriving in the Prague airport with two friends last August, I asked a British businessman if he could recommend a hotel.</p>
        <p>"Hotel?" he grinned. "I always stay private."</p>
        <p>Indeed, he had been coming to Prague for a number of years, and now always stayed with the same family. They would meet him at the airport. He suggested we tell the taxi driver to take us to Cedok, the government tourist office. I later learned one could book private rooms through Cedok from abroad.</p>
        <p>Cedok gave us a name and address, and we arrived by taxi at an elegant old building near Prague's Wenceslas Square. Our hostess spoke only Czech, but she indicated how to make coffee and where the bathroom was. The two bedrooms each had huge double beds and down comforters. One -- which ended up being mine -- also doubled as a study. Jars of pickled vegetable from the garden of our hostess's mother lined the hall. I found out about the source of the pickles from our hostess' sister, whom she almost immediately had put on the phone. The sister, a student who spoke fluent English, wanted to meet us. Could we have dinner?</p>
        <p>OUR Czech holiday became the tale of the Pied Piper; we collected all the sister's bilingual friends, a Bulgarian accounting student, a Cuban professor, several Czech artists and a language teacher who spoke English, Spanish, Portuguese, Russian, Chinese and Serbo-Croatian, and who was a walking encyclopedia of Czech history. The group kept getting bigger. Restaurant reservations were made where none were to be had, and we explored offbeat pubs and restaurants and out-of-the-way museums.</p>
        <p>I've had similar experiences in Budapest, where my hosts, who lived in a tree-lined villa on a hilltop overlooking the city, threw a dinner party in my honor with a large group of English-speaking Hungarians, many of whom had lived in the States. I found it just as fascinating to watch my host's grandmother slowly roll out the dough for apple strudel on a lace tablecloth before dinner as I did to listen to the stories about the 1956 crushing of the Hungarian uprising.</p>
        <p>More than half my private home stays have been in eastern Germany, which since last October is part of a united Germany. Indeed, I should have figured out the Wall was going to tumble on my very first private stay in September 1989 in Leipzig. My hostess, Elli Kunstmann, a secretary in her mid-50's, held her towels up to the considerably plusher towel I had chucked in my suitcase from my home in West Berlin. Exclaiming in a slow, deliberate German so I would be sure to understand her, she said, "I get up at 5 every morning and can't even buy a decent towel."</p>
        <p>People were already demonstrating in the streets of Leipzig, and Mrs. Kunstmann watched the demonstrations on television, and dreamed of visiting an uncle in Frankfurt she had not seen since she was 8 years old.</p>
        <p>In those days, Westerners could easily stay in East Germany in private homes only twice a year, during the fall and spring Leipzig Fair. There simply weren't enough hotel rooms to go around.</p>
        <p>Although I could never prove it, I suspected that Elli had given up her bedroom to have me as a house guest. The room I stayed in had a big double bed, a firm and comfortable mattress, lace curtains and a comfortable, plush armchair. It was opposite the spacious and well-appointed bathroom. Elli slept in the living room, where she insisted she always slept when her husband was away. The kitchen was the nicest room of all, bright, sunny and spacious.</p>
        <p>ELLI cooked me the best meal of sauerbraten I've ever had in East, West or United Germany. She pointed me in the right direction for buses and trolleys; she made telephone calls for me, because my German was shaky.</p>
        <p>My first stay in East Germany after the fall of the Wall in November 1989 was actually a bit disappointing. The spacious room, in an immaculate one-story house in a Dresden suburb, was very comfortable and cost $14 including breakfast. The guest rooms -- mine was large and airy, with an ample closet -- were divided from the house, and were provided with their own television room, bathroom and breakfast room. Another guest, a Turkish man, a heavy smoker, who had driven up to Dresden with a Mercedes-Benz filled with leather jackets to sell to the East Germans, wanted to watch television, smoke and talk. I pleaded weariness and went to bed before dark.</p>
        <p>On that trip my accommodations told me no more about life in Dresden than a hotel stay would have. But such anonymous neutrality is not usually the case in private stays.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, I went back to Leipzig. The government tourist office booked me into the apartment of Ilse Lindner, a 68-year-old retiree I had guessed was about 50. Near downtown, the apartment was huge with high ceilings and freshly wallpapered. A man -- I could never figure out if he was a shy husband or a relative or a laborer -- was helping to renovate.</p>
        <p>My room still smelled of freshly put-up white wallpaper. The bed was small, but comfortable with the usual down comforter, and well-furnished with two upholstered chairs, a large table and an imitation wooden wardrobe. A large black and white television set dominated one corner of the room. The toilet -- just across the hall -- was a separate room from the bath and shower, also opposite my room.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lindner recommended a restaurant, and I rather suspected a comfortable room would be all I would gain from the experience.</p>
        <p>I was wrong. When I returned from the restaurant, she invited me into the living room, filled with an unlikely combination of tacky 1950's furniture, turn-of-the-century antiques and a collection of Meissen porcelain.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Lindner poured me a glass of Hungarian wine and began -- in a mixture of German and English -- to recount how she watched the demonstrations that would topple the Communist government. But now that Germany is united, prices are higher in Leipzig than in the western part of Germany, she complained. "If we're the same country, we should be the same in everything," she said. VISITOR'S GUIDE TO PRIVATE RENTALS</p>
        <p>In Eastern Europe, your hosts will usually prefer to receive dollars or German marks instead of the local currency. If you deal with a state tourist agency to reserve your room, you may pay the agency in hard currency and your hosts may receive payment in local currency. A very small service fee, usually equivalent to $2 or $3, is sometimes charged.</p>
        <p>The most I've paid for a single room was the equivalent of $18. Most single rooms cost between $10 and $15, doubles between $12 and $20. Prices depend on country, comfort and distance from downtown. If you find your room through an agency, be sure to tell them whether you're looking for comfort and convenience or sheer economy. Because the move from government to private control in Eastern Europe is so fluid, the rates may well change.</p>
        <p>A simple breakfast is often included in the room price, and I've found that many hosts throw in a dinner or two. In general, home cooking in Eastern European countries is far superior to what you'll find in restaurants (Hungary is the exception), and you avoid problems with restaurant reservations. Even when you're charged separately for meals, the price is invariably much less than you'll pay in a restaurant.  Eastern Germany</p>
        <p>Private rooms can be found easily through the government-run tourist offices in most major cities and towns attracting tourists. These are often in railroad stations or on the town square.</p>
        <p>Berlin (the eastern half). Verkehrsamt Berlin Alexanderplatz, 0-1020 Unter dem Fernsehturm; telephone 2 12 45 12.</p>
        <p>Dresden. Dresden-Information 10-11 Prager Strasse; telephone 4 95 50 25 (tourist information); 4 95 31 08 (private room service).</p>
        <p>Dessau. Dessau-Information, 12 Friedrich-Naumann-Strasse; telephone 46 61.</p>
        <p>Leipzig. Fremdenverkehrsamt Leipzig Leipzig-Information, 1 Sachsenplatz, telephone 79 59 326 (tourist information); 79 59 340 (private room service).  Czechoslovakia</p>
        <p>Hotel rooms only can be reserved through the New York office of Cedok, the recently privatized travel agency, at 10 East 40th Street, New York, N.Y. 10016; (212) 689-9720. In its Prague office, Cedok will make arrangements for private rooms only on the day the accommodations are wanted and only if the traveler shows up in person. Double rooms cost $20 to $25 a night in hard currency, with a minimum stay of two nights. Cedok is at 5 Panska Ulica; telephone 2127111; the agency has other offices throughout the country. Taxi drivers and small hotels are also good sources for finding private rooms.  Hungary</p>
        <p>Hungary has one of the most efficient private room services in Eastern Europe. Information, but not reservations for individuals, is available from Ibusz, 1 Parker Plaza, Suite 1104, Fort Lee, N.J. 07024; telephone (800) 367-7878. In Budapest, Ibusz (3-5 Petofi; telephone 1185707) is open daily 24 hours a day and makes arrangements for private accommodations. Telephone reservations are not made, but fax reservations are accepted at 1179099. Give date of arrival, number of nights and price range; Ibusz will confirm by fax. Double rooms for a minimum of two nights with use of bath and toilet range from $9 to $17, payable in hard currency. Apartments are available for a minimum of a week for about $27 a night. Poland</p>
        <p>Poland's accommodation system for private rooms is not as developed as Czechoslavakia's or Hungary's. People who have rooms to rent often stand outside government tourist offices, and taxi drivers are often in the know. In Warsaw, you might also try the Syrena Accommodation Bureau, 16 Krucza; telephone 217864. Bulgaria</p>
        <p>You can book private accommodations through Balkan Holidays, 41 East 42d Street, Suite 606, New York, N.Y. 10017; telephone (212) 573-5530. Rooms are about $30 to $40 a night.</p>
        <p>JUNE CAROLYN ERLICK lives in Berlin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JUNE CAROLYN ERLICK lives in Berlin.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
