<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Trying to Learn a River Better Than the Fish Do</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="478961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WRIGHT, LEONARD M JR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEVERSINK (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDE1538F934A35753C1A967958260" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Trying to Learn a River Better Than the Fish Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Neversink  One Angler's Intense Exploration of a Trout River  By Leonard M. Wright Jr.  191 pages. The Atlantic Monthly Press. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Leonard M. Wright Jr.'s absorbing new book begins with trout fishing, just as his previous 10 books do, among which is the innovative "Fishing the Dry Fly as a Living Insect" (E. P. Dutton, 1972). But unlike his other books, "Neversink: One Angler's Intense Exploration of a Trout River" so thoroughly explores the environment of trout fishing that by the end of it the reader has almost forgotten that it is a trout book.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Neversink  One Angler's Intense Exploration of a Trout River  By Leonard M. Wright Jr.  191 pages. The Atlantic Monthly Press. $19.95.</p>
        <p>Leonard M. Wright Jr.'s absorbing new book begins with trout fishing, just as his previous 10 books do, among which is the innovative "Fishing the Dry Fly as a Living Insect" (E. P. Dutton, 1972). But unlike his other books, "Neversink: One Angler's Intense Exploration of a Trout River" so thoroughly explores the environment of trout fishing that by the end of it the reader has almost forgotten that it is a trout book.</p>
        <p>Many years ago, Mr. Wright went up to the Catskill Mountains, in upstate New York, and acquired a stretch of the West Branch of the Neversink River, whose name doesn't mean what it says but is a phonetic form of the Indian word for this river, which meant "water between highlands."</p>
        <p>Like a typical member of his species, Mr. Wright fished and fished for trout until he noticed there weren't as many to be caught anymore. Then he began to worry about building up the supply instead of depleting it. The obvious answer was stocking his river with fish raised in hatcheries, but he soon discovered certain drawbacks to that approach. Hatchery trout had their wildness bred out of them. They weren't as much fun to catch or as tasty as native fish. Yet being bigger they tended to crowd out the smaller, wild trout. Stocking was like addiction: "The more you did it, the more you</p>
        <p>had</p>
        <p>to do it." So he kicked that habit.</p>
        <p>Instead, he explored the conditions under which his native trout lived. He tried to improve their space by building a dam. But he soon discovered that periodic flooding had the power to blast dams away. He tried enriching the food supply by raising the alkalinity of the water with limestone gravel. But the Neversink's tendency toward scouring floods took care of that solution too.</p>
        <p>Nothing he tried worked easily. He had discovered a basic law of nature: whatever is congenial to a given environment will already be there, and, conversely, whatever isn't won't.  Eventually, he improved the space for his fish with a complex series of structures that harnessed the power of floodwaters. And he fed the new fish that arrived not by raising the insect population, but instead by purchasing ground-up cattle lungs, or "lights," which float extremely well, and casting them upon his waters.  "Feeding trout this way is almost as much fun as fishing," he reports.</p>
        <p>While having these adventures, Mr. Wright learned a great deal about his river. Studying the acidity of the water forced him to understand the geology that produced the Catskills' vast stands of hemlock trees and gave rise to the tanning industry that filled the high demand for leather products during the American Civil War.</p>
        <p>Following the links of the food chain taught him the shapes of the streambed rocks that insects thrive best under, as well as to learn the metamorphic cycles of those insects once their nymphal stages have departed those rocks. And of course trout behavior came into his purview: how they rest, how they feed, how they reproduce and how they take the hook.</p>
        <p>The reader will learn too, not the rote lessons of stray disconnected facts that so many fishing books try to teach you -- how to read the stream, select a fly, how to cast, how to hook and land a fish -- but instead an exercise in environmental reason, a picture of the world in which all those lessons fit together naturally.  "Neversink" makes for a good trout-fishing primer. It also serves as a first-rate refresher.</p>
        <p>The only thing that Mr. Wright neglects to explain is why people continue to love fishing even in an age when they have agreed to let go most of what they catch. He describes "the moment of exultation in fly fishing -- when you see the fish take your fly and feel the solid resistance as you pull the hook home." He adds: "The tug-of-war that follows is pleasing, but it's not the sorcery that lures us back to the river again and again."</p>
        <p>And for those who dare kill an occasional catch he offers unconventional cooking advice: saute after rigor mortis has come and gone; butter burns at too low a temperature so use bacon fat instead; depending on size, cook the fish 20 to 25 minutes.</p>
        <p>Beyond such superficial raptures he never plunges.</p>
        <p>Still, as "Neversink" makes clear, fishing has unified the world for its author. Every Friday evening, he drives up from New York City to be in his house beside his stretch of the Neversink. Inside that house he keeps binoculars at hand to see what is happening on his trout water.</p>
        <p>In a chapter on the flora in his valley, he admits: "I am no botanist or even wildflower collector, but certain plants command my attention because they act as milestones that mark the progress of the season far more accurately than does the calendar with those too-good-to-be-true naked ladies the local garage hands out." He admires the sedge grass that lines sections of river bank because it grows in "ottoman-sized hummocks" and provides "elegant seating for anglers watching the water for rises or changing flies."</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Wright is obsessed.  But what reader can argue that finding such a unifying principle to one's days isn't finally one of the points of living?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
