<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pastor's Conduct Divides East Side Congregation</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="478923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITARIAN UNIVERSALIST CHURCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALL SOULS UNITARIAN CHURCH (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHURCH, F FORREST (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD81239F934A35753C1A967958260" item-length="1169" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pastor's Conduct Divides East Side Congregation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A prominent Unitarian church on the Upper East Side is being torn by accusations that actions by its pastor -- one of Manhattan's most admired clergymen -- have undermined the trust essential to congregational life and to his credibility as a spiritual leader.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 15, members of All Souls Unitarian Church will vote on whether to reaffirm their confidence in the Rev. F. Forrester Church, or to ask him to resign as senior minister of the church that he is credited with revitalizing over the last 14 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A prominent Unitarian church on the Upper East Side is being torn by accusations that actions by its pastor -- one of Manhattan's most admired clergymen -- have undermined the trust essential to congregational life and to his credibility as a spiritual leader.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 15, members of All Souls Unitarian Church will vote on whether to reaffirm their confidence in the Rev. F. Forrester Church, or to ask him to resign as senior minister of the church that he is credited with revitalizing over the last 14 years.</p>
        <p>The turmoil, which has been growing and becoming more public for months,began last spring when Dr. Church admitted to the All Souls board of trustees that he was sexually involved with a woman active in the congregation, Carolyn Buck Luce. He also acknowledged that last February, when he and his wife, Amy Furth Church, told the congregation they were ending their 20-year marriage, his wife did not know of his extramarital relationship with Ms. Luce. Ms. Luce's marriage also ended in the course of this relationship, and Dr. Church said the couple plan to get married.  A Private Matter</p>
        <p>The church's board, in a letter to congregants, urged them to "put these matters behind us." The trustees view Dr. Church's marital problems as "a private matter, and not the public business of the church," said Mary-Ella Holst, first vice president of the nine-member board.</p>
        <p>But in an open letter to church members distributed outside All Souls before yesterday's services, Sean C. Connor, who headed the board in 1986, contended that Dr. Church had violated the Code of Professional Practices of the Unitarian Universalist Ministers Association, which forbids sexual relations with members of a congregation or their spouses.</p>
        <p>With Dr. Church greeting congregants nearby, many took copies of Mr. Connor's letter and hurried into church without reading it. A few spoke with Mr. Connor. One couple ripped the letter up and thrust the pieces back at him.</p>
        <p>Dr. Church's critics contend that he and the trustees have tried to stifle serious debate about his future.</p>
        <p>They also express outrage that before Ms. Luce's husband, Michael, learned of his wife's affair, Dr. Church sent a letter to Mr. Luce, offering marital counseling.  A Dedicated Pastor</p>
        <p>Dr. Church said that sending the letter to Mr. Luce "is what I regret most." But he said it was a standard letter sent on behalf of the entire ministerial staff to anyone thought to be in need of assistance. It was always clear that another minister would deal with Mr. Luce, Dr. Church said.</p>
        <p>No one denies that Dr. Church, the son of the late Senator Frank Church of Idaho, has been an extraordinarily charismatic and dedicated pastor. When he came to All Souls, the church at 80th Street and Lexington Avenue had 388 members; there are now more than 1,300. The congregation is deeply involved in programs aiding the city's homeless and people with AIDS.</p>
        <p>"There's right, there's wrong and there's real," said Ms. Holst, in explaining her esteem for the minister.  "My husband died six years ago on a Saturday mid-morning when Forrest was in Boston, and by one o'clock he had flown back to be with me," she said. "That's real."</p>
        <p>Mr. Connor, who handed out the letter criticizing Dr. Church yesterday, still considers him "one of the most talented people I've ever known, an absolute natural leader."</p>
        <p>In the early 1980's, Mr. Connor said, "I thought he was the best person to carry the message of liberal religion to the United States. I thought it was really important that someone could do this because of the rise of fundamentalism."</p>
        <p>But Robert A. Miness, also standing outside the church yesterday, was less favorable in his comparison of Dr. Church with a fundamentalist figure.  "Jimmy Swaggart in tweeds," he said.</p>
        <p>For Alexander C. Sanger, a parishioner and the president of Planned Parenthood of New York, "the overall issue is not whether Forrest should be forgiven personally," but "whether his actions justify continuing faith in him to be our moral leader."</p>
        <p>"The fact that the letter was sent out over his signature was incredible," Mr. Sanger said. "The appearance of conflict of interest is enormous."</p>
        <p>Barbara Ascher, an author, said: "A love affair and a divorce -- it happens. What really touches my heart and soul as well as my intellect is the revelation of extreme dishonesty."</p>
        <p>Dr. Church said that at first he hadnot felt free to speak in detail of his behavior before the whole congregation, but that he had been completely open with the trustees and Unitarian officials.</p>
        <p>"I failed with my marital vows," he said. "This is a major failure in my life. I own it, I admit it, I have learned from it."</p>
        <p>"In some ways," he said, "I can minister more effectively and in other ways less effectively. I am no longer the Wizard of Oz. I am a flawed human being who has a much deeper experience now of failure and pain. That helps me in my ministry. I also know that my failure in my marriage and my failure to be completely honest about my new relationship harms my ministry."</p>
        <p>So far, Dr. Church appears to have the backing not only of the trustees but of most of his congregation, many of whom greeted him warmly at church yesterday. Last June, after months of rumors and a few demands for his resignation, he fielded questions at a meeting of more than 100 church members.  Expressions of Confidence</p>
        <p>Valerie Amsterdam, president of the board of trustees, recalled it as a brutally frank session, but also as an expression of confidence in the 43-year-old minister and impatience with his critics. "The overwhelming feeling -- 20 to one -- was, 'We don't want to hear this, how dare you do this, this church has a mission in the community and we don't want to bother with this,' " she said.</p>
        <p>Both sides believe they are supported by Unitarian tradition. To Ms. Holst, the fact that Unitarianism emphasizes religious questioning and has no established creed makes Unitarians tolerant of individuals whose sincere decisions seem to run counter to social norms.</p>
        <p>"Do Unitarians look to the Ten Commandments as something literal and written in stone?" Ms. Amsterdam asked. "We don't have a set of absolute rules as do some other churches."</p>
        <p>But Dr. Church's critics appealed to the same tradition. Unitarians pride themselves on "deeds not creeds," said Mr. Miness, while Dr. Church was substituting "words for deeds."</p>
        <p>The Rev. David C. Pohl, who oversees ministers' credentials for the Unitarian Universalist Association, said that extramarital relationships were not his agency's main concern. "That doesn't mean adultery is acceptable," he said, but "our primary concern is to prevent abuse of the ministerial trust."</p>
        <p>Dr. Church's former wife noted the peculiar psychological conflict the situation poses for church members. "Because many Unitarians have left other traditions that they found too judgmental," Amy Furth Church said, "they have a difficult time in a situation like this."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
