<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Says Dole's Plan Would Bust The Budget</title>
    <meta content="09CLIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="POLITICS: THE DEMOCRAT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="870390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: THE DEMOCRAT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Salinas (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Union of Police Associations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E7DD133EF93AA3575BC0A960958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Says Dole's Plan Would Bust The Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>SALINAS, Calif., Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, campaigning in Salinas, Calif, ridicules Bob Dole's sweeping $548 billion tax cut plan and pledges not to offer any tax cuts that would jeopardize balancing of Federal budget; is endorsed by International Union of Police Associations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Savoring a last moment in the California spotlight before the Republican National Convention takes center stage, President Clinton today ridiculed Bob Dole's sweeping plan for $548 billion in tax cuts over the next six years and promised that he himself would not offer any tax cuts that jeopardized a balancing of the Federal budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton never mentioned his Republican opponent by name. But under a bright sun here in the Central Valley that was Steinbeck country, he told a crowd, ''You'll hear a lot of talk between now and November about tax cuts and how much we should have and whether we can afford them, and they all sound good.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Savoring a last moment in the California spotlight before the Republican National Convention takes center stage, President Clinton today ridiculed Bob Dole's sweeping plan for $548 billion in tax cuts over the next six years and promised that he himself would not offer any tax cuts that jeopardized a balancing of the Federal budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton never mentioned his Republican opponent by name. But under a bright sun here in the Central Valley that was Steinbeck country, he told a crowd, ''You'll hear a lot of talk between now and November about tax cuts and how much we should have and whether we can afford them, and they all sound good.''</p>
        <p>''It's like going to the candy store,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''You know, 'I'll have some of that and some of that and some of that and some of that.'  But if you eat it all at once, you might get sick.''</p>
        <p>The President held out as a counterpoint his own proposals for tax credits for specific purposes like community-college tuition, and implied that Mr. Dole's approach would jeopardize programs like Medicare and Medicaid.</p>
        <p>''I say to you that it might not be popular,'' he said, ''but I will not advocate any cuts in taxes in this election that cannot be paid for in our attempts to balance the budget.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole has said his economic plan would eliminate the deficit over six years even with the tax reduction, for which he would partly pay with a surge in growth that he envisions as resulting from the cut. But the White House has ridiculed his adoption of that supply-side approach, and the targets of some of the budget cuts that would also be needed to pay for the tax breaks have been left sketchy.</p>
        <p>California, with its 54 electoral votes, is a must-win state for Mr. Clinton, and he has lavished attention and Federal money on it, through flood, earthquake and the post-cold-war conversion of the defense industry.</p>
        <p>Today, with Republicans arriving in San Diego for a weeklong convention that will mount a concerted assault on his record, Mr. Clinton devoted his 26th trip to the state as President to emphasis on his economic, crime-fighting and education credentials.</p>
        <p>Much of the battle for California between Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole has focused on crime-fighting, an issue the Republicans had long dominated until the President adopted an approach that mixed his gun-control efforts with those on victims' rights and on punitive measures like expanding the Federal death penalty.</p>
        <p>On a stage outside the Salinas courthouse today, Mr. Clinton, surrounded by uniformed police officers, received a formal endorsement from a police organization for the first time in the current campaign. ''You, more than any other President, have understood law enforcement,'' said Sam Cabral, the president of that group, the 80,000-member International Union of Police Associations, which supported Mr. Clinton in 1992 as well.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also used the occasion to announce that for the first time in seven years, the arrest rates among juveniles for murder and for violent crime as a whole both declined in 1995, an announcement timed to coincide with the release in Washington of new data from the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
        <p>And the arrival back home of a local Olympic hero, Alvin Harrison, born to poverty but today wearing around his neck the gold medal he won in Atlanta as a member of the 4-by-400-meter relay team, led Mr. Clinton to make a pitch for an additional way of fighting crime: providing opportunity to those who might otherwise gravitate toward gang violence.</p>
        <p>''When you tell kids that they matter,'' he said, ''and you tell them they can belong and that they can amount to something and they can live out their dreams and that no matter where they might start out they might wind up with a gold medal, and at least they can win a gold medal in the race of life if they do the right things, then you can change this.''</p>
        <p>Besides being significant for its electoral votes, California has been a wellspring of money for Mr. Clinton and other Democrats, and this trip was centered on a fund-raising event tonight at the Los Angeles home of Marc Nathanson, a cable television executive. The event was expected to raise $1.2 million for Democratic Congressional candidates.</p>
        <p>Earlier, in San Jose, the President made a highly partisan speech that was delivered by satellite to a Pittsburgh conference of the United Steelworkers of America. In it, he attacked the Republican Congress and called for the Democrats to be put back in control of Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>''You remember what they tried to do,'' he said of the Republicans, ''how they shut the Government down twice, what they tried to do to Medicare, Medicaid, education and the environment. Unless we win the Presidential race and change the composition of the Congress, they'll keep trying to do it over and over and over again.''</p>
        <p>A CELEBRATION TURNS ROWDY</p>
        <p>Of the hundreds at the opening of Clinton-Gore campaign headquarters in New York, half were protesters. Metropolitan Report, page B1.</p>
        <p>POLITICS: THE DEMOCRAT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
