<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>KERRY CHOOSES EDWARDS, CITING FORMER RIVAL'S POLITICAL SKILL</title>
    <meta content="07KERR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/07/politics/campaign/07KERR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040708T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1594964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 ELECTION: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Carolina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John Edwards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040707T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E0D9143BF934A35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>KERRY CHOOSES EDWARDS, CITING FORMER RIVAL'S POLITICAL SKILL</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kerry Chooses Edwards, Citing Former Rival's 'Political Skill'</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER; David E. Rosenbaum and Adam Nagourney contributed reporting from Washington for this article, and John Tierney from Pittsburgh.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, July 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry names John Edwards as his vice presidential running mate, saying North Carolina senator has shown courage and conviction as champion of middle-class Americans and those striving to reach middle class; Edwards and family join Kerry family in Pittsburgh after Kerry campaign makes announcement to supporters by e-mail; photos; Democrats say Edwards's buoyant personality and sunny speaking style will bring needed jolt of energy to ticket, and provide striking contrast to Vice Pres Cheney; also hope Edwards, with black support, will put North Carolina and other Southern states into play (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry named John Edwards as his running mate on Tuesday, turning to a youthful North Carolina senator whose nimble campaign skills, engaging personality and evident appeal across different regions of the country had made him the top choice of many Democratic leaders.</p>
        <p>''I have chosen a man who understands and defends the values of America,'' Mr. Kerry told a roaring crowd at a morning rally at Market Square here, minutes after an announcement of his choice had been e-mailed to hundreds of thousands of supporters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry named John Edwards, the top choice of many Democratic leaders, as his running mate on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John Kerry named John Edwards as his running mate on Tuesday, turning to a youthful North Carolina senator whose nimble campaign skills, engaging personality and evident appeal across different regions of the country had made him the top choice of many Democratic leaders.</p>
        <p>''I have chosen a man who understands and defends the values of America,'' Mr. Kerry told a roaring crowd at a morning rally at Market Square here, minutes after an announcement of his choice had been e-mailed to hundreds of thousands of supporters.</p>
        <p>''A man who has shown courage and conviction as a champion for middle-class Americans and for those struggling to reach the middle class,'' Senator Kerry added, citing the themes that Mr. Edwards had made his own in the Democratic primaries. ''A man who has shown guts and determination and political skill in his own race for the presidency of the United States.''</p>
        <p>In the 51-year-old Mr. Edwards, Senator Kerry, who is 60, chose a relative newcomer to American politics, and a man who was his longest-lasting major rival in the Democratic nominating contests.</p>
        <p>After a surprisingly strong second-place finish in the Iowa caucuses -- some Kerry aides say they believe Mr. Edwards would have won had the caucuses occurred two days later -- Mr. Edwards held on until the first week of March as others once thought to have more star power, like Howard Dean and Gen. Wesley K. Clark, fell behind.</p>
        <p>''I was humbled by his offer and thrilled to accept it,'' Mr. Edwards said in a statement before his wife and children joined him to fly to Pittsburgh to spend the evening with the Kerry family at Teresa Heinz Kerry's estate near here.</p>
        <p>The Kerry campaign orchestrated the selection for maximum exposure, managing to keep it a secret across the holiday weekend, making both a traditional rally announcement as well as one by e-mail and delaying the ticket's first joint appearance until Wednesday. The two men and their wives are to embark Wednesday on a four-day tour through the swing states of Ohio, Florida, West Virginia and New Mexico before ending the week with a rally in North Carolina on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Democrats who hailed the selection on Tuesday said Mr. Edwards's buoyant personality and drawling, sunny speaking style would bring a needed jolt of energy to Mr. Kerry's ticket. They said he would provide a striking contrast to Vice President Dick Cheney, though Republicans countered that a debate between the two would be a face-off between sizzle and substance, particularly over the Iraq war, when Mr. Edwards's relative lack of foreign policy experience would be an issue.</p>
        <p>Several Democrats also said that Mr. Edwards's selection would put to rest questions that Mr. Kerry, of Massachusetts, was writing off the South. Rather, they said, the addition of Mr. Edwards -- and his support from blacks, among other mainstay Democratic constituencies -- would put North Carolina into play and bolster Mr. Kerry's bid in other Southern states, improving his chances of outdoing the abysmal performance in the South of Al Gore, a native Tennessean, four years ago.</p>
        <p>The choice of Mr. Edwards is also likely to have a powerful effect on the future of the party, giving a platform to a younger Democrat and setting up a potential leadership clash between Mr. Edwards, as Mr. Kerry's presumptive heir, and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, who is widely thought to have designs on the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards's background as a trial lawyer is certain to help Mr. Kerry and the Democratic Party raise money heading into the fall campaign, but Republicans and industry officials said it also would propel business executives, manufacturers and other proponents of curbs on civil litigation and jury awards to increase contributions to President Bush.</p>
        <p>More immediately, the choice of Mr. Edwards forced aides to Mr. Kerry to try to reconcile his dismissal of Mr. Edwards as unready for the presidency when the two men were vying in the Democratic primaries.</p>
        <p>''In the Senate four years -- and that is the full extent of public life -- no international experience, no military experience,'' Mr. Kerry said in Iowa in January. ''When I came back from Vietnam in 1969, I don't know if John Edwards was out of diapers.''</p>
        <p>And in February, Mr. Kerry warned, ''This is not the time for on-the-job training in the White House on national security issues.''</p>
        <p>Republicans immediately played up Mr. Kerry's past remarks. ''This is the person he now considers qualified to be president of the United States?'' said Steve Schmidt, a Bush campaign spokesman, as Republicans circulated a 23-page, 16,000-word dossier on Tuesday that depicted Mr. Edwards as an unaccomplished, inexperienced, disingenuous liberal.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign also began airing a television advertisement featuring what it described as ''John Kerry's first choice for a vice presidential running mate,'' Senator John McCain of Arizona. Mr. McCain, a Republican with an appeal to independents, had deflected several approaches by Mr. Kerry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards, the son of a millworker who became a wealthy plaintiff's lawyer, has said he was driven to enter politics after his eldest son Wade's death as a teenager in a car accident in 1996. Two years later, in his first race, he unseated Senator Lauch Faircloth of North Carolina, then began running for the presidency before his first term was over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry left questions to aides on Tuesday afternoon as he flew from here to Indianapolis to speak to a convention of the African Methodist Episcopal Church. His campaign manager, Mary Beth Cahill, acknowledged that strategy played a part in choosing Mr. Edwards but said that Mr. Kerry was more concerned that his running mate ''be in a position to succeed him.''</p>
        <p>When asked when and how Mr. Kerry had satisfied himself of Mr. Edwards's readiness to assume the presidency, Ms. Cahill cited Mr. Edwards's ''tireless'' campaigning for Mr. Kerry.</p>
        <p>''When you're competing in the primaries, you are thinking about getting through the primaries,'' she said. ''When you look at who is a good running mate, a good partner, that is a different calculus. And when he went through that, it was clear to him that Senator Edwards would be a great partner to win the presidency in November.''</p>
        <p>In his announcement, Mr. Kerry provided clues to how his estimation of Mr. Edwards had risen. ''I've seen John Edwards think, argue, advocate, legislate and lead for six years now,'' he said. ''I know his skill, I know his passion, I know his strength, I know his conscience, I know his faith.''</p>
        <p>''John Edwards is ready for this job,'' Mr. Kerry said. ''John Edwards is ready for this job,'' he repeated, adding, ''I am determined that we reach out across party lines, that we speak the heart of America, that we speak of hope and optimism, and John Edwards will join me in doing that.''</p>
        <p>For all their friction in the primaries, Mr. Kerry and Mr. Edwards had two influential Democrats in common as advisers: Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts, who took Mr. Edwards under his wing in the Senate and took an increasingly large role in Mr. Kerry's campaign in the primaries; and Bob Shrum, the speechwriter and media consultant who worked for both Mr. Kerry and Mr. Edwards until both men's entry into the primary race led him to drop Mr. Edwards as a client last year.</p>
        <p>They have voted alike on every important issue likely to arise during the presidential campaign, starting with the Iraq war. Both voted to authorize Mr. Bush to deploy troops in Iraq. They have voted in favor of abortion rights, gun control, changes in campaign finance laws, stronger environmental standards and the antiterrorism law known as the USA Patriot Act. They also voted against impeaching President Bill Clinton and against the Bush tax cuts.</p>
        <p>In Congressional Quarterly's 10 to 15 ''key votes'' of the year, since 1999, when Mr. Edwards entered the Senate, he and Mr. Kerry have been on opposite sides of these issues only twice, on whether a nuclear waste disposal site should be built in Nevada (Mr. Edwards in favor, Mr. Kerry against) and on whether Mr. Bush's plan for closing military bases should be adopted (Mr. Kerry in favor, Mr. Edwards against).</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards was not in the Senate in 1993 when Congress approved the North American Free Trade Agreement, which Mr. Kerry supported. This year, Mr. Edwards said he would have voted against the measure. In the Senate, their records on trade matters have differed only slightly.</p>
        <p>The announcement on Tuesday concluded an extraordinarily secret vetting and decision-making process, one in which Mr. Kerry concealed his intentions from even his closest aides until late Monday night. The first person other than Mr. Kerry's wife to learn of Mr. Edwards's selection was a contractor hired to redecorate the fuselage of his jet with both men's names, aides said. Mr. Kerry called the contractor about 6 p.m. Monday so he could have the plane ready by Tuesday morning. He did not tell his campaign manager and other senior aides until about 10:30 p.m., they said.</p>
        <p>In keeping his own counsel, Mr. Kerry drew on his displeasure at having learned from television reports of his rejection in 2000, when both he and Mr. Edwards were considered and ultimately passed over by Mr. Gore. Aides said Mr. Kerry called Mr. Edwards about 7:30 a.m. Tuesday, about the time that news organizations were first reporting his decision and minutes before the mass e-mail message was sent. Mr. Edwards learned the news from Mr. Kerry, judging from their telephone conversation, Ms. Cahill said.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, who had made known his plans to retire from politics if Mr. Kerry did not choose him, called the Kerry-Edwards pairing ''a ticket that can excite, motivate and most importantly defeat George Bush and Dick Cheney in November.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt said he would continue to campaign with and for Mr. Kerry and Mr. Edwards, as did Gov. Tom Vilsack of Iowa, the little-known Midwesterner whose close ties with Mr. Kerry and leadership of a crucial swing state helped vault him into close contention for the job.</p>
        <p>THE 2004 ELECTION: THE OVERVIEW</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 8, 2004, Thursday  A front-page article yesterday about John Kerry's selection of John Edwards as his running mate misstated the number of terms served by Lauch Faircloth, whom Mr. Edwards defeated for the Senate from North Carolina in 1998. It was one term, not three.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 8, 2004, Thursday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about John Kerry's selection of John Edwards as his running mate misstated the number of terms served by Lauch Faircloth, whom Mr. Edwards defeated for the Senate from North Carolina in 1998. It was one term, not three.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
