<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winning the Series Can Be Dangerous</title>
    <meta content="03BASE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7DF1438F930A35752C1A960958260" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winning the Series Can Be Dangerous</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baseball Notebook; sidelights on New York Yankees World Series victory (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As euphoric as the final out of the World Series was for John Wetteland, the pile that ensued on the mound at Yankee Stadium was frightening for him. That's because the Yankee closer was on the bottom.</p>
        <p>''I was screaming for people to get off me,'' Wetteland related later. ''It was scary. I felt this shooting pain go through my ankle. I was yelling, 'Get off, get off.' They thought I was just yelling and kept piling on. Finally, Rock Raines heard me and started throwing people off me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As euphoric as the final out of the World Series was for John Wetteland, the pile that ensued on the mound at Yankee Stadium was frightening for him. That's because the Yankee closer was on the bottom.</p>
        <p>''I was screaming for people to get off me,'' Wetteland related later. ''It was scary. I felt this shooting pain go through my ankle. I was yelling, 'Get off, get off.' They thought I was just yelling and kept piling on. Finally, Rock Raines heard me and started throwing people off me.''</p>
        <p>Wetteland had reason to be concerned. In 1960, Vernon Law won the first and fourth games of the World Series for Pittsburgh, then left Game 7 in the sixth inning with a 4-1 lead. In the post-game celebration, Bob Oldis, a catcher, yanked off one of Law's shoes without untying it, and Law wound up with an injured ankle.</p>
        <p>A 20-game winner that season, Law struggled for the next several seasons, a situation that was blamed on his ankle ailment.</p>
        <p>Bulletin Board Material</p>
        <p>In an ironic twist to the World Series, the Yankees said the Atlanta Braves' behavior and remarks after their victories in the first two games helped motivate the Yankees in the next four games. The Braves offered a similar observation about St. Louis players after they rallied from a 3-1 deficit and beat the Cardinals for the National League pennant.</p>
        <p>When the Braves were in the midst of their comeback, it was the Cardinals who had made the inflammatory comments. Nevertheless, Braves Manager Bobby Cox dismissed the idea that such remarks can inspire a team.</p>
        <p>''It's not like football, where you can take your aggression out on a guy six inches from your nose,'' Cox said. ''Baseball is a real skilled sport. You don't want to be so fired up that you can't perform. I'm not one to post stuff on the bulletin board.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather get a broken bat hit for a game winner. There's no motivation a bulletin board article is going to give you. If a guy has to be motivated by something some guy says, you're in deep trouble.''</p>
        <p>Did They Use Invisible Ink?</p>
        <p>The Rawling Sporting Goods Company, which makes the major leagues' baseballs, has been advertising the ''only official 1996 World Series baseball.'' But for $19.95, the buyer does not get a Bud Ball.</p>
        <p>For the first time since 1991, the balls used in the World Series bore the signature of a commissioner, or in this case, an acting commissioner. The signature was that of Allan H. Selig, Office of the Commissioner. But the balls Rawlings advertises as official have no signature. In the spot where it would be, the balls say, ''Official Ball 1996 World Series.''</p>
        <p>So much for authenticity.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
