<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That Courthouse Religion</title>
    <meta content="03MARGOLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Margolick, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cochran, Johnnie L Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutten, Tim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Journey to Justice (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1DB1339F930A35752C1A960958260" item-length="2127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That Courthouse Religion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Margolick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Margolick, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Margolick reviews book Journey to Justice by Johnnie L Cochran Jr with Tim Rutten; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOURNEY TO JUSTICE  By Johnnie L. Cochran Jr. with Tim Rutten.  Illustrated. 383 pp. New York:  One World/Ballantine Books. $26.</p>
        <p>Johnnie L. Cochran Jr. was the undisputed king of People v. Orenthal James Simpson. His client knew that Mr. Cochran was his surest ticket to freedom and implored him to take the case. Mr. Cochran's former underling, Judge Lance A. Ito, was clearly in awe of him and coddled him throughout the yearlong trial. Mr. Cochran ruled the ''Dream Team,'' relegating his erstwhile rival, Robert L. Shapiro, to a humiliatingly marginal role. The lead prosecutor, Marcia Clark, proved no match for either Mr. Cochran's satiny charm or his silken ruthlessness, yet could not resist him, flirting with him flagrantly. Mr. Cochran drove her colleague Christopher A. Darden crazy, and relished every minute of it. Even reporters who thought Mr. Cochran slippery found him fetching. As for the jurors -- the ''downtown,'' that is, largely minority, panelists ''Mr. Johnnie'' has always wowed -- their sound-bite deliberations revealed just how complete was his mastery of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOURNEY TO JUSTICE  By Johnnie L. Cochran Jr. with Tim Rutten.  Illustrated. 383 pp. New York:  One World/Ballantine Books. $26.</p>
        <p>Johnnie L. Cochran Jr. was the undisputed king of People v. Orenthal James Simpson. His client knew that Mr. Cochran was his surest ticket to freedom and implored him to take the case. Mr. Cochran's former underling, Judge Lance A. Ito, was clearly in awe of him and coddled him throughout the yearlong trial. Mr. Cochran ruled the ''Dream Team,'' relegating his erstwhile rival, Robert L. Shapiro, to a humiliatingly marginal role. The lead prosecutor, Marcia Clark, proved no match for either Mr. Cochran's satiny charm or his silken ruthlessness, yet could not resist him, flirting with him flagrantly. Mr. Cochran drove her colleague Christopher A. Darden crazy, and relished every minute of it. Even reporters who thought Mr. Cochran slippery found him fetching. As for the jurors -- the ''downtown,'' that is, largely minority, panelists ''Mr. Johnnie'' has always wowed -- their sound-bite deliberations revealed just how complete was his mastery of them.</p>
        <p>Outside Los Angeles Superior Court, Mr. Cochran's stock was iffier. Many loathed him as a high-priced hustler who had turned what they considered a grisly but garden-variety murder into a parable of American racism and had transformed a double murderer into Dred Scott or Rosa Parks. But Mr. Cochran, with his periwinkle suits and phosphorescent neckties, his ''God Is Love'' lapel pins and utterly unflappable manner, didn't pay much mind, and why should he have? He was a lawyer at the absolute top of his game, perfectly equipped to win the last, best Trial of the Century.</p>
        <p>''Journey to Justice'' is partly Mr. Cochran's account of how he reached so high a professional pinnacle. In that capacity, the book is a likable, if literary-lite, memoir, in which he tells of parlaying devoted parents, religious faith, a quick mind, a silver tongue and an intermittently genuine smile into a successful legal career, and how, by heeding heroes like W. E. B. Du Bois, Thurgood Marshall and Joe Louis, and taking on a racist and lawless Los Angeles Police Department before anyone else, he became wealthy, famous and important in the process. But once the journey reaches Judge Ito's courtroom, the book hits the skids. On the subject for which his publisher paid him millions, Mr. Cochran is more interested in rehashing -- or, sometimes, literally reprinting -- old arguments, rewriting or evading history and settling old scores than he is in telling us anything new.</p>
        <p>No one would expect Mr. Cochran to admit that he always thought O. J. Simpson was guilty and his story suspect, though other books about the case say that he dropped such hints. But one did expect Mr. Cochran to argue more persuasively for Mr. Simpson's innocence or to reconstruct his defense more revealingly, to praise him more originally -- or at least to describe him more vividly. After all, in the year after Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald Goldman were murdered, no one spoke with, joked with, sat with, prayed with, cried with, commiserated with and, ultimately, celebrated with the football star turned celebrity defendant more.</p>
        <p>How could someone as charismatic and clever as Mr. Cochran make so fascinating a trial and enigmatic a client so dull and so predictable? The blame can't go to his co-author, Tim Rutten, a reporter at The Los Angeles Times, whose fingerprints are detectable only in some overly erudite allusions and a few glowing references to his wife, the lawyer Leslie Abramson, of the Menendez trials. Nor can it rest with divine providence, to which Mr. Cochran credits much else in his life, from his initial decision to take on the L.A.P.D. to the discovery of Detective Mark Fuhrman's tape-recorded racist rantings (which really did seem like manna from heaven). Nor can it be assigned solely to Mr. Simpson's latest lawyers, who, anxious to protect him at his civil trial and to earn their keep, have clearly run the book through the deflavorizing machine.</p>
        <p>No, the blame rests squarely with Mr. Cochran. While his familiar voice -- alternately effusive, soothing, unctuous, smoothly indignant, polysyllabically hypersincere, an amalgam of the preachers he heard as a child, the insurance salesman he once was and the disk jockey he could have been -- is amply on display, he says little with it. One cannot help feeling that, having led a charmed life of late, Mr. Cochran has simply chosen to coast.</p>
        <p>By far the most engaging and informative pages of ''Journey to Justice'' are the early ones. Affectionately and emotionally, Mr. Cochran describes his childhood in Shreveport, La., ''a world where your food was always fried and everyone you knew was black and a Baptist.'' When he was 6 years old, in 1943, his family moved to California, where his father took a wartime job in a shipyard. When the fighting stopped, he resumed his work as an insurance salesman, first around Oakland, later in San Diego and Los Angeles. The Cochran home was stable and loving: for the last 40 years of her life, Mr. Cochran called his mother nightly; his elderly father still lives with him. And with a few chilling exceptions, it was a life in which, he says, he was kept largely insulated from discrimination. His classmates were white and, at the prestigious Los Angeles High School, often Jewish (one was Dustin Hoffman). It was from the children of Jewish garment manufacturers, he says, that he picked up his taste for fancy clothes. Indeed, Mr. Cochran repeatedly takes pains to stress his close ties to the Jewish community, dropping Yiddish words and references to seders and kibbutzim and Holocaust memorials.</p>
        <p>Much to his mother's disappointment, he resolved early on to become a lawyer. After attending the University of California, Los Angeles, and Loyola Law School, he joined the Los Angeles City Attorney's office. There, watching police officers routinely lie in drunk-driving cases and haul in mangled black men who had supposedly resisted arrest (while the officers themselves invariably remained unscathed), he learned that lawlessness, deceit, racism and brutality were endemic in the local police culture. For the next 30 years he battled it, mostly in private practice, representing victims and their families in personal injury cases (and briefly in the L.A. District Attorney's office, where Gil Garcetti -- who would head that office during the Simpson trial -- served with him and Lance Ito served under him). The millions Mr. Cochran made helped him branch off into entertainment law, taking on clients like Lou Rawls, Aretha Franklin and Michael Jackson (whose settlement of child molestation charges he dispatches in a sentence or two).</p>
        <p>Mr. Cochran and Mr. Simpson were but casual acquaintances until June 12, 1994. Within a few days, Mr. Simpson was calling him incessantly from jail, maintaining his innocence, pleading for help. Bill Cosby -- ''a valued friend and adviser'' -- urged Mr. Cochran to steer clear of the case. But after a visit to his mother's grave, he signed on. Strictly as business, Mr. Cochran writes, it was a bad move. ''But at the end of the day, you decide certain questions with your heart rather than your head,'' he states.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cochran denies the charge, contained in Jeffrey Toobin's ''Run of His Life: The People v. O. J. Simpson,'' that before taking the case he told someone that Mr. Simpson was guilty. Any reservations he had, he writes, disappeared upon hearing his client declare, ''with as much conviction as I have ever heard in a courtroom,'' that he was ''absolutely, 100 percent not guilty.'' But according to another account of the trial -- ''American Tragedy: The Uncensored Story of the Simpson Defense,'' by Lawrence Schiller and James Willwerth -- Mr. Cochran spoon-fed those words to Mr. Simpson. Mr. Cochran the memoirist has tougher rivals now than Mr. Cochran the Dream Team lawyer ever had; these other books make ''Journey to Justice'' look shallow and disingenuous. Apart from calling Mr. Simpson ''a nice guy'' and ''the most instinctively perceptive client I've ever represented'' (and slapping his wrist for failing to come to ''appropriate terms'' with his wife-beating), Mr. Cochran grapples hardly at all with the character of his most famous client.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Mr. Cochran denies playing the race card, insisting that by harping on the bigotry of the local police he played ''the history and credibility cards'' instead. Nor, he insists, did the defense ever claim that ''some shadowy cabal'' of police officers set out to frame Mr. Simpson because he is black. He characterizes Mr. Simpson instead as the victim of ''a process far more complex and amorphously malevolent,'' orchestrated by the lazy and ''dishonest'' detectives in charge of the case (Philip Vannatter and Tom Lange), a hate-mongering policeman working under them (Mark Fuhrman) and an ambitious prosecutor (Marcia Clark). Nothing new there. On other issues -- his dubious insistence that one cannot identify some blacks by their voices and that to suggest so is racist; his own marital history; his use of Fruit of Islam security guards; his decision not to call promised witnesses like Rosa Lopez, or Mr. Simpson himself for that matter, to the stand; Mr. Simpson's supposedly spontaneous statement to the court waiving his right to testify -- Mr. Cochran is either evasive, sketchy, silent or downright deceptive.</p>
        <p>Nothing is more striking about ''Journey to Justice'' than its religiosity. Mr. Cochran frequently quotes Scripture, compares himself to Jesus Christ and likens himself ad nauseam to David battling the Goliath of the Los Angeles Police Department. But for all of its ostentatious piety, the book is conspicuously un-Christian, at least concerning Jesus' admonition about turning the other cheek.</p>
        <p>Sure, Mr. Cochran's former wife has written a tell-all book about him, but did she really give him such unvarying, terrible, selfish career advice at every stage of their marriage? Sure, Mr. Shapiro has accused him of dealing the race card ''from the bottom of the deck'' and tape-recorded defense meetings surreptitiously. Sure, Mr. Darden sparred regularly with him in court, then in his own book. But just as he could always afford to call Judge Ito ''wise,'' the triumphant Mr. Cochran is perfectly positioned to kill these people with kindness, to maul them with magnanimity, to include them in his own ''circle of benevolence.'' Instead, he attacks them obsessively and unbecomingly.</p>
        <p>Not content to depict Mr. Shapiro as a publicity-seeking, money-craving, treacherous crybaby, he goes on to ridicule his track record (''large number of minor cases''), his knowledge of murder trials (''essentially . . . ignorant'') and even the size of his law office (''cramped'' and with no validated parking privileges). He even likens Mr. Shapiro to Kato Kaelin (I don't understand the comparison either). Worse, he contrasts Mr. Shapiro unflatteringly with his archenemy on the Dream Team, F. Lee Bailey. ''As my good opinion of Bob Shapiro declined, the esteem in which I held F. Lee Bailey . . . increased,'' he writes. You can't get much meaner than that.</p>
        <p>Again with Mr. Darden, to whom he had always been a hero, Mr. Cochran goes out of his way to be brutal. In part because of Mr. Cochran's own inflammatory rhetoric in court -- he charged that Mr. Darden had been added to the prosecution simply because he was black, and ridiculed his desire to keep the word ''nigger'' out of the proceedings -- no lawyer in the Simpson trial had a tougher assignment than Mr. Darden, a black prosecutor prosecuting a black legend. But rather than brush aside or rise above their disputes, Mr. Cochran tears away at Mr. Darden's competence and character, then pretends he's doing nothing of the sort. All this may be Mr. Cochran's way of boasting that Mr. Darden would never catch up to him as a lawyer. But it may just as well reflect his fear that Mr. Darden had already caught on to him as a man.</p>
        <p>In downtown Los Angeles, Mr. Cochran says, he was playing on his ''home court.'' But in ''Journey to Justice,'' he's moved to a larger, more difficult arena, and the show has not traveled well. Someday, perhaps, he will tell us what he really thinks about Mr. Simpson and his story. In that key respect, at least, ''Journey to Justice'' never gets much past its first, single step.</p>
        <p>David Margolick, who covered the O. J. Simpson trial for The New York Times, is now a contributing editor at Vanity Fair.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Margolick, who covered the O. J. Simpson trial for The New York Times, is now a contributing editor at Vanity Fair.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
