<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Midtown World Of Worldly Cuisines</title>
    <meta content="03REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="GOOD EATING" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD EATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Good Eating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61E39F930A35752C1A960958260" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Midtown World Of Worldly Cuisines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of reviews of midtown Manhattan restaurants featuring cuisines from around world (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARTUSI **</p>
        <p>(212) 582-6900; 36 West 52d Street; $$$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>Artusi, dedicated to the great Italian gastronome who wrote one of the premier works on Italian cooking at the turn of the century, offers serious food in a comfortable setting. For starters, there is warm bruschetta laden with shrimp and pieces of green apple accompanied by a well-seasoned salad of frisee; vitello tonnato, a classic version of tuna in veal sauce sprinkled with capers and embellished with a bouquet of baby arugula, and Arista, the roasted pork loin of Tuscany, sliced paper thin and surrounded by eggplant, lettuce, sun-dried tomatoes and potatoes. Pastas are excellent and include tagliolini blended with prosciutto di Parma and quail eggs, and sweet potato and pumpkin cannelloni in marjoram sauce with Parmesan. There are entrees of roast rack of lamb with chestnuts and a rosemary sauce, pan-roasted striped bass with spinach, and braised veal spiced with garlic and orange zest and paired with a carrot galette. (Review: 8/2/ 96)</p>
        <p>CHINA GRILL *</p>
        <p>(212) 333-7788; 60 West 53d Street; $$$$; all major credit cards</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARTUSI **</p>
        <p>(212) 582-6900; 36 West 52d Street; $$$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>Artusi, dedicated to the great Italian gastronome who wrote one of the premier works on Italian cooking at the turn of the century, offers serious food in a comfortable setting. For starters, there is warm bruschetta laden with shrimp and pieces of green apple accompanied by a well-seasoned salad of frisee; vitello tonnato, a classic version of tuna in veal sauce sprinkled with capers and embellished with a bouquet of baby arugula, and Arista, the roasted pork loin of Tuscany, sliced paper thin and surrounded by eggplant, lettuce, sun-dried tomatoes and potatoes. Pastas are excellent and include tagliolini blended with prosciutto di Parma and quail eggs, and sweet potato and pumpkin cannelloni in marjoram sauce with Parmesan. There are entrees of roast rack of lamb with chestnuts and a rosemary sauce, pan-roasted striped bass with spinach, and braised veal spiced with garlic and orange zest and paired with a carrot galette. (Review: 8/2/ 96)</p>
        <p>CHINA GRILL *</p>
        <p>(212) 333-7788; 60 West 53d Street; $$$$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>China Grill is an airy, clamorous and friendly place with soaring ceilings and marble floors where East meets West pleasingly on the plates. Dinner might begin with little rolls of sake-cured salmon with a lemongrass vinaigrette; stir-fried lobster pancakes with coconut milk, chili and scallions, or the light sashimi tempura, wrapped in seaweed and served with a hot-mustard Champagne sauce. The menu carries entrees of barbecued salmon with Chinese mustard sauce and sauteed greens, grilled shrimp in a curry-coconut sauce and served with black fettuccine, and grilled beef prepared Sichuan style in a spicy sauce of soy, sake, shallots and cilantro. (Review: 11/19/93)</p>
        <p>CHRISTER'S **</p>
        <p>(212) 974-7224; 145 West 55th Street; $$$; American Express, Mastercard, Visa</p>
        <p>Christer's looks like an upscale urban lodge with its giant stone fireplace and exposed logs overhead. Fish sculpture catches the eye in every corner of the restaurant, and fish dominates the menu. As for Christer Larsson's cooking, the Swedish-born chef fuses classic Scandinavian with contemporary American. For starters, consider the traditional smorgasbord, an excellent sampler of herring and salmon served in various ways. The eggplant terrine with goat cheese and mushrooms or the Fisher's Island oysters on the half shell are other choices. Mr. Larsson's main dishes include sauteed monkfish served with mashed potatoes and a sauce of roasted plum tomatoes, snapper baked in an almond crust and finished with a paprika broth, and veal fricadelles, or Swedish meatballs, served over mashed potatoes and topped with smoky bits of bacon and a plum compote sauce. (Review: 2/ 18/94)</p>
        <p>DARBAR ***</p>
        <p>(212) 432-7227; 44 West 56th Street; $$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>This superior restaurant specializes in the refined Mogul cuisine of northern India. It is decorated with handsome tapestries and hammered-copper hangings. A good way to start is with an assortment of pakoras, tasty fritters of vegetable, shrimp or chicken; mulligatawny soup, made of lentils, tomatoes and spices, or samosas, little vegetable-filled pastries. Among main courses are a traditional dish called mughlai korma, in which boneless pieces of chicken are cooked in sweet coconut and yogurt and finished with various nuts and spices; shahi lamb chops, which are marinated in yogurt, ginger and garlic and then roasted in the tandoor; lobster in coconut cream, and rogan josh, tender pieces of lamb cooked in a sweet onion sauce with yogurt, cream and almonds. (Review: 8/10/90; article: 10/30/92)</p>
        <p>MICHAEL'S **</p>
        <p>(212) 767-0555; 24 West 55th Street; $$$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>Michael's, a pioneer in California-style cooking, has become a haven for salad eaters. Choices include the Cobb salad, a blend of watercress, avocado, bacon, blue cheese, chicken, eggs and tomatoes in a balsamic vinaigrette; a lovely nicoise with freshly grilled tuna, olives, capers, potatoes, eggs, grilled peppers, tomatoes and Parmesan cheese, and an assembly of baby greens, grilled chicken, goat cheese, roasted peppers and grilled onions glistening in a cilantro, lime and olive-oil dressing. Among appetizers, oysters and littleneck clams are winners, as is the excellent gravlax with mustard-dill sauce and toasted brioche. (Review: 9/22/95)</p>
        <p>MENCHANKO-TEI ++  (212) 247-1585; 9 West 55th Street; $; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>There are many Japanese soba shops in New York City, and this is one of the best. There are five categories of hot and cold noodle options to choose from when ordering the soups here. The menu maps it all out, not only with lengthy descriptions of each variation, but also with diagrams of the various preparations. Kikuzo ramen is a deep bowl of squiggly fresh noodles, scallions, bamboo shoots, fish cakes and tasty slices of lean pork. Hakata ramen is served in a porcelain bowl, its pale, rich, restorative broth replete with roast pork, mushrooms and slivers of ginger on a bed of soft, white noodles. And menchanko, the house specialty, comes in a deep brass bowl, a flavorful broth filled with pressed bean curd, soba noodles, cabbage, fish cakes, bean sprouts and other vegetables. ($25 and Under: 4/24/92; article: 12/26/93)</p>
        <p>TANG PAVILION **</p>
        <p>(212) 956-6888; 65 West 55th Street; $$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>Much prized in China and quite different from the more familiar southern fare is the complex cuisine of the East, from cities like Shanghai. The secret at this elegant restaurant is to ask for the menu of Shanghai specialties, and you're in for a real treat. Begin with drunken poached chicken, its heady, musky flavor imparted from a marinade of Shao Hsing wine; the delicate terrine of a vegetable pie, or the light green bean and tofu sheet, with long white bands of almost translucent dried bean curd tossed with small bright green beans. Also recommended are the sweet mixture of baby eel strips, yellow chives and ginger; golden strands of jellyfish slicked with sesame oil; braised pork in soy sauce, rice wine, sugar and ginger, and braised duck stuffed with a sweet rice mixture. (Review: 3/18/94)</p>
        <p>AQUAVIT ***</p>
        <p>(212) 307-7311; 13 West 54th Street; $$$$; all major credit cards</p>
        <p>Surrounded by glass and sky, Aquavit occupies a magical space filled with changing light and the gentle sound of falling water. The delicate and beautiful food is a balance of Swedish tradition and modern taste. There are starters of smoked salmon complemented by a warm potato and goat-cheese tart and crowned by sevruga caviar, seared duck with pickled wild mushrooms and a roasted-nut salad, and mixed greens laced with julienned root vegetables and roasted tomatoes. For main courses, venison is served in a prune crust and presented with a celeriac reduction and an accompaniment of pear-potato strudel, and pan-roasted sea bass comes with a little crab salad and tomato tagliatini. (Review: 9/29/95)</p>
        <p>Summaries of reviews use the star system; others are culled from articles (indicated by +), the $25 and Under column (++) and Diner's Journal ($S).</p>
        <p>The Star System  The New York Times's star system rates restaurants on the following scale.</p>
        <p>**** Extraordinary  *** Excellent  ** Very Good  * Good  None Poor to Satisfactory</p>
        <p>Price Range  The price symbols are based on the cost of a three-course dinner with tax and a 15 percent tip (drinks not included).</p>
        <p>$ $25 and under  $$ $25 to $40  $$$ $40 to $55  $$$$ $55 and over</p>
        <p>Past reviews. Hundreds of Times restaurant reviews are available from @times, an arts and entertainment guide on America Online. Software and information: (800) 548-5201.</p>
        <p>GOOD EATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
