<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="359496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1F3CF934A35755C0A966958260" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Violence erupted in a Soviet republic. Moscow reported that at least 40 people had been killed in three days of ethnic rioting and Soviet troop countermeasures in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Violence erupted in a Soviet republic. Moscow reported that at least 40 people had been killed in three days of ethnic rioting and Soviet troop countermeasures in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-15</p>
        <p>Violence erupted in a Soviet republic. Moscow reported that at least 40 people had been killed in three days of ethnic rioting and Soviet troop countermeasures in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia.</p>
        <p>Page A1</p>
        <p>Nuclear plants in Eastern Europe fall far short of Western safety standards and in many cases should be radically modified or closed, West European scientists who inspected the reactors have concluded.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The man who ruled Czechoslovakia as Communist Party chief for two years until the party was overthrown last November was seized for interrogation on ''criminal offenses,'' including his role in the Soviet-led invasion in 1968.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Baker seeks Europe security group shift</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Interpreters: hours of tedium and moments of precision</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Soviets to repay lend-lease after a trade accord</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Warsaw declares market conversion complete</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>News analysis: The historic meeting between President Gorbachev and President Roh Tae Woo of South Korea has been interpreted very differently by the two leaders.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>China may sell chemicals to Libya that can be used to make poison gas, according to intelligence reports received by the U.S., Bush Administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>China releases 97 held in protests</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Justice agency warned on inquiry of loans to Iraq</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>A Gandhi crusades against a befouled India</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Leader of Liberia refusing to quit</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Guerrilla hideout is raided in Lima</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Medellin journal: Savagery is the habit in cocaine capital</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A16-21, B6-8, D22</p>
        <p>California's tax revolt has faded. A decade after they led a revolt against taxes and spending, voters approved higher gasoline taxes, a looser state spending limit and more than four billion dollars in bond issues.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The former Mayor of San Francisco, Dianne Feinstein, emerged from the primary not only as the Democratic nominee for governor of California but also as a charismatic centrist figure who may appeal to wayward Democrats and independents.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Each side says primaries prove strength on abortion</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Helms's opponent sets strategy</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Oakland mayor loses his job</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>A plan for reducing military spending may be offered by the Bush Administration. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said he would prepare a study showing the policy effects of a 25 percent cut in troops, ships and air wings over five years.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Lawmakers hear stealth praised</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The export of dangerous pesticides would be banned under legislation approved by the Senate Agriculture Committee. A similar proposal is pending in the House.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Jail Poindexter, prosecutors urge</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Kemp urges tightened F.H.A. insurance program</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Jackson urges Barry to seek plea agreement</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Washington Talk: Barney Frank isn't yet done for</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>The woman who committed suicide with a doctor's help after learning she had Alzheimer's disease had been at the center of a struggle by her family to keep her from killing herself.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Physician fulfills a goal: aiding a suicide</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>Diagnosis of Alzheimer's is no matter of certainty</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>A feud over the Missouri River has ended up in court. After nearly three years of drought in the upper basin states, only a season of plentiful rain across the river's western watershed can resolve interstate tensions.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Group says pollution fight won't hurt economy</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>Donations in U.S. climb, but worries linger</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Federal judge rules rap album is obscene</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>From Voyager 1, a space snapshot of six planets</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Shuttle must go to repair hangar</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>B1-4</p>
        <p>Donald J. Trump's three casinos in Atlantic City must supply the cash he needs to keep his sprawling empire going. But restoring the strength of his once-lucrative gaming houses will require management skills that Mr. Trump has yet to demonstrate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A church treasurer who disappeared from Suffern, N.Y., in 1982 with $267,000 in church funds may have been found in Taos, N.M. He was spotted by a parishioner from the church.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A mandatory drug-testing policy adopted by the New York City Transit Authority in the mid-1980's for all job applicants and employees was declared unconstitutional by a Federal judge in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>M.T.A. to run TV ads to gain subway riders</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Albany was dealt another setback. A major credit agency lowered New York State's long-term credit rating one notch. The move comes three weeks after the state adopted a budget that its political leaders insisted was sound.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The ruling on New Jersey school aid prompted the Florio administration and the State Legislature to tailor the Governor's proposals on how the state raises and spends money to conform to the court decision.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Soil contaminated with radium will be removed from around and under as many as 400 houses in the New Jersey communities of Glen Ridge, Montclair and West Orange. Federal officials said they would spend more than $250 million on the project.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Woman concedes lying after slaying</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Jack Henry Abbott, the ''lawyer,'' objects</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Brooklyn judge drops charge against grocer</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>New charge barred in Howard Beach retrial</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Murder suspect almost walks out of court in Queens</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>At the Bronx Zoo, a damsel in distress is rescued</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>The manager of the New York Yankees was dismissed. Bucky Dent was replaced by Carl (Stump) Merrill, a longtime Yankee employee and the manager this season at the baseball team's Columbus affiliate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Dream comes true for Merrill</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>News analysis: Change won't help</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Yankees lose to Red Sox</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Mets set back Expos</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>Column: Anderson on Yankees</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Soccer: U.S. braces for rough stuff</p>
        <p>B15</p>
        <p>Tennis: Muster gains semifinals</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>The Home Section</p>
        <p>The class of '90 looks ahead to family life</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Gardener's World</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Doghouses to bark about</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>When Karan handles it, fur can look like silk</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Health</p>
        <p>Pregnant women can gain more and skip vitamins</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>New findings tie cut in smoking to drop in heart disease</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Meeting skin problems head-on in the summertime</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>A search to bar retardation in a new generation</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>D23</p>
        <p>Vasily V. Kuznetsov, a Soviet Vice President and envoy</p>
        <p>Joseph C. Bevis, among first to monitor public opinion</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Legislators rebuff extension on arts panel</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>A Falstaff who transcends sex</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Theater: ''Prin'' by Andrew Davies</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>''Sisters''</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>Film: ''My Dinner With Abbie''</p>
        <p>C15</p>
        <p>Music: Troupe seeks rare operas</p>
        <p>C16</p>
        <p>Dance: Robbins festival opens</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Word and Image: ''First Hubby,'' comic novel</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>Jerry Seinfeld in a comedy</p>
        <p>C22</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Spend fairly for schools</p>
        <p>Canada's latest identity crisis</p>
        <p>Dying, Dr. Kevorkian's way</p>
        <p>Topics: Ethical update</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: Warmth and ice</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Tom Wicker: The public voice - amplified</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Michael Aronson, Christopher J. Georges: Dukakis triumphs</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Leonard S. Spector: India-Pakistan war could be nuclear</p>
        <p>A23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
