<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Few Fine Trips for the Two-Wheel Set</title>
    <meta content="28BIKE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="960893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard Jay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motorcycles, Motor Bikes and Motorscooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2D7103BF93BA1575AC0A961958260" item-length="2246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Few Fine Trips for the Two-Wheel Set</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM AND JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne; Scholem, Richard Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article offers several routes for motorcycle trips through parts of Long Island, NY; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR bikers the lure of Long Island is unsurpassed. Nowhere are the rewards greater and more varied than in Nassau and Suffolk Counties. The land mass between Montauk Point and New York City offers diverse views of seascapes and cityscapes, country lanes, boardwalks, vast beaches, rolling hills, flatlands and historic reminders of days gone by. For novices who ride 5 or 10 miles with plenty of stops to serious bikers who grind out 100 or more miles a day, the possibilities are exhilarating: the Montauk Lighthouse, the Jones Beach boardwalk, the spectacular beaches of the Hamptons and Montauk, a ferry ride to Shelter Island and the wineries of the North Fork and.</p>
        <p>The five best Long Island rides offered here have some similarities. They all are on flat to gently rolling terrain. Whenever possible, they use little-traveled roads in rural, pastoral and waterfront areas. Each offers a longer route or shorter ones. Picturesque sites are designated for lunch. All afford easy access to beaches, so in warm weather, be sure to pack a bathing suit.</p>
        <p>Ride 1 -- A Spring Tonic: Bethpage to the Jones Beach Boardwalk</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR bikers the lure of Long Island is unsurpassed. Nowhere are the rewards greater and more varied than in Nassau and Suffolk Counties. The land mass between Montauk Point and New York City offers diverse views of seascapes and cityscapes, country lanes, boardwalks, vast beaches, rolling hills, flatlands and historic reminders of days gone by. For novices who ride 5 or 10 miles with plenty of stops to serious bikers who grind out 100 or more miles a day, the possibilities are exhilarating: the Montauk Lighthouse, the Jones Beach boardwalk, the spectacular beaches of the Hamptons and Montauk, a ferry ride to Shelter Island and the wineries of the North Fork and.</p>
        <p>The five best Long Island rides offered here have some similarities. They all are on flat to gently rolling terrain. Whenever possible, they use little-traveled roads in rural, pastoral and waterfront areas. Each offers a longer route or shorter ones. Picturesque sites are designated for lunch. All afford easy access to beaches, so in warm weather, be sure to pack a bathing suit.</p>
        <p>Ride 1 -- A Spring Tonic: Bethpage to the Jones Beach Boardwalk</p>
        <p>This 30-mile ride is a perfect season opener. All but four miles is on traffic-free bike paths and the terrain is mostly flat (a few hills at the beginning and end). Those who make the ride before April 1 will have an added bonus: miles of boardwalk riding at Jones Beach (not permitted during the season).</p>
        <p>Begin the ride in Bethpage State Park, from Exit 8 (Powell Avenue) on Route 135. Enter the park, go beyond the Polo Grounds and park in the lot adjacent to the picnic area. The trail begins there and heads south for seven miles. After six miles at Sunrise Highway, jog left to cross with the light and turn right to get back on the path.</p>
        <p>At Merrick Road, tired bikers can turn back for a total ride of 14 miles. Those proceeding to Jones Beach must travel west (right) two miles to link up with the bike trail, to the beach. To avoid busy Merrick Road as much as possible, follow this route: right on Merrick, take the first right onto Massapequa Avenue, go one block then left on School Street (becomes Elm Street). At end, go left on Seaford Avenue to Merrick Road, right on Merrick and then right at the first turn (Washington Avenue). In about one and a half blocks, turn left on Waverly Avenue, take it to the end, then turn left on Willoughby Avenue. Take a right on Merrick. Go three blocks to Cedar Creek Park (on the south side of Merrick Road). Enter the park on the bike trail. With the restrooms in front of you, turn right to link up with the trail to Jones Beach (about five miles). When the trail ends, cross the large parking lot diagonally to the right toward the ocean. Go through the tunnel to the boardwalk where there are concessions, picnic tables and restrooms. Reverse directions for the return trip.</p>
        <p>Ride 2 -- A Shelter Island Circle</p>
        <p>This 31-miler -- which begins and ends in Sag Harbor and includes a round-trip ride on the Shelter Island Ferry, shaded trees aplenty, lunch at Crescent Beach and proximity to water and beaches throughout -- is especially ideal for summer. The terrain is flat to gently rolling and a swim can accompany lunch.</p>
        <p>Park near the waterfront marina at the foot of Main Street in Sag Harbor (public restrooms). Head west over the bridge following Route 114 three miles to the ferry. Upon arriving on Shelter Island, go straight on Route 114 (also called South Ferry Road). In a mile and a half, where Route 114 veers left, go straight on Cartwright Road. A mile and a half later, turn right on Ram Island Road. A mile on, there is an option. Riders who want to do the entire 31 miles should turn right on Ram Island Drive. Those who wish to eliminate 5 1/2 relatively hilly miles can continue straight ahead on Gardiner's Bay Drive. The long ride continues on Ram Island Drive to the end, where a right turn puts you on South Ram Island Drive. Return on it. Upon departing Ram Island, turn right on Gardiner's Bay Drive.</p>
        <p>A mile and a half later go right on Point Lane, which becomes Rock Road, which a half mile later turns into Dinah. Three-tenths of a mile ahead go right on Manhasset then take a fast right on Haven's Road, a quick left on Nichol Road and an equally quick left on Sylvester Road, which becomes Shore Road. In about a mile Shore becomes Winthrop and in another mile it runs into Route 114 (North Ferry Road). Go left, then a half mile later go right on West Neck Road, which becomes Shore Road. Seven-tenths of a mile after that, at the bottom of a steep hill take a sharp left on Shore to Crescent Beach and lunch (18 miles into the ride).</p>
        <p>After lunch, proceed straight ahead on Shore, up a hill at the end. At the top of the hill turn left on Nostrand Parkway, which becomes Brander Parkway. Take it to the end. The road will turn right and become Peconic Avenue. A mile later, turn right at Crab Creek and a fast left back onto Brander, then a quick right onto tiny Sudee Glen (or Bootleggers Alley). Then a fast left on Worthy Way, which becomes West Neck Road. About a mile and a half later, turn right with West Neck Road, a half-mile after that, go right onto North Midway Road, which becomes Midway, then South Midway. Two and a half miles later, you will hit Route 114, turn right, go to the ferry and return to Sag Harbor.</p>
        <p>Ride Three -- East to Orient</p>
        <p>This is a 37 1/2-mile ride of mostly flat terrain with a few rolling hills. The rewards include a lovely four-mile ride on a bike path in Orient Beach State Park, lunch and a swim at the beach, a ramble through the quaint village of Orient and a visit to the Horton Lighthouse. Although the ride encompasses a long stretch on Route 25, from Greenport to Orient, there is a wide shoulder that has recently been resurfaced.</p>
        <p>Begin at the small shopping center (northside) in the heart of Southold (Route 25-Main Road). Head east (left) on Route 25 to Greenport. Five and a half miles into the ride, in Greenport, turn left on Third Street. Take it to the end (one mile) and go right on Webb, then left on East Main. In a half mile, when the road ends, turn right (Route 25) and go all the way to Orient Beach State Park. Get on the bike trail (to the right) and go to the beach and lunch (concessions, restrooms). Return on the bike trail to Route 25 and head west (left). In about two miles turn left onto Narrow River Road, which becomes King Street in about a mile or so, later it becomes Village Lane. After enjoying Orient, continue ahead, then left back onto Route 25. When Route 25 turns left into Greenport do not follow it, go straight ahead on Route 48. About three miles later, after Hashamomuck Beach, turn right onto Soundview Avenue, a beautiful run of rolling, three-shaded hills. Two miles later, turn left on Lighthouse Road (those who want to visit the lighthouse should turn right before returning to the ride). In a half-mile jog right onto North Road and then a quick left onto Youngs  Avenue. Stay on Youngs for one and a half miles until it ends at Route 25. Turn right and return to the cars.</p>
        <p>Ride Four -- From County Seat to Quietude</p>
        <p>This 36-mile, flat-to-rolling ride features wonderful country lanes, lunch on an appealing beach in New Suffolk and a return through wine country and farms.</p>
        <p>From the Long Island Expressway, take Route 25 to the center of Riverhead. Park in the municipal parking lot behind the stores at East Main Street and Peconic Avenue. Ride as far east or right as you can,  go in the parking lot and then turn right onto East Main Street. In one mile turn right onto Hubbard Avenue. At the end in about two miles turn right, cross the railroad tracks and pick up unmarked Meeting House Creek Road. In a half-mile turn left onto Peconic Bay Boulevard.</p>
        <p>In six miles, when this lovely road ends, go left onto Bay Avenue. In less than a mile turn right onto Main Road (Route 25). In three-tenths of a mile turn right onto beautiful New Suffolk Avenue. Ride the four miles to the end and have lunch at the beach in New Suffolk (14 miles into the ride).</p>
        <p>Riders who want to cut out about eight miles can return to the cars by reversing these directions. Those who go on the long ride should head east parallel to the water to the end of the road. Turn left onto Orchard and in a few blocks right onto New Suffolk Road (not Avenue). In one and a half miles turn right onto Route 25, then left one-tenth of a mile onto Depot Lane. Go two miles and left onto Oregon. In two miles left onto possibly unmarked Mill Lane.</p>
        <p>In about a half-mile right onto Tuthill Road, which becomes Wickham. In less than a mile turn right on Route 27 called North or New Middle Road. In three-tenths of a mile, turn right on Westphalia. Westphalia curves left in about a mile, a half-mile later turn right onto Cox Neck Road. In about a half-mile turn left onto Bergen Avenue (be on the lookout, the sign may be hidden by trees). At the end, turn left onto unmarked road. In a half-mile turn right onto Sound Avenue.</p>
        <p>Ride for five and a half miles on Sound Avenue past farmstands and vineyards. Palmer Vineyards often has live music on its deck on weekends (and restrooms). Turn left onto Doctors Path. In three miles go straight ahead onto Route 25, then two more miles back to the cars.</p>
        <p>Ride Five -- Montauk -- The Biking End</p>
        <p>This 30-mile ride is more hilly than many on the East End but skipping the six-and-a-half-mile climb to the lighthouse and back eliminates most hills. The rest of the ride is rolling to flat. Park in the big parking lot across the street from Gosman's at Montauk Harbor (public restrooms). Go left out of the parking lot. In one-tenth of a mile go right onto Soundview. In about a mile turn left onto Pine Tree. In a half-mile go left onto Blackberry then a fast right, straight across Flamingo onto East Flamingo. When the road ends in a half-mile go right onto West Lake.</p>
        <p>In a quarter-mile take the first right, which dead-ends into Greenwich. Go left onto Greenwich. Go a half-mile and turn right onto Glouster. In a half-mile, at the yield sign, left onto Fairview. In two-tenths of a mile, at the stop sign, turn right with Fairview. In about a mile go right on Essex, which becomes Fairview (half right). Go completely around the state park, staying on Fairview, repeating part of the ride until you are back at Essex (a three-mile circle). Right on Essex, then an immediate left onto Elwell. At bottom, turn right onto Edgemere. In a quarter of a mile left on Industrial Road. In three-quarters of a mile turn left on Second House Road.</p>
        <p>In one mile take a left on Montauk, then immediately turn right onto South Eton, then go left on Edgewater to the end. Left on Essex to Montauk Highway. Right on Montauk. In one mile go right on Ditch Plains Road. Go to the end and have lunch at Ditch Plains Beach (restrooms and hot dog truck in season). This is about 12 1/2 miles into the ride. After lunch, go right on Deforest, which runs parallel to the water. In about a quarter of a mile turn left onto Prentice, then take the first right onto Agnew, which becomes Caswell. Then go right onto Montauk Highway. In three-tenths of a mile turn left onto East Lake Drive. Go the three beautiful miles to the beach at the end (restaurants and hot dog truck in season). Sit and watch the boats enter Lake Montauk, spot Gosman's and your car across the lake.</p>
        <p>Turn around and go back to Montauk Highway. This is 19 1/2 miles into the ride. Turn left for the six-and-a-half-mile round trip to the lighthouse (concessions and restrooms) and return to this point (East Lake Drive). Turn right on Montauk Highway (or straight ahead, if you have gone to the lighthouse). In a half-mile turn right onto Old West Lake Road. In a mile turn right onto West Lake Road. Ride two and a half miles back to the cars.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Here are come-as-you-are dining suggestions:</p>
        <p>Ride 1: Eddie's at 333 Jericho Turnpike, Syosset (496-3253).</p>
        <p>Ride 2: The Paradise on Main Street (725-6080) in Sag Harbor. .</p>
        <p>Ride 3, The Hellenic Snack Bar, at 5145 Main Street in East Marion (477-0138).</p>
        <p>Ride 4, The Polonez Polish-Russian Restaurant, 123 West Main Street (369-8878), Riverhead.</p>
        <p>Ride 5: Turtle Crossing, 221 Pantigo Road, East Hampton (324-7166).</p>
        <p>Maps of Long Island detailing biking routes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
