<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIARY: August 26-31</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D91738F931A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIARY: August 26-31</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>OPEC Decides to Give the Desired Response</p>
        <p>One doesn't just order a cab driver in the Arab world to head across town. One respectfully inquires if he is going in that direction. On Wednesday, the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries announced that it is, indeed, going where the United States would like.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>OPEC Decides to Give the Desired Response</p>
        <p>One doesn't just order a cab driver in the Arab world to head across town. One respectfully inquires if he is going in that direction. On Wednesday, the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries announced that it is, indeed, going where the United States would like.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>OPEC Decides to Give the Desired Response</p>
        <p>One doesn't just order a cab driver in the Arab world to head across town. One respectfully inquires if he is going in that direction. On Wednesday, the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries announced that it is, indeed, going where the United States would like. OPEC members are now free to pump all the oil they can. For weeks, the United States and its allies have requested that OPEC compensate for the boycott of Iraqi and Kuwaiti supplies. But Iraq has threatened neighbors who comply with United States requests. Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates, backed by an OPEC accord, appear ready to produce even more than experts thought they could. An agency representing major oil consumers decided against drawing down emergency oil reserves, but doubted that OPEC could pump enough to avoid serious shortages come winter. For now, OPEC unity has brought lower oil prices - from $30.91 to $27.32 a barrel last week.</p>
        <p>Satellites for Tonga?</p>
        <p>The tiny, South Pacific island kingdom of Tonga has volcanoes, coral reefs, coconuts and bananas. Its 100,000 residents have 5,000 radios and 4,000 telephones. Now King Taufa'ahau Tupou 4th wants to add at least 13 communications satellites. Tonga has found a loophole in international law allowing it to claim the last orbital slots for satellites than can link Asia and the United States. Not that Tongans are clamoring for more ''I Love Lucy'' reruns or the ability to check coconut futures on the commodity exchanges. Tongasat, a Government-sponsored company with no money of its own, instead aims to raise perhaps $500 million from investors, then charge users millions of dollars a year for each satellite slot. Officials of Intelsat, the consortium of 199 nations that supplies most international satellite service, are fuming over the potential loss of the slots. They say that Tongasat is a front for a savvy American telecommunications specialist, Matt C. Nilson, who thought up the venture and convinced the Tongans to adopt it.</p>
        <p>Japan's Rate Rise</p>
        <p>The Japanese tightened last week, and the United States is likely to feel the squeeze. Japan raised its discount rate to 6 percent from 5.25 percent last Thursday, the fifth increase in just over a year. Japanese interest rates are approaching the levels of United States rates - even though economists expect Japanese consumer prices to rise less than 3 percent this year, not half as much as in the United States. Economists say that higher Japanese interest rates could hurt the value of the dollar and repatriate Japanese money that has been flowing into American bonds. The likely result is higher interest rates in the United States on the eve of a recession.</p>
        <p>Soviet-Saudi Raprochement</p>
        <p>The Russian Republic in OPEC? Just a recent suggestion from Boris N. Yeltsin, the republic's president, who claims control of the region's oil. The Soviet Union was drawing closer to Saudi Arabia even before the Middle East crisis, allowing Moslem pilgrims to visit Mecca for the first time. No formal diplomatic relations yet, but the Soviets hosted Saudi Arabia's Ambassador to the United States last month.</p>
        <p>Bush Passes the Hat</p>
        <p>President Bush sounded like the chairman of a global United Way last week as he urged other nations ''to bear their fair share'' of Middle East costs. The United States is spending billions on military forces and economic sanctions there. The President intends to dispatch Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady and Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d to West Germany, Japan and the Middle East, seeking contributions of as much as $25 billion.</p>
        <p>In Brief</p>
        <p>Toys 'R' Not Us: The Japanese relaxed their laws to allow some large American stores to open shop. But now come the Japanese retailers with plans to gang up against newcomers. Toys 'R' Us, which plans 100 Japanese stores in the next 10 years, faces organized opposition from domestic toy retailers who promise to aid competing shops.</p>
        <p>Ernest W. Saunders, the former chief of Guinness P.L.C., was sentenced to five years in prison. He was convicted of conspiracy, fraud and theft in his successful 1986 battle to take over the Distillers Company.</p>
        <p>Japan's Ministry of Finance gave one- and two-day suspensions to four investment houses, including Daiwa Securities and a Citicorp susidiary, for aiding in stock manipulation.</p>
        <p>COMPANIES</p>
        <p>A Boost for the Air Bag</p>
        <p>At first, auto companies offered air bags as options costing as much as $800. Then they cited the weak response from customers as proof there was little demand. Last week, the General Motors Corporation said that by 1995, a driver's-side air bag would be in every car it builds in the United States. Some safety experts say the air bags might save thousands of lives, especially since the company's passive seat belts are said to be flawed. A G.M. spokesman explained the move with marketing language instead, saying, ''There's little doubt the American car-buying public is moving into a more safety-conscious mode.''Chrysler already equips almost all its cars with air bags, and Ford plans to in the mid-1990's. Toyota and Honda appear to be lagging behind - giving American companies a rare design advantage over their major Japanese rivals.</p>
        <p>The United Automobile Workers named G.M. as its ''strike target'' last Tuesday. Contracts with the auto makers expire Sept. 14.</p>
        <p>IN BRIEF</p>
        <p>When two of the South's largest banks agreed last year to merge, they at first decided to call themselves the Avantar Financial Corporation, a name that reeked of adventure, perhaps in outer space. Well, the Citizens and Southern Corporation and the Sovran Financial Corporation were officially united yesterday - as the C&amp;S Sovran Corporation. A mouthful, perhaps, but at least familiar food.</p>
        <p>The Tisch family, betting on weak banking stocks to revive, has bought major stakes in Continental Bank, Baybanks and Equimark.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Arguing With the Census</p>
        <p>They will fight in the fields and in the streets. They will fight block-to-block and then house-to-house. Local and state politicians will not flag or fail until the Government admits there are heaps more Philadelphians, Atlantans, Houstonians and New Yorkers than the Census Bureau estimated last week. Never mind that satisfying all these complaints might leave the nation with a population larger than India's. This is what the agency gets for letting local authorities review preliminary figures. The final numbers will determine not only Congressional representation and Federal benefits, but also where many businesses and investors direct their money and jobs. For many local officials, the census has become nothing more than the continuation of politics by other means.</p>
        <p>The Countryside Shrinks</p>
        <p>Don't look for rural areas to rebound during the 1990's. The countryside suffered greater population losses than expected during the last decade - as many as 1.4 million people, according to preliminary census figures - after gaining during the 1970's. Doug Bachtel, a sociologist at the University of Georgia, says that the exodus is likely to continue. Even if farming becomes more profitable, it will continue to become more mechanized, he said. And factories that moved into small towns searching for cheap labor are now looking overseas. So the young and the educated move to the cities, leaving the poor and elderly back home. In Taliaferro County, Ga., where the population fell from 2,032 to 1,761 during the decade, more than one in five residents are older than 65, compared with less than one in eight nationally. ''People in Florida are getting their retirement benefits from Merrill Lynch,'' Mr. Bachtel said, referring to their investments. ''People in rural America are getting their benefits from Uncle Sam.''</p>
        <p>Consumer Confidence Drops</p>
        <p>Consumers swore they felt an earthquake in August, rattling them so badly that they might be afraid to go out to shop. Two indexes showed last week that, as the Middle East crisis intensified, consumer confidence took the sharpest plunge since the October 1987 stock market crash. The University of Michigan reported that consumers were less confident than at any time since the 1982 recession. And the Conference Board, a business group, confirmed Michigan's finding that consumers are especially pessimistic about the next six months - which often foreshadows a recession. Lacy H. Hunt, the chief economist at Carroll McEntee &amp; McGinley, said that with unemployment claims also rising in the last two weeks, ''The best that we can expect is very sluggish growth.'' Economists are waiting for September figures to see whether consumers really felt an earthquake, or just the neighbors moving their furniture around upstairs.</p>
        <p>More Bad S.&amp;L. News</p>
        <p>A healthy savings and loan these days seems to be one whose cancer is not terminal. The Office of Thrift Supervision reported last week that losses and loan problems are growing at many of the nation's strongest institutions. The figures raise questions about whether the savings and loan industry can survive without being taken over by commercial banks.</p>
        <p>Energy: Lack of Policy</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary James D. Watkins responded to the prospect of oil shortages by suggesting a rough sail and a bumpy ride. He wants to sail into the waters off Santa Barbara, Calif., to pump oil near a coastline cherished by environmentalists and tourists. And he wants all Americans to inflate their tires to the maximum pressure for more energy-efficient, but more jarring, rides. No sense in speeding the development of a comprehensive energy policy due for delivery to the Capitol next spring, Mr. Watkins added. Better to do the easy things now, make the tougher changes later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
