<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First It Was Drugs, And Now It's Mother</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="381213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LINFIELD, SUSAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, CARRIE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">POSTCARDS FROM THE EDGE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA133AF931A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First It Was Drugs, And Now It's Mother</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN LINFIELD; Susan Linfield, the executive editor of Savvy Woman magazine, writes frequently about the arts.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LINFIELD, SUSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Like countless other Americans, Carrie Fisher comes from a broken home, is divorced and has had problems with drug abuse. Nothing unusual.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Like countless other Americans, Carrie Fisher comes from a broken home, is divorced and has had problems with drug abuse. Nothing unusual.</p>
        <p>Like countless other Americans, Carrie Fisher comes from a broken home, is divorced and has had problems with drug abuse. Nothing unusual.</p>
        <p>In Ms. Fisher's case, though, her parents were Debbie Reynolds and Eddie Fisher, and their breakup - Eddie left Debbie for Elizabeth Taylor in 1958 - became the Divorce Heard Round the World. Her former husband is the pop star Paul Simon. Most important, perhaps, Ms. Fisher's drug abuse and rehabilitation - rather than simply languishing as a bad memory - became the basis of her widely praised 1987 best-seller, ''Postcards From the Edge,'' a kind of literate trash novel. The at-least-semi-autobiographical book charted the chemical, sexual and emotional obsessions of a frantic, wisecracking 30-year-old Hollywood actress named Suzanne Vale, who sums herself up thus: ''Sometimes I feel like I've got my nose pressed up against the window of a bakery, only I'm the bread.''</p>
        <p>On Sept. 14, the screen version of ''Postcards'' opens - with a screenplay by Ms. Fisher, directed by Mike Nichols and starring Meryl Streep as Suzanne and Shirley MacLaine as her mother, a boozy, bossy old-time star named Doris Mann. The Hollywood all-star cast includes Gene Hackman, Dennis Quaid, Rob Reiner and Richard Dreyfuss.</p>
        <p>Like the book, the film relates Suzanne's misadventures with drugs, directors and would-be lovers. In moving to the screen, however, ''Postcards'' has become a sort of '' 'Terms of Endearment' Goes Hollywood,'' concentrating on the conflicted relationship between Suzanne and Doris - a theme that was virtually nonexistent in the novel.</p>
        <p>''Mothers are something I've always been interested in,'' Mr. Nichols says. ''Elaine May and I did a sketch - and God knows Elaine had a mother - where she, the mother, complains that I don't call her enough. And I say, 'Mother, you've made me feel awful,' and she says, 'If that's true, you've made me the happiest woman in the world.' So the mother character is not only a Hollywood type.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fisher admits, however, that she was ''always uncomfortable'' with the film's focus on Doris ''because I knew people would think it was my mother - and I don't want to humiliate my family. My mother is this fantastic character. Eccentric wouldn't even quite cover it. But I couldn't write my mother - it's like the Zen saying, 'To describe is to distort.' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. MacLaine recalls, ''Debbie and I go back a very long time. Carrie was a little girl. I was all ready to do 'The Unsinkable Molly Brown,' when Debbie called and said, 'You'll get other parts. I need this. Can I have it?' I said yes. So I consider this a swing of the karmic pendulum, 25 years later.''</p>
        <p>Ms. MacLaine first heard about the film almost two years ago at a New Year's Eve party. ''Carrie Fisher walked up to me and said, 'You would be great playing my mother. You'll probably get a call.' So I immediately called Debbie: 'Is this all right with you?' And she said, 'Of course, dear. The main thing about playing me is just to be funny.' ''</p>
        <p>The surprise casting is that of Ms. Streep, who is known, at least on screen, for her serious, slightly cool demeanor - a far cry from the frazzled Suzanne.</p>
        <p>''I mostly did this kind of thing in drama school,'' Ms. Streep says. ''I never played any real, serious people till I got into the movies.'' And, she adds, ''I don't feel cool - in fact, I'm always overheated. Maybe my image comes from being blond with a brain - that means aloof.''</p>
        <p>Although ''Postcards From the Edge'' contains several scenes set in a drug rehabilitation clinic and depicts Suzanne's subsequent struggle to stay sober, it is not intended as a film about drugs - nor is it meant as an antidrug film. (One scene mocks Nancy Reagan's ''just say no'' campaign.) ''There are very few gifted people who haven't had a brush with alcohol or drugs or depression,'' says Mr. Nichols. ''It's very hard to get through the whole thing without stepping on one of those mines. But to survive and reject all those snares is to start your real life.''</p>
        <p>If it is not about drugs, ''Postcards'' is about Hollywood. In fact, much of its casting is a bit of a sly Hollywood in-joke: Richard Dreyfuss, who has had his own problems with drug abuse and is a friend of Ms. Fisher's, plays the doctor who pumps out Suzanne's stomach after an overdose and subsequently tries to court her; Dennis Quaid seems to spoof all the sexy bad boys he has ever played; the director Rob Reiner is the unctuous producer who demands a drug test from Suzanne, and the noted British actor and biographer Simon Callow portrays Simon Asquith, a pretentious and decidedly second-rate director.</p>
        <p>Beyond its characters, though, the film is about the generational struggle between the old, image-conscious Hollywood, represented by Doris, and the more anarchic Hollywood that developed in the wake of the studios' demise, represented by Suzanne.</p>
        <p>''Actors have to be much more inner-directed now,'' Mr. Nichols says. ''Nobody's looking to shape anybody's career any more. Hollywood used to be more about seeing than being. Part of the job, and part of the kick for both the movie people and the audience, was that the stars were royalty - but much more fun, because they could do anything, and they never got old. Hollywood - and the concerns of the movies - are now more about either people's actual lives, or fantasies of the future. But they are not about the life of an elite, like the old Hollywood.''</p>
        <p>Another difference between the old and new Hollywoods - at least in the eyes of those who made ''Postcards From the Edge'' - is the industry's current hostility, or at best indifference, to women. ''Postcards'' may, in fact, be an example of an increasingly rare breed: the woman-friendly film. Says Ms. Streep, ''I just love all that stuff in the film about what it's like for girls - and older women - in Hollywood. And it's all true.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nichols observes: ''When you look at the movies of the 40's and 50's - with Stanwyck and Davis, Garbo and Dietrich - these women were so powerful, and they insisted on playing women of drive and vitality, women who controlled their lives. They were adjuncts to no one. That's slipped away.'' Ms. MacLaine cites Hollywood's current concentration on action-adventure films for the (male) youth market. ''It isn't so much sexist as it is materialistic; it's the greed to make hits instead of movies.''</p>
        <p>If ''Postcards'' is, ultimately, a film about Hollywood and the people who inhabit it, will it play in the heartland, where people might not be interested in a leading character who is described in the movie as ''a selfish, spoiled, coked-up little actress?'' Ms. MacLaine observes, ''I don't know whether people in Peoria will relate to Suzanne - but I'm sure everybody out there feels their mother is too overbearing, too.''  FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
