<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Niches and Other Places to Stow Odds and Ends</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D91531F935A15751C1A965958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Niches and Other Places to Stow Odds and Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLUTTER is an inevitable byproduct of home repair, as anyone who has hung a picture or oiled a hinge can attest. Where to keep the extra picture wire? The can of oil?</p>
        <p>Manufacturers of storage products seem to know that, and abound with gadgets like boxes, bins, hooks, trays, magnetic strips and jars on revolving racks that are a kind of clutter by themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLUTTER is an inevitable byproduct of home repair, as anyone who has hung a picture or oiled a hinge can attest. Where to keep the extra picture wire? The can of oil?</p>
        <p>Manufacturers of storage products seem to know that, and abound with gadgets like boxes, bins, hooks, trays, magnetic strips and jars on revolving racks that are a kind of clutter by themselves.</p>
        <p>Common sense and a bit of experience often are more effective than ingenuity when it comes to keeping home-repair supplies and tools handy and safe. Over all, try to find a way to keep things like tools and fasteners compartmentalized for easy selection and in plain sight for accessibility. If possible, store all repair paraphernalia in one place or maintain a separate kit of the most-used items in a convenient spot.</p>
        <p>For bulky items like supplies and power tools, make or invest in sturdy utility shelves. Place large heavy items near the bottom and any hazardous substances, or items to be kept from children, near the top. Store frequently used items in the middle so they can be spotted easily.</p>
        <p>Where there is wall space for storing tools, build one or more racks from perforated hardboard paneling. Pegboard is one brand. Such paneling accepts a variety of inexpensive hooks, clips, shelves, bins and small cabinets. Perforated hardboard is sold in 4 x 8 sheets, and many lumberyards cut it to size. Home centers often sell half-sheets measuring four feet on each side.</p>
        <p>To fasten hardboard to wallboard, plaster or wood paneling, use ordinary roundhead wood screws if the fasteners will penetrate studs in the wall. If the fasteners have to enter the wall between studs, use sturdy hollow-wall fasteners like molly bolts. A rack should be attached to at least one wall stud to support the weight of the tools. Studs are usually at 16-inch intervals.</p>
        <p>With all fasteners, place a flat metal washer beneath the head to distribute pressure against the hardboard. It is also important to thread one or two thick rubber or plastic spacing washers onto the fasteners after inserting them. Such washers are usually in kits of hooks and hangers for perforated hardboard. The washers hold the panel off the wall, providing clearance for the backs of fittings.</p>
        <p>To fasten hardboard to masonry, mount strips of 1 x 3 lumber horizontally across the wall at intervals of 16 to 24 inches. Do that with concrete screws or, for extra sturdiness, wedge- or sleeve-type concrete anchors. Attach the hardboard to the strips with roundhead wood screws and washers.</p>
        <p>Another way to mount a panel is to fasten to the top, bottom and sides strips of solid lumber at least three-quarters of an inch thick. Use spacing washers to avoid losing the use of rows of holes on the rack. Attach the assembly to the wall so that the strips are at the rear. The frame surrounding the panel allows building a cabinet to enclose it. Use 1 x 6 or 1 x 8-inch solid lumber or plywood to make the cabinet sides, top and bottom.  Fasten those to the strips with screws. Add hinged doors, which are made by framing plywood panels three-eighths of an inch or a half-inch thick with lumber strips having the same thickness as the cabinet parts. Install magnetic catches to close the doors.</p>
        <p>For storing fasteners, few products sold for that outdo ordinary coffee cans or small plastic food containers. Leave the lids off, except to prevent spilling. If you often carry quantities of fasteners from place to place, consider a five-gallon bucket with compartmented trays. Two manufacturers from which they can be ordered are the Duluth Trading Company of Duluth, Minn. (800-505-8888) and Journeyman Products Ltd. of Millersville, Md. (800-248-8707). Prices start around $20.</p>
        <p>An exception is for unsorted fasteners. All households accumulate odd fasteners and bits of hardware that cannot be sorted. Keep those in large shallow trays.</p>
        <p>For portability or if wall space is unavailable, store tools in a compartmentalized tool chest, tool tray or other carrier. Some tool carriers are designed around footstools that can double as small work surfaces. Cloth tool bags with compartments also are available, including those that fit around the outside of a bucket. The inside can then hold power tools, extension cords, tubes of caulking compound and other bulky items.</p>
        <p>A tool apron is convenient for holding tools and supplies when you are working. An inexpensive model with its own belt, two or three pouches for fasteners or small tools and a few loops or pockets for larger tools is usually adequate. Larger sizes when laden will make you feel like a pack horse.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
