<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sasser Still Won't Let Go, A Habit Perplexing to Mets</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="445483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SASSER, MACKEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDF1439F936A25756C0A967958260" item-length="348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sasser Still Won't Let Go, A Habit Perplexing to Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, May 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the first pitch Monday night, the problem was obvious and there was every indication it would be unconquerable. Soon, Mackey Sasser's difficulty returning the baseball to the pitcher was out of control, and the crowd's taunting was constant and fierce.</p>
        <p>It all amounted to a sad and humiliating relapse for the catcher for the Mets, and posed once again a dilemma for the team: Can it endure the distractions and risk the potential liability caused by Sasser's mental block about firing the baseball back to the mound?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the first pitch Monday night, the problem was obvious and there was every indication it would be unconquerable. Soon, Mackey Sasser's difficulty returning the baseball to the pitcher was out of control, and the crowd's taunting was constant and fierce.</p>
        <p>It all amounted to a sad and humiliating relapse for the catcher for the Mets, and posed once again a dilemma for the team: Can it endure the distractions and risk the potential liability caused by Sasser's mental block about firing the baseball back to the mound?</p>
        <p>If not, can it afford not to have Sasser's potentially explosive bat in the lineup when its inconsistent offense has begun to look more like a trait than a trend?</p>
        <p>"The problem is unsolvable by us and impossible for us to understand," Manager Bud Harrelson said of Sasser's affliction. "A habit is a habit. It comes back."</p>
        <p>At the outset of the 5-2 loss to the Padres on Monday night, the habit surfaced with a vengeance. Sasser, who in Saturday's start against the Giants had at least managed a modicum of control over his mysterious malady, double-clutched in delivering the baseball to David Cone. The throws that resulted were more like popups, and Cone was forced to perform like an infielder, repeatedly driven off the mound to track down the tosses.</p>
        <p>Further complicating the scene was Sasser's inability to maintain his balance as he struggled from his squat to fight through the hitches and get the baseball to the mound.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Umpire Doug Harvey was constantly dodging from behind Sasser as the catcher repeatedly stumbled backward, often almost landing on the ground.</p>
        <p>The fans noticed immediately and savaged Sasser with catcalls throughout.</p>
        <p>"I was definitely uncomfortable, you could tell that," said Sasser, who did not want to talk at length about the problem after the game. "I'll keep working at it. It was a rough night, and that's it."</p>
        <p>Harrelson also said he thought Sasser was trying to make up for his embarrassing ailment by producing wildly with the bat. Sasser was 0 for 3 at bat on Monday, dropping his season average to .250.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
