<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commencements; Power Failure Doesn't Disrupt Ceremonies at Rutgers</title>
    <meta content="22COMM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jewish Theological Seminary</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ben-Porat, Miriam (Comptroller)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EEDF1139F931A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commencements; Power Failure Doesn't Disrupt Ceremonies at Rutgers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PISCATAWAY, N.J., May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rutgers University and Jewish Theological Seminary hold commencements; brief power failure at Rutgers' Livingston Campus fails to disrupt commencement; Israel's State Comptroller Miriam Ben-Porat gives commencement address at Jewish Theological Seminary (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Louis Broom Athletic Center at the Livingston Campus of Rutgers University went dark for several moments today, right in the middle of the national anthem. A power surge had knocked out the lights at the gym, where faculty members, honorees and many of the 2,971 master's and doctoral degree recipients and 6,852 baccalaureates were gathered for the 232d commencement.</p>
        <p>But the crowd remained calm and the Rutgers Glee Club, which sang the anthem, did not miss a beat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Louis Broom Athletic Center at the Livingston Campus of Rutgers University went dark for several moments today, right in the middle of the national anthem. A power surge had knocked out the lights at the gym, where faculty members, honorees and many of the 2,971 master's and doctoral degree recipients and 6,852 baccalaureates were gathered for the 232d commencement.</p>
        <p>But the crowd remained calm and the Rutgers Glee Club, which sang the anthem, did not miss a beat.</p>
        <p>Francis L. Lawrence, the university president, focused his commencement address on the need to learn new skills to stay competitive in the information age. He cited a scene in the movie ''Primary Colors'' in which the fictional President addresses a room full of laid-off factory workers. '' 'Muscle jobs are going to go where muscle labor is cheap -- and that's not here,' '' he said, quoting the Clintonesque protagonist of the film. '' 'This whole country's going to have to go back to school.' ''</p>
        <p>In one of the more solemn moments of the three-hour ceremony,  Brandon Michael Poli, who had muscular dystrophy and died two weeks ago, was awarded a master's degree in city and regional planning. His father, Michael Poli, who accepted the degree with Brandon's mother, Helen, said later that he hoped some of the day's graduates would take up public service. ''It's important that they do the work a lot of handicapped people can't do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Liza Farina, 23, a graduate of Rutgers' College of Nursing who was posing for pictures with her family outside the athletic center, said she intended to work in public health policy after a hands-on job at a hospital. ''I think you need to start at the bedside,'' said Ms. Farina, who went on to describe how she felt about entering the work world. ''Ready and excited,'' she said. ''Those are two good words.''</p>
        <p>Jewish Theological Seminary</p>
        <p>A better understanding of religious books would ''help ease the tension existing nowadays in Israel,'' Miriam Ben-Porat, Israel's State Comptroller, told the graduates of the Jewish Theological Seminary today.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ben-Porat, who was the first woman on Israel's Supreme Court, drew on teachings from the Bible and the Talmud as she discussed the country's political situation. ''Religion and democracy are not necessarily antithetical and can exist in the same regime,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In addition to the 97 degrees conferred to students at the Manhattan seminary, honorary degrees were given to Ms. Ben-Porat; Haim Harari, president of the Weizmann Institute of Science in Israel; Mayer Mitchell, the philanthropist; Ronald S. Lauder, the American Ambassador to Austria in the mid-1980's, and  Robert S. Rifkind, president of the American Jewish Committee. The last three are trustees of the school.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
