<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge in Brawley Case Pares Down Defense's Witness List</title>
    <meta content="22SHAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hickman, S Barrett (Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brawley, Tawana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pagones, Steven A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mason, C Vernon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maddox, Alton H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharpton, Al (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libel and Slander</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDC1039F931A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge in Brawley Case Pares Down Defense's Witness List</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <dateline>POUGHKEEPSIE, N.Y., May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Supreme Court Justice S Barrett Hickman, suggesting that he is frustrated with length of Tawana Brawley defamation trial, limits questions defense can ask some witnesses and bars other witnesses who have been subpoenaed by defense (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suggesting that he is frustrated with the length of the Tawana Brawley defamation trial, the judge today limited the questions the defense can ask some witnesses and barred other witnesses who had been subpoenaed by the defense.</p>
        <p>''This has been an extremely lengthy trial,'' Justice S. Barrett Hickman of State Supreme Court said in a written ruling he released today. ''The defendants should expeditiously proceed forward with their individual defense cases, in accordance with this decision, and let the jury make its determinations.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suggesting that he is frustrated with the length of the Tawana Brawley defamation trial, the judge today limited the questions the defense can ask some witnesses and barred other witnesses who had been subpoenaed by the defense.</p>
        <p>''This has been an extremely lengthy trial,'' Justice S. Barrett Hickman of State Supreme Court said in a written ruling he released today. ''The defendants should expeditiously proceed forward with their individual defense cases, in accordance with this decision, and let the jury make its determinations.''</p>
        <p>Among the witnesses the judge said the defense could not call were Geraldo Rivera and Phil Donahue, the television talk show hosts.</p>
        <p>Alton H. Maddox Jr., one of three former advisers to Ms. Brawley who are fighting the suit, said the ruling showed a bias by the judge in favor of the plaintiff, Steven A. Pagones, a former prosecutor who sued the advisers after they said he had raped and abducted Ms. Brawley in 1987. Mr. Pagones was exonerated by a grand jury in 1988. ''It shows how desperate people have gotten and how they perceive the defense is winning,'' Mr. Maddox said.</p>
        <p>Michael A. Hardy, a lawyer for the Rev. Al Sharpton, another defendant, said the limitations imposed on the defense were unheard-of in a case raising constitutional issues. Mr. Hardy said the judge was being swayed by public opinion because he has been criticized for losing control of the trial. ''You cannot run your courtroom according to public criticism,'' Mr. Hardy said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pagones rested his case on Monday, six months after the trial began. The defense is to begin its presentation on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox said today's ruling was so unfair that it would make it impossible for the defense to call Ms. Brawley as a witness. She has never testified about the allegations, and the advisers have suggested that they might call her.</p>
        <p>''This was supposed to be an exercise in the truth,'' Mr. Maddox said. ''People have always said, 'Why doesn't Tawana talk?' The question now is, 'Why won't the judge let the other witnesses talk?' ''</p>
        <p>Justice Hickman's ruling said Ms. Brawley's name was ''conspicuously absent'' from a list of proposed witnesses that Mr. Maddox submitted  this week. Mr. Hardy has said he may not call witnesses, and Stephen C. Jackson, the lawyer for the third adviser, C. Vernon Mason, has said he is uncertain which witnesses he will call.</p>
        <p>Justice Hickman said he would permit Mr. Maddox to call Dr. Michael Baden, a pathologist who testified before the grand jury that concluded Ms. Brawley's account of abduction and rape was a hoax, and Dr. A. J. Aplasca, the pathologist who conducted the autopsy of Harry Crist Jr., a friend of Mr. Pagones's who died in 1987. The grand jury concluded that Mr. Crist's death was a suicide. But Mr. Maddox has suggested that Mr. Pagones played a role in killing Mr. Crist to silence him.</p>
        <p>In today's ruling Justice Hickman barred Mr. Maddox from calling Mr. Crist's father, Harry Crist Sr., saying his testimony was unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Justice Hickman said Mr. Maddox could ask limited questions of Scott Patterson, a friend of both Mr. Pagones's and Mr. Crist's. The grand jury accepted Mr. Pagones's account of having been shopping in Connecticut with Mr. Crist, Mr. Patterson and a third friend during one of the four days Ms. Brawley said she was held captive and attacked.</p>
        <p>Among the witnesses Justice Hickman said Mr. Maddox could ask questions limited to topics the judge specified were Gerald Hayes, a lawyer who once represented Mr. Pagones; Richard Pienciak, a former reporter for The Daily News who wrote about the case, and Edwin Garcia, a former New York State trooper who wrote to Mr. Sharpton from prison last year. Mr. Garcia said he had information about grand jury leaks to Mr. Pagones that could have helped Mr. Pagones create an alibi.</p>
        <p>In subpoenaing the television personalities, Mr. Maddox had said he needed to question Mr. Donahue and Mr. Rivera about the ''mechanics of their programs including the selection of guests and the posing of questions.'' The Brawley advisers made many of the accusations that Mr. Pagones says were defamatory on the television broadcasts.</p>
        <p>Justice Hickman noted that he had permitted the defense to show the jury ''hours and hours'' of videotapes of those programs. Mr. Pagones's lawyer had played only portions, but the defense lawyers insisted that the entire programs be viewed. After the jurors had seen the entire broadcasts, Justice Hickman ruled, the testimony of Mr. Rivera and Mr. Donahue ''would be of little or no value to the jury in making its final determinations.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
