<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vallone Calls For Changing School Repair</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644951"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARBANEL, JOSH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VALLONE, PETER F (SPEAKER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D81E31F935A15753C1A965958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vallone Calls For Changing School Repair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARBANEL, JOSH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attributing the decline in the maintenance of New York City public schools to "muddled bureaucracy" more than chronic underfinancing, City Council Speaker Peter Vallone yesterday said he would oppose additional maintenance money until the system for making repairs is overhauled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone laid down his conditions as he released a City Council report that describes an unresponsive maintenance system in which, he said, repairs are poorly coordinated, supplies often unavailable and contractors inadequately supervised. Custodians, he said, often do little to help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attributing the decline in the maintenance of New York City public schools to "muddled bureaucracy" more than chronic underfinancing, City Council Speaker Peter Vallone yesterday said he would oppose additional maintenance money until the system for making repairs is overhauled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone laid down his conditions as he released a City Council report that describes an unresponsive maintenance system in which, he said, repairs are poorly coordinated, supplies often unavailable and contractors inadequately supervised. Custodians, he said, often do little to help.</p>
        <p>"This is a disgrace and an embarrassment," Mr. Vallone said. "We live in the greatest city in the country yet our schools are in horrendous physical condition."</p>
        <p>He called for school officials to decentralize maintenance by putting much of the planning in the hands of the 32 district superintendents, and parents, teachers and principals. Once officials have agreed to that step, he said, he will support the use of up to $150 million in surpluses from the state's Municipal Assistance Corporation for school maintenance and discuss additional city spending.</p>
        <p>Although the City Council does not have a direct say in how Municipal Assistance Corporation money is spent, in the past, the board has made its decisions in consultation with the Governor and the city government. It is unlikely that money would be allocated over the Council's objections.</p>
        <p>The report comes at a time of rising parental discontent -- in the midst of City Council and mayoral elections -- over an asbestos crisis that has demonstrated the systematic neglect of the 1,069 public school buildings.</p>
        <p>By decentralizing, the City Council would be responding to complaints about neglect .  But school officials worry that if all maintenance spending is decentralized, some schools in poor condition may get shortchanged, unless the board can protect the citywide interests.</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor Ramon C. Cortines said yesterday that he had already begun giving district superintendents a larger role in maintenance programs. But, he said. "The main problem is a severe lack of funding and not mismanagement."</p>
        <p>He would support improvements in procedures and accountability "especially if significantly more funding is made available to address two decades of neglect."</p>
        <p>School officials say the city has provided only enough money to carry out the most urgent repairs, not enough to maintain buildings properly.</p>
        <p>The director of the Division of School Facilities, Amy Linden, has said it would take as much as $1.2 billion and five years to clear up a backlog of more than 40,000 repairs in the school system. A Board of Education report last December said that 563 schools needed new roofs and 340 needed new windows. Studies have shown that New York spends less on school maintenance than other large cities and less than the state average.</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins has castigated the school system for bungling school maintenance, and proposed turning maintenance over to the School Construction Authority, a state agency. Richard Breyers, a spokesman for Rudolph W. Giuliani, the Republican-Liberal candidate, said that Mr. Giuliani would use his budget powers to reduce bureaucracy and make sure more repair money got down to the schools.</p>
        <p>In the past, Mayor Dinkins opposed the use of $200 million surpluses of the Municipal Assistance Corporation, a state agency set up to sell bonds for the city, in schools, favoring other priorities instead. But during this campaign he has proposed using some of it for a fund to pay for innovative school programs.</p>
        <p>Quentin B. Spector, the executive director of the assistance corporation, said he had Mr. Vallone's report under study.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone's report chronicled a series of maintenance problems, listing Intermediate School 394, in Brooklyn, where walls were repeatedly replastered after severe water damage from leaking windows, and Junior High School 115 in the Bronx, where the swimming pool had to beclosed because school officials ignored repeated maintenance requests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone called for reassigning skilled trades workers to school districts and creating school-based survey teams to assess the conditions of school buildings.</p>
        <p>Stanley Litow, a former Deputy Schools Chancellor, said that during the last few years, the City Council, facing pressure to hold the line on property taxes and hire more police, was unable to make education spending one of its top priorities.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, the Council approved more money for plastering and painting without providing enough funds for basic roof and brick repairs, and this in turn contributed to some of the cases cited in the report.</p>
        <p>"Everybody understood at the time, that it was a plastering and painting program, not a maintenance program," Mr. Litow said. "Everybody understood what the risks were."</p>
        <p>The study also found that more than 7 of 10 principals surveyed rated the existing maintenance system as poor -- though most found their own school custodian's work to be satisfactory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
