<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undefeated Tennessee's Two Quick Strikes Stop Georgia</title>
    <meta content="COLL11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Georgia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6DC1F3BF932A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undefeated Tennessee's Two Quick Strikes Stop Georgia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy W</byline>
      <dateline>ATHENS, Ga., Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Tennessee's football team defeats team from University of Georgia, 22-3 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a long time since Georgia was a national powerhouse in college football. The school last earned a national championship in 1980, with a freshman named Herschel Walker in the backfield. Behind a heady freshman quarterback, Quincy Carter, the Bulldogs were again getting that prominent feeling this season.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere and opponent were right for the Bulldogs to test themselves today -- an electrified sellout crowd of 86,117 at Sanford Stadium and and undefeated Tennessee on the field. It took just 6 minutes into the third quarter, though, for Georgia to find out that it still has some building to do if it wants to step into the elite class.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a long time since Georgia was a national powerhouse in college football. The school last earned a national championship in 1980, with a freshman named Herschel Walker in the backfield. Behind a heady freshman quarterback, Quincy Carter, the Bulldogs were again getting that prominent feeling this season.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere and opponent were right for the Bulldogs to test themselves today -- an electrified sellout crowd of 86,117 at Sanford Stadium and and undefeated Tennessee on the field. It took just 6 minutes into the third quarter, though, for Georgia to find out that it still has some building to do if it wants to step into the elite class.</p>
        <p>The Volunteers (5-0) ripped off two touchdowns -- both 3-yard passes by quarterback Tee Martin -- to break open a close game and sink the Bulldogs' hopes for grander things. Tennessee's 22-3 victory pointed out two things for Georgia (4-1): the Bulldogs are still building and they still need a great running back. Can't be a powerhouse rushing for only 59 yards in a game.</p>
        <p>We probably jumped up there a little quicker than we deserved, Georgia Coach Jim Donnan said. We had a shot at these guys. They had the opportunity there at the start of the second half and they took the ball game over.</p>
        <p>Tennessee made it eight victories in a row against Georgia -- a mastery that dates to 1988 and the Vince Dooley era -- but the Volunteers took no special pleasure in putting Georgia in its place.</p>
        <p>We just want to be focused on our season and focused on ourselves as a team, running back Travis Stephens said.</p>
        <p>Stephens was just half of an equation that solved the problem plaguing Tennessee heading into this game. The Vols lost their leading rusher, Jamal Lewis, with a season-ending knee injury last week against Auburn. Lewis had been averaging 124.3 yards a game and many did not believe that Tennessee would muster enough firepower without Lewis.</p>
        <p>So, Tennessee Coach Phillip Fulmer went to his lab and came up with the Travis solution -- Travis Stephens and Travis Henry. Stephens rushed for 107 yards on 20 carries and Henry rushed for 53 yards on 16 carries. And quarterback Martin rushed for 45 yards on 15 carries.</p>
        <p>We knew what we could do, but we never got the opportunity to show anyone, Stephens said. It's just too bad that we didn't get a chance to do it until Jamal got hurt. We like Jamal. We'd like to do it with Jamal in the lineup.</p>
        <p>That would be a scary thought. Almost as frightening as what Tennessee's defense did to Georgia's Carter, who had been sensational in the first four games but was brought down to earth, literally. He entered this game having completed 71 percent of his passes and having thrown just 1 interception in 93 pass attempts. With relentless pressure from defensive end Shaun Ellis and linebacker Al Wilson, Carter completed only 14 of 38 attempts for 195 yards with 2 interceptions.</p>
        <p>He was sacked six times officially. Unofficially, he had to pick himself up after almost every pass play. They put a lot of pressure on us and we couldn't pick up the blitzes, Carter said. I knew they were going to be coming, but we didn't handle it. We couldn't figure out what they were doing.</p>
        <p>Carter wasn't the only one taking his lumps from a brutal Tennessee defensive assault. The Georgia receivers were getting knocked around like pinballs.</p>
        <p>It's hard to have an offense play well when they're getting their heads knocked off, said Georgia left tackle Matt Stinchcomb.</p>
        <p>Despite only 15 yards rushing and 3 first downs, the Bulldogs trailed by only 9-3 at the half. They also hurt themselves with foolish penalties (9 for 86 yards for the game). But Tennessee wiped out all hope in the second half.</p>
        <p>Martin set up a touchdown on a 29-yard run that gave the Vols a first-and-goal at the 3 on Tennessee's first possession of the second half. Three plays later he threw a 3-yard touchdown to Cedrick Wilson that made it 15-3. A 2-point conversion run was stuffed.</p>
        <p>On the Bulldogs' first possession of the second half, Carter overthrew Tony Small, and cornerback Dwayne Goodrich intercepted at the Tennessee 30 and ran 11 yards to the 41. Nine plays later, Martin zipped a pass to Peerless Price and he dived into the end zone on a 3-yard play that helped make it 22-3 with 6:06 left in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
