<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Country-Eastern Night Out</title>
    <meta content="11WORK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING IT WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DF153AF932A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="1347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Country-Eastern Night Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA SIEGAL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sound of fiddles pierces the silence on Avenue W in Gravesend, Brooklyn, on Wednesday evenings, and Don Coy's amplified Kentucky drawl echoes down the street. In the basement of Our Lady of Grace Roman Catholic Church, at East Fourth Street, Mr. Coy leads about 100 people through the basic square-dance steps: ''Do-si-do, allemande left, ladies chain, dive on through.''</p>
        <p>While New York's places of debauchery are prominently advertised on street corners, wholesome activities like folk dancing are tucked away in church basements, public school auditoriums and hospital cafeterias, where women in ruffled petticoats and men in cowboy shirts and bolo ties can be found twirling to country music on almost every night of the week. At least six clubs, with more than 1,500 members, promote American folk dance in the city, charging, on average, $4 for an evening of do-si-do that includes juice and cookies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sound of fiddles pierces the silence on Avenue W in Gravesend, Brooklyn, on Wednesday evenings, and Don Coy's amplified Kentucky drawl echoes down the street. In the basement of Our Lady of Grace Roman Catholic Church, at East Fourth Street, Mr. Coy leads about 100 people through the basic square-dance steps: ''Do-si-do, allemande left, ladies chain, dive on through.''</p>
        <p>While New York's places of debauchery are prominently advertised on street corners, wholesome activities like folk dancing are tucked away in church basements, public school auditoriums and hospital cafeterias, where women in ruffled petticoats and men in cowboy shirts and bolo ties can be found twirling to country music on almost every night of the week. At least six clubs, with more than 1,500 members, promote American folk dance in the city, charging, on average, $4 for an evening of do-si-do that includes juice and cookies.</p>
        <p>But while the clubs in the city share the same moves and music, they draw different kinds of crowds. Country Dance New York, which holds dances in the West Village, tends to appeal to folk music aficionados, more hippie than hillbilly, who go casually dressed for fast-paced spinning to live traditional music. Times Squares, also in the West Village, offers ''gender-free'' dancing for lesbians and gay men, in which men and women can choose the role they want to dance. In Brooklyn, Al'e'Mo Squares and Kings Squares attract couples and single retirees, who wear traditional costumes. Staten Island's Ocean Waves and Richmond Dancers are also more traditional.</p>
        <p>Club organizers say folk dancing has become increasingly popular in New York in recent years. ''Here in Brooklyn, we're getting more and more members,'' said Vincent Nunziato, co-president of Al'e'Mo. Five years ago, the club had 40 members, he said; now it has 130. Other club leaders also say more people are joining, or just dropping in to dance.</p>
        <p>Yet nationwide, folk dancing has been in decline since the 1980's, said Gordon Goss, editor of the National Square-Dance Directory, a comprehensive list of clubs. At its peak of popularity in the mid-80's, Mr. Goss said, there were 11,000 folk-dancing clubs, compared with 9,000 to 10,000 now.</p>
        <p>But Bernie Coulthurst, a former chairman of Legacy International, a national group of square-dance leaders and editor of its journal, said folk dancing is doing well in New York and in Wisconsin and Washington State. Clubs in these places, he said, are ''doing a good job of marketing and there's strong leadership.'' Some clubs, including several in New York, promote themselves on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Whatever club's events they attend, dancers say they the camaraderie, the alcohol-free revelry and the exercise are the draw. ''It's the one place where you come in and you're immediately accepted,'' said Sharon Green, a member of the board of Country Dance New York. ''All you have to do is join in the dance.''</p>
        <p>Nick Martellacci, a square-dance caller for various groups, said, ''This is the most fun you can have with seven other people without breaking any laws or commandments.''</p>
        <p>And for some, folk dancing offers a way to meet people. ''I was going through a bereavement process and I wanted to do something that would get me out,'' said Mr. Nunziato, a retired vice president for Chemical Bank who lives in Gravesend, Brooklyn. For the last several years, he has been sharing the dance floor, and the title of club president, with Caroline Parlato, who lives in the same neighborhood. Together they have traveled the folk-dance circuit from Staten Island as far away as Germany and Japan.</p>
        <p>Like the Kings Squares, Al'e'Mo is a more traditional dance group, and members wear club colors -- Al'e'Mo is red, Kings is purple -- so they can be identified when one club visits another. Expert dancers adorn their costumes with dangles, coin-sized charms that hang from plastic name tags.</p>
        <p>Twenty-four dangles hang from Ms. Parlato's identification pin, telling a tale of five years' worth of good turns on the dance floor. A small red badge etched with a white angel indicates that she coached a new dancer. A white charm with a purple heart set in the center testifies that she once danced with three callers at the same time. (Callers are notoriously exuberant partners.) Another simply attests, ''I danced in Ottawa 1998.''</p>
        <p>Members of the Times Squares have an official club shirt, with a purple-sequined pattern of the New York skyline on the back, but on a recent Thursday-night ''gender free'' dance at Public School 3, many of the 200 or so dancers were wearing cowboy shirts and jeans.</p>
        <p>''The first thing people have to do is decide who wants to be the girl and who wants to be the boy,'' said Terrence Dineen, who books callers for the Times Squares. The ''gents'' wear red bandannas, and the ''ladies'' get more twirling, said Mr. Dineen, who has danced both parts.</p>
        <p>Just blocks away, at the Metropolitan Duane Hall on 13th Street in the West Village, dancers line up every Saturday night to do a different kind of folk dancing, called contra dancing, with Country Dance New York. Instead of forming squares, partners face each other and dance, at first just with the couple next to them. The two couples finish a round of moves and then switch, moving down the line to the next couple. By the end of the dance, each couple has danced with every other couple in their line.</p>
        <p>The 400-member club offers a panoply of dance styles at its weekly events, from regular squares to Swedish folk dancing, but contra dancing is the mainstay. Despite the name, the club's literature says, ''We receive absolutely no funding from Oliver North.''</p>
        <p>MAKING IT WORK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
