<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Season of Color Not So Vibrant</title>
    <meta content="LEAF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EED7143BF932A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Season of Color Not So Vibrant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM LIBBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Libby, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Autumn foliage season in Connecticut is less than splendid as leaves wilt and fall prematurely, before vibrant colors set in (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE cumulative effect of three years of extreme, abnormal weather is having a very destructive and visible impact on the autumn foliage this year. Throughout Connecticut leaves are prematurely wilting, and falling, portending a less than splendid show of color.</p>
        <p>Norway, silver, and red maples, and occasionally sugar maples, are affected, says Dr. Sharon M. Douglas, of the State Agricultural Experiment Station's department of plant pathology and ecology. The maples are particularly important to the season's show of vibrant shades of red and orange. But leaves on oaks, ash, horse chestnuts, dogwood and crab apple, as well as shrubs -- mountain laurel, rhododendron, azalea -- are suffering fungal blights, she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE cumulative effect of three years of extreme, abnormal weather is having a very destructive and visible impact on the autumn foliage this year. Throughout Connecticut leaves are prematurely wilting, and falling, portending a less than splendid show of color.</p>
        <p>Norway, silver, and red maples, and occasionally sugar maples, are affected, says Dr. Sharon M. Douglas, of the State Agricultural Experiment Station's department of plant pathology and ecology. The maples are particularly important to the season's show of vibrant shades of red and orange. But leaves on oaks, ash, horse chestnuts, dogwood and crab apple, as well as shrubs -- mountain laurel, rhododendron, azalea -- are suffering fungal blights, she said.</p>
        <p>The primary cause of the blights was two consecutive wet springs during which water stood for long periods of time on new leaves, Dr. Douglas said.</p>
        <p>These conditions allowed large amounts of fungus to develop in 1997. The same condition last spring caused an explosive growth of funguses like anthracnose, further encouraged by a warm and humid summer.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, the state's forests and landscape trees had been weakened by extreme weather conditions since 1995, making them less able to resist fungal blights and other diseases, said Dr. Douglas. It was in 1995 that the state had its worst drought in 30 years and the driest summer since 1944. The winter of 1995-96 had record snowfall, followed by no discernable spring. The 1997 and 1998 growing seasons were dry in most regions of the state.</p>
        <p>Weather extremes like drought, record breaking snowfall and cold, warm winters with extreme temperature fluctuations and lack of snow cover, singly or in combination cause stress and damage to trees, Dr. Douglas said.</p>
        <p>Drought or dry soil results in damage and death of the trees' roots. If enough of the root system is destroyed, water and nutrients will not reach to nourish the trees' crowns, which will eventually wilt and die. Drought also triggers metabolic changes which will cause trees to produce fewer leaves the following spring, a thinning of the forest's canopy. It causes leaves to brown and prematurely drop, weakens and predisposes plants to diseases and pests, and raises sensitivity to road salts, air pollution and pesticides.</p>
        <p>The abnormally warm winters of 1996-97 and 1997-98 meant trees came out of their winter dormancy too early -- in February, in fact, and last February's temperatures were the warmest ever recorded. Premature budding was followed by the return of more normal cold conditions and late season frosts. This caused extensive leaf damage. By spring, leaves already appeared stunted, and blackened; by summer, the premature fall began.</p>
        <p>Symptoms of leaf spotting funguses became visible in late June, Dr. Douglas said.</p>
        <p>All the conditions for this season's foliage change have not yet been set, said Dr. Douglas. ''But if you look at the forest canopy you can see a lot of  dead brown leaves particularly on maple trees. I don't want to be the bearer of news of doom and gloom, but these brown leaves are not going to miraculously regenerate and produce bright colors.''</p>
        <p>This season's foliage change will still inevitably be spectacular, insists Gerard Barton, assistant manager of the Mayflower, a resort hotel in Washington, who looks forward to the influx of leafers each year.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Clarkson, the founder of The River School in Old Saybrook also looks forward to the season. Every day this month the school's  wooden vessels take passengers on foliage excursions on the Connecticut River. Commentary during the river foliage excursions will explain what produces, accentuates or mutes the forests' autumnal color. ''There are some seasons that are better than others,'' said Mr. Clarkson. ''ButI've never seen a bad one.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
