<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cup Victory Met With Relief</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="178154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACES AND REGATTAS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO YACHT CLUB</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONNER, DENNIS</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AMERICA'S CUP</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">STARS &amp; STRIPES (CATAMARAN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEW ZEALAND (YACHT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1DA1238F933A2575AC0A96E948260" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cup Victory Met With Relief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Sept. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The crowd was not as large in the San Diego Yacht Club today as it was on the night last year when Dennis Conner recaptured the America's Cup in Australia. The celebration was not as raucous, the mood not as euphoric.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The crowd was not as large in the San Diego Yacht Club today as it was on the night last year when Dennis Conner recaptured the America's Cup in Australia. The celebration was not as raucous, the mood not as euphoric.</p>
        <p>The crowd was not as large in the San Diego Yacht Club today as it was on the night last year when Dennis Conner recaptured the America's Cup in Australia. The celebration was not as raucous, the mood not as euphoric.</p>
        <p>But then, the victory was not as complete or the competition so gratifying. As the twin-hulled Stars &amp; Stripes crossed the finish line today to defeat the challenge by the monohull New Zealand, the predominant feeling at the cup's current home seemed to be one of relief that one of the most controversial episodes in yachting history was coming to an end, save for a continuing legal fight that could give New Zealand the victory in court that it failed to win on water.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad we won, but it's too bad it had to be this way,'' said Sandra Barnes as she and several hundred fellow San Diego Yacht Club members watched the end of the race on television.</p>
        <p>The only real thrill of the day for most of Conner's fans came when he unexpectedly guided Stars &amp; Stripes up to the yacht club's dock on his way back into San Diego Harbor. Chants of ''Dennis'' and ''U.S.A.'' greeted him as the catamaran was tied up and the crew gave the skipper his ritual dunking. Bitterness Lingers</p>
        <p>Looking tired but happy, Conner stayed at the club long enough to casually greet a few friends and well-wishers. Then, accompanied by a fleet of powerboats and sailboats, he sailed off again toward the Stars &amp; Stripes compound near downtown San Diego.</p>
        <p>To the end, many members of the club remained bitter toward Michael Fay, the organizer of the New Zealand challenge. After Conner recaptured the cup last year off Fremantle, Australia, the club had planned to use its trusteeship to promote sailing and turn the cup challenges into a popular sporting event.</p>
        <p>Instead, what was once considered a gentlemen's sport was dragged into a legal and public-relations battle that threatened to tarnish the competition permanently.</p>
        <p>''We just want to get this thing over so that we can have the rest of the world join us in an international race,'' said G. Cal Callaghan, the San Diego Yacht Club's dockmaster. 'Played Our Cards Better'</p>
        <p>Calling Fay a ''whiner,'' Callaghan defended San Diego's decision to meet the New Zealand challenge with a catamaran. ''We came up with the more intelligent and better technology; we read the deed of gift more carefully and we played our cards better,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some sailors here were still hopeful that something positive might come of the imbroglio. They grudgingly gave Fay credit for recognizing that new boat designs might invigorate the competition.</p>
        <p>''They've done everything they could do with 12-Meters,'' Philip Freedman, a San Diegan who sailed in the Olympic trials, said, referring to the design traditionally used in cup competition. But Mr. Freedman and others pointed out that new designs, especially big boats like New Zealand, are exciting to watch but expensive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
