<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republicans Now Facing Daunting Challenge</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD8163CF933A25752C1A967958260" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republicans Now Facing Daunting Challenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH F. SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOON after he took office last year, Gov. Jim Florio emerged from Drumthwacket, the Governor's mansion in Princeton, to tell reporters he had just had a meeting with legislative leaders. When one reporter asked him which Republicans were at the meeting, Mr. Florio looked surprised.</p>
        <p>"Oh, there were no Republicans," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOON after he took office last year, Gov. Jim Florio emerged from Drumthwacket, the Governor's mansion in Princeton, to tell reporters he had just had a meeting with legislative leaders. When one reporter asked him which Republicans were at the meeting, Mr. Florio looked surprised.</p>
        <p>"Oh, there were no Republicans," he said.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Florio wants to meet with legislative leaders starting in January, there will be nothing but Republicans around the table. Democrats were suddenly thrust into the role of virtual spectators for the next two years by voters who rejected the Democratic response to the state's economic problems and gave Republicans a landslide victory in legislative races on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Republicans, who are accustomed to being in the minority, were given such large majorities in both the Senate and the Assembly that they can pass any bill they want without Democratic votes and can override any veto Mr. Florio may affix to one of their bills. The present Democratic majorities of 23 to 17 in the Senate and 43 to 37 in the Assembly will be replaced by Republican majorities of 27 to 13 in the Senate and 58 to 22 in the Assembly. In short, the Republican Party is in charge. For many lawmakers who have spent their entire careers in the minority, the change may be daunting. After years of opposing solutions offered by the majority, they must now propose solutions of their own.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Wayne R. Bryant, a Camden County Democrat who will continue to serve as majority leader until the 205th Legislature is sworn in early next year, pledged his cooperation with the coming Republican majority, but added, "Now they'll have to govern, and it can't be done with smoke and mirrors."  'A Lot to Say' About Property Tax</p>
        <p>Other Democratic leaders, including Joseph V. Doria, the Assembly Speaker, whose thumbnail synopsis of the election was that "perception has won out over reality," and John A. Lynch, the Senate President, have promised to work with the Republican majority. But Mr. Lynch said he would "have a lot to say" if the Republicans rolled back Democratic initiatives designed to hold down property taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch had better loosen his vocal cords. Assemblyman Robert D. Franks of New Providence, the state Republican chairman, said that "substantial changes" in the Florio administration's programs would have to be made to satisfy the mandate the voters gave the Republicans on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>And he pointed out that the public's anger over Mr. Florio's $2.8 billion tax program had quickly turned into a personal dislike for the Governor that led directly to the Democrats' loss of leadership in the Legislature. "People didn't like the message, and they really didn't like the messenger," Mr. Franks said.</p>
        <p>The kind of wholesale legislative changes seen last week usually occur only in years when a candidate for governor scores a landslide victory and pulls in legislative candidates on his coattails. A midterm election normally breaks down into individual contests in the 40 legislative districts because of the absence of a statewide election at the top of the ballot to support a unifying theme.</p>
        <p>Although he wasn't on the ballot, and won't be until 1993 if he decides to seek re-election, Mr. Florio was the unifying presence around which the Republicans were able to devise a simple strategy: tie the Democrats to the $2.8 billion in new taxes and to Mr. Florio, whose positive performance rating has not climbed above 25 percent in public opinion surveys over the last year.</p>
        <p>Stephen A. Salmore, a professor of political science at Rutgers University and a Republican Party consultant, said, "The campaign was probably monotonous and not very exciting, but it was effective."</p>
        <p>Republicans will have a few weeks to savor their victory and prepare to deal with the harsh realities they will face next year, some of them of their own making. Republicans have promised to roll back the state sales tax to 6 percent from the 7 percent it was set at in the Florio program. They also have said they will not raise taxes.  Continuation of Problem Seen</p>
        <p>The economy is still in a recession, and there have been predictions of a continuing budget problem next year even with all present taxes in place. A drop of a penny in the sales tax will cost the treasury about $500 million.</p>
        <p>In addition, some revenue-raising moves by the Florio administration to close holes in the current budget, like selling a portion of the state highway system to the New Jersey Turnpike Authority for $400 million, were one-time measures. Whoever is in charge next year is already faced with finding some replacement for that money.</p>
        <p>Norman J. Glickman, director of the Center for Urban Policy Research at Rutgers, said the problems facing the new Republican leadership were enormous.</p>
        <p>"The recession is not going to end in the next few months and pull New Jersey out of its problems," he said. "If the Republicans roll back the sales tax, they must find other sources of revenue or make draconian cuts in the budget, and that will be extremely hard to do.</p>
        <p>"Some people have said the one-cent drop in the sales tax could jump-start the economy, but that's a fantasy. The way things are shaping up, the Republicans are going to have to find more than $1 billion to balance next year's budget."  Planning to Make Changes</p>
        <p>In addition to the financial problems that will dominate the coming legislative session, as they have the last two years, the Republicans have said they want to make changes in other major initiatives of Mr. Florio's first two years in office -- automobile insurance revision, school financing and the ban on the sale of assault weapons.</p>
        <p>The National Rifle Association and the New Jersey Education Association were vocal critics of the Governor's bills and contributed heavily to Republican candidates in the legislative campaign. The rifle association succeeded in getting amendments to the gun law through the Legislature a few months ago, but Mr. Florio vetoed the amending legislation. He won't be able to do that in the future.</p>
        <p>For the Governor, who was a lawmaker for all his 22 years in public life in the New Jersey Legislature and in Congress before winning the governorship in 1989, the role of executive was a new one. Mr. Florio was not a consensus builder during his first two years in office. He dealt with a small cadre of advisers and kept his initiatives under wraps until he was ready to push them aggresively through the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Chuck Haytaian, the Republican minority leader, who will move up to Assembly Speaker in January, said he had only two meetings with the Governor during the first 20 months of the administration.  'Sent Message to Orther States'</p>
        <p>Mr. Haytaian said the New Jersey election had national significance. "It sent the message to other states that people want less government and less taxes," he said.</p>
        <p>The speed with which Mr. Florio passed his tax increase package through the Democratic Legislature after telling voters during his campaign that he saw no need for new taxes stunned many taxpayers and inspired the anti-Florio sentiment that translated into Republican votes on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The Governor and his aides were not good at selling their programs. It took a week for the Governor's office to produce charts that showed that only 17 percent of the state's taxpayers would pay higher income taxes under the new plan. By then, the middle-income wage earners whom the program was designed to help were furious and had stopped listening.  A Pledge opf Cooperation</p>
        <p>Just exactly how Mr. Florio will deal with his reduced power in the legislative process remains to be seen. He has said he intends to work cooperatively with the new leadership, but many Republicans, recalling the snubs of the last two years, are skeptical.</p>
        <p>At his meeting with reporters at Drumthwacket on Wednesday, Mr. Florio said that he would have a legislative program to present to the Legislature in January and said that if the Republicans found a responsible way to reduce the sales tax, he would go along with it.</p>
        <p>At one point Mr. Florio said that some of his policies had undoubtedly persuaded some voters to go out and vote Republican. He also said he had been told that his "bedside manner leaves something to be desired." He added, "I can accept that."  Choice of 'Divided Power'</p>
        <p>Emphasizing that the election is over, Mr. Florio said, "The people have chosen divided power, but they don't want paralyzed government."</p>
        <p>The Governor could just sit back and watch the Republicans wrestle with the same set of problems he has faced and be prepared to make political capital out of any gaffes to help his re-election chances in 1993. But it is unlikely that he will remain silent, given his reputation for confronting problems head-on rather than seeking compromise solutions based on a broad consensus.</p>
        <p>The Republicans strongly criticized Mr. Florio's stewardship in the Republican Party's platform, adopted earlier this year. In it the Republicans said, "After 20 months of Governor Florio and the Democrats, one thing is clear: this is the worst managed state government in the history of New Jersey."</p>
        <p>Even though they do not hold the Governor's office, with the enormous power they were handed by the voters last week, the Republicans will now have to show that they can do a better job.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
