<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Car Crashes in Bronx, Killing the Driver and Five Passengers</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORIARITY, DANNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D7153BF933A25752C1A967958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Car Crashes in Bronx, Killing the Driver and Five Passengers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five young people were crushed to death and a sixth was fatally injured yesterday when their sports car veered off a Bronx street notorious as a speed strip and slammed into a large tree. The police said it was the worst vehicular accident of the year in the city.</p>
        <p>Investigators said beer bottles were found in the car and quoted witnesses as saying the vehicle had been traveling at 80 to 85 miles per hour -- so fast that the roaring impact of the crash left the mangled wreckage embedded in the four-foot thick tree.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five young people were crushed to death and a sixth was fatally injured yesterday when their sports car veered off a Bronx street notorious as a speed strip and slammed into a large tree. The police said it was the worst vehicular accident of the year in the city.</p>
        <p>Investigators said beer bottles were found in the car and quoted witnesses as saying the vehicle had been traveling at 80 to 85 miles per hour -- so fast that the roaring impact of the crash left the mangled wreckage embedded in the four-foot thick tree.</p>
        <p>The police said the crash occurred at 3:20 P.M. when the white, two-door Pontiac Firebird, speeding south on Webster Avenue, veered right, ran up on a small leaf-strewn lawn beside Woodlawn Cemetery and crashed into the tree about a quarter of a mile north of Gun Hill Road in Woodlawn.</p>
        <p>Five passengers -- three men and two women, all believed to be in their early 20's -- apparently died instantly, the police said, crushed in a maze of twisted metal that had to be pried apart to extricate the bodies. 'It's a Tragedy'</p>
        <p>But the sixth, a young man believed to have been the driver, was found alive, dangling from an open door, and was rushed by ambulance to the Bronx Municipal Hospital Center, where he died shortly before 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>"It's a tragedy -- somebody's crying tonight," said Willie May, a 79-year-old resident of the neighborhood, who said speeding was common and accidents were frequent at the place where the young people died. "They come through here like they're crazy," she added.</p>
        <p>The police and local residents said the area where the accident occurred -- a one-mile stretch of Webster Avenue between East 233d Street and Gun Hill Road -- was a virtual race course for speeders and drag-strippers: a straight and level stretch of roadway without stoplights or guardrails, bounded on the east by Metro-North tracks and on the west by Woodlawn Cemetery.</p>
        <p>The speed limit of 25 m.p.h. is ignored by virtually every passing car, many of which roar along at 50, 60 or 70 m.p.h., sometimes hitting the trees lining the four-lane, non-divided roadway. Indeed, the tree where yesterday's victims died showed the scars of previous crashes, as do other trees set at 25- to 30-foot intervals. Room Set Aside for Families</p>
        <p>The driver in yesterday's crash was identified by relatives as Danny Moriarty, 19 years old, a senior at Mount St. Michael's High School in the Bronx. His brother, Robert, said Danny was planning to attend college next year, although he had not selected a school.</p>
        <p>The identities of the other five who died were withheld by the police pending notification of their families.</p>
        <p>Mike Wren, a friend of Mr. Moriarty and some of the others, said: "They were really nice guys. They don't speed or drag race. There might have been beer in the car, but it was a Saturday night and they might have been going to a party. They wouldn't drink and drive."</p>
        <p>Vicki Ciampa, a spokeswoman for the Bronx Municipal Hospital Center, said the hospital had made a room available for the families and friends of the victims, who gathered there after the accident. Many sobbed as they waited for word on Mr. Moriarty.  Panic at Hospital</p>
        <p>One teen-age girl ran up to two friends and hugged them tightly and wailed: "I thought you were in the car! I thought you were in the car!"</p>
        <p>The police closed off all traffic on Webster Avenue between Gun Hill Road and East 233d Street after the crash for the rest of the day as investigators examined the scene for evidence. Sgt. Edward Burns, a police spokesman, said the six deaths made it the city's worst motor vehicle accident this year.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Burns also said beer bottles had been found in the car, but the police said they did not know if alcohol had been consumed by any of the victims or whether it had played any role in the crash.</p>
        <p>Capt. Karin DeShore, a supervisor of ambulance crews with the city's Emergency Medical Service, who went to the scene with three crews, described a scene of tragedy. "When we arrived on the scene, we found a white, two-door passenger car embedded in a tree. One of the patients appeared to be viable. He was removed immediately. The others were all pronounced dead at the scene." 'It Was Gruesome'</p>
        <p>Mr. Moriarty's heart had stopped beating, the captain said, but was revived by the ambulance crew and doctors in the emergency room at the hospital.</p>
        <p>Special prying equipment known as "the jaws of life," was used to remove the car from the tree in which it was lodged and then to peel back the roof of the wreckage to remove the bodies of the other victims. It took police officers and firefighters nearly an hour to retrieve the bodies.</p>
        <p>"It was gruesome," said Wayne Genovese, a salesman at Lasorsa Buick, a car dealership at nearby Gun Hill Road. "There were bodies all over the place."</p>
        <p>A colleague, Mike Sassano, said the wreckage was all but unidentifiable. "The only way you could tell what type of car it was was by the wheels." He said there had been another serious accident last year at the same spot. "It might have been the same tree," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
