<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Place to Call Home</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="485955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, DINITIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOX, PAULA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUNTING, EVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARBOUR, KAREN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MONKEY ISLAND (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FLY AWAY HOME (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MR BOW TIE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DB123DF933A25752C1A967958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Place to Call Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dinitia Smith;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, DINITIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MONKEY ISLAND</p>
        <p>By Paula Fox.  151 pp. New York: A Richard Jackson Book/Orchard Books.</p>
        <p>FLY AWAY HOME</p>
        <p>By Eve Bunting.  Illustrated by Ronald Himler.  32 pp. New York: Clarion Books. $13.95. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>MR. BOW TIE</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Karen Barbour.  Unpaged. San Diego: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. $13.95. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MONKEY ISLAND</p>
        <p>By Paula Fox.  151 pp. New York: A Richard Jackson Book/Orchard Books.</p>
        <p>FLY AWAY HOME</p>
        <p>By Eve Bunting.  Illustrated by Ronald Himler.  32 pp. New York: Clarion Books. $13.95. (Ages 5 to 9)</p>
        <p>MR. BOW TIE</p>
        <p>Written and illustrated by Karen Barbour.  Unpaged. San Diego: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich. $13.95. (Ages 4 to 8)</p>
        <p>One autumn morning 11-year-old Clay Garrity wakes up in a welfare hotel in Manhattan and discovers that his mother has left him. Clay's father, who has also disappeared, is an unemployed magazine art director. His mother, until recently, had a job working with computers. Clay is white, he has been to good schools (he can read "Robinson Crusoe") -- an atypical homeless child. He is the hero of "Monkey Island," Paula Fox's delicate and moving novel, one of the first describing middle-class homelessness for young readers.</p>
        <p>The sight of homeless people pushing shopping carts down the street or sleeping on benches in local parks has become a fact of life, and for children they are the ultimate representation of a terrifying fantasy -- of parents leaving, of loss and displacement. How does a writer make the unbearable bearable without violating the basic truth of the situation?</p>
        <p>Ms. Fox, who has won an American Book Award for children's fiction for her novel "A Place Apart," the Hans Christian Andersen Medal for her collected children's work and a Newbery Medal for the young adult novel "The Slave Dancer," has written a relentless story that succeeds in conveying the bitter facts.</p>
        <p>She depicts life in a welfare hotel precisely: the way Clay's pregnant mother needs the sound of a portable radio all the time to drown out her increasing despair; the way the woman next door cares -- alone and lovingly -- for her retarded son who sits all day watching television, "his feet turned out like a duck's feet." The elevator is a "a poison box," the halls are littered with trails of coffee grounds from leaking garbage bags. A trip to the bathroom can be a dangerous journey.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Clay makes his way to a city park -- called "Monkey Island" by thugs who prey on homeless people there. Like most of the newly homeless, Clay has trouble sleeping. The recent arrivals "were in a panic for days," one character observes. "They were also the angriest if someone or something woke them up in the middle of the night." Life is a constant, primal search. A portable toilet at a construction site is a gift, a broken water fountain means no way to wash that day. For an old woman, counting her few possessions over and over again is "a kind of housekeeping."</p>
        <p>Although the focus of Ms. Fox's story is a middle-class family, she never lets us forget the way race and class affect destiny. When Clay catches pneumonia, his black friend, Buddy, wants to take him to a hospital but knows a taxi probably will not stop for him.</p>
        <p>"Nigger</p>
        <p>is the longest word I know," says Buddy.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Clay is placed in a foster home where people are kind. But, one wonders, how will Ms. Fox ever resolve Clay's abandonment? Will she stage a scene of false forgiveness? When Clay and his mother</p>
        <p>are</p>
        <p>finally reunited, his mother</p>
        <p>doesn't</p>
        <p>ask Clay to forgive her. "Sorry can't erase all that," his mother says. She can only hope that one day she and Clay will find a way "to go on caring for each other that's . . . beyond</p>
        <p>sorry.</p>
        <p>"</p>
        <p>"Fly Away Home" is about a homeless boy, Andrew, about 6 years old, who is living in an airport with his father. But the author, Eve Bunting, makes homelessness seem almost like fun. The airport is clean, and there seems to be enough to eat -- a lot of it sugar. Andrew says he doesn't mind having to walk all the time. Judging from Ronald Himler's watercolor illustrations, Andrew and his father even have reasonably nice clothes.</p>
        <p>Although we're told -- sketchily -- that Andrew's mother has died and his father has only a part-time job, that's not enough explanation. There's needless stereotyping: Andrew's father says school is "important. We'll work it out," while Mrs. Medina, the mother of Andrew's Hispanic friend, says</p>
        <p>her</p>
        <p>son "can wait for a while" to go to school. There is something lazy about this story book, which is intended for 5- to 9-year-olds.</p>
        <p>"Mr. Bow Tie" is a picture book about homelessness for even younger children, in this case 4- to 8-year-olds. Mr. Bow Tie is a homeless man who always wears a bow tie somewhere on his person -- young readers will enjoy finding it in each picture. But with his wonderful, brightly-colored clothes, he doesn't bear much resemblance to any homeless people they've known. He is luckily befriended by a family who let him take a bath. Although he never says a word, the family is miraculously able to find out who he is simply by taking him "downtown to a big office." To make things all the more palatable, it turns out Mr. Bow Tie may be an aristocrat too -- Elliot Lyman Bristow, with parents willing to take care of him, insane though he is.</p>
        <p>The author and illustrator, Karen Barbour, has turned homelessness into a fantasy of color and reunion that is nice to look at, but the Matisse-like drawings with their flattened perspective give little information and provide no understanding. Both of these books for younger children are essentially fairy tales, and condescending ones. Even a 4-year-old can recognize loss and dishevelment on the street. Young readers need -- and deserve -- to understand homelessness. Only "Monkey Island" attempts an accurate picture and succeeds in moving us. And Clay Garrity understands just how different his fate is from that of so many other homeless children. Not everyone is reunited with a loving parent and ends up in a nice apartment that smells all "soapy," "fresh" and "new."  CHILDREN'S BOOKS Dinitia Smith, the author of two novels, "The Hard Rain" and "Remember This," is a contributing editor of New York magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dinitia Smith, the author of two novels, "The Hard Rain" and "Remember This," is a contributing editor of New York magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
