<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amusement Park Worker Dies After Being Pinned Under Ride</title>
    <meta content="01coaster" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/01/nyregion/01coaster.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1698844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DB1731F932A3575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amusement Park Worker Dies After Being Pinned Under Ride</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amusement Park Worker Dies After Being Pinned Under Ride</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER C. BELLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A North Babylon teenager who spent the summer working at the Adventureland amusement park in Farmingdale, N.Y., died early yesterday after being run over on Tuesday night by a car on the roller coaster he was operating.</p>
        <p>The teenager, Stephen Gary, 18, was the third person killed in an amusement park accident in the state this month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A North Babylon teenager who spent the summer working at the Adventureland amusement park in Farmingdale, N.Y., died early yesterday after being run over on Tuesday night by a car on the roller coaster he was operating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A North Babylon teenager who spent the summer working at the Adventureland amusement park in Farmingdale, N.Y., died early yesterday after being run over on Tuesday night by a car on the roller coaster he was operating.</p>
        <p>The teenager, Stephen Gary, 18, was the third person killed in an amusement park accident in the state this month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary was operating the Lady Bug coaster when he was struck by one of the two-person cars about 10:40 p.m., according to Lt. Jack Fitzpatrick of the Suffolk County police homicide squad. No one was riding the Lady Bug at the time, according to a statement released by the park.</p>
        <p>A fellow employee witnessed the accident, which occurred next to the platform that houses the ride's controls, the police said. The employee, who was not identified by the police, told investigators that Mr. Gary was leaning over the ride's elevated track when he was struck. Mr. Gary was left dangling two feet off the ground, his upper torso pinned under the car, Lieutenant Fitzpatrick said.</p>
        <p>Adventureland employees quickly improvised a way to hoist the car off Mr. Gary, freeing him, and he was taken to Nassau University Medical Center in East Meadow, the lieutenant said.</p>
        <p>He was pronounced dead about 5:30 a.m. yesterday, a hospital spokeswoman said. Lieutenant Fitzpatrick said that Mr. Gary suffered crushing injuries and blunt-force trauma. An autopsy was scheduled for today.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Gary remained conscious for a while after the accident, investigators say they do not know why he was on the tracks of the ride. ''According to everybody at the park, there was no reason he should be on the tracks,'' Lieutenant Fitzpatrick said.</p>
        <p>The federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration and the New York State Department of Labor are also investigating, the police said.</p>
        <p>According to the statement released by the park, Mr. Gary had worked there for two years.</p>
        <p>Last week, a worker died while setting up midway rides at the New York State Fair in Syracuse. And earlier in August, a 7-year-old boy died at the Playland Amusement Park in Rye after he became wedged under a conveyor belt on Ye Old Mill boat ride.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
