<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Road, Christopher Is Finding His Footing</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIDDLE EAST-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER, WARREN (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D9103DF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="1568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Road, Christopher Is Finding His Footing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his meeting with President Hafez al-Assad in Damascus the other day, Warren Christopher joked that he was old enough to be Bill Clinton's father, getting a laugh out of the Syrian leader. In Kuwait City, he pressed the Emir -- unsuccessfully -- to give women the right to vote, noting that America's own history on the subject was far from perfect. And in Amman, he took reporters along to a soccer field for his daily 20-minute, two-mile run, graciously insisting that they do another lap while he waited in the car.</p>
        <p>On his 10-day, 10-country overseas debut as Secretary of State, Mr. Christopher began to define himself. Struggling to shed his image as the loyal, but colorless No. 2 to Secretary of State Cyrus R. Vance during the Carter Administration, Mr. Christopher is smiling more, making himself more accessible to reporters and trying to act, well, robust, an adjective he likes to use in discussing what good diplomacy should be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his meeting with President Hafez al-Assad in Damascus the other day, Warren Christopher joked that he was old enough to be Bill Clinton's father, getting a laugh out of the Syrian leader. In Kuwait City, he pressed the Emir -- unsuccessfully -- to give women the right to vote, noting that America's own history on the subject was far from perfect. And in Amman, he took reporters along to a soccer field for his daily 20-minute, two-mile run, graciously insisting that they do another lap while he waited in the car.</p>
        <p>On his 10-day, 10-country overseas debut as Secretary of State, Mr. Christopher began to define himself. Struggling to shed his image as the loyal, but colorless No. 2 to Secretary of State Cyrus R. Vance during the Carter Administration, Mr. Christopher is smiling more, making himself more accessible to reporters and trying to act, well, robust, an adjective he likes to use in discussing what good diplomacy should be.</p>
        <p>When he thinks about the responsibility that comes with the job, he genuinely seems weighted. He has said in informal settings that he has not quite become accustomed to the deference that is paid to him, the security that surrounds him, the privacy he has lost, and the worry that in concentrating on the details of the day, he may fail to look around the globe. Measuring Up</p>
        <p>In the most private of moments, the 67-year-old Los Angeles lawyer has even admitted to having self-doubts about his ability to manage it all. His thoughts while touring the Yad Vashem Memorial in Israel to the six million Jews who lost their lives in the Holocaust, for example, were described to reporters in this way:</p>
        <p>"There is a heavy responsibility being Secretary of State, and I worry about acquitting it well. It was brought home yesterday where I couldn't help but think, am I able to evaluate all the responsibilities? Am I able to sort out which of these things are possible situations like the Holocaust. You have a whole series of things that come across your plate. Is it Cambodia? Or is it Bosnia? Or is it Haiti? Can one possibly live up to those responsbilities?"  Facilitator and Catalyst</p>
        <p>In pressing the Arabs, Israelis and Palestinians to come back to the negotiating table, he has revealed a distinct negotiating style. He is not a diplomatic dealmaker in the style of James A. Baker 3d, who would withhold part of his agenda from his interlocutors, stake out positions for the parties to embrace and threaten to get back on the plane and go home if they didn't.</p>
        <p>Rather, Mr. Christopher is a facilitator, a publicly invisible catalyst who uses trust rather than fear to move the parties forward, culls workable ideas from what they say and relies on their friends to press them to be flexible. In an effort to have the parties resume the Middle East peace talks, for example, Mr. Christopher embraced an Egyptian initiative to nudge the Israelis and a Russian idea to invite the Palestinians to Moscow, and then issued a call for a new round of talks only after asking the advice of all the parties.</p>
        <p>Except for the negotiating style, Warren Christopher is a man hard to get to know. He does not like the spontaneity, instant analysis or chitchat that traditionally comes with the job, admitting quietly that he is not very good at "schmoozing" and would never pretend to be.</p>
        <p>At least one Arab leader seemed taken aback when Mr. Christopher started their talks not with the usual diplomatic filigree, but with an enumeration of the many points he wanted to make. He has told aides that he feels exposed when the camera lights are trained on him, the microphones thrust in his face, when he must respond quickly to complicated issues he'd rather think about first. Awkward Moments</p>
        <p>At times, the desire to reflect but the impulse to react has put him one frame behind or ahead of the conversation. During the tour of the Yad Vashem Memorial, the memorial's director, Yitzhak Arad, explained how the sculptor who cast an ambitious five-part frieze was himself a Holocaust survivor and that one of the sculptor's sons was killed in a bomb blast in Jerusalem. "Is that carved from stone?" Mr. Christopher asked. "No, from aluminum," Mr. Arad replied.</p>
        <p>At a briefing site on the Golan Heights, Gen. Yitzhak Mordechai, commander in chief of Israel's northern command, spread out large maps and, using a pool cue, gave an impassioned lecture on Israel's geographical vulnerability and the importance of the strategic plateau, which Israel captured from Syria in the 1967 Middle East war, for the country's security. Mr. Christopher's question -- where were the borders before Israel occupied the territory? -- left Israeli officials puzzled. Was it a trick of some sort? Did Mr. Christopher really not know where the pre-1967 borders were, or did he somehow want to draw attention to what Israel used to be?</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher has said more than once that he aspires "to the standard of Shakespeare's statesman, of whom it is said, 'He can hold his tongue in 10 different languages.' " The Secretary obviously feels more comfortable listening than talking. In fact, he has developed what might be called the Christopher Rules of Good Listening: listen hard when people restate their positions to see if they have left something out; restate the position of the parties on more conciliatory terms to see if they agree with the milder formulation; ask people to articulte their adversary's position to discover what they consider important.</p>
        <p>He says he never gets angry except on purpose, and once during his last incarnation in the State Department, he told an interviewer, "That's part of my job, being controlled."  A Memorial Tests Composure</p>
        <p>Indeed, throughout most of the tour of Yad Vashem, which contains haunting photographs of Holocaust victims, Mr. Christopher was able to keep his composure. But the final exhibit, a memorial to children, tested his determination to mask his emotions.</p>
        <p>He entered a large darkened room where a single candle was reflected countless times in mirrors and panes of glass, giving the impression of an infinite number of tiny points of light representing the 1.5 million children killed in the Holocaust. Recorded voices spoke the names of the children, their ages, and their countries of origin.</p>
        <p>To keep control as he made his way through the darkness, Mr. Christopher stopped, looked up at the ceiling, and then began to walk very slowly as he approached the exit, his eyes fixed straight ahead. "It was one of the most moving experiences of my life," he told a reporter who asked his reaction. For a full 10 seconds he remained silent, then finished the sentence, "a reminder of the responsbility we all have who have governmental positions."</p>
        <p>But the inclination to keep his own counsel clashes with a steely determination not to let what he considers misstatements or misdeeds slip by him. In a discussion of Syria's inclusion on the State Department list of countries that support terrorism, Syria's Foreign Minister, Farouk al-Sharaa, made the point that there was armed opposition to the peace process in Israel as well. Mr. Christopher let him lecture on, and then replied, "Mr. al-Sharaa, may I remind you that Israel is a democracy and the character of the opposition matters."</p>
        <p>And following a joint news conference in Geneva with the Russian Foreign Minister, Andrei V. Kozyrev, on Thursday, an angry European reporter shouted at the stage that the State Department press had dominated the event, Mr. Christopher turned back to inform him tersely, "We didn't organize it." Still Finding His Voice</p>
        <p>In a sense, Mr. Christopher is still trying to find his voice, and the flowery language that could help him out of uncomfortable moments just does not come naturally, at least not yet.</p>
        <p>There he was in Amman, with King Hussein at his side, asked by a reporter whether he brought the King an invitation from Mr. Clinton to visit Washington. He could have replied that, of course, the King is always welcome in Washington. Instead, Mr. Christopher froze for a second, before he answered hesitantly that Mr. Clinton had sent the King a message, but that such things were private.</p>
        <p>In his spare time on the road, Mr. Christopher promises to be an inveterate tourist. George P. Shultz played many of the best golf courses in the world. James A. Baker 3d closeted himself in his room working the phones and plowing through the cable traffic. But Mr. Christopher wants to see the sights.</p>
        <p>Trekking through the sand and the camel dung while touring the Pyramids near Cairo the other day, he at times seemed downright jaunty, bouncing out of his limousine and posing -- with a hesitant smile -- for photographers. Coincidental Tourist</p>
        <p>"It seems to me you always want to learn all that you can about the traditions and history of the country you are visiting," he said after leaving the 4,500-year-old Solar Boat.</p>
        <p>Dressed in a pair of chinos, a navy-blue windbreaker and brand-new suede Rockport Wallabees, he bore a remarkable resemblance to Mr. Rogers, the gentle soul of children's television.</p>
        <p>The Pyramids and the Sphinx were "breathtaking, awesome," he said. His last-minute helicopter trip to Beirut was "exhilarating." And in a sign that there was a child behind the droopy face, with a flat Midwestern voice, he added, "I really like helicopter rides very well."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
