<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weeds: Nutrient, Vegetable or Nuisance?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D7163BF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weeds: Nutrient, Vegetable or Nuisance?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE next time anyone considers weeds as mere nuisances, they just may want to think again. No one knows what value some of these ordinary plants may have, and there could be a beneficial function to society in their future.</p>
        <p>As a case in point, look at what is happening to purslane, a rather common garden weed. It sprawls, has fat rounded leaves and is a nuisance, even though a somewhat attractive one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE next time anyone considers weeds as mere nuisances, they just may want to think again. No one knows what value some of these ordinary plants may have, and there could be a beneficial function to society in their future.</p>
        <p>As a case in point, look at what is happening to purslane, a rather common garden weed. It sprawls, has fat rounded leaves and is a nuisance, even though a somewhat attractive one.</p>
        <p>Yet, this ordinary weed could have a big future as a vegetable, as strange as it may seem. The Weed Science Laboratory, which is part of the United States Department of Agriculture, has been studying this rather lowly plant and found that purslane is a rich source of fatty acid, vitamin E and other key nutrients. The researchers conclude that these findings indicate that this lowly weed may just be a prime candidate for a new vegetable crop.</p>
        <p>One thing in purslane's favor is that it thrives in arid areas and could be a particularly useful crop in the Southwestern states where there is not only dry soil but also a severe alkaline condition. These are two negative factors that need a strong positive to provide a viable solution.</p>
        <p>Although there are probably 200 species of purslane, or portulaca (their common name), the scientists were most interested in the annual form, Portulaca oleracea, which grows worldwide. The researchers know that purslane will thrive in poor soils and its seeds have a long survival rate, up to 40 years.</p>
        <p>Purslane can be eaten raw or cooked. In salads it provides a crunchy texture with a nutty flavor, something akin to bean sprouts. When cooked, purslane is believed to have 10 times more linolenic acid than is found in spinach and that is considered essential in animal diets.</p>
        <p>As research continues on the benefits of different plant life the merits of many other plants may soon become clear. Scientists are just beginning to identify the value of many tropical species, thus the rush to save flora in the rain forests.</p>
        <p>Sometimes gardeners try to be their own pioneers, but amateurs should never experiment with plants on their own, as there are some poisonous actors out there. Anyone venturing with new tastes must be very clear in plant identifications.</p>
        <p>Which brings to light another useful weed. Several years ago I visited Ruth Stout, an expert in mulch gardening. She was a devoted organic gardener who practiced diligently what she preached in many of her mulch gardening books.</p>
        <p>During the visit she proved to be a great raconteur and lest the time be spent indoors listening to glorious stories, the moment came to visit the mulch-vegetable garden.</p>
        <p>The vegetable garden was near the house and enclosed by a not-too-attractive fence. A thick layer of spoiled hay covered the vegetable plantings, and around the perimeter were massive patches of weeds, lamb's quarters to be exact. The overall effect was, well -- messy.</p>
        <p>The vegetables looked great, the plants were robust. But a rather disturbing glance was made toward the weedy patches.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stout caught my reaction and noted: "I leave them there. They're delicious, try them. The leaves are good for salads." She thrust a few leaves of lamb's quarters into my hand.</p>
        <p>Rather reluctantly I munched and, to my delight, found them succulent and delicious. I was also told the lamb's quarters could be cooked as a good substitute for spinach.</p>
        <p>Lamb's quarters belongs to the great goosefoot clan. The weed in question is Chenopodium album, a name stemming from the Greek "chen," meaning a goose, and podion, a little foot. If left to its own devices, this ubiquitous weed can grow quite tall, perhaps four to five feet, which is about how tall they were in Ruth Stout's garden.</p>
        <p>Lamb's quarters is related to a weed that grows prominently in England and is called Good King Henry. But it has larger, triangular-shape leaves. Researchers have traced its seeds to Roman times and it is believed to have been cultivated as a vegetable.</p>
        <p>Many botanists and researchers have tried to define weeds, mostly negatively. And dictionaries generally describe weeds as plants that have no usefulness or beauty. Perhaps one of the most quoted phrases is the definition once given by a professor. He believed that weeds were "plants out of place."</p>
        <p>By far the kindest definition of a weed was penned by Ralph Waldo Emerson, who said that a weed was a "plant whose virtues have not yet been discovered."  GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
