<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In India, Nationhood Rips Along Old Seams</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE WORLD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HINDUISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARGAN, EDWARD A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D7113BF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In India, Nationhood Rips Along Old Seams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD A. GARGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GARGAN, EDWARD A</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEACE has never come easy to India. At independence in 1947, the blood of more than a million Muslims and Hindus was spilled as colonial India was sundered into India and Pakistan. India has since endured decades of caste wars and sectarian strife. But through it all, the country has been ruled virtually unchallenged by the Congress Party, India's most important unifying force, the architect and exponent of the ideal of secular democracy.</p>
        <p>Now, in a drama that is only beginning to unfold, the central tenets of India's political unity are being severely challenged by a newly invigorated national force -- Hindu fundamentalism as organized in the Bharatiya Janata Party. Last week, the Congress Party Government found it necessary to garrison the capital and arrest 100,000 people to forestall the threat that enormous Hindu demonstrations would bring the Government down. It defended its ideal behind barbed wire, steel-pipe barricades and 100,000 police and paramilitary troops. The tactic worked, for the moment, but the need to employ it suggested far more trouble to come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEACE has never come easy to India. At independence in 1947, the blood of more than a million Muslims and Hindus was spilled as colonial India was sundered into India and Pakistan. India has since endured decades of caste wars and sectarian strife. But through it all, the country has been ruled virtually unchallenged by the Congress Party, India's most important unifying force, the architect and exponent of the ideal of secular democracy.</p>
        <p>Now, in a drama that is only beginning to unfold, the central tenets of India's political unity are being severely challenged by a newly invigorated national force -- Hindu fundamentalism as organized in the Bharatiya Janata Party. Last week, the Congress Party Government found it necessary to garrison the capital and arrest 100,000 people to forestall the threat that enormous Hindu demonstrations would bring the Government down. It defended its ideal behind barbed wire, steel-pipe barricades and 100,000 police and paramilitary troops. The tactic worked, for the moment, but the need to employ it suggested far more trouble to come.</p>
        <p>"The B.J.P. has become a national party for the first time," one of India's most thoughtful columnists, Tavleen Singh, observed recently. "It isn't the Congress Party versus the B.J.P. anymore. It's the B.J.P. versus the rest."</p>
        <p>More than the Congress Party's power is under siege. So is the goal it has had since Nehru's time: that of a modern state that submerges the tensions of religious division in a secular identity as citizens. To be sure, India is a land of Hindus, who make up more than 80 percent of the population. But there are Muslims, Christians, Jains, Parsees and Sikhs as well. What the Congress has tried to do is to turn political attention away from the gods one worships and onto the national identity one embraces.</p>
        <p>But the strategy isn't working any more, if it ever really did. Over the years, the Congress Party became not just an instrument of national unity but also a family business handed down from Nehru to his daughter, Indira Gandhi, and then to her sons. The party depended on the strengths, and the tyranny, of the family. Now the Gandhis are gone, and the glue that held the system together has come unstuck.</p>
        <p>For three years, the once feeble and virtually invisible Hindu political party, the Bharatiya Janata Party, has collaborated with other Hindu fundamentalist and chauvinist groups to alter the definition of what it means to be an Indian.  The three years began with a procession toward the northern holy town of Ayodhya to reclaim a 16th century mosque many Hindus believe was built on a spot holy to them. Beneath the symbolism, the central issue was the plight of India's Hindus. The power of the issue is shown by the increase in the Hindu party's representation in Parliament -- from two seats in 1989 to 119 of the 533 presently active seats in the elections of 1991. Pushing On</p>
        <p>Buoyed by success, the party and its allies have pushed relentlessly forward. First they demanded the demolition of the Ayodhya mosque, denounced the Congress Party for "appeasing" Muslims, and promised to bring a Ram Rajya, the rule of the god Ram, to India. Last December, when the judiciary and Government weren't moving fast enough for them, they stormed into Ayodhya and demolished the mosque. Last week, the party's president, Murli Manohar Joshi, said the destruction upheld a higher law than those of the Indian state because it reflected "the collective will of the people."</p>
        <p>Razing the mosque inflamed passions on both sides of India's central religious divide: It emboldened Hindus to assert their identity in uncompromising terms and it intimidated the country's Muslim minority. For Ms. Singh, the columnist, it signaled a transformation of Indian politics. "The fight now is, can the B.J.P. win?" she said. "People feel that since that wretched mosque came down, this is a party that can get things done. Until that mosque came down there was one national party, the Congress. Now the B.J.P. has become a national party."</p>
        <p>Above all, the Hindu party has managed to give vent to Hindu frustrations and aspirations, real or imagined. It also has made the oppression of Muslims acceptable politically and socially.  When Hindu extremists conducted a pogrom against Bombay's Muslim population, burning homes and businesses, killing more than 600 Muslims and driving hundreds of thousands from the city -- with the collaboration of the police -- not a word of protest or denunciation was uttered by the Bharatiya Janata Party, by the Congress Party, or Prime Minister P. V. Narasimha Rao, who is the Congress Party president.</p>
        <p>And despite the Government's suppression of the protest last week, the fundamentalists' appeal to Hindu sentiments has probably been enhanced. For although Mr. Rao demonstrated that he could marshal the forces of state power to stop a political rally, he has not exhibited any signs that his vision of India, the one handed down from Nehru, is still compelling.</p>
        <p>For the Hindu party and Hindu fundamentalists, the rally's suppression appears to have done little to dampen spirits. Party extremists speak openly of a need to destroy two more mosques, which Muslims have said they will defend.</p>
        <p>Confrontations between Mr. Rao's Government and the Hindu party are sure to continue, and it seems almost certain that there will be more polarization of Indian society, between Hindus and Muslims, and between secular Hindus and Hindu chauvinists. And if India's recent history is any guide, there will be further bloodshed. Whether the Indian state as it now exists will survive, whether the resilience it has shown in its first 45 years can persist, is the bigger question.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
