<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paper Chase May Find Hidden Deductions</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR TAXES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GIFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHILANTHROPY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSEN, JAN M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D91339F93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paper Chase May Find Hidden Deductions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN M. ROSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSEN, JAN M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"DEDUCTION is a very popular word between January and April," said Avery E. Neumark, a partner in Weber, Lipshie &amp; Company, New York-based certified public acountants, commenting on Americans' search for ways to lighten their tax burdens.</p>
        <p>About the only deduction that can be put in place retroactively for 1992, he said, is an I.R.A. of up to $2,000 by April 15. But it is available only to people whose incomes are low enough or who are not covered by a qualified retirement plan and whose spouses also are not covered. The income ceiling is $50,000 for married taxpayers filing jointly with phaseouts above $40,000 and $35,000 for single taxpayers with phaseouts above $25,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"DEDUCTION is a very popular word between January and April," said Avery E. Neumark, a partner in Weber, Lipshie &amp; Company, New York-based certified public acountants, commenting on Americans' search for ways to lighten their tax burdens.</p>
        <p>About the only deduction that can be put in place retroactively for 1992, he said, is an I.R.A. of up to $2,000 by April 15. But it is available only to people whose incomes are low enough or who are not covered by a qualified retirement plan and whose spouses also are not covered. The income ceiling is $50,000 for married taxpayers filing jointly with phaseouts above $40,000 and $35,000 for single taxpayers with phaseouts above $25,000.</p>
        <p>Still, a paper chase through last year's records may turn up an unexpected deduction. "The medical deduction is creeping back slowly," Mr. Neumark said. After Congress raised the threshhold for medical deductions in 1986, making unreimbursed medical expenses deductible only to the extent they exceed 7.5 percent of adjusted gross income, most taxpayers lost that deduction, and many stopped keeping track of such outlays, he said.</p>
        <p>In the last year or so, however, many people have had to pay more of their own health insurance, policy deductibles have risen and many reimbursements cover only part of a doctor's bill. Thus many people once again qualify for medical deductions.</p>
        <p>Conversely, some taxpayers still think they can deduct credit-card interest, Mr Neumark said. They cannot. Deductible interest is generally limited to acquisition debt of up to $1 million on a first and second home, home equity debt of up to $100,000, business interest, investment interest as matched by investment income and passive activity interest to the extent of passive activity income.</p>
        <p>From a tax standpoint, Mr. Neumark said, it makes sense to take out a home-equity loan and pay off personal interest like that on credit cards or car loans. However, the same cannot be done by taking out a margin loan on brokerage accounts, because unlike home-equity loans, investment interest is subject to complex tracing rules.</p>
        <p>Sidney Kess, a New York certified public accountant and lawyer, cautions that people cannot deduct mortgage interest unless it is their own obligation. Many parents in the last year paid bills for adult children who lost their jobs, he said, assuming they could deduct the mortgage interest, but they cannot. On the other hand, he said, medical bills paid for someone like an adult child who would qualify as a dependent except that he or she earned more than $2,300 count toward a medical deduction.</p>
        <p>While most people deduct their cash contributions to charities, Mr. Neumark said, many overlook related charitable deductions like the fair market value of clothing, toys or furniture donated to a charity; expenses incurred as a delegate to a charitable convention, or car costs of 12 cents a mile when using one's automobile for a charity. Form 8283 must be used for noncash contributions of more than $500, and appraisals must be attached for valuable items.</p>
        <p>People who donate appreciated securities to charity and are not liable for the alternative minimum tax can deduct the fair market value without having to pay capital gains tax.</p>
        <p>Miscellaneous deductions have a floor of 2 percent of adjusted gross income, but there are so many of them that more people may qualify than realize it, Mr. Neumark said. These include union and professional dues; job search expenses in the same field, even if unsuccessful; unreimbursed employee business expenses for travel (28 cents a mile for a car), education, equipment like a fax machine used at home or for business publications including the daily newspaper, investment and tax preparation fees.</p>
        <p>A teen-ager can earn up to $3,600 tax-free, Mr. Kess noted, because he or she can take a standard deduction for that much, and the parents are still entitled to the personal exemption if they provide more than half their child's support. The limit would rise to $5,600 if the teen-ager contributed to a deductible I.R.A., he said, and if the parents employed the teen-ager in their own business it would not be necessary to pay Social Security taxes.</p>
        <p>YOUR TAXES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
