<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beleaguered Bosnian President Meets With Gore</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">US-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-YUGOSLAVIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA-HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BINDER, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IZETBEGOVIC, ALIJA (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AKMADZIC, MILE (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILAJDZIC, HARIS (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DA103DF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beleaguered Bosnian President Meets With Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BINDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BINDER, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The President of Bosnia and Herzegovina, Alija Izetbegovic, conferred with Vice President Al Gore today on the Bosnian conflict, and after a 90-minute meeting Mr. Gore issued a statement saying he had "expressed the profound hope that an equitable and durable solution would be found to the problems of former Yugoslavia."</p>
        <p>Mr. Izetbegovic was invited to Washington as part of an effort by the Clinton Administration to persuade him to rejoin peace talks in New York under the supervision of the United Nations and the European Community.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The President of Bosnia and Herzegovina, Alija Izetbegovic, conferred with Vice President Al Gore today on the Bosnian conflict, and after a 90-minute meeting Mr. Gore issued a statement saying he had "expressed the profound hope that an equitable and durable solution would be found to the problems of former Yugoslavia."</p>
        <p>Mr. Izetbegovic was invited to Washington as part of an effort by the Clinton Administration to persuade him to rejoin peace talks in New York under the supervision of the United Nations and the European Community.</p>
        <p>Mr. Izetbegovic has told Cyrus R. Vance, the United Nations mediator, and Lord Owen of Britain, representing the European Community, that he will attend the next session of the talks on Monday in New York. Said He Would Not Return</p>
        <p>At the beginning of February, Mr. Izetbegovic told Mr. Vance and Lord Owen that he would not return to the negotiations because of his objections to their plan for ending the fighting in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>The other main participants in the New York talks are Radovan Karadzic, leader of the Bosnian Serbs, and Mate Boban, leader of the Bosnian Croats.</p>
        <p>On the eve of the resumption of the talks, a dispute has erupted between Mr. Izetbegovic, who is a Muslim, and his Prime Minister, Mile Akmadzic, an ethnic Croat who is a member of the Croatian delegation at the talks.  Challenge to President</p>
        <p>In a letter to Senator Joseph R. Biden, chairman of the Europe subcommittee of the Foreign Relations Committee, Prime Minister Akmadzic contended that Mr. Izetbegovic's two-year term as President of Bosnia and Herzegovina expired in December and had not been legally extended.</p>
        <p>Mr. Izetbegovic remains a member of the republic's presidency, Mr. Akmadzic acknowledged, but not as President any longer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Akmadzic also disputed testimony before the panel on Feb. 18 by Haris Silajdzic, the Bosnian Foreign Minister.</p>
        <p>The rift symbolizes the ethnic conflicts engulfing the former Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>In the letter, Mr. Akmadzic said that Mr. Izetbegovic and Mr. Silajdzic represent the Muslim side in the negotiations but not the Government of the republic.</p>
        <p>Referring to the New York negotiations, the Prime Minister wrote: "I therefore ask you to keep in mind that the testimony of Mr. Silajdzic on the current stage of the Vance-Owen talks and on the national history of Bosnia and Herzegovina is representative of the view of some Muslims of the Government, and not the Government as a whole." Objects to Vance-Owen Plan</p>
        <p>In his testimony to the Biden subcommittee, Mr. Silajdzic portrayed himself repeatedly as representing the Government of Bosnia and Herzegovina, but not as a member of the Bosnian Muslim delegation to the peace talks.</p>
        <p>He strongly objected to the Vance-Owen proposal to replace the current Government with a new central authority consisting of Bosnian Muslims, Serbs and Croats on a basis of ethnic parity, although his delegation accepted that principle in writing in Geneva last month.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Silajdzic proposed before the Senate panel that "the continuity of the legal authorities in Bosnia-Herzegovina will be secured."</p>
        <p>At the hearing, Senator Biden said he, too opposed the Vance-Owen plan. He warmly praised Mr. Silajdzic, saying he was "impressed" by his testimony.</p>
        <p>"I regret having to be so blunt," Mr. Akmadzic wrote in his response to Mr. Biden, requesting that the senator circulate his letter to his Congressional colleagues and enter the letter into the record of the Foreign Relations Committee.  Biden Statement</p>
        <p>In a statement, Senator Biden said he would make Mr. Akmadzic's letter part of the committee record, adding: "It is impossible to discern all that may lie behind such a letter. But it is not difficult to discern one possible effect, which is to undermine the credibility of the very Governmentof which Mr. Akmadzic is a part."</p>
        <p>Mr. Biden's office also distributed a letter faxed to him by Mr. Izetbegovic, asserting that he remained "President of the Presidency" of his republic because of the "emergency situation" created by the fighting.</p>
        <p>Disputes between Muslims and Croats in Bosnia began on the ground last summer in clashes between rival armed forces over who would control territories where both ethnic groups were present in large numbers.</p>
        <p>The disputes have since extended into the Sarajevo Government.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister, speaking by telephone from New York, said: "My point is that all three peoples, Muslims, Serbs, Croats are equal, regardless of their numbers. All are equal in rights to exercise authority in Bosnia and Herzegovina participating on a parity basis."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
