<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Soups and Stews With Seafood</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUPS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HODGSON, MOIRA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soups</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DD163BF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Soups and Stews With Seafood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MOIRA HODGSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HODGSON, MOIRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH I spent a great deal of my childhood in Dorset in the southwest of England not far from the sea, I don't remember eating shellfish until I moved to New York. On my first day in the city, my mother took me to the Oyster Bar at Grand Central Terminal, where I tasted bluepoints for the first time and had my first bowl of clam chowder. I was 17, and for me the experience was an initiation into an exciting new world.</p>
        <p>Since then, I have discovered the seafood soups and stews of the Mediterranean, Italian zuppa di pesce, mussels mariniere loaded with garlic, bourride with aioli and countless other ways of cooking different kinds of shellfish and seafood in a pot. The recipes sometimes look rather daunting at first, because there are so many ingredients, but the stews or soups take only a short time to cook, which makes them particularly good for informal entertaining or for a dinner prepared after work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH I spent a great deal of my childhood in Dorset in the southwest of England not far from the sea, I don't remember eating shellfish until I moved to New York. On my first day in the city, my mother took me to the Oyster Bar at Grand Central Terminal, where I tasted bluepoints for the first time and had my first bowl of clam chowder. I was 17, and for me the experience was an initiation into an exciting new world.</p>
        <p>Since then, I have discovered the seafood soups and stews of the Mediterranean, Italian zuppa di pesce, mussels mariniere loaded with garlic, bourride with aioli and countless other ways of cooking different kinds of shellfish and seafood in a pot. The recipes sometimes look rather daunting at first, because there are so many ingredients, but the stews or soups take only a short time to cook, which makes them particularly good for informal entertaining or for a dinner prepared after work.</p>
        <p>Bottled clam juice can be used in place of fish stock. The shellfish need to be scrubbed, but these days they usually come pretty clean. The vegetables are sauteed and simmered in stock and wine, and then the seafood is added and cooked for only a few minutes before being brought to the table. Croutons of peasant bread spread with garlic and olive oil or aioli goes well with these soups and stews. Saffron Seafood Soup With Aioli</p>
        <p>Total time: 35 minutes</p>
        <p>1 1/2 pounds fish fillets (such as red snapper, cod or halibut)  1 pound medium shrimp  1 pound scallops  1/4 teaspoon saffron threads  2 tablespoons olive oil  1 medium onion, chopped  1 clove garlic, minced  1 carrot, chopped  1 celery stalk, chopped  6 cups fish stock or clam juice  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  2 tablespoons chopped Italian parsley  1 loaf French or Italian bread, sliced and toasted  Aioli (see recipe below).</p>
        <p>1. Cut the fish fillets into inch-and-a-half pieces. Peel the shrimp; cut the scallops in half if they are large. Sprinkle the saffron threads into half a cup of water and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, heat the olive oil in a heavy casserole or stock pot. Saute the onion, garlic, carrot and chopped celery stalk until soft and golden. Add the fish stock or clam juice to the vegetables with the saffron water and cook, uncovered, for 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Add fish, scallops and shrimp and cook four to five minutes. Remove from heat, season with salt and pepper and sprinkle with parsley. Serve the stew in heated bowls, passing the bread and aioli separately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings. Aioli</p>
        <p>Total time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>2 egg yolks  3 cloves garlic  Juice 1/2 lemon (or more to taste)  Approximately 1 cup extra-virgin olive oil  Coarse salt and freshly ground  pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Put the egg yolks, garlic and lemon in a food processor. Blend for 10 seconds.</p>
        <p>2. Slowly add the oil until you have a thick mayonnaise. Season to taste with salt and pepper and place in a bowl.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 cup aioli. Provencal Fish Stew</p>
        <p>Total time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>2 leeks  1 green pepper, seeded and chopped  1 red pepper, seeded and chopped  2 carrots, chopped  1 bulb fresh fennel, chopped  2 cloves garlic, minced  3 tablespoons olive oil  1/4 teaspoon red pepper flakes  2 cups peeled Italian tomatoes (fresh or canned)  4 large potatoes, cut into fourths  1 dozen mussels  1 dozen clams  1 cup dry white wine  1 pound fish fillets (red snapper, cod, halibut or monkfish)  1/2 pound cleaned squid  1/2 cup chopped Italian parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the leeks and place them in a bowl of cold water. Rinse thoroughly to make sure all the grit is removed.</p>
        <p>2. Saute the peppers, carrots, fennel and garlic in the olive oil with the pepper flakes until soft but not brown. Add the tomatoes and a cup and a half of water. Add the potatoes and simmer gently for about 20 minutes or until the potatoes are cooked.</p>
        <p>3. Meanwhile, scrub the mussels and the clams. Heat the white wine in a large pan and add the shellfish. Cook them over high heat until they open (the mussels will open first). Remove them from the pan as soon as they open their shells; otherwise, they will become tough. Strain the cooking liquid if there is any sand in it and add it to the tomatoes and vegetables.</p>
        <p>4. Cut the fish fillets into two-inch pieces. Cut the squid into one-inch pieces. Add them to the casserole, cover and cook for five minutes. Add the shellfish just long enough to heat through. Sprinkle with parsley and serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings. Zuppa di Pesce</p>
        <p>Total time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>2 leeks  1/4 cup olive oil  2 cloves garlic, minced  1/4 cup Italian parsley, chopped  2 cups tomatoes, peeled, seeded and chopped (fresh or canned)  2 teaspoons tomato paste  1 teaspoon thyme leaves  1 teaspoon rosemary leaves  6 cups fish stock or clam juice  1 cup dry red wine  1 pound fish fillets (halibut, red snapper, monkfish or cod)  1 pound shrimp, peeled and deveined  1 pound bay scallops  Coarse salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the leeks and place them in a bowl of cold water. Rinse thoroughly to make sure all the grit is removed. In a large stock pot or heavy casserole, heat the olive oil and saute the leeks and garlic. Add the parsley, tomatoes, tomato paste, thyme, rosemary, fish stock and wine. Bring to boil, turn down heat and simmer for 20 minutes, uncovered.</p>
        <p>2. Add the fish fillets, shrimp and scallops and cook for five minutes. Correct seasoning and serve the soup immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
