<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Issues: Sellers Win, Buyers Lose</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOUGHRAN, TIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RITTER, JAY R (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Gretchen Morgenson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DB1639F93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Issues: Sellers Win, Buyers Lose</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Initial public offerings, as any broker will be happy to tell you, are often great investments. They are your chance to get in on the ground floor, to share in the growth of business.</p>
        <p>Now along come a couple of academics who studied the record of companies that went public over a 20-year period. Tim Loughran, a graduate student at the University of Illinois, and Jay R. Ritter, a finance professor, found the brokers are wrong. Most I.P.O.'s are overpriced, and that problem is worst when the market is hot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Initial public offerings, as any broker will be happy to tell you, are often great investments. They are your chance to get in on the ground floor, to share in the growth of business.</p>
        <p>Now along come a couple of academics who studied the record of companies that went public over a 20-year period. Tim Loughran, a graduate student at the University of Illinois, and Jay R. Ritter, a finance professor, found the brokers are wrong. Most I.P.O.'s are overpriced, and that problem is worst when the market is hot.</p>
        <p>Such facts are unlikely to discourage buyers, especially because a lot of institutions that buy new issues couldn't care less about the long-term. They hope the price will leap the first day, providing quick profits.</p>
        <p>And sometimes it does. Consider Mathsoft, a software company that was one of this month's better issues. Offered at $13, it opened for trading at $20.50, and the first day's volume saw more shares trade than had been sold in the offering, as the lucky buyers cashed out.</p>
        <p>By no means should you refuse such opportunities. But unless you work for a powerful institution, or have friends at the company going public, you're not likely to get in on the hot ones. It's a little bit like Groucho Marx's remark about private clubs: If they are willing to let you in on the offering, it's probably not one you want. Investors who bought Mathsoft the first day paid prices that have not been seen since.</p>
        <p>The Illinois study looked at performance of stocks over the five years after they went public, assuming purchase at the closing price on the first day of trading. It found that the average new issue produced annual returns of 2 percent, about one-seventh the average profit from similar public companies.</p>
        <p>Why are I.P.O.'s such bad investments? The Illinois study suggests that companies time their offerings when market prices for their industries are near peaks. And they often go public shortly before the company's growth pattern begins to slow, disappointing investors who expected the growth to continue.</p>
        <p>Is there a way to figure out scientifically which initial public offerings are better than others? One way is to check out what's hot, and then stay away. A previous study by Mr. Ritter found that offerings that did not rise the first day tended to do a bit better over three years than those that soared in the first trading. And the new study indicates that the best time to buy new issues is when few are being sold.</p>
        <p>There are indications that the new issue market is getting jittery. Two offerings in what had been hot areas -- a casino company and a restaurant -- were withdrawn after they plunged in price this month. But even without them, Securities Data calculates that new offerings raised at least $2.3 billion this month.</p>
        <p>With the public putting $10 billion a month into stock mutual funds, perhaps the new issue market will stay strong. But the Illinois study should make long-term investors reconsider whether they really want to participate.  MARKET WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
