<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hartford Benefit for People With AIDS</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD1F3CF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="1072" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hartford Benefit for People With AIDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A PAIR of benefit concerts can be heard today at 4 P.M.: the double bassist Gary Karr and the pianist Harmon Lewis will play in Hartford at Immanuel Congregational Church, while choral and instrumental ensembles of South Church in Hartford will perform at the Second Congregational Church in Middle Haddam in a program directed by Richard Donohue.</p>
        <p>The Karr-Lewis duo has donated its services to support Bread and Roses, an organization providing residential care for people with AIDS-related diseases, and while there is no formal admission charge, donations are requested. For more details, call 527-8121.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A PAIR of benefit concerts can be heard today at 4 P.M.: the double bassist Gary Karr and the pianist Harmon Lewis will play in Hartford at Immanuel Congregational Church, while choral and instrumental ensembles of South Church in Hartford will perform at the Second Congregational Church in Middle Haddam in a program directed by Richard Donohue.</p>
        <p>The Karr-Lewis duo has donated its services to support Bread and Roses, an organization providing residential care for people with AIDS-related diseases, and while there is no formal admission charge, donations are requested. For more details, call 527-8121.</p>
        <p>In Middle Haddam the people at South Church whose numerous benefit programs made possible the 1992 restoration of the Appleton organ at Second Congregational will now try to raise money to insure the proper maintenance of the instrument, only seven of which are known to exist.  Mr. Donohue will demonstrate the organ, playing and conducting hymns, anthems and other works that may have been heard on the original instrument a century ago (583-9152 or 249-8627).</p>
        <p>Three other recitals of note this afternoon start at 3 when the guitarist Christopher Parkening plays Bach, Albeniz, Granados and more -- some in collaboration with the pianist David Brandon -- at the Palace Theater in Stamford (325-4466). An hour later, the cello-piano duo of Lois Errante and Irina Chukovsky will offering Brahms and Debussy sonatas, along with shorter works of Cassado and Messiaen, at the Westport Unitarian Church (762-2964).</p>
        <p>Also at 3, at First Presbyterian Church in Stamford, the Pro Arte Singers are staging "a Renaissance Fest", with period costumes and historic instruments. "We'll be creating an exciting festival atmosphere," said the group's music director Arthur Sjogren, "with sacred pieces, lively madrigals, bird calls, songs popular in Renaissance courts throughout Europe, even a parade of the banners by fifth grade students who have created their own heraldic flags" (323-7955).</p>
        <p>The New Haven Symphony gets the orchestral ball rolling this week with an 8 P.M. Tuesday concert at Woolsey Hall in which Michael Palmer will conduct works by Beethoven, Bartok and Brahms. More specifically, the audience will hear the Prometheus Overture, Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta, and the B-flat Piano Concerto, with Garrick Ohlsson the guest soloist (776-1444).</p>
        <p>Symphonic Brahms comes to Woolsey on Friday at 8, with Gunther Herbig leading the Yale Philharmonia in the First Symphony. Earlier in the evening, the conducting fellow Steven Lipsitt will be on the podium for Weber's "Euryanthe" overture and the Avery Fisher prize-winning cellist, Bion Tsang, featured in the Dvorak Concerto. There is no admission charge (432-4157).</p>
        <p>Guest maestros take charge of two other Saturday programs, Donald Schleicher giving the 8:15 downbeat to the Greater Bridgeport Symphony at Klein Memorial Auditorium, while at 8:30 Keith Brion leads the Waterbury Symphony in works by John Philip Sousa in the Kennedy Auditorium.</p>
        <p>The watchword in Bridgeport is fiesta, with such Spanish or Hispanic-influenced pieces on display as Manual de Falla's "Three-Cornered Hat," Aaron Copland's "Salon Mexico" and "Feria Magica" by Carlos Surinach, who now lives in Connecticut and is expected to attend the concert. For reservations, call 576-0263.</p>
        <p>In Waterbury, Keith Brion, in full Marine Corps uniform, salutes both the memory of America's march king and the 100th anniversary of the Sousa Band with a program recreating the kind of symphonic pops program that was popular around the turn of the century. Kimberly Parsons, Frank Covey and Patrick Smith are among the soloists, and audiences are promised music by Tchaikovsky, Suppe, Grainger and Tchaikovsky, although it seems safe to predict that a Sousa march or two will find a way into the musical proceedings (574-4283).</p>
        <p>There is similar musical diversity on the vocal scene. Andrew Lloyd Webber's "Evita" begins a two-week run at the Shubert Theater in New Haven on Tuesday. For performance times, call the box office at 562-5666.</p>
        <p>Folk fans will not want to miss the song and dance of the Ballet Folklorico Nacional de Mexico in the company's single performance on Thursday at 8 in Jorgensen Auditorium in Storrs (486-4226) or the nostalgic close harmonies of Peter, Paul and Mary at the ever-popular trio's 8 P.M. Friday show in the Stamford Palace (325-4466). At Norwalk Community-Technical College at 8 P.M. on Saturday the singers, musicians and step dancers of Cuchullan present an evening of Irish entertainment (857-7271).</p>
        <p>Mozart is the composer of choice as Connecticut Concert Opera prepares to unveil its edition of Mozart's comic masterpiece "The Abduction From the Seraglio." "We have a terrific cast" said John Wadhams, the opera's publicity chairman. "Constance Rock, on the faculty of the University of Connecticut and one of the best Mozart singers I've heard, will be our Konstanze, Osmin is ably handled by John Seabury, a veteran of many Mozart productions at New York City Opera, Wayne Rivera is the Belmonte and, as Pedrillo, we have Jerome Pruett, head of the voice faculty at the Hartt School of Music."</p>
        <p>The performances will be in German, with English supertitles, and audiences have a choice of two performances at the Wallace Stevens Theater in Hartford: 8:15 P.M. Friday and next Sunday afternoon at 3. For reservations or more information about the company, call 247-4147.</p>
        <p>Mozart is also on the composer's roster at the Mendelssohn Choir's evening of "Music for the Theater: Opera to Broadway" So too is Donizetti, Bernstein and Andrew Lloyd Webber, with Carole Ann Coyne-Maxwell conducting the 8 o'clock concert at First Presbyterian Church in Fairfield (259-9435 or 254-0658).</p>
        <p>Connecticut College is preparing to offer the fourth Biennial Arts and Technology Symposium from Thursday through next Sunday on its New London campus. "This will be "a serious, mind-bending hoot," said a college official, Christopher Cory, "with 75 cutting-edge bridge builders from all over the world coming to strut their esthetic and intellectual stuff for one another and interested bystanders." Information on any of the panels, lectures, demonstrations of interactive videos and other new entertainment technologies, as well as three evening concerts can be had by calling 439-2001 for a schedule of dates and times or registration information.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
