<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This California Dream Is All About Auto Insurance</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILE INSURANCE AND LIABILITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWYERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL PROFESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D7103BF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This California Dream Is All About Auto Insurance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WANT to cut auto insurance premiums by a third -- and, as a bonus, rid the roads of uninsured drivers, untangle traffic, reduce highway fatalities and help clean up the air? This may sound suspiciously like the teaser for one of those late night infomercials on the miraculous rejuvenating powers of pureed vegetables, but read on.</p>
        <p>Inspired by proposals from the financial writer Andrew Tobias and the National Insurance Consumer Organization, some influential Democratic politicians in California are pressing for radical changes in how motorists pay for auto insurance and collect for injuries -- changes that they believe would slash consumer costs and improve the quality of insurance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WANT to cut auto insurance premiums by a third -- and, as a bonus, rid the roads of uninsured drivers, untangle traffic, reduce highway fatalities and help clean up the air? This may sound suspiciously like the teaser for one of those late night infomercials on the miraculous rejuvenating powers of pureed vegetables, but read on.</p>
        <p>Inspired by proposals from the financial writer Andrew Tobias and the National Insurance Consumer Organization, some influential Democratic politicians in California are pressing for radical changes in how motorists pay for auto insurance and collect for injuries -- changes that they believe would slash consumer costs and improve the quality of insurance.</p>
        <p>Their plan, called "pay at the pump," would use a surcharge on gasoline to cover the cost of auto accidents. As part of a strict no-fault group insurance plan, it is to to be introduced in the state legislature this coming month. Although it has already drawn heavy fire from trial lawyers and insurance agents, it is attracting allies new to insurance reform fights, notably environmentalists. "It's a win-win for drivers and the environment," said Ralph Cavanagh, the energy program director for the Natural Resources Defense Council in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>As in most states, California's auto insurance premiums rose in the 1980's almost three times as fast as the general cost of living. Premiums reached levels that chased off many people; fully a quarter of California motorists break the law by driving without coverage.</p>
        <p>Frustrated voters vented their wrath on the insurance industry, passing a 1988 ballot initiative requiring a rollback in rates, a cap on profits and limits on insurers' right to link premiums to area of residence, age or sex. But enforcement is snarled in the courts. And in the view of dispassionate experts, clamping down on the industry can never generate the promised savings because insurers are, at most, bit players in the drama of escalating premiums.</p>
        <p>The management consulting firm McKinsey &amp; Company estimated that in California, agents' commissions, administrative costs and profits ate up 22 cents of the premium dollar in 1989. Most of the rest went to auto repairs (27 cents), medical care (15 cents), compensation for pain and suffering (18 cents) and litigation costs (10 cents).</p>
        <p>Advocates of no-fault insurance see the last two items -- pain and suffering and lawyers' fees -- as the easiest targets. Under a strict no-fault system, those injured would be automatically compensated for medical costs and some lost wages, but would rarely be able to collect more.</p>
        <p>Consumer groups, however, are divided over the key issue of the right to sue, and the insurance industry has never managed to convince customers that accident victims would be better off with the guarantee of half a loaf than a long shot at taking home the bakery.</p>
        <p>Trial lawyers have blocked no-fault plans in many states, including California. Where legislatures have passed no-fault statutes, opponents have usually managed to riddle the systems with exceptions that make it easy to go to court. Hence the challenge is to assemble a political coalition powerful enough to overcome that.</p>
        <p>The out-of-pocket cost is politically off-putting, too, especially now that a new Federal energy tax is likely to pile on top of California's climbing gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>To sell pay-at-the-pump, Mr. Tobias and Bob Hunter, president of the National Insurance Consumer Organization, offer a no-fault plan with benefits far more generous than the stripped-down ones preferred by insurers. They have won support from most consumer groups, including a number representing Mexican Americans and the urban poor. Next, they added the feature with such appeal to law-abiding drivers, who are furious about the rising tide of uninsured vehicles, and to environmentalists, who are eager to cut pollution and congestion: Rather than writing checks every six months, drivers automatically buy insurance every time they fill up.</p>
        <p>Most of the revenue would come from a surcharge of 30 to 50 cents a gallon. That is expensive, but right now, a typical motorist's insurance premiums cost the equivalent of 85 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>The rest would come from extra fees on car registrations and drivers' licenses. To encourage safe driving, those fees would be linked to people's safety records. For a driver with many accidents and traffic tickets, the fees could run to hundreds of dollars.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Tobias and Mr. Hunter offered a twist intended to save an extra 10 to 15 percent of the premium dollar. Today, auto insurance, unlike most health insurance, is sold one policy at a time by independent agents or insurance company employees, who must evaluate underwriting risks one applicant at a time. With pay-at-the-pump, all car owners could be divided by computer into statistically identical groups of 5,000, and private insurers would be invited to bid competitively for the right to handle a group's claims.</p>
        <p>"The agents and trial lawyers will fight to the death," predicted Mr. Hunter. But he reckons that the economies from group underwriting, along with an end to pain-and-suffering awards and litigation over liability, would make it possible to keep benefit levels high and costs low.</p>
        <p>Michael Horowitz, an expert on tort liability at the Manhattan Institute, an independent research group, is not convinced that pay-at-the-pump will work. He worries about increased government involvement in setting rates, in particular the "adjustments" for riskier drivers. And he thinks that the sponsors are exaggerating the potential savings of their brand of no-fault.</p>
        <p>The costs of unlimited medical benefits, he argues, would be hard to contain. Moreover, most people, he believes, would wish to supplement the standard group policy with both theft insurance and collision coverage beyond the proposed $5,000 maximum. And that would mean plenty of extra work for insurers.</p>
        <p>Most important, he sees the gasoline surcharge as a deal-breaking political liability. Thanks to tough environmental standards, pump prices are already relatively high in California and are supposed to go up by another 10 to 15 cents a gallon in the mid-1990's. The energy tax proposed by President Clinton would add another 7.5 cents by 1996. "Washington has beaten them to the pump," Mr. Horowitz said.</p>
        <p>But politicians are not about to write off the Tobias-Hunter approach. Even those who think the California Legislature will gridlock over the plan say proponents may turn it into a winning ballot initiative, and a national movement.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
