<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="QNAOCTRC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/10/travel/10qna.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1617879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Q&amp;A"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3D91E38F933A25753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q &amp; A</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Golf and Ski, the Same Day; Vatican Museum Hours; Paris Couture Shows</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY CORMIER; Ariane Bernard contributed reporting from Paris for this column, and Jason Horowitz from Rome.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Golf and Ski, the Same Day</p>
        <p>Q. Where would you suggest my husband and I go for a vacation to indulge our seasonally disparate, mutually exclusive interests -- golf and skiing? -- Alma H. Paty, Washington</p>
        <p>A. In North America, the most likely places to hit the slopes and the links on the same day are mainly out West, and mainly in the spring. Here are a few examples:</p>
        <p>About 70 miles west of Denver, the Keystone Resort has two golf courses that generally open in mid-to late May. The resort is about a 10-minute drive from Arapahoe Basin, which has had skiing into July and this year closed June 13. For information on Keystone call (800) 468-5003 or see www.keystoneresort.com; for Arapahoe, (888) 272-7246 and arapahoebasin.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York Times editors answer readers' travel-related questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Golf and Ski, the Same Day</p>
        <p>Q. Where would you suggest my husband and I go for a vacation to indulge our seasonally disparate, mutually exclusive interests -- golf and skiing? -- Alma H. Paty, Washington</p>
        <p>A. In North America, the most likely places to hit the slopes and the links on the same day are mainly out West, and mainly in the spring. Here are a few examples:</p>
        <p>About 70 miles west of Denver, the Keystone Resort has two golf courses that generally open in mid-to late May. The resort is about a 10-minute drive from Arapahoe Basin, which has had skiing into July and this year closed June 13. For information on Keystone call (800) 468-5003 or see www.keystoneresort.com; for Arapahoe, (888) 272-7246 and arapahoebasin.com.</p>
        <p>A bit north, the Loveland Ski Area generally has skiing into May and is about 55 miles from Denver, with many golf courses in between, noted Ainsley Kasten, the marketing manager there. Information: (800) 736-3754 and www.skiloveland.com.</p>
        <p>In the Four Corners area of Colorado, ski season at the Durango Mountain Resort, (800) 982-6103, www.durangomountainresort.com, is Thanksgiving to April. A highly rated public golf course, Pinon Hills, in Farmington, N.M., (505) 326-6066 and www.fmtn.org/depts/parks/golf/phills.html, is about 45 minutes from Durango and 75 minutes from the resort; this year, the course closed only about three weeks, in January. A Durango public course, Hillcrest, (970) 247-1499, usually opens March 15, and Conquistador in Cortez, (970) 565-9208, is open from about March 1.</p>
        <p>According to Nathan Rafferty of Ski Utah (skiutah.com), Snowbird Ski and Summer Resort, (800) 232-9542, www.snowbird.com, 25 miles southeast of Salt Lake City, has the longest season in Utah, often to Memorial Day. At least a half dozen golf courses are within a half hour of the lodge, says Dave Fields, a spokesman for Snowbird.</p>
        <p>Western Canada offers possibilities, too. In May, according to Judy Love Rondeau of Travel Alberta International (www.travelalberta.com), the Banff area has skiing at Sunshine Village, (403) 762-4561, www.skibig3.com, 25 minutes from the 27 holes of the Fairmont Banff Springs resort, (403) 762-2211, www.fairmont.com. Doug Wood, the golf pro there, said the sports generally overlap in the first two or three weeks of May.</p>
        <p>In British Columbia, golfers play on Vancouver Island year round, says Heather McGillivray of Tourism Victoria, www.tourismvictoria.com, while the ski season at Mount Washington Alpine Resort, (888) 231-1499, www.mtwashington.ca, generally runs from December to late April. Crown Isle Golf Resort, (888) 338-8439, www.crownisle.com, is about a half-hour from the lifts.</p>
        <p>On the mainland, a number of golf courses near the city of Vancouver are open all year as well, and ski areas like Cypress Mountain, (604) 419-7669 and www.cypressmountain.com, run from December into April, according to Kate Colley Lo at Tourism Vancouver, (604) 683-2000, www.tourismvancouver.com.</p>
        <p>Within two hours of Vancouver, the main ski season at Whistler Blackcomb Mountains, (866) 218-9690, www.whistlerblackcomb.com, goes to early June, and there is summer skiing on Horstman Glacier. Five nearby courses open around May 1.</p>
        <p>In Europe, Switzerland, while not noted for golf, has courses in areas with summer skiing. Near Gstaad, for example, you can ski at Glacier 3000 and play a round at the Gstaad-Saanenland Gold Club; www.gstaad.ch has information on both. Near Sion, there are four courses at Golf Club Crans-sur-Sierre, (41-27) 485-9797 and www.golfcrans.ch. Information: Switzerland Tourism, 608 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10020, (212) 757-5944, fax (212) 262-6116; and at usa.myswitzerland.com.</p>
        <p>Vatican Museum Hours</p>
        <p>Q. Two of my favorites among the Vatican Museums -- the Ethnological Missionary Museum and the Carriage Pavilion -- are often closed. Is there a way to learn their schedules? -- Robert Kahn, White Plains</p>
        <p>A. These two museums have been closed for renovations, but a small part of the Ethnological Missionary Museum just reopened.</p>
        <p>This museum holds about 80,000 works, most donated by missionaries from every continent but Europe, and was shut for three years for the conservation and cleaning of each object -- items like Australian totem poles and American Indian statues. While it will take another two or three years to finish the job, the China exhibition reopened on Sept. 26.</p>
        <p>The director of the museums, Don Roberto Zagnoli, said that it was impossible to say when the other sections would open, but that the Asian section would be first.</p>
        <p>The Carriage Pavilion, a collection of carriages and automobiles used by the popes, can be visited only on request. Requests, in any language, should be made at least a week ahead by mail to Direzione dei Musei Vaticani, 00120 Città del Vaticano, by fax to (33-06) 6988-5061 or by e-mail to musei@scv.va.</p>
        <p>Daily admission to all the museums is $15, at $1.25 to the euro.</p>
        <p>The other Vatican museums generally open Monday to Saturday at 8:45 a.m., closing on weekdays from March through October at 4:45 p.m.; the rest of the year, on all Saturdays and on the last Sunday of the month, they close at 1:45 p.m. Details are online at mv.vatican.va/3--EN/pages/MV--Home.html.</p>
        <p>Paris Couture Shows</p>
        <p>Q. How can I obtain tickets to couture shows in Paris in January? -- T.C., New York, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A. When the couture designers show their spring collections Jan. 24 to 27, there will be only clients (or likely clients), journalists and industry buyers in the audiences, according to Cathy Horyn, the fashion critic for The Times. They will have been invited by the fashion houses.</p>
        <p>But, according to the French Couture Federation in Paris, a fashion fan could try to get in touch with the publicity company that handles a particular show and ask for an invitation. The big names are unlikely to respond, but some of the smaller houses, those showing on the first or last day of each fashion week, might.</p>
        <p>For individual show schedules, go to www.modeaparis.com, the Web site for the couture federation. To try your luck with publicists, follow the press contact links to see which one handles the houses for which you would like to seek invitations.</p>
        <p>RAY CORMIER</p>
        <p>Q&amp;A</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
