<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METROPOLITAN DIARY</title>
    <meta content="30DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/30/nyregion/30DIAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Metropolitan Diary"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Africa</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Case Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2D6103DF933A05754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METROPOLITAN DIARY</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Dear Diary</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Enid Nemy</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>A few months ago, much to my dismay, my daughter Stephanie announced that she was sending in the required video and application to be on the next ''Survivor'' television series. Those chosen would have to spend 42 days in Africa.</p>
        <p>To the question of why she thought she could be a survivor, Stephanie answered that after dating in New York for three years, she felt she could survive anything.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite having "Survivor" ambitions, there are some whose fear of mice would stop them cold</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>A few months ago, much to my dismay, my daughter Stephanie announced that she was sending in the required video and application to be on the next ''Survivor'' television series. Those chosen would have to spend 42 days in Africa.</p>
        <p>To the question of why she thought she could be a survivor, Stephanie answered that after dating in New York for three years, she felt she could survive anything.</p>
        <p>Of 50,000 applicants, she was one of 800 chosen to be interviewed. She survived a four-hour interview to be among those picked when the field was narrowed to 48. She signed many releases but, alas, was eventually told, ''Thanks for your time.''</p>
        <p>A few days later, I got an emergency call from her, asking me to go immediately to her apartment in an Upper West Side brownstone. She thought she had seen a mouse, had already called everyone she knew and couldn't find anyone available. I told her I could not come over but suggested she use a glue trap. Fifteen minutes later, she called again -- from atop her kitchen table. The mouse, caught in the trap, was screeching at her. Now what to do?</p>
        <p>Africa? Survivor? I think not.</p>
        <p>Rose Axelrod</p>
        <p>''Dear Dolores Case,'' the letter from the medical laboratory began. ''We are writing to you concerning your outstanding balance of $0.00. This balance is for tests performed. Considering that this balance is now over 90 days old, we must receive your payment or we will be forced to initiate collection procedures.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Case, worried that her credit rating might suffer, sent in a check for $0.00. Now she's worried that the command center will think she is trying to be a smart aleck and that the computers will wreak revenge. Stay tuned.</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was helping out a tenant who operates a kosher take-home food store and had to pick up a hot pan of chicken. I had only one rag towel and asked an employee, who is Mexican, to please hand me another. He looked at me and I repeated my request, but I could see he didn't understand.</p>
        <p>Just then the manager came up and said: ''Ask him for a shmatte. He doesn't know what rag towel means.'' (Shmatte is rag in Yiddish.)</p>
        <p>I asked the manager why he didn't teach him English words. The employee, who overheard the exchange, said, ''I thought shmatte was English.''</p>
        <p>Arthur Palgon</p>
        <p>A PRAYER</p>
        <p>''Like'' is useless.</p>
        <p>''Like'' means nothing.</p>
        <p>How can it ever be stopped?</p>
        <p>Perchance there'll be a law one day:</p>
        <p>No more ''like''; just go away.</p>
        <p>Before ''like'' came ''you know.''</p>
        <p>''You know'' was used like ''like.''</p>
        <p>In place of ''like,'' one said ''you know'';</p>
        <p>Then one day, you know, ''you know''</p>
        <p>Just up and died or went away.</p>
        <p>Before ''you know'' came ''uh.''</p>
        <p>It was ''uh, uh, uh'' all the time.</p>
        <p>No meaning, of course.</p>
        <p>Just the same, it was said</p>
        <p>Again and again and again.</p>
        <p>There will come a day, or so I pray</p>
        <p>When we all shall be able to happily say</p>
        <p>Farewell, adiós and au revoir</p>
        <p>To ''like,'' ''you know,'' and, of course ''uh.''</p>
        <p>I can hardly wait.</p>
        <p>Hamilton Hertz</p>
        <p>Nicole Arnaboldi and her family returned recently from a European vacation during which her 5-year-old son, Andrew, hearing many unfamiliar sounds, often asked what language was being spoken. When they returned, Ms. Arnaboldi took him to visit Times Square for the first time and told him it was a famous site. He listened to the crowd and looked confused. ''Mom, what language do they speak in Times Square?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Scene: R train leaving the 95th Street station in Brooklyn. A homeless woman is stretched across a row of seats.</p>
        <p>Observer: Marie Montalbano.</p>
        <p>Action: A male passenger walks by.</p>
        <p>Homeless woman: ''Mister, can you spare some change?''</p>
        <p>Man: ''Sorry, I don't have any.''</p>
        <p>Homeless woman: ''Got a cigarette?''</p>
        <p>Man: ''No, I don't smoke.''</p>
        <p>Homeless woman: ''Do you dance?''</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Roast chicken is a popular takeout dish at the Costco warehouse store in Sunset Park, Brooklyn. On a recent day, demand was so high that the huge spits couldn't keep up, and a large group of customers milled about waiting for the next batch.</p>
        <p>When the attendant started pulling the newly roasted chickens off the spit, a good-natured line formed. I was in third place and suddenly found myself being elbowed by a middle-aged, well-dressed gentleman obviously trying to edge ahead.</p>
        <p>Just as I turned to remonstrate, he stopped, threw up his hands and stammered an apology.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me,'' he said. ''When the line began to form, I suddenly thought I was back in Moscow where if you weren't among the first, you never got anything. I forgot I was in New York where there is always too much of everything.''</p>
        <p>The entire line shared a good laugh.</p>
        <p>Joanne S. Karlikow</p>
        <p>Andrea Schechter and her husband, David, were on their way to 42nd Street for an Off Broadway matinee when they stopped at Amy's Bread on 46th Street. Before they left the store the heavens opened, and the manager gave them plastic bags to put over their heads, even cutting out armholes. Although the makeshift rain gear helped somewhat, they arrived at the theater soaking wet, only to be greeted by a quick-witted employee who asked, ''Would you like to check your bags?''</p>
        <p>A LITTLE LATIN</p>
        <p>A quid</p>
        <p>is a pound sterling</p>
        <p>or something to chew</p>
        <p>early in the morning,</p>
        <p>and quiddity is what</p>
        <p>marks a thing from what it is not,</p>
        <p>and quid pro quo</p>
        <p>I'm sure you know.</p>
        <p>Ed Rossmann</p>
        <p>On her first day of jury duty in Manhattan, Beth Rosen, who is self-employed, hoped that any trial she might be selected for would not last more than two days. She was concentrating on a short story she was writing about her sister Nomi when a familiar voice intruded. She turned around and there was Nomi, at which point she began figuring the odds on being picked for jury duty on the same day as a sibling.</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Diary</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
