<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Analysts say Kent Electronics can endure any economic phase.</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="658985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KENT ELECTRONICS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">KENT ELECTRONICS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KENT ELECTRONICS CORP</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D61030F93AA15751C1A965958260" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Analysts say Kent Electronics can endure any economic phase.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert Hurtado</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SETTING recent buoyant economic news aside, many large investors recommend looking for stocks than can appreciate in almost any phase of the economy's cycle.</p>
        <p>One that seems to fit the profile, some Wall Street professionals say, is the Kent Electronics Corporation, a Houston-based distributor of electronics components. "Economic phases wax and wane, but Kent keeps chugging along," Mark Plummer, an analyst with Stephens Inc., said. Indeed, the company has reported 30 consecutive quarters of increased sales and earnings since its initial public offering in June 1986.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SETTING recent buoyant economic news aside, many large investors recommend looking for stocks than can appreciate in almost any phase of the economy's cycle.</p>
        <p>One that seems to fit the profile, some Wall Street professionals say, is the Kent Electronics Corporation, a Houston-based distributor of electronics components. "Economic phases wax and wane, but Kent keeps chugging along," Mark Plummer, an analyst with Stephens Inc., said. Indeed, the company has reported 30 consecutive quarters of increased sales and earnings since its initial public offering in June 1986.</p>
        <p>Like the rest of the industry, Kent has benefited as component makers have increased their reliance on distributors, rather than selling direct, to build market share and control costs. For instance, AMP Inc., the world's largest producer of electronic connectors, named Kent in the fall of 1992 as one of its four nationally authorized distributors.</p>
        <p>Kent has avoided the highly volatile semiconductor business and instead supplies components like resistors, capacitors and connectors -- a more stable but still growing market, analysts said. Last year, distributors sold more than $6.2 billion of these types of parts in the United States.</p>
        <p>For the year that ended on March 31, Kent had revenues of $154.7 million, with two-thirds derived from component sales and the rest from the company's growing contract-manufacturing business. In those operations, Kent provides custom-built electronic units to original equipment manufacturers in industries like telecommunications, medical devices, energy, computers and data processing.</p>
        <p>"Kent's expertise in contract manufacturing plays right into the rapidly growing outsourcing market, where equipment makers rely on outside vendors to supply assembled parts that meet specifications," Carlene Murphy, a portfolio manager for Strong/Corneliuson Capital Management, said. "Driving original equipment manufacturers to the outsourcing of engineered product systems and subsystems is the growing realization that American business must dedicate finite resources to strategic priorities, such as new product development, reduced inventory risk and improved operating efficiencies."</p>
        <p>Analysts say Kent's contract-manufacturing business has grown at an annual rate of 33 percent during the last five years and they expect yearly growth to exceed 25 percent in 1994 and 1995. Earlier this year, Kent reported that gross margins for contract manufacturing dipped slightly because of some pricing pressure, but Wall Street believes margins have settled to a range of 26 to 27 percent, compared with historic levels of 27.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Acquisitions are considered another important avenue for growth. Electronics distribution is a highly fragmented business, with about 1,500 small operators. Kent, which has a balance sheet free of debt and $27 million in cash, is considered by some market analysts to be well positioned as an acquirer. Indeed, the company has completed three acquisitions in the last six years. Each contributed immediately to earnings and increased the company's geographic reach. Since the last deal was made almost two years ago, some large investors think Kent is again on the prowl.</p>
        <p>Investor interest helped to drive the stock to a new high of $28.75 a share on Dec. 8 in New York Stock Exchange trading. It closed yesterday at $27.125 a share, up 25 cents. Without including potential acquisitions, earnings, which were $1.20 a share in the fiscal year that ended on March 31, are expected to increase to $1.45 a share in 1994 and $1.75 a share in 1995, according to a Bear, Stearns &amp; Company research report.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
