<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, Even Now, There Are Pro-Clinton C.E.O.'s</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="729351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAYNE, LESLIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DE1F30F937A35751C1A962958260" item-length="1743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, Even Now, There Are Pro-Clinton C.E.O.'s</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WAYNE, LESLIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is almost an oxymoron to combine the words "Democrat" and "chief executive officer." Yet there is a small, but hardy, band of Democratic business executives. And, despite the recent Republican sweep of Congress, they are standing by their man, President Clinton, though with some reservations and concerns.</p>
        <p>More than any other Democratic Presidential candidate in recent times, Bill Clinton in 1992 reached out to business and business responded. From bankers on Wall Street to entrepreneurs in Silicon Valley, the Clinton-Gore campaign courted executives with the message that business had nothing to fear from a Democratic Administration. This effort had many goals: To lend credibility to the Clinton campaign, to tap into the deep pockets of business and to gain votes that had traditionally gone to Republicans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is almost an oxymoron to combine the words "Democrat" and "chief executive officer." Yet there is a small, but hardy, band of Democratic business executives. And, despite the recent Republican sweep of Congress, they are standing by their man, President Clinton, though with some reservations and concerns.</p>
        <p>More than any other Democratic Presidential candidate in recent times, Bill Clinton in 1992 reached out to business and business responded. From bankers on Wall Street to entrepreneurs in Silicon Valley, the Clinton-Gore campaign courted executives with the message that business had nothing to fear from a Democratic Administration. This effort had many goals: To lend credibility to the Clinton campaign, to tap into the deep pockets of business and to gain votes that had traditionally gone to Republicans.</p>
        <p>And this effort paid off. More than 400 business leaders, nearly a third of whom were Republicans who had voted for President Bush, publicly endorsed Mr. Clinton. Now, two years and a bruising partisan setback later, feelings are softer. Many of these leaders say President Clinton has done a poor job of articulating what they claim are his many successful pro-business accomplishments -- and that the President should get that message out in a hurry.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration is given high marks for a budget bill that began to rein in the deficit, for keeping interest rates low and the economy strong, for reducing unemployment and creating jobs, for Commerce Department trade missions that have been effective in promoting the sale of American goods overseas, for backing the North American Free Trade Agreement and GATT, for reducing taxes on small business and for supporting a whole array of regulatory initiatives that have cut red tape and spurred business development.</p>
        <p>But, these business leaders say, these accomplishments have gotten little attention. "This Administration has a level of sophistication about business and many accomplishments," said Steven J. Green, chief executive of the Astrum International Corporation, which owns Samsonite luggage and Culligan water systems. "But it does a poor job of communicating what it has done well and an excellent job of communicating what it has not done well."</p>
        <p>Some in the Administration say the midterm Democratic defeat should help business -- forcing President Clinton to focus more on centrist business issues of the type typically favored by executives and by the Republican majority in Congress.</p>
        <p>"This is an opportunity for the President," said Kenneth D. Brody, a former Goldman Sachs partner and president of the Export-Import Bank. "There's an intersection with what the Republicans want and what the President wants. A lot of good things will get done. Beatings like this will have the President and his advisers focused on what the American people really want."</p>
        <p>Just last week, Felix Rohatyn, the investment banker, appeared before the National Press Club in Washington to appeal for bipartisanship and for support for Mr. Clinton from the business community. "At this time," he said, "the Clinton Administration must regain the confidence it had originally gained from the business community, and which it subsequently lost. Whatever its shortcoming, I believe that the Administration is entitled to such support as a result of its economic policies."</p>
        <p>If Democrats sniff opportunity in defeat, so do Republicans. Barbara Hackman Franklin, a former Commerce Secretary and a Republican fundraiser, said: "I'd like to see the G.O.P. capitalize on this victory and explain why business people are better off with us." As for fundraising for the Republican Party, Ms. Franklin added, "it's going to be a lot easier."</p>
        <p>What follows is a midterm assessment by several prominent executives who voted for President Clinton.  Bernard L. Schwartz Chief executive of the Loral Corporation, a New York-based military electronics manufacturer.</p>
        <p>"I'm frustrated, but not disillusioned and I've not lost heart. The President is smart enough to read the election returns. He's delivered quite a lot. But the common perception is that government doesn't work. So he's got to skinny down his agenda and focus. He's also got to get people who are a little more seasoned and a little less idealistic on his team. I'd like to see a little more gray hair at the White House.</p>
        <p>"This Administration has done a yeoman's job in helping the industrial base in a nonpartisan way. He's made good friends in the defense and aerospace industries. My advice is to stay the course -- we're only in the third or fourth inning, not the ninth. 1996? You tell me what the level of the stock market is in 1996 and the inflation rate and I'll tell you who will win." Paul A. Allaire</p>
        <p>President of the Xerox Corporation, based in Stamford, Conn.</p>
        <p>"There are a number of things Clinton has done that are positive for business. Clearly his approach to free trade is something we can feel very good about. The budget package helped produce a growing economy and created new jobs. And raising competitiveness to the forefront and acting to assure that our nation is more competitive is positive, too.</p>
        <p>"Business would like to see the President and Congress working together so we don't get gridlock. We've had business, labor and government working together well. I don't think business leaders were very strong Clinton supporters in the beginning. Even though he's done a lot of things that business would say is good, business feels negative about other things -- like health care -- and that's colored their view." Paul Montrone  Chief executive of Fisher Scientific International, a Hampton, N.H., scientific instrument supplier.</p>
        <p>"Bill Clinton has been consistently supportive of the business community. But that's not kept a lot of business people from falling by the wayside in their support of him. Why? The answer is a combination of form and the people he has surrounded himself with that deal with the business community.  [ Commerce Secretary ]  Ron Brown has been a great business ambassador. But at the White House there are not a lot of players who understand how to deal with the business community and how to build alliances. They don't know what buttons to push and a lot of business people think he is too liberal.</p>
        <p>"Bill Clinton's own thinking is pro-business. He needs to have some real solid business people close to him and follow their advice and lead. If that happens, it could possibly help in a major way. I'm hopeful." Sanford R. Robertson  Chairman, Robertson, Stephens &amp; Company, a San Francisco investment bank.</p>
        <p>"I do a lot of business in Silicon Valley and he's been very good for us. He's lowered trade barriers to high-tech companies and cut red tape. Ron Brown has been terrific. The President has done a lot of things he hasn't gotten credit for.</p>
        <p>"Business, however, was scared by health care. They saw the costs, and they didn't like the way it was handled. They saw the symbolism of big government. His support seemed to be O.K. until health care. Then it fell away fast.</p>
        <p>"He can recover. But he's got to take the middle again and he's got to get to the middle fast. Maybe he can hop on the Dole capital gains tax cut proposal. He's on the right side in opposing the proposals on the new accounting treatment for corporate stock options. But Senator Phil Gramm has picked up the flag on that. If the President succeeds, there's a chance the Republicans will get all the credit." Neil Bluhm President of the JMB Realty Corporation, a Chicago-based real estate company.</p>
        <p>"I was a supporter and still am. From a business perspective, he's done a good job. Frankly, I was surprised at the midterm elections. They can't be based on the economy because interest rates are way down and the President and his advisers were instrumental in getting that done.</p>
        <p>"I'm in real estate and it's certainly a lot better environment. When Clinton came into office, everyone felt the U.S. was a second-rate power to Japan and Europe. People don't feel that way now.</p>
        <p>"It must be that the public is fed up with big government and there are elements of the Democratic Party which are not responsive to that mood. Corporate America has downsized. It's gotten lean and mean. Now government has got to do the same and the liberal wing of the Democratic Party has got to understand that."  Steven J. Green  Chief executive of the Astrum International Corporation, a holding company based in Miami.</p>
        <p>"This Administration truly understands the global changes in the economy and has been better at promoting business abroad than any other Administration I've seen. When people voted in Bill Clinton, they said that the system didn't work and they wanted change. But Clinton hasn't given them the perception that that's happening.</p>
        <p>"The Republicans will probably get some benefit for supporting a capital gains tax cut. Every businessman earning over $200,000 a year wants it and will become a Republican supporter for it. If so, it will be difficult for the President to gain the momentum in the business community that he deserves -- especially if you look at what he's done for business.</p>
        <p>"But the President has two years. In politics, that's a long time. Clinton is the master of escape. He's capable of pulling out of a tailspin. He's wounded and knocked down. But the referee hasn't counted to 10 yet. So I wouldn't give up." Alan Patricof  Chairman of Alan Patricof &amp; Company, a New York venture capital company.</p>
        <p>"I'm an active supporter of Bill Clinton. And, from the standpoint of small business, a lot of good things have been happening. The No. 1 thing for small business is capital, and the regulators have made it easier for banks to lend and have cut paperwork. The Small Business Administration has been rejuvenated and has a new attitude -- they talk about small businesses as 'customers.' Small entrepreneurial business is now represented at cabinet meetings.</p>
        <p>"A lot has been happening that's positive. But it seems like the P.R. isn't getting out for the good stuff. That's disappointing. I'm not jumping ship. The President has the right instincts and, if he acted on them, we could have an interesting Presidency. Maybe we will begin to see government work better. That was the clear message of the midterm elections. Congress had better start working better regardless of who is in the White House."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
