<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="744282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD7123FF93AA25751C0A963958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>N.H.L.  Penguins' Streak Ends  Robert Kron scored twice, including a crucial goal late in the game, as the Hartford Whalers beat the visiting Pittsburgh Penguins, 4-2, yesterday, ending the Penguins' bid for the best start in National Hockey League history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>N.H.L.  Penguins' Streak Ends  Robert Kron scored twice, including a crucial goal late in the game, as the Hartford Whalers beat the visiting Pittsburgh Penguins, 4-2, yesterday, ending the Penguins' bid for the best start in National Hockey League history.</p>
        <p>The loss dropped the Penguins to 12-1-1, leaving them two games short of tying the best N.H.L. start, held by Edmonton, which started 12-0-3 in the 1984-85 season. (AP) CAPITALS 4, NORDIQUES 2: Craig Berube and Steve Jones scored 32 seconds apart early in the third period as Washington beat visiting Quebec last night, denying the Nordiques a chance to record a franchise-record eighth straight victory.(AP) AUTO RACING  Little Dodges Wreck  Chad Little of Spokane, Wash., dodged a wreck the way his car owner and fellow Washington State alumnus, Mark Rypien, used to dodge linebackers, and won the Goody's 300 Busch Grand National race yesterday in Daytona Beach, Fla. Little, who started 42d in a Ford Thunderbird, eased by Steve Grissom in turn four on the 117th of the 120 laps around the Daytona International Speedway.</p>
        <p>Little's front bumper was so close to the rear bumper of Grissom's Chevy Monte Carlo that it was unclear from television replays whether the two cars actually touched or Little's car upset the air coming off Grissom's rear spoiler. In either case, Grissom had to slow suddenly to keep control, and Mark Martin, following right behind in a Thunderbird, hit Grissom's car.</p>
        <p>That set off a wreck that took out most of the leaders. Michael Waltrip was able to dip below the melee in his Pontiac to finish second as the race ended under a yellow flag. Little, whose car is owned by Rypien, the former Super Bowl-winning quarterback, won $71,411. SWIMMING  New Butterfly Mark  Angela Kennedy of Australia broke one of swimming's oldest world records -- the 100-meter butterfly mark held by Mary T. Meagher -- to highlight the first day of the short-course World Cup in Gelsenkirchen, Germany. Kennedy swamped the competition by almost a full second yesterday in breaking the American swimmer's 14-year-old mark. She touched the wall in 58.77 seconds to eclipse Meagher's 58.91 set in January 1981. Mark Warnecke of Germany swam the 50-meter breast stroke in 27.00 seconds to shatter the five-year-old world mark held by Dmitri Volkov by 15-hundredths of a second. (AP) TENNIS  Graf to Face Pierce  Steffi Graf rolled to her most impressive victory in months when she beat fifth-ranked Jana Novotna, 6-3, 6-2, yesterday in the semifinals of the Paris Indoor Open. Graf's opponent in the final today will be second-seeded Mary Pierce, who beat Iva Majoli of Croatia, 6-3, 6-4.</p>
        <p>Graf lost her No. 1 ranking to Arantxa Sanchez Vicario because injuries had sidelined the German for three months. She could become No. 1 again with a victory today. It would be her first title since winning in San Diego last July. (AP) MARTIN BEATS SAMPRAS: Two match points away from victory yesterday, Pete Sampras tightened up. The world's top player won his first set, 6-4, against Todd Martin in the St. Jude Indoor tournament semifinals in Memphis. But Sampras missed two match points as Martin pulled out a 4-6, 7-6 (8-6), 6-3 victory. Martin will play Paul Haarhuis, who beat unseeded Jonathan Stark, 6-4, 7-5, last night, in today's finals. (AP) GOLF  Perry Regains Lead  Kenny Perry shot a five-under-par 67 yesterday to regain the lead after four rounds of the Bob Hope Chrysler Classic in Palm Desert, Calif.</p>
        <p>Perry, who was the first-round leader, was at 23-under 265 after 72 holes of play. Curtis Strange, David Duval, Tommy Tolles and Harry Taylor were two strokes back at 267. (AP) TRACK AND FIELD  Boys &amp; Girls Triumphs  Boys &amp; Girls of Brooklyn, scoring 41 points in the last 4 events, 3 of which it won, took the boys' team title while Prospect Heights, also of Brooklyn, captured the girls' crown for the first time yesterday in the Public Schools Athletic League indoor championships at the West 168th Street Armory.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
