<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enjoying an Occasional Buttery Indulgence of Brioche</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="744329"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FOODS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DE143EF93AA25751C0A963958260" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enjoying an Occasional Buttery Indulgence of Brioche</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOW fat is simply not an option when it comes to certain baked goods. Brioche, for example, must be buttery and eggy. And for those who believe that when it comes to diet, moderation is the best advice, an occasional indulgence is not out of place.</p>
        <p>This rich, golden brioche loaf has a bit of crunch in its texture, thanks to the addition of cornmeal. It is excellent to serve with good jam for brunch or sliced thin alongside a salad, an elegant terrine or with smoked fish or meats. Additional butter is not needed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOW fat is simply not an option when it comes to certain baked goods. Brioche, for example, must be buttery and eggy. And for those who believe that when it comes to diet, moderation is the best advice, an occasional indulgence is not out of place.</p>
        <p>This rich, golden brioche loaf has a bit of crunch in its texture, thanks to the addition of cornmeal. It is excellent to serve with good jam for brunch or sliced thin alongside a salad, an elegant terrine or with smoked fish or meats. Additional butter is not needed.</p>
        <p>And it can also be turned into a lush bread pudding studded with raisins or French toast crusted with almonds and suitable for dessert. Cornmeal Brioche Total time: 4 hours  1 packet active dry yeast  1/3 cup warm light cream  1/2 cup sugar  1/3 cup stone-ground yellow cornmeal  10 ounces butter (2 1/2sticks), softened  6 eggs  2 teaspoonssalt  5 cups flour (approximately).</p>
        <p>1. Dissolve the yeast in the warm cream in a bowl. Mix with two tablespoons of the sugar and set aside to proof for 10 minutes. When the mixture starts becoming frothy, stir in the cornmeal. Cover and set aside in a warm place for 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Meanwhile, beat the remaining sugar with the butter until fluffy, either by hand or in an electric mixer. Beat in the eggs one at a time. Stir in the cornmeal mixture and the salt.</p>
        <p>3. Beat in the flour about one half cup at a time either by hand or using an electric mixer fitted with a dough hook, to form a soft, elastic dough. The dough should be kneaded about eight minutes.</p>
        <p>4. Transfer the dough to a clean, lightly oiled bowl, cover and set aside to rise until doubled, about two hours.</p>
        <p>5. Punch the dough down, divide it in half and form each into a rectangle nine inches on one side. Roll each tightly and shape them into two oblong loaves. Butter two loaf pans, nine by five by three inches, and put the loaves into the pans, seam side down. Allow to rise until doubled, about one hour.</p>
        <p>6. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Bake about 40 minutes, until golden. Allow to cool completely before slicing.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 loaves. Brioche French Toast With Apples Total time: 1 hour  4 tablespoons butter  3 golden delicious apples, peeled, cored and sliced thick</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons sugar  1 teaspoon freshlemon juice  2 large eggs  1 1/2 cups milk  6 slices brioche, each about3/4-inch thick  1/4 cup sliced almonds  Confectioners' sugar.</p>
        <p>1. Heat two tablespoons of the butter in a heavy skillet. Add the apples and three tablespoons sugar and cook over very high heat until the apples are lightly caramelized and tender but still hold their shape. Sprinkle with lemon juice and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Beat the eggs and milk together in a shallow bowl. Add the brioche slices one at a time, leaving each in the bowl long enough to become saturated. As the slices are soaked, transfer them to a foil-lined baking pan big enough to hold them in a single layer.</p>
        <p>3. Scatter half the almonds over the slices and lightly press them in. Sprinkle with half a tablespoon of sugar.</p>
        <p>4. Melt the remaining butter in a large skillet or a griddle. Put the slices, almond-side down, in the skillet and cook over medium heat until lightly browned. While the slices are cooking, scatter the remaining almonds and sugar on them, lightly pressing the almonds in. Turn the slices when they have browned, to brown the second side.</p>
        <p>5. Serve the slices while still warm, dusted with sifted confectioners' sugar, with the apples on the side. If desired, the French toast and apples can be made in advance and reheated in a 200-degree oven.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings. Brioche Bread Pudding Total time: 2 hours  1 loaf brioche  1 cup raisins  1/4 cup warm rum  2 cups milk  2 cups heavy cream  4 eggs  2 egg yolks  1 cup sugar  Pinch of salt  1 teaspoon vanilla extract  Butter for the baking dish  1 teaspoon cinnamon.</p>
        <p>1. Slice the brioche half an inch thick and lightly toast the slices. Set aside. Put the raisins in a bowl, cover with the rum and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Combine the milk and cream in a saucepan and scald.</p>
        <p>3. Beat eggs and yolks with sugar. Add vanilla and salt. Slowly whisk in warm milk and cream mixture.</p>
        <p>4. Butter a glass baking dish.</p>
        <p>5. Cut each slice of brioche in half and line the bottom of the baking dish with the slices, overlapping them slightly. Scatter half the raisins over the slices, then spoon on about a third of the egg mixture. Top with a second layer of slices and the remaining raisins. Pour in remaining egg mixture. Set aside for 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>6. Preheat oven to 300 degrees. Sprinkle the top of the pudding with cinnamon. Put in the oven and bake for about one hour, until the pudding is set. Serve while still warm.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.  FOODS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
