<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capturing the Playfulness of 1920's Swedish Ballet</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOUIS, MURRAY, DANCE CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D81339F931A25753C1A963958260" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capturing the Playfulness of 1920's Swedish Ballet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ballet enjoyed itself in the 1920's in Europe, and the spirit of fun ran noticeably through the Ballets Suedois, the avant-garde troupe that the Swedish  arts patron Rolf de Mare directed in Paris from 1920 to 1925.</p>
        <p>It is this playfulness that the American modern-dance choreographer Murray Louis captured so successfully in his small-scale gloss on four Ballets Suedois productions on Monday night at the John Jay College Theater. The program, "Homage to the Swedish Ballet," was performed by the Murray Louis Dance Company in the Works and Process at the Guggenheim series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ballet enjoyed itself in the 1920's in Europe, and the spirit of fun ran noticeably through the Ballets Suedois, the avant-garde troupe that the Swedish  arts patron Rolf de Mare directed in Paris from 1920 to 1925.</p>
        <p>It is this playfulness that the American modern-dance choreographer Murray Louis captured so successfully in his small-scale gloss on four Ballets Suedois productions on Monday night at the John Jay College Theater. The program, "Homage to the Swedish Ballet," was performed by the Murray Louis Dance Company in the Works and Process at the Guggenheim series.</p>
        <p>Mary Sharp Cronson, the producer, commissioned Mr. Louis on the recommendation of Bengt Hager, whose European design exhibitions about the Ballets Suedois in the 1960's and 70's revived interest in a once-forgotten company. The link is not new: Mr. Hager has often written that Alwin Nikolais, Mr. Louis's collaborator, continued the Swedish company's use of abstract form,  especially its melding of dancer and decor. Dance was only one element in these  1920's ballets: they are remembered chiefly for the French painters, poets and composers who collaborated with de Mare's Swedish choreographer, Jean Borlin.</p>
        <p>Borlin's choreography, in fact, has disappeared. But some of the music, including Darius Milhaud's jazz-influenced "Creation of the World," has entered  the international repertory. The more concrete legacy consists of the costume and set designs on view in the current exhibition, "The Swedish Ballet 1920-1925," at the Museum at the Fashion Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>Mr. Louis's starting point was these costumes, although he familiarized himself with the works. Essentially he did his own thing choreographically. He knows, however, how a mask can rule a dancer's personality. Alberto Del Saz, dancing in a weighted manner in the 1920 "Sculpture Negre," proved the point as  the African statue, designed by Paul Colin, came to life to Poulenc's music. Colin's backdrop, like the others, was seen in a slide projection.</p>
        <p>Frank Garcia, assisted by Chris Beckstrom, brilliantly recreated all the costumes. In the excerpt from the 1921 "Man and His Desires," Mr. Louis echoed the the designs of Andree Parr. He used both the curves of her moon-women, carrying red and blue disks, and the dynamic impact of her feathered forest creatures with red manes. Wisely, he did not delve into Paul Claudel's complex dream scenario, but Milhaud's Brazilian-inspired rhythms dominated.</p>
        <p>"Relache," an anti-ballet that caused an uproar in 1924, struck Mr. Louis as  a circus, and he simply transferred a set piece from one of his circus ballets,  "Hoopla," to this program. The gymnastic trio in Francis Picabia's dotted leotards fit surprisingly well with Satie's music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Louis strikingly met the Ballets Suedois esthetic on its own ground in a  passage from "Creation of the World" that featured the mix of Cubism and African art in Fernand Leger's marvelous costumes. The original three deities were reduced to an allegorical master of ceremonies. Flapping his big sleeves and moving with small steps, this rounded figure surveyed his delightful realm: monkeys with Slinkies as sleeves, insects propelled on skateboards and mobiles shaped like birds. The slats and sticks on the world's first man and woman turned their prancing duet into a percussion number. It was an ingenious touch.  The fine performers included Kay Andersen, Andreas Bjerneboe, Kimberly Gibilisco, Pamela Levy, Sharon Livardo, Miro Magloire, Susan Pajak, Trista Redavid, Ismael Rodriguez and Ted Thomas.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
