<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Old Political Order Gone, Leaders in India Vie for Power</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS,DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAO, P V NARASIMHA (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAJPAYEE, ATAL BIHARI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BASU, JYOTI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINGH, V P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURNS, JOHN F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D71539F932A25756C0A960958260" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Old Political Order Gone, Leaders in India Vie for Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURNS, JOHN F</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, May 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>India's rival political groups clamored for power today after a general election that shattered the traditional base of the Congress Party and gave new  leverage to a tumultuous assemblage of groups representing the mosaic of castes, regions and languages in this nation of 930 million people.</p>
        <p>With results nearly complete, India appeared to have crossed a watershed. The India of nearly 50 years since independence, dominated by the Congress Party except when scandals and other excesses prompted voters to punish it with two brief spells in opposition, seemed to have given way to a new, more fractious period in which the country would wear many political faces, reflecting India's  ancient diversities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>India's rival political groups clamored for power today after a general election that shattered the traditional base of the Congress Party and gave new  leverage to a tumultuous assemblage of groups representing the mosaic of castes, regions and languages in this nation of 930 million people.</p>
        <p>With results nearly complete, India appeared to have crossed a watershed. The India of nearly 50 years since independence, dominated by the Congress Party except when scandals and other excesses prompted voters to punish it with two brief spells in opposition, seemed to have given way to a new, more fractious period in which the country would wear many political faces, reflecting India's  ancient diversities.</p>
        <p>The election ended with the most fragmented Parliament in India's history, with no group coming close to a governing majority. The Congress Party lost more than half the seats it held in the last Parliament, and was left with less than  a quarter of the membership of the 545-seat Parliament.</p>
        <p>Party leaders acknowledged that it was a debacle without precedent for the 110-year-old party and one in which, in the words of Sharad Pawar, one of the party's most powerful figures, "the masses of the people have gone away from us."</p>
        <p>Two of the major gainers in the election -- the Bharatiya Janata Party, a right-wing Hindu nationalist group, and a coalition of leftist, centrist and regional parties known as the National Front-Left Front alliance -- demanded the chance to form the new government.</p>
        <p>But with both groups dozens of seats short of a majority in Parliament, the stage seemed to be set for days of bitter in-fighting, with almost as many aspirants for the Prime Minister's post as there were parties in Parliament.</p>
        <p>The resignation tonight of Prime Minister P. V. Narasimha Rao, whose aloof campaigning style came to symbolize a party that seemed out of touch with the country's mood, seemed almost like a footnote at a time of hectic maneuvering.</p>
        <p>As a disconsolate Mr. Rao presided over the last meeting of a Cabinet reduced to a rump by corruption scandals and election defeats, more than a dozen parties engaged in a round of negotiations and blandishments aimed at securing a share of the power monopolized for four decades by the Congress Party.</p>
        <p>While the Congress Party has had bad periods before, especially when it went  into the political wilderness in 1977 after Prime Minister Indira Gandhi's seizure of emergency powers, even party veterans seemed to think that there would be no quick recovery this time. Instead, the election seemed to have confirmed that Indian politics, at the national level, will take on more of the  chaotic character that has long marked politics in the country's regions, with the Nehrus and the Gandhis, the commanding figures of the past, replaced by a babel of unfamiliar voices.</p>
        <p>So complete was the Congress Party's humiliation that some of the new political satraps spoke as though even dealing with the remainder of the Congress Party in Parliament was an unsavory experience.</p>
        <p>"If some people come forward from the Congress, who have no charges or allegations against them, we can accept their support," said Somnath Chatterjee, a 66-year-old Communist leader from Calcutta, who was in the thick of efforts to build a coalition government around the National Front-Left Front group in the new Parliament.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chatterjee said his group wanted nothing to do with the Congress Party, as though any formal involvement of the Congress in a coalition with the  Communists and their allies might fatally taint the enterprise.</p>
        <p>The approach seemed calculated to tally with the views of many who survived the Congress rout in the elections, like Mr. Pawar, who went into a Congress Party meeting in New Delhi saying the party should resolve to stay out of power  and "re-build our rapport with the masses."</p>
        <p>At the center of the maelstrom over the formation of a new government was India's President, Shankar Dayal Sharma, a 77-year-old veteran of Congress Party governments whose position is largely ceremonial. He was faced with what Indian constitutional experts described as one of the most testing moments in the history of independent India.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharma, who was once a law teacher at Cambridge University, seemed increasingly impatient in recent months with what he is said to have viewed as Mr. Rao's foot-dragging on corruption investigations swirling around the Government. He summoned the 74-year-old Prime Minister on Thursday night to tell him that he would wait no longer than Friday evening for his resignation.</p>
        <p>As the last election results trickled in from around the country, it became clear that the 300 million voters, choosing from more than 500 parties, had produced such a finely balanced result among the three main political groups --  the Hindu nationalists, the centrist-leftist alliance and the Congress -- as well as such a spread of seats among more than 20 other splinter parties that forming anything like a stable government from among them was likely to be a sisyphean task.</p>
        <p>With results for almost all of the seats in Parliament, the Hindu nationalists held a wide lead, with the Bharatiya Janata Party and its smaller ally, the Shiv Sena, holding 185 seats, the Congress Party 134 seats, and the centrist and leftist allance 102 seats. At least another 92 seats went to parties not formally linked to any of the three main groups, and it was in contacts with the leaders of these smaller parties that the focus of the maneuvering over a new government centered.</p>
        <p>How fragmented Indian politics has become was evident from the state-by-state breakdown of the election results. The Congress Party was decimated across the country, retaining a majority of parliamentary seats in only two of India's larger states, Andhra Pradesh and Orissa. It had substantial representation in only a handful of others.</p>
        <p>The Hindu nationalists of the Bharatiya Janata Party and the Shiv Sena won 130 of their 185 seats in only four states. The alliance of centrists and leftists had similarly spotty support around the country.</p>
        <p>This left enormous leverage with the smaller parties that draw on caste affiliations, language differences and regional identification. These groups took close to half the total vote across the country. An immediate consequence was that leaders of both the Hindu nationalists and of the alliance, each seeking the splinter parties' support to form a government, stressed a readiness to decentralize political power, which has been highly concentrated since the days of British rule.</p>
        <p>Several regional leaders indicated that they would accept nothing less.</p>
        <p>"Relations between the center and the states have to be redefined," said Chandrababu Naidu, leader of a regional party in the southern state of Andhra Pradesh that controls a key bloc of 17 seats.</p>
        <p>A Hindu nationalist official, Govindacharya, who uses only one name, agreed.  "Over-centralization has been the reason for the inefficiency of government in India," he said.</p>
        <p>On early indications, the struggle for power did not seem to favor the Hindu  nationalists, who have always been anathema to the Congress Party and to many other groups that now control crucial blocs of votes. Even if the nationalists draw one or two of the larger regional parties to their side, they will still have the support of only about 220 members in the new Parliament, far short of a majority, or 273 seats. While the alliance started from a much lower number of seats, its prospects of drawing in enough coalition partners seemed brighter.</p>
        <p>Some alliance leaders were hoping that the defeat would cause a new schism in the Congress, as it did on two previous occasions, in 1969 and 1978, and that a  breakaway Congress faction might defect to the alliance.</p>
        <p>But any potential outcome seemed unlikely to produce a strong government, regardless of which parties are involved, and many Indians said they were steeling themselves for a repeat of the two previous occasions when the Congress lost elections, which were followed by governments that quickly self-destructed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
