<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nokia Shares Plunge on Sour Quarterly Earnings Report</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="849545"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FINLAND</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NOKIA OY AB</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DA1539F933A25756C0A960958260" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nokia Shares Plunge on Sour Quarterly Earnings Report</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKHOLM, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares of Nokia Oy, a Finnish telecommunications equipment maker, tumbled today after the company reported an unexpected drop in first-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>Nokia said a 70 percent decline in pretax earnings was mainly a result of "poor organization and logistics" that led to a small operating loss in the mobile phone division, which accounts for half of the company's total sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares of Nokia Oy, a Finnish telecommunications equipment maker, tumbled today after the company reported an unexpected drop in first-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>Nokia said a 70 percent decline in pretax earnings was mainly a result of "poor organization and logistics" that led to a small operating loss in the mobile phone division, which accounts for half of the company's total sales.</p>
        <p>Nokia, which competes with Ericsson A.B. of Sweden and Motorola Inc. of the  United States in the global mobile telecommunications market, is still struggling to deal with the rapid growth that goes with success, analysts said.</p>
        <p>"The loss in the mobile phone division was the big surprise," said Martti Larjo, an analyst at Merita Securities, a unit of Finland's largest bank. "I expected them to make some money there." Mr. Larjo said he would lower his 1996  forecasts by 10 to 20 percent after today's report.</p>
        <p>Nokia's pretax profit fell to 399 million markkaa, or $84.4 million, from 1.35 billion markkaa in the quarter a year earlier. The company also repeated its warning that first-half profit this year would be "significantly lower" than the first half of last year.</p>
        <p>On the Helsinki Stock Exchange, Nokia shares plunged 20 percent before recovering to end at 165 markkaa, down 9 markkaa, or 5.2 percent.  Its American  depository receipts, each representing one "A" share in Finland, fell 12.5 cents, to $37.125, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Shares of Nokia, once a favorite of international fund managers, are down 50  percent since September, when the company's problems first came to light.</p>
        <p>Nokia's mobile phone division was hit by weak demand in Europe and the United States and lower prices. The company did not say what the division's operating loss was.</p>
        <p>The company said it hoped to sort out the internal problems in its mobile phone business in the second half. The problems involve everything from delivery glitches to being forced to use components that were purchased long ago at higher prices.</p>
        <p>"The concern now is if Nokia can turn the mobile phone division into profit again and the big question really is when," Mr. Larjo, the analyst with Merita Sercurities, said.</p>
        <p>Jorma Ollila, chief executive of Nokia, said, "Our outlook for the second half is positive, but, as always, actual performance will depend on a variety of external factors." The mobile telephone division will "gradually improve from the first quarter," he said.</p>
        <p>Nokia's announcement came a day after Ericsson showed strong growth. Ericsson said sales for its radio telecommunications division, which covers both cellular systems and phones, rose 36 percent in the most recent quarter as total pretax profit rose 28 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
