<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Becomes a Part of Celebrating Marconi's Achievements</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="719957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVENTIONS AND INVENTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAM RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HIGHLANDS (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCONI, GUGLIELMO (1874-1937)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRAGA, GIOIA MARCONI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMIN, ARTHUR Z</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFD81E3CF930A15753C1A962958260" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Becomes a Part of Celebrating Marconi's Achievements</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ARTHUR Z. KAMIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMIN, ARTHUR Z</byline>
      <dateline>HIGHLANDS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY is once again taking its turn on the world stage this year.</p>
        <p>This time, along with Bologna, Italy, as academics, scientists, historians, corporate leaders and a small army of amateur radio operators home in on Guglielmo Marconi in this 100th anniversary of the inventor's initial experiments with electromagnetic waves and the 95th anniversary of the first practical demonstration, from this shore town to Manhattan, of wireless telegraphy in America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY is once again taking its turn on the world stage this year.</p>
        <p>This time, along with Bologna, Italy, as academics, scientists, historians, corporate leaders and a small army of amateur radio operators home in on Guglielmo Marconi in this 100th anniversary of the inventor's initial experiments with electromagnetic waves and the 95th anniversary of the first practical demonstration, from this shore town to Manhattan, of wireless telegraphy in America.</p>
        <p>The ham radio enthusiasts gathered Sept. 10 and 11 in a special ceremony encampment atop a hill 200 feet above sea level here, where Marconi made history. They erected a duplicate of his original antenna and then honored the man who made it possible for them to send their voice messages and their code signals to operators all over the globe.</p>
        <p>"This is our way of saying thanks to Marconi," said Ira Goldstein of Lakewood, president of the 138-member Ocean-Monmouth Amateur Radio Club. "His inventions changed the world."</p>
        <p>As he spoke, his radio operators were announcing that their "special event station," with the call letters WA2TSM, was on the airwaves and that it had been set up in Highlands to commemorate the first commercial use of radio by Mr. Marconi. They were bringing in responses from hams all over the country and from Europe and South America and South Africa.</p>
        <p>"Everybody wants to be a part of this event," Mr. Goldstein, AA2RZ, said. Hams address their colleagues by their call letters -- not their names.</p>
        <p>"This whole thing is extraordinary," said Dr. William F. Baker, the vice president of WNET/Thirteen, the public television station, visiting here for the first time. "What a treasure for New Jersey."</p>
        <p>An amateur radio operator with the call letters KA1WEG, Mr. Baker looked out on the crystal clear day across the water at the World Trade Center in New York City where the Channel 13 antenna is situated and exclaimed: "My God, these are our roots. This is our history. Marconi changed the way we communicate in the world."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Dr. Enrique Marcatili of Rumson, recently retired from AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories in Holmdel and a pioneer in optical fiber research, delivered a major address Sept. 24 in Cesena, Italy, at a conference sponsored by the Guglielmo Marconi Foundation near the University of Bologna.</p>
        <p>"It is a great honor to deliver a paper at this meeting," he said. It all started with Marconi in Bologna, his birthplace."</p>
        <p>And, as significant as many regard 1994 in the commemorative chronology of Marconi's achievements, an even greater effort is being planned for 1995 -- 100 years after he succeeded in his first experiment in transmitting a signal via electromagnetic waves in Bologna.</p>
        <p>Several New Jerseyans -- including Marconi's daughter, Gioia Marconi Braga of Alpine -- will play major roles in next year's event to celebrate the first centenary of the invention of radio.</p>
        <p>She is the chairwoman of the Marconi International Fellowship Council founded 20 years ago to commemorate his contributions to scientific invention, engineering and technology. It now awards a $100,000 grant once a year to an individual who has made a "significant contribution" to the advancement of the technology of communications.</p>
        <p>Two of the winners are from the New Jersey. In 1987, the award was presented in Washington to Dr. Robert W. Lucky of Fair Haven, now the vice president for applied research with Bellcore, the Bell Communications research arm in Lincroft. In 1992, Dr. James L. Flanagan of Warren Township received the award in Madrid. He is now the vice president of research at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p>The recipient in 1979 was Dr. John R. Pierce, then of the California Institute of Technology who had been with AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories at Murray Hill and at Holmdel. Dr. Pierce had lived in Berkeley Heights and now lives in Palo Alto, Calif. His award was presented in Rome, Italy.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Braga, who has lived in Alpine 40 years, said the Marconi International Fellowship Council had an endowment of about $3 million and her goal was to raise it to $4 million. "When you think that we started from scratch, it is quite a feat," she said.</p>
        <p>The fellowship is administered by the Polytechnic University in Brooklyn. One of the council members is from New Jersey -- Dr. William O. Baker of New Vernon, the retired chairman of AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories at Murray Hill. He said the award was the top honor worldwide in radio and telecommunications.</p>
        <p>A key event will be the presentation on June 22 of the 21st Marconi award by the president of Italy at a formal ceremony in Bologna. Dr. Lucky is chairman of the selection committee. The first fellowship recipient was Dr. James R. Killian Jr., who had been the president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>Still, it was in New Jersey -- and it is not generally known -- where many of Marconi's engineering and entrepreneurial enterprises began to take shape not only at the state's Twin Lights historic site in this tiny borough, overlooking Raritan and Sandy Hook Bays, the New York City skyline and the Atlantic Ocean, but in such areas of the state as Belmar, Wall Township and New Brunswick.</p>
        <p>According to a Twin Lights plaque, the first use of wireless telegraphy came on Sept. 30, 1899 to receive reports from the steamship Ponce on the progress of the Hudson River naval review planned by President Theodore Roosevelt to salute the triumphant return from the Philippines of Commodore George Dewey, the victor of Manila Bay.</p>
        <p>Then on Oct. 16, 1899, the same wireless apparatus was used to gather information on the America's Cup races between the Shamrock and the Columbia. Marconi had been invited to America by James Gordon Bennett, the publisher of The New York Herald, who wanted his newspaper to get the America's Cup results ahead of the opposition newspapers.</p>
        <p>Twin Lights came into being in 1828 as the Neversink Light Station, a safety beacon for ocean-going ships and its distinctive towers became a Monmouth County landmark. Thomas A. Laverty, the Twin Lights curator, said the site attracted about 80,000 visitors a year. This year, because of the Marconi anniversaries, the number has increased with the museum and its duplicate of a wireless telegraph and other memorabilia as attractions.</p>
        <p>And the recording that is played at the audiovisual station near the site where Marconi's 1899 receiving mast was in place -- was written and is narrated by Mrs. Braga. "That was one of my greatest joys," she said. She is a frequent Twin Lights visitor.</p>
        <p>And a link has been established between Marconi and New Jersey's most notable inventor, Thomas A. Edison, in West Orange, said to Dr. Lisa Gitelman, an assistant editor of the Edison Papers project at Rutgers University. One of Edison's patents drew the attention of Marconi, she said, and eventually he became one of Marconi's technical advisers and also received stock in the Marconi wireless telegraph company.</p>
        <p>There is no confirmation that Edison and Marconi ever met, but Mrs. Braga has written about the two inventors. She quotes Edison as saying about her father: "I would like to meet the young man who had the monumental audacity to attempt and succeed in jumping an electrical wave across the Atlantic."</p>
        <p>Marconi died in Rome in 1937. He had already produced the first trans-Atlantic wireless signal in history in 1901 from Poldhu, Cornwall, England to St. John's in Newfoundland. He shared the 1909 Nobel Prize in Physics for the development of wireless telegraphy. And, during that period, the wireless telegraph was required on all seagoing ships. According to historians, that equipment was responsible for saving many lives at sea, including the 705 survivors of the Titantic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
