<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When a Copy-Machine Jockey Longs for Something More</title>
    <meta content="22MAN.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/22/movies/22man.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1666668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Furtado, Jorge</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramos, Lazaro</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Man Who Copied, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Man Who Copied, The (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDB1731F931A15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When a Copy-Machine Jockey Longs for Something More</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When a Copy-Machine Jockey Longs for Something More</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie The Man Who Copied, written and directed by Jorge Furtado and starring Lazaro Ramos; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until it makes a screeching hairpin turn from social realism into noirish fantasy, Jorge Furtado's film ''The Man Who Copied'' appears to be a sober kitchen-sink portrait of working-class life in the southern Brazilian city of Porto Alegre. As its 20-year-old narrator, André (Lázaro Ramos), who lives with his mother, describes his daily routine as a photocopier, you realize sadly that he is one of millions of bright, frustrated young Latin Americans looking at a dead-end future.</p>
        <p>André's dry-eyed analysis of his financial predicament offers a detailed dollars-and-cents picture of an existence one step above poverty. A major obstacle to a brighter future was his expulsion from high school after he hit a fellow student over the head with a bottle. Since then, his education has been reduced to retaining scraps of knowledge from the documents he copies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until it makes a hairpin turn from social realism into noirish fantasy, Jorge Furtado's film appears to be a sober kitchen-sink portrait of working-class life in Brazil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until it makes a screeching hairpin turn from social realism into noirish fantasy, Jorge Furtado's film ''The Man Who Copied'' appears to be a sober kitchen-sink portrait of working-class life in the southern Brazilian city of Porto Alegre. As its 20-year-old narrator, André (Lázaro Ramos), who lives with his mother, describes his daily routine as a photocopier, you realize sadly that he is one of millions of bright, frustrated young Latin Americans looking at a dead-end future.</p>
        <p>André's dry-eyed analysis of his financial predicament offers a detailed dollars-and-cents picture of an existence one step above poverty. A major obstacle to a brighter future was his expulsion from high school after he hit a fellow student over the head with a bottle. Since then, his education has been reduced to retaining scraps of knowledge from the documents he copies.</p>
        <p>For André to succeed with women, he needs enough money to go on dates, which his budget prohibits. His curvaceous co-worker, Marinês (Luana Piovani), a constant temptation, remains tauntingly out of reach. A technical virgin, keenly aware of her marketable assets, she is the first to admit that she is holding out for a rich husband.</p>
        <p>One of André's only luxuries is a pair of binoculars he uses to study the residents of the opposite building, and he develops a crush on a young woman he spies on nightly. When he finally meets this secret love, Sílvia (Leandra Leal), in a women's clothing store where she works as an assistant, she appears to be a shy, girlish creature even more naïve and fumbling than he. As their cautious friendship develops, she reveals a literary streak and knowledgeably quotes Shakespeare; André, who fancies himself a cartoonist, in turn draws a picture of her.</p>
        <p>What seems to be a modest little movie turns inside out the moment André decides to counterfeit a $50 bill and, in the most suspenseful sequence, succeeds in changing it at a lottery. The temptation to go for broke proves irresistible. And with Cardoso (Pedro Cardoso), a casual acquaintance who pines after Marinês like a puppy dog but can't afford her, he plunges into counterfeiting, then into bank robbery, violence and homicide.</p>
        <p>The movie never recovers from its jarring turn into a rushed, unconvincing caper movie with a blasé, Robin Hood attitude. André, Sílvia, Marinês and Cardoso become a criminal band of four, intoxicated by cash, which seems to rain from the heavens into their laps. Sweet, shy Sílvia reveals a scheming dark side that is only a shade lighter than that of Barbara Stanwyck in ''Double Indemnity.''</p>
        <p>Marinês and Cardoso, meanwhile, prove even more crass than we suspected, as they embark on an epic shopping spree. André, almost overnight, reveals himself a sophisticated criminal strategist and master escape artist.</p>
        <p>A deeply cynical movie, ''The Man Who Copied'' blares out the message that wealth and happiness are not only synonymous but also worth pursuing with every last ounce of effort, letting nothing stand in the way.</p>
        <p>The Man Who Copied  Opens today in New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Written (in Portuguese, with English subtitles) and directed by Jorge Furtado; director of photography, Alex Sernambi; edited by Giba Assis Brasil; music by Leo Henkin; art director, Fiapo Barth; produced by Nora Goulart and Luciana Tomasi; released by TLA Releasing. At the Quad Cinema, 34 West 13th Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 124 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Lázaro Ramos (André), Luana Piovani (Marinês), Leandra Leal (Sílvia) and Pedro Cardoso (Cardoso).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
