<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Surge, But Investors Remain Cautious</title>
    <meta content="22STOX$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/22/business/22stox.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1666809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dash, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE3DD1431F931A15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Surge, But Investors Remain Cautious</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Stocks Surge, but Investors Remain Cautious</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC DASH and JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan; Dash, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stocks surge, but investors remain cautious; Dow Jones industrial average gains 206.24 points, or 2.1 percent, to close at 10,218.60; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index is up 22.45 points, or 2 percent, to 1,159.95; Nasdaq composite index surges 48.65 points, or 2.5 percent, to 1,962.41; three market measures reamin down 4.3 percent or more for year; graphs; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mimi Rauschelbach, a retired businesswoman from Phoenix, says she is confident about the strength of the American economy. But that is not translating, as it often does, into confidence in the stock market.</p>
        <p>Like thousands of individual investors across the country, she has become more cautious than she was in years past about investing in stocks. And it may not make much difference that the stock market's main measures had their best day of the year yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even with Thursday's rally, the market has yet to recover from last week, the worst for the market since August.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mimi Rauschelbach, a retired businesswoman from Phoenix, says she is confident about the strength of the American economy. But that is not translating, as it often does, into confidence in the stock market.</p>
        <p>Like thousands of individual investors across the country, she has become more cautious than she was in years past about investing in stocks. And it may not make much difference that the stock market's main measures had their best day of the year yesterday.</p>
        <p>Bolstered by signs of corporate profit growth, investors made up for a sharp downturn on Wednesday, when stocks fell to their lows for the year. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 206.24 points yesterday, or 2.1 percent, to close at 10,218.60. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gained 22.45 points, or 2 percent, to 1,159.95. For the two benchmarks, it was the biggest daily gain since October 2003.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index surged 48.65 points, or 2.5 percent, to 1,962.41, its best one-day gain since last March. Google said after the market closed that its earnings beat forecasts by 40 percent, a report that could help propel stocks higher today.</p>
        <p>Still, all three market measures remain down 4.3 percent or more for the year. Individual investors are weathering one of the more trying times in the market since the early months of 2003, just before stocks rallied to end the three-year market plunge after the equity bubble burst in 2000.</p>
        <p>One consequence is a sudden jump in market volatility, something that can frighten investors. In just the last seven trading days, the S.&amp;P. 500 has had daily moves of 1 percent or more in either direction five times. In the 69 other trading days this year, there were only 6 days when the index moved 1 percent or more.</p>
        <p>It appears, based on data on the flow of money in and out of mutual funds, that many investors have recently decided that they have had enough of stocks. In the first three weeks of April, there was a net outflow of $147 million from domestic stock mutual funds, according to AMG Data Services. That net outflow comes after inflows of $3.5 billion in January, $9.3 billion in February and $5.9 billion in March.</p>
        <p>For investors like Mrs. Rauschelbach there is not the blind faith in, nor the blind betting on, certain sectors that was rampant at the end of the 1990's. She is making her investment decisions more thoughtfully than she did before.</p>
        <p>''I try to buy more carefully,'' said Mrs. Rauschelbach, who is in her early 60's. Mrs. Rauschelbach and her husband live on the income from their retirement nest egg. ''They talk about a stock pickers' market; I think that is absolutely the case.''</p>
        <p>Several recent surveys suggest investors are less positive about economic growth and the stock market than they were at the start of the year. According to the UBS index of investor optimism, which was released in March, sentiment about the economy dipped to the same level it was in October, the lowest it had been since June 2003, on worries of permanently higher gas prices. About 77 percent of investors last month said gas prices would rise permanently, compared with 54 percent in May 2004.</p>
        <p>Investors still have ''concern when you talk about the stock market,'' said Kenneth S. Janke, chairman of the National Association of Investors Corporation, an umbrella organization for investors and investment clubs. ''If they see any kind of bad news, whether its predictable or not, they take that as a sign to sell.''</p>
        <p>Tobias M. Levkovich, chief United States equity strategist at Citigroup, said, ''We are certainly at heightened levels of anxiety.'' Based on recent visits to many big institutional investors, he said ''they are afraid to buy into this market; they don't know where the bottom is.''</p>
        <p>Even with yesterday's rally, the market has yet to recover from last week, the worst for the market since August. And adding to the worries of slower-than-expected economic growth that suddenly appeared last week, the government reported Wednesday that inflation jumped sharply in March and is running at a 3 percent annual rate at the consumer level.</p>
        <p>Federal Reserve policy makers, who meet next on May 3, are expected to keep raising their short-term interest rate benchmark, especially if inflation pressures persist. But if those rate increases come while the economy is slowing, the effect on economic growth and corporate earnings could be more than the stock market could take.</p>
        <p>Investors like Mrs. Rauschelbach find that their heads tell them to stick with stocks because the economy is doing well while their stomachs tell them that the days of peppy economic growth may be coming to a close because of near-record oil and gasoline prices and the prospect of high interest rates in the months ahead. And for her, there is so little to choose from.</p>
        <p>''Technology stocks aren't a good place anymore,'' she said. Oil stocks, she added, have run up and ''are no longer a good place.''</p>
        <p>''Pharmaceuticals were great growth stocks and now we really don't want them anymore.'' And, she lamented, ''real estate values are out of sight.''</p>
        <p>Alex Ring, a 20-year-old finance major at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, said that the recent market plunge has made him bearish on the market even though he has about $15,000 invested.</p>
        <p>''There are opportunities in individual stocks, but in the market as a whole, I am more uncertain,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said he planned to continue to take short positions in the Nasdaq exchange-traded fund he owns through an online broker for at least the next month, betting that its price will go down. By taking a short position -- borrowing to sell something now -- an investor can profit if that security or index falls and he or she buys it back later.</p>
        <p>But while not betting on the overall market, Mr. Ring is still willing to take a narrower bet on a stock sector he likes. In this case that is oil and gas companies, through index funds like iShares Goldman Sachs Natural Resources fund. Some investors still want to stay the course, however.</p>
        <p>''Economic reports come and go and investor sentiment changes as quickly as the wind on an Oklahoma plain,'' said Jake Dollarhide, chief of the Longbow Asset Management Company in Tulsa, Okla.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dollarhide understands why many investors are so worried. ''Whenever the market has a very bad day or an extended period of days we see triple-digit declines, it's human nature to get out. It's human nature to panic.''</p>
        <p>Joseph N. Craig, 58, of Ellicott City, Md., finds the recent decline less unnerving because he sees it as an opportunity. ''This might be a real good time to be looking for bargains rather than abandoning the market,'' he said. ''I tend to hope or think that when the headlines say doom and gloom, it is time to back up the truck and go shopping.''</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
