<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Accreditation To Bring Athletics Closer to Academics</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="447122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCREDITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN ASSOCIATION OF COLLEGES AND SCHOOLS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accreditation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DC1E3EF932A15756C0A967958260" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Accreditation To Bring Athletics Closer to Academics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The battle for control over intercollegiate athletics has taken a significant turn with a proposal by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools to deny accreditation for colleges at which athletic programs fail to meet certain guidelines.</p>
        <p>On paper, the proposal represents a compelling alternative to the National Collegiate Athletic Association's practice of applying sanctions, like loss of scholarships or television revenue, to members who break the rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The battle for control over intercollegiate athletics has taken a significant turn with a proposal by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools to deny accreditation for colleges at which athletic programs fail to meet certain guidelines.</p>
        <p>On paper, the proposal represents a compelling alternative to the National Collegiate Athletic Association's practice of applying sanctions, like loss of scholarships or television revenue, to members who break the rules.</p>
        <p>"The penalties are only directed toward the athletic programs, meanwhile the educational enterprise in the institution goes unchallenged," said Ernest L. Boyer, president of the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.</p>
        <p>"What we're talking about here is compromising, not the rules of the athletic game. We're talking about compromising the education integrity of the institutions, and the only one monitoring that are the accrediting agencies. They're the ones who should start blowing the whistle." Forces Presidents to Action</p>
        <p>The Southern association's recommendation digs at the university's foundation by threatening to remove a credential that affects the entire university and student body. Thus, the proposed measure forces university presidents to define clearly the role and mission of intercollegiate athletics.</p>
        <p>"There was a feeling on the part of the commission that we have a problem out there," said Dr. James T. Rogers, executive director of the Southern association. "We feel an obligation to do something, we'd rather deal with the problem ourselves rather than wait for outside agencies to move in and control college athletics."</p>
        <p>If that sounds familiar it's because Richard Schultz, the executive director of the N.C.A.A, uses the same rationale to protest outside interference in his enterprise. In fact, with the Southern association entry, accrediting bodies and the N.C.A.A. are potential allies.</p>
        <p>The accreditation bodies and the N.C.A.A. share many of the same constituents as well as a shared goal. The institutions want to keep Government out of their business, while the N.C.A.A. desperately wants to keep politicians out of intercollegiate athletics.</p>
        <p>As the gap between academics and athletics widens, it has become increasingly apparent to academic groups like the Southern association that the N.C.A.A. is not equipped -- or inclined -- to balance its athletic interests with its academic responsibilities. The N.C.A.A. is first and foremost an athletic organization.</p>
        <p>There are a number of problems, however, with the Southern association's proposal. The association is only one of six major accrediting agencies in the country, and it seems unlikely that all of the others will follow suit.</p>
        <p>"They may need it more because they have more powerhouse schools in sports than we do," said Howard Simmons, the executive director of the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools, which has jurisdictions over institutions from New York to Washington. "I think this will cause other accrediting bodies to stop and take a look, but in this region, we don't see it as something that needs to be added."</p>
        <p>But in fact, the Middle States association has had its share of problems. In 1986, investigations at Maryland after the death after Len Bias from cocaine intoxication revealed widespread academic and admissions irregularities involving the basketball program.</p>
        <p>Also Syracuse is undergoing an internal investigation that was triggered after a series of newspaper articles alleged widespread wrongdoing in the basketball program.</p>
        <p>Threatening to deny accreditation is one thing; taking it away is something else, and in that respect, the accrediting group and the N.C.A.A. are once again shrewd allies. The accrediting body, whose voting representatives are college presidents, is not interested in taking away accreditation, particularly from a major institution. The N.C.A.A., which historically has been run by athletic directors, is not interested in seeing its flagship programs placed on probation.</p>
        <p>"One would have a right to be skeptical," said Boyer, a former United States commissioner of education, "because it's only one of the six involved. To be blunt about it, the record of accrediting bodies moving in against the big institutions for almost any violation is very limited.</p>
        <p>"The accrediting agencies can blow the whistle on small and weak institutions. But when it comes to holding hostage big institutions in the region, that's a different story."  Intermediate Sanctions</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, there are intermediate steps the accrediting body could take short of stripping an institution of its certification. One step, deferral of recognition, would require a school to meet certain conditions before its certification is renewed. And it could lead to frequent on-site inspections if a college or university athletic department is implicated in wrongdoing. If the inspection teams determine that the situation has not improved, the accrediting body can then issue a warning that it intends to withdraw accreditation within a specified period of time.</p>
        <p>In fact, Schultz realizes that the most serious threat to the N.C.A.A.'s autonomy is not an accrediting agency, but state legislatures, which are trying to chip away at the N.C.A.A.'s power, particularly at its investigative arm.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
