<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prime Minister of Romania Steps Down</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="476515"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BUCHAREST (ROMANIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROMAN, PETRE (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ILIESCU, ION (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania/Bucharest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D81F38F934A1575AC0A967958260" item-length="652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prime Minister of Romania Steps Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>BUCHAREST, Romania, Sept. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Petre Roman announced his resignation today in the face of violent street protests. But riots in the capital continued unabated, with demonstrators insisting that the President step down as well.</p>
        <p>The violence, which began on Wednesday when thousands of miners descended on Bucharest to demand higher pay and better working conditions, has left at least 3 people dead and 137 injured.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Petre Roman announced his resignation today in the face of violent street protests. But riots in the capital continued unabated, with demonstrators insisting that the President step down as well.</p>
        <p>The violence, which began on Wednesday when thousands of miners descended on Bucharest to demand higher pay and better working conditions, has left at least 3 people dead and 137 injured.</p>
        <p>"I've come to the conclusion that we have to come to a political solution that will stop the violence, which endangers democracy," Prime Minister Roman said in a statement of resignation broadcast on Bucharest radio. 'To Protect Democracy'</p>
        <p>But Mr. Roman added that the governing National Salvation Front would continue "to protect democracy" until a new government was formed by the Parliament. His remarks left doubt among many citizens that the front, whose membership includes many members of the former Communist bureaucracy, intends to loosen its hold on power.</p>
        <p>President Ion Iliescu accepted Mr. Roman's resignation and said that talks would soon begin on forming a coalition government of "national openness."</p>
        <p>But chants of "Down With Iliescu!" rang through the heart of Bucharest as thousands of miners and local residents descended on Victory Square for a second day. Clashes Throughout City</p>
        <p>The unrest spread through the city, with protesters clashing with the army and police forces in University Square and in front of the national television broadcast center.</p>
        <p>Romanian radio reported that hundreds of rioters stormed the Parliament building, smashing the chamber. The security forces responded with tear gas.</p>
        <p>Like many other post-Communist governments in Eastern Europe, the Romanian leadership is facing growing popular discontent over its drive toward a free-market economy. Prices and unemployment are soaring as the Government loosens central controls and shuts down outmoded state enterprises.  Meeting With Iliescu</p>
        <p>A group of miners met with President Iliescu early in the day and were told all their demands would be met, the radio said. Nevertheless, street clashes continued into the night.</p>
        <p>The miners had added the resignation of the Government to their demands after Prime Minister Roman and President Iliescu refused to meet with them on Wednesday. They continued to call for the President's resignation despite the announcement that the Prime Minister would step down.</p>
        <p>The miners' opposition to the National Salvation Front marks a distinct change from their stance in June 1990, when they entered Bucharest at the invitation of the Government to crush pro-democracy protests. The governing front thanked the miners and promised them higher wages and living conditions, but the pledge was not kept. Trainloads of Miners</p>
        <p>Today, miners continued to arrive in Bucharest through the day after commandeering trains from the central towns of Petrosani and Tirgu Jiu.  Crowds milled in Victory Square, cheering each new group of miners that arrived. Wearing helmets and rubber boots, the miners strode through the streets carrying sticks, metal pipes, chains, rubber hoses and axes.</p>
        <p>Later the crowd tried to rush the Government building, which was encircled by army tanks. Several miners jumped on top of the tanks defending and pounded on the hatches. They were turned back by a volley of tear gas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iliescu and other leaders of the National Salvation Front took power on Dec. 22, 1989, proclaiming themselves the representatives of the popular movement that overthrew the Communist dictator Nicolae Ceaucescu. The front won national elections by a landslide in May 1990.</p>
        <p>But some factions of the Romanian press and the opposition argue that the front simply took advantage of the national revolution in December 1989 to make a grab for power, and that it held the elections quickly so the opposition would not have time to organize.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
