<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dry Climate May Have Forced Invention of Agriculture</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLE, FRANK (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCORISTON, JOY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDB1F3EF931A35757C0A967958260" item-length="2121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dry Climate May Have Forced Invention of Agriculture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SMALL step for a man, a giant leap for mankind: that's the phrase grandly applied to the first moon landing. But it suits even better an event whose outlines are emerging ever more clearly from the mists of prehistory: the discovery that wild grasses could be deliberately planted, cultivated and harvested as cereals.</p>
        <p>That step opened the way to an unprecedented expansion of food supplies and of human population that, in turn, made cities and civilization possible. Archeologists in recent years have narrowed their search for the origins of agriculture in the Near East, and a provocative new theory seeks to explain with some precision where and when this epochal event took place and what caused it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SMALL step for a man, a giant leap for mankind: that's the phrase grandly applied to the first moon landing. But it suits even better an event whose outlines are emerging ever more clearly from the mists of prehistory: the discovery that wild grasses could be deliberately planted, cultivated and harvested as cereals.</p>
        <p>That step opened the way to an unprecedented expansion of food supplies and of human population that, in turn, made cities and civilization possible. Archeologists in recent years have narrowed their search for the origins of agriculture in the Near East, and a provocative new theory seeks to explain with some precision where and when this epochal event took place and what caused it.</p>
        <p>The earliest archeological sites with evidence of domesticated grain lie in the southern Levant, at the north end of the Dead Sea, and date to about 10,000 years ago. Long before that, people in the region had gathered and eaten wild grain. Scientists now believe they have pinpointed the transition from wild to domesticated cereals to an area within 50 to 100 miles of the Dead Sea, just before 10,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Why was this time and place the site for one of the most revolutionary events -- along with the first use of fire -- in human prehistory?</p>
        <p>A new thesis draws on recent findings about the ancient climate, vegetation and cultures of the region to explain why its peoples were driven to invent agriculture. According to Dr. Frank Hole and Joy McCorriston, both of Yale University, the planting of grasses as food crops began as a response to two grave challenges that often intervene in human history: climatic change and overexploitation of natural resources.</p>
        <p>Their study focused on people belonging to the Natufian culture, named after an archeological site in the Judean hills known as Wadi-al-Natuf. The Natufians just preceded the time span at which domesticated plants begin to appear in the archeological record, and the Yale archeologists believe they were the probable inventors of agriculture in the Near East.</p>
        <p>Unlike previous humans, nomads who gathered only intermittently in fixed settlements, Natufians gradually adopted the settled life as a permanent one. They had well-built houses and a sophisticated social structure, as suggested by the seashell badges of rank they wore. The presence in their settlements of many feet of falcons, birds not good to eat, suggests the Natufians used the feathers for decoration. They hunted gazelles and deer for food. Seeds recovered by archeologists are evidence they also ate wild wheat and barley. They had flint sickles and stone mortars and pestles to harvest and process grains, products of millions of years of slow technological development. The Natufians, in short, possessed both the technology to process wild grains and the social organization to store and distribute them.</p>
        <p>Starting around 12,000 years ago, according to the Hole-McCorriston theory, the summertime climate in the Jordan Valley region became much hotter and extremely arid, and the Natufians' environment came under severe stress. The small lakes on which they depended for water dried up, compelling a retreat to larger lakes in the Dead Sea region. The swelling crowds of migrants caused summertime food shortages. At the same time, the intense summertime drought reduced the habitats of wild game and cut the growing season short.</p>
        <p>But the transformed climate, say Ms. McCorriston and Dr. Hole, also presented a solution: it favored annual species of wild grains and legumes, which completed their life cycle in late spring, at the expense of perennials. The large seeds of the annuals, protected inside their husks, survived the killing drought of summer to germinate in the wet, cool winters of the growing season. In this way they flourished and proliferated. By dropping seeds every year, the annuals also lent themselves to manipulation by humans who could store and distribute their seeds. 'People Are Ready'</p>
        <p>Given all these preconditions, the Yale archeologists suggest, it was only a short, logical step for the Natufians to switch from passive dependence on wild grass harvests to the practice of saving seeds, planting them in the next wet season and reaping enough food to last through the following dry summer.</p>
        <p>The scenario represents "a convergence of some historical accidents," said Dr. Hole: "People are ready. They have technology adapted to plant foods. The plants themselves are proliferating. And the climate requires people to overcome long periods when foods are not available." Such a convergence of available wild grains, technology, social organization and need have been found nowhere else at an earlier date, he said.</p>
        <p>The analysis by Ms. McCorriston and Dr. Hole, which appears in the current issue of the journal American Anthropology, is the latest published attempt at a synthesis of recent research. The Natufians' achievement, say the scientists, enabled them and future humans to maintain a stable, year-round food supply that could easily be expanded, by planting new fields, as population increased.</p>
        <p>While the Natufians "probably eased into it," Dr. Hole said, "we can pinpoint a moment in archeological time when this all happened. The change is manifest in changes we see in the seeds themselves."</p>
        <p>The carbonized remains of domesticated grains have indeed been recovered by archeologists from settlements inhabited by the Natufians' immediate successors. These neolithic agriculturalists were direct biological descendants of the Natufians, differing from them only in that some of their tools were more advanced. Archeologists can tell domesticated remains from wild ones because they have different shapes and characteristics. The domesticated form of the wild einkorn wheat that was abundant in the region, for instance, has a fatter grain that adheres to the stem more readily when ripe.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hole and Ms. McCorriston say they believe the first domestication occurred a few hundred years earlier than the earliest carbonized seeds found so far. So far, no domesticated plant remains have been turned up in Natufian archeological sites. "We are still looking for the smoking gun," said Dr. Hole. The earlier date is set, they suggest, by a unique convergence of climatic and ecological changes that occurred at that time.  Telltale Leathery Leaves</p>
        <p>Dr. Hole, an archeologist, and Ms. McCorriston, an archeobotanist and doctoral student who specializes in the ancient flora of the Near East, believe they have come up with an important ecological part of the puzzle, one that may enable the other parts to be put into place.</p>
        <p>They note that cores of ancient sediment drawn from lake bottoms portray the invasion of a particular mixture of trees and plants during the drier summers of the Natufian period. This group of "mediterranean" plants had generally leathery leaves, adapted to the dry climate and included such species as pistachio, olive, cedar, juniper, myrtle and some species of pine and oak. Scientists have traced the southwest-to-northeast advances of these plants across the Levant as climatic change worked its way generally northward.</p>
        <p>The spread of annual grasses generally accompanies the mediterranean plants, Dr. Hole and Ms. McCorriston say. This climate-induced change in vegetation seems to have occured just at the time when the Natufians' summertime supply of wild foods was being threatened by heat and drought -- and by the humans' own need to support the denser settlements that grew up around the few remaining freshwater lakes.</p>
        <p>But what induced the Natufians to select within the genetic variety of wild grains those strains that led to the domesticated version? In the Yale archeologists' reconstruction, this pivotal step may have happened as a matter of convenience, whether consciously or otherwise.</p>
        <p>The stalks of most of the individual wild annual grain plants became brittle on ripening and the seeds would scatter when plucked, making it hard to harvest them. But occasional mutant plants, Ms. McCorriston says, had tougher connections between stalk and seed and would have been easier to harvest. More of these mutants were likely to make it back to the village without losing their seeds, and hence their seeds were more likely to be planted. Their proportions would increase with each planting until they completely dominated the crop.</p>
        <p>This process could have been surprisingly fast. Calculation by other scientists suggests that in as little as 22 years the cultivated fields could have been completely overtaken by the mutant variety. This selection of seed-retaining, fat-grained mutants marked the advent of domestication. Animals Came Later</p>
        <p>With domestication, says Dr. Hole, "hunting drops off quickly," and the mobile hunting camps that some Natufians continued to maintain disappear from the archeological record.</p>
        <p>The scientists estimate that the domestication of wheat, barley, peas and beans spread northward into Turkey and eventually into Mesopotamia, moving at about one kilometer, or five-eighths of a mile, a year as the expanding population moved into new territory. The climatic and ecological changes preceded them, according to this analysis.</p>
        <p>The domestication of animals came at least 1,000 years after the domestication of plants.</p>
        <p>None of the findings, Dr. Hole said, apply to the separate and subsequent emergence of farming elsewhere in the world. Different plants and different climatic and ecological circumstances applied there, he said, and those developments must be analyzed in their own terms.</p>
        <p>Several experts endorse the idea that climatic stress converged with technology and social organization in the Levant to give birth to agriculture, and some agree with the particular scenario proposed by Dr. Hole and Ms. McCorriston.</p>
        <p>"Right now, it looks as though Frank's got it; as he puts it together, it looks very, very good," said Dr. Robert J. Braidwood, emeritus professor of archeology at the University of Chicago and a former teacher of Dr. Hole.</p>
        <p>Other experts note the idea lacks proof, and some argue that agriculture would have developed whether the climate changed or not.</p>
        <p>The McCorriston-Hole paper synthesizes much of the latest thinking on the subject "quite nicely and elegantly," said Dr. Ofer Bar-Yosef of Harvard University, an expert on the ancient Near East. He said he agreed that a convergence of climatic stress, technology and social organization led to the domestication of plants but quarreled with some features of the Hole-McCorriston theory. "We agree on the principle but not on the details," he said. Precise Date Unlikely</p>
        <p>One idea he disputes is that climatic change caused a major change in the distribution of annual plants like cereals. He cited a not-yet-published study by Israeli scientists who have found charred remains of wild grains at a pre-Natufian settlement uncovered at the Sea of Galilee. The site was found to be 19,000 years old, which to Dr. Bar-Yosef suggests that annual grains were widely available long before domestication took place.</p>
        <p>Dr. Donald O. Henry of the University of Tulsa, an expert on the Natufians, argues that they would have begun domesticating crops sooner or later, with or without climatic stress. As soon as people settle in fixed hamlets, he said, "population goes up dramatically," adding, "That's borne out by the archeological data." This growing population would have overwhelmed the supply of wild foods, he said: "They were going to go belly up whether it was wet, dry or in between."</p>
        <p>Even so, he said, the advent of hot, dry summers could have imposed extra seasonal stress, intensifying the Natufians' predicament, forcing their hand and accelerating the move toward agriculture. Dr. Hole and Ms. McCorriston have provided "a more detailed ecological explanation of what could have triggered it," he said. "I think that's a large contribution."</p>
        <p>Will scientists ever be able to pinpoint the date and place of the earliest domestication any more precisely than within a period of several hundred years and a range of several hundred square miles?</p>
        <p>It's a very long shot, say Dr. Hole and Ms. McCorriston. Since the transition from wild to domestic could have happened in as little as a quarter of a century, they say, its precise timing could be all but archeologically invisible given the margin of error of several hundred years in dating by the radiocarbon method. Likewise, they say, it is unlikely that the exact site where the transition first took place will ever be pinned down.</p>
        <p>"The chances of archeologically coming on that settlement with the remains preserved are fairly slender," said Ms. McCorriston.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
