<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Top Ogilvy Officials Seen in Plan to Buy Agency</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">OGILVY &amp; MATHER WORLDWIDE INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WPP GROUP PLC</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D81530F931A35757C0A967958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Top Ogilvy Officials Seen in Plan to Buy Agency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIM FOLTZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME of Ogilvy &amp; Mather's top executives have been quietly talking with at least one investment bank about a plan to buy the agency back from the WPP Group, its financially troubled parent, some prominent American advertising executives and bankers said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The banking executives said that details of the plan were sketchy but that the offering price was a little more than $200 million. That is far less than the $850 million WPP paid for Ogilvy in 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME of Ogilvy &amp; Mather's top executives have been quietly talking with at least one investment bank about a plan to buy the agency back from the WPP Group, its financially troubled parent, some prominent American advertising executives and bankers said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The banking executives said that details of the plan were sketchy but that the offering price was a little more than $200 million. That is far less than the $850 million WPP paid for Ogilvy in 1989.</p>
        <p>Several advertising industry analysts said WPP, based in London, was unlikely to be tempted to sell Ogilvy for that price, even though some banks involved in the parent company's continuing debt restructuring had urged WPP to sell some assets. Aside from Ogilvy, WPP's big holdings are the J. Walter Thompson agency and Hill &amp; Knowlton, the big public relations firm.</p>
        <p>Considering the depressed nature of the advertising business in the United States and Britain, some analysts said Ogilvy could be purchased for a bargain price. But analysts said a more realistic amount would be about $500 million.</p>
        <p>Ogilvy, which creates advertising for Maxwell House coffee, American Express and Hardee's Food Systems, had gross revenues last year of $775 million and billings of more than $5 billion worldwide. It is the third-largest American agency, according to the trade publication Advertising Age.</p>
        <p>Chuck Walsh, the chief financial officer of Ogilvy Worldwide in New York, said, "There has been no approach to Ogilvy management here." He left open the possibility, however, that top agency executives elsewhere in the world might have had talks about a buyout. But Graham Phillips, the chairman and chief executive of Ogilvy Worldwide, said the rumors about a buyout were "untrue and totally speculative."</p>
        <p>WPP executives would not comment. But last month, in remarks released with WPP's year-end financial statement, Martin S. Sorrell, the company's chief executive, said he did not intend to sell assets except for the Scali, McCabe, Sloves agency. No deal has yet been struck for Scali.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, some advertising analysts said last month that another company had offered about $100 million for WPP's Hill &amp; Knowlton unit. Executives of both Hill &amp; Knowlton and WPP denied that there had been negotiations.</p>
        <p>WPP is particularly vulnerable now, some analysts said. The company is negotiating with its banks to restructure its huge debt of about $800 million. Pressed for cash, WPP has canceled two recent dividends, and some analysts have predicted that it will not pay dividends for several years.</p>
        <p>John Hompe, a spokesman for J. P. Morgan &amp; Company, which is representing the banks in WPP's restructuring, said the plan would be completed within about two weeks.</p>
        <p>Some agency executives and analysts said some Ogilvy executives would welcome a buyback because they had been unhappy about financial constraints imposed by WPP. Executives said substantial cutbacks had hindered attempts by Ogilvy's New York office to pull itself out of a slump.</p>
        <p>Some Ogilvy executives were also displeased by WPP's recent closing of the agency's special advertising research center in California.</p>
        <p>In addition, some analysts said Mr. Sorrell had angered Ogilvy executives by calling on some of the agency's most important clients and not inviting the appropriate Ogilvy executives to sit in on these meetings.</p>
        <p>But some industry executives said the time was probably not right for a buyback. The executives said the lengthy negotiations with Mr. Sorrell, who is known as a hard bargainer, would be too distracting for Ogilvy executives, who are just now beginning to get the agency back on track and winning new business.</p>
        <p>David Ogilvy, who led the agency to prominence in the 1950's and 1960's, is now chairman of WPP, a title he was given when WPP bought his agency.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
