<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Killings Harden a Debate on Capitol Hill</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="703801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE HEALTH CARE DEBATE: THE ABORTION ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCEST</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PENSACOLA (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRETT, JAMES H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILL, PAUL J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRITTON, JOHN BAYARD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Pensacola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Incest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DE1231F930A3575BC0A962958260" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Killings Harden a Debate on Capitol Hill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEELYE, KATHARINE Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since last week's double slaying at a Florida abortion clinic, both sides in the debate have redoubled their resolve over how the emerging health care bills should cover abortion, with the Democratic leadership still searching for a compromise.</p>
        <p>Abortion-rights proponents said today that the killings at a Pensacola clinic underscored the necessity for making abortion part of a basic benefits package. Not to do so, said Eleanor Smeal, president of the Fund for a Feminist Majority, would "marginalize" women and abortion providers and set them up for being "picked off, terrorized and tortured."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since last week's double slaying at a Florida abortion clinic, both sides in the debate have redoubled their resolve over how the emerging health care bills should cover abortion, with the Democratic leadership still searching for a compromise.</p>
        <p>Abortion-rights proponents said today that the killings at a Pensacola clinic underscored the necessity for making abortion part of a basic benefits package. Not to do so, said Eleanor Smeal, president of the Fund for a Feminist Majority, would "marginalize" women and abortion providers and set them up for being "picked off, terrorized and tortured."</p>
        <p>But Douglas Johnson, chief lobbyist for the National Right to Life Committee, said the proponents were "exploiting" the killings "to further a legislative agenda that has very little public support." He said the health care bill should exclude abortion from any benefits package and disallow any Federal subsidy for abortion beyond current policy, which bars Federal money for abortions except for Medicaid recipients whose pregnancies threaten their lives or are the result of rape or incest. Walling Off Emotion</p>
        <p>The killings may have heightened the emotion in the debate, but Speaker Thomas S. Foley of Washington seemed determined today to wall off the emotion from the mechanics of passing a bill. The killings, while tragic, amount to "a simple act of preventing violence," Mr. Foley said, but this "does not translate into the concerns that members have on the question of financing."</p>
        <p>"We are looking for some means of reaching a position, which both sides can support, in an agreement to disagree upon this issue," he said, suggesting that the issue would still be hanging by the 6 P.M. Wednesday deadline for House Democrats to draft their language on health care.</p>
        <p>The House bill outlined on Friday by Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the majority leader, skirted the issue. The bill put forward today in the Senate by George J. Mitchell of Maine, the majority leader, closely follows President Clinton's original proposal by including abortion in the basic benefits package.</p>
        <p>Many involved in the debate agree that the House is more likely to get bogged down in a struggle over abortion than is the Senate, in part because all House members have to run for re-election this fall, while only one-third of the senators do.</p>
        <p>About 75 abortion-rights advocates in the House, most of them Democrats, and about 35 opponents have signed letters to the leadership suggesting that they will not give on the issue and are willing to hold up the entire health care package if abortion is not settled to their liking. Looking for a Compromise</p>
        <p>A small group of House members has met a half-dozen times to fashion a compromise. One of them, Representative David E. Bonior of Michigan, the majority whip, said Mr. Mitchell's proposal would be unacceptable to those House members who oppose abortion.</p>
        <p>"I don't think they'll accept that," Mr. Bonior said. "You've got to find something that's more of a balance with the status quo."</p>
        <p>As it stands now, many private insurers cover abortion, but consumers can buy insurance that does not include it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonior said that both sides did agree on a clause that would allow individuals and religious institutions to opt out of abortion coverage. "That's not a problem," he said, although the nation's Roman Catholic bishops have objected to such a conscience clause, saying that Catholic hospitals would be subsidizing abortion even if they did not use the benefit themselves.</p>
        <p>But the larger problem -- whether abortion should be part of any standard benefits package -- remains. Threat of Opposition</p>
        <p>Abortion-rights advocates in the House are adamant that it should. Representative Patricia Schroeder, a Colorado Democrat and a leader of the women in the House, said that despite the Florida killings, she and other abortion-rights supporters were "very nervous" that the leadership was not taking them seriously.</p>
        <p>"There seems to be an attitude of, 'Now, now, girls,' and that we will cave in the end and go along with them, so they don't have to pay attention," Ms. Schroeder said. "I think they're misreading it."</p>
        <p>"We will probably be good scouts for a little bit," she said, "but it's becoming more and more evident that we can't get anything we can live with" and will have to vote against the bill.</p>
        <p>She added, "I'm not incredibly optimistic. And I worry that the spin will be, 'Can you believe that the women wouldn't vote for health care because it didn't have abortion?' rather than that in 1994, there are still politicians who want to micromanage women's lives."</p>
        <p>Some abortion-rights advocates believe that despite some indication that the White House may compromise on abortion, President Clinton will not accept a bill that excludes it from basic coverage. "We are , the pro-choice community, one of the few groups that the Clinton Administration has kept its commitments to, to date," said Pamela J. Maraldo, president of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America. Talk of 'Phony Compromise'</p>
        <p>But Mr. Johnson of the Right to Life Committee said that complaints like Ms. Schroeder's were disingenuous. In his view, the leadership has already worked out a "phony compromise" that will make it appear as if the abortion-rights supporters are compromising but really are not.</p>
        <p>"I don't believe Gephardt and Bonior will put anything in the bill that isn't acceptable to Schroeder," Mr. Johnson said. "We believe the leadership is going through this exercise to set the stage for the phony compromise, which will be to let the individual opt out.</p>
        <p>"The script now is for this to be unveiled as the great middle ground.  But under that proposal, abortion will still be in the benefits package, so every health plan would have to offer coverage of unlimited abortions."</p>
        <p>He said this would lead to "massive Federal funding" of abortions, the nullification of state regulations on matters like parental consent and would force rural areas that have no abortion clinics to build them.</p>
        <p>Several polls show that Americans do not support paying for abortion. A New York Times poll last month asked whether abortion coverage should be part of the basic health plan, should be optional or should be excluded. Fifty-three percent of the respondents said it should be excluded; 28 percent said it should be optional and 16 percent said it should be included.</p>
        <p>A June survey by the Times Mirror Center for the People and the Press said that the public opposed abortion coverage in a Federal package by 68 percent to 26 percent.</p>
        <p>The National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League disputes these surveys, saying that answers depend on how the question is asked. The officials said their own survey showed that most Americans favored inclusion of abortion benefits in a health care package.</p>
        <p>THE HEALTH CARE DEBATE: THE ABORTION ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
