<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raising CUNY to a Higher Level</title>
    <meta content="14TRAU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Community Colleges</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baruch College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">City University of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Traub, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstein, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Admissions Standards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D9103CF937A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raising CUNY to a Higher Level</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Traub</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Traub, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by James Traub on Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's call to end open admissions at City University of New York; says better plan was proposed by Matthew Goldstein, president of Baruch College, who called for new version of old stratified master plan, with several elite senior colleges at top and tightened standards for others; says community colleges would still accept any high school graduate, but remedial courses would be limited to one year; says stratified system is unfair only if it condemns people in advance to its lower reaches, which Goldstein's plan does not (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph Giuliani provoked an uproar with his recent call to end open admissions at the City University of New York. He argued that students who needed remedial help should not be allowed in community college and that they should take make-up courses from private companies instead. As a sometime critic of CUNY admissions policies, I was glad to see the Mayor draw a line in the sand. But I think he drew it in the wrong place, and in a way that is bound to perpetuate a bitter debate.</p>
        <p>CUNY's community colleges, which are the ''open admissions'' portion of the system, now accept anyone with a high school diploma or a G.E.D. Barring the door to anyone who needs remedial work would certainly improve the colleges' very low academic standards, but at a stunning cost: 87 percent of the students now entering the CUNY community colleges take at least one remedial course. And since many of these students would not be able to afford private courses, they would be excluded from higher education. Community colleges are intended to provide broad access to higher education, often with a vocational rather than an academic goal -- and every high school graduate should have a chance at that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph Giuliani provoked an uproar with his recent call to end open admissions at the City University of New York. He argued that students who needed remedial help should not be allowed in community college and that they should take make-up courses from private companies instead. As a sometime critic of CUNY admissions policies, I was glad to see the Mayor draw a line in the sand. But I think he drew it in the wrong place, and in a way that is bound to perpetuate a bitter debate.</p>
        <p>CUNY's community colleges, which are the ''open admissions'' portion of the system, now accept anyone with a high school diploma or a G.E.D. Barring the door to anyone who needs remedial work would certainly improve the colleges' very low academic standards, but at a stunning cost: 87 percent of the students now entering the CUNY community colleges take at least one remedial course. And since many of these students would not be able to afford private courses, they would be excluded from higher education. Community colleges are intended to provide broad access to higher education, often with a vocational rather than an academic goal -- and every high school graduate should have a chance at that.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the fight over open admissions has obscured the larger issue of increasing academic standards.</p>
        <p>Thirty years ago, CUNY's administrators were preparing to put into effect a master plan intended to sustain high standards while providing universal access: the top quarter of high school graduates would attend the senior colleges, the middle 40 percent would go to community colleges, and the rest would go to vocational ''skills centers.'' The pitched battle in 1969 over City College's low rate of admissions for minority students forced CUNY to scrap this hierarchical design, but the idea is now being revived.</p>
        <p>In a recent speech, Matthew Goldstein, the president of Baruch College, one of the system's most respected campuses, complained that CUNY lacked institutions of ''national stature'' like the University of California at Berkeley or the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein proposed a new version of the old stratified master plan, with several elite senior colleges at the top and tightened standards for the others. Community colleges would still accept any high school graduate, but remedial courses would be limited to one year.</p>
        <p>The open admissions shibboleth has made it almost impossible to talk about stratification without being accused of elitism, or even racism. But a stratified system is unfair only if it condemns people in advance to its lower reaches -- or if the very idea of distinctions in ability is illegitimate.</p>
        <p>First-rate scholars want to come to New York, and they want to teach the students who really need them. CUNY could compete with Columbia or New York University; its graduate center already does. But you can't have excellence without an element of hierarchy. Indeed, Baruch and Queens Colleges have already ratcheted standards slowly upward. And in recent years, CUNY has begun to place limits on remedial classes in the senior colleges. Perhaps there's an element of exclusion to these mild reforms, but it's an exclusion that is plainly good for the institution and the students.</p>
        <p>There are other costs to stratification. California's ''university'' colleges are whiter than the state or community colleges. The same is also true at CUNY's better schools, and raising standards would probably accentuate the difference. But the pool of potential students is so heavily nonwhite and non-middle class that stratifying the system is unlikely to have that large an impact.</p>
        <p>Excellence encourages excellence, just as mediocrity encourages more mediocrity. New York's high school students will respond to the incentive to take hard courses, as they've responded to the disincentive in the past. As Matthew Goldstein put it, ''Every time colleges lower the river, high school students have fewer reasons to learn how to swim.''</p>
        <p>James Traub is a staff writer at The New Yorker and the author of ''City on a Hill: Testing the American Dream at City College.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Traub is a staff writer at The New Yorker and the author of ''City on a Hill: Testing the American Dream at City College.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
