<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rain This Time, but at Least No Earthquake Yet</title>
    <meta content="14SKII$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: ALPINE SKIING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EED7113CF937A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rain This Time, but at Least No Earthquake Yet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>HAKUBA, Japan, Saturday, Feb. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First week of Olympic Winter Games has been plagued by snow and rain, causing disruptions and delays in skiing events; chart of weather postponements; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Believe it or not, it has been worse.</p>
        <p>If you think the weather has been inclement at the Nagano Olympics -- where two more Alpine skiing events were postponed this morning -- consider what happened at the last major international skiing competition held on the central Japanese island of Honshu. The 1993 world championships in Morioka, approximately 200 miles north of Nagano, featured rain, fog, heavy snow, high winds, myriad logistical problems, one very mild earthquake and one canceled race: the men's super-G.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Believe it or not, it has been worse.</p>
        <p>If you think the weather has been inclement at the Nagano Olympics -- where two more Alpine skiing events were postponed this morning -- consider what happened at the last major international skiing competition held on the central Japanese island of Honshu. The 1993 world championships in Morioka, approximately 200 miles north of Nagano, featured rain, fog, heavy snow, high winds, myriad logistical problems, one very mild earthquake and one canceled race: the men's super-G.</p>
        <p>It should have been an easy act to follow, and after the Nagano Organizing Committee resolved the seemingly interminable conflict over the starting point of the men's downhill, these Winter Games were off to a flying start.</p>
        <p>But one week after the opening ceremony, not a single Alpine race has been able to begin as originally scheduled and only three of the events have been completed instead of five. This morning, both the men's super-G and the women's downhill were postponed because of the driving rain falling on the resort of Happo'one. The super-G has been rescheduled for Sunday morning at 10:15 (Saturday night Eastern time) and the women's downhill for Monday morning at 10:15, followed by the women's combined downhill. But more snowfall is anticipated on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The good news is that there has not been an earthquake -- at least not yet.</p>
        <p>''This is ridiculous,'' said Ingeborg Helen Marken, Norway's top hope in the downhill, in an interview with Norwegian reporters. ''Everyone knew the weather in Nagano is like this at this time of the year. The I.O.C. knew this, too, and shouldn't have given Nagano the Olympics.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the International Olympic Committee could argue that if the Olympics had started one week earlier, none of the speed events would have been postponed at all. ''I was here just before the Olympics for a veterans' race,'' said Franck Piccard of France, the 1988 gold medalist in the men's super-G. ''We had five days of complete sunshine.''</p>
        <p>It has certainly been bad luck for CBS. The delays have played havoc with the network's schedule and contributed heavily to CBS's ratings woes. Last Saturday night, the men's downhill was to be the live marquee event. Without it, CBS's Nielsen rating was a slim 12.3. When CBS finally showed the race on Thursday night, the rating was 19.5. But the rating for Friday night may falter again because of the postponement of the women's downhill.</p>
        <p>With CBS's seven-night rating mired at 16.8, the network will probably have to offer ''make good'' ads to advertisers who were guaranteed an overall prime-time 19.0 rating. Four years ago in Lillehammer, Norway, CBS came away with a 27.8 rating; in 1992, its total prime-time rating for the Games in Albertville, France, was an 18.7.</p>
        <p>For the moment, there is little concern that any Olympic races will have to be canceled. Eight days remain in these Games, and there are seven events to complete. The slalom and giant slalom races scheduled for next week are much less susceptible to cancellation in foul weather because they do not have the same security concerns. If conditions continue to be poor, the organizers could even schedule men's and women's slalom races on the same day.</p>
        <p>But knowing that does not make the waiting any easier or drier.</p>
        <p>''It's raining cats and dogs again, as I've learned to say in school from my English teacher,'' said the United States' women's head coach, Herwig Demschar, who was born in Austria.</p>
        <p>''It gets to the point where you just have to laugh,'' said the American skier Chad Fleischer, who was scheduled to start the super-G. ''You don't really get mad. You just try to figure out what to do with your time.''</p>
        <p>As for those downhillers who banged their bodies against the snow in Friday's controversial men's downhill, the Austrian star Hermann Maier escaped his spectacular crash with a sprained right knee and contusions on his left shoulder and thorax. Although he said he was feeling ''not so good,'' he was scheduled to start the super-G this morning.</p>
        <p>The Italian skier Luca Cattaneo, who was transported off the hill by helicopter after tearing his left Achilles' tendon in a crash, is out for the season. The Italian team announced today that he had been flown back to Italy for surgery.</p>
        <p>Though some news reports indicated that the reason for Maier's crash was the late decision by the organizers to move the position of a gate, he told Austrian reporters that was not his explanation: ''I was aware of the gate; I was just carrying too much speed into it.''  THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: ALPINE SKIING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
