<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Canadians Voting Today in a Close Race</title>
    <meta content="Y27CAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/27/world/27CANA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chretien, Jean (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Stockwell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5D81F3AF934A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Canadians Voting Today in a Close Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>OTTAWA, Nov. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canadians will vote on November 27 for new government after five-week campaign whose outcome opinion polls suggest is too close to call with approximately 20 percent of voters undecided among candidates from five parties; race could decide political fate of Prime Min Jean Chretien, who has headed government for past seven years, and faces stiff opposition from principal challenger Stockwell Day, conservative who heads new Canadian Alliance; polls indicate Liberals will lose seats in West to Alliance and to separatist Parti Quebecois in Quebec and Ontario; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Canadians vote for a new government on Monday after a five-week campaign that quickly derailed from high-minded debate over taxes and health care to sniping over topics like creationism.</p>
        <p>With opinion polls indicating that about 20 percent of voters have yet to choose among candidates from the five parties, the race is deemed too close to predict the political fate of Jean Chretien, the prime minister for the last seven years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Canadians vote for a new government on Monday after a five-week campaign that quickly derailed from high-minded debate over taxes and health care to sniping over topics like creationism.</p>
        <p>With opinion polls indicating that about 20 percent of voters have yet to choose among candidates from the five parties, the race is deemed too close to predict the political fate of Jean Chretien, the prime minister for the last seven years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chretien hopes to win enough seats for his Liberal Party to form a third consecutive majority government, a feat not seen here since World War II.</p>
        <p>But polls indicate that the Liberals will lose seats in the West to the new conservative party, the Canadian Alliance, in Quebec to the separatist Bloc Quebecois, and here in Ontario, the nation's political powerhouse, where about a third of Canada's 31 million people live.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Chretien fails to win a majority in Parliament, he will have to forge a governing alliance with other members of what has been called ''the pizza Parliament.''</p>
        <p>The two smaller slices that might provide a majority are the socialist New Democratic Party and the fiscally conservative Progressive Conservative Party.</p>
        <p>Although the Liberals fare slightly better in opinion polls than the 38.5 percent they won in 1997, party leaders fear that voters may stay home, apathetic about the prospect of giving their 66-year-old prime minister a third term.</p>
        <p>The Globe and Mail, an influential Toronto newspaper with a national circulation, demonstrated the deep ambivalence in an editorial on Saturday urging readers to vote Liberal, but admonishing: ''Mr. Chretien has to go. He has become a one-man band, loving power for its own sake.''</p>
        <p>The newspaper reasoned that 16 months from now, in a leadership review, the Liberals will probably replace Mr. Chretien with Paul Martin, his popular finance minister. The lengthy editorial was titled: ''Why We Recommend a Vote for Paul Martin.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, The Toronto Star, Canada's largest-selling newspaper and a staunch Liberal Party backer, gave only a ''reluctant endorsement'' of Mr. Chretien.</p>
        <p>Canada's 36-day campaign has not been kinder to Stockwell Day, the leader of the Canadian Alliance and Mr. Chretien's leading opponent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Day, who stepped down last spring as treasurer of Alberta to enter national politics, hoped to lead a national discussion about cutting taxes to make Canada more competitive with the United States and, gingerly, to explore ways to improve the national health care system, a topic debated with near-religious fervor here.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Chretien, fearing that the Alliance was on the rise, called the election only four months after Mr. Day, a telegenic 50-year-old, became leader of the new party. Without time to organize and to drill candidates in the Alliance platform, the party soon stumbled.</p>
        <p>Last week, one Alliance candidate, Ken Epp, told an interviewer that the party would dismantle Canada's social security system, a stance that party leaders quickly denied.</p>
        <p>Earlier, another Alliance candidate, ignoring the new party's wide support among Chinese and Indian immigrants in British Columbia, complained about ''the Asian invasion'' of Canada. Party leaders immediately forced the candidate, Betty Granger of Manitoba, to resign.</p>
        <p>After that, Brian Fitzpatrick, a balding Alliance candidate in Saskatchewan, a province with a large aboriginal voting population, joked to indigenous protesters, ''You can't scalp me because I haven't got much hair on the top of my head.''</p>
        <p>The remark helped to fuel a series of Indian protests against Mr. Day, including the occupation of his parliamentary district office in British Columbia.</p>
        <p>In addition to putting out fires set by other candidates, Mr. Day spent much of last week ducking questions about a Canadian Broadcasting Corporation report that he had given a lecture in 1997 outlining his beliefs that the first men and women were created 6,000 years ago, living alongside the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>'' 'The Flintstones' is not a documentary,'' Warren Kinsella, a Liberal strategist, gleefully commented. Soon reporters on the Day campaign bus were humming the theme song of the cartoon series, in which Fred, Wilma and their baby, Pebbles, coexist with dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>''If you're looking for dinosaur politics, you need to look at the federal Liberals,'' Mr. Day shot back, while aides noted that Mr. Chretien was waging his 12th campaign for federal office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Day, an evangelical Christian whose campaign jet was nicknamed Prayer Force One, did not campaign today, obeying a self-imposed vow to devote Sunday to church and family. But in a last-ditch attempt to reach voters in Ontario, he bought evening time on several provincial television stations for a 15-minute direct appeal.</p>
        <p>In Ontario, where immigrants make up a quarter of the population, the Liberals have had success in painting the Alliance as anti-immigrant. ''As a minority, I have to vote Liberal,'' said Mitch Rezaei, a Toronto taxi driver from Iran. Referring to Mr. Day's political predecessor, Preston Manning, he added, ''All he was thinking about was making obstacles for newcomers.''</p>
        <p>In the last two elections, Ontarians did not elect any parliamentary candidates from Mr. Manning's Reform Party, a group that last spring transformed itself into the Alliance to try to win Ontario seats. Leery about Mr. Day's chances, Mike Harris, Ontario's Conservative premier, pointedly remained on the sidelines during the federal campaign.</p>
        <p>''The religious thing doesn't wash in Ontario,'' Alan Lysaght, a documentary filmmaker, said the other day while watching Mr. Day's campaign bus, emblazoned ''A Time for a Change,'' roll through the Toronto financial district. ''He can win the whole western side of the country, but Ontario rules.''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Simpson, a Globe and Mail columnist, agreed, writing last week: ''Social conservatism is a ball and chain around any party in a largely secular and deeply pluralistic country, especially in Ontario, the most pluralistic province of them all.''</p>
        <p>While Ontario fills 103 of Parliament's 301 seats, Quebec, Canada's second-most-populous-province, may flex its political muscles in a different way on Monday. Mr. Chretien, a Quebecker who ardently believes in national unity, scores low in opinion polls in Quebec -- so low that a collection of the prime minister's verbal bloopers is a best-seller in Montreal.</p>
        <p>A mass rally in Montreal brought together what the Quebec press calls ''the three tenors of separatism'' -- Lucien Bouchard, Quebec's premier; Gilles Duceppe, leader of the Bloc Quebecois; and Jacques Parizeau, who, as Quebec's premier in 1995 narrowly lost the last referendum on independence. The Bloc is expected to pick up several Liberal seats in the largely French-speaking province.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
