<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boing! Pop-Up Books Are Growing Up; Flaps, Foldouts and Complexities Attract Adult Eyes</title>
    <meta content="27POPU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/27/arts/27POPU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DB1F3AF934A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boing! Pop-Up Books Are Growing Up; Flaps, Foldouts and Complexities Attract Adult Eyes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pop-up books, formerly reserved for children, have entered adult market; creators are rarefied group of self-taught paper engineers who court mature readers with lavish illustrations and inventive mechanics; some pop-up books are so complex that copies consist of more than 600 hand-glued pieces; Brooklyn Public Library mounts exhibit, Brooklyn Pops Up, featuring more than 100 pop-ups or 'movable books,' more dignified label preferred by adult collectors; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the pages of a pop-up picture book, the pink lady of Junior's Deli springs alive in V-fold formation.</p>
        <p>One delicate paper hand is wrapped around a Junior's cheesecake box while the other gestures toward a foaming egg cream. But on closer inspection, there is more to this pop-up book celebrating Brooklyn than mere seltzer froth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the pages of a pop-up picture book, the pink lady of Junior's Deli springs alive in V-fold formation.</p>
        <p>One delicate paper hand is wrapped around a Junior's cheesecake box while the other gestures toward a foaming egg cream. But on closer inspection, there is more to this pop-up book celebrating Brooklyn than mere seltzer froth.</p>
        <p>A reflection in the egg cream glass is a faint image of a man and a woman. It represents a sly homage to Jan van Eyck's ''Arnolfini's Marriage,'' which contains a similar glint of the artist reflected in a mirror.</p>
        <p>Pop-up books may be the literary preserve of children, but lately the whirligig pages of flaps, foldouts, pull-tabs and double wheels are moving frenetically to attract grown-ups.</p>
        <p>The creators are a rarefied group of self-taught paper engineers who court mature readers with lavish illustrations and inventive mechanics. Some pop-up books are so complex that copies consist of more than 600 hand-glued pieces assembled high in the Andes in Ecuador. And the titles feature plots and symbols that may inspire profound adult soul searching: does the pop-up interior of a haunted house symbolize a spooky scene or sexual awakening?</p>
        <p>The ancient bookmaking craft dates back to the 13th century when titles were intended for adults. And now the books are finding cachet once again with sober institutions like the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, which will publish a 45-pop-up book of California images in March to follow a museum exhibition on the state's image and identity.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn Public Library has spent more than $70,000 in state grants to organize ''Brooklyn Pops Up'' an elaborate exhibition featuring more than 100 pop-ups or ''movable books'' -- the more dignified label preferred by adult collectors. It also has jointly produced with the Movable Book Society (an organization of adult aficionados and collectors) and Little Simon (an imprint of Simon &amp; Schuster) a companion volume with the same title. The library's three-dimensional tribute to Coney Island and brownstones costs $19.95 and has nearly sold out its first printing of more than 16,500.</p>
        <p>From the bustling lobby of the Central Library at Grand Army Plaza, a paper Elvis rises from a bookbinding to shimmy with his backup band in a star-studded scene of Las Vegas. There are nods in the newly constructed showcases, of course, to children's tales like ''Pinocchio,'' ''Alice in Wonderland,'' and ''Winnie the Pooh and the Bees.''</p>
        <p>But the adult tilt is unmistakable; one book depicts pop-up cocktails. A book of phobias opens to a page entitled ''dentophobia,'' which features a beady-eyed dentist bursting forth with an oversized drill.</p>
        <p>The exhibition will remain at the Central Library through Dec. 30 and then travel to 24 neighborhood branches. These tributes are taking place at the same time that a pop-up book published by Little Simon has achieved the rare feat of claiming a spot on a New York Times best-seller list. This week Robert Sabuda's elaborate commemorative version of ''The Wonderful Wizard of Oz'' climbed to No. 4 on the children's picture book list.</p>
        <p>An illustrator and a paper engineer dubbed the Prince of Paper by Publishers Weekly, Mr. Sabuda has designed a kinetic book of iridescent paper sculptures that shifts from a whirling tornado to a floating hot-air balloon and a byzantine Emerald City castle of towers and cupolas that spreads across two pages. A pair of green spectacles is helpfully tucked away in a side pocket for the reader.</p>
        <p>Although the book is labeled a children's title, Mr. Sabuda has his own suspicions about who is actually reading his creation, which contains attached foldout booklets with L. Frank Baum's original text and costs about $25. ''You can tell when adults come up and ask you to autograph a book and they say, 'Sign it for Harold,' '' the artist said.</p>
        <p>Part of the credit for such appeal, Mr. Sabuda added, is the adult crossover popularity of J. K. Rowling's Harry Potter series of children's novels. ''It made adults recognize that they don't have to go into a bookstore and head for the adult section,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Brooklyn exhibition showcases the evolution of movable books, which date back to the 13th century when the Catalan mystic and poet Ramon Llull created hand-drawn layered circles that charted the stars or astrological projections.</p>
        <p>The companion volume features contemporary works by an international group of paper engineers, including Kees Moerbeek and Carla Dijs, Dutch artists who managed to create paper egg creams without having ever tasted one.</p>
        <p>''To my knowledge, no library has ever done a pop-up book before,'' said Martin Gomez, the executive director of the Brooklyn Public Library. The aim of the exhibition, he added, was to ''demonstrate that the library is relevant in the 21st century and that it can play an important role to celebrate the value of reading.''</p>
        <p>Maurice Sendak, the Brooklyn-born author of ''Where the Wild Things Are'' and long a collector of pop-up books, designed the cover of the Brooklyn pop-up book with the assistance of paper engineers like Mr. Sabuda.</p>
        <p>''They came to convince me to do it certainly with the view that somebody as curmudgeonly as me wouldn't be open to suggestions,'' Mr. Sendak said. ''I was really entranced with their work and of course I wanted to do it, but not unless I could be involved in the whole thing.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''This is not just about making it move. Who cares about that. It's about making the book move in a personal sense.'' His cover is an illustration of a young girl and boy dressed in oversized clothes and gripping a Walt Whitman book. A finger pull moves their arms and heads, prompting the bearded figure of Brooklyn-bred Whitman to rise from the book along with a lush, leafy tree.</p>
        <p>''It suggests 'Leaves of Grass' and 'A Tree Grows in Brooklyn,' a book that my sister and I read avidly,'' Mr. Sendak said.</p>
        <p>Unlike their ''flat book'' cousins, there is an emotional quality about pop-up books that prompts deep introspection among adult readers, who debate the meaning of symbols.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Moerbeek wrote a psychological analysis this summer of Jan Pienkowski's classic ''Haunted House'' pop-up for the Movable Book Society's quarterly newsletter, Movable Stationery. He argues that this tale of a haunted house contains symbols with deep subthemes, representing a farewell to childhood and the awakening of adolescence.</p>
        <p>The white mice in the illustrations, he argued, represent the ''color of virginity.'' And the real meaning of the flowered wallpaper in one scene is obvious: ''They look like flowers, but in fact they are hardly disguised spermatozoa,'' he said, adding: ''We get a more than clear picture of the real meaning of this book. It's a story about the first sexual experience.''</p>
        <p>Through the last century the popularity of pop-up books ebbed and flowed with paper shortages, world wars, the quality of modern glue and the rise in the late 1960's of a cottage industry in book production. Today most movable books are painstakenly printed and cut in Cali, Colombia, and assembled and glued by dozens of Andean piece workers in Ibarra, Ecuador. Typically each pop-up book, like ''The Art Pack,'' a history of Western art, is made up of as many as 600 intricate pieces.</p>
        <p>''We print in 32 languages for more than 100 countries,'' said Guillermo Holguin, the general manager of the book printing division of Carvajal Caragraphics, in Colombia, which dominates the pop-up field. ''The market is changing, and it's becoming more demanding. In the past if a book was a three-dimensional product, it could sell fairly well. Now it has to have nice design, more information and more educational material. Because of that, the books are reaching adults, and books are being published that wouldn't have existed before.''</p>
        <p>And with that complexity, the prices of pop-ups are rising. The pop-up book to be brought out next year by the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and Universe Publishing will contain pop-up scenes by various paper engineers and artists that depict the Golden Gate Bridge, the Egyptian Theater in Hollywood and Hearst Castle.</p>
        <p>Universe, an imprint of Rizzoli International Publications, last year issued a New York pop-up title intended for adults, and in December plans to publish Isabelle De Borchgrave's elaborate history of costumes and dresses, ''Fashion a la Mode.'' Among the large trade publishers in New York, Little Simon has published four pop-up books this year, including ''The Wonderful Wizard of Oz,'' and St. Martin's Press has just signed a contract to publish a title in a series aimed at adults, ''The Pop-Up Book of Nightmares.''</p>
        <p>''People are interested in handmade books as a counterreaction to what you're seeing that you can get on the Web,'' said Charles Miers, the publisher of Universe. ''They're interested in tactile things and there's a certain retro quality to the pop-up book.''</p>
        <p>There is no training program for the small elite group of paper engineers who devise the intricate mechanics of parallel folds, angle folds and wheels. ''There really isn't a school,'' said David A. Carter, a paper engineer and designer who has tried to fill the gap with one of his own books, ''The Elements of Pop-Up.'' ''It's something that you learn on your own by looking at other pop-up books and taking them apart,'' he added.</p>
        <p>''There are basically about 44 core designs or mechanisms,'' said Mr. Carter, who has published a number of pop-up books featuring goggle-eyed bugs and most recently an adaption of ''The Nutcracker.'' ''What I see happening is that authors, designers and illustrators are figuring out ways to apply new ideas to those basic structures,'' he said. ''It's more integrated, and I think you're seeing a renaissance.''</p>
        <p>For adult readers, pop-ups can be habit-forming, even consuming. Ellen G. Rubin, a member of the Movable Book Society, which helped organize the Brooklyn library exhibition, said she has collected about 4,000 pop-up titles.</p>
        <p>''A book lover my whole life, I still never collected 'flat' books,'' said Mrs. Rubin, who is a physician's assistant in Scarsdale, N.Y. ''Pop-ups have the characteristic of making the reader interactive, complicit in the storytelling. The paper engineer acts as a puppeteer, but hands the strings to the reader.''</p>
        <p>So deep is Mrs. Rubin's passion that she traveled to Ibarra in Ecuador to watch as dozens of women in white coats pounded, assembled and glued miniature boxes of Junior's cheesecakes, Nathan's frankfurters and foamy egg creams. High in the Andes, she said the sight of such Brooklyn symbols was like ''finding a yo-yo in a Tibetan monastery.''</p>
        <p>But there was no doubt about how she viewed the impact of her pilgrimage. It is, she said, ''the holy city of pop-up Mecca.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
