<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Road, but Not Quite Kerouac</title>
    <meta content="15NJBTW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1672755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BY THE WAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED91E30F936A25756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Road, but Not Quite Kerouac</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Christine Contillo</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spring is here, and that means it's time to inflate the tires on the ol' Schwinn, dose the chain with a blast of WD-40 and hit the roads. But here, in the country's most densely-populated state, can saddle sores, skinned knees and the occasional concussion be far behind?</p>
        <p>Don't fret. Diane Goodspeed -- don't let her name scare you -- offers a sane approach to cycling in her new book, ''Family-Friendly Biking in New Jersey and Eastern Pennsylvania'' (Rutgers University Press, $16.95).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spring is here, and that means it's time to inflate the tires on the ol' Schwinn, dose the chain with a blast of WD-40 and hit the roads. But here, in the country's most densely-populated state, can saddle sores, skinned knees and the occasional concussion be far behind?</p>
        <p>Don't fret. Diane Goodspeed -- don't let her name scare you -- offers a sane approach to cycling in her new book, ''Family-Friendly Biking in New Jersey and Eastern Pennsylvania'' (Rutgers University Press, $16.95).</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodspeed understands that family biking, especially when it includes preschoolers or toddlers, is less about wearing bright, tight-fitting aerodynamic outfits as you burn up the roads and nettle motorists than it is about finding uncluttered paths where you can appreciate the sights as you aimlessly pedal by -- especially if there's an ice-cream stand waiting at the end of the trip.</p>
        <p>After giving some general, not-too-technical advice about selecting bikes, carriers and child seats, Ms. Goodspeed helps her readers/riders frame their expectations. Cycling is no longer about how far and fast you can go, but about how you can all enjoy it together. She adopts a strict definition of family-friendly trails: they should be reasonably level and accessible to what ''fun stuff'' is nearby.</p>
        <p>The book suggests 24 trails, including five in eastern Pennsylvania. Each chapter has a rating for the skill level of the rider, the distance, the type of trail (loop or out-and-back) and trail surface. In addition, she provides valuable information about where to park, where to start and what to expect. That may be where the nearest restroom is, if there's fast food nearby or a bit of history to help Mom or Dad impress the kids with their vast and diverse reservoir of knowledge.</p>
        <p>Fifteen trails are listed at the very end of the book with the reasons they were left off the main list -- usually too much traffic or because they were better suited for mountain biking. As your young riders become more proficient, you may decide to give one of these extra trails a try.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodspeed admits that after having children she and her husband felt forced to give up biking for several years because traveling on congested roads with kids in tow just didn't seem safe or worth the effort. She initially located some trails through the Rails-to-Trails Conservancy, and then found and investigated restored canal towpaths in the state. Luckily for us, she has shared results of all that legwork.</p>
        <p>Christine Contillo</p>
        <p>BY THE WAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
