<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Award to Local Director For Wetlands Advocacy</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="355023"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WETLANDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL WETLANDS AWARD</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL WETLANDS NEWSLETTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CALLAHAN, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEILLEUX, NICOLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TESSIER, LAURA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DB173FF933A15756C0A966958260" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Award to Local Director For Wetlands Advocacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM CALLAHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CALLAHAN, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN Laura Tessier returned to her desk at the County Soil and Conservation District office in White Plains last month after a vacation, she found a letter informing her that she was one of six winners of the first National Wetlands Awards. The honor was for her ''commitment to wetlands conservation,'' said Nicole Veilleux, who wrote the letter and is editor of The National Wetlands Newsletter in</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: WHEN Laura Tessier returned to her desk at the County Soil and Conservation District office in White Plains last month after a vacation, she found a letter informing her that she was one of six winners of the first National Wetlands Awards. The honor was for her ''commitment to wetlands conservation,'' said Nicole Veilleux, who wrote the letter and is editor of The National Wetlands Newsletter in</p>
        <p>WHEN Laura Tessier returned to her desk at the County Soil and Conservation District office in White Plains last month after a vacation, she found a letter informing her that she was one of six winners of the first National Wetlands Awards. The honor was for her ''commitment to wetlands conservation,'' said Nicole Veilleux, who wrote the letter and is editor of The National Wetlands Newsletter in Washington.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tessier, who has been program director of the Soil and Conservation District since 1982, said her reaction was embarrassment at all the attention.</p>
        <p>''It's an honor not just for me,'' she said, ''but for the entire district. It is one of the first recognitions of what's being done by professionals at the local level. In my experience, there is a lot of attention paid to Federal and state efforts. But there's an abundance of talent and consistently progressive programs at the local level that don't receive much attention.''</p>
        <p>The Westchester district is a ''quasi state and county agency,'' Ms. Tessier said, with a $200,000-a-year budget almost entirely paid by the state. The staff has three county employees and one Federal employee.</p>
        <p>It was established in 1967 in accordance with state law and is designed to provide local municipalities with technical information about soil and water conservation. Thirty-eight county municipalities have signed agreements with the district that entitles them to technical reviews of all proposed development in their jurisdictions.</p>
        <p>Purpose Is Site Review</p>
        <p>''The main purpose of our program is site review,'' Ms. Tessier said. ''If municipalities didn't have experts to give them technical assistance, environmental concerns may be overlooked in development and planning.</p>
        <p>''Developers have their own consultants. But local planning boards might not have the resources to understand the information given them. What we provide is an objective non-adversarial environmental review of development proposals.''</p>
        <p>The district receives 200 to 300 requests a year for assistance and responds to 30 to 40 percent of them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tessier said there was an imbalance in environmental reviews because although the Federal and state governments had environmental regulations, it was up to the local authorities to insure adherence, for which they may often not have the resources or technical expertise.</p>
        <p>''The district is helpful in providing an area of expertise that I don't have,'' said Edward Buroughs, the Somers Planning Director. ''It's like having an extension of your own office. It is a cooperative service between levels of government.''</p>
        <p>Beaver Swamp Watershed</p>
        <p>Ms. Tessier emphasized that the agency was not anti-development, saying, ''We don't see the issue as stopping development, but having more sensitive development, which often means a lower site density for projects.''</p>
        <p>The Westchester district differs from others in the state in that its focus is on urban conservation, and not agricultural.</p>
        <p>In addition to site review, the district worked with the village of Mamaroneck, the city of Rye and the town of Harrison in 1985 to create a storm-water management plan for the Beaver Swamp Brook watershed.</p>
        <p>The district also issued a model wetlands ordinance, and Somers is considering adopting it.''</p>
        <p>The National Wetlands Award is sponsored by the Environmental Law Institute, a private group; the Federal Environmental Protection Agency and the Association of State Wetlands Managers.</p>
        <p>Two winners are from Federal and state governments, one from business, one from a nonprofit agency and two from local government.</p>
        <p>The director of communications for the Environmental Law Institute, Lori Wainright, said Ms. Tessier had received ''10 or 11'' nominations from groups and individuals in Westchester.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Harrison Planning Board, Bruno Strati, wrote a letter on Ms. Tessier's behalf. ''I can't say enough about her,'' Mr. Strati said in a telephone interview. ''Laura has been tremendously helpful to the Harrison Planning Board over the years and helped us preserve more than 30 acres of wetlands on a development site five years ago. She is tremendously knowledgeable in her field. She has gone well beyond the call of duty in preserving the quality of life in open space in Westchester.'' Ms. Tessier said she preferred to credit her staff. ''What's being done on the local level has a cumulative effect on the environment,'' she said. ''It may be a hackneyed slogan, but it is true: you have to think globally about the environment but work locally.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
