<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Breaking Ground By Going on Tour</title>
    <meta content="25THEA$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THEATER" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="932306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Jersey Shakespeare Festival</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drew University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monte, Bonnie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5DC123BF936A15756C0A961958260" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Breaking Ground By Going on Tour</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Shakespeare Festival will produce five plays in three different spaces this summer; its new $7.5 million F M Kirby Shakespeare Theater at Drew University is scheduled to open next summer; architect's rendering; artistic dir Bonnie J Monte photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sounds of reconstruction, which began on Tuesday, signal a magnificent theater in the place of a makeshift one for the New Jersey Shakespeare Festival. But the grand opening of that multi-million-dollar dreamscape is next year's news.</p>
        <p>Producing five plays in three different spaces inevitably brings forth no-roof-over-its-head comments about this summer's festival. But the festival's board president, Margaret Domber, won't hear of the word ''homeless.'' ''Use homefull instead,'' she says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sounds of reconstruction, which began on Tuesday, signal a magnificent theater in the place of a makeshift one for the New Jersey Shakespeare Festival. But the grand opening of that multi-million-dollar dreamscape is next year's news.</p>
        <p>Producing five plays in three different spaces inevitably brings forth no-roof-over-its-head comments about this summer's festival. But the festival's board president, Margaret Domber, won't hear of the word ''homeless.'' ''Use homefull instead,'' she says.</p>
        <p>In this peripatetic summer, the festival is presenting what it calls  ''a movable feast'' before the projected opening of the $7.5 million F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater at Drew University (formerly the Bowne Theater) next summer. Whatever the designation, a troupe of strolling players is a Shakespearean concept indeed. So we're not talking Parma, ''then Mantua, then Padua,'' as the lyric of ''We Open in Venice'' from ''Kiss Me, Kate'' goes. For the festival, always true to Shakespeare in its fashion, they open in Morristown; they next play Madison. Then they open again -- where? -- in Morristown!</p>
        <p>The next jump is Madison, but this time to the football field at Bayley-Ellard High School, where  the price of admission includes a foam-cushioned seat, bug spray and a bottle of water. A fine and mighty place for ''Henry V'' -- ''a play about gaining land and losing land,'' as the festival's artistic director, Bonnie J. Monte, reminds us. On those nights, July 15 to Aug. 10, there will be no roof over anyone's head. And the set will be struck after each performance.</p>
        <p>''If this is an alien experience for people who may not know theater etiquette, then they'll know the sports arena,'' Ms. Monte added in a telephone interview. ''If they scream and shout and root for England and France, that's fine with me.''</p>
        <p>Invariably, performances in a football field involve power lines and scaffolding, rain dates and portable toilets, and ''amplification we don't want to sound amplified,'' Ms. Monte said. ''The actors should not be forced to take an intimate scene and scream it.''</p>
        <p>The festival will stage three plays in the Community Theater of Morristown, a 1,200-seat artifact of the Walter Reade movie chain that was reopened three years ago for pop and classical concerts and recitals, touring companies of Broadway shows, and theater for children.</p>
        <p>There, ''A Midsummer Night's Dream, directed by Ms. Monte, is to unfold from June 13 to 29 on a ''stage within a stage, as a dream within a dream, a play within a play, in a space within a space,'' as Ms. Monte puts it. The festival will use 500 of the seats and an abstract setting made of huge gauze boxes.</p>
        <p>The nomadic season closes in Morristown with Noel Coward's ''Blithe Spirit'' at the Community Theater Aug. 8 to 24.</p>
        <p>Since the festival's season is take place on other stages, its experimental series, Other Stage, and its annual colloquium weekend are taking the summer off.</p>
        <p>I F the festival is customarily the centerpiece of New Jersey's professional summer season -- more so than ever this year and next -- there are other diversions, both glittering and laid-back, from an up-to-the-nanosecond musical to the centenary of an oft-told tale about a geisha and the American naval officer who does her wrong, pre-Puccini style.</p>
        <p>For Thursday's glitzy premiere of George Faison's original musical, ''Heaven and the Homeboy,'' at Theaterfest at Montclair State University, Oprah Winfrey, the pop singers Ashford and Simpson,  and Roberta Flack are expected.</p>
        <p>The poet Maya Angelou should be there on the second night. When all the hoopla simmers down, attention will be paid to the blues-gospel-rap show that means to be a morality play, not just a musical jamboree. After ''Homeboy'' comes ''The Sound of Music''; then there's a new farce, ''Do Not Disturb,'' by Jane Milmore and Billy Van Zand, who turn them out once (or is it twice?) a year. This one is to be directed by Olympia Dukakis at Theaterfest's Next Stage Theater (capacity: 100).</p>
        <p>It is cheering to welcome back the East Lynne Company, ''Purveyors of American Theatricals.'' The first of three productions in Cape May is ''Madame Butterfly,'' the original play by David Belasco and John Luther Long, taken from Mr. Long's short story published in Century magazine in 1897.</p>
        <p>Stephen Sondheim in any form  is not a staple of New Jersey's professional theaters. For Sondheim aficionados, who cannot be choosy, the Foundation Theater in Pemberton is to offer ''Marry Me a Little,'' a concoction by Craig Lucas and Norman Rene, in which early Sondheim songs about lonely people are strung together for two actors playing lonely people on Saturday nights. A Feydeau farce, ''Love by the Bolt,'' is to follow.</p>
        <p>Cape May Stage producing a season of Brian Friel (''The Faith Healer''), A. R. Gurney (yes, it's ''Sylvia''), Tennessee Williams (''A Lovely Sunday for Creve Coeur'') and ''The Complete Works of William Shakespeare (Abridged),'' by the Reduced Shakespeare Company, which travels light.</p>
        <p>Information and schedules of New Jersey's professional summer theaters may be obtained from the New Jersey Theater Group, 17 Cook Avenue, Madison, N.J. 07940; (201) 593-0189.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
