<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Crowd Sees Maryland and Princeton Win and Advance to the N.C.A.A. Final</title>
    <meta content="25LACC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="LACROSSE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="932550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="LACROSSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Maryland</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Syracuse</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, William N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6D61E3BF936A15756C0A961958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Crowd Sees Maryland and Princeton Win and Advance to the N.C.A.A. Final</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wallace, William N</byline>
      <dateline>COLLEGE PARK, Md., May 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Princeton University and University of Maryland capture one-goal victories at Byrd Stadium to reach National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I lacrosse tournament final; Princeton defeats Duke University, 10-9; Maryland defeats University of Syracuse, 18-17 (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Undefeated Princeton and upstart Maryland captured tense one-goal victories at Byrd Stadium today to reach the National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I tournament final.</p>
        <p>The assembly of 30,580, the biggest ever for lacrosse, saw the Tigers freeze the ball for the last 4 minutes 40 seconds of their game against Duke to seal a 10-9 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Undefeated Princeton and upstart Maryland captured tense one-goal victories at Byrd Stadium today to reach the National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I tournament final.</p>
        <p>The assembly of 30,580, the biggest ever for lacrosse, saw the Tigers freeze the ball for the last 4 minutes 40 seconds of their game against Duke to seal a 10-9 victory.</p>
        <p>Maryland, ranked 10th in the tournament's field of 12, failed to do the same for the last two minutes against Syracuse but managed to hold on for an 18-17 triumph.</p>
        <p>So Princeton (14-0), seeded No. 1 and the defending champion, will play Maryland (11-4) here Monday for the championship.</p>
        <p>No. 3 Syracuse (11-3), which played in an N.C.A.A. semifinal for the 15th season in a row, and No. 5 Duke (12-4) went home. They both played well, but not quite well enough.</p>
        <p>Roy Simmons Jr., the Syracuse coach, said: ''We are used to a street fight, and we had a good one. Today we got thrown by Maryland.''</p>
        <p>Matt Hahn scored the winning goal for the Terrapins at 12:39 of the final period after Syracuse had finally tied the score at 17-17. It was Hahn who had the winning goal in overtime last Sunday in a quarterfinal upset of No. 2 Virginia, 10-9.</p>
        <p>''Warriors'' is how Coach Dick Edell described his overachieving Maryland athletes. ''We didn't intend this to be a shootout with Syracuse, for sure,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But that is how the match turned out in the second half, when 19 goals were scored. The game's total of 35 goals was 3 short of the N.C.A.A. tournament record.</p>
        <p>After Hahn's score, the Terrapins twice lost the ball to Syracuse, but the Orange attackers never got off a good shot on the Maryland goalie, Sean Keenan.</p>
        <p>Casey Powell was an outstanding performer as usual for Syracuse and scored four goals, as did his teammate Rob Kavovit.</p>
        <p>Ryan Powell, Casey's freshman brother, had three, his last the 17th for the Orange, which trailed by 4-3 after one period and by 9-7 at halftime.</p>
        <p>As for Duke, the Blue Devils could have used basketball's shot clock to force Princeton to take a shot in the final 4:40 of their contest.</p>
        <p>After Chris Massey had scored Princeton's 10th and final goal, the Tigers' James Mitchell won the subsequent face-off.</p>
        <p>His teammates then passed the ball for the remainder of the game, and the Blue Devils could not snatch it away.</p>
        <p>This became a hard game for Princeton after an easy beginning. The Tigers' first six shots went through goalie Joe Kirmser as they took a 6-1 lead. Jesse Hubbard, Lorne Smith and Massey seemed able to score at will.</p>
        <p>Then came a furious Duke rally that tied the score at 6-6 at halftime and then gave the Blue Devils a two-goal lead, 9-7, at the close of the third.</p>
        <p>John Fay and his brother, Ed, from Canton, N.Y., found crevices in the Princeton defense and punched goals past Patrick Cairns.</p>
        <p>Duke outscored Princeton by 8-1 in the second and third periods. But it was all Princeton in the final 15 minutes of play.</p>
        <p>The Tigers' discipline never wavered, and they produced three goals, by Jason Osier, Todd Eichelberger and Massey, to none for the Blue Devils as 9-7 became 10-9, Tigers. Massey and John Fay led their teams with three goals apiece.</p>
        <p>LACROSSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
