<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reliable Service With No Fare Increases</title>
    <meta content="09COMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1640547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUTER'S JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models and Replicas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grand Central Terminal (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Transit Museum (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kadden, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grand Central Terminal (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD81039F93AA35752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reliable Service With No Fare Increases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK KADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kadden, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Kadden Commuter's Journal on Holiday Train Show at New York Transit Museum Gallery Annex in Grand Central Terminal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TUCKED away in a dark corner of Grand Central is a little museum that gets very busy this time of year.</p>
        <p>It is the New York Transit Museum Gallery Annex, and the attraction is model trains, which, I know from experience, can have a powerful effect on little boys of all ages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TUCKED away in a dark corner of Grand Central is a little museum that gets very busy this time of year.</p>
        <p>It is the New York Transit Museum Gallery Annex, and the attraction is model trains, which, I know from experience, can have a powerful effect on little boys of all ages.</p>
        <p>For the third straight year, the annex is host to the Holiday Train Show, which runs until Jan. 17. Besides model subway cars decorating the walls, it involves an elaborate model train layout with rural, urban and suburban scenes. The annex has various shows throughout the year, but the train show is consistently the most popular, drawing 120,000 visitors, roughly twice as many as the other exhibitions.</p>
        <p>It was easy to see why on a rainy Wednesday morning as Christopher LoPresti, 4, stood inches from the layout, watching in rapt attention as model trains went by.</p>
        <p>''Look at that subway train!'' he shouted to his mother, Jenny. Christopher's brothers -- Anthony, 7, and Harrison, 1 -- were just as excited.</p>
        <p>''They're fascinated by anything on rails,'' said Mrs. LoPresti of Allentown, N.J. ''It's a race between Anthony and Christopher over who's more obsessed.''</p>
        <p>She added that the boys have their own trains at home. ''We have an O-gauge ceiling layout that goes around Anthony's room, an HO Disneyland train and Brio trains.''</p>
        <p>The boys' father, Anthony, said he was never a big fan of trains, but he works in the Chrysler Building and often stops in at the annex. ''I come here now and then to see what they have on display,'' he said.</p>
        <p>I do the same thing. The annex, which is next to the stationmaster's office on the main floor, is at the top of an escalator that I use almost every day, so it's easy to pop in for a minute or two on my way to work. Besides, it's free.</p>
        <p>Being in a high-traffic place like Grand Central has been critical to the success of the annex, which outdraws the main Transit Museum in Brooklyn by almost 3 to 1 -- it had 270,000 visitors last year, while the museum had 100,000.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely our bread and butter because the volume of visitors is so gigantic,'' said Amy Hausmann, the museum's manager of product development and retail operations. ''We get lots of tourists, we get lots of commuters, we get lots of New Yorkers who are looking for a special gift or who have gone away and want to bring something back.''</p>
        <p>The 2,000-square-foot annex opened in 1999, and roughly half the space is devoted to retail sales -- everything from toy trains and railroad calendars to jewelry made from subway tokens. There's even a Metro-North model train set.</p>
        <p>The museum's retail operation, including its Web site, brings in about $1 million a year, the bulk of it from the annex.</p>
        <p>''The museum relies heavily on the revenue from the stores to support its operations,'' Ms. Hausmann said. ''We make most of our money for the year in these two months.''</p>
        <p>Those two months just happen to coincide with the Holiday Train Show. ''We started doing it in part because we realized people were looking for a holiday train experience,'' Ms. Hausmann said. ''We try to make it as glitzy and fabulous as we can.''</p>
        <p>The layout is sponsored and built by M.T.H. Electric Trains, a Columbia, Md., model train manufacturer. Every year, the layout is trucked to New York for display, then broken down and returned to Maryland for storage. ''It disassembles into four crates,'' said Charles Sheely, product development manager at M.T.H. ''It's kind of like a tiered cake, where the city scene pops off and the country scene pops off. It's the largest layout that we've ever built that's movable.''</p>
        <p>Asked how many feet of track the layout has, Mr. Sheely said he had no idea, ''We're pretty much artists,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The layout includes a Metro-North train, a Long Island Rail Road train, a subway train, and a train pulled by a New Haven Railroad engine. There are sound effects, signal lights, a hobo's flickering campfire, and a blinking neon sign in the window of a hobby shop. The city scene includes Grand Central Terminal, which made its debut in last year's show, and the Chrysler Building, which was added for the current show.</p>
        <p>''I think what we'd like to do is every year add a new addition to the layout, some notable New York landmark,'' said Todd Ludlam, a technician at the Transit Museum.</p>
        <p>The trains on the layout have computer chips inside, and they can operate largely without any human involvement. But in a possible case of art imitating life, Mr. Ludlam said, the Metro-North train was out of service for a day recently.</p>
        <p>''It was accidentally knocked off its rails,'' he said.</p>
        <p>COMMUTER'S JOURNAL E-mail: kadden@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: kadden@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
