<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Music of the Stores</title>
    <meta content="09NJAMBIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1640585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubis, Anastasia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0D61039F93AA35752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Music of the Stores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANASTASIA RUBIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubis, Anastasia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anastasia Rubis essay on demise of quiet, background 'elevator music,' offers random sampling of what is being heard in some stores in New Jersey; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVER notice how ambient music in public places isn't so ambient nowadays? If you've suffered through throbbing temples while navigating a mall or needed throat lozenges after Mom's birthday dinner, you'll hear me when I say, ''I'm overstimulated, and I'm not going to take it anymore.''</p>
        <p>Easy-listening Muzak -- where is ''The Girl From Ipanema'' when you need her? -- was once behavior modification for soothing jangled nerves in the dentist's chair, or the claustrophobia of hurtling down an elevator shaft. While dentists have graduated to DVD's, background music has mutated into a 24/7 assault on the senses. We live with an omnipresent soundtrack to our public lives. Walk into five different stores and your equilibrium is rocked by five clashing ''audio experiences.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVER notice how ambient music in public places isn't so ambient nowadays? If you've suffered through throbbing temples while navigating a mall or needed throat lozenges after Mom's birthday dinner, you'll hear me when I say, ''I'm overstimulated, and I'm not going to take it anymore.''</p>
        <p>Easy-listening Muzak -- where is ''The Girl From Ipanema'' when you need her? -- was once behavior modification for soothing jangled nerves in the dentist's chair, or the claustrophobia of hurtling down an elevator shaft. While dentists have graduated to DVD's, background music has mutated into a 24/7 assault on the senses. We live with an omnipresent soundtrack to our public lives. Walk into five different stores and your equilibrium is rocked by five clashing ''audio experiences.''</p>
        <p>White noise, come back, all is forgiven. Or, if a racket is necessary, how about some New Jersey sounds: Sinatra, a Bayonne tugboat, a semi bellowing down the Turnpike.</p>
        <p>As evil marketers commission studies on how ambient music persuades us to buy more stuff, the only more stuff I seem to crave is Advil. Maybe I'm getting old, but even my husband, John, can't stand the barrage, and he's a musician. ''Abercrombie &amp; Fitch is like a techno club in Ibiza,'' John says, smirking. ''Makes me want to strip and order a vodka tonic.''</p>
        <p>Certain retailers, Victoria's Secret, for example, try to project an upper-crust image by piping in classical music. I don't know about you, but I always blast Bach when wriggling into a thong.</p>
        <p>Here's a random sampling of what you might be bombarded with on a typical day of errands. And, honestly, whatever happened to subliminal?</p>
        <p>SUPERCUTS -- ENGLEWOOD ''Upside down you're turning me, you give your love instinctively,'' shrieks 103.5 FM-WKTU, crackling with commercials. My body sways involuntarily, though I forgot my platform shoes. ''Corporate gives us a choice of which radio stations to play,'' says the manager, Tondra Martinez, but no rap or acid rock. Of the jarring ads, she says, ''They don't want to spend the money on satellite, I guess.''</p>
        <p>Management, however, has invested in psychology. ''They've found that with upbeat music, we cut faster,'' she says. ''With more laid-back music, we slow down.'' So, next time, don't blame a bad haircut on scissors-happy artistes. Blame it on disco.</p>
        <p>BEST BUY -- WEST PATERSON The noise level is like that of a bowling alley trapped inside a Chuck E. Cheese. It's media convergence gone haywire: computers, PlayStations, cellphones, MP3 players, car stereos and a 3-year-old noodling on an electronic keyboard. And add to the mix Best Buy Radio, three corporate CD's produced monthly -- no oldies -- with the obscenities snipped. ''But you can't hear the music with all the TV's and stereos going,'' shrugs the manager, Tom Bergamo, ''unless you're in the middle of the store.''</p>
        <p>No kidding. I venture toward the fridges and washing machines and strain to hear the faintest ''Paper Angels'' by Jimmy Wayne. Suddenly 20 plasma TV's explode with the trailer for ''Sky Captain and the World of Tomorrow.'' I merely jump 10 feet.</p>
        <p>WHOLE FOODS -- MONTCLAIR It's 9 a.m. I'm standing by the kale, pondering organic produce, when a sleepy rendition of, ''Why Did You Have to Be a Heartbreaker?'' wafts up. Followed by: ''I can hardly wait to hold you, feel my arms around you. Don't ever go.'' More whining than 30-something. The store manager says it's DMX Satellite Radio. She typically plays Channel 20, ''Love Songs,'' or Channel 97, ''Familiar Favorites.''</p>
        <p>How about sounds of the rain forest? That's organic. Or some granola-fed folkie from North Dakota? ''I use salsa to get the guys going at 5 a.m. when they come in, though,'' she admits. Well, she just might need something spicier to keep the customers from falling asleep in the salad. Perhaps a dollop of Enya intercut with this affirmation over the loudspeakers: ''I will grow rich enough to afford this store!''</p>
        <p>ABERCROMBIE &amp; FITCH/HOLLISTER -- WILLOWBROOK MALL, WAYNE Party, party, party. Abercrombie's house music must be on, dewy-eyed salesgirls explain. Corporate regulations. They never get sick of it. ''If it's not on, we're bored. At first we don't like it. By the end of the month, we get to know the songs and love it.'' Die-hard customers can tune into last month's in-store entertainment at www.abercrombie.com.</p>
        <p>Music is even more integral at Hollister, the sister store of Abercrombie that mimics a tiki bar. Inside, young suburbanites pretending to be California surfer dudes create their own play lists from a jukebox made by Touch Tune. ''That's the Thrills playing,'' my husband lights up excitedly, punching his own buttons. ''It's post-Britpop. Fountains of Wayne, Franz Ferdinand, Jet, Air, Strokes. See, I can keep up with these kids.'' The alternative rock is more melodic, less driving than at Abercrombie. Music to kick back by and read, say, Skateboard or Thrasher or any number of magazines for sale at the register along with CD's. The loungelike armchairs and coffee tables are regularly dismantled for Hollister rock concerts staged right in the store. ''They're selling lifestyle,'' my husband says in awe as we exit. ''Clothes, music, you can even come out with a girlfriend. I'm surprised they haven't integrated a hair salon or cafe, like American Girl.''</p>
        <p>Now there's an idea.</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
