<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serbs in Bosnia See No Peace for Their Dead . . .;. . . And Are Angry at Leaders and Themselves</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="823523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES(ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LJUBINJE (BOSNIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA &amp;HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4D81139F93BA25752C0A960958260" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serbs in Bosnia See No Peace for Their Dead . . .;. . . And Are Angry at Leaders and Themselves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>LJUBINJE, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Jan. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this rural town, which before the war was part of a successful regional economy and a place where ethnic minorities lived peacefully, many Serbs say they are ashamed of what they have done.</p>
        <p>Following people they now call extremists, they forced their Croatian and Muslim neighbors to flee, and they fought in a war that has left them impoverished, isolated and vilified.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this rural town, which before the war was part of a successful regional economy and a place where ethnic minorities lived peacefully, many Serbs say they are ashamed of what they have done.</p>
        <p>Following people they now call extremists, they forced their Croatian and Muslim neighbors to flee, and they fought in a war that has left them impoverished, isolated and vilified.</p>
        <p>They are now not sure how they will recover, and many want no part of the only thing they feel they gained: a semi-autonomous country within Bosnia known  as the Serbian republic.</p>
        <p>The main streets are filled with men still in uniform, though it would be a mistake to call them an army anymore. Many wear uniforms because that is all they have; they are in the streets because there is no work.</p>
        <p>At a tiny store across from City Hall, eight men in their 20's somberly tried to recall what the war had been about.</p>
        <p>"I don't remember what we were trying to do with this war, and now I don't care," said Zeljko Berberovic. "I got out alive, and now the only thing I want is to leave the Serbian republic. I'll go almost anywhere else."</p>
        <p>The other seven agreed. "Our town suffered for something that is worthless,"  one man said.</p>
        <p>In the area controlled by the Bosnian Serbs, the largest city, Banja Luka, and the village known as the Bosnian Serb capital, Pale, usually generate the most news. But most Bosnian Serbs live in hamlets and towns like this one, and residents here may reflect an attitude more typical than that of, say, Serbs living near Sarajevo, who are moving away rather than subject themselves to Bosnian Government rule.</p>
        <p>If American or NATO officials are worried about widespread Serbian resistance to the peace agreement in places like this, five minutes on these streets could  put their fears to rest.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the war, nearly four years ago, Serbs here withdrew behind trenches and roadblocks, making a front line from which they attacked neighboring areas.</p>
        <p>Now they say that they are eager to contact the world again, and that their difficulty is knowing how to begin. Though they say they hope for assistance and even commerce, they still mistrust their former neighbors and they fear revenge.</p>
        <p>Here the first steps came from the outside.</p>
        <p>On Friday residents were astonished to find that an American relief organization, Nobody's Children, had actually come to see what kind of help was  needed. Two aid workers arrived at the local Red Cross office with a Spanish NATO officer. The officer announced, "I've brought two trucks with food and some clothes."</p>
        <p>The words hung in the air of the tiny, cold, bare office. A local Red Cross official just stared, as if not believing it possible.</p>
        <p>The official had still not recovered when Moira Kelly, an aid worker, began suggesting more elaborate help -- a youth center, she said, or perhaps a public  kitchen serving one meal a day.</p>
        <p>"We have a team of doctors from the States which can come down here," Ms. Kelly said. "And would you be interested in a physiotherapist, say, three times  a week?"</p>
        <p>To a Red Cross official in a town with one remaining dentist, who is so low on supplies that he solves most problems by extraction, the idea of a visiting physiotherapist was hard to grasp.</p>
        <p>That the leaders whom residents followed in war are unable to provide the standard of living they consider basic has further alienated people. United Nations officials say that during the war, the Bosnian Serb leaders usually controlled the distribution of aid, and often diverted much of it to the military.</p>
        <p>By the official census, there are 5,600 people hanging on here, three hours by car from Mostar, which used to be a popular tourist and cultural center. Before the war, people here considered Mostar their regional capital, but now it is on the other side of the former battle line, and today the residents live in  isolation, too afraid to try to get to Mostar.</p>
        <p>Out of a pocket in the smart checkered blazer he still wears, as if to hold on to his past life, Nedo Sikimic pulled photographs of himself and his former colleagues at a Mostar hotel he used to manage, before he fled here.</p>
        <p>"I think about my friends all the time these days," he said. "Most of them were Croats and Muslims. I want to see them again, but I would not feel safe in  Mostar."</p>
        <p>Still, in their yearnings to revive this town and see old friends once again, many skip over the dark parts of what happened here.</p>
        <p>Town officials are keen to talk about foreign investment to restart local businesses but less talkative when asked who organized the expulsion of the town's several hundred Muslim and Croatian residents. The Croatian Catholic church is shot up, and where the mosque once stood, now there is only a concrete slab.</p>
        <p>But the atmosphere in town has changed so much now that people can openly criticize things about which they used to keep silent. In the house next to where the mosque had been, Marko Salvarica, a farmer, said some in the town had  been misled by extremists.</p>
        <p>"The good people here never supported what happened to our neighbors," he said. And then he wondered out loud if it was time the Muslims and Croats came back: "I think they could begin to return. I think they would be safe again now."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
