<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Lawmakers in Support of Superfund</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="823579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY, USA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA) ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTIONAGENCY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED81139F93BA25752C0A960958260" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Lawmakers in Support of Superfund</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The entire New Jersey delegation in the House called on the Republican leadership today to restore "full funding" for the Environmental Protection Agency's Superfund program, which seeks to clean up the most seriously polluted  toxic waste sites in the United States.</p>
        <p>In a letter signed by Republicans and Democrats alike, the delegation said the continuing budget impasse between Congress and the Administration had left the program in "unacceptable" disarray.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The entire New Jersey delegation in the House called on the Republican leadership today to restore "full funding" for the Environmental Protection Agency's Superfund program, which seeks to clean up the most seriously polluted  toxic waste sites in the United States.</p>
        <p>In a letter signed by Republicans and Democrats alike, the delegation said the continuing budget impasse between Congress and the Administration had left the program in "unacceptable" disarray.</p>
        <p>Congress must take prompt action to remedy the situation by approving legislation that President Clinton will sign into law that provides the E.P.A. with the needed funds to maintain its cleanup regime," the letter said.</p>
        <p>It was circulated by Representative Marge Roukema, a moderate Republican from northern New Jersey, and sent to Representative Robert L. Livingston, the Louisiana Republican who is chairman of the House Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>Work stopped this month at hundreds of Superfund sites across the country because the environmental agency lacks the money to supervise and pay private contractors who do the cleanup work. New Jersey has 114 Superfund projects, more than any other state.</p>
        <p>The state's delegation in the House consists of eight Republicans and five Democrats.</p>
        <p>The letter illustrates the kind of widespread discomfort in Congress over the effects of the budget stalemate and the Republican leaders' plans to finance environmental programs only partly for the rest of the year by passing what party leaders call targeted spending bills.</p>
        <p>"I have every intention of mobilizing more support," Mrs. Roukema said, adding that she had already begun to get in touch with members of the New York,  Connecticut and Pennsylvania delegations about the issue.</p>
        <p>House Republican leaders plan to meet next Monday to decide how to go about selecting which programs to target with additional spending beyond Jan. 26, when the latest temporary spending measure expires.</p>
        <p>On the same day moderate Republicans, who have increasingly broken ranks with their leaders on environmental issues, will meet to plan strategies to influence the continuing budget debate, Congressional aides said.</p>
        <p>The problem facing Congressional Republican leaders is how to maintain unity  in their ranks and present narrowly drawn spending bills without opening up the  debate in the House and Senate to proposals to expand the spending.</p>
        <p>Since Oct. 1, the environmental agency has operated under a series of temporary spending measures, punctuated by nearly total shutdowns of its operations.</p>
        <p>As a result, along with cutting back Superfund operations, the agency has suspended most inspections and enforcement actions at factories and treatment plants, delayed issuing regulations called for by environmental laws, cut travel and otherwise restricted its day-to-day activities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
