<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southampton Sleeper With Top Choices</title>
    <meta content="09DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Plaza Cafe, The (Southampton, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E3DB153BF93AA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southampton Sleeper With Top Choices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews The Plaza Cafe in Southampton, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Plaza Cafe is a sleeper. It opened in Southampton in December with little fanfare. It is still not filled to the rafters as are more touted Hamptons spots. But it should be.</p>
        <p>This is the season's best East End restaurant. Plaza Cafe may resemble all the others: sponge-painted walls, bouquets of flowers and airy good looks, but its food makes it a standout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Plaza Cafe is a sleeper. It opened in Southampton in December with little fanfare. It is still not filled to the rafters as are more touted Hamptons spots. But it should be.</p>
        <p>This is the season's best East End restaurant. Plaza Cafe may resemble all the others: sponge-painted walls, bouquets of flowers and airy good looks, but its food makes it a standout.</p>
        <p>This gem is an example of the classic formula for restaurant success, with a chef-owner in the kitchen and co-owner in the dining room.  Douglas and Andrea Gulija, husband and wife, are joined by the older generation. His mother makes the desserts, and his father helps out behind the bar.</p>
        <p>In fact, the whole staff displays a cooperative, family-like, we're-all-in-this-together attitude. Our waitress one evening mentioned that the fresh herbs adorning our plates and the organic raspberries gilding the sorbets were from her garden. All servers are well informed about the ingredients in the dishes, articulate in describing them and efficient and accurate in their delivery.</p>
        <p>''She's the waitress of the year,'' murmured one guest. The woman's model-like looks might have influenced that man's rating but I agree:  She did a terrific job. Service went well beyond the basics. When one diner asked for water without ice and a small cube inadvertently slipped into the glass, it was whisked away and another (without ice) was brought from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Like clockwork, the staff also delivers hot, crusty rolls. When the delicious treats are eaten, others appear. Resist making a pig of yourself over those rolls, for every morsel to follow is a delight. Over the course of three evenings, we ate our way through the menu (plus a half-dozen specials) and found nothing that disappointed. Naturally, some dishes were more appealing than others but that was a matter of personal taste.</p>
        <p>My guests chose the tender, tasty, herb-crusted rack of lamb with its satiny garlic flan, grilled asparagus and earthy morel sauce, and the grilled jumbo shrimp encircling a centerpiece of creamy herbed risotto atop a red pepper coulis with crispy leeks, and other prime picks. I resigned myself to the pasta or the chicken. But I could not play the martyr for long, for both dishes were world class. The penne with huge sauteed shrimp, crunchy asparagus, prosciutto, basil and sun-dried tomatoes was a delicious meld. The moist, juicy free-range chicken sparked by garlic, parsley and lemon was perched above a yummy mound of garlic mashed potatoes.</p>
        <p>Still, fish is the way to go here. The menu is loaded with fish, and the chef is a master of it. Most memorable are the roasted salmon atop a tasty melange of red bliss potatoes, frisee, shallots and haricots verts on a plate drizzled with a mustard seed vinaigrette; flaky sauteed cod in a spunky horseradish crust, snowy white poached halibut augmented by a pale pink lobster sauce, red snapper over Mediterranean-style orzo flecked with black olives, and local bass given a South of the Border spin with an arugula-black bean salad, mango salsa and tracings of chipotle aioli on the plate.</p>
        <p>The chef's signature dish is a seafood shepherd's pie, which is loaded with big chunks of lobster, monkfish, shrimp and shiitakes under a tasty chive-potato crust. A special rivaled it one night: large sea scallops set over a luscious fresh corn polenta that was a cross between the classic and creamed corn.</p>
        <p>A special appetizer selection of oysters on the half shell was an indulgence ($12.95) we found worth every penny. The oysters were enhanced by Absolut vodka, creme fraiche and caviar. The top opener from the menu is the crab cake, a loosely packed giant that goes beyond the cliche. This one shares the plate with a tomato salsa and an avocado vinaigrette. Another hit was the mountain of truly tender pan-seared calamari garnished with field greens, julienned peppers and a lemon-herb vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Salads all passed muster as did a light Manhattan style seafood chowder with mussels in the shell, clams, halibut and fresh corn.</p>
        <p>Desserts ranged from the expected, a satiny creme brulee, to the seldom seen: a warm apple pecan cake with caramel sauce and vanilla ice cream. All of the ice creams were homemade and the trio of sorbets garnished with berries was especially appealing. So, too, was a layering of sponge cake, fresh peaches and butter cream frosting.</p>
        <p>Unlike the many Island restaurants that carry just enough American wine to insulate them from criticism, the Plaza Cafe offers 11 from 8 different makers, often sticking in another one or two by-the-glass selections. Among the 50 all-American choices here are a flavor-filled, concentrated 1995 Palmer chardonnay ($6 a glass, $20 a bottle), a sound, accessible 1995 Columbia Crest sauvignon blanc (ditto) and one of the Island's most outstanding merlots, a soft, intensely fruity 1995 Bedell ($32).</p>
        <p>The Plaza Cafe  61 Hill Street (behind the movie theater), Southampton, 283-9323.  Excellent  Atmosphere The Hamptons look with a warm, friendly afterglow.  Service A+  Recommended dishes Crab cake, calamari, oysters, seafood chowder, all salads, cod, salmon, grilled shrimp, halibut, shepherd's pie, penne, chicken, rack of lamb, bass, red snapper, all desserts.  Price range Appetizers $5.95 to $12.95; entrees $17.95 to $26.95.  Credit cards All the majors.  Hours 5 to 11 P.M. Sunday through Thursday, till midnight Friday and Saturday.  Reservations Recommended.  Wheelchair accessibility No steps.  The Ratings Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Poor to Satisfactory.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambiance and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
