<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1,800 Injured Overwhelming Kenya Hospital</title>
    <meta content="09HOSP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BOMBINGS IN EAST AFRICA: IN NAIROBI"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kenya</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nairobi (Kenya)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya/Nairobi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3D61E3BF93AA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1,800 Injured Overwhelming Kenya Hospital</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenyatta National Hospital in Nairobi is overwhelmed by the grievously maimed and walking wounded; treats 1,600 people in hours after blast; doctors, nurses and technicians are strained to their limits to treat victims of car-bomb attack; hospital is running out of basic supplies; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The grievously maimed and the walking wounded filled the wards, corridors and intensive-care beds at Kenyatta National Hospital here today, and doctors, nurses and technicians were strained to their limits as they struggled to treat the victims of the car-bomb attack on the American Embassy on Friday.</p>
        <p>''This place was filled with blood,'' said Henry Njoroge, an X-ray technician at the hospital, Kenya's largest, which treated 1,600 people in the hours after the blast and has admitted 257 other victims. ''We treated so many who were unconscious and in shock, and we were shocked ourselves.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The grievously maimed and the walking wounded filled the wards, corridors and intensive-care beds at Kenyatta National Hospital here today, and doctors, nurses and technicians were strained to their limits as they struggled to treat the victims of the car-bomb attack on the American Embassy on Friday.</p>
        <p>''This place was filled with blood,'' said Henry Njoroge, an X-ray technician at the hospital, Kenya's largest, which treated 1,600 people in the hours after the blast and has admitted 257 other victims. ''We treated so many who were unconscious and in shock, and we were shocked ourselves.''</p>
        <p>Kenyatta Hospital is running out of X-ray film, respirators, sterile gloves, pain-killing drugs and other basics, hospital administrators and technicians said. A remarkable public response has helped the hospital staff cope so far. Hundreds of people have donated blood, food and blankets. Doctors and medical students have been working around the clock.</p>
        <p>Still, the Red Cross said today that there were blood shortages at some of the seven hospitals treating more than 4,000 wounded, and handwritten signs taped on Kenyatta Hospital's walls appealed for blood donations.</p>
        <p>But brain surgeons and other experts as well as heart monitors and other high-tech equipment will be needed to save the lives of the most seriously wounded, particularly those with head wounds, nurses and doctors said.</p>
        <p>Some medical relief began to arrive this morning as American medical teams flew into Nairobi. An American cargo aircraft carrying 44 people with medical supplies, food and communications equipment touched down just after 9 A.M., and a second arrived a few minutes later with more medical equipment.</p>
        <p>On Friday morning, the 10-story hospital, about two miles from the American Embassy, trembled with the force of the explosion. Within 10 minutes, hundreds of people, their faces torn by flying glass and their bones shattered by the blast and the debris, began streaming into Kenyatta Hospital's front doors. Many victims were driven to the hospital by Kenyans who pitched in to help, as well as by ambulances. Doctors in private practice and off-duty medical students arrived minutes later.</p>
        <p>''It was very overwhelming,'' said Kepha Maroro, a 21-year-old medical student at the University of Nairobi. ''There were so many, we didn't know who to attend to. We were so few, and the numbers were so large. If someone could walk, we could not attend to them.''</p>
        <p>On the seventh floor of the hospital, Alice Mothoni, a 34-year-old government clerk, lay on a metal bed in a room with six other people. She had been on the 16th floor of a building next to the American Embassy when the first blast went off. She and her co-workers rushed to the windows, and the second blast shattered glass that badly cut Miss Mothoni's face.</p>
        <p>In the hospital's intensive care unit on the first floor, doctors and nurses where struggling to save lives tonight. In one crib was a tiny girl with a shattered head, who was listed  as ''unknown African child.'' Three blast victims died in the operating room here today, and five more who were in the intensive care unit also died, a nurse said.</p>
        <p>Kenyatta Hospital's spokesman, Stephen Mureithi, said that Nairobi had never experienced anything as devastating as the explosion on Friday, and that the collective shock had not worn off.</p>
        <p>''We have been touched by horror,'' he said. ''There you are, walking down the street, no worries at all, and suddenly you are in a hospital, with broken bones or a broken skull. But the public response -- we have coped.''</p>
        <p>BOMBINGS IN EAST AFRICA: IN NAIROBI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
