<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Beat</title>
    <meta content="09DICKM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dickstein, Morris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amburn, Ellis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerouac, Jack (1922-69)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Subterranean Kerouac (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DF1038F93AA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Beat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Morris Dickstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dickstein, Morris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Morris Dickstein reviews book Subterranean Kerouac: The Hidden Life of Jack Kerouac by Ellis Amburn; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUBTERRANEAN KEROUAC  The Hidden Life of Jack Kerouac.  By Ellis Amburn.  Illustrated. 435 pp. New York:  St. Martin's Press. $27.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUBTERRANEAN KEROUAC  The Hidden Life of Jack Kerouac.  By Ellis Amburn.  Illustrated. 435 pp. New York:  St. Martin's Press. $27.95.</p>
        <p>Many of the stars of the 60's counterculture have faded -- some weren't that bright to begin with -- but the Beats, who most influenced them, seem to fascinate us more than ever. Perhaps this is because they were genuine writers, not simply media material. A flood of comment burst forth when Allen Ginsberg and William Burroughs died last year. Jack Kerouac's ''On the Road'' (1957), which took six years to find a publisher, has now sold more than three million copies. Greeted mostly by withering reviews when it first appeared, it changed many readers' lives and stimulated writers and performers as different as Norman Mailer, John Updike, Ken Kesey, Bob Dylan, Robert Stone, Thomas Pynchon, Hunter Thompson, Jack Nicholson, Nick Nolte, Jim Morrison and even the buttoned-up Tom Wolfe.</p>
        <p>Numerous biographies and memoirs have traced Kerouac's troubled life since Ann Charters's pioneering work in 1973, a life he himself minutely chronicled in more than 20 volumes. Kerouac was not only blessed with total recall but wrote constantly and, as if anticipating his own fame, saved and neatly filed every scrap of paper. The first installment of his selected letters came out in 1995, and Viking will also publish several volumes culled from his 120 journal notebooks (a selection recently appeared in The New Yorker). Ellis Amburn's ''Subterranean Kerouac'' is only the first of several new biographies.</p>
        <p>What emerges from these books and documents is an absorbing story, at once exhilarating and ineffably sad. Kerouac was one of many gifted outsiders -- Jews, blacks, Southern women, homosexuals, children of working-class immigrants -- who laid siege to American literature after the war. Of all of them he had perhaps the farthest to travel. Born into a French Canadian family in a mill town in Massachusetts, he was a shy and dreamy child who spoke no English till he was 5 or 6 years old. From local fame as a high school football star, he found his way into a peripatetic bohemian world that stretched from Morningside Heights, where he twice dropped out of Columbia, to the Bay Area, Mexico City, Paris and Morocco. Dreading boredom more than death itself, he was always on the move, always searching for new experiences to turn into writing.</p>
        <p>His cross-country travels with the hyperkinetic Neal Cassady proved to be his greatest subject, and Cassady inspired his breakthrough into a new, more spontaneous style. Between the completion of ''On the Road'' in 1951 and its belated publication, Kerouac wrote a dozen works of free-form recollection, all of them rejected by knowing publishers. By the time Ginsberg's ''Howl'' and Kerouac's novel launched the media craze over the Beat Generation, Kerouac had largely lost interest in the Beat ''phenomenon.'' He spent his final decade living with his fierce and bigoted mother, lost contact with his Beat friends (whom she detested) and grew increasingly bitter and conservative. He drank himself to death at the age of 47 in 1969. During this period when Kerouac was out of touch and out of fashion, Ellis Amburn was his last editor, occasionally offering encouragement and querying him about certain passages but forbidden by contract from actually touching his work.</p>
        <p>Amburn makes much of his phone conversations with Kerouac and quotes generously from his own letters, but it's not clear they ever actually met. Though he provides some new details about the publication of Kerouac's last novels, ''Desolation Angels'' and ''Vanity of Duluoz,'' the connection was too limited to provide any personal knowledge. The only justification for telling Kerouac's story again is to shed new light on his work, to explore its indelible impact on American culture. Although Amburn dedicates the book to two eminent critics, F. W. Dupee and Lionel Trilling (''mentors who set me on my life's course''), he disclaims such a literary purpose: ''I leave that formidable task to scholars.'' Instead he sets out to expose Kerouac as a homophobic homosexual who was destroyed not simply by drink and fame but by a fundamental dishonesty -- by guilt feelings about his engagement with art and his attraction to men.</p>
        <p>Despite some careless errors, which suggest haste, Amburn tells much of Kerouac's story quite well. Yet his book is a prime example of what Joyce Carol Oates once called ''pathography,'' a reductive emphasis on dysfunction that not only overshadows the subject's achievements but makes them virtually inconceivable. In its neglect of his books and its zeal to dish up the dirt, this is more like the idol-smashing biography of a pop star than a book about a writer.</p>
        <p>Amburn seems to be of two minds about Kerouac and about the Beats in general: sometimes he trumpets their influence and showers their work with banal superlatives; a few pages later they become despicable specimens of humanity, constantly sleeping with one another, writing about one another, taking drugs with one another and helping to destroy people who come their way, especially women. At one moment the Beats are offering America ''a new vision of human experience, one based on community, freedom, spontaneity and love.'' But when Burroughs shoots his wife, Joan, in a notorious William Tell incident, Amburn describes her as ''the best example of the Beats' abuse of women, a sacrifice on the altar of bogus masculinity and dishonest sexuality.'' There's some truth to this, but he seems never to notice the discrepancies; they're built into his own hyperbolic style.</p>
        <p>Like Ginsberg, Burroughs made no bones about being gay; as much as friendship or writing ambition, homosexuality was the glue that held the Beats together. But Kerouac, as a believing Catholic raised in a hard-drinking working-class family, was clearly tormented by having sex with men, though nearly all the evidence comes from his own words. On a merchant marine ship early in the war, he stumbled into a hotbed of sexual activity in a safely macho milieu. But even when he deals with Kerouac's childhood, describing young Jack's feelings for his older brother, Gerard, and his bosom friend Sebastian (Sammy) Sampas, Amburn sets out to expose any trace of same-sex attraction -- at an age when such feelings are virtually universal. At the same time he keeps insisting that only the guilt was the problem: poor Kerouac should have realized ''that the solution lay in acceptance of his homoerotic self as wholesome and natural'' -- this in the early 1940's! Amburn tries to have it both ways, tracking Kerouac's sex life in prurient detail yet, with the privilege of hindsight, constantly lecturing him from the high ground of a tolerant morality the Beats helped create.</p>
        <p>Just as he documented everything else in his life, Kerouac kept a sex list where he recorded his many relationships with women, including the number of times he slept with each one. None of these affairs lasted more than a year or two, some were much shorter, but as we know from books like ''Tristessa,'' ''Maggie Cassidy'' and ''The Subterraneans,'' they were passionate and intense. Despite his brave confessional honesty in other things, Kerouac did want the world to see him as more heterosexual than he was. He pressed Seymour Krim to censor his introduction to ''Desolation Angels'' so that it attested to his ''non-participating acceptance of the homosexuality of his literary pals.'' But this does not make homosexuality the key to his life, any more than the key can be found in the ugly racism, fascism and anti-Semitism that Amburn also harps upon, mostly on evidence from his miserable last years.</p>
        <p>Amburn muddies the waters by conceding that ''in the end, Kerouac cannot be defined by his beliefs and prejudices any more than he can by his sexuality or even by his violent behavior,'' though this is exactly what he keeps doing in this book. In 1948 Kerouac wrote an unguarded letter to Neal Cassady, the seductive hero of ''On the Road,'' worrying that future readers studying his letters would think him ''queer.''</p>
        <p>''I consider queerness a hostility, not a love,'' he said. ''Posterity will laugh at me if it thinks I was queer . . . little students will be disillusioned.'' More telling than Kerouac's halfhearted denial is his confidence, before he's published a line, that not only his books but his letters would be read someday, that he belongs to literature. He was stubborn in defending the integrity of his work against any editor who tried to alter it, including Amburn. For all his self-loathing, this was finally what mattered to him.</p>
        <p>Amburn is just the kind of reader Kerouac feared, someone who would use his sexual confusions to discredit him. But at other moments Amburn veers wildly in the opposite direction, comparing Kerouac's arrival in San Francisco to Lenin's at the Finland Station (it was ''the start of the Beat Generation's takeover of California'') and arguing that his effect on American morals was greater than anyone since Cotton Mather, the fierce Puritan preacher. By Amburn's logic, Mather's long dark night of repression was undone only by Kerouac's groovy sense of liberation. It would be impossible to list all of Amburn's breaches of literary tact and plain common sense. ''At roughly the same age as Siddhartha and Christ, he began at this period what can only be called his ministry.'' Yet a page earlier he writes of the interracial affair described in ''The Subterraneans'': ''Like many racists, he was prejudiced everywhere except in bed, where his partner's perceived subhuman status neutralized his feelings of inadequacy and enhanced his virility.'' This is sheer rant.</p>
        <p>Kerouac was neither a demon nor a saint but a fallible, notably gentle, deeply conflicted and finally self-destructive person whose dream from childhood was to be a writer, not a moral beacon to humanity. Often the passive observer, he was mesmerized by forceful characters like Ginsberg, Burroughs, their friend Lucien Carr and especially Cassady -- orphan, car thief, ladies' man, con man -- who seemed more at home in their skin, exempt from self-doubt. People who met Kerouac in his prime, like Norman Mailer and Gore Vidal (not always generous in assessing the competition), invariably mention ''the sweetness of his character'' (in Vidal's words), his ''animal charm.''</p>
        <p>Yet in spite of himself, he did become a kind of liberator, freeing other writers from formal conventions as he freed readers, usually young and male, from conventional inhibitions. He loved the great jazz performers for their improvisational genius, which he tried to duplicate in a prose that makes up in vivid lyrical fluency what it lacks in narrative sinew. As one reader wrote, ''He infused that rush of words with some vague and indescribable longing.'' The gospel of the day was home, family and maturity; in ''On the Road'' and other books about his Beat friends, he created a rival myth about spontaneity, flight and living on impulse. It was a wedge that helped crack postwar American culture wide open. The literary bohemianism of the Beats may seem passe, but their restless quest for personal meaning -- through sex, drugs or some form of spiritual discipline -- has become a key part of the way we live now.</p>
        <p>Morris Dickstein's ''Gates of Eden: American Culture in the Sixties'' has recently been reissued with a new introduction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Morris Dickstein's ''Gates of Eden: American Culture in the Sixties'' has recently been reissued with a new introduction.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
