<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Fidel Without Fear; An Old Star Loses His Punch Lines</title>
    <meta content="09ROHT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Grenada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Grenada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D7103BF93AA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Fidel Without Fear; An Old Star Loses His Punch Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>ST. GEORGE'S, Grenada</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fidel Castro, who has used world as his stage since coming to power forty years ago, seems to be playing smaller houses now, as in state visit to tiny island of Grenada; photo; Cuba's famous revolutionary is treated more like dotty old uncle in most capitals today, and welcome in Grenada is festive despite Castro's exhortations (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE high point of Fidel Castro's state visit to this 133-square-mile ''Spice Isle'' last week was the speech he delivered at Tanteen, a cricket field flanked by a simple grandstand and a stack of cargo containers. As a couple of thousand people listened patiently and the occasional dog ambled across the grounds, the Cuban leader lectured Grenadians for an hour and a half on the history of slavery in the West Indies and assorted other topics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE high point of Fidel Castro's state visit to this 133-square-mile ''Spice Isle'' last week was the speech he delivered at Tanteen, a cricket field flanked by a simple grandstand and a stack of cargo containers. As a couple of thousand people listened patiently and the occasional dog ambled across the grounds, the Cuban leader lectured Grenadians for an hour and a half on the history of slavery in the West Indies and assorted other topics.</p>
        <p>Since coming to power nearly 40 years ago, Mr. Castro has used all the world as his stage, but he seems to be playing smaller houses these days. Leslie Pierre, editor of the leading newspaper in this country of 100,000 people, the weekly Grenadian Voice, intended it as a compliment when he called the Cuban president ''a Caribbean man.'' Yet that designation also implies that Mr. Castro and his message matter little these days outside a region that itself seems increasingly on the fringe of world events.</p>
        <p>The Melody Lingers</p>
        <p>Treated in recent years as a dotty old uncle in most capitals, even those of Latin America where his calls for revolution once resonated, Mr. Castro found himself saluted here by Prime Minister Keith Mitchell as an historical figure ''who can only be compared in the 20th Century to Nelson Mandela.'' He was also serenaded with a rousing version of the ''Internationale.''</p>
        <p>But the atmosphere was festive rather than threatening. Without the Soviet Union to back it up, the Communist anthem has lost its ability to frighten the capitalist world. So, too, Mr. Castro.</p>
        <p>A decade and a half ago, the Reagan Administration's fear of Mr. Castro and his seemingly unlimited ability to make mischief generated a bonanza of aid and attention for the newly independent English-speaking states in the Caribbean. Even as the other islands were being promised preferential trade benefits as part of a regional Caribbean Basin Initiative, some 6,000 American troops invaded Grenada in October 1983 to expel Cuban forces, and Washington followed that up with a promise to bring Grenada into the circle of preferred treatment.</p>
        <p>The 1990's, in contrast, have seen the Clinton Administration close down its regional aid office, downgrade the embassy here to a mission and slash aid, grants and scholarships. While Cuba, itself economically prostrate, cannot make up for that gap, Mr. Mitchell and his regional colleagues have seized on Cuba's own need for friends in hopes of creating a countervailing weight to Washington's indifference.</p>
        <p>Whether such a strategy will work is another matter. ''In a post-cold war world, this region unfortunately is no longer relevant'' to the great powers, one diplomat in the region said. Caribbean leaders may see Mr. Castro as a useful card to play to get Washington's attention, ''but I'm not sure even that is true,'' the diplomat added. ''Cuba wants to be headmaster of the Caribbean family, but since it is a Soviet proxy no longer, the United States really doesn't worry about it.''</p>
        <p>During the heyday of Cuba's alliance with Grenada, Mr. Castro aimed high, agreeing to build an airport that could be used to bring in tourists -- and to refuel Cuban planes ferrying troops to and from Africa. This time around, what he was offering seemed modest, even innocuous, reflecting straitened circumstances in both countries: a new wing on a hospital here and 22 additional scholarships for Grenadians to study at Cuban universities.</p>
        <p>For Cuba, the principal benefit of such aid efforts today is not that they advance a geopolitical strategy. Rather, it is that they provide employment for Cuban doctors, engineers and teachers who would otherwise be idle at home or seeking jobs as hotel doormen or taxi drivers.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most telling moment of Mr. Castro's visit, however, came when Grenada's Education Minister, Lawrence Joseph, acknowledged during a meeting that one thing is always certain when local students get scholarships to Cuba. Unlike those who enroll in Britain, Canada or the United States, they always return home just as soon as their studies are done.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
