<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bell Atlantic Phone Workers Go on Strike Over Contract</title>
    <meta content="09STRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Communications Workers of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bell Atlantic Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DF1F3BF93AA3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bell Atlantic Phone Workers Go on Strike Over Contract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of workers at Bell Atlantic go on strike after company and two unions, Communications Workers of America and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, fail to reach agreement on new contract; about 73,000 members of communications workers union go on strike, but 12,000 members of Electrical Workers Union decide not to strike after agreeing to extend contract for few days while talks continue; union officials say key point is union's efforts to get Bell Atlantic to stop expanding its nonunion subsidiaries and moving work done by unionized workers into those subsidiaries; strike is not expected to disrupt normal telephone service for Bell Atlantic customers but will cause some delays in service requests (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of workers at Bell Atlantic walked off the job this morning as the telephone company and two unions failed to reach agreement before the workers' old contract expired at 12:01 this morning.</p>
        <p>The workers began their strike after a day of tense talks between Bell Atlantic and the two unions, the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers. The two sides voiced optimism this morning that they might still be able to reach an agreement today and thus keep the strike very short and the disruption to a minimum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of workers at Bell Atlantic walked off the job this morning as the telephone company and two unions failed to reach agreement before the workers' old contract expired at 12:01 this morning.</p>
        <p>The workers began their strike after a day of tense talks between Bell Atlantic and the two unions, the Communications Workers of America and the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers. The two sides voiced optimism this morning that they might still be able to reach an agreement today and thus keep the strike very short and the disruption to a minimum.</p>
        <p>''We hope to keep negotiating,'' Jeffrey Miller, spokesman for the communications workers union said just after midnight. ''The talks haven't really broken off. We just ran up against the deadline, and our members are adamant that they're not going to work without a contract. So therefore we're on strike. We hope to keep negotiating and work out a settlement.''</p>
        <p>The strike by 85,000 workers is not expected to disrupt normal telephone service for Bell Atlantic's 26 million customers from Maine to Virginia. But the strike will cause delays in reaching directory assistance, in making operator-assisted calls, in contacting business representatives and in having telephone service repaired or new lines installed.</p>
        <p>Susan Kraus, a Bell Atlantic spokeswoman, said in a telephone interview shortly after midnight that the company did not have official notification of a strike.</p>
        <p>''We don't have official notification of that ourselves,'' she said. ''Obviously the deadline has passed, and we're all staying at the bargaining table. We're still trying to bargain and reach a fair agreement. We'll continue to negotiate. Hopefully, we'll be able to announce an agreement soon.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Kraus said Bell Atlantic had put contingency plans in effect, so that management employees would be on duty at 7 A.M. today to do some of the work done by the striking employees. ''We're going to take every step to assure that our customers are served,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Union officials said the main sticking point was the union's efforts to get Bell Atlantic to stop expanding its nonunion subsidiaries and to stop moving work done by unionized workers into those subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said, ''The main problem area remains that whole area of the jobs of the future at Bell Atlantic and whether there's going to be good high-skill high-wage jobs or whether the jobs of the future are going to be marginalized and substandard.''</p>
        <p>The union also said that shortly before midnight it reached a tentative agreement with Bell South, which serves nine states in the Southeast. The settlement, reached in Atlanta, averted a strike by 48,000 workers that was scheduled to begin this morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller said that the phone company workers have a long tradition of walking out as soon as their contract expires, unless a new agreement has already been negotiated. He said repair workers and operators began picketing this morning at a Bell Atlantic building at 40 West Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Phone company and union officials said that two sets of negotiations were held yesterday, in New York City and in Washington. The negotiators have been seeking to reach a single contract, although there will be some separate contract language for employees who worked for Nynex and employees who worked for Bell Atlantic, before the two companies merged.</p>
        <p>In attacking Bell Atlantic's growing use of nonunion operations, officials in the communications workers union complain that two-thirds of the new jobs added by Bell Atlantic over the past three years have gone to nonunion workers, who are generally paid less than the unionized workers. The nonunion workers do telemarketing to sell phone company services, handle some accounts and install advanced phone lines for Internet use.</p>
        <p>According to union officials, one of the company's nonunion subsidiaries, Bell Atlantic Plus, based in Norfolk, Va., has 700 employees and is seeking an additional 1,400 employees. Union officials said that Bell Atlantic had transferred some work done by unionized workers to that new subsidiary -- a move the union fears will jeopardize the job security of union members.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic officials defend these new subsidiaries on the ground that they have lower labor costs than unionized operations.</p>
        <p>Other issues of contention include wages, Bell Atlantic's use of forced overtime, its employing temporary workers and the terms of a long-delayed financial package to encourage workers to take early retirement.</p>
        <p>To step up pressure on the phone company, thousands of Bell Atlantic workers staged a wildcat walkout for two-and-a-half hours on Friday throughout New York State.</p>
        <p>Also on Friday, the communications workers reached a tentative agreement with Southern New England Telecommunications, which provides service to most of Connecticut, averting a strike against SNET.  In that contract, SNET agreed to give the 6,300 unionized workers an 11 percent raise over the 32-month contract and to eliminate any obligation for them to pay premiums toward their health insurance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
