<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop/Jazz; A Maker of Dark Songs That Dig Beneath Logic</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="571690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOEMER, KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLCOMB, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">BiographyReview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DA143EF933A15752C1A964958260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop/Jazz; A Maker of Dark Songs That Dig Beneath Logic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN SCHOEMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHOEMER, KAREN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robin Holcomb was having a hard time being heard. She was sitting in a busy, noisy East Village restaurant trying to articulate her ideas about being a singer, pianist and composer, but the bustle and activity around her seemed to crowd her words; she was trying to explain some of the feminine themes behind her new album, "Rockabye" (Elektra Musician), but the bright lights from the bar seemed to wash out her thoughts. Ms. Holcomb's voice, when speaking or singing, might be placed somewhere in the tradition of women like Joni Mitchell and Emmylou Harris. But drowning her out on the restaurant's sound system was that behemoth of pop commercialism, Michael Jackson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Holcomb regularly struggles with the problem of being heard. In September she opened a benefit concert headlined by 10,000 Maniacs. "I think people really wanted to hear a rock band," Ms. Holcomb said. "I hear every sound in the audience, and it was like a big party going on out there. It was almost psychedelic for me."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robin Holcomb was having a hard time being heard. She was sitting in a busy, noisy East Village restaurant trying to articulate her ideas about being a singer, pianist and composer, but the bustle and activity around her seemed to crowd her words; she was trying to explain some of the feminine themes behind her new album, "Rockabye" (Elektra Musician), but the bright lights from the bar seemed to wash out her thoughts. Ms. Holcomb's voice, when speaking or singing, might be placed somewhere in the tradition of women like Joni Mitchell and Emmylou Harris. But drowning her out on the restaurant's sound system was that behemoth of pop commercialism, Michael Jackson.</p>
        <p>Ms. Holcomb regularly struggles with the problem of being heard. In September she opened a benefit concert headlined by 10,000 Maniacs. "I think people really wanted to hear a rock band," Ms. Holcomb said. "I hear every sound in the audience, and it was like a big party going on out there. It was almost psychedelic for me."</p>
        <p>Tomorrow night Ms. Holcomb performs at the Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity in Brooklyn Heights, where the cathedral ceilings, stained glass and rarefied atmosphere should better enhance her style. For despite the fragility of her persona, Ms. Holcomb has, in the last year or two, quietly and gradually established herself as one of the most dynamic and inventive voices in the singer-songwriter field. Coming from a background that combines folk and rock, poetry and improvisation, "Rockabye" and "Robin Holcomb," her 1990 major-label debut, gracefully dare to redefine the expectations of a singer and songwriter. Songs That Don't Shout</p>
        <p>Ms. Holcomb's songs do not shout, declare or inform. Their narratives are a-linear, and their images provoke on a subliminal and emotional level, rather than a literal and intellectual one. Their tone is often dark, desolate, even violent, but never aggressive or obvious. And beneath their fragility is a distinctly feminine core of strength.</p>
        <p>"Rockabye," the title track of the new album, discusses the need for safety and security in an unsure world:</p>
        <p>I remember a room lit by one brilliant light</p>
        <p>Throw the windows wide open</p>
        <p>We'll sit in the dark tonight.</p>
        <p>"So Straight and Slow," from "Robin Holcomb," juxtaposes images from a road trip as loosely as scenes passed from a highway: "a deer struck down by a car," "no open gas off the interstate."</p>
        <p>"That comes from something that happened," Ms. Holcomb said. "I used to drive across the country a lot, in this old VW. I did it quite a few times in the space of a few years. Once we ran out of gas in this reservation in the very early morning hours. We were waiting for the gas station to open. There was a Native American -- I forget what tribe he was from -- and he said, 'Come in.' We drank beer trying to stay awake. It was this eerie morning, right in the middle of the heart of the country. The deer thing comes from a poem I read in some anthology of Native American poetry. It just seemed to make sense."</p>
        <p>"I'd like to be able to tell more literal stories," she added. "It's hard. It seems to be how it works for me, to imply a lot of things." Growing Up in California</p>
        <p>In general, Ms. Holcomb's style derives from two sets of influences: traditional folk music and avant-garde improvisational technique. "I've always listened to Cecil Taylor and the Art Ensemble of Chicago, and the Band and Bob Dylan," she said. "It was never really one or the other. I wrote poems for a long time when I was in my late teens, early 20's. In college I fell into improvising at the piano."</p>
        <p>Now in her mid-30's, Ms. Holcomb was born in Georgia but spent most of her youth in the California mountain region near Santa Cruz and San Jose. Her father was a trombonist who played in various big-band and jazz combos; her mother was a weaver and craftswoman. She studied composition at the University of California at Santa Cruz, where she met the composer Wayne Horvitz, who is now her husband. "I think Wayne had the key to the concert hall there," she said. "It had this great piano. Sometimes we'd go in there late at night and just play all night."</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, Ms. Holcomb participated in the downtown New York experimental scene. She switched from writing words to writing music, and for a while performed instrumental pieces, which appeared on two albums, "Larks They Crazy" and "Todos Santos," recorded for the European label Sound Aspects.</p>
        <p>In 1986, she gave birth to a daughter, Nica. "Maybe it's coincidence, but I started singing after Nica was born," Ms. Holcomb said. "I started to write more songs about that time. It just happened that way. Now I make up songs for her a lot, and I seem to write more lullabies. There's songs that she definitely doesn't like and songs that she does. It's sort of like a new critic on the earth."</p>
        <p>Being a singer and songwriter "is something I longed for for many years," Ms. Holcomb said. "I remember walking along the East River and saying, 'I should just give up all this free improvising and write songs,' but I didn't have the nerve to do it. Now I'm doing something that I've wanted to do all my life, and Nica's here. It's nice that it happened at the same time."</p>
        <p>Ms. Holcomb performs tomorrow night as part of the Arts at St. Ann's series at the church, 157 Montague Street, at Clinton Street, Brooklyn Heights. Show time is 8 P.M. Tickets are $15 for reserved seats, $13 general admission. Information: (718) 858-2424.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
