<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.I.'S TO INCREASE U.S. SUPERVISION OF IRAQI POLICE</title>
    <meta content="30military" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/30/international/middleeast/30military.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1728466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5D61330F933A05751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.I.'S TO INCREASE U.S. SUPERVISION OF IRAQI POLICE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">G.I.'s to Increase U.S. Supervision of Iraqi Police</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEXTER FILKINS</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Dec. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American commanders are planning to increase significantly the number of soldiers advising Iraqi police commando units, in part to curtail abuse that the units are suspected of inflicting on Sunni Arabs, a senior commander in Iraq said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, which the officer said he expected would be formally approved in a few weeks, the number of advisers working with the Iraqi units would be greatly expanded. The advisers themselves would be under the command of American officers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The increase in Army advisers aims in part to curtail abuse that Iraqi units are suspected of inflicting on Sunni Arabs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American commanders are planning to increase significantly the number of soldiers advising Iraqi police commando units, in part to curtail abuse that the units are suspected of inflicting on Sunni Arabs, a senior commander in Iraq said Thursday.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, which the officer said he expected would be formally approved in a few weeks, the number of advisers working with the Iraqi units would be greatly expanded. The advisers themselves would be under the command of American officers.</p>
        <p>American advisers now accompany commando units as part of the vast effort to train and equip security forces to take over the fight against the insurgency and to maintain order.</p>
        <p>But the number of advisers is relatively small: currently, groups of about 40 American soldiers each are attached to seven of the nine special Iraqi police brigades.</p>
        <p>Under the new plan, which would be put in force in and around Baghdad, all the Iraqi units would get American advisers, and the advisers' total number would be increased by several hundred, said the commander, who spoke to reporters in Baghdad only on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>In one case, he said, an entire American battalion, typically with more than 500 soldiers, will be attached to a particular Iraqi brigade.</p>
        <p>The increase is seen as a way to exert firmer control over the commando units, which are suspected of carrying out widespread atrocities against civilians in Sunni Arab neighborhoods. Human rights groups here say the units may be guilty of murdering and torturing hundreds, and possibly thousands, of Sunni Arab men of military age.</p>
        <p>The conduct of the commandos has become a source of intense friction between the Shiite-led Iraqi government and American officials, who say the reports of the atrocities are jeopardizing the campaign to persuade Sunnis to stop supporting the insurgency.</p>
        <p>The plan to increase the number of American advisers is a significant departure from the overall American strategy of giving the Iraqis the lead role in fighting the insurgency. Indeed, the allegations of atrocities arose only after Americans began to give the Iraqi units more freedom to act on their own.</p>
        <p>Even as he talked about the increase in advisers, the officer confirmed details of a shift to fewer American troops covering more Iraqi ground.</p>
        <p>The Fourth Infantry Division, which is now preparing to deploy in Baghdad and central Iraq, is being given a substantially larger piece of Iraqi territory than the unit it is replacing, and with fewer troops. The Americans are hoping that Iraqi units can pick up the slack; Iraqi forces operating more or less independently now are in charge of securing 60 percent of the capital.</p>
        <p>Many of the Iraqi commando units are thought to be filled by gunmen drawn from the military wings of Shiite political parties, including the Supreme Council for the Islamic Revolution in Iraq, or Sciri, which forms part of the Shiite coalition that is expected to lead the next government. The Mahdi Army, a militia run by the rebel cleric Moktada al-Sadr, is also believed to have hundreds of gunmen working in the Iraqi police and commando units.</p>
        <p>As a result, the units, which are ostensibly under the control of the Interior Ministry, are thought to be all but indistinguishable from Sciri's militia, known as the Badr Brigade, and from the Mahdi Army.</p>
        <p>American officials say it is unclear whom the units are taking orders from, the ministry or militia commanders. The minister of the interior, Bayan Jabr, is a senior member of the Badr Brigade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jabr is fighting the American plan to place more advisers in the Iraqi commando units, according to the senior American commander. ''We'd know exactly what they are doing, and we'd have some more control,'' the commander said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the American headquarters in charge of training in Iraq, Lt. Col. Fred Wellman, confirmed that preparations for an increase in advisers were under way.</p>
        <p>A similar plan is already in place with the Iraqi Army, whose soldiers have a reputation among Iraqis as being more humane than the commandos.</p>
        <p>The police commando units and public order brigades, which together contain about 15,000 troops, are considered to be some of the most effective Iraqi fighters against the insurgency.</p>
        <p>In contrast to conditions in the new Iraqi Army, American supervision of the commandos has been lax; some units, which include former members of the Iraqi Army, came together and began fighting the insurgency on their own, without formal American or Iraqi approval.</p>
        <p>''The commandos and the public order brigades sort of grew like Topsy, very quickly, without much control, and without much training, but with lots of influence from the Ministry of the Interior and the Sciri-Badr organization,'' the American commander said. ''The exact roles and responsibilities of those units is not clear to us.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the commander painted a troubling picture of security in Baghdad, where some armed militias appear to act with the backing of the Ministry of the Interior and the Ministry of Defense.</p>
        <p>''It is not easy to identify that some operation tonight was legitimately directed by somebody in the security organization of M.O.I. or M.O.D.,'' the commander said, ''or whether it was some people in stolen uniforms, or somebody's posse or militia or projection cell who decided to attack someone's opposite number in some other tribe or neighborhood.''</p>
        <p>A police commando unit was thought to be responsible for running the secret underground prison raided by Americans in November. Nearly 170 Iraqis were found inside, some bearing signs of torture.</p>
        <p>With that, the Americans vowed to clamp down on human rights abuses by the police and military and have since raided two more prisons, one in Baghdad and the other in Tal Afar. Inmates in both of those prisons showed signs of abuse, American officials said.</p>
        <p>American commanders here say that such practices, while abhorrent in their own right, tend to provoke consequences almost precisely the opposite of what is desired. Rounding up young Sunni Arab men and killing them will only spur the growth of the insurgency, they say.</p>
        <p>''You are making new enemies here,'' the American commander said. ''You've got to be more moderate. You must follow the rule of law.''</p>
        <p>The commander also gave a snapshot of progress against the insurgency in and around Baghdad, and of the shifting role of American and Iraqi forces.</p>
        <p>American soldiers in and around Baghdad are still being attacked an average of 28 times a day, and as many as 18 soldiers a month are being killed. Still, the number of suicide and car bombings has fallen sharply, from about 20 a week in April and May, to about 6 now.</p>
        <p>The Third Infantry Division, whose 30,000 troops are deployed over 1,600 square miles around Baghdad, will soon be replaced by about 25,000 soldiers from the Fourth Infantry Division, who will take over a much larger area. The Fourth Infantry, which is returning for its second tour in Iraq, will be responsible for the territory between Taji, north of Baghdad, all south to the Saudi border -- a huge area including Baghdad, Najaf and Karbala.</p>
        <p>Iraqi forces will be counted on to give more support to the Americans. Twelve Iraqi battalions are now responsible for their own territory inside Baghdad. As the Iraqi battalions take over in Baghdad, the commander said, the American units will be able to move to areas outside Baghdad.</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
