<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shareholders Win in Effort To Alter Pay</title>
    <meta content="Y27PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/27/business/27PLAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1515014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Market Place"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Siebel Systems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Teachers Retirement System of Louisiana</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siebel, Thomas M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Siebel Systems Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Teachers Retirement System</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0DC1039F934A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shareholders Win in Effort To Alter Pay</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shareholders Win in Effort to Alter Pay</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Siebel Systems, maker of customer service software and company known for giving its management and directors plenty of stock options, agrees to change its executive compensation practices, modify its board and improve its disclosure of executive and director pay; company agrees to changes as part of settlement in lawsuit brought by shareholder Teachers Retirement System of Louisiana; settlement is latest in series of concessions made by large US companies to their increasingly restive shareholders; chief executive Thomas M Siebel comments; photo (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For what seems like forever, activist shareholders have been fighting to rein in runaway executive pay -- and losing every battle. Yesterday, the forces against excessive compensation won one.</p>
        <p>Siebel Systems, a maker of customer service software in San Mateo, Calif., and a company known for festooning its management and directors with stock options, agreed yesterday to change its executive compensation practices, modify its board and improve its disclosure of executive and director pay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Siebel Systems, a company founded by Thomas M. Siebel and known for its generous stock options, agreed to change its compensation practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For what seems like forever, activist shareholders have been fighting to rein in runaway executive pay -- and losing every battle. Yesterday, the forces against excessive compensation won one.</p>
        <p>Siebel Systems, a maker of customer service software in San Mateo, Calif., and a company known for festooning its management and directors with stock options, agreed yesterday to change its executive compensation practices, modify its board and improve its disclosure of executive and director pay.</p>
        <p>The company, founded and run by Thomas M. Siebel, agreed to the changes as part of a settlement in a lawsuit brought by a shareholder, the Teachers Retirement System of Louisiana.</p>
        <p>''Siebel was well known for being out there on the executive pay scale, way out on the extreme,'' said Stuart M. Grant, a partner at Grant &amp; Eisenhofer in Wilmington, Del., and the lawyer for the Louisiana fund. ''If Tom Siebel is coming back into the fold and saying 'I can live with these corporate governance changes,' then certainly the others in Silicon Valley ought to be doing the same thing.''</p>
        <p>The settlement is the latest in a series of concessions made by large United States companies to their increasingly restive shareholders. Some have been a result of shareholder litigation, while others have come from regulatory pressure. For example, in a settlement with shareholders this year, Sprint appointed an independent director to oversee its board. And MCI said yesterday that it would limit the terms of its directors as it adopted governance changes recommended by a court-appointed monitor.</p>
        <p>Under the terms of the settlement with the retirement fund, Siebel will advise shareholders of the specific criteria used by its compensation committee to determine executives' and directors' pay. The company also said it would add a new director to its board and allow officials of the retirement fund to have significant input in that director's selection. Three of the company's board committees -- those relating to compensation, nominating and corporate governance -- will expand from two members to three.</p>
        <p>Siebel also agreed to reimburse the retirement fund for up to $900,000 in legal fees associated with the suit, if the court requires it. And for the next three years, the company's outside auditor will scrutinize its practices to ensure that Siebel complies with all aspects of the settlement.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey R. Amann, general counsel at Siebel, said: ''As a company, we have always been committed to high standards of corporate governance and disclosure practices. So we are happy any time we have a chance to enhance those practices. The settlement gave us an opportunity to do so.''</p>
        <p>Siebel was sued last September by the $10 billion retirement fund, which owns 392,000 Siebel shares. The fund's lawyers contended that between 1996 and 2001, the company's board awarded more stock options to Mr. Siebel than shareholders had approved. The suit also contended that option grants to some Siebel directors were not disclosed. The suit was scheduled to be heard in California state court in November.</p>
        <p>Carol Bowie, director of governance research services at the Investor Responsibility Research Center in Washington, said that the Siebel settlement represented a shift in the balance of power between executives and investors.</p>
        <p>''The shareholder-management relationship is going through a sea change, with shareholders asserting their prerogative as owners of the company,'' she said. ''We went through a long period where shareholders didn't interfere with management. These lawsuits are not just to recoup money anymore -- they involve forcing companies to change their practices.''</p>
        <p>Since its creation in 1993, Siebel has been a big believer in stock options. From 1996 through 2001, Mr. Siebel received options worth almost $1 billion when granted, according to the Louisiana lawsuit. From 1998 to 2001, Mr. Siebel exercised almost six million options, realizing gains of $321 million, the lawsuit said.</p>
        <p>Even as Siebel's compensation committee doled out the maximum amount of options to the chief executive, it met less and less often, the lawsuit noted. In 1996, when Mr. Siebel earned $320,000 in cash and two million options, the committee met five times. In 2000, when he received $2.5 million in cash and eight million options, the committee met just once.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, Siebel will limit the compensation of its directors to levels that have been disclosed previously to shareholders. Siebel's directors include Charles R. Schwab, the brokerage executive; Eric E. Schmidt, the chairman of Google, the closely held Internet search-engine company; and George T. Shaheen, the former chief executive of Webvan, an Internet grocery store that is now defunct. Marc F. Racicot, the chairman of President Bush's re-election campaign and a former governor of Montana, is another board member.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amann could not specify exactly which details relating to the company's compensation practices would be disclosed to shareholders by the compensation committee in coming years. ''We believe it's important for compensation committees to explain to shareholders how they arrive at certain compensation practices and we have agreed to take that to the next level,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Siebel received $1 in salary and no bonus or options. And in January, he surrendered 26 million options that he had received since 1998. Siebel stock has lost 92 percent of its value since its peak in 2000, putting many of Mr. Siebel's options under water.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grant said that the settlement with Siebel achieved two goals: It cured dubious practices from the past, and will help prevent those practices from recurring. Forcing the company to justify its compensation practices, he said, may result in better pay decisions.</p>
        <p>''We are hoping that other companies will start voluntarily adopting many of the provisions we have in the settlement,'' Mr. Grant said. ''But if they don't, I think you're also going to see shareholder resolutions trying to adopt some of these things.''</p>
        <p>Market Place</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
