<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Heirs of Franco Woo Spain's Centrist Voters</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SPAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANZAR, JOSE MARIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5D71F39F935A15752C0A960958260" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Heirs of Franco Woo Spain's Centrist Voters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, Jan. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Franco could have come back from the dead and visited Madrid this weekend, the old dictator would have had trouble distinguishing right from left and friend from foe.</p>
        <p>The people who he thought would carry on his right-wing ideas were gathered at a party convention, singing and applauding. But there were no veterans in uniform or stiff-arm salutes in sight. Instead, the right-wing Popular Party had outfitted itself with cobalt blue banners and large video screens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Franco could have come back from the dead and visited Madrid this weekend, the old dictator would have had trouble distinguishing right from left and friend from foe.</p>
        <p>The people who he thought would carry on his right-wing ideas were gathered at a party convention, singing and applauding. But there were no veterans in uniform or stiff-arm salutes in sight. Instead, the right-wing Popular Party had outfitted itself with cobalt blue banners and large video screens.</p>
        <p>Stranger still was the conference slogan. Proclaiming "The Center Is Winning," the party asserted that it now stood at the political center of Spain.</p>
        <p>Recasting the conservative opposition party as centrist and moderate is a key step in the election strategy of Jose Maria Aznar, 42, the man who is well placed to become Spain's next Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>As he prepares to run in the general election on March 3, Mr. Aznar is taking no risks. The Socialists, who have governed Spain for the last 13 years, have long held that they occupied the center. The conservatives know that this is the ground they must now conquer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aznar has been anxious to erase his party's long-standing association with the right and with the 36-year Franco dictatorship, which ended with Franco's death in 1975. Many Spaniards still have dark memories or knowledge of  Franco's time.</p>
        <p>"Do you want the fascists in power again?" is a phrase that makes many Spaniards uncomfortable, and it has been used effectively against Mr. Aznar and  his followers.</p>
        <p>But it may not work this time. The Socialists are increasingly cornered by corruption and political scandals. Spaniards who normally thrive on political gossip and conspiracy theories say they are tired of Socialist infighting and of officials charged with embezzlement and theft.</p>
        <p>"We just want change, even boring change will be better," said Angel Asturias, a teacher who was taking his class to the Prado Museum and said he would vote reluctantly for Mr. Aznar.</p>
        <p>It is a point Mr. Aznar himself now likes to make. This weekend, he told his  party conference: "Although there are people who say they don't like us, the need for change is so great that they will vote for us. We will get a majority."</p>
        <p>Polls give Mr. Aznar a lead of up to 10 points over his opponent, Prime Minister Felipe Gonzalez.</p>
        <p>The two men could not be more different. Mr. Gonzalez, a seductive politician and fiery speaker, spent much of his youth dodging Franco's political police. Mr. Aznar worked as a tax collector. His manners are stiff and his speeches, despite coaching, remain stern and droning.</p>
        <p>Although the election campaign does not formally begin until February, the two camps have already spent so much time slinging abuse at each other that insiders say it has interfered with Government business.</p>
        <p>Adolfo Suarez, a former Prime Minister, believes that the sour mood of the capital is due in part to the tensions between the candidates. He has quietly mediated between Mr. Gonzalez and Mr. Aznar and tried to get them to communicate.</p>
        <p>"I know and I like them both," he said in an interview last November. "But they don't trust each other. The problem is almost physical. They can't stand each other's company."</p>
        <p>Jesus Ceberio, the editor of El Pais, a leading newspaper that was once a strong supporter of Mr. Gonzalez, said Spain urgently needed change because of the erosion of political life. He said the vitriolic mood had permeated journalism and led to wild and often unsubstantiated accusations against politicians and officials in the press. "Many publications have abandoned all standards of decency and fairness," he said. "They print anything: rumor, lies,  insults. Radio stations are now the worst."</p>
        <p>This weekend, the mood in the ranks of the Popular Party was more than buoyant. Its three-day convention in a brightly lighted hall festooned with banners and throbbing with snappy songs, seemed to have taken more from American political conventions than from traditional Spanish style.</p>
        <p>After a carefully orchestrated entrance, Mr. Aznar strode to the platform for an address that had the grave tone of an inaugural speech. This was not just a party convention, he said. "This is the conference of a Government," he announced, his face glowing with confidence.</p>
        <p>But three days of pomp and endorsement of Mr. Aznar's leadership did not produce a concrete program for the party. Mr. Aznar promised to bring decency back into public life, cut the income tax, trim the public sector and negotiate  with Spain's influential labor unions.</p>
        <p>Across town, labor leaders holding their own convention sounded skeptical. They wanted to know more about Mr. Aznar's private promises to businessmen, which included cutting social spending and changing labor laws to make it easier to fire workers.</p>
        <p>"Remember the French," said one leader, referring to the strikes that paralyzed much of France in December after the Government announced plans to dismantle parts of the welfare state.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
