<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Performer Who's Early In a Singer's Lifespan</title>
    <meta content="31hugh" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/31/arts/music/31hugh.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DC123FF932A05753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="462" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Performer Who's Early In a Singer's Lifespan</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Performer Who’s Early in a Singer’s Lifespan</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 22, an appealing actor or a gifted tennis player can be well into a successful professional career. Most classical pianists start young and by their early 20's are already experienced performers.</p>
        <p>But a voice suitable for classical music takes time to reveal itself. So at 22, many singers are just starting to explore the full nature and capacity of their voices. This seems true of the gifted California-born bass-baritone Evan Hughes, who gave a smartly programmed and sensitively sung recital on Sunday afternoon at St. Bartholomew's Church in Manhattan, accompanied by Tamara Sanikidze, a technically nimble and supportive pianist. This was the first event in this season's ''On Wings of Song'' recital series, presented by the Marilyn Horne Foundation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The gifted bass-baritone Evan Hughes gave a smartly programmed and sensitively sung recital on Sunday afternoon at St. Bartholomew’s Church in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 22, an appealing actor or a gifted tennis player can be well into a successful professional career. Most classical pianists start young and by their early 20's are already experienced performers.</p>
        <p>But a voice suitable for classical music takes time to reveal itself. So at 22, many singers are just starting to explore the full nature and capacity of their voices. This seems true of the gifted California-born bass-baritone Evan Hughes, who gave a smartly programmed and sensitively sung recital on Sunday afternoon at St. Bartholomew's Church in Manhattan, accompanied by Tamara Sanikidze, a technically nimble and supportive pianist. This was the first event in this season's ''On Wings of Song'' recital series, presented by the Marilyn Horne Foundation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hughes's voice is earthy and warm. He sings with good technique and musicianship. Lanky and personable, he proved a naturally communicative artist who is sure to gain confidence as his voice matures.</p>
        <p>One of his teachers was Ms. Horne, who worked with him at the Music Academy of the West in Santa Barbara, Calif. Last year he won a competition there sponsored by Ms. Horne's foundation. Hence this New York recital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hughes grew up in Santa Barbara, and singing was part of his upbringing. During a brief post-performance interview with the tenor Robert White, which was taped for broadcast on WQXR, the radio station owned by The New York Times Company, on the evening of Nov. 11 , Mr. Hughes was asked for his earliest memory of hearing inspired singing. In the womb, he replied. His mother, a soprano, was pregnant with him when she was a student at the Academy of the West and sang Susanna in scenes from Mozart's ''Nozze di Figaro.''</p>
        <p>For this 60-minute program he chose music that clearly mattered to him. The longest work came last, ''To Cast a Shadow Again,'' a song cycle composed in 1991 by the American composer Eric Ewazen. It sets a group of elusive poems by Katherine Gekker that explore the intimate rituals and ultimate loss of love. To the mix of voice and piano the composer adds a solo trumpet that mostly functions as a commentator, weaving pensive, consoling and assertive lines in between the vocal phrases. Mr. Ewazen's conventional harmonic language is reminiscent of Samuel Barber's. Still, the music was authentic and moody, with some episodes of gnashing intensity.</p>
        <p>Though Ms. Sanikidze and the trumpeter, Rachel Serber, played beautifully, it was Mr. Hughes's vulnerable singing that pulled you into the work. He also gave tender renditions of Jacques Ibert's bewitching ''Chansons de Don Quichotte'' and fine accounts of five Schubert lieder.</p>
        <p>''On Wings of Song'' will be presented next on Dec. 3, at St. Bartholomew's Church, Park Avenue at 51st Street; (212) 378-0248.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
