<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Envoy Arrives in Iraq As Tough Options Loom</title>
    <meta content="31policy" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/31/world/middleeast/31policy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1801206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hadley, Stephen J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunni Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hadley, Stephen J</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maliki, Nuri Kamal al-</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Casey, George W Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baker, James A III</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D9123FF932A05753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Envoy Arrives in Iraq As Tough Options Loom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Envoy Arrives in Iraq as Tough Options Loom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and JOHN F. BURNS; David E. Sanger reported from Washington, and John F. Burns from Baghdad. Sabrina Tavernise contributed reporting from Baghdad.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F; Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush's national security adviser Stephen J Hadley makes unannounced trip to Baghdad to discuss how to pull country back from brink; options said to include substantial increase in number of American and Iraqi troops patrolling Baghdad; other proposals now being discussed range from how to permit greater autonomy for Shiite, Sunni and Kurdish sections of country without splitting country apart; how to share oil revenues among Iraq's population; and amnesty for those who attacked Iraqi or American troops; before his trip, Hadley described series of American goals, including new effort to get more financial and other support from neighboring states; critics of Bush administration, many of them Republican, say administration must lower its sights for democratic Iraq and simply regain semblance of stability there; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush's national security adviser, Stephen J. Hadley, arrived in Baghdad on Monday on an unannounced trip to discuss how to pull the country back from the brink.</p>
        <p>Though American officials would describe Mr. Hadley's talks only in the vaguest of terms, one option widely discussed in Washington and Baghdad in the days before his arrival, according to American and Iraqi officials, is a substantial increase in the number of American and Iraqi troops patrolling Baghdad. It would signal yet another effort to reassert control over the Iraqi capital, which officials in both governments said remains their top priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>One option, according to officials, is a substantial increase in the number of American and Iraqi troops patrolling Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush's national security adviser, Stephen J. Hadley, arrived in Baghdad on Monday on an unannounced trip to discuss how to pull the country back from the brink.</p>
        <p>Though American officials would describe Mr. Hadley's talks only in the vaguest of terms, one option widely discussed in Washington and Baghdad in the days before his arrival, according to American and Iraqi officials, is a substantial increase in the number of American and Iraqi troops patrolling Baghdad. It would signal yet another effort to reassert control over the Iraqi capital, which officials in both governments said remains their top priority.</p>
        <p>Those officials cautioned that no decision had been made about that option, which would amount to a third effort this year to contain the spreading violence in Baghdad. On Monday evening, J. D. Crouch, the deputy national security adviser, said Mr. Hadley was in Iraq to express support for the Iraqi government and warned, ''He is not preconfiguring military options.'' Mr. Crouch added that he was ''not aware'' of anyone proposing an increase in American troops.</p>
        <p>Other American officials said that such options have been informally discussed. They said that before any American forces in Baghdad could be increased, Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki of Iraq would have to deliver more Iraqi troops, who would patrol the streets of the capital along with the Americans and take the lead whenever possible.</p>
        <p>Other proposals now being discussed inside and outside the two governments range from how to permit greater autonomy for Shiite, Sunni and Kurdish sections of the country without splitting the country apart; how to share oil revenues among Iraq's population; and an amnesty for those who attacked Iraqi or American troops.</p>
        <p>Many of these options may not be dealt with for months, because Shiites, Sunnis and Kurds within the ''unity government'' in Baghdad are still far apart on issues touching on Iraq's division of power and wealth.</p>
        <p>In an interview Friday evening, Mr. Hadley said that ''I wish you could find a silver bullet that could solve this in 30 days,'' but that ''I doubt it.''</p>
        <p>He described a series of American goals, including a new effort to get more financial and other support from neighboring states, saying that ''given the risks of chaos in Iraq, and given the threat and aspirations of Iran,'' each country in the region has ''a huge stake'' in a stable Iraq. But such appeals have failed in the past.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hadley faces critics -- many in his own party -- who say that the Bush administration's effort has devolved to picking the least bad of a dismal set of options, and that the administration must lower its sights for a democratic Iraq and simply regain a semblance of stability there.</p>
        <p>''It is folly to think we can win in Iraq the way some of us thought possible in 2003,'' Eliot A. Cohen, the director of the Center for Strategic Studies at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, wrote this month in The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>Speaking in Baghdad on Sunday as Mr. Hadley headed to Iraq to meet him, Mowaffak al-Rubaie, Iraq's national security adviser, seemed to set out a Shiite vision when he said that while Shiites ''have the numbers'' in Baghdad, Sunnis who joined in building the new Iraq could look forward to ''sharing the wealth'' in oil.</p>
        <p>But he implied that Sunnis were having difficulty reconciling to the new political realities. ''Some of these politicians are not prepared, mentally or psychologically, to make the compromises necessary for us to live cohabitively,'' he said.</p>
        <p>More Troops</p>
        <p>In the interview on Sunday, Mr. Rubaie declined to discuss specifics of recent conversations with Washington over increasing troop levels. But he said, ''Baghdad is the core of the issue.'' When it comes to turning the tide of the war, he said, ''It's Baghdad, Baghdad, Baghdad.''</p>
        <p>American officials in Washington and Baghdad who discussed changes in the Baghdad security plan, including possible troop increases, said it was unlikely that any announcements would be made until after the elections on Nov. 7. Bush administration officials have said that any major changes in American policy will require bipartisan support, and they are clearly waiting to see which party will control the House, and possibly the Senate, before proceeding. A week ago, General George W. Casey Jr., the top American commander in Iraq, said that if he needed more troops, ''I will ask for the troops we need, both coalition and Iraqi.''</p>
        <p>In Washington, the debate over whether to increase troops comes as the White House seems to be groping for new ideas. The administration has resisted efforts to increase the overall number of American troops in Iraq. At times, tours have been extended for individual brigades, which amount to about 5,000 troops, for 90 days or so. But recent history suggests that any plan to significantly increase the American deployment in Baghdad would require more sweeping changes, by keeping 10,000 to 30,000 troops in Baghdad beyond their scheduled rotations home, even as new troops rotate in.</p>
        <p>In the interview on Friday evening, Mr. Hadley declined to discuss internal deliberations. Still, he said: ''Everyone says there is no military solution to the problem. That's true. But you also have this Catch-22 element to the problem. You can't have security without political and economic progress, but it's hard to have political and economic progress without security. There is some minimum element of security you need.''</p>
        <p>Outside experts who favor an American withdrawal say that almost all the options now being considered would be doomed to failure.</p>
        <p>''It's not going to make any difference,'' said Peter W. Galbraith, the author of ''The End of Iraq'' (Simon &amp; Schuster) and a scholar at the Center for Arms Control and Non-Proliferation. ''It's not a country, and you can't build an army in the midst of a civil war. And elements of the Iraqi army are partisans in the civil war. You can't use the combatants as if they were neutral players.''</p>
        <p>Regional Governments</p>
        <p>In Washington, Senator Joseph R. Biden Jr. of Delaware, the top Democrat on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, has called for the establishment of three regional governments -- one Kurdish, one Sunni, one Shiite -- responsible for administering their own regions. The idea is adapted from one first proposed by Leslie H. Gelb, the former president of the Council on Foreign Relations.</p>
        <p>So far the Bush administration has opposed solutions that would give the regions too much autonomy for fear that could ultimately lead to partition. In Washington on Monday, Reuters reported, the Saudi ambassador to the United States, Prince Turki al-Faisal, said any partition of Iraq would lead to ''ethnic cleansing on a massive scale, sectarian killing on a massive scale.''</p>
        <p>This month, Iraq's new Parliament approved a law that empowers the country's 18 provinces to assemble into regions, but that delays, for 18 months, any practical steps toward forming those regions, in a bid to defuse the explosive political tensions that underlie the debate.</p>
        <p>Nearly a year after national elections, the Sunnis, and not just the insurgents, remain unreconciled to the loss of primacy they enjoyed for generations -- and to the loss of revenue they enjoyed under Saddam Hussein. ''The problem is that in 2003 the Sunnis got 70 percent of the oil, and now they are being asked to take 20 percent,'' Mr. Galbraith said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Shiites, or at least the leaders of the religious parties that control the government, have become increasingly strident in insisting that after generations of Sunni domination, it is now their turn to rule. While a process of ethnic and religious separation is already under way in cities including Baghdad, Mosul and Kirkuk -- with tens of thousands of people from the three principal communities fleeing to safer havens in those parts of the country where they are in the majority -- any policy that explicitly espoused this kind of separation would be likely to ignite an even fiercer struggle.</p>
        <p>The subtext for the debate is the struggle for control of the country's oil and gas revenues. The Iraqi Constitution, narrowly adopted last year, envisages a formula for dividing the revenues among provinces or regions proportional to the populations in each area, with some adjustments. Though the timetable set by the American and Iraqi governments calls for legislation to be passed on the issue by the end of October, there is now little chance it will happen before the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Reconciliation and Amnesty</p>
        <p>When he took office in May, Mr. Maliki made national reconciliation a centerpiece of his policy. But today it is foundering.</p>
        <p>At the dispute's heart is the issue of a possible amnesty. It would cover both those responsible for the repressive violence during Mr. Hussein's 24 years in power, and the killing that has ensued, by insurgents and sectarian militias, since his fall.</p>
        <p>Shiite politicians, in particular, have adamantly opposed any amnesty that would cover the decades of Shiite suffering under Mr. Hussein, or the widespread killing of Shiites by Sunni insurgents since the American-led invasion in 2003. As Shiite death squads have killed Sunnis over the past year, Sunni politicians, too, have hardened their stand. American officials, eager to promote Iraqi reconciliation, have still balked at any provision to spare insurgents or sectarian militiamen who have killed American soldiers.</p>
        <p>Iraqi officials designated by Mr. Maliki to lead the reconciliation effort now seem to be despairing.</p>
        <p>''Iraq has only two options, fragmentation or civil war,'' Sayed Ayyad Jamaluddin, a secular Shiite who is a member of the Maliki-appointed Higher Council for National Reconciliation, said last month. ''And civil war,'' he added, ''will be a catastrophe, because it will be fought on the basis of religion.''</p>
        <p>A Strongman</p>
        <p>Some American experts have suggested that the Bush administration should abandon the effort to create a Western-style democracy and throw its weight behind a stronger Iraqi government. Mr. Cohen, in the Wall Street Journal article, which the White House e-mailed to reporters because it concluded that a withdrawal of American troops would be disastrous, wrote that ''a junta of military modernizers might be the only hope of a country whose democratic culture is weak, whose politicians are either corrupt or incapable.'' But he also highlighted the downsides of returning to a strongman government.</p>
        <p>Iraqi newspapers have adopted the theme of a government change, speculating on the possible composition of a ''national salvation government,'' backed by the United States, that would wrest power from the Shiite alliance that chose Mr. Maliki for prime minister. Iraqi officials have said that Mr. Maliki has been deeply shaken by rumors that he might be forced from office by year's end. However, President Bush, in two conversations over the past two weeks, has assured him of support.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
