<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DB1139F933A15753C1A963958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dulcie Leimbach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are no typical children in New York City, but there are plenty of children doing typical things. A random sample found that some young New Yorkers spend their weekends going to movies, shopping, watching television, playing soccer or baseball, visiting museums and running around in the neighborhood park. They also do offbeat things: Max Beron, for example, who is 7 and lives in SoHo, studied the panpipe, the primitive reed instrument. Here is what children  from three families say they like to do on the weekend. Carla and Julio Barrios Fordham, the Bronx</p>
        <p>Carla and Julio Barrios are graced: they have an Aunt Dimetra who takes them places in her Buick on the weekends. Dimetra Makris is not really an aunt, but a longtime friend of their parents; she taught them English seven years ago at Lehman College in Bedford Park, the Bronx. Carla, who is 13, and Julio, who is 10, attend school at Our Lady of Refuge in the Bronx. Their parents, also named  Carla and Julio, left Nicaragua 10 years ago. Mrs. Barrios worked as an agronomist there, and her husband worked at the newspaper La Prensa; now Mrs. Barrios works in the housekeeping department at the Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx, and Mr. Barrios is an assistant to a manager at a building-maintenance company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are no typical children in New York City, but there are plenty of children doing typical things. A random sample found that some young New Yorkers spend their weekends going to movies, shopping, watching television, playing soccer or baseball, visiting museums and running around in the neighborhood park. They also do offbeat things: Max Beron, for example, who is 7 and lives in SoHo, studied the panpipe, the primitive reed instrument. Here is what children  from three families say they like to do on the weekend. Carla and Julio Barrios Fordham, the Bronx</p>
        <p>Carla and Julio Barrios are graced: they have an Aunt Dimetra who takes them places in her Buick on the weekends. Dimetra Makris is not really an aunt, but a longtime friend of their parents; she taught them English seven years ago at Lehman College in Bedford Park, the Bronx. Carla, who is 13, and Julio, who is 10, attend school at Our Lady of Refuge in the Bronx. Their parents, also named  Carla and Julio, left Nicaragua 10 years ago. Mrs. Barrios worked as an agronomist there, and her husband worked at the newspaper La Prensa; now Mrs. Barrios works in the housekeeping department at the Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx, and Mr. Barrios is an assistant to a manager at a building-maintenance company.</p>
        <p>A daughter of Greek immigrants, Ms. Makris is a writer who lives in Long Island City, Queens. She feels blessed: Carla likes her younger brother so much, Ms. Makris says, that she is willing to take him with her wherever she goes, especially when she's with Ms. Makris. Ms. Makris has escorted them to the Cirque du Soleil, nature centers, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Cooper-Hewitt Museum and even Mickey Mantle's restaurant in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Last fall, Ms. Makris and the children went apple picking in Rockland County, where they had fun climbing the trees. The Orchards of Concklin, in Pomona, N.Y., does not allow tree climbing, but it seems that a few apples had to be plucked that way. Later they baked pies.</p>
        <p>The orchard is on South Mountain Road and Route 45; apple-picking hours are 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. on weekends through the end of October. Poles can be rented for $1 (with a $5 deposit), and the apples (mostly Jersey Red Rome baking apples now) are 70 cents a pound for less than 15 pounds and 60 cents a pound for more  than 15 pounds. The orchard is offering pony and hay rides this Sunday. Information: (914) 354-0369.</p>
        <p>Perla Bernstein TriBeCa and SoHo</p>
        <p>When 7-year-old Perla Bernstein is with her mother every other week (she is with her father on alternate weeks), her life swirls around TriBeCa. Her mother, Melanie Hayes, recently moved to the neighborhood, where Perla attends the Early Childhood Center, a public school. On weekends, she and her mother go to the Washington Market Park (Chambers and Greenwich Streets) and the Hudson River Park (at the westernmost end of Chambers Street).</p>
        <p>The Washington Market Park is small, with a grassy lawn and sand pits, and everyone seems to know one another. The Hudson River Park is more universal, with clear views of the river, a large, pristine playground and wide sidewalks where skaters and bikers meld. Perla and her mother also play miniature golf at  Pier 25, North Moore Street at the West Side Highway, two blocks north of Chambers Street; information: (212) 353-0366.</p>
        <p>When they want to explore, Perla and her mother, who is an office manager for an investment firm, walk across the Brooklyn Bridge and eat brunch in Brooklyn Heights. Or they take a ferry from the World Financial Center to Hoboken, N.J.;  for ferry information, call N.Y. Waterway at (800) 533-3779.</p>
        <p>Perla's father, Morty Bernstein, a computer programmer who lives in SoHo, finds time for Rollerblading. Father and daughter skate at the Chelsea Piers at  dusk, when the sun sets and New Jersey turns pink. The outdoor rink is on Pier 62 at 23d Street and the West Side Highway; information: (212) 336-6200.</p>
        <p>Yellda and Hudda Balouch Flushing, Queens</p>
        <p>Yellda Balouch is named after what Afghans call the "night of yellda," the longest day of the year. Her younger sister's name, Hudda (pronounced HOO-dah),  means "right way" in Arabic. Yellda's name, however, is of Persian origin. Yellda is 2 1/2 and Hudda is 1 1/2. Their mother, Shukria, stays home and takes  care of the children while her husband, Ahmad, runs his electrical-contracting business. The girls' parents left Kabul, the capital of Afghanistan, about a decade ago.</p>
        <p>On the weekends, it's Dad's turn to keep the girls busy. In the summer and early fall, he usually takes them around the corner to the Queens Botanical Garden at 43-50 Main Street; information: (718) 886-3800. "As soon as I take them," he said, "they want to get into the grass." There are lots of flowers, and couples being married are often there having their pictures taken. Mr. Balouch also walks the girls over to the nearby John Bowne Playground (Union Street and Sanford Avenue), which he said had "people from all kinds of nations: French, German, Afghan, Indian, Russian." "The kids play, and the grown-ups sit  and talk," he said.</p>
        <p>But there's nothing like the place that reminds Mr. Balouch of Kabul: Bear Mountain in upstate New York.  "I have a good feeling driving on the highway with my family, going for barbecues, renting boats there," he said of the state park. "The girls love it."</p>
        <p>Bear Mountain is at the last exit off the Palisades Parkway, near Harriman; weekends, the parking fee is $3. Information: (914) 786-2701.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
