<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unsung Heroes Of October: The Scouts</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="95 WORLD SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD SERIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5DB1139F933A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unsung Heroes Of October: The Scouts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 1988 World Series will always be remembered for the one-legged, pinch-hit home run Kirk Gibson hit with two out in the ninth inning that turned around not only that game but also the entire series, in which the Oakland Athletics had been expected to prevail over the Los Angeles Dodgers. As stunning as the development was, there was more to it than was readily apparent.</p>
        <p>"The home run Gibby hit was strictly off a scouting report," Tim Belcher, then a pitcher with the Dodgers, recalled. "Phil Regan, Jerry Stephenson and Mel Didier told all our left-handed hitters if you're in a game late and Eckersley is in and the game is on the line, which it will be if he's in, sit on a 3-2 slider, a backdoor slider. He's done it all year. That's what he threw Gibby. It was a good pitch but not when you're looking for it."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 1988 World Series will always be remembered for the one-legged, pinch-hit home run Kirk Gibson hit with two out in the ninth inning that turned around not only that game but also the entire series, in which the Oakland Athletics had been expected to prevail over the Los Angeles Dodgers. As stunning as the development was, there was more to it than was readily apparent.</p>
        <p>"The home run Gibby hit was strictly off a scouting report," Tim Belcher, then a pitcher with the Dodgers, recalled. "Phil Regan, Jerry Stephenson and Mel Didier told all our left-handed hitters if you're in a game late and Eckersley is in and the game is on the line, which it will be if he's in, sit on a 3-2 slider, a backdoor slider. He's done it all year. That's what he threw Gibby. It was a good pitch but not when you're looking for it."</p>
        <p>Scouting reports are a routine part of a team's post-season endeavors, but they and the people who prepare them generally go unnoticed. Sometimes, though,  the players who use the reports leave telltale signs.</p>
        <p>The pitching staffs of the Cleveland Indians and Atlanta Braves offered such  signs in winning this year's league championship series and moving into the World Series, which opens tomorrow night in Atlanta. Their staffs were the most  effective in their leagues this season, but in the league series they went beyond their in-season performances.</p>
        <p>The Cincinnati Reds scored only five runs in four games against the Braves. The Seattle Mariners scored 12 runs and batted .184 against the Indians. Those are pitching feats unparalleled in post-season play.</p>
        <p>"You're looking for an edge, something that will make your guys better," said Dom Chiti, one of the Cleveland scouts who scrutinized the Mariners. "But advance scouting is the easier part of it. The harder part is executing. Our guys showed how good they were. It looked like they followed the report."</p>
        <p>Guy Mader, the other scout who watched the Mariners against the Yankees, said scouts look for tendencies, hitters who are hot or cold, what their weak spots might be. "That's basically what we were looking for," he added. "We happened to come up with a good report on these guys."</p>
        <p>Perhaps the single most impressive achievement so far this post-season was the Indians' effort against Edgar Martinez, limiting him to 2 hits in 23 at-bats for an .087 average after he won the American League batting title with a .356 average and hit .571 in the playoff series against the Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Indians' pitchers benefited from a plan put together by Chiti, Mader and  Mark Wiley, the pitching coach.</p>
        <p>"We wanted to pitch him two different ways," Mader said yesterday. "One was down and away, the other coming in tight. They started away at the beginning of  the series, then came in tight with him.</p>
        <p>Chiti said it was imperative not to pitch Martinez with any consistent pattern.</p>
        <p>"You have to move the ball and consistently change speeds," he explained. "You do a lot of different things with a lot of different speeds, changing speeds and locations. Try to keep him off balance. Take his power away from him."</p>
        <p>The Indians' pitchers did what the Yankees' pitchers couldn't do.</p>
        <p>"He killed the Yankees," Mader said. "He was the best hitter in baseball that week."</p>
        <p>Speaking generally of the matchup of the Yankees' pitchers against the Mariners' hitters, Mader added: "They weren't placing the ball that well. They were struggling. They were tired from trying to get there. They really didn't have the location they should have. They challenged hitters too many times when  they didn't have to, especially when they were ahead in the count. Then the bullpen was pitching to their strengths. Those guys are good fastball hitters and the bullpen is fastball pitchers."</p>
        <p>The Indians' pitchers, on the other hand, pitched the Mariners almost perfectly, Mader said.</p>
        <p>"On Blowers," the scout related, "we said, 'You can get him away but make sure it's away.' But in the second inning of the first game, Dennis Martinez threw Mike Blowers a fastball that went too far over the plate, and Blowers hit  a two-run home run.</p>
        <p>"That was the only mistake they made," Mader said. "They did an outstanding job."</p>
        <p>The Braves had been in the playoffs the three previous seasons there were playoffs, and they were determined to reach the World Series again and this time win it. As part of their quest, they sent their scouts out early and, because of the large number of wild-card contenders, initially covered 14 teams, seven in each league.</p>
        <p>"John had us start earlier this year, before teams clinched," Paul Snyder said, referring to General Manager John Schuerholz. "That makes a difference. You get to see them do the things they do when they're trying to win. You see them when they're still bunting, stealing, running."</p>
        <p>An added benefit, Snyder said, was that "when you're out there that long, you're going to find some pitcher who has similar stuff to what you have. How does he work him? Did he have success? You draw analogies. The more we watched them, the more became obvious to us."</p>
        <p>Atlanta scouts covered about 25 Reds games. "In that time," Snyder said, "we  were able to find proper matchups. You can take a guy like Kirk Rueter in Montreal. He does a lot of things like Tom Glavine does."</p>
        <p>The Braves' pitchers are seasoned and they are good. In opposing National League hitters, they have their own ideas of how to pitch them. The scouts give  them updates. The Indians present a different task.</p>
        <p>"We don't have an underlying pool of experience or data from our pitchers because we haven't played them," Schuerholz said. "The advance scouting, going up against the other league, really becomes paramount and takes on greater importance."</p>
        <p>Many of the Atlanta hitters, on the other hand, have seen some of the Cleveland pitchers because Orel Hershiser, Dennis Martinez and Ken Hill came from the National League.</p>
        <p>"That may be one advantage our hitters have," Snyder said. "There's nothing hitters hate more than to hit against pitchers they've never seen."</p>
        <p>95 WORLD SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
