<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Springsteen as Mentor For a Milder Comrade</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ROCK REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSEROCKERS, THE (MUSIC GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARELES, JON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPRINGSTEEN, BRUCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRUSHECKY, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D91138F933A15753C1A963958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Springsteen as Mentor For a Milder Comrade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PARELES, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Were Bruce Springsteen and Joe Grushecky separated at birth? They could have been lucky and unlucky brothers when they sang side by side at Tramps on Wednesday night. Mr. Grushecky is taller, slightly fairer and balding, but the two men had the same gritty vocal approach, the same Middle Atlantic accent, the same style of beard, the same combination of workingman's woe and guitar gumption.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Springsteen was conquering arenas, Mr. Grushecky has been leading his band, the House- rockers, in and around Pittsburgh since the 1970's. He worked a day job, teaching emotionally disturbed children, until last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Were Bruce Springsteen and Joe Grushecky separated at birth? They could have been lucky and unlucky brothers when they sang side by side at Tramps on Wednesday night. Mr. Grushecky is taller, slightly fairer and balding, but the two men had the same gritty vocal approach, the same Middle Atlantic accent, the same style of beard, the same combination of workingman's woe and guitar gumption.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Springsteen was conquering arenas, Mr. Grushecky has been leading his band, the House- rockers, in and around Pittsburgh since the 1970's. He worked a day job, teaching emotionally disturbed children, until last month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Springsteen produced Mr. Grushecky's eighth album, "American Babylon" (Razor &amp; Tie), and collaborated on two songs. His appearance, though unadvertised, apparently drew most of the audience to the packed club, where shouts of "Bruuuuce!" started during the opening set by John Eddie.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Springsteen joined the Houserockers partway through the set, he tried to keep the spotlight on Mr. Grushecky. He sang only two of his own songs, "Murder, Inc." and "Light of Day"; most of the time, he shared backup vocals, played lead guitar, grinned and sweated along with the rest of the band. Late in the set, Dion Di Mucci and Scott Kempner (formerly of the Del-Lords and Dictators) joined them for a bluesy version of Dion's hit "The Wanderer."</p>
        <p>As a producer and collaborator, Mr. Springsteen has remade Mr. Grushecky in his own image, though Mr. Grushecky was already partway there. Like Mr. Springsteen, he writes about honest laborers trying to support their families in hard times; he also writes weary love songs. And like Mr. Springsteen, he favors midtempo anthems that move from folk-rock or blues riffs into ringing marches.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Grushecky's new songs, the Houserockers have turned into a western auxiliary of the E Street Band. Often, the first verse uses a basic guitar strum and a light drumbeat; the full band kicks in on the second verse, arriving like a rescue team to turn the humdrum into the heroic.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Springsteen, Mr. Grushecky wrote didactically about big issues: the exploitation of American Indians ("Dark and Bloody Ground") and the decline of steel-mill towns ("Homestead"); his own "American Babylon" had the earnest chorus, "Do you really care?" Mr. Grushecky's lost-love songs, like "Chain Smokin'," "No Strings Attached" and "Never be Enough Time," carried less rhetorical baggage; so did some of his older material, like "Swimming with the Sharks."</p>
        <p>In "Talking with the King," a resurrected Elvis told the singer he was better off as an unknown with a loving family; it took on different, more complicated meanings with Mr. Springsteen, a rock king who's also a secure family man, singing alongside Mr. Grushecky.</p>
        <p>Mr. Springsteen clearly hopes that his fans will transfer some of their loyalty to Mr. Grushecky. But by bringing out their similarities, he encouraged comparisons that don't favor Mr. Grushecky. Mr. Grushecky's songs are staunch, but slightly flat-footed; his voice is less resonant than Mr. Springsteen's, and his guitar solos didn't slice and wail like Mr. Springsteen's bluesy attacks. The Houserockers, who have been making albums with Mr. Grushecky since 1979, also hit harder when Mr. Springsteen was onstage.</p>
        <p>There are other ways to arrange songs besides the E Street approach. In older material, the Houserockers looked toward the Rolling Stones, and many of the recent songs could have tilted toward country or folk-rock instead of E Street anthems. Mr. Springsteen has helped Mr. Grushecky get some attention; now, Mr. Grushecky has to find his own voice.</p>
        <p>ROCK REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
