<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not Just a New Ferry Terminal, but a Fanciful One</title>
    <meta content="25FERR$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="911379"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Staten Island Ferry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Clifford J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2D81F3EF936A15751C0A961958260" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not Just a New Ferry Terminal, but a Fanciful One</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levy, Clifford J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Staten Island officials say that they want to replace borough's aging St George Ferry Terminal with $100 million building, twisting, chimerical structure that would continue to receive passengers while also housing museum; rendering (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Staten Island officials said yesterday that they wanted to replace the borough's aging St. George Ferry Terminal with a $100 million building, a twisting, chimerical structure that would continue to receive passengers while also housing a museum. The new building would be a striking fusion of infrastructure and culture, beckoning visitors to the southern end of New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>But the officials acknowledged that they must overcome several major obstacles before construction can begin. The most daunting is that the neighborhood around the terminal is now zoned for industrial use, not for a museum, so sponsors of the proposal would have to get special approval from the city for it to move forward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Staten Island officials said yesterday that they wanted to replace the borough's aging St. George Ferry Terminal with a $100 million building, a twisting, chimerical structure that would continue to receive passengers while also housing a museum. The new building would be a striking fusion of infrastructure and culture, beckoning visitors to the southern end of New York Harbor.</p>
        <p>But the officials acknowledged that they must overcome several major obstacles before construction can begin. The most daunting is that the neighborhood around the terminal is now zoned for industrial use, not for a museum, so sponsors of the proposal would have to get special approval from the city for it to move forward.</p>
        <p>The design, by the architect Peter Eisenman, could also stir controversy. Mr. Eisenman, who has been acclaimed for his provocative buildings but has never done a project in New York City, has sketched a structure with an otherworldly look that is supposed to represent the flow of energy.</p>
        <p>Guy V. Molinari, the Staten Island Borough President, said the project would be financed by a mix of government and private money. He said it would revitalize the neighborhood around the terminal and would be one of the first large museums to be built in New York City in recent years.</p>
        <p>''This is probably one of the most exciting proposals that I have ever been involved with,'' Mr. Molinari said. ''This is going to be a showcase for us, the gateway to Staten Island.''</p>
        <p>He added, though, that it would take a concerted alliance of city officials and private groups for the plan to become a reality. ''This is a very complex project, a magnificent undertaking, but not one without problems,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The museum part of the structure would be the new home of the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, which is now a few blocks away. The institute, which was founded in 1881, would have 170,000 square feet of space on top of the ferry terminal, Hedy Hartman, its president, said.</p>
        <p>The institute is to pay for the construction of the museum section through a $40 million bond issue approved by the New York State Dormitory Authority. The city is to pay for most of the new terminal itself, officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisenman said yesterday that he was confident that the project's sponsors would surmount the zoning barriers. He said regulators needed to embrace the idea of melding a transportation project with a cultural one.</p>
        <p>''They picked us because they want a fresh image for Staten Island,'' Mr. Eisenman said. ''They want something that is going to say, 'Hey, we ought to go to Staten Island to see that building.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
