<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>President of U.S. Chamber Will Resign After 21 Years</title>
    <meta content="25CHAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="911306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Richard L. Lesher</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Chamber of Commerce</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lesher, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1D71E3EF936A15751C0A961958260" item-length="595" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>President of U.S. Chamber Will Resign After 21 Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard L Lesher says he will resign as president of United States Chamber of Commerce after 21 years in that post; Lesher, considered dean of business lobbying, created multimillion-dollar communications system whose television facilities produce syndicated business programming along with training seminars and town hall meetings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard L. Lesher, the dean of business lobbying, who raised the profile of the United States Chamber of Commerce during his 21 years as its president, announced today that he was resigning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lesher, who is 63, said he had been thinking of leaving his $520,000-a-year post for some time. He dismissed suggestions that the decision might reflect dissatisfaction among members or disagreements over policy following years of lagging growth in the organization, even as it has become increasingly visible as a sponsor of business television.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard L. Lesher, the dean of business lobbying, who raised the profile of the United States Chamber of Commerce during his 21 years as its president, announced today that he was resigning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lesher, who is 63, said he had been thinking of leaving his $520,000-a-year post for some time. He dismissed suggestions that the decision might reflect dissatisfaction among members or disagreements over policy following years of lagging growth in the organization, even as it has become increasingly visible as a sponsor of business television.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to do something else, maybe the time to do it is now,'' Mr. Lesher said, indicating that he hoped to write, do volunteer work and take on additional corporate directorships.</p>
        <p>Acquaintances of Mr. Lesher said they were inclined to take his statement at face value.</p>
        <p>''He's ready to turn it over to someone else,'' Thomas J. Donohue, head of the American Trucking Associations and a former chamber vice president, said. ''He just wants to smell the roses.''</p>
        <p>Throughout a tenure dating to the Ford Administration, Mr. Lesher built a reputation for standing his staunchly conservative ground. One of his biggest confrontations came in 1982 when President Ronald Reagan wanted to raise taxes and the chamber's chairman, Paul Thayer of the LTV Corporation, supported him, along with a majority of the board.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lesher opposed the idea and was ultimately successful in both withholding chamber endorsement of the tax increase and in healing the rift that had widely been thought to threaten his job.</p>
        <p>More recently, Mr. Lesher was at first somewhat receptive to President Clinton's plan for health care overhaul, but, under pressure from smaller chamber members, he decided in the end to oppose the plan.</p>
        <p>''I think we had a major role in defeating it,'' Mr. Lesher said.</p>
        <p>Much of Mr. Lesher's legacy involves the creation of a multimillion-dollar communications system based in the group's neo-classical limestone headquarters overlooking the White House. Its television facilities produce syndicated business programming along with training seminars and town hall meetings.</p>
        <p>Perhaps best known is ''It's Your Business,'' a weekly public affairs program featuring Mr. Lesher as a permanent panelist. Another is ''First Business,'' a news program for small business.</p>
        <p>Other initiatives include the National Chamber Litigation Center, a legal arm that represents business interests in the Federal courts, and an extensive system to track, rank and endorse members of Congress based on their voting record on business issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lesher credits Lewis Powell, a retired Justice of the Supreme Court, with helping to shape the direction the chamber has taken. Before joining the Court, Mr. Powell told a member of the chamber board that the group should become more outspoken and ended up writing a memorandum on how to do this that the group still refers to as ''the Powell memo.''</p>
        <p>Most members of the chamber's board were told of Mr. Lesher's departure only at today's meeting, but a search committee has already been formed. Mr. Lesher will remain with the chamber for at least a portion of the search process.</p>
        <p>Though the chamber bills itself as the world's largest business federation, its growth has lagged. The $70 million annual budget, for example, is no larger than 15 years ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
