<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rop Ignores the Pain And Glides to Victory</title>
    <meta content="04MENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/04/sports/othersports/04MENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1437749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="KENYANS HEAT UP A CHILLY DAY: MEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kenya</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rop, Rodgers</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chebet, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kipkemboi, Laban</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodgers, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salazar, Alberto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheboiboch, Christopher</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Rop, Rodgers</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chepchumba, Joyce</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDC153EF937A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rop Ignores the Pain And Glides to Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rop Ignores Pain, Glides to Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rodgers Rop of Kenya wins New York City Marathon in 2:08:17; becomes fourth man to win New York and Boston Marathons in same year, after Bill Rodgers, Alberto Salazar and Joseph Chebet; Kenyan sweep of top three places is completed by Christopher Cheboiboch in 2:08:17 and Laban Kipkemboi in 2:08:39; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 25th mile of yesterday's New York City Marathon, Rodgers Rop of Kenya grabbed his right side, feeling a stitch. He grimaced. Two countrymen sat on his heels, and his elegant stride seemed as if it might abandon him.</p>
        <p>Last year, Rop hung for 20 miles with the eventual winner, Tesfaye Jifar of Ethiopia, until the muscles in his legs seized. He dropped off of a hammering pace to finish third. This would not happen again, he promised.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rodgers Rop led Kenya to an unprecedented 1-2-3 men's sweep with a winning time of 2 hours 8 minutes 7 seconds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the 25th mile of yesterday's New York City Marathon, Rodgers Rop of Kenya grabbed his right side, feeling a stitch. He grimaced. Two countrymen sat on his heels, and his elegant stride seemed as if it might abandon him.</p>
        <p>Last year, Rop hung for 20 miles with the eventual winner, Tesfaye Jifar of Ethiopia, until the muscles in his legs seized. He dropped off of a hammering pace to finish third. This would not happen again, he promised.</p>
        <p>''If the leader pushes, I will go with him, even if I die by the roadside,'' Rop said before yesterday's race.</p>
        <p>Confident that the stitch would dissipate, convinced that his competitors had weakened, Rop made a final move in a race of clever and forceful surges to win in a field of 32,185 entrants in 2 hours 8 minutes 7 seconds. The time, posted on a cold, clear day into a frequent headwind, did not threaten Jifar's course record of 2:07:43, but it did provide Kenya a 1-2-3 sweep of New York for the first time. Christopher Cheboiboch finished second in 2:08:17, and Laban Kipkemboi took third in 2:08:39.</p>
        <p>This was only the third time that Rop had run 26 miles 385 yards, yet at age 29 he has built a career of distinction, joining Alberto Salazar and Bill Rodgers of the United States and Joseph Chebet of Kenya as the only men to win both the New York City and Boston Marathons in the same year. Having held on in Boston in April to beat Cheboiboch by three seconds in 2:09:02, Rop added rigorous speed work to his training regimen, and yesterday he won by splendid, grinding attrition.</p>
        <p>Kenyans have dominated international marathon running for years, except at the Olympics, where they have never won. That mastery was evident yesterday as Joyce Chepchumba of Kenya won the women's race in 2:25:56. She and Rop are coached by Volker Wagner of Germany, who also trained Tegla Loroupe, the two-time New York champion.</p>
        <p>Rop's ascendancy, however, might be considered inadvertent, given that he has trained as a serious runner for only two or three years.</p>
        <p>The son of a deputy headmaster at a Kenyan primary school, Rop began his career as a steeplechaser in high school, tutored by the 1984 Olympic gold medalist Julius Korir. Rop discontinued running for two years after graduation, working instead as a laborer on a flower farm. One of 13 children, he said he felt it urgent to gain employment, which seemed more reliable with his hands than his feet.</p>
        <p>''You can't depend on your parents anymore,'' he said. ''You have to look for your own life.''</p>
        <p>Apparently, though, he found horticulture too sedentary.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Rop answered a recruiting ad for the Kenyan national police. When he finished second among 40 recruits in a mass run of the metric mile, his running career was revived. His police assignment became a sinecure; his real job was to win races. In 2001, Rop signed with Wagner and moved to Germany, running 14 races in three months, winning 10 and setting a world record of 1:13:44 at 25 kilometers (15.5 miles).</p>
        <p>''When I was running a 10K under 28 and a half-marathon in sub-61, I knew one day I was going to be at the top,'' Rop said.</p>
        <p>In April, he named his son Boston after his victory there. Still, the marathon can teach harsh lessons. It is really two races, the first 20 miles and the final 6.2, when the body becomes depleted and the mind can drift. Cramps accosted Rop at 20 miles last year in New York. In Boston, he felt poorly in the final miles, sapped by Heartbreak Hill.</p>
        <p>To raise his endurance for a return to New York, Rop elevated his speed drills, including workouts of 25x400 meters in 61 seconds at sea level in Germany, 64 seconds at altitude in Kenya and 20x1,000 meters in 2:45 to 2:50. Determined today, he wore gloves and a headband to cover his ears in the 44-degree chill.</p>
        <p>While the women's race grew tactical, the men pushed hard from the beginning. Jifar, the defending champion, ran among a lead pack of 22, but his stomach grew queasy at Mile 15, just before the Queensboro Bridge spanned the course into Manhattan. He withdrew, stood on the side of the road and vomited.</p>
        <p>On the downhill portion of the bridge, Rop made his first surge. He pushed again on First Avenue, running the 17th mile in a blistering 4:34 and Mile 18 in 4:41. The lead pack shattered like a mirror, leaving only five contenders among the shards of competitors. One of them was Meb Keflezighi, a naturalized United States citizen from Eritrea who was attempting to become the first American to win New York in two decades.</p>
        <p>Keflezighi briefly took the lead at 18 miles in his first marathon, but he let himself be lured by the siren call of the crowd on First Avenue. It is a common and dangerous mistake of inexperience, to get carried away by the treachery of swelling noise. His legs soon emptied of aspiration, leaving Keflezighi to coast home ninth in 2:12:35, a disappointing half-minute shy of the automatic qualifying time for the 2004 Summer Olympics in Athens.</p>
        <p>''I went for it,'' Keflezighi said. ''I do not regret it. Live and learn.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, Rop seemed out for a simple afternoon run, his face impassive his torso leaning slightly forward, his stride as light and purposeful as the stroke of a painter's brush. He could sense that the Kenyans running with him were drained. Cheboiboch grimaced, his arms began to flail, and he dropped for a time into third place. Kipkemboi kept pace, but the exertion drew his lips into a thin line.</p>
        <p>''When I pushed, they didn't respond,'' Rop said. ''They wore out.''</p>
        <p>Then Rop, too, felt the stab of a stitch in his side. Yet in the 25th mile, he began to draw away. It was the slowest mile of the race, 5:16 in the sapping hills of Central Park. The lead began to expand, from 4 seconds to 6 and finally to 10. With first place came $120,000, a car and the knowledge that he could leave his competitors exhausted, bereft of expectation.</p>
        <p>''I knew I was going for the victory,'' Rop said of the stitch in his side. ''The pain did not stop me.''</p>
        <p>With the rare twin victories at New York and Boston, Rop could leave an indelible mark on his career by becoming the first Kenyan to win at the Olympics. The country's track and field federation, however, is notorious for playing political games with its Olympic roster. Rop called federation officials corrupt and said he would not be crushed if he did not compete in Athens. Still, he wants a chance.</p>
        <p>''I hope to run in the Olympics,'' he said, ''to see what is wrong and see why Kenyans are not winning.''</p>
        <p>KENYANS HEAT UP A CHILLY DAY: MEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
