<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Closing Leaves a Hole in a Town's Retail Heart</title>
    <meta content="04JOUR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/04/nyregion/04JOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1437779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Tupper Lake Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tupper Lake (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ames Department Stores</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foderaro, Lisa W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discount Selling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Ames Department Stores Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EEDA153EF937A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Closing Leaves a Hole in a Town's Retail Heart</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Closing Leaves a Hole in a Town's Retail Heart</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA W. FODERARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Foderaro, Lisa W</byline>
      <dateline>TUPPER LAKE, N.Y., Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents in and around of depressed Adirondack village of Tupper Lake are dismayed over closing of Ames Department Store, longtime source of toys, brooms, blankets, sunglasses, jewelry, blue jeans and range of everything else; Ames was also a major employer in Tupper Lake; Ames' closing is part of discount chain's recent bankruptcy and liquidation of 327 stores in Northeast and mid-Atlantic states; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When a Bradlees or a Caldor store closes in the retail-rich New York suburbs, people shrug their shoulders and drive another six minutes to the nearest Kmart or Target.</p>
        <p>But when the automatic doors of the Ames Department Store slid shut here for the final time in October, residents of this depressed Adirondack village suddenly had no place to buy underwear. And what would register as an inconvenience downstate has become a calamity for this thinly populated region, where the piney woods are already dusted with snow. ''It's like a death in the family,'' said Edith La Londe, 67. ''It's horrible. I can't imagine how we're going to survive without it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the local Ames Department Store closed, residents of an Adirondack village have no place to buy underwear, toys or brooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When a Bradlees or a Caldor store closes in the retail-rich New York suburbs, people shrug their shoulders and drive another six minutes to the nearest Kmart or Target.</p>
        <p>But when the automatic doors of the Ames Department Store slid shut here for the final time in October, residents of this depressed Adirondack village suddenly had no place to buy underwear. And what would register as an inconvenience downstate has become a calamity for this thinly populated region, where the piney woods are already dusted with snow. ''It's like a death in the family,'' said Edith La Londe, 67. ''It's horrible. I can't imagine how we're going to survive without it.''</p>
        <p>For Tupper Lake, population 3,935, and surrounding towns and hamlets, Ames was it: the place (sometimes the only place) to buy toys, brooms, blankets, sunglasses, jewelry, blue jeans, curtains, yarn, CD's, Christmas lights. The list goes on.</p>
        <p>The closest department store was a half-hour away in Saranac Lake, but that was an Ames, too, and it also closed this month. Now residents find themselves having to drive the hour and 20 minutes to Plattsburgh, where there is a Wal-Mart, for many basic needs. ''We were in Plattsburgh last weekend, and the number of people there from Tupper Lake was unbelievable,'' said Sandra A. Strader, the Tupper Lake mayor. ''The big thing was, 'I'm buying underwear.' ''</p>
        <p>The closings were part of the discount chain's recent bankruptcy and liquidation of 327 stores in the Northeast and the mid-Atlantic states. A dozen stores were scattered across the Adirondacks, a six-million-acre state park, and the state's North Country -- two regions where residents had few shopping options even before Ames closed.</p>
        <p>But Tupper Lake appears to be taking the loss the hardest. Ames was a major employer in the village, and the town's economy was already shaky, with the recent demise of the A.&amp;P. supermarket and Big Tupper Ski Area.</p>
        <p>Saranac Lake and Lake Placid (or, as locals joke, ''Lake Plastic,'' as in credit cards) have stores, true. But they tend to be boutiques catering to tourists, selling moose-shaped candelabras and pine-scented sachets.</p>
        <p>''It's an hour and a half in any direction to another department store,'' said Jane Denis, from nearby Piercefield. ''The saddest part is we'd like to do our business in Tupper Lake.''</p>
        <p>Judy Reandeau's week illustrates the void. On Tuesday, she drove to Plattsburgh to buy plastic sheeting for her windows, now that temperatures at night are in the teens. On Wednesday, she tried to find oil for her sewing machine at the Family Dollar store here, without success. ''Ames would have had that,'' she said, ''and the plastic for my windows, too. They had some of everything. I'm driving to Plattsburgh once a week now.''</p>
        <p>While Saranac Lake may be more prosperous than Tupper Lake -- and a half-hour closer to Plattsburgh -- it, too, is anxious about the shutdown of Ames. Rose Nadon, 76, does not know where to find materials for her needlepoint. She could go to Plattsburgh, but she does not own a car.</p>
        <p>Jennie Frenette, a high school music teacher and mother of three, said Saranac Lake was blessed with an arty toy store. But, she wondered: ''Where do you find a Barbie doll in town? I don't know.''</p>
        <p>State officials say they are aware of the hardship wrought by Ames's closing and are working to find a replacement. ''We're confident that a new opportunity for other businesses to step in will materialize, and we will work with local officials to make that happen,'' said Michael Marr, a spokesman for the Empire State Development Corporation, the state's economic development agency.</p>
        <p>Grant Sanborn, executive vice president of operations of Ames Department Stores, which is based in Connecticut, said no retailers had inquired about moving into the Ames stores in Tupper Lake or Saranac Lake, although some developers had ''expressed interest.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Strader, the mayor, said she had reached out to Wal-Mart to try to interest the company in the 30,000-square-foot Ames site. ''They told me they're coming, but they haven't given us a time,'' she said. ''We're keeping our fingers crossed that something will come in.''</p>
        <p>The Ames store is technically still here, as the company, founded in 1958, tries to liquidate the assets.</p>
        <p>This week it was quiet. The store manager, Sue Trudeau, and a local man hired to oversee the liquidation, Patrick Klouse, were alone in a beige landscape of naked shoe racks and empty jewelry spinners that once held 14-karat gold charms for $14.89. A giant sign that read ''Infants'' leaned against a wall.</p>
        <p>Ms. Trudeau said the Tupper Lake store was hardly a money loser. ''All of the New York stores were really profitable, especially in the North Country,'' she said. (Mr. Sanborn said he could not confirm that.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Klouse's wife, Sharon, had worked in the store's jewelry department.</p>
        <p>Now she collects unemployment insurance while she looks for a job. Mr. Klouse went through the same thing himself last year when the A.&amp;P. closed. He had been with the store for 31 years, 28 years as the manager.</p>
        <p>''You get by,'' he said. ''You make things work out. But there's not much in town, that's the thing.''</p>
        <p>Tupper Lake Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
