<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Kerik, There's One Way To Run the Police, at a Sprint</title>
    <meta content="26POLI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/26/nyregion/26POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1280949"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerik, Bernard B (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">City Council</org>
        <org class="online_producer">His office</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DF113CF935A15750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Kerik, There's One Way To Run the Police, at a Sprint</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of New York City Police Comr Bernard B Kerik after first seven months in office appraised; he has burnished image as intense, hands-on manager; decision-making style is described by some as impetuous, but by others as decisive; even those who regard his new approach as incremental or ordinary see little evidence of self-doubt; under his tenure as city's 40th police commissioner, many of senior staff members have departed abruptly, either for private jobs or for less visible posts in department; Kerik's decisiveness attributed to realization that he has little time to reach goals of continued crime reduction, improved community relations and of resurrecting morale since he may lose job when new mayor is elected in eight months; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik stood with an aide at the window of his 14th-floor office, wagging his finger at the street below. He was perplexed. Several enormous ornamental lights outside the headquarters of what he often calls ''the greatest, biggest police department in the country'' were dark, apparently broken.</p>
        <p>How could this be?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik stood with an aide at the window of his 14th-floor office, wagging his finger at the street below. He was perplexed. Several enormous ornamental lights outside the headquarters of what he often calls ''the greatest, biggest police department in the country'' were dark, apparently broken.</p>
        <p>How could this be?</p>
        <p>The aide, John Picciano, did not take a memo or start to make a windy excuse. He sat down and dialed building maintenance. The lights were fixed immediately, which was precisely the time frame Mr. Kerik had in mind.</p>
        <p>''I'm not big on doing things that are a waste of time,'' Mr. Kerik said. ''If it's a waste of time, get rid of it. If it's a bad manager, get rid of them.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Kerik's first seven months as New York's 40th police commissioner, a corps of senior staff members have departed abruptly, either for private jobs or for less visible posts in the department.</p>
        <p>The moves, which seemed unfair to some, helped to fuel an impression of Mr. Kerik as a man in a hurry. His marathon days, filled with community meetings and station house tours, have only burnished his image as an intense manager, the kind who often stands during meetings, prefers briefings to lengthy memos and pounds coffee (half regular, half hazelnut) throughout the day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik's decision-making style is described by some as impetuous, by others as decisive. But even those who regard his new programs as incremental or ordinary see little evidence of self-doubt.</p>
        <p>''If you bring an issue to Bernie Kerik,'' said Thomas J. Scotto, president of the union that represents detectives and a self-described Kerik fan, ''it is usually resolved within 24 hours.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik has good reason to act quickly. In eight months, after a new mayor is elected, he stands to lose this job, one he has been dreaming about since 1986, when he was a patrolman walking a beat in an untamed Times Square. So there is little time left to reach his goals: continued crime reduction, improved community relations and resurrected morale.</p>
        <p>Early returns have been promising. Crime is down and community relations appear to have improved. No less a police critic than the Rev. Al Sharpton offers faint praise. ''My fears were that he would be a puppet of the mayor,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''I'm not saying he's not, but the strings are a lot looser than we thought they would be.''</p>
        <p>The morale problem, however, which Mr. Kerik has addressed by repairing station houses and praising dedicated officers, may well require more than paint and pats on the back. The department remains riddled with problems. Recruiting has been sluggish. Retirements continue to soar. And only a few weeks ago, bitterness over low pay led 7,000 officers to picket City Hall.</p>
        <p>''Although we have a good dialogue,'' the president of the Patrolmen's Benevolent Association, Patrick J. Lynch, said, ''there is absolutely no way we could bring morale up to where it should be, where people want to stay on the job, and attract new members, unless we get a livable wage.''</p>
        <p>The starting salary for an officer is $31,305, under a contract that expired in July 2000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik's greatest impact has been in community relations, where he has repaired some damage from incidents like the station house torture of Abner Louima. He has begun surveying public attitudes toward the police, retraining commanders in neighborhood diplomacy and devising ways to measure their responses to local complaints.</p>
        <p>The progress has been evident at meetings like a City Council hearing this month where Councilwoman Juanita E. Watkins, who represents a largely black section of Queens, told Mr. Kerik, ''You are, in my estimation, one of the good guys.''</p>
        <p>But not everyone is charmed. Several critics of police policies say they have had trouble arranging meetings with Mr. Kerik. ''His outreach does not include the Civil Liberties Union yet,'' said Donna Lieberman, the interim director of the New York Civil Liberties Union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik, who formerly ran the Correction Department, has been aided in his outreach efforts by the fact that he grew up in a largely black section of Paterson, N.J., that resembles some New York neighborhoods where many people have grown wary of aggressive police tactics.</p>
        <p>His personal style is also quite different from that of his predecessor, Howard Safir, a reserved man who often came across as stiff and defensive. Mr. Kerik is gregarious by nature and sometimes hugs officers at promotion ceremonies or whispers remarks into their ears. This openness has helped him forge ties with police labor leaders, despite the bitter contract negotiations. Several said they had already met more times with Mr. Kerik than they did with Mr. Safir.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik has also been blessed by seven months of relative calm, free of any highly publicized incident of police brutality.</p>
        <p>''Certainly he has made some good moves,'' said Thomas A. Reppetto, president of the Citizens Crime Commission. ''But people are defined by some sweeping program like Compstat or quality-of-life enforcement, or how they respond to crises. And the new programs were put in some years ago, and thankfully there has not been a crisis, so it's difficult at this point in time to really give him a score.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik's crime-fighting strategies may amount to little more than tinkering, but the overall approach has worked. Crime for the first 11 weeks of this year is down 10 percent compared with the same period last year. He has reorganized the intelligence division to increase information sharing and expanded the warrant squad, which hunts fugitives.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani chose Mr. Kerik for the police job last August largely because as correction commissioner he won accolades as a manager who slashed overtime and jail violence. But the selection was also a nod to loyalty. Mr. Kerik had served as a campaign bodyguard for the mayor in 1993. Today, Mr. Giuliani is godfather to Mr. Kerik's daughter.</p>
        <p>The relationship seemed to work to Mr. Kerik's advantage this year, when he persuaded Mr. Giuliani to begin transferring the Police Department's power to prosecute some officers charged with misconduct to the Civilian Complaint Review Board, a move the mayor had previously avoided.</p>
        <p>''Bernie was able to get it done,'' said Michael P. Jacobson, a friend of Mr. Kerik and a former Giuliani aide who is now a professor at John Jay College of Criminal Justice, ''partly because he made an argument on the merits and partly because the mayor has a tremendous amount of trust in him.''</p>
        <p>Other times, the friendship has seemed a liability. Mr. Kerik seemed to follow the mayor's political agenda, rather than a policing strategy, when he held a press briefing several months ago to attack the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey for a minor upturn in airport crime, just as Mr. Giuliani was in the midst of a campaign against the Port Authority.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerik has also been largely distant from the contract negotiations, saying he supports a raise for officers but views it as the mayor's business, not a prerequisite to better morale. ''I don't have much to do with the contract,'' he told supervisors at a briefing last month.</p>
        <p>To repair morale, Mr. Kerik has found new equipment for station houses and has visited police officers on the job, something he says never happened when he walked the streets. Mr. Kerik was so intent on becoming a New York City police officer that he quit a job as a New Jersey jail warden in 1986 and took a $27,000 cut in pay, a financial misstep that helped lead him to declare bankruptcy a year later. In his eight years on the force, Mr. Kerik rose to the rank of third-grade detective, serving undercover in a ponytail to make drug buys, and was decorated for saving his partner's life in a shootout.</p>
        <p>He clearly still identifies with those adrenaline-packed days. His cuff links are miniature versions of his old shield. His office wall features pictures of him wielding an M-16. And some nights he still patrols with his security detail, making arrests. Mr. Kerik, a black belt in karate who is built like a fireplug, has made four arrests as commissioner.</p>
        <p>''When I was a police officer I was very good at what I did,'' he said. ''My instincts were very good. And the problem is -- it's not a problem  -- it kind of never goes away.''</p>
        <p>Although he does not have a college degree, which is a prerequisite for the rank of captain and above, Mr. Kerik is something of a policy expert on management issues. He says performance indicators can gauge everything from sick time to community relations. Recently, he focused on reducing the average response time to emergency calls. It has dropped to just under 10 minutes from 12 since December.</p>
        <p>''What gets measured, gets done,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As it turns out, however, Mr. Kerik has done little to control police overtime, which is likely to top $290 million this year, more than the total city budget for libraries. That kind of money will become very scarce as the economy struggles. And other minefields await. Many people in the communities he is looking to build bridges to are awaiting his decision on whether to discipline the officers who shot Amadou Diallo.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kerik survives those shoals, he might like to stay on with a new mayor, his friends said. But he called that talk premature.</p>
        <p>''Right now, I just want to do the best job I can,'' he said. ''I don't think I would think about that until after.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
