<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fleeing Iraqis Find a Refuge, And Kind Treatment, in Iran</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="AFTER THE WAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFUGEES AND EXPATRIATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIITE MOSLEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, JUDITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910403T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D61538F930A35757C0A967958260" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fleeing Iraqis Find a Refuge, And Kind Treatment, in Iran</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH MILLER, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, JUDITH</byline>
      <dateline>HOVEIZA, Iran, April 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abbas Bossfon stepped on a land mine and lost his left foot fighting Iran in the Iraq-Iran war six years ago. Six days ago, he turned to the country he had fought asking for safe haven, and was granted refuge.</p>
        <p>Terrified by the uprising against Saddam Hussein in Amara, his hometown, Mr. Bossfon loaded his wife and seven children into the tiny orange taxi he owns and fled to the Prairie of the Liberated refugee camp here in southwestern Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Abbas Bossfon stepped on a land mine and lost his left foot fighting Iran in the Iraq-Iran war six years ago. Six days ago, he turned to the country he had fought asking for safe haven, and was granted refuge.</p>
        <p>Terrified by the uprising against Saddam Hussein in Amara, his hometown, Mr. Bossfon loaded his wife and seven children into the tiny orange taxi he owns and fled to the Prairie of the Liberated refugee camp here in southwestern Iran.</p>
        <p>More than 40,000 Iraqi civilians, mostly Shiite Muslims from the south, have fled to the many refugee camps sprinkled throughout this border province, Khuzistan, since the rebellion against President Hussein began just over a month ago. An 'Overwhelming' Problem</p>
        <p>Iranian officials refused to disclose information about the flow of Iraqi refugees, but a senior Iranian official described the problem as "overwhelming."</p>
        <p>The refugees, he said, were draining Iran's reserves of shelter and food. But he stressed that Iran was determined to do what was needed to cope with the influx on its own.</p>
        <p>During a tour of two refugee camps in the border region, arranged for a reporter by the Government in Teheran, a local official said the number of refugees was "growing by the hour."</p>
        <p>At the Prairie of the Liberated camp, Mr. Bossfon and other refugees interviewed today in this Arabic-speaking region of Persian Iran said they did not fear coming to the land of a former enemy.</p>
        <p>"I feel safe here," Mr. Bossfon said, pointing to the cardboard wrapped by elastic below his ankle that now serves as his foot. "I never gave it a second thought,"  Tents for 10,000 Refugees</p>
        <p>He has had little reason to fear. Iran has welcomed these people with a generosity that has impressed diplomats from Teheran and a few of the others who have been permitted to visit the area.</p>
        <p>At this camp, 1,400 tents housing 10,000 refugees have been pitched; water tanks have been placed at several stations; latrines have been dug for sanitation, and 30 showers have been installed. Canned beans, dates and flat bread are distributed daily, and local authorities are making every effort to unite families, many of whom have arrived apart in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>A young paramedic said 20 doctors and paramedics were working in the camp. Several refugees showed vaccination cards. About a week after they arrived, they were treated for various illnesses, and their children were vaccinated against tetanus, polio, chicken pox, dysentery and whooping cough.</p>
        <p>Eventually these people are to be moved to other camps with sturdier and cooler housing for the long hot summers in the province, where temperatures routinely reach 110 degrees.</p>
        <p>Some of the refugees are clearly more than neutral citizens. Several of the tents are decorated with pictures of Mohammed Bakr-Hakim, the leader of the Supreme Council of the Islamic Revolution of Iraq, the self-proclaimed spiritual leader of Iraqi Shiites. His forces have been fighting in Iraq, but Mr. Hakim has been a resident of Teheran for years, and is supported by the Government.</p>
        <p>Many refugees expressed hatred for President Hussein, who they said had destroyed their towns and villages, repressed the Shiite branch of Islam and deprived them of liberty.</p>
        <p>Talif Salbough Hussein, a 22-year-old former medical student at the University of Basra, said he had fled just as the uprising started and had arrived here last night.</p>
        <p>"If Saddam Hussein would be gone, we would all go home tomorrow," he said. "You must tell the world: Saddam Hussein is a murderer. He's killed hundreds in my town. And he's repressed the people."</p>
        <p>A student at the University of Baghdad said he and 11 friends left at once several days ago, all without their families, who nonetheless encouraged their departure. "There is no freedom in Iraq," he said.</p>
        <p>Revolutionary fervor was also evident at another camp a half hour's drive toward the border from here. Local officials have pitched drab olive green tents for 100 Iraqis who would not be separated from their cattle. As cows and goats grazed peacefully on a field covered with yellow wildflowers, a man who identified himself as Ahmed described his life of fear inside Iraq.</p>
        <p>His two brothers were executed by the Baghdad Government in 1983, he said. After that he and other members of his family refused to join "Saddam's army."  'We're Fine Here'</p>
        <p>Instead, some of his brothers took up arms against President Hussein. The rest of them "played hide-and-seek" with Iraqi soldiers. Finally, the family decided that their livelihood -- 1,000 heads of cattle -- had to be saved. So he and some 50 members of his extended family crossed the border three weeks ago.</p>
        <p>"We're fine here," he said. "The Iranians have given us everything we need."</p>
        <p>Ahmed's two wives recently arrived at Prairie of the Liberated camp, and the authorities have made arrangements for them to be reunited here near the border.</p>
        <p>Iraqi refugees interviewed today said Iranian officials screen new arrivals just after they cross the border to insure that they are not infiltrators sent by Baghdad.</p>
        <p>Only yesterday, Teheran Radio reported an attack at the northern border town of Qasr-i-Shirin by the People's Mujahedeen, a militant Iranian opposition group financed and armed by Baghdad. The attack was driven back by Iranian soldiers, the radio said, but fear of recurrence of such attacks is widespread.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Iran has absorbed more than two million refugees of Afghan and Iraqi origin. Unlike Pakistan, which has received substantial aid for refugees, Iran has not asked for or received such aid.</p>
        <p>"Other countries have turned refugees into an industry," said a Western diplomat in Teheran. "With all of its problems, this country has not done that."</p>
        <p>AFTER THE WAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
