<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kyoto as It Used to Be</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KYOTO (JAPAN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1139F933A05756C0A965958260" item-length="1999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kyoto as It Used to Be</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE essence of old Kyoto, a city often described as the cultural soul of Japan, may lie behind an onion patch. It is a plain patch of broad furrows, with a few wispy rows of vegetables in spring that point toward a droopy thatch-roofed hut, but the history of that cottage and its environs are part of what make this section of Kyoto, called Arashiyama, one of the more evocative spots in a splendid city threatened by overdevelopment.</p>
        <p>The ancient cottage, known as Rakushisha, or the hut of fallen persimmons, rests in a quiet residential neighorhood alongside a lane shaded by towering trees. It is the sort of place that might inspire a poet skilled at capturing the transcendent moments when man and nature seem to intersect. That, in fact, is a part of what this unusual area remains to this day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE essence of old Kyoto, a city often described as the cultural soul of Japan, may lie behind an onion patch. It is a plain patch of broad furrows, with a few wispy rows of vegetables in spring that point toward a droopy thatch-roofed hut, but the history of that cottage and its environs are part of what make this section of Kyoto, called Arashiyama, one of the more evocative spots in a splendid city threatened by overdevelopment.</p>
        <p>The ancient cottage, known as Rakushisha, or the hut of fallen persimmons, rests in a quiet residential neighorhood alongside a lane shaded by towering trees. It is the sort of place that might inspire a poet skilled at capturing the transcendent moments when man and nature seem to intersect. That, in fact, is a part of what this unusual area remains to this day.</p>
        <p>The great haiku poet Matsuo Basho stayed at an earlier hut here 300 years ago, composing his powerfully elliptical verse, and the site still offers a bucolic respite from a city transformed during the 1980's by the jackhammer and feverish property development. Arashiyama, in Kyoto's often overlooked western district, is a sort of haiku of a neighborhood, a reference to quieter times and their special delights.</p>
        <p>Arashiyama is an earthy realm of bamboo groves and thatched teahouses, without a high-rise in sight. It has several temples that were once imperial palaces, so they are not modest. But unlike some of the more famous spots in Kyoto, where the gardens are oases of green amid office and apartment buildings, Arashiyama's sights still lie within the hills and natural scenery that were intended to be a part of their charm.</p>
        <p>The area also has some of the city's best traditional inns and restaurants, for those whose budgets can accommodate the high prices. Even visitors disinclined to spend $50 on an exquisite vegetarian lunch can enjoy Arashiyama, however, since there are plenty of inexpensive places to eat and stay.</p>
        <p>One can walk or ride bikes from temple to temple, alongside wooded hills, listening to the gray-green Oi River, also known as the Hozu, rather than the coarser rhythms of street traffic and nightclubs.</p>
        <p>No one, of course, is suggesting that you ignore the exquisite gardens of raked pebbles, the glittering temples, castles and palaces in the more-trafficked parts of this ancient capital city. It is just that visiting the better-known sites of Kyoto, situated mostly in the central and eastern precincts, can be an intensely urban experience these days.</p>
        <p>Arashiyama is hardly undiscovered; on a weekend in the popular spring and fall seasons Japanese visitors fill the streets. But the pace is notably gentler than in the rest of Kyoto. The neighborhood's distance from the city's center have protected it so far from rapid development.</p>
        <p>Any visit ought to begin with a short stop at Togetsukyo, or the moon-crossing bridge, at a spot where the Hozu River is broad and shallow. Although the low bridge now rests on concrete, rather than wooden supports, it has the lightly arched look of a traditional Japanese bridge and offers a good perspective on the district.</p>
        <p>As one looks upstream, Arashiyama itself rises to the left, on the south side of the river. The name means storm mountain, but themountain is really a large hill whose flanks are covered with a rich mix of trees. Amid the deep green pines are cherry trees originally brought here from Yoshino, a sacred spot, some 700 years ago by imperial order.</p>
        <p>On the right bank are several of the area's finer inns, such as Hotel Arashiyama, Benkei and Hotel Rantei. They lie along a promenade where one often sees women in kimono and rickshaw drivers pulling visitors. The river itself is usually dotted with boats, from the rowboats rented by the hour to the long, gondola-like boats that can be hired with their boatmen for whole afternoons or evenings. This is a favorite spot for moon-viewing on clear nights.</p>
        <p>The visitor tour should begin by heading back from the bridge to the north bank, either by foot or on one of the bicycles that can be rented from shops on the area's main street, in front of Togetsukyo.</p>
        <p>Delightfully, one can cover the area this way without having to fight traffic on the narrow streets.</p>
        <p>Just a hundred yards or so from the the bridge, Tenryu-ji, a large Zen Buddhist temple complex, is on the left. Tenryu-ji was originally a villa for Emperor Kameyama, in the late 13th century; his grandson, who went on to become Emperor Go-Daigo, was raised there.</p>
        <p>After Go-Daigo's death, in 1339, a Zen temple was erected on the site by the reign- ing shogun, Ashikaga Takauji, to placate the spirit of the deceased emperor, with whom he had fought. It was a spectacular offering; the complex eventually covered four square miles and comprised some 150 structures. But it was caught up in a series of feuds and was razed many times.</p>
        <p>Today Tenryu-ji covers a fraction of the original site and its few remaining structures were built in 1899. The buildings are rather formal and show some Chinese influence in their tall, peaked roofs. Perhaps because the grounds were rebuilt so recently, they do not have the lofty old shade trees of many other temples.</p>
        <p>But the surrounding hills are a constant presence, and Tenryu-ji does retain its original garden. It is laid out around a pond cut in the shape of the character for kokoro, which means heart or soul, a symbol for the Zen ideal of enlightenment.</p>
        <p>After a stroll through the grounds it is pleasant to spend a few minutes looking at the pond, particularly the famous dry waterfall arranged on its west bank, a series of seven angular rocks meant to evoke the landscape in a Chinese painting.</p>
        <p>The temple also serves lunch. Full-course vegetarian meals, known as shojin ryori, featuring a series of tofu and vegetable dishes, are served for prices ranging from $27 to $63.</p>
        <p>On leaving Tenryu-ji, go back to the main road, turn left away from the bridge, and make the next left. This is one of the most pleasant stretches of the tour, leading through a thick grove of dark green bamboo, a forest of towering stalks that sway and hum in the wind. It ends at one of the largest and loveliest gardens in Kyoto, the Okochi Sanso, spectacular for the traditional-style home in the five-acre garden as well as the views down its sinuous paths.</p>
        <p>ON leaving, turn to the left and walk past a small pond, along another narrow lane. At the T-junction, turn left again and you will find yourself at the long row of steps leading up to Jojakko-ji, a serene temple.</p>
        <p>The visitor passes through an unusual thatch-roofed gate -- they generally have tiles -- with two imposing guardian figures seated on either side. Then one tackles a long set of steps up to a terrace.</p>
        <p>To the left is a small chapel with a series of benches for resting.</p>
        <p>The porch of one of the temple structures is a good place to contemplate the temple's unusual garden. Arranged in moss and stones with a small pond, it incorporates virtually the entire hillside.</p>
        <p>A short but steep walk farther up the hill is an excellent example of a two-story pagoda from the Edo Period, which lasted from 1615 to 1868. It is a masterful work of carpentry.</p>
        <p>It is easy to miss one of Jojakko-ji's lovelier, hidden spots, a little waterfall spilling through a recess in the hillside. About a third of the way back down the main steps, step off to your right and you will find this little hideaway, a damp, mossy spot where one can offer a coin to the small stone Buddha image .</p>
        <p>After leaving Jojakko-ji, walk straight ahead less than 50 yards and you will find yourself looking out over the vegetable patch in front of Rakushisha, the hut of the fallen persimmons.</p>
        <p>There is a precious quality to Rakushisha, but it is hard not to feel a rush of appreciation for its historical importance -- a bit like finding the place where Shakespeare composed his sonnets. (The structure is believed to date from the second half of the 18th century, after Basho's time, but scholars believe it is modeled after the original.)The simple entryway frames an old mud wall, from which hangs a traditional round straw hat and straw rain cape, like those Basho wore on his treks around Japan in the late 17th century. The original hut was owned by Mukai Kyorai, one of Basho's key disciples, and the master is said to have visited it three times between 1689 and 1694, shortly before he died.</p>
        <p>It was during his second stay, from April 18 to May 5, 1691, that he composed his Saga Diary (Saga being the name of this immediate area). A poem from the diary, as well as poems of some of his disciples and those who have helped preserve the cottage, are carved into stones in the garden.</p>
        <p>Several of the cottage's rooms are arranged as though the master had just dropped by. A pot with fresh flowers sits on the straw mats, a painted screen lies open against the wall, a pair of old-fashioned bamboo sandals rest on a rock.</p>
        <p>From Rakushisha, turn to the right and take the lane that leads behind the cottage. The narrow street stretches for a half-mile or so past temples and shops, modern restaurants and ice-cream shops.</p>
        <p>One of the nicer shops is Koto-en, which specializes in the distinctive pottery of Shigaraki, a village east of Kyoto that has been producing pots for more than a thousand years. The shop carries a good selection of the rough pots covered with lumpy, mottled ash-glazes that potters from this area have perfected, which make a dramatic counterpoint to well-arranged flowers. Pieces run from 2,500 yen to 200,000 yen.</p>
        <p>AMONG the other temples along this stretch is Gio-ji, a thatched temple in the shadow of some trees. This is a contemplative spot, the simple cluster of structures looking quite rural with their thick roofs, the grounds a play of moss, maples and shadows. It is dedicated to Gio, a dancer whose story is celebrated in a famous book, "Tales of the Heike." She was the mistress of a powerful warlord in the 12th century, but found herself replaced by another young woman whom she had introduced to her lover. She scribbled a poem about the fleeting nature of happiness before she departed, then became a nun here; the woman who had pushed her aside found the poem and was so moved by it that she, too, became a nun.</p>
        <p>A short walk past this temple are two beautiful thatched huts, both several hundred years old. They were once used by pilgrims making the ascent to the shrine atop Mount Atago, where the people of Kyoto prayed for protection against the ruinous fires that swept the city periodically.</p>
        <p>Both houses are now restaurants serving tea and sweets or meals of ayu, a sort of small trout caught in the Hozu River, and a local specialty, yu-dofu, cubes of tofu simmered in clay pots and dipped in a soy-based sauce.</p>
        <p>Another temple of great historical importance, Daikaku-ji, can be easily reached from here by heading due east about a quarter-mile from the tea houses. It was originally a palace for Emperor Saga, who took his name from this region. It was turned into a Buddhist temple in the ninth century.</p>
        <p>It is most famous as the site where the imperial throne was split between two feuding brothers during the 13th century, before a warlord brought an end to the division. Today Daikaku-ji is a rambling series of handsome wooden structures connected by covered walkways, most of it shaded by tall old trees. Among its treasures are beautiful painted sliding doors; some of the more famous depict peonies and hunting falcons . The compound has a large terrace that overlooks a pond, with a tall pagoda visible through the trees to the north.</p>
        <p>Basho, at least, found all this history and scenery quite seductive. As he wrote, in concluding his Saga Diary: "Tomorrow I leave the hut of the fallen persimmons and nostalgia hangs over my heart."</p>
        <p>Then he wrote a haiku, which is also carved into a stone in the garden behind the hut: Springtime rains  on the walls remain  scraps of poems once pasted there.</p>
        <p>JAMES STERNGOLD is a correspondent in the Tokyo bureau of the Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JAMES STERNGOLD is a correspondent in the Tokyo bureau of the Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
