<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush on the Offensive in Defending C.I.A. Choice</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (CIA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GATES, ROBERT M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D91E39F936A15754C0A967958260" item-length="402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush on the Offensive in Defending C.I.A. Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush today issued another brisk defense of his choice to head the Central Intelligence Agency, Robert M. Gates, calling news reports linking the nominee with unapproved intelligence operations "phantoms" and "shadows."</p>
        <p>The President's remarks came amid open worries by some of Mr. Gates's supporters in Congress and outside of government that the debate over his nomination was spinning out of the White House's control, in part because of the Administration's preoccupation with winning Senate confirmation of Judge Clarence Thomas to the Supreme Court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush today issued another brisk defense of his choice to head the Central Intelligence Agency, Robert M. Gates, calling news reports linking the nominee with unapproved intelligence operations "phantoms" and "shadows."</p>
        <p>The President's remarks came amid open worries by some of Mr. Gates's supporters in Congress and outside of government that the debate over his nomination was spinning out of the White House's control, in part because of the Administration's preoccupation with winning Senate confirmation of Judge Clarence Thomas to the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Bush opened a photograph session with Republican leaders with an attack on news reports about Mr. Gates, predicting with apparent irritation that "fairness will out in the end" and that Mr. Gates would be confirmed to the C.I.A. post.</p>
        <p>"I think that the man deserves to be confirmed," Mr. Bush said, "and I've seen nothing other than innuendo and reports that he must have known this or something. I don't want to get started. I told the Cabinet yesterday how strongly I feel about this and so I will stand by this man." 'Get the Facts Out'</p>
        <p>After the meeting with Mr. Bush, one of the Republican leaders, Senator Phil Gramm of Texas, said of Mr. Gates's nomination that it was "important to get the facts out on the table, to give him an opportunity to make his case to the committee and to get on with it."</p>
        <p>"I'm not worried about it," Mr. Gramm said. "I'm worried about a process where we delay and delay and delay and then often people who could be good public servants decide it's not worth it."</p>
        <p>Since his nomination in May, Mr. Gates, the President's deputy national-security adviser, has been bombarded by news reports exploring his handling of the Iran-contra affair when it unraveled in 1986. At the time, Mr. Gates was the chief deputy to the Director of Central Intelligence, William J. Casey.</p>
        <p>The Senate Intelligence Committee recently voted to postpone hearings on the nomination until September after a former C.I.A. officer, Alan D. Fiers Jr., said that a subordinate of Mr. Gates ordered him to conceal some aspects of the scandal from Congress. The panel plans to ask Mr. Fiers what Mr. Gates knew about the affair. Mr. Fiers's admission was contained in court documents made public earlier this month after he pleaded guilty to two misdemeanor charges of withholding information from Congress.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
