<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carrot-Stick Budget; Weicker's Income-Tax Plan, giving Everyone Something, Is Hard to Kill</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="424324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEICKER, LOWELL P JR (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DE173BF93BA25751C0A967958260" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carrot-Stick Budget; Weicker's Income-Tax Plan, giving Everyone Something, Is Hard to Kill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, Feb. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The income-tax plan that Gov. Lowell P. Weicker Jr. presented last week seems likely to shatter the state's once-monolithic opposition to a wage tax, leaving in its place a fragmented battlefield of half- enemies and half-friends.</p>
        <p>Such indecision is perhaps the plan's only hope, given the abortive and bitter history that income- tax legislation has had in Connecticut and the fact that Mr. Weicker, as an independent Governor, has no legislators bound by party loyalty to defend his ideas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The income-tax plan that Gov. Lowell P. Weicker Jr. presented last week seems likely to shatter the state's once-monolithic opposition to a wage tax, leaving in its place a fragmented battlefield of half- enemies and half-friends.</p>
        <p>Such indecision is perhaps the plan's only hope, given the abortive and bitter history that income- tax legislation has had in Connecticut and the fact that Mr. Weicker, as an independent Governor, has no legislators bound by party loyalty to defend his ideas.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Weicker expected his plan to win few cheers, he also crafted it to be hard to kill. Meant to resolve a projected $2.4 billion shortfall in tax revenue, the budget is built around an interlocked series of tax rewards and cuts in state aid that the Governor hopes will push lawmakers into a corner. In both a positive and negative sense, it is a plan with something for everybody.</p>
        <p>At its core, it would link a flat 6 percent wage tax -- an immensely unpopular concept in many areas of the state -- to a series of other major changes that lawmakers in both parties have for years been clamoring for. Connecticut is one of only 10 states that do not tax wages. Accompanied by Tax Cuts</p>
        <p>Business taxes, long derided as too high, especially by Republicans, would be cut from 13.8 percent to 11.5 percent. The 8 percent sales tax, long an anathema to many Democrats, who feel it hurts the poor, would be cut nearly in half, to 4.25 percent.</p>
        <p>The rapid growth in state spending of recent years, attacked by moderates in both parties, would be brought to a screeching halt. Total spending would decline 2.3 percent in the fiscal year that begins July 1 -- to $7.48 million.</p>
        <p>There are also some elements that could divide opponents by region. Many residents of Fairfield County in particular -- by far the state's wealthiest corner -- would see their tax bills decline sharply under the plan, although many others would certainly pay more.</p>
        <p>Most residents who commute to New York State, for example, would still pay only the New York income tax that they do now. But their income from dividends and interest, now taxed by Connecticut at a progressive scale that peaks at 14 percent for family income over $100,000, would be cut to 6 percent.</p>
        <p>Of the $1.1 billion in state spending cuts identified in the plan, the wealthiest towns would be hit the hardest. They would in many cases get less aid than they did last year, especially for education, thus creating further hesitation for legislators representing those communities. If no other revenue source could be found, legislators could be faced with a no-win proposition to take home to their constituents: Will it be teacher layoffs or an income tax? A Puzzle for Legislators</p>
        <p>"A lot of reps and senators who would be inclined to vote against an income tax are caught between a rock and a hard place," said Senator George Jepson, a Democrat from Stamford. "Without the revenues, their communities stand to lose enormous amounts of aid."</p>
        <p>So far it seems that Mr. Weicker has at least partly succeeded in disrupting the united front of income-tax opposition. But whether that will lead to any coalition that actually backs the plan is still open to question.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, who hold the majority in both chambers, are seemingly divided enough to require some Republican votes for the plan to pass, a fact that lawmakers on both sides say puts the Republican minority in the driver's seat.</p>
        <p>But the Republicans are not that solidly unified either. Forty-two were elected last year on direct promises to oppose an income tax, and few of the remainder are friendly to the idea, noted the minority leader in the House, Representative Edward C. Krawiecki Jr., a Republican from Bristol.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the Republican caucus has not yet said that its goal is to kill the $2.1 billion income tax. There have been indications that Republican support of an income tax would be contingent on a constitutional or statutory ceiling on growth in spending in future years.</p>
        <p>"I expect you would find members receptive to the idea of that kind of tax with meaningful structural reforms," Mr. Krawiecki said. He said he would push for such changes.  A Hard Choice for Democrats</p>
        <p>Some Democrats think that whatever the Republicans say now, they will ultimately close ranks and vote against an income tax. This might force the Democratic majority in the Legislature to face the odious prospect of uniting and voting for the tax to balance the budget, but risking the public wrath in next year's elections. The Democrats have 89 seats in the House to the Republicans' 62. In the Senate there are 20 Democrats and 16 Republicans.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats who have long favored an income tax will seek to change Mr. Weicker's version of one. Lawmakers in both parties have complained, for example, that the flat rate -- unlike the progressive systems in other states, where the income-tax bite increases with one's earnings -- would fall hardest on middle-income families.</p>
        <p>Under the Weicker proposal, the first $25,000 of a family's adjusted gross income, or $12,500 for an individual, would be tax-free. The 6 percent rate would begin on money earned over those amounts.</p>
        <p>Amendments are also expected that would allow greater deductions, especially for children, to protect larger families and single-parent households. But there is hesitation over how much of what the Governor has proposed can be tinkered with safely.</p>
        <p>"Saving the baby is the first order of business -- then let's change the temperature of the bath water afterwards," said Representative Miles S. Rapoport, a Democrat from West Hartford and a longtime advocate of an income tax.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
