<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. DETAINS ARAB TIED TO MILITANTS</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="778258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXTRADITION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED ARAB EMIRATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HAMAS (ISLAMIC FUNDAMENTALIST MOVEMENT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARZOOK, MOUSA MOHAMED ABU</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/United Arab Emirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DA163AF93BA15754C0A963958260" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. DETAINS ARAB TIED TO MILITANTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United States officials have taken into custody a Palestinian they say is one of the senior leaders of Hamas, the militant Islamic group that has claimed responsibility for recent bombings in Israel, Attorney General Janet Reno said today.</p>
        <p>Immigration officials said they detained the Palestinian, Mousa Mohamed Abu Marzook, at Kennedy Airport in New York on Tuesday as he was arriving from abroad because he was on a terrorist watch list. Mr. Marzook, who American and Israeli authorities say is the head of Hamas's political committee, is being held at the Metropolitan Correctional Center in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United States officials have taken into custody a Palestinian they say is one of the senior leaders of Hamas, the militant Islamic group that has claimed responsibility for recent bombings in Israel, Attorney General Janet Reno said today.</p>
        <p>Immigration officials said they detained the Palestinian, Mousa Mohamed Abu Marzook, at Kennedy Airport in New York on Tuesday as he was arriving from abroad because he was on a terrorist watch list. Mr. Marzook, who American and Israeli authorities say is the head of Hamas's political committee, is being held at the Metropolitan Correctional Center in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The Immigration and Naturalization Service filed papers this afternoon in immigration court in Manhattan that called for expelling Mr. Marzook because he "appears to be an alien who is engaged in terrorist activity" and because the Attorney General "has reasonable grounds to believe" that he is likely to engage in terrorist activities after being admitted.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Marzook is not indicted under American law or extradited to Israel, immigration officials said, he would most likely be expelled to the United Arab Emirates, the country he most recently left from.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said the exclusion proceedings might be pre-empted if the Justice Department decided to prosecute Mr. Marzook for activities they are investigating, such as illegally raising funds to promote terrorism.</p>
        <p>Stanley L. Cohen of Manhattan, a lawyer for Mr. Marzook, said his client supported Hamas's goals like hundreds of thousands of other Palestinians, but he denied Mr. Marzook was a leader of Hamas.</p>
        <p>"We categorically deny that my client has been involved in any criminal activities anywhere at any time," said Mr. Cohen. "He denies categorically that he is a terrorist. He denies categorically these wild and sweeping claims being bandied about by the Israelis and U.S. as disinformation."</p>
        <p>Administration officials said Mr. Marzook was surprised to be taken into custody because he has had a green card since 1990 and has maintained a residence in the United States for 14 years, most recently with his wife and six children in northern Virginia. Mr. Cohen said the Marzook family was in the process of moving to Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>One Administration official said Mr. Marzook was not arrested previously because he was only recently put on the watch list.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marzook arrived at Kennedy Airport with his wife and children on a flight from the United Arab Emirates that had stopped in London. His lawyer said Mr. Marzook's entire family had been subjected to strip searches, which he called an outrage.</p>
        <p>American and Israeli officials called Mr. Marzook one of the most influental members of Hamas, who, they said, had traveled in recent months to Syria, Iran, Sudan and Egypt to promote terrorism and undermine Middle East peace efforts.  Last month, Jordan expelled Mr. Marzook after calling him a ringleader in efforts to sabotage Jordan's peace prospects with Israel.</p>
        <p>Israeli security officials said Mr. Marzook is the top political leader of Hamas and thus sets political as well as strategic policy, including questions like whether the group employ terrorist attacks.</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials said Mr. Marzook had been one of the most active members in the United Association for Studies and Research, based in Springfield, Va., which they said was a Hamas front. But one leader of an Arab-American organization said that assocation was a small propaganda outfit.</p>
        <p>While the American authorities said they could not link Mr. Marzook to any specific terrorist act, they said the political leadership of Hamas helped promote the organization's terrorist activities, including recent bombings in Israel.</p>
        <p>Administration officials also said they were seeking to determine if Mr. Marzook, who holds a Yemeni passport, had engaged in illegal fund-raising activities for Hamas. They were also studying whether to turn him over to Israeli authorities.</p>
        <p>Dan Arbell, a spokesman for the Israeli Embassy, said, "We have a keen interest in Dr. Marzook, who is one of the acknowledged leaders of Hamas, the head of its political bureau, and as such has been one of the principal orchestrators of attacks against Israeli civilians." But it was not clear if the Israelis would seek his extradition.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials said Mr. Marzook was born in 1951 in the Rafiah refugee district at the southern end of Gaza. They said he has a doctorate in engineering.</p>
        <p>In a statement today, Imad Faluji, a senior Hamas official in Gaza, condemned the decision to detain Mr. Marzook and virtually acknowledged that he was a Hamas leader. "This is a serious precedent, an unjustified step," he said. "It comes as an attempt to tighten the ring on the Islamic movement."</p>
        <p>Mr. Faluji urged the United States to free Mr. Marzook on the ground that he was a political figure and not a terrorist.</p>
        <p>One senior Administration official said the situation was complicated because some Israeli officials had hinted they would like Mr. Marzook extradited, but the Israeli Government has said only that it is considering whether to seek extradition.</p>
        <p>At the same time, American officials acknowledged that while they strongly believe he promoted terrorist activities abroad, they are not sure he commited any crimes in the United States that they can prosecute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Marzook is said to have spent most of his time in the Middle East over the last three years, after which, officials said, he came under intensified investigation for his pro-Hamas work in the United States. Security officials say he went to Teheran in October 1992, in the role of Hamas's "foreign minister," to establish relations with Iran.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen, Mr. Marzook's lawyer, said: "During the time he has lived in the United States, he has never been arrested, charged with any offense or suspected of any criminal activities. It's interesting that given the extensive intelligence sharing between the Israelis and the United States, even now he's not charged with any crime. What's happened is outrageous."</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen said that his client had worked in the construction business and investment business.</p>
        <p>According to immigration officials, Mr. Marzook was last in the United States five months ago. They said he was not detained when he left because the Government does not usually check if departing passengers are on the watch list.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
