<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daley Easily Wins Re-election, Nearing a Record in Chicago</title>
    <meta content="28daley" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/28/us/28daley.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Richard M (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daley, Richard J (1902-76)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saulny, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Daley, Richard M</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DD1F3EF93BA15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daley Easily Wins Re-election, Nearing a Record in Chicago</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Daley Easily Wins Re-election in Chicago</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Feb. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Richard M Daley wins landslide re-election over two challengers and is in position to become Chicago's longest-serving mayor if he completes full term; his father, Richard J Daley, holds record with 21 years in office; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley won a landslide victory over two relatively obscure challengers here Tuesday, putting him in a position to become the city's longest serving mayor.</p>
        <p>With 87 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Daley had captured 72 percent of the vote, well over the 50 percent needed to avoid a runoff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If he serves his full term, Mayor Richard M. Daley will surpass by a year the 21 years his father, Richard J. Daley, spent in office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Richard M. Daley won a landslide victory over two relatively obscure challengers here Tuesday, putting him in a position to become the city's longest serving mayor.</p>
        <p>With 87 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Daley had captured 72 percent of the vote, well over the 50 percent needed to avoid a runoff.</p>
        <p>''Thank you, Chicago, thank you again,'' Mr. Daley told a boisterous crowd in a Hilton Hotel ballroom.</p>
        <p>He added, ''We must continue to work together and put aside any personal or political differences to keep Chicago moving forward on behalf of all the people of our great city.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley's victory came despite a short and lackluster campaign, the loss of traditional support from organized labor and his place at the center of a ballooning federal inquiry into the administration's hiring practices. Mr. Daley, a Democrat, has not been accused of any crime, but some of his top aides have been indicted.</p>
        <p>Despite those challenges -- any of which might have meant defeat for a less powerful incumbent -- if Mr. Daley, 64, serves a full term, he will surpass by a year the 21 years his father, Richard J. Daley, had in office.</p>
        <p>Some political observers expect this to be Mr. Daley's last term. But they do not expect to see a lame duck. As his lack of strong competition showed, Mr. Daley's power remains largely unquestioned.</p>
        <p>''The day after the election is going to be the same as the day before the election,'' said Don Rose, a political consultant here. ''There's no pressure in any direction. He really doesn't have any significant opposition on the City Council or from the media, so he can go on doing what he's doing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daley's critics in organized labor and among more independent-minded Democrats thought they had an opportunity this election to chip away at some of his power, given the hiring scandals and his decision last year to veto an ordinance that would have imposed minimum wage regulations on stores like Wal-Mart.</p>
        <p>They made some progress. For instance, in the Seventh Ward, a battleground area of the South Side, Sandi S. Jackson defeated the incumbent, Darcel A. Beavers, the daughter of the former alderman, and longtime Daley ally.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jackson is married to Representative Jesse L. Jackson Jr., a son of the Rev. Jesse Jackson and a longtime Daley foe. As recently as November, Mr. Jackson was considered a serious potential challenger to Mr. Daley. But after the Democrats won control of Congress, he decided against a run for mayor.</p>
        <p>Unlike Chicago, many other big cities have mayoral term limits, preventing the sort of political domination that Mr. Daley has accomplished over his 18 years in office.</p>
        <p>The father-son Daley dynasty has done more to shape the modern political history and physical landscape of Chicago, the nation's third-largest city, with its diversified economy and glittering downtown, than perhaps any other force.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Daley brags about Chicago as though it is his personal possession, he has played down that legacy. Even Tuesday, he refused to make comparisons with his father.</p>
        <p>''I'll compare my city to any city in America right now,'' Mr. Daley said, citing safe neighborhoods and new libraries and parks.</p>
        <p>''You don't run for office just to be there and say, 'I beat a record,' '' he added, seeming a little testy. ''You really want to accomplish things.''</p>
        <p>Minutes earlier, when Mr. Daley arrived at Old St. Mary's Catholic Church on the South Side to cast his vote, he seemed relaxed and unconcerned about the election.</p>
        <p>There was no last-minute rallying of the troops. No visible excitement or nervousness. And no entourage.</p>
        <p>During the campaign, Mr. Daley hardly acknowledged his opponents, Dorothy Brown, the clerk of the Cook County Circuit Court, and William Walls, a former aide to Harold Washington, the city's first elected black mayor. There were no debates.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Daley voted, a reporter asked what grade he would give himself as mayor so far.</p>
        <p>''You don't give grades,'' he said. ''Grades are only given on Election Day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
