<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>John Galliano Kicks Up His Heels</title>
    <meta content="28FASHION" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/28/fashion/28FASHION.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FASHION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Balenciaga</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dior, Christian</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Watanabe, Junya</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Yamamoto, Yohji</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DF1F3EF93BA15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>John Galliano Kicks Up His Heels</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">John Galliano Kicks Up His Heels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We should always ask ourselves when looking at the new fashion of a first-rate designer if these are clothes we want to wear on the street. If the answer is an enthusiastic yes, then the designer has not done his job. All he has done is to meet the most meager of our expectations.</p>
        <p>This was the problem today with Nicolas Ghesquiere's collection for Balenciaga. The vivid English school blazers and slender cargo pants looked very cool and young. They seemed to pulse with street energy, as did the loose dresses in a patchwork of silk prints, velvet and metallic fringe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reviews of the Balenciaga, Christian Dior, Junya Wantanabe, Rick Owens, Undercover, Viktor &amp; Rolf and Yohji Yamamoto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We should always ask ourselves when looking at the new fashion of a first-rate designer if these are clothes we want to wear on the street. If the answer is an enthusiastic yes, then the designer has not done his job. All he has done is to meet the most meager of our expectations.</p>
        <p>This was the problem today with Nicolas Ghesquiere's collection for Balenciaga. The vivid English school blazers and slender cargo pants looked very cool and young. They seemed to pulse with street energy, as did the loose dresses in a patchwork of silk prints, velvet and metallic fringe.</p>
        <p>But is it the direction you expect from a leader like Mr. Ghesquiere? After the couture finesse and futurism of the last two seasons, it may be that he hankered for more familiar clothes. They will doubtlessly sell like hot cakes. But they are not telling us anything that we can't imagine.</p>
        <p>More and more we look to designers who can truly design. Not embellish, not trick us with irony. People recognize the difference. This is why John Galliano's collection today for Dior stood out. Last season, he gave his bosses what they thought they wanted: nice, salable suits.</p>
        <p>Well, the Dior show should be a lesson to all fashion executives: Don't tell a genius how to design -- if you're lucky to have a genius. ''I got more space,'' Mr. Galliano said with supreme tact, meaning creative freedom, as Bernard Arnault, the chairman of LVMH Moët Hennessy Louis Vuitton, came backstage to congratulate him.</p>
        <p>''There's no one like him,'' Mr. Arnault said.</p>
        <p>Indeed. Mr. Galliano took the elements of his January couture show -- the mouth-watering colors, the glamorous cutting and draping -- and turned them into dynamic ready-to-wear. Against Michael Howells's stairway-to-heaven set, the fur-doused coats and suits (with origami details or splashes of silvery embroidery) enticed and agitated. There wasn't a dud among the 58 outfits.</p>
        <p>The looks just kept coming: a draped silk top with a floaty skirt in matching yellow gazar; a smoldering gray tweed dress with a low, squared-off back; an ink-blue calf-hair coat with lavish black fox cuffs, a gorgeous white silk evening dress with a cascading black collar. A few years ago editors were complaining that Mr. Galliano needed to move on. But did they ever imagine he could have this much fun?</p>
        <p>So the Paris shows are changing our expectations.</p>
        <p>Black leather jackets and deconstructed dresses over leggings gave Junya Watanabe's collection a street vitality. And because he frequently designs clothes for men that are easy, we forget that he is capable of much more sophistication and surprise than he delivered today.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Jun Takahashi's clothes for Undercover were at once simple and imaginative. He combined knitwear and sports fabrics like Gortex, often using linings that absorb body heat. A beige silk coat was quilted to resemble a sweater, and mink was shaved and grooved so that it assumed a completely different attitude. There were mink hot pants worn with wool tights in fresh shades of plum and aqua, and sweaters done in a patchwork of knitted wool and organza. This is the direction you expect from a designer.</p>
        <p>Halfway through Yohji Yamamoto's utterly entrancing show, a quartet of models appeared in full polka-dot skirts and black cutaway coats. They paused and, by a hidden mechanism, the tiers of their skirts began to spin. The women stood a moment, their faces a mask of somber Japanese beauty, and then they left the stage, the only sound a slight electronic whir coming from under their skirts.</p>
        <p>In a season of toughness, Mr. Yamamoto reminds us of the immense lure of romance. To all his pretty skirts and mysterious layers, he put a pair of masculine pants. Yet, his romance is a counterweight to Mr. Galliano's, and in the nine black strapless dresses that appeared at the show's end, all worn with trousers and black boots, you felt the unsentimental essence of modern Japanese fashion.</p>
        <p>Their sleeves like wands, Rick Owens's jackets in wool fleece and leather seemed to float on the body. His show was the most complete expression of the style he started in Los Angeles a decade and a half ago.</p>
        <p>His silhouette has become more sophisticated, more engrossing. Not only did he offer cropped jackets with loose funnel necklines or wide lapels of white fleece to make your face more beautiful, he also did a number of longer styles with a draped Poiret back. Poiret is as Parisian as the cobblestones, yet you never felt Mr. Owens was parading the fact.</p>
        <p>Nor did he did bother with color. There were just black, mushroom shades of brown, and winter white. And the draped jersey skirts were of the classic Owens mold. It was as though everything he had to say this time was trained on the modern architecture of a jacket, and he said it very well. The models all wore chunky knitted caps or smooth hoods, and on their feet suede booties with Seuss-like clumps of glossy hair.</p>
        <p>A male guest leaving the Viktor &amp; Rolf show was overheard to say to a friend: ''Did you like it? It was funny. Poor girls!'' To ask women barely out of their teens to wear large metal frames on their backs -- similar to the lighting apparatus you see at shows -- and then walk on high-heeled Dutch wooden shoes is to take advantage of them. Of course they won't complain. And the idea of individually spotlighting models was not new; Martin Margiela did it several years ago.</p>
        <p>That leaves the question of judgment. What is the matter with Viktor Horsting and Rolf Snoeren if they can't see that nothing was accomplished by this pantomime except sadistic humiliation? Poor them.</p>
        <p>FASHION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
