<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greek Classics, Without the Tragedy</title>
    <meta content="28unde" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining, Dining Out/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Dining and Wine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/28/dining/reviews/28unde.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DF1F3EF93BA15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greek Classics, Without the Tragedy</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Greek Classics, Without the Tragedy</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Meehan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meehan, Peter</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONERA ousted! Dona, done! Both of those celebrated restaurants have been consigned to antiquity. And so, the only place to catch Michael Psilakis's cooking at the moment is Kefi, where he presides over a menu of classic Greek cooking in the Upper West Side space that once housed Onera.</p>
        <p>How to explain such a fall? Could it be some variation on the story of Icarus, with Donatella Arpaia, his partner in Dona and a soon-to-open restaurant called Anthos in Midtown, as an encouraging and nonpaternal Daedalus, who cheered the chef on as he foolishly winged his way from a menu of adventurous kidney dishes and forward-looking foams to a deep plunge into a plebeian sea of easy-to-enjoy Greek standards?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kefi, with its immensely appealing menu of affordable and approachable Greek cuisine, should be an Upper West Side favorite.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONERA ousted! Dona, done! Both of those celebrated restaurants have been consigned to antiquity. And so, the only place to catch Michael Psilakis's cooking at the moment is Kefi, where he presides over a menu of classic Greek cooking in the Upper West Side space that once housed Onera.</p>
        <p>How to explain such a fall? Could it be some variation on the story of Icarus, with Donatella Arpaia, his partner in Dona and a soon-to-open restaurant called Anthos in Midtown, as an encouraging and nonpaternal Daedalus, who cheered the chef on as he foolishly winged his way from a menu of adventurous kidney dishes and forward-looking foams to a deep plunge into a plebeian sea of easy-to-enjoy Greek standards?</p>
        <p>Nope. That'd be a load of Bulfinch. Those old stories are suffused with too much tragedy to trace the arc of Mr. Psilakis, who went from calamari-slinging on Long Island just a few years ago to critical recognition for his progressive Greek cooking at Onera and Dona. Dona's demise was attributable to a real estate snafu; Onera was overhauled because Mr. Psilakis thought the food he was doing there needed a bigger, brighter stage, which is what he hopes Anthos will be.</p>
        <p>Kefi is what he has put in Onera's place. There's fried calamari on the menu, though no marinara to dunk it in. Affordable and approachable, it's the sort of restaurant any neighborhood would welcome with open arms, any neighborhood except the one it's in, perhaps: the dining room was scarcely populated or downright empty every time I visited. That lack of diners has me suspecting that Upper West Siders might have a greater affection for reading about the mythological scarcity of restaurants on the Upper West Side than they do for patronizing restaurants that prove how untrue that is.</p>
        <p>Emptiness doesn't do much for a dining room that's already somewhere between demure and depressing, stuck in a subterranean floor of a townhouse without a window out to the street or the city.</p>
        <p>Regardless of what you make of the room, the menu is immensely appealing. Its range is part of the appeal: the conservative diner could start a meal with a brilliantly composed Greek salad; others might be more enticed by expertly crisped sweetbreads, accompanied by artichokes. But it's the low prices that drive the deal home: I have paid more for tuna salad sandwiches than I did for those $7.95 sweetbreads, prepared in same kitchen that was widely praised for its all-offal tasting menu only months ago.</p>
        <p>All those low prices and enticing dishes can cause a problem: chronic over-ordering. When you order the $9.95 selection of spreads, know that those spreads are all two people will need to start a meal. And you will order them, unless you are intent on missing out on the work of a chef who says he will be pushing the limits of what diners consider Greek cuisine at his next place, but who is at this moment focusing his attention on nailing the classics.</p>
        <p>The selection includes tzatziki, taramosalata, an eggplant spread and a chickpea spread, all of which have been gently tweaked, with a suggestively heavy dose of roasted garlic, for example. It's easy to burn through the pile of grill-warmed pita that accompanies the selection to the table.</p>
        <p>The entree lineup ($9.95 to $15.95) is filled with the usual suspects -- pastichio, moussaka and grilled branzino (originally served on the bone, but now filleted), and all are worthwhile. Particularly good options include a braised lamb shank served over orzo, to which dill adds a touch of brightness, and a simple dish of flat pasta sauced with graviera cheese and tender shreds of rabbit meat that was faintly seasoned with cinnamon.</p>
        <p>Though the wine list has been pared down since Kefi was Onera, there are still plenty of great bottles on the list, most at very good prices. If $39 isn't too dear a price, the barrel-fermented moschofilero from the Tselepos winery would be my recommendation for washing back your order of Mr. Psilakis's excellent pork souvlaki, grilled expertly and served with tangy tzatziki over warm pita.</p>
        <p>Kefi  222 West 79th Street (Broadway), Upper West Side; (212) 873-0200.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES -- Flat pasta with braised rabbit; braised lamb shank; pork souvlaki; meatball soup; Greek spreads.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers, $4.50 to $9.95; main courses, $9.95 to $15.95; desserts, $3.95 to $7.95.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Cash only.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- 5 p.m. to 10 p.m. Sunday through Thursday; 5 p.m. to 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Ramp between sidewalk and entrance, which is below ground; restrooms accessible.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
