<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Birthplace of the Uprising Experiences a New Birth</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JABALIYA (GAZA STRIP)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GAZA STRIP</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JERICHO (ISRAELI-OCCUPIED TERRITORY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PALESTINE LIBERATION ORGANIZATION (PLO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENBERG, JOEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DF1638F936A25756C0A962958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Birthplace of the Uprising Experiences a New Birth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENBERG, JOEL</byline>
      <dateline>JABALIYA, Gaza Strip, May 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jabaliya refugee camp, birthplace of the Palestinian uprising and the scene of some of its most violent street battles, woke up today free of Israeli occupation.</p>
        <p>In the dark of early morning, the last Israeli soldiers walked out of the base in the heart of this teeming refugee district of 72,000, leaving it to a detachment of Palestinian policemen who had come from a Palestine Liberation Army base in the Sudan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jabaliya refugee camp, birthplace of the Palestinian uprising and the scene of some of its most violent street battles, woke up today free of Israeli occupation.</p>
        <p>In the dark of early morning, the last Israeli soldiers walked out of the base in the heart of this teeming refugee district of 72,000, leaving it to a detachment of Palestinian policemen who had come from a Palestine Liberation Army base in the Sudan.</p>
        <p>The overnight transformation was the latest in a rapidly spreading handover of control from Israel to the Palestinians throughout the Gaza Strip and in Jericho, but it had particular significance here. Jabaliya was the only refugee camp with an Israeli outpost in its midst, and it was here that the first Palestinian was killed in clashes with Israeli troops as the uprising erupted on Dec. 9, 1987.</p>
        <p>Israeli troops also began pulling out of Gaza City today, handing over a base in the Shajaiye neighborhood to Palestinian forces. A total of 9,000 Palestinian policemen are supposed to be posted in the Gaza Strip and Jericho, on the West Bank, after the Israeli withdrawal is complete. Watchtower Is Draped</p>
        <p>A soaring watchtower dominating Jabaliya, for years a looming symbol of Israeli rule, was draped today with a huge Palestinian flag. Hundreds watched as a Palestinian policeman and an armed man in camouflage fatigues climbed up to the lookout perch, where the civilian gunman unleashed volleys of rifle and pistol shots into the air.</p>
        <p>Throngs of residents, many of them boys who had hurled stones at the base in a daily ritual of defiance, strolled through it today, chatting with the uniformed Palestinian officers and visiting cells where they had once been jailed. Brightly colored balloons were strung over the entrance, and vendors sold juice and nuts where Israeli soldiers had often stood, guns at the ready, to repel angry crowds.</p>
        <p>Young men swept and washed floors, readying rooms for the policemen. Graffiti signed by several Palestinian factions, including the militant Islamic group Hamas, welcomed the police and urged residents not to vandalize the Israeli-built structures now used by the Palestinian force.</p>
        <p>"I feel free, and I'm not afraid any more," said 13-year-old Nabil Abu Oun. "The stone-throwing is over. Now we're building a state."</p>
        <p>A car carrying gunmen, who fired out the windows, pulled into the compound, where it was immediately mobbed by the crowd. Ahmad Saleh, who said he had been wanted by the Israelis for eight months, emerged from the vehicle with his friends -- fugitives no more. Still firing occasionally in the air, they walked off into the dusty streets trailed by bands of children. Weapons to Be Collected</p>
        <p>According to the Israeli-Palestinian agreement on self-rule in Gaza and Jericho, no armed force may operate except for the police, and no one may have a gun without official authorization. Muhammad Shalayl, a Palestinian officer visiting from Deir el Balah, insisted that the weapons would be collected.</p>
        <p>"Now people are firing them because they are happy," he said, "but later we will take them."</p>
        <p>Maj. Abdel Safi Sharif, the commander of the Jabaliya police base, dismissed suggestions that his men might meet violent resistance from militants opposed to the accord with Israel.</p>
        <p>"Before there was an occupation," he said, "but these are our brothers, sisters and cousins. They will abide by the rules."</p>
        <p>As for the watchtower, Major Sharif said he might dismantle it and use its struts to build sports equipment, streetlights or a bridge. But Muhammad Shaaban, a local teen-ager, said the tower "should be a monument to the oppression we were under."</p>
        <p>There were more immediate problems at the Palestinian police center in Shajaiya, where distraught officers pushed back crowds that mobbed the base.</p>
        <p>"We're happy to be with you, but we're tired," said one officer, speaking through a megaphone. "We haven't slept for four days, and we haven't had a chance to change our clothes."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
