<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Dogwood Lights Up the Land</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DA1638F936A25756C0A962958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Dogwood Lights Up the Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE name has absolutely nothing to do with man's best friend. But who cares? When the dogwood trees are in bloom, everything seems right with the world.</p>
        <p>Actually, the name dogwood is an adulteration of "dagwood," referring to a time when the wood was used to make daggers for skewering meat. The tree belongs to the huge Cornus genus, which contains about 60 species. They range in size from the low-to-the-ground bunchberry (Cornus canadensis) to the stately Northwestern tree, Cornus nuttalli, which can be more than 70 feet tall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE name has absolutely nothing to do with man's best friend. But who cares? When the dogwood trees are in bloom, everything seems right with the world.</p>
        <p>Actually, the name dogwood is an adulteration of "dagwood," referring to a time when the wood was used to make daggers for skewering meat. The tree belongs to the huge Cornus genus, which contains about 60 species. They range in size from the low-to-the-ground bunchberry (Cornus canadensis) to the stately Northwestern tree, Cornus nuttalli, which can be more than 70 feet tall.</p>
        <p>Where the native flowering dogwood reigns, clouds of its snow white flowers fill the woodlands and suburban street scenes.</p>
        <p>The favorite choice for most people is the white-flower dogwood (Cornus florida). Its layer upon layer branching habit offers landscape magnificence, enhanced by the fact that the showy white bracts (not petals; the true flower is the tiny center) come out long before the leaves do.</p>
        <p>This tiered look is so much the style of these splendid trees that their identity is always a sure thing. Although white is the favorite, more and more landscapers choose the pink cultivars or a combination of both types to add some zest to the Maytime scene.</p>
        <p>The native dogwoods have been going through a decline of sorts in the last few years. The fungal disease anthracnose has threatened them for some time. Researchers predicted that the population might be gone in a few years, and many dead or half-dead trees were taken out. Yet with much coddling and annual fertilizer applications, many of these specimens have come around, survived and are glorious springtime pluses once again.</p>
        <p>Some of the dogwoods' troubles have been attributed to drought in previous years as well as the troublesome dogwood borers. Some of the decline is simply old age.</p>
        <p>As a result, many homeowners opted for an alternate choice. Enter the popularity of the Kousa dogwood (Cornus kousa). This Oriental species, sometimes called the Japanese dogwood, blooms later in the season, around mid-June. The bracts, which are pointed, lie upon the leaves. This rather dramatic display is winning wide support. Although the tree has been available for more than 100 years, it is only within the last few decades that it has won a place in the landscaper's eye.</p>
        <p>The ideal spring-combo is to have both kinds of trees, if the property is large enough, for a continuous performance. One plus quality of the Kousa is its bark. After the tree matures, the bark starts to exfoliate, break off, to reveal a mottled pattern underneath something like that found on the trunks of sycamores and stewartias.</p>
        <p>When the disease problem occurred with the native species, many of the plant professionals got to work and hybridized the trees with disease-resistant species. As a result, a great number of hybrids came onto the market with the disease-resistant factor inbred. These new forms have won wide acceptance.</p>
        <p>One of the best-known experts who worked to solve this problem is Dr. Elwin Orton, of Rutgers University in New Jersey, who crossed the native flowering dogwood with the Kousa to produce some spectacular hybrids. He named these trees the Stellar series, of which there are currently six. The trees combine the best qualities of the two species; all are white-flowered except one named Stellar Pink. The series bloom season is between that of the earlier native American species and the mid-June Kousas.</p>
        <p>Although much is touted for the major dogwood species, a few plugs should be given to the less showy shrublike species, which also have their proper places. Of these a particular favorite is the red-barked red osier dogwood (Cornus sericea), which can often be seen along river banks and in damp meadows. It is easy to identify in the winter months, when there are no leaves to compete, as the red bark shows off splendidly.</p>
        <p>Another fine specimen that gives taxonomists a challenge is Cornus alternifolia. The genus as a whole has opposite leaves. This is one of the first clues that taxonomists look for. Except this particular tree fools them with its alternatve leaf branching pattern. It is a native species, too, although not as spectacular as the famous species.</p>
        <p>A bit should be added here on the cultural demands of dogwood trees. Although the trees are generally quite tough, it is important to know that they are short-lived and shallow rooted. The trees are excellent lawn specimens, but they should never be neglected. Be careful not to damage the bark when mowing around the base of the trees. (This weakens the bark and invites borers.)</p>
        <p>Also, do not neglect the trees in fall. If they are planted in the lawn, provide them with their own dose of acid-type fertilizer after the leaves drop. Grass is an active rival for soil nutrients and the dogwood should have its own supply.  GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
