<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What to Wear In a Recession</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="523036"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BERNADINE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FASHION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D6123DF932A15757C0A964958260" item-length="588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What to Wear In a Recession</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNADINE MORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BERNADINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sportswear dressing, born during the Great Depression -- is with us again. There are new pieces to put together in the separates scheme, which is a key to casual dressing.</p>
        <p>The vest is a basic component, worn over a blouse or, new this season, over a jacket. Leather is a major factor, to be mixed with other leather pieces or with silk and wool. The scarf is a significant addition, large enough to serve as a blanket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sportswear dressing, born during the Great Depression -- is with us again. There are new pieces to put together in the separates scheme, which is a key to casual dressing.</p>
        <p>The vest is a basic component, worn over a blouse or, new this season, over a jacket. Leather is a major factor, to be mixed with other leather pieces or with silk and wool. The scarf is a significant addition, large enough to serve as a blanket.</p>
        <p>Put together matching pieces and you have a suit. Separate the parts and you have separates.</p>
        <p>Does today's torpid economic climate have anything to do with the revival? Everything, says Louis Dell'Olio, who designs for Anne Klein and is one of the foremost practitioners of the art of separates dressing. Women are not in the mood to go out and buy complete new wardrobes each season, he said. But they are not at all averse to buying a piece or two. And if it is the right piece, it will spruce up a lot of other styles. It doesn't have to be a weird piece. The right long skirt will do. So will a pair of clingy pants or even a well-cut jacket.</p>
        <p>"The designer's job is to show the way, to offer ideas on how to mix things up," Mr. Dell'Olio said.</p>
        <p>This line of reasoning bears a close relationship to the one that gave rise during the 1930's to the kind of clothing known as sportswear, though it had nothing to do with the playing fields. Women who could not afford a dress could buy a sweater and a blouse, which cost less. They could alternate to make their wardrobe look larger than it was, especially useful if the woman worked. An American Specialty</p>
        <p>During the next decade sportswear blossomed. In this country, cut off from Parisian sources of inspiration during World War II, it emerged as a great creative force, a new, less-formal take on fashion. Designers like Claire McCardell, Tom Brigance and Clare Potter emphasized simple, casual cuts, fresh color combinations (like blue with green, pink with red).</p>
        <p>The core of their collections was not the meticulously tailored suit or the elaborately jeweled ball gown, but the simple shirt or blouse, the twin sweater set, a casual jacket and a skirt. These could be rearranged in multiple ways. A splatter of sequins on a jersey blouse or a floor-length skirt could adapt these clothes for evening. This mode of dressing fell into disrepute in the 1950's, when Paris couture revived itself. In the 1960's, the minidress, born in London, dominated fashion, followed by blue jeans and pants suits.</p>
        <p>Not until the late Anne Klein opened her own business, in the 1970's, did sportswear move to center stage. It came to epitomize American style once again, with practitioners like Calvin Klein, Perry Ellis, Ralph Lauren and Donna Karan bringing their own visions to casual dressing.</p>
        <p>Bill Blass, identified with more formal clothes, has always had an affinity for casual suits and sweaters. Part of his American heritage, he says.</p>
        <p>"Wardrobes must be versatile," Louis Dell'Olio said. "Some days a woman may want to wear a conventional suit. Some days she might want to look a little way out. Maybe she wants to try a long skirt, but she isn't too sure about it. Separates dressing enables her to test the waters."</p>
        <p>As the fashion free-for-all of the 1980's turns into the more restrained 1990's, separates dressing offers women a chance to dip a toe into a new style without total commitment. Sensing this, sportswear designers have widened their net to include new materials and new components. Separates are more relevant than ever.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
