<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Verdicts in West Palm Beach</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="493723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST PALM BEACH (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Palm Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD81E3EF930A25751C1A967958260" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Verdicts in West Palm Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The swiftness of William Kennedy Smith's acquittal strongly suggests that the jury had far more than the reasonable doubt required to find him not guilty in his famous rape case. During the hour and a quarter they took to elect a foreman and fill out a verdict form, the jurors placed the burden on the state, where it belongs, and quickly recognized that the prosecution had failed to meet it. Does this mean that it was unjust and a waste of judicial resources even to put Mr. Smith on trial?</p>
        <p>Not by any means.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The swiftness of William Kennedy Smith's acquittal strongly suggests that the jury had far more than the reasonable doubt required to find him not guilty in his famous rape case. During the hour and a quarter they took to elect a foreman and fill out a verdict form, the jurors placed the burden on the state, where it belongs, and quickly recognized that the prosecution had failed to meet it. Does this mean that it was unjust and a waste of judicial resources even to put Mr. Smith on trial?</p>
        <p>Not by any means.</p>
        <p>The case was hardly frivolous. Millions of Americans watching the trial on television were impressed by the accuser's testimony. Her case was strong enough to virtually compel the defendant to take the witness stand, where his own account proved even more persuasive. Not persuasive of his virtue, only the plausibility of his claim that he may have been a careless cad but was not a rapist.</p>
        <p>But was Mr. Smith punished for being a Kennedy? He is indeed heir to the misfortunes as well as the fortunes of a rich and powerful political family, including the reputation of his uncle, Senator Edward Kennedy, for evading responsibility at Chappaquiddick. Even if Florida authorities saw weaknesses in the rape case, the pressure to let the accusatory process run its course was intense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith may not think so, but he's better off after the ordeal of a long investigation and trial than he would have been with an early dismissal that could remain forever subject to question.</p>
        <p>The trial reflected a salutary change of climate in the nation's attitudes toward rape. The prosecutor, Moira Lasch, who managed to be both ineffective and unfairly provocative in her cross-examination of Mr. Smith, made some necessary points. Rape, real rape, is criminal, not romantic. Even a woman who meets a man at a bar and drives him home is not thereby consenting to sex.</p>
        <p>The defense did not argue the contrary or resort to the crude contention that a "no" really meant "yes." Instead it argued that the sex had been consensual from the beginning. The arguments over whether a rape occurred in Palm Beach, and the debate across the country, were a notably elevated discourse on relations between the sexes, however unelevated the sexual encounter might have been in this case.</p>
        <p>Another signal advance was the televising of trials, even rape trials. Viewers, whatever their personal verdicts, now know fully the evidence on which the jury based its verdict. They have their own basis for judging whether a Kennedy scion or his accuser got justice. They experienced the tedium as well as the drama, and they saw in Judge Mary Lupo a highly competent presiding officer.</p>
        <p>Both the Court TV network and Cable News Network engaged in excessive second-guessing by sideline experts, and CNN's commercial interruptions were often ill timed. But the camera coverage was skillful and informative. It also was discreet and orderly, rendering the raucous scene on the steps outside as unnecessary to trial coverage as it was irrelevant to justice. For all its anguish, the trial was full of information about justice and human relationships.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
