<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q. &amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="27QNA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1171676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD153CF934A15752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q. &amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What Is It? Rose Campion</p>
        <p>Q.  I'm enclosing a photograph of a plant I love. Can you identify it and tell me where to find it? The foliage is silvery green. The flower is a beautiful deep rose-red. I am almost certain it is a perennial. I've shown the photograph to nurseries, but they have not known its name.  A.  Plant photographs lie at least as often as they give useful clues. But in this case there's no mistaking old-fashioned rose campion, Lychnis coronaria, which has been a staple of dooryard gardens for centuries in spite of its straggly habits and neon magenta flowers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What Is It? Rose Campion</p>
        <p>Q.  I'm enclosing a photograph of a plant I love. Can you identify it and tell me where to find it? The foliage is silvery green. The flower is a beautiful deep rose-red. I am almost certain it is a perennial. I've shown the photograph to nurseries, but they have not known its name.  A.  Plant photographs lie at least as often as they give useful clues. But in this case there's no mistaking old-fashioned rose campion, Lychnis coronaria, which has been a staple of dooryard gardens for centuries in spite of its straggly habits and neon magenta flowers.</p>
        <p>Lychnis does have a few merits. It thrives in tough conditions, unbothered by poor soil and drought. And it  blooms for a long time. Though the flowers are small and widely separated, rose campion keeps putting out new ones (albeit fewer and fewer of them) for six to eight weeks after the initial burst of blossom in early July.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, it may be that the plant persists simply because each flower makes roughly a zillion seeds, all of which germinate, so before long your garden is full of the silvery little rosettes of the first-year leaves. But don't worry. As long as you keep your place well fertilized and amply watered, most of them will rot.</p>
        <p>L. coronaria is classed as both biennial and perennial. It flowers in its second year and usually, but not always, dies after flowering. To keep a clump going in the same spot, just thin out all but two or three of the babies that sprout near the parent plant.</p>
        <p>The only difficult part of growing these almost-weeds is having the discipline to cut them down when they start looking tatty, even though they're still covered with buds. (Full disclosure: I love rose campion's ghostly twin, L. coronaria alba, which floats on its Tinkertoy architecture all over my white garden.)</p>
        <p>The easiest way to get campion plants is to beg a few babies from someone who has them. Otherwise, rose campion plants are available from Bluestone Perennials, 7211 Middle Ridge Road, Madison, Ohio, 44057; (800) 852 5243. Seeds, which should be chilled for six weeks before planting for best germination, are available from Pinetree Garden Seeds, P.O. Box 300, New Gloucester, Me. 04260; (207) 926-3400. Both catalogs are free.</p>
        <p>L. coronaria alba is available in plant form from Avant Gardens, 710 High Hill Road, North Dartmouth, Mass. 02747; (508) 998-8819; catalog, $3. Seeds are sold by Thompson &amp; Morgan, P.O. Box 1308, Jackson, N.J. 08527; (800) 274-7333; free catalog.</p>
        <p>Willful Basil</p>
        <p>Q.  Last fall, I brought a big pot of basil in from the terrace. It has been sitting in a sunny window and providing us with leaves ever since, but lately it seems to be declining, and the few leaves it has produced don't have much flavor. I've tried to keep the flowers pinched out. Is there anything else I can do?  A.  Basil is an annual plant. It wants to make lots of leaves, then switch its energy into making lots of flowers, followed by lots of seeds. That accomplished, it wants to die. Keeping the flowers pinched out will stave off the end for a while, but as you've noticed, the plant is determined.</p>
        <p>Now that it is in flowering mode, it will focus on flowers -- or trying for flowers -- until exhaustion puts it out of its misery.</p>
        <p>So that's it for last year's plant, but before you rush off to get a new one, please consider just doing without until next basil season. Basil needs strong, unfiltered sunlight to produce the essential oils that make it so tasty, and even the best greenhouse-grown plants tend to be pale shadows of the summer herb.</p>
        <p>Address questions to Garden Q.&amp; A., The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York 10036, or by e-mail to gardening@nytimes .com. Those of general interest will be published. Unpublished questions cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
