<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Covering Yourself Against an Unhappy Landing</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="565375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE1430F937A15753C1A964958260" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Covering Yourself Against an Unhappy Landing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's one of those things that nobody likes to think about. Whenever you fly on a commercial airline, there is a possibility, a very slim possibility, that the plane will crash and passengers will die or be seriously injured.</p>
        <p>Many travelers buy flight insurance to protect themselves against such a possibility. This type of protection is a category of special-risk life insurance and pays benefits for accidental death and dismemberment. Often it is packaged with other insurance for travelers, like trip cancellation and medical insurance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's one of those things that nobody likes to think about. Whenever you fly on a commercial airline, there is a possibility, a very slim possibility, that the plane will crash and passengers will die or be seriously injured.</p>
        <p>Many travelers buy flight insurance to protect themselves against such a possibility. This type of protection is a category of special-risk life insurance and pays benefits for accidental death and dismemberment. Often it is packaged with other insurance for travelers, like trip cancellation and medical insurance.</p>
        <p>Within the insurance industry, however, there is a long-running controversy over the efficacy of flight life insurance. Proponents say it meets a specific need at a relatively low cost; opponents say adequate life insurance should be purchased to cover all contingencies, so add-ons would not be necessary when flying.</p>
        <p>"The chances that you're going to go down in a plane are remote," said Holly Richmond, a vice president of Tele-Trip, a subsidiary of the Mutual of Omaha Insurance Company, the largest seller of flight insurance at airports. "But some people will not get on a plane without buying insurance. For a small amount of money, it would be worth it." Airports or Travel Agents</p>
        <p>Robert Hill, an executive vice president of the Prudential Insurance Company of America, sees the matter differently. "We believe life insurance should be used to cover long-term, permanent kinds of needs," he said. "If you have a need for death protection, I don't think it exists only when you are flying on a plane."</p>
        <p>Individuals generally acquire flight insurance either at an airport -- often as an impulse item -- or through a travel agent. At airports, it is sold over the counter by company employees or at self-service drop slots; purchased from a travel agent, it usually requires completing a form that is mailed directly to the insurer.</p>
        <p>"There is no health check for this insurance," said Stephen Young, a spokesman for the American Council of Life Insurance, a trade association. "All you have to do is plunk down the money and you can get it."</p>
        <p>Some bank-card issuers and the American Express Company offer free common-carrier travel-accident insurance -- which includes travel by bus, train or ship, as well as by plane -- to any cardholder if the fare for the trip has been charged to that card. For example, the Marine Midland Bank in New York, the First National Bank of Chicago and Seafirst Bank in Seattle make this provision available to their Mastercard holders. Cardholder Benefits</p>
        <p>"Banks typically provide $100,000 to $250,000 worth of insurance under this program," said Kristen L. Ott, Mastercard's director of enhancement services. "And the consumer does not pay for this."</p>
        <p>American Express not only gives its cardholders $100,000 in common-carrier travel-accident insurance at no charge, but also lets them enroll in a separate automatic flight-insurance plan for travel on scheduled airlines, with a premium fee per trip. That charge, billed on monthly statements, ranges from $4 a round trip for $250,000 worth of coverage ($4.50 in New York because medical and home-care benefits are included) to $14 a trip for $1 million worth of coverage.</p>
        <p>In addition, a cardholder can purchase a frequent-air-travelers option in all states but New York, with annual premiums ranging from $3.50 for $250,000 in coverage to $9.75 for $1 million in coverage. "This covers you on no-fare tickets like those from frequent-flier programs and those issued as a result of being bumped from a flight," said Denise Aranoff, an American Express manager.</p>
        <p>For those consumers who pay separately for flight life insurance, the price is usually modest. Ms. Richmond of Tele-Trip gave the example of a traveler who buys $50,000 worth of coverage, with four possible alternatives: A one-time flight policy would cost $1.65; an annual flight policy would cost $20; a 24-hour accident insurance policy -- covering all accidents while traveling -- would cost $18.75 for a week, and an annual 24-hour accident-insurance policy would cost $60. Automated Sales Machines</p>
        <p>The sale of flight insurance at airports may be going high-tech soon, Ms. Richmond added. Tele-Trip plans to test a prototype of an interactive machine, similar to automated tellers at banks, through which travelers could buy insurance with their credit cards and receive a policy confirmation as proof of purchase.</p>
        <p>As for those who choose an accidental-death benefit rider to a traditional life-insurance policy, the premium is likely to be higher but the coverage is broader, encompassing accidents resulting from any causes. For instance, Neil Brown, president of Sumco Systems, a brokerage company in Larchmont, N.Y., cited $100,000 policies available to a 50-year-old, nonsmoking male. A rider covering accidental death on a whole-life policy would cost $92, or 92 cents per $1,000 of coverage, while a similar rider on a term policy would cost $71, or 71 cents per $1,000 of coverage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown noted that a better approach might be to purchase additional life insurance, instead of an accidental-death rider. "Unless you fly a lot, the bottom line here is to buy a higher face amount of regular insurance with the money you would have spent on an accidental-death rider," he said. "Then if you die for any reason, the policy would pay off."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
