<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Officials Say Fatal Crash Might Have Been Avoided</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="565183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MANSLAUGHTER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">VERNON (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAMPBELL, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAO, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RYAN, MATTHEW J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Manslaughter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC103DF930A15753C1A964958260" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Officials Say Fatal Crash Might Have Been Avoided</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAO, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>SECAUCUS, N.J., Oct. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State transportation officials acknowledged today that a July bus accident that killed six people might have been avoided if the bus had been inspected within the previous year, as required under state law.</p>
        <p>But the state's bus industry is largely self-regulating, the officials said. Without major new expenditures of taxpayers' money, they said, regulators can do little more to bring operators into compliance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State transportation officials acknowledged today that a July bus accident that killed six people might have been avoided if the bus had been inspected within the previous year, as required under state law.</p>
        <p>But the state's bus industry is largely self-regulating, the officials said. Without major new expenditures of taxpayers' money, they said, regulators can do little more to bring operators into compliance.</p>
        <p>"He was an unscrupulous operator," Matthew J. Ryan, director of the state commercial vehicle safety bureau, said of Robert Campbell, who owned the Brooklyn-based bus and who has been charged with aggravated manslaughter in the accident. "It's like a drug dealer, a murderer, a thief. It's hard to catch them."</p>
        <p>Six people died and 48 were injured when the 20-year-old bus careered out of control on a steep hill in Vernon, N.J. The bus, which had been carrying families from Brooklyn to an amusement park, collided with two cars and burst into flames. 'This Accident Was a Fluke'</p>
        <p>In more than two hours of often sharp questioning by investigators from the National Transportation Safety Board, Mr. Ryan was repeatedly asked whether the accident had exposed inadequacies in New York State's bus-monitoring system.</p>
        <p>"This accident was a fluke," Mr. Ryan said. "Look at the millions of people in New York City who are transported by bus daily. From a practical standpoint, this system is working excellently."</p>
        <p>But safety board officials said the crash had raised questions about the effectiveness of programs intended to catch unsafe bus companies.</p>
        <p>Only two of the five state and Federal agencies that regulate charter buses knew of the company involved in the July crash, Sensational Golden Sons, said Susan M. Coughlin, vice chairwoman of the safety board.</p>
        <p>"I'm concerned this was not a fluke," Ms. Coughlin said. She said the safety board will issue a report on the accident in the spring. Failed to Get Inspections</p>
        <p>In testimony yesterday, state officials provided information about how Sensational Golden Sons had repeatedly escaped regulation, even though some parts of the government were aware it was doing business.</p>
        <p>When a new bus company comes into existence, it is required to have its buses inspected after they have been registered with the state. Once the bus has been inspected for the first time, it is entered into a log, and state inspectors follow up to make sure it is inspected every six months.</p>
        <p>But in the case of Sensational Golden Sons, Mr. Campbell never had his 1972 coach bus inspected after he started the company in 1989, Mr. Ryan said. As a result, the bus was never logged into the inspection records and there was never any follow-up by state officials.</p>
        <p>By the time of the crash, the bus's brakes were corroded, out of adjustment and missing parts, investigators said. A Fine but No Payment</p>
        <p>On two occasions in 1989, state regulators were alerted to problems with the company, but both times they failed to bring it into compliance with state regulations.</p>
        <p>In June and again in September 1989, a state inspector who noticed Mr. Campbell releasing passengers on Manhattan streets gave him summonses for operating a bus that had not been inspected.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Campbell failed to pay a $250 fine, the Department of Transportation mailed him a letter in January 1991 demanding payment. He has yet to pay the fine. But there was no attempt to suspend Mr. Campbell's registration. And there was no follow-up to insure that Mr. Campbell had his buses inspected.</p>
        <p>"People don't like to hear it, but there are limits to what we can do," said Mr. Ryan, adding that his agency makes 110,000 bus inspections a year. Changes in Laws Considered</p>
        <p>Mr. Ryan said the Department of Transportation is now considering changing state laws to require new bus operators to have their buses inspected before they are licensed.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, bus companies are required to have inspections before they register their buses, New Jersey officials testified yesterday. In addition, state troopers make roadside checks for valid inspection stickers.</p>
        <p>Last year 8,010 buses were given roadside examinations, and 1,155 were put out of service on the spot because they violated state regulations, said George Georgeles, a New Jersey state trooper.</p>
        <p>New York State officials said roadside inspections were less common in New York City because it can be difficult or dangerous to force buses out of service in the city.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
