<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Array of Americana On a Hudson River Pier</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="565215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTIQUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FALL ANTIQUES SHOW (NYC)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIF, RITA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D6143FF930A15753C1A964958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Array of Americana On a Hudson River Pier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REIF, RITA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Americana at this year's Fall Antiques Show moves from the sublime to the outrageous in a fair laced with whimsy as well as such staples as quilts, weathervanes and painted furniture.</p>
        <p>The excitement at this year's show, which continues through Sunday at the Hudson River pier at 52d Street, comes from some new discoveries that could enlarge the boundaries of folk art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Americana at this year's Fall Antiques Show moves from the sublime to the outrageous in a fair laced with whimsy as well as such staples as quilts, weathervanes and painted furniture.</p>
        <p>The excitement at this year's show, which continues through Sunday at the Hudson River pier at 52d Street, comes from some new discoveries that could enlarge the boundaries of folk art.</p>
        <p>One find is a witty 1940's biplane steered by moon men, a wire wonder whose twirling propellers and flapping wings operate on battery power. Ronald and Penny Dionne are offering it at their booth for $950.</p>
        <p>Another is a piece of advertising art: a 5-foot-high thread-sheathed wooden structure, the tower of which is stacked with dozens of spools of J. &amp; P. Coats Clark threads in a rainbow of hues. The 1930's architectural model is $8,800 from Alan Katz at his booth, Advertising Americana.  Porcine Road Sign</p>
        <p>Pam Hill's booth is dominated by a grinning eight-foot-tall pig. "Porky here was a road sign for a drive-in restaurant in Ohio," Ms. Hill said. "That's why it's covered with glass illuminators." The price is $11,000.</p>
        <p>"There's less traditional folk art here than a decade ago," said Gerard C. Wertkin, the director of the Museum of American Folk Art, which sponsors the show. "But the diversity of Americana is astounding. It keeps expanding in the direction of pop culture, roadside artifacts, amusement-park equipment, transportation images, advertising materials, American Indian items and even Latin American expressions."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Americana at this show does encompass objects from Latin America. "I couldn't resist these giant heads from Guatemala," said Amy Finkel of M. Finkel &amp; Daughter, a Philadelphia dealer. The seven boldly carved images of men and women (from $450 to $800) were made several decades ago and were meant to be worn in street processions.</p>
        <p>The traditional folk art on display is often notable for its size, shape or subject matter. One 19th-century weathervane-like sculpture at Peter Tillou is five feet tall; the zinc colt, painted gold, reigned for more than a century on the roof of the Colt Firearms factory in Hartford. At $1.2 million, it carries the show's highest price tag.  Sailing-Ship Vane</p>
        <p>Stephen Score brought a 70-inch-long copper vane of a sailing ship, green with weathering, to the show. "I've been after this two-masted schooner for 15 years," he said. "We needed an 85-foot crane to remove it from its roost on the cupola of a carriage house." The 19th-century piece is $145,000.</p>
        <p>American Indian art first became a major factor at this show in the mid-1980's. This year, William Channing, a Santa Fe, N.M., dealer, is showing a two-foot-tall Apache willow basket on which horses and men are depicted, for $28,000. And Joel Kopp, the owner of America Hurrah, has a 1933 Navajo rug emblazoned with a biplane; he said it was woven for Mabel Walker Willebrandt, an aviator who served as an assistant Attorney General under Presidents Harding, Coolidge and Hoover. "She received the rug in lieu of payment when she won a land-grant case for a Navajo woman against the Federal Government," Mr. Kopp said. It is $9,500.</p>
        <p>There are objects as well for those with pockets less deep. At Perrisue Silver, Victorian bonbon spoons are $45 each. Betty Mintz has Navajo bracelets and earrings, each under $125. Laura Fisher, in step with the season, offers crepe-paper political-rally hats at $5 each.</p>
        <p>"In the 1980's, everyone seemed to need to buy something before someone else did," said Sanford L. Smith, the show's manager. "These days, everyone seems cautious. But at this show there's been a lot of buying among the dealers, which is a good sign, and some serious purchases by collectors. The energy we lacked for the last two years is back."</p>
        <p>The 14th Fall Antiques Show, with 115 dealers from 22 states, is open from 11 A.M. to 9 P.M. today and tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. on Sunday. A shuttle bus runs continuously between the Museum of American Folk Art Gallery, 2 Lincoln Square (Columbus Avenue between 65th and 66th Streets) and Pier 92 on the Hudson River at West 52d Street.</p>
        <p>Tickets are $10 (free for those under 16 accompanied by an adult). Proceeds from sales of the $5 catalogue benefit Hale House in Harlem, a home for babies born with drug addictions or H.I.V. Information: (212) 777-5218.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
