<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SENATE WILL SEEK U.S. COURT ACTION ON CLINTON NOTES</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="817561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITEWATER CASE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARKANSAS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MADISON GUARANTY SAVINGS &amp; LOAN</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHITEWATER DEVELOPMENT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MADISON GUARANTY SAVINGS &amp; LOAN ASSN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LABATON, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOSTER, VINCENT W JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON,HILLARY RODHAM HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arkansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whitewater Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3D71439F932A15751C1A963958260" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SENATE WILL SEEK U.S. COURT ACTION ON CLINTON NOTES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LABATON, STEPHEN;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a day of spirited and deeply partisan debate, the Senate tonight approved a resolution to ask a Federal judge to order President Clinton to comply with subpoenas and turn over material related to the Whitewater matter that the White House says is protected by the lawyer-client and executive privileges.</p>
        <p>The resolution was approved by a vote of 51 to 45, breaking entirely on party lines. Three Senators did not vote: Daniel K. Inouye, Democrat of Hawaii, and Phil Gramm of Texas and William V. Roth Jr. of Delaware, both Republicans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a day of spirited and deeply partisan debate, the Senate tonight approved a resolution to ask a Federal judge to order President Clinton to comply with subpoenas and turn over material related to the Whitewater matter that the White House says is protected by the lawyer-client and executive privileges.</p>
        <p>The resolution was approved by a vote of 51 to 45, breaking entirely on party lines. Three Senators did not vote: Daniel K. Inouye, Democrat of Hawaii, and Phil Gramm of Texas and William V. Roth Jr. of Delaware, both Republicans.</p>
        <p>The material, notes of a 1993 meeting of President Clinton's senior aides and his lawyers to discuss Whitewater, has been the subject of a bitter fight between the White House and Republicans on the Senate Whitewater committee for the last few weeks.</p>
        <p>Republicans have speculated that the notes could show that White House aides  improperly provided confidential information about two politically sensitive investigations to private lawyers for Mr. Clinton and his wife, Hillary Rodham Clinton. The White House has said the notes will shed no new light on the conduct of the Clintons or their aides.</p>
        <p>In the sharpest Republican attack yet, Senator Lauch Faircloth of North Carolina said on the Senate floor that Mrs. Clinton had lied to Federal investigators, in violation of the law, about how she and her firm, the Rose Law Firm, had come to represent a savings and loan association, Madison Guaranty, which had been operated by James B. McDougal, the Clintons' business partner in  the Whitewater land venture.</p>
        <p>"Mrs. Clinton made false statements to the Resolution Trust Corporation, a Federal crime, about who brought Madison to the Rose firm," Mr. Faircloth said.  "It is becoming increasingly clear that Mrs. Clinton lied to Federal investigators."</p>
        <p>Democrats responded angrily that Mr. Faircloth and other Republicans had distorted the conclusions of investigators and that months of Federal and Congressional investigations had uncovered no crimes on the part of the Clintons.</p>
        <p>This morning, the White House dropped most of its remaining conditions for releasing the material and said it would make the documents public if the House  Banking and Financial Services Committee, which is also investigating Whitewater, agreed that such a disclosure would not waive the President's lawyer-client privilege.</p>
        <p>The White House's new posture came shortly after it announced that the Whitewater independent counsel, Kenneth W. Starr, had agreed to this condition.  The Senate Whitewater committee had said the disclosure of the material would not constitute a waiver; Republicans on the panel say that because the meeting is not protected by the lawyer-client privilege anyway, disclosing the notes would not waive any privilege.</p>
        <p>So, as the debate raged in the Senate, White House lawyers met with the chairman of the House Banking committee, Representative Jim Leach of Iowa. But Mr. Leach early in the day expressed his reluctance to reach an agreement with the White House because, he said, it could impinge on his committee's ability to investigate whether Clinton officials improperly disclosed confidential information to the First Family's personal lawyers.</p>
        <p>"Given the White House denial under oath to a House committee that a transfer of information to parties outside the White House occurred, White House efforts  to place limitations upon the House's ability to gather information necessary to fulfill its legitimate oversight functions takes particular chutzpah," Mr. Leach wrote in a letter to Speaker Newt Gingrich today.</p>
        <p>By the end of his meeting with White House lawyers, Mr. Leach declined to change his mind. But he also held out the hope that the matter could be resolved before Senate lawyers file court papers next month. He agreed to hold further talks this week with White House officials over the waiver issue.</p>
        <p>In the Senate debate, Republican after Republican rose to denounce the White  House, compare Whitewater to Watergate, and accuse the President of stonewalling by failing to comply with the Whitewater committee's subpoenas. In a carefully choreographed presentation, the Republicans used the subpoena debate to outline  questions they had raised about the Clintons and a savings association that bank examiners have concluded was rife with corruption.</p>
        <p>"What we're attempting to do is find the truth of what happened and why Madison Guaranty collapsed to taxpayers at a cost of $65 million," said Senator  Alfonse M. D'Amato, the New York Republican who heads the Senate Whitewater committee.</p>
        <p>The Democrats accused the Republicans of trying to provoke a confrontation with the White House in an effort to perpetuate a political fishing expedition.</p>
        <p>"We have seen more 'smoking guns' in this investigation than I've ever seen in a cowboy movie," said Senator Barbara Boxer, Democrat of California. Senator  Christopher J. Dodd, Democrat of Connecticut, said, "This is becoming a political sideshow." . But the most commonly asserted defense of the Clintons today by the Democrats was a new report provided to Congress in recent days by Federal regulators. Democrats made the contents of the report public today by entering it into the record of the Senate debate. The report was prepared by a private law firm hired by the Resolution Trust Corporation to examine how Madison's collapse was related to the Whitewater venture.</p>
        <p>The report focused on a more narrow question than that under investigation by the independent counsel: whether the Clintons knew that the Whitewater Development Corporation may have been receiving fraudulent benefits from Madison. The report concluded that investigators could not prove that the Clintons were involved in fraud, intentional misconduct or conspiring with others in intentional misconduct. A preliminary report had found that Mr. McDougal and his wife, Susan, had lost about three times as much as the Clintons in the Whitewater venture.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
