<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; Not a Rose Garden</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="587213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDC1E3AF932A35751C0A965958260" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; Not a Rose Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After the election, Republicans charged that the press was biased against George Bush. A conservative think tank produced a solemn report to the same effect.</p>
        <p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, look at the press now and think again. Reporters and commentators are savaging Bill Clinton. They are doing what comes naturally to a free press: criticizing those in authority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After the election, Republicans charged that the press was biased against George Bush. A conservative think tank produced a solemn report to the same effect.</p>
        <p>Well, ladies and gentlemen, look at the press now and think again. Reporters and commentators are savaging Bill Clinton. They are doing what comes naturally to a free press: criticizing those in authority.</p>
        <p>The battering the new President is taking arises from two episodes of his first 10 days in office: the forced withdrawal of his nominee for Attorney General, and his forced compromise on homosexuals in the armed forces. Those episodes carry important lessons on the problem of governing in contemporary America.</p>
        <p>We have moved rapidly in this country toward a form of mass-participatory democracy. The American public learns instantly what happens in Washington, and members of that public massively and almost as instantly tell their leaders what they think.</p>
        <p>The public awareness and response are a product of technology but also of something else: the discontent with government that was so evident in the 1992 election campaign. The sour feelings that brought Ross Perot 19 percent of the vote are still there, and focused on the new President.</p>
        <p>The idea of participatory democracy is quite different from the political system that the founders of this country meant to create. James Madison and the other Framers of the Constitution feared the whim -- the tyranny -- of passing majorities. They tried to construct a system insulated from the winds of public passion.</p>
        <p>But here we are, in a new age and a new reality with which every President will have to deal, starting with Bill Clinton. Doing so means not just yielding to instant public emotions but working to keep alive the Framers' constitutional design for a more reflective, more considered form of government.</p>
        <p>The danger of mass participatory democracy is that it can be manipulated: shaped by ideologues and demagogues. That was the concern when Ross Perot proposed his "electronic town hall," which he said would make "the White House and Congress, like a ballet," pirouette around the stage. And the danger has been evident in these first days of the Clinton Administration.</p>
        <p>The negative public reaction to Zoe Baird's past use of illegal aliens for child care -- the telephone calls to senators -- seemed genuine. Sensitized by the scandals of recent years, the public did not want an Attorney General who had violated a law.</p>
        <p>But the protests against President Clinton's plan to end the ban on gay men and women in the services were different. To a considerable degree they were orchestrated by the religious right and conservative extremists.</p>
        <p>Randall Terry of Operation Rescue, the group that tries to terrorize women out of having abortions, turned to the homosexual issue. He said, "We're avalanching  [ Congress ]  with phone calls and letters," because "sodomy is against God's law." The extreme-right talk show hosts on Thug Radio also denounced the Clinton plan.</p>
        <p>So it is important to have some perspective on manifestations of public emotion. Randall Terry, Pat Robertson and others in the religious right opposed Bill Clinton in the election, as did the talk show hosts. They lost.</p>
        <p>In such turbulent and dangerous conditions, it is harder than ever to be an effective President. And quite plainly Bill Clinton was insufficiently prepared for the storm. He misjudged the public temper, and he failed to pay due deference to Congressional egos.</p>
        <p>One necessary corrective is obvious. President Clinton needs some aides with political sensitivity. He had picked one of the best, Harold Ickes, to be deputy chief of staff but held off when Mr. Ickes was attacked for having had as a legal client an unsavory labor union. Judging lawyers by their clients is a particularly poor form of guilt by association. If the President needs Mr. Ickes -- and he does -- he should give him the job.</p>
        <p>But in the end what will be required in this new political world will be more of the old bully pulpit of Presidential leadership. If Bill Clinton wants to cut the deficit, if he wants to reform health care, he can overcome the opposition of vested interest only by persuading us.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
