<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Sonic Saturation, a Quiet Return to Hi-Fi Values</title>
    <meta content="08LARR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE NEW SEASON/Audio Technology" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="875846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEW SEASON/Audio Technology"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Loudspeakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Lawrence B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5D71138F93BA3575AC0A960958260" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Sonic Saturation, a Quiet Return to Hi-Fi Values</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE B. JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Lawrence B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence B Johnson comment on home audio systems sees resurgence of hi-fi values and what might be called new seriousness in presentation of multi-channel sound for the home; discusses developments in home-theater speaker systems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF YOU AREN'T IN THE HOME theater business, say many proprietors of what were once hi-fi salons, you aren't going to be in business long. Such is the degree to which the audio market has come to be driven by the mania for multichannel sound and, especially, movie soundtracks.</p>
        <p>That truth was already evident a year ago, and it had an alarming ring to it. One could see the standards of hi-fi sound falling to the lowly aspirations of bass-heavy tracks for action films. Today, the outlook appears brighter. Piecing together an industry prospectus for consumer audio in the months ahead, one cannot fail to note a resurgence of hi-fi values amid what might be called a new seriousness in the presentation of multichannel sound for the home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF YOU AREN'T IN THE HOME theater business, say many proprietors of what were once hi-fi salons, you aren't going to be in business long. Such is the degree to which the audio market has come to be driven by the mania for multichannel sound and, especially, movie soundtracks.</p>
        <p>That truth was already evident a year ago, and it had an alarming ring to it. One could see the standards of hi-fi sound falling to the lowly aspirations of bass-heavy tracks for action films. Today, the outlook appears brighter. Piecing together an industry prospectus for consumer audio in the months ahead, one cannot fail to note a resurgence of hi-fi values amid what might be called a new seriousness in the presentation of multichannel sound for the home.</p>
        <p>It's surely safe to say that home theater is maturing, and that the first beneficiary is the quality of sound. Much of the industry shows signs of outgrowing the early fascination with whiz-bang sonic effects, and of rediscovering the more powerful appeal of sound reproduction that is well tempered and naturally proportioned: the sound of music.</p>
        <p>In fact, such a musical or hi-fi ''recovery'' is no small achievement in the wholly artificial world of movie soundtracks. The recording and reproduction of acoustical music on one hand and movie sound on the other have little in common; it was only when the audio industry, especially loudspeaker designers, shunned the easy sell of quick impact and restored a factor of subtlety that the multichannel mindset could begin to accommodate music in a proper fashion.</p>
        <p>Compactness, versatility and ease of use have become crucial to consumers facing the complexity and physical intrusion of home theater sound systems. Not the least of these is versatility.</p>
        <p>For obvious reasons, most people live with a single speaker system, which must serve music as well as movie soundtracks. And while home theater has become the industry preoccupation, and the typical context for demonstrating and selling speakers, most people probably spend more hours listening to music -- playing music, anyway -- than listening to movie sound.</p>
        <p>''You're going to see an increasing demand for a new level of tonal accuracy,'' said Ross Keim, vice president for United States sales of the high-end British company Meridian. ''A lot of people are no longer wowed by sonic impact alone. We've gone through our gestation period with home theater. Certainly among high-end consumers, there's a new realization that the home theater sound system is still the family stereo. And it doesn't matter whether you're listening to movie dialogue or an aria; fidelity is what it's about.''</p>
        <p>Paul Barton, president and chief engineer of PSB Speakers, makes the compelling point that the rising standard of home theater speakers now exposes many people to better sound than they have ever experienced in simply ''watching TV.'' Mr. Barton, a violinist himself, has turned his thoroughly musical line of speakers to excellent home theater purpose, and two smaller versions of his widely admired Alpha loudspeaker are just now coming to market.</p>
        <p>The new, or resurrected, watchword for loudspeaker design in the coming season might be ''sophistication.'' Jeffrey L. Percy, director of media relations for Audio Products International of Canada, the maker of Mirage and Energy speakers, noted that both companies will add beefed-up center-channel models. And both will introduce several subwoofers with glossy finishes attuned to room decor.</p>
        <p>''There's a great deal of pressure to bring prices down and to deliver higher value,'' Mr. Percy said. In response, Energy will market its first mini home theater system, an array of five speakers called Take Five. ''It's very clear to us that consumers are looking for better-quality -- let's say, more serious -- speakers for home theater,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>HAVING SURVIVED SEVeral generations, home theater has proved its adaptability, its environmental fit. Six-channel amplifiers, which perhaps made sense as stereo-times-three but didn't match up with five channels of sound, are giving way to five-channel and three-channel amps. Even the mono amplifier has gained a new respect; it's tailor-made for the odd-channel purposes of home theater, and several high-end specialty companies will add to an already remarkable assortment of mono amps in multichannel settings.</p>
        <p>One sure sign of home theater's sonic evolution lies in the digital surround-sound hookups to be introduced in new receivers.</p>
        <p>Digital surround sound takes conventional Dolby Surround to a new level of precision. In Dolby Surround, the center-channel information (most important, dialogue) and monophonic rear-channel ambient sound are derived from a two-channel stereo signal. In the new digital surround sound, all five channels are recorded and reproduced independently.</p>
        <p>Onkyo will be among the first to offer receivers with built-in Dolby Digital decoders. Two models in Onkyo's upper-end Integra line, the TX-DS939 and the TX-DS838, should reach store shelves in mid-autumn. Around the same time, Yamaha expects to roll out its new flagship receiver, the RX-V990, a five-channel model fitted with standard RCA connections to accept the signal from a Dolby Digital decoder.</p>
        <p>For several months to come, the influx of digital surround-sound receivers probably won't amount to more than a trickle, and they will continue to be pricey. But in the usual cyclical mode of audio evolution, prices will drop, and the trickle will swell to a flood as digital surround sound becomes as common as two-channel stereo once was.</p>
        <p>And that time of commonality may arrive with startling swiftness. It is fascinating to see digital surround sound looming so large so quickly in the mainstream, on one hand, and in the once devoutly two-channel precincts of the high end, on the other.</p>
        <p>In December, Meridian, known for its digital engineering, will bring to market a radical series of components centered on the Model 861 surround-sound processor-preamp. Unlike conventional processors, which use chips to decode surround information, the 861 is actually a computer, with software-based programs. It will be able to support any form of surround coding in as many as 64 channels.</p>
        <p>Closer at hand is Harman Kardon's new ADP-303 Dolby Digital processor, usable as a stand-alone unit or in conjunction with a receiver. Rotel takes a different approach to the Dolby Digital linkup in its forthcoming RTC970 combination tuner, preamp and processor. It will require a 25-pin computer-type cable for connection to an external digital decoder.</p>
        <p>The coming months should also bring a head-to-head battle between high-profile Dolby Digital surround sound and the fledgling -- though seemingly elegant -- consumer version from DTS Technology. DTS is reportedly set to announce the names of 26 electronics companies that will begin putting its decoder in their components.</p>
        <p>So formidable a list might appear to set the stage for a divisive format war in the classic mold of VHS versus Betamax. But in the digital era, a Dolby-DTS contest need not be a battle to the death, or even to the detriment of digital technology or consumers' best interests. Happily, there is room for both. Motorola, in fact, is said to be developing a chip that will decode Dolby and DTS.</p>
        <p>Home theater stands fully emerged, its future assured. And beyond doubt, multichannel sound is the future of audio. For the first time since this phenomenon raised its curious head, the outlook for home entertainment sounds as promising as its looks.</p>
        <p>THE NEW SEASON/Audio Technology</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
