<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fishing for Rainbows in Semiprivate Paradise in Montana</title>
    <meta content="08OUTD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="OUTDOORS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trout</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaminsky, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFDA143BF93BA3575AC0A960958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fishing for Rainbows in Semiprivate Paradise in Montana</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Kaminsky</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaminsky, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Kaminsky Outdoors article on fishing for rainbow trout in Montana; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The morning air smelled of warm, sweet cinnamon. Maybe it was the aroma of freshly mown hay mingling with the acres of wild mint along the bottom land of the Hanson Ranch on Sheep Creek in south central Montana. The night before, we had fished our way up a mile of lightly pressured stream and kept a few wild fish that I fried up and flaked over hash brown potatoes with peppers and frizzled onions.</p>
        <p>Our fishing had been on semiprivate water: There is little truly private water in Montana, whose enlightened access laws allow the angler to wade up any stream bed he or she desires, if he or she feels up to miles of difficult and exhausting wading to get to the prime fishing. The Hansons, like a number of Montana's old ranch families, have begun to allow paying hunters and fishers onto their land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The morning air smelled of warm, sweet cinnamon. Maybe it was the aroma of freshly mown hay mingling with the acres of wild mint along the bottom land of the Hanson Ranch on Sheep Creek in south central Montana. The night before, we had fished our way up a mile of lightly pressured stream and kept a few wild fish that I fried up and flaked over hash brown potatoes with peppers and frizzled onions.</p>
        <p>Our fishing had been on semiprivate water: There is little truly private water in Montana, whose enlightened access laws allow the angler to wade up any stream bed he or she desires, if he or she feels up to miles of difficult and exhausting wading to get to the prime fishing. The Hansons, like a number of Montana's old ranch families, have begun to allow paying hunters and fishers onto their land.</p>
        <p>My guide for a recent visit with some of these families was Doug McClelland, who teaches business law at Montana State University and is a former president of Trout Unlimited. He is also director of the fishing program at Off the Beaten Path, a company in Bozeman that specializes in arranging trips for visitors to the Rocky Mountains. Joining us was Laurance Aiuppy of Livingston, Mont., a photographer of life and wildlife in the Rockies.</p>
        <p>One would think that a handful of anglers might not figure mightily in the business calculations of ranchers with spreads of 20,000 acres, but in fact, those ranchers who have opened their doors to recreational users for a fee find that their overall income has increased by an average of 5 percent. This is a significant amount in a low-margin business governed by the twin furies of nature and the market price of beef.</p>
        <p>Edwin Nelson, whose family owns the fabled Nelson's Spring Creek, is proof that fee fishing can work for both angler and rancher. His is stunning water, full of huge fish that glow like red and gold ghosts against the rich green grass beds.</p>
        <p>''Cattle ranching is great, but you can't make a living at it,'' he said. ''If you're a rancher you need to have fishing, bird hunting or big-game hunting.''</p>
        <p>Across the river from Nelson, floods from the same Yellowstone that nourishes his springs have destroyed the four miles of water that made up Armstrong and Depuy's spring creeks, two trout-fishing jewels that provided precious spawning habitat for the rainbows and cutthroats on the mid Yellowstone. Young Todd O'Hair feels that his family's ranch will not survive if he is not allowed to restore the stream bed by erecting a levee across the encroaching side channel of the Yellowstone.</p>
        <p>''To raise a cow costs about $360,'' he said. ''This year, we will be lucky to get $350 for an animal. This ranch needs the spring creek, and the fishermen, to stay afloat. It's basic economics.'' O'Hair's restoration application is currently up before the Army Corps of Engineers.</p>
        <p>But there are also a number of fly fishermen who oppose any channeling of any part of the Yellowstone, even though they agree that a great fishing resource is at stake.</p>
        <p>From Paradise Valley, we drove north to the Hanson Ranch. The Hansons have taken in paying guests for about five years and they, too, report a stabilizing effect on the family economy. The guest book recorded reported 26-inch trout and grizzly bears. I saw neither. Still, we had Sheep Creek to ourselves and the pleasure of an old cabin all alone.</p>
        <p>Following the morning of the cinnamon-scented air, we headed north, 50 miles along the gravel-surfaced Milligan Road. We came upon a missile silo guarded by a number of fierce-looking armored vehicles and fully armed soldiers.</p>
        <p>Having just seen ''Independence Day,'' I was sure they were battling some alien or at least vacuuming a warhead. I addressed the sergeant in command.</p>
        <p>''I can't say,'' he advised. ''But there is one thing I can say.''</p>
        <p>''What's that?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''You have a flat tire.''</p>
        <p>The sergeant, Gene Kelly of Stony Point, N.Y., offered assistance, but Larry and Doug had things under control, so Kelly and I talked about trout fishing in the Missouri and crabbing in the Hudson while they worked away.</p>
        <p>We moved on to a stream that I'll call Kitty Creek (the rancher preferred to stay out of the newspaper). Having been warned to keep an eye out for the rattlesnakes who have come down from the parched hills, we fished the smaller upper reaches of Kitty.</p>
        <p>An Ausable Wulff produced three or four little trout. At that point, McClelland returned from an upper pool and advised me to put on a hopper. I did and instantly caught a half dozen rainbows. The biggest was 16 inches and the smallest not much smaller. For the next hour, I experienced glorious Montana fishing that included two fat brown trout of 15 and 17 inches.</p>
        <p>We made our way to the challenging (and public) tailwaters of the Missouri, which were alive with impressive rises to teeny flies. Aiuppy, McClelland and I -- with a hundred years of collective flyrod experience -- cast a thousand times and we each succeeded in hooking, but not landing, one fish. It was a humbling counterpoint to the ingenues of the ranch streams.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
