<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Literary Lion</title>
    <meta content="08DOWD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Liberties" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="876166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Liberties"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DB153BF93BA3575AC0A960958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Literary Lion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column says literary lionizing of Dick Morris, disgraced consultant to Pres Clinton, proves that there is no floor to shamelessness (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One August night, I was having cocktails with a couple of Times reporters at the Jefferson Hotel. We were sulking about the tedium of the campaign. Little did we know, the biggest political story of the summer was unfolding right above our buttery Chardonnay.</p>
        <p>There, in the seraglio marked 205, was an imbroglio. Dick Morris was pouring cognac for his mistresses and murmuring sweet nothings like, ''Let me tell you about the Government shutdown,'' ''I got my head torn off by Hillary when I tried to soften her image,'' and ''Only you could keep me from the polls.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One August night, I was having cocktails with a couple of Times reporters at the Jefferson Hotel. We were sulking about the tedium of the campaign. Little did we know, the biggest political story of the summer was unfolding right above our buttery Chardonnay.</p>
        <p>There, in the seraglio marked 205, was an imbroglio. Dick Morris was pouring cognac for his mistresses and murmuring sweet nothings like, ''Let me tell you about the Government shutdown,'' ''I got my head torn off by Hillary when I tried to soften her image,'' and ''Only you could keep me from the polls.''</p>
        <p>The headlines keep coming: ''Adviser Had Secret Deal for Book'' -- The New York Times. ''The Other Other Woman; Secret Love Child'' -- The New York Post. ''Dick Morris May Testify on FBI Files'' -- The  Washington Post.</p>
        <p>Dick Morris has become to Bill Clinton what the picture of Dorian Gray was to Dorian Gray. All the transgressions we thought we would see in one, we see in the other.</p>
        <p>By getting extravagantly rewarded for stripping authenticity from public life, and proving you can get further fixing an image than fixing on a principle, Dick Morris showed there is no floor to our shamelessness.</p>
        <p>As one friend of mine put it: ''You're driving home late at night after a few pops and you run over a nun. Whoopsie daisy, no problemo.''</p>
        <p>Doing something heinous used to get you into trouble. Now it gets you into a higher tax bracket. We're playing by Morris rules now. There is no honor, no reticence, no loyalty.</p>
        <p>After he was pushed out, exposed as an adulterer who betrayed his wife and his boss with a prostitute, Mr. Morris was able to earn the breathless cover of Time magazine for the second straight week and renegotiate his book deal upward -- to an astonishing $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>Among his other secrets was a five-month-old deal with Harry Evans at Random House. That means he was taking notes on the President's conversations and selling out his White House colleagues while he was still working with them.</p>
        <p>Judith Regan, the New York publisher, said that Mr. Morris, looking for an even better deal, pitched his book to her last week as a flattering portrait of the Clinton Presidency. Isn't it a little late for that, now that the self-proclaimed genius and savior has blabbed to a prostitute with a diary that he found Mr. Clinton to have no core or compassion?</p>
        <p>The air rings with piety. ''This is not a book about a call girl but the governance of America and the White House and other important subjects,'' Mr. Evans said.</p>
        <p>Sure it is. Just as Random House's new O. J. Simpson book by New Yorker writer Jeffrey Toobin is about the waywardness of the legal system and the role of police in a decaying inner-city environment.</p>
        <p>Harry Evans paid top dollar for the inside scoop of a self-destructive narcissist who filled up an insecure, insincere President with poll-driven ideas. We can only hope he takes a bath on the book.</p>
        <p>Eileen McGann, valiantly transforming her private sorrow into public service, will help her husband edit his book on ''governance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris and Ms. McGann found a felicitous match in Mr. Evans and his wife, Tina Brown, editor of The New Yorker. The couples sealed the  book deal over lunch at the Evans-Brown East Side apartment. Ms. Brown bestowed literary legitimacy -- or whatever literary legitimacy The New Yorker has left to bestow -- on Mr. Morris by inviting him to be the honored guest, with Harvard professor Henry Louis Gates Jr., at a New Yorker breakfast for advertisers.</p>
        <p>It breaks new ground in cultural synergy to have The New Yorker sell itself on the back of the Star. We may also soon be witnessing special hearings by the House of Representatives on the back of the Star.</p>
        <p>Republicans, not above scouring the tabloids, declared that Mr. Morris should testify to explain the Sherry Rowlands diary entry quoting him as fingering Hillary Clinton as the one who asked for F.B.I. files of former Republican officials.</p>
        <p>It isn't prurience that makes me linger over the Dick Morris scandals. I have a terrible sinking feeling that they tell us more about ourselves than the 15 percent tax cut or the 48-hour stay in the maternity ward ever will.</p>
        <p>Liberties</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
