<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shakespeare, Quick and Quirky. Huzzah!</title>
    <meta content="20artsnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/20/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/20artsnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Arts And Entertainment"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shakespeare Theater of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Gorce, Tammy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Shakespeare Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shakespeare, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4D71031F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shakespeare, Quick and Quirky. Huzzah!</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shakespeare, Quick and Quirky. Huzzah!</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMMY LA GORCE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">La Gorce, Tammy</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Shakesperience, daylong student Shakespeare festival at Shakespeare Theater of New Jersey in Madison; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEFORE the wedding, there were multiple stabbings and a swordfight. And by the time it was over, several teachers had collapsed.</p>
        <p>But through it all, Shakesperience -- the Shakespeare Theater of New Jersey's first gathering of middle and high school students from across the state -- maintained a lively tone, with 123 teenagers and preteens, some in Renaissance costume and others in ripped jeans, shouting ''Huzzah!'' and otherwise making merry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Shakespeare festival for students is all about exuberance, diversity and knocking the stuffiness out of the plays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEFORE the wedding, there were multiple stabbings and a swordfight. And by the time it was over, several teachers had collapsed.</p>
        <p>But through it all, Shakesperience -- the Shakespeare Theater of New Jersey's first gathering of middle and high school students from across the state -- maintained a lively tone, with 123 teenagers and preteens, some in Renaissance costume and others in ripped jeans, shouting ''Huzzah!'' and otherwise making merry.</p>
        <p>Make-believe violence was a necessary component of the daylong event here on April 26; another Shakesperience will be held on Wednesday at Rider University in Lawrenceville. The main draw was a batch of 20-minute festival-style student stagings of plays like ''Macbeth,'' ''Othello'' and ''Romeo and Juliet.'' But getting the teachers from the seven participating schools onstage was a surprise to everyone: an intermission skit, ''high-speed Hamlet,'' had the wary-looking but game adults reciting rapid-fire dialogue and crumpling to dramatic make-believe deaths in front of their 7th- through 12th-grade students.</p>
        <p>It was a sideshow the students savored. But over all, the day -- one the theater and Rider University plan to repeat annually as part of a new partnership with the Folger Shakespeare Library in Washington -- belonged to them.</p>
        <p>''You guys ate up that stage,'' said Christina Moreno, a literacy teacher at Hillsborough Middle School, who was moved to tears after her squad of 23 seventh and eighth graders performed a heavily edited version of ''Cymbeline'' at 9 a.m.</p>
        <p>''To see everything finally come to fruition after all this practice, after them coming to school early two times a week to get ready -- it's wonderful. They took it and they ran with it.''</p>
        <p>Other students ran with their performances in very different ways, as demonstrated by two other schools: Summit High School's 14 actors came equipped with period costumes and impressive accents for their pared-down version of ''Twelfth Night,'' while Newark Tech High School's 17 cast members gave a brief reading of ''Romeo and Juliet'' before ad-libbing a slangy, slapstick interpretation of the play's wedding scene.</p>
        <p>The disparity in performance styles was by design: ''It's in our mission statement,'' said Jamie Brink-Grant, the Shakespeare Theater's associate director of education. ''One of the purposes of doing this is to bring schools from diverse backgrounds together.'' (Other schools in attendance included Purnell School in Pottersville, Montville High School and two drama programs for home-schooled children, the Faith Hope Love Academy in Belle Mead and the Merely Shakespeare Players in Princeton.)</p>
        <p>Most important, Mr. Brink-Grant said, was that the students walk away with a sense that Shakespeare isn't stuffy. ''We want this festival to be helpful in shaking the assumption that Shakespeare has to be a museum piece,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For Sean Willkens, 18, an aspiring professional actor who played Sebastian in Summit High School's ''Twelfth Night,'' deciphering the playwright was never a problem. ''The language is beautiful, really gorgeous,'' he said. ''It's like a puzzle for you to unscramble. Everyone at our school has a pretty comprehensive grip on it, I think.''</p>
        <p>Others were less sanguine. Alex Toke, a 12-year-old from Hillsborough Middle School who played Posthumus Leonatus in ''Cymbeline,'' said he admired Shakespeare's prolific output and skillful plotting. ''But the words are really hard to memorize, because they go backwards sometimes,'' he said. ''They're in the wrong order.''</p>
        <p>Still, a good story is a good story. Which is why Rachel Thompson, 15, a Summit High sophomore who signed on to be stage manager of ''Twelfth Night'' but ended up taking the role of a priest when a classmate got sick, plans to read ''Macbeth'' this summer. A Shakesperience performance of a scene from the play by the Faith Hope Love Academy sparked her interest. ''I like how they did it,'' she said. ''I need to find out what else happened.''</p>
        <p>For some, the festival, which ended with the handing out of jokey awards for such honors as ''manly maiden'' and ''world-weary woman,'' was a way to work out stage fright. Joey DiCarlo, 14, an eighth grader from Hillsborough Middle School, felt ''really nervous'' playing Jupiter in ''Cymbeline.'' In the end, though, ''it all came together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>For some, it was a wake-up call on the realities of show business. ''I loved being able to play Macduff in 'Macbeth,' '' said Ruth Martin, 14, who attends weekly classes at Faith Hope Love and who wore her long hair tied back for the part. She snagged the role because there were 12 girls and only 4 boys in the class.</p>
        <p>''Some of the female roles in Shakespeare I wouldn't mind playing,'' she said. ''Like Beatrice in 'Much Ado' -- she's interesting. But most of the good roles, especially in Shakespeare, are for boys.''</p>
        <p>Arts And Entertainment</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
