<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Living Larger, and Drawing Fire</title>
    <meta content="20RmcmansionWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zegart, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DA1031F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Living Larger, and Drawing Fire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN ZEGART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zegart, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on efforts in many towns across New York City metropolitan area to pass ordinances that dictate size and style of homes in order to control proliferation of McMansions; efforts are pitting town officials and residents against developers and would-be homeowners; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE the many Eskimo words for snow, a multitude of nicknames exist for the oversize houses commonly referred to as McMansions, and they mirror the uneasiness over the spread of the homes.</p>
        <p>''You hear them called starter castles, beltway baronials, mini Taj Mahals, but my favorite is parachute homes, because of the disregard for local styles -- like they were dropped from the sky,'' said Edward J. Trawinski, a lawyer and land-use expert from Morristown, N.J.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE the many Eskimo words for snow, a multitude of nicknames exist for the oversize houses commonly referred to as McMansions, and they mirror the uneasiness over the spread of the homes.</p>
        <p>''You hear them called starter castles, beltway baronials, mini Taj Mahals, but my favorite is parachute homes, because of the disregard for local styles -- like they were dropped from the sky,'' said Edward J. Trawinski, a lawyer and land-use expert from Morristown, N.J.</p>
        <p>Although the names may be amusing, many owners of smaller homes, especially in older communities dominated by more traditional architecture, find it anything but funny when one goes up in their neighborhood. With the proliferation of mammoth residences throughout the suburbs of New York City and beyond, some towns are trying to restrict the size and, sometimes, the look of new homes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trawinski has helped municipalities in northern New Jersey, including Wayne, Montclair and Bergenfield, write such laws, which commonly set maximums for height and square footage on a sliding scale that varies with the lot size. The laws may also dictate the slope of roofs and require side yards to be large enough so the new home does not loom over its neighbors.</p>
        <p>Such laws draw sharp dividing lines between some residents and builders. The debate is particularly fierce in towns like Westport, Conn., where builders say smallish lots and high land values make tearing down existing homes and replacing them, often with much larger houses, necessary to provide a reasonable profit.</p>
        <p>''I live with these regulations all the time, and they're so complicated and so hard to understand,'' said Rick Benson, a Westport resident and builder. ''And now they're not only getting more complicated, they're actually regulating taste.'' He estimated that he had six houses in various stages of completion; two of them were teardowns. All will be much bigger than those they replaced.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benson said builders respond to market demands and contended that Westport's standards for size were arbitrary. ''I just did a 13,000-square-foot house on six to nine acres smack in the middle of town,'' he said. ''It's massive. It looks like a hotel in the Adirondacks. Not a peep about that one.''</p>
        <p>But the issue of large new houses is so contentious, said Gordon Joseloff, Westport's first selectman, that two previous efforts to pass a home-size ordinance in Westport were voted down. ''The attitude of a lot of people here is, 'You're messing with my nest egg,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>The Town of New Castle, N.Y., is grappling with a similar problem as it pushes ahead with a new law based on floor-area ratio that adjusts the allowable size of a house depending on the lot size. It is an approach sanctioned by courts in several states, including New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, and is based on what Mr. Trawinski called a recognition ''that it's not size per se but the perception of size.''</p>
        <p>''A big house on a little postage stamp of land just looks terrible,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the main goal of such ordinances is not to mandate smaller homes, but to preserve a community's ''streetscape'' by preventing houses that are so much larger than the prevailing architecture as to be jarring, said Virginia Kurshan, chairwoman of the Maplewood, N.J., Historic Preservation Commission.</p>
        <p>At one extreme, she said, nearby Glen Ridge declared the entire borough a historic district, putting tight restrictions on any building allowed. Maplewood, she said, is considering a less drastic law that might apply to new construction and additions.</p>
        <p>Like Maplewood, New Castle has little undeveloped land left, said Frank Annunziata, the town engineer. ''Like a lot of towns that are almost completely built out, we're worried about older, maybe historic houses being knocked down and replaced with something that's inappropriate and much bigger,'' he said. Proposed zoning changes would permit a house of up to 10,391 square feet on four acres; quarter-acre lots would be capped at 4,100 square feet.</p>
        <p>Aesthetics are less of a factor in Sagaponack, near East Hampton, on Long Island, with its expanses of open acreage. Nevertheless, critics have little trouble finding examples for their cause in this newly created village, which is writing its first zoning ordinance.</p>
        <p>There is the 66,000-square-foot mansion on 63 beachfront acres, for example, or the structure called ''the Great Wall of Sagaponack,'' a sprawling residence protected by a wall more than 100 feet long and 20 feet high.</p>
        <p>''We have generally large lots, most at least three acres, but there's still concern over really large houses,'' Mayor Bill Tillotson of Sagaponack said. ''They still stick out.''</p>
        <p>Builders argue that large-scale homes are an inevitable result of skyrocketing land values and changes in home-buying habits.</p>
        <p>''You never used to have 9-, 10-foot ceilings with cathedral space,'' said Stuart R. Koenig, a lawyer and land-use consultant to the New Jersey State League of Municipalities, who estimates that half of New Jersey's towns have tried to regulate housing size. ''And once you do that, if you want to still have living area, you need a bigger building.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benson, the Westport builder, also said that modern tastes dictate larger houses. ''Older houses have low ceilings and out-of-date kitchens,'' he said. ''People don't want to live in houses built in the '40s, '50s and '60s. So they tear them down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benson said he finds ordinances restricting large houses infuriating because they take aim at a problem that is disappearing on its own. ''We've had three years of an economic slowdown, and market conditions and energy costs are causing builders to build smaller houses,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As an example, he cited two houses he built on adjoining lots in Westport: one a 6,500-square-foot home on one and a half acres, which was purchased well before completion, the second a 9,600-square-foot residence on two acres, which took two years to sell.</p>
        <p>''I had to keep dropping the price,'' he said. ''It was just too big.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
