<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outrageous Fortune</title>
    <meta content="Applegate.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/20/books/review/Applegate-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Cooperstown</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cooperstown (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Clark Art Institute</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weber, Nicholas Fox</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Clarks of Cooperstown, The: Their Singer Sewing Machine Fortune, Their Great and Influential Art Collections, Their Forty-Year Feud (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1DE1431F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outrageous Fortune</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Outrageous Fortune</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBBY APPLEGATE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applegate, Debby</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE CLARKS OF COOPERSTOWN</p>
        <p>Their Singer Sewing Machine Fortune,</p>
        <p>Their Great and Influential Art Collections, Their Forty-Year Feud.</p>
        <p>By Nicholas Fox Weber.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 420 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>An American dynasty’s pursuit of big money, high living and fine art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE CLARKS OF COOPERSTOWN</p>
        <p>Their Singer Sewing Machine Fortune,</p>
        <p>Their Great and Influential Art Collections, Their Forty-Year Feud.</p>
        <p>By Nicholas Fox Weber.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 420 pp. Alfred A. Knopf. $35.</p>
        <p>Near the end of Henry James's career, Edith Wharton reproached him for repudiating the novels of Gustave Flaubert. Why, she asked, was Anna Karenina a better subject than Madame Bovary? ''Ah,'' James replied, ''but one paints the fierce passions of a luxurious aristocracy, the other deals with the petty miseries of a little bourgeois in a provincial town.''</p>
        <p>It is hard not to think about Henry James while reading Nicholas Fox Weber's fascinating but flawed family biography, ''The Clarks of Cooperstown.'' All the favorite plot elements are here: the rise of a nouveau riche industrial fortune; the second generation seduced by Europe; the third, spoiled and squabbling, but redeemed by its passion for turning money into beauty. Among them, the Clarks endowed dozens of beloved institutions -- from the Museum of Modern Art to the Baseball Hall of Fame -- and owned thousands of the world's most renowned works of art. In 1954, when Stephen Clark exhibited two dozen items from his collection at a charitable benefit for the Fresh Air Association of St. John, he hung works by El Greco, Rembrandt, Manet, Copley and Hals; two by Seurat, including ''Circus Sideshow''; four by Renoir; and five by Cézanne, including ''The Card Players.'' Also included were Eakins's portrait of Dr. D. Hayes Agnew, Homer's ''Morning Bell'' and Van Gogh's ''Night Café.'' Aristocratic luxuries, indeed.</p>
        <p>Edward Cabot Clark, born in 1811, was an ambitious young Manhattan lawyer when he met Isaac Merritt Singer, an eccentric machinist, actor and hustler who had patented a mechanical sewing machine. In exchange for half-ownership of Singer's new company, the strait-laced lawyer helped the brassy inventor turn his idea into the Model T of sewing machines: cheap, sturdy, culturally transformative and a source of vast wealth. (Singer, who fled the country after fathering 24 children with five overlapping women, deserves a biography all his own.)</p>
        <p>Edward invested in real estate in Manhattan and Cooperstown, N.Y., building some of the first luxury apartments. He died in 1882 while work was under way on a fortresslike structure at 72nd Street and Central Park West, then so far from the city center that he was mocked: ''Why don't you go a few more blocks and build it out in Dakota?'' The name stuck.</p>
        <p>Edward's heir, Alfred Corning Clark, never held a job, instead devoting himself to art, scholarship and philanthropy. Weber suggests that Alfred led a dual life: a quiet family man in America and a gay aesthete in Europe, especially in France, which he declared ''the Mecca of brotherly feeling.'' He was a generous patron to male artists; for 19 years his closest companion was a Norwegian tenor named Lorentz Severin Skougaard. When his father's death forced him to return to Manhattan, Alfred installed Skougaard down the block from the town house where he lived with his wife and children. James's shadow lingers longest in this chapter; surely this was the sort of thing he meant by those uneasy intimations that beneath Europe's splendor and refinement lurked something unspeakable. Weber's bluntness, by contrast, highlights how much of that beauty was created by gay men seeking warm communities of free expression.</p>
        <p>Alfred died in 1896, leaving nearly $50 million to his four sons. Two, Edward and Ambrose, became stolid country squires, devoted to dogs, thoroughbreds and Champagne. The other two, Sterling and Stephen, despite great differences in temperament and taste, shared a compulsive passion for art and institution-building, inherited from their father.</p>
        <p>Sterling, the second oldest, might today be described as bipolar. He pursued feuds and lawsuits with the same gusto as he sought cigars, Burgundy, paintings, silver, rare books, racehorses and manor houses. A manic shopper, he owned 39 Renoirs. But paranoia overtook him. After he sued unsuccessfully to break the family trust in 1927, he did not speak to his brothers for nearly three decades. The federal income tax enraged Sterling, and in 1934, he was accused of joining a cabal of Wall Street plutocrats plotting a coup to replace Franklin Roosevelt with a fascist dictator on the model of Mussolini. Ensuring that neither the government nor his brothers would get his art collection after his death, he built the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute in Williamstown, Mass., where he deemed it less likely to be destroyed in case of atomic attack.</p>
        <p>The youngest son, Stephen, had the starchy appeal of Peter Arno cartoons (which, surprisingly, he collected). As a Yale undergraduate, he was distinguished only by his nickname, ''Bathroom Clark,'' won when his doting mother installed a modern bathroom in his college room. After college, Stephen became besotted with the post-Impressionists. In 1913 he created a stir at the Manhattan Armory Show by buying its most expensive sculpture, ''Standing Woman,'' by Wilhelm Lehmbruck. He went mad for Matisse, hanging 12 of the Frenchman's paintings in the former nursery of his Upper East Side mansion, which he'd decorated to match the pictures, with gaudy flowers and bright floral rugs, pillows and tablecloths. Matisse was reportedly irate when he saw it. Nonetheless, such zeal earned Stephen a seat on the board of trustees of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the brand-new Museum of Modern Art. Although crucial to MoMA's early success, Stephen is remembered primarily for firing its brilliant founding director, Alfred Barr Jr., in a still controversial act that Weber takes pains to defend. Stephen later broke with MoMA, leaving his choicest pieces to the Met and the Yale University Art Gallery.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Weber's skills as a storyteller do not do full justice to this extraordinary material. Instead of evoking a dramatic family saga, he structures his book as a series of meandering and repetitive biographical sketches that muddle the plot and tax the reader's patience. All the same, art lovers will be intoxicated by the sheer abundance of masterworks. Here, Weber is at his best, describing the art in a vivid, straightforward manner, free of pedantry. And he has a gift for breathing life into styles now out of vogue. These days it isn't hard to instill appreciation for, say, Van Gogh's ''Night Café,'' the gloomy masterpiece Stephen gave to Yale. More impressively, Weber conjures the exhilaration of pictures like the Clark Art Institute's perennial favorite, William Bouguereau's frolicsome ''Nymphs and Satyr,'' a scandal in 1873 but already considered old-fashioned when Sterling was seduced by it.</p>
        <p>Better yet, go see these masterpieces for yourself. This summer the Met will mount ''The Clark Brothers Collect: Impressionist and Early Modern Paintings,'' which had its debut at the Clark Art Institute. For the first time, the cream of these rival collections will hang side by side, the magnificent legacy of our eccentric American aristocracy.</p>
        <p>Debby Applegate won a Pulitzer Prize this year for ''The Most Famous Man in America: The</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Debby Applegate won a Pulitzer Prize this year for ''The Most Famous Man in America: The</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
