<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last Shot</title>
    <meta content="20funny--humor.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="52" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/20/magazine/20funny-humor-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE TALES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gannon, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amateur Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EED91231F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last Shot</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Last Shot</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Gannon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gannon, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Gannon article on playing lousy round of golf that was redeemed by 125-yard shot into the cup on 18th green; says shot really impressed a group of college players gathered at green because they had seen nothing of what preceded it; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was feeling a little more blue than usual. I was sitting in my second-story office looking down at the street. I wasn't thinking of jumping, but I was thinking about thinking of jumping. I found myself having Edgar Allan Poe-type thoughts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Feeling blue? All you need is a good heart, optimism, painkillers and golf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was feeling a little more blue than usual. I was sitting in my second-story office looking down at the street. I wasn't thinking of jumping, but I was thinking about thinking of jumping. I found myself having Edgar Allan Poe-type thoughts.</p>
        <p>So I sprang into action. I called a couple of friends for support. They were not home, and their answering-machine messages sounded more than a little sarcastic. ''I'm not in.'' What the hell did they mean by that?</p>
        <p>I thought that now was the time to either a) begin drinking alcohol or b) drive to the gym and work out. Both of these sounded less than good. For a moment I thought: Why not drink and work out? I saw a guy do it once. I remembered him as one of the most pathetic human beings I ever encountered. But still.</p>
        <p>No. I quickly dismissed all thoughts of exercise, drinking, meditating, trying to be a better person by volunteering or reading something really good. I looked across my office. Suddenly, one single idea took control.</p>
        <p>Golf.</p>
        <p>There in the corner gleamed my ticket out of feeling down: my golf clubs! I hadn't touched them in three years. I used to play golf a lot, but then I hurt my back. It pained me now even to address the ball. After my injury (I fell out of my attic), I still went to golf courses, but I did not play. I just rode around in golf carts with people who were playing and made withering comments, which I found amusing for a while. But then I gave that up too.</p>
        <p>I checked and counted the clubs. They were all there. I had balls and tees -- everything but golf shoes. I looked in one of the zippered compartments and found something that confirmed my view that yes, I should play golf, and that God wanted me to: not one but two prescription painkillers. Darvocets. I swiftly swallowed them. A little pain wouldn't stop me now. I had a good heart, optimism and narcotics. What more do you need?</p>
        <p>I drove out to the course at the University of Georgia, about 50 minutes from my house -- precisely the time needed for the Darvocets to work their magic. The course was almost empty, so the pro-shop guy let me go out by myself. He didn't make me wait until another psychotic loner came along. I decided that this was O.K. I would appear stately and aloof rather than sad and drugged. So I started out, with lots of love in my heart for all my fellow golfers. I holla at them, whatever that means.</p>
        <p>At this point, the best ending to this story would be: I played really great and had a magical day on the links. I actually played horribly, even worse than usual. Several psychotic loners came and went as I hacked through my dismal round.</p>
        <p>I was taking my sixth shot on the 18th. It was a little chip out from the trees to the fairway. After that, I had about 125 yards, then a drive home followed by drinking. Then, hopefully, unconsciousness.</p>
        <p>As I took out my 9-iron, I noticed that the University of Georgia's golf team was standing up on the green. Great, I thought. I have to have the golf team watch me while I hit this ball off to the side, or pop it up, or hook it, or dribble it, or slice it or, possibly, it explodes.</p>
        <p>I took my swing and hit the ball. It didn't follow the path of my usual golf shot. It went straight and actually looked as if it might land on the green.</p>
        <p>It did land on the green, hopped a few times and disappeared right into the hole. I had just holed it out from 125 yards! What a guy I am!</p>
        <p>Of course, holing that shot meant that I had a 7 on the hole, hardly a Tigerish score. But nobody on the award-winning University of Georgia golf team knew that. They saw only the last shot. For all anybody knew, I might have just hit my second shot into the hole from 125 for an eagle! A 2 on a par 4!</p>
        <p>I could feel the golf team's eyes on me. I tried to be stately. I had faced adversity, and I had conquered. As I calmly walked onto the green, I heard the golf team's voices.</p>
        <p>''Great shot!''</p>
        <p>''Unbelievable!''</p>
        <p>''Awesome, man!'' (This must have been a freshman.)</p>
        <p>I leaned over and plucked my ball from the hole.</p>
        <p>''What did you use?'' asked one of my fellow great golfers.</p>
        <p>''I always use a 9 for shots like that,'' I said. ''I can usually get close with that.''</p>
        <p>I was very glad I had played. I was very glad I had played alone. I was very, very glad that an award-winning, nationally ranked golf team had witnessed my last sensational shot. For the first time that day, I was just very glad all over the place.</p>
        <p>THE FUNNY PAGES: II: TRUE-LIFE TALES Frank Gannon is the author of four books, including, most recently, ''Midlife Irish: Discovering My Family and Myself.'' His last True-Life Tale was about almost drowning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Frank Gannon is the author of four books, including, most recently, ''Midlife Irish: Discovering My Family and Myself.'' His last True-Life Tale was about almost drowning.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
