<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lavender Hill Mob</title>
    <meta content="Gorra.t" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/20/books/review/Gorra-t.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1848511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Mallon, Thomas</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Fellow Travelers (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DE1431F933A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lavender Hill Mob</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Lavender Hill Mob</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL GORRA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gorra, Michael</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FELLOW TRAVELERS</p>
        <p>By Thomas Mallon.</p>
        <p>354 pp. Pantheon. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Mallon’s novel explores the anti-gay purges of McCarthy-era Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FELLOW TRAVELERS</p>
        <p>By Thomas Mallon.</p>
        <p>354 pp. Pantheon. $25.</p>
        <p>IT'S Washington in 1953, and the senator from Wisconsin has the gavel in his hand. The city is full of muck and fear and the naming of names, but red isn't the only color the McCarthyites claim to abhor. There's lavender too, though the question remains the same: ''Are you now or have you ever been. ...'' At the State Department, the forces of decency work in the Bureau of Security and Consular Affairs, an office whose name sounds to Hawkins Fuller ''like a C.I.A. front: the little publishing house in Vienna, the art dealer in Rome.'' At Fuller's own interrogation, he's asked to walk across the room, then read aloud from Somerset Maugham. But there's nothing swishy about this Navy veteran, and when the lie detector is brought out his pulse holds steady.</p>
        <p>Thomas Mallon's appealing seventh novel opens in 1991 at the newly established American Embassy in Tallinn, Estonia, where Fuller, at 66, is the deputy chief of mission. It's the last stop on what he knows hasn't ''been that much of a career,'' but he's always had other things on his mind, and in Estonia now -- well, some of the few remaining Russian troops are ''awfully good-looking.''</p>
        <p>Fuller had lied to the lie detector, and then rapidly acquired a bride, a properly credentialed and willfully unsuspecting Wellesley girl. Now he looks across the Baltic toward ''Finland, that country so like himself, for so long half free and quite comfortable.'' Other people aren't so lucky, however, and a letter on his desk sends the novel back to 1953, to a bench in Dupont Circle and his first meeting with a nice milk-drinking Roman Catholic boy.</p>
        <p>Tim Laughlin has come to the capital for a summer job on The Washington Star -- a Fordham graduate whose family believes that Joe McCarthy is doing God's work. He too has shaved the truth, having absorbed enough from the Jesuits to tell the draft board he has no homosexual tendencies, since '' 'tendencies' could be proved only by experience, and he'd certainly had none of that.'' Fuller solves this problem and gets him a job too, where in working for a Republican senator Tim will come close to McCarthy himself.</p>
        <p>Mallon has placed historical fiction in Washington before, most notably in ''Henry and Clara,'' his 1994 novel about the couple who shared the Lincolns' box at Ford's Theater. Yet ''Fellow Travelers'' bears a closer resemblance to his wonderful ''Dewey Defeats Truman,'' a novel with a Michigan setting that improbably fuses romantic comedy and electoral politics. This new book has more shadows, but despite its subject it never really seems dark.</p>
        <p>The electronic record has made the sounds and sights of the recent past perpetually available. We have a clear sense of how people used to look, and while that slightly faded Technicolor doesn't bring us any closer to the internal rhythms of the past, it does give today's historical novelists better props than the ones their predecessors had. Mallon writes crisp, buoyant prose, and he has a perfect ear for his period -- for what would spark nostalgia, for what would last -- in a way that makes his account of the 1950s resemble the name-brand realism of the '80s.</p>
        <p>To Fuller's colleague Mary Johnson, Tim looks ''like the lovesick Donald O'Connor in 'Call Me Madam,' '' while Mary herself is much more ''the sort of coed who went to Paris than the kind who became a government girl.'' Fuller attends a reception for some Eastern European exiles in ''a room full of smoked fish and stained suits,'' and the book as a whole mounts a parade of the once well known, of Perle Mesta and Drew Pearson and a dozen now-forgotten senators. It all makes this trip into what Ward Just has called the ''city of fear'' carry instead a kind of sweet promise, as though even after such knowledge it could still be a bright morning in America.</p>
        <p>Mallon establishes a clear link between the ''red menace'' and what's been called ''the lavender scare,'' seeing both purges as part of the same web of suspicion. At the time, some people made that connection too, yet the novel's main characters don't. Their sexual identities are an entirely private matter, something removed from politics. Tim firmly believes in the cause of freedom, but what will most engage his passion is the Hungarian uprising of 1956. It doesn't occur to him that there might be other forms of liberation, and in this, ''Fellow Travelers'' reminds us that the past really is a different country. Or is it? Tim never loses his sense that McCarthy has done more good than bad, and his particular form of Catholic anti-Communism goes a long way toward explaining the National Review and maybe even the Log Cabin Republicans.</p>
        <p>Tim's faith gives him some Graham Greene-ish moments in the confessional, reluctant to seek absolution for what he can no longer believe is a sin, and traveling through a spiritual desert as a consequence. This is where ''Fellow Travelers'' seems least successful. Mallon lets his character go through the motions of anguish, but the novelist himself remains too sanguine to sustain it. So it's just as well that Tim is finally a less tragic figure than he appears -- which makes Hawkins Fuller oddly more so. Or no, not tragic but hollow. Fuller has taken his own measure too calmly, knows too well the limits within which he will stay. It is the only camp thing about him.</p>
        <p>''Fellow Travelers'' sags in the middle, and its plot is a bit too busy. It's not just that the McCarthy hearings are as hard to follow in these pages as any actual government imbroglio, but rather that the narrative becomes cluttered with minor characters. Yet the book lights up every time Fuller's cold, confident face appears, and Mallon is nowhere better than in the deliberately underplayed scene in which the man from Foggy Bottom makes his final choice.</p>
        <p>Michael Gorra is chairman of the English department at Smith College and the author, most recently, of ''The Bells in Their Silence: Travels Through Germany.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Gorra is chairman of the English department at Smith College and the author, most recently, of ''The Bells in Their Silence: Travels Through Germany.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
