<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="619669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD1F3DF936A35754C0A965958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 2-5  WHAT SUMMIT? JAPANESE MAY ASK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 2-5  WHAT SUMMIT? JAPANESE MAY ASK</p>
        <p>Kiichi Miyazawa presides as host this week for a meeting of the Group of Seven in Tokyo, but instead of preparing for it, he has been forced to plead with voters to have mercy on his governing party.  1  The White House wants to announce an accord on aid to Russia.  4  GERMAN INTERIOR MINISTER QUITS  Germany's Interior Minister unexpectedly resigned over a shootout between anti-terrorist officers and two suspected leaders of the Red Army Faction, dealing a political setback to Helmut Kohl.  2  FOR BOSNIANS, ENEMIES WITHIN  Since the siege of Sarajevo began 15 months ago, there has been a war within the war as various groups expend scarce bullets in a violent struggle for power and profit.  3  MANDELA AND DE KLERK HONORED  President Clinton presented Nelson Mandela and F. W. de Klerk with a joint award in Philadelphia for the advances that have been made toward democracy in South Africa.  3  FOR HAITI, MORE STRUGGLES AHEAD  With an agreement on restoring democracy in Haiti, diplomats say, the country faces the challenge of building an economy and supporting political stability in a place with virtually no tradition of compromise.  4  Haiti's military chief began trying to sell the U.N. democracy accord.  4  U.S. MAY QUIT MIDEAST TALKS  Warren Christopher warned that the U.S. might halt its active role in the Mideast peace talks, saying all sides "have to want peace," despite his belief that the Arabs and the Israelis wanted U.S. participation.  5  Bill Clinton's White House troika plots the policy road map.  5  Puri Journal: 600 years later, a Hindu juggernaut keeps on rolling.  2  National 6-8,  REVIVAL OF THE ROAD TRIP  With gasoline expected to remain cheap through the summer, more American vacationers are hitting the road than in the past few years.  37  HISPANIC GRAVITATION TO G.O.P.  The nation's Hispanic population, once a bulwark of the Democratic Party, is slowly defecting to Republican ranks.  1  ANGER OVER CATHOLIC SCHOOLS  Catholics are accusing their church of abandoning the poor in Pennsylvania, where the archdiocese recently closed 14 churches and 8 schools in black neighborhoods.  6  NOW HONORS ORDINARY WOMEN  Under fire for being more concerned with radical feminists than with average women, NOW chose this year to focus on "Everyday Women, Extraordinary Acts." 6  COSTS OF MILITARY CUTBACKS  Nowhere are the immediate costs of military cutbacks more stark than in Charleston, where the Navy employs five times as many people as the next largest employer.  7  BUY THIS HOUSE FOR A SONG  In Maine, where housing prices have tumbled, one seller is offering his home to the person who writes the best jingle of 41 words or less.  6  REALITY MEETS ECONOMIC THEORY  After five months as Labor Secretary, Robert B. Reich's theories have collided with economic reality, littering the budget landscape with fallen campaign promises.  7  Metro Digest 23  DINKINS AND THE HOMELESS  Increasingly, Mayor Dinkins has found himself in the unexpected role of stern rule-maker for the homeless. The Mayor who had maintained that the homeless are like everyone else approved a reduction in public housing apartments for them because his advisers believed they often made bad tenants.  1  U.S. TO ACT ON EXTRADITION  Secretary of State Christopher said that the United States would act swiftly on Egypt's request for the return of Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, the radical Islamic cleric who was detained on Friday in New York on immigration charges.  1  BLIMP CRASHES ON ROOFTOP  A commercial blimp porpoising along above an urban scene of office towers, tenements and busy streets began to deflate and crash-landed on the roof of an apartment building on Manhattan's West Side in a spectacular Fourth of July mishap that left its two crew members injured and a neighborhood agape.  1  Business Digest 37  Arts/Entertainment 13-19  A Gershwin sister reminisces.  13  Shaw's will reawakens a war of words.  13  Art scholars debate a tale of poison.  13  Theater: Dusting off Ziegfeld's spirit.  18  Music: Caramoor Festival opens.  13  Summergarden season opens.  19  Books: "Just Tell Me When to Cry," by Richard Fleischer.  19  Sports 29-36  Baseball: Giants beat Mets.  29  Yanks lose to A's.  31  Former Dodgers remember Drysdale.  32  Phillies beat Padres.  31  Another loss for Tigers.  31  Boxing: An era ends at the Garden.  33  Columns: Berkow on Drysdale 29  Vecsey on Wimbledon 34  Cycling: American rookie tackles the Tour.  32  Horse Racing: Devil His Due wins Suburban.  33  Sports People: 36  Tennis: Sampras defeats Courier for title.  29  Best and worst from Wimbledon.  34  Track and Field: Senior assault on four-minute mile.  32  Obituaries 28  Don Drysdale, Hall of Fame pitcher.</p>
        <p>Joseph Gruss, a philanthropist who supported Jewish schools.</p>
        <p>Joseph Wishy, a producer of programs on the performing arts.</p>
        <p>Curly Joe DeRita, Three Stooges comic.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed 20-21  Editorials  Keep the aid flowing to Russia.  A magic formula for cutbacks.  Karl E. Meyer: Slave trade.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: Skeletons of apartheid.  Fred Ritchin: Foreigners frame America. Chronicle 26  Bridge 18 Crossword 19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
