<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Painter's Best Work Mirrors the Fury of Nature</title>
    <meta content="11liart" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1701124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DC1231F932A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Painter's Best Work Mirrors the Fury of Nature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <dateline>Springs</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE of the difficult, painful lessons of Hurricane Katrina is a realization of nature's power and unpredictability and an acceptance that freak events like it are a condition of living in harmony with nature.</p>
        <p>Syd Solomon, who divided much of his life between beachside homes and studios in East Hampton and Sarasota, Fla. before his death last year at 86, knew all about nature's power and unpredictability. He spent a lifetime painting churning surf and stormy seascapes spattered with white foam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE of the difficult, painful lessons of Hurricane Katrina is a realization of nature's power and unpredictability and an acceptance that freak events like it are a condition of living in harmony with nature.</p>
        <p>Syd Solomon, who divided much of his life between beachside homes and studios in East Hampton and Sarasota, Fla. before his death last year at 86, knew all about nature's power and unpredictability. He spent a lifetime painting churning surf and stormy seascapes spattered with white foam.</p>
        <p>Several of Mr. Solomon's works on paper are on exhibit at the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center here. It is a small exhibition, no more than a dozen works, but each is a pocket tsunami: brimming with energy and vitality, they depict drifting, silvery mounds of choppy water.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomon's paper works have a spontaneity that is beguiling. He applied the paint with seemingly random strokes and gestures, building each image through intuition and experimentation. My guess is that not all of his paintings employing this chancy technique are equally successful, but the ones here, selected by the curators -- Helen A. Harrison, the Pollock House director, and Mike Solomon, the artist's son -- are all first-rate.</p>
        <p>His color combinations are also intriguing. Hot colors (yellows and reds) flirt freely with cooler ones (blues, greens and grays), creating dazzling -- if often perplexing -- atmospheric sublimities. And there is also his attention to qualities of light reflected on water, as Mark Ormond's fine essay in the exhibition catalog suggests. Mr. Solomon was an idiosyncratic colorist.</p>
        <p>He also mixed media, applying combinations of gouache, ink, oil and acrylic paint to the surface of images. He worked wet-on-wet (a technique in which the artist doesn't wait for the layers of paint to dry), mixing, integrating and blurring media and colors. It makes for richly layered lively imagery, giving pride of place to process and technique over what is depicted.</p>
        <p>I also like the way that these paintings are so spatially ambiguous. Looking at them, you are never quite sure where you are in relation to the water, which somehow seems to surround you. Sometimes you will feel your consciousness awakened, with the mind now alert to a possible threat. You may even feel yourself there, in the surf, tossing and turning.</p>
        <p>''George Plimpton's Night on Bastille Day'' (1978) is the rare work on canvas here. It is also less abstract and was probably inspired by a concrete experience: a warm July evening watching fireworks in the company of Mr. Plimpton, Mr. Solomon's neighbor in East Hampton, a well-known journalist, editor and sometime Hollywood actor. The painting is nicely turbulent, the artist mingling smashing explosions with puffs and coils of colored smoke.</p>
        <p>Other works here have the look of hand-colored monoprints. They are not prints, of course, just skillfully layered images. That Mr. Solomon served in a camouflage battalion in the Army Corps of Engineers during World War II suddenly seems pertinent. His paintings are about concealment, in part, the artist inviting us to look closer in order to see the real thing.</p>
        <p>''Syd Solomon: Abstractions of Land, Sea and Sky,'' Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, 830 Fireplace Road, East Hampton, through Oct 29. Information: (631)324-4929 or naples.cc.sunysb.edu/CAS/pkhouse.nsf.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
