<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DC1730F932A05753C1A963958260" item-length="579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance C. R. White</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Show-Week Opportunities</p>
        <p>Retailers like Bloomingdale's, Saks Fifth Avenue and Bergdorf Goodman see show week as a marketing opportunity, a chance to ride the wave of interest generated by runway shows around town. Both Saks and Bergdorf have devoted their windows to promotions related to fashion week.</p>
        <p>Bloomingdale's has taken the tie-in a step further. Today, it will open its first Todd Oldham shop and introduce Mr. Oldham's new jeans line to coincide with the designer's show, which is to take place tonight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Show-Week Opportunities</p>
        <p>Retailers like Bloomingdale's, Saks Fifth Avenue and Bergdorf Goodman see show week as a marketing opportunity, a chance to ride the wave of interest generated by runway shows around town. Both Saks and Bergdorf have devoted their windows to promotions related to fashion week.</p>
        <p>Bloomingdale's has taken the tie-in a step further. Today, it will open its first Todd Oldham shop and introduce Mr. Oldham's new jeans line to coincide with the designer's show, which is to take place tonight.</p>
        <p>Stores and editors routinely preview collections before runway shows to glean advance information about fashon direction. This season, previews by Bloomingdale's executives have led them to believe miniskirts will be a strong trend for young forward designers, so this week the store will feature minis in its windows and publish advertisements touting the new look.</p>
        <p>"We want to show clothes in stock for purchase as people follow the various looks shown on the news and in newspapers," said Kal Ruttenstein, the senior vice president of fashion direction for Bloomingdale's.</p>
        <p>Dawn Mello, the president of Bergdorf Goodman, says that customers start calling the store for information on new styles within hours or days of having seen them in newspaper or television coverage of the runway shows.</p>
        <p>"We have customers who are just as aware as we are about what's going on," she said.</p>
        <p>Retailers also want to capitalize on the public relations opportunity that show week presents. The window promotions at Saks feature sample clothes from American designers and accessories drawn from the collections designers are presenting to the trade as part of Seventh on Sixth. Since they are for the spring season, none of the products are for sale.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruttenstein's campaign also serves a purpose beyond direct sales. "You have editors and buyers from all over the world, all over the country coming through the store during show week," he said. "Everybody has to put their best foot forward." Lauren in a New Field</p>
        <p>The newest product from Ralph Lauren can neither be worn nor draped over a Cordovan leather chair. Next week, Mr. Lauren will introduce four compact disks of selected music, each compiled to complement a particular mood.</p>
        <p>The CD's will be sold for $15 each in Ralph Lauren stores and Federated stores, which include Macy's and Bloomingdale's. They are being produced in association with the Sony Music Corporation.</p>
        <p>The idea for the recordings, the Lauren company said, was spurred by the numerous requests it received for tapes of the music played in Mr. Lauren's Polo stores and at his shows.</p>
        <p>It is also a mass-market idea coming from a source that aspires to exclusivity. Martha Stewart has also released compilations of music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lauren's CD's are titled, "The Black Tie Collection," "Songs Across America," "The Classical Collection" and "Holiday." Selections are from popular songs. "Songs Across America," for instance, includes selections like "Wildfire" and "Brown-Eyed Girl."</p>
        <p>Wear the correct outfit while listening. The Shifting Spotlight</p>
        <p>If the supermodels are doing a slow fade, who is going to fill the vacuum?</p>
        <p>Young entertainers seem to be getting more attention from the fashion community. Madonna's second advertising campaign for Gianni Versace has just been released. Prada likes Drew Barrymore, and Nicole Miller was sending a bevy of young actresses down her runway on last night.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
