<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guggenheim Foundation, Long a Donor, Is Now Having to Seek Donations</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRANTS (CORPORATE AND FOUNDATION)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GUGGENHEIM FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARENSON, KAREN W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grants (Corporate and Foundation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D8153AF932A05753C1A963958260" item-length="1639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guggenheim Foundation, Long a Donor, Is Now Having to Seek Donations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARENSON, KAREN W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For 70 years, the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation has bestowed grants on promising scholars, scientists and artists -- from Aaron Copland, Ansel Adams and James Baldwin to Henry A. Kissinger, Linus Pauling and Paul Samuelson -- 13,500 in all.</p>
        <p>But now, cup in hand, the foundation, set up with proceeds from the Guggenheim mining fortune, is asking others for contributions so it can continue to give money to a new generation of artists and researchers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For 70 years, the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation has bestowed grants on promising scholars, scientists and artists -- from Aaron Copland, Ansel Adams and James Baldwin to Henry A. Kissinger, Linus Pauling and Paul Samuelson -- 13,500 in all.</p>
        <p>But now, cup in hand, the foundation, set up with proceeds from the Guggenheim mining fortune, is asking others for contributions so it can continue to give money to a new generation of artists and researchers.</p>
        <p>Pleas from the American Cancer Society, the American Red Cross and CARE come by the armful. But a request from the Guggenheim Foundation seems about as likely as the computer magnate William H.  Gates asking for a loan.</p>
        <p>"People look at us," said Joel O. Conarroe, a literary scholar who is president of the Guggenheim Foundation. "They say: 'You're a foundation. You have the Guggenheim name. Why do you need money?' "</p>
        <p>But years of generous spending, coupled with erratic investment earnings resulting from an overly conservative investment strategy, eroded the wealth of the foundation in the 1970's and 1980's. Now the Guggenheim Foundation is on a quest to add some $10 million to $20 million to its $150 million endowment.</p>
        <p>While it is not unusual for foundations to have difficulty earning high enough investment returns year after year to replace what they spend and to keep pace with inflation, it is highly unusual for a private foundation like the Guggenheim to resort to raising money.</p>
        <p>Although some argue that foundations ought to spend themselves out of existence rather than being self-perpetuating fonts of grant money, the Guggenheim's directors say they do not think that closing down makes sense for them.</p>
        <p>"There was discussion of the board about whether we should exist in perpetuity or go out of business, but no real debate," said Robert V. Lindsay, the former president of the Morgan Guaranty Trust Company and the chairman of the foundation; he leads its fund-raising campaign. "Everyone felt we would be more and more needed."</p>
        <p>The Guggenheim Foundation was set up by Senator Simon Guggenheim and his wife, Olga, after the death of their 17-year-old son at Phillips Exeter Academy in 1922, shortly before he was to enter Harvard. The Senator's idea, developed after consultations with several Rhodes scholars, was to provide grubstakes for exceptional scholars, scientists and artists, or, in his own words, "to continue the influence of the young life of eager aspiration."</p>
        <p>In the years since then, the Guggenheim Foundation has acquired a luster that rubs off on its recipients.</p>
        <p>"Guggenheim invented the prestige fellowship," said Stanley N. Katz, president of the American Council of Learned Societies. "It's not just the money. For young academics, it was the Good Housekeeping Seal of Approval. With its peer review process, it came to have a cachet that was invaluable."</p>
        <p>Other foundations grant fellowships, as do Government agencies, like the National Science Foundation, the National Endowment for the Arts and the National Endowment for the Humanities, and a growing number of research centers at universities. But many of these have a narrower vision. The Guggenheim Foundation offers fellowships in 79 fields; computer studies is one of the newest. And the National Endowments, the biggest sources of financing in their fields, face deep cuts from Congress and an uncertain future.</p>
        <p>"In terms of what's available, the Guggenheims are critical," said Mr. Katz, whose own organization gives about $1.1 million in fellowships in the humanities and social sciences annually, about half of what the Guggenheim Foundation spends in those areas each year.</p>
        <p>The grants are not large. The average fellowship last year was $27,031, and the highest was $31,000; the amount is based on need. But for professors with a half-year's salary for a year's sabbatical leave, or for writers and artists used to living frugally, they often make an important financial difference.</p>
        <p>The realization that the foundation needed to tighten its belt if it wanted to stay in business began to take shape in the mid-1980's, about the time that its second president, Gordon Ray, was preparing to retire.</p>
        <p>With an endowment hovering between about $100 million and $120 million, the foundation had been awarding, since the 1950's, about 300 fellowships each year, including about 25 to 30 awards each year in Latin America, where Guggenheim mining activities brought in huge profits.</p>
        <p>While foundations are required by law to spend an amount equal to at least 5 percent of their assets annually, the Guggenheim had spent more than that in many years to maintain the number of grants and to try to adjust the value of the grants to account for inflation.</p>
        <p>But, like numerous other foundations, its investment returns have been erratic, with big gains in some years and losses in others. In some years, its investment earnings did not even cover its grants. Like many foundations and other investors in the 1980's, the Guggenheim had left all its assets in the hands of one bank money manager, rather than trying for more diversification and more aggressive money managers who might have brought in higher returns. The trustees began to realize that those results, combined with inflation, meant that if the foundation continued along the path it was on, it faced a gradual erosion of its spending power in coming decades.</p>
        <p>With the help of a planning grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, the Guggenheim Foundation called in a consulting firm that confirmed the worst fears of the trustees: they could not continue to hand out grants at the rate they had been if they wanted the foundation to be around indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Under the new president, Mr. Conarroe, who had been the dean of the School of Arts and Sciences at the University of Pennsylvania and a Guggenheim fellow himself, the foundation adopted in 1989 a four-step plan that involved cutting costs, awarding fewer fellowships, following a more aggressive investment strategy for the endowment and raising money.</p>
        <p>The foundation handles some 3,500 applications a year, but it is modestly run. Its staff members opt for subways over taxis, and they bring up food from the delicatessen downstairs. Its flashiest assets are its Park Avenue address, its prestigious name and the copious works by fellows that adorn the offices: shelves and shelves of books by well-known authors like Edna St. Vincent Millay, Hart Crane, Saul Bellow and John Updike, and walls lined with the work of big-name photographers like Adams and Diane Arbus.</p>
        <p>Still, it trimmed its staff and cut the number of grants by almost half. "The cuts were really draconian," Mr. Connaroe said. "Where before we might have had 12 composers or 12 poets, now we had only six or seven."</p>
        <p>The foundation also added two new investment experts -- Leon Levy of Odyssey Partners and S. Parker Gilbert of Morgan Stanley -- to its board of trustees and finance committee. They have helped reshape the investment strategy, which will take the foundation into some less conventional investments, like specialized hedge funds. And, for the first time ever, the foundation took on a part-time development officer to help raise money.</p>
        <p>So far, the fund raising, now in its fourth year of formal solicitations, has been low-key. Efforts to raise money from other foundations proved difficult, so the Guggenheim Foundation is focusing on its own body of fellows and friends, calling on former fellows like Wendy Wasserstein, the playwright; E. Annie Proulx, the novelist, and Theodore R. Sizer, the educator, to write artful letters to other fellows in their fields.</p>
        <p>"Lord knows, fund raising is not my thing," Ms. Proulx said. But she agreed to do it. "The foundation is a wonderful place to put your money if you have some -- the awards are so important," Ms. Proulx said. But she added: "Guggenheim or not, a lot of writers are not exactly rolling in the chips. So, as a group to appeal to, they have shallow pockets."</p>
        <p>While the trustees recognize that, they still say it is the appropriate place to start.</p>
        <p>"We are taking a rather quiet approach -- with a rifle, not a shotgun," said Mr. Lindsay, the foundation chairman. "It's going to be a slow process. It may seem too deliberate, but that doesn't worry me."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindsay said the goal was to be able to back 20 to 40 more fellowships by the end of the century, or enough to bring the total to about 200 per year. That would still be fewer fellowships than the foundation had been awarding each year through 1989.</p>
        <p>So far, the campaign has taken in about $2 million of its $10 million to $20 million goal, not counting bequests or a recent pledge of $500,000 by Mr. Levy. It is also working out final details on a $1 million challenge grant from William T. Golden, a philanthropist who was a trustee.</p>
        <p>So far, 1,776 fellows have made donations, and 97 more have designated the foundation as a recipient after their deaths. The average gift last year was $225.</p>
        <p>But even among fellows who talk of the Guggenheim program as one of the highlights of their lives, it is a hard sell.</p>
        <p>"They're as worthy as anything else I give to," said Sondra Perl, a professor of English at Lehman College of the City University of New York. "The Guggenheim was invaluable, and their fund-raising letter made me think. But I certainly didn't get the feeling that their existence was in any way threatened."</p>
        <p>But there are others who appear to be more inclined to help. John Kenneth Galbraith, the Harvard University economist, said that he would be more than willing to contribute.</p>
        <p>"For better or worse, I would have not written "The Affluent Society" without my Guggenheim," he said. "It gave me a year off in Switzerland to write with no interruptions. I'm eternally grateful."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
