<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What the Tapes in the Simpson Case Say</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="784246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D9103BF930A1575BC0A963958260" item-length="1350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What the Tapes in the Simpson Case Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MARGOLICK</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Transcripts of taped interviews with the former police detective who is a central prosecution witness in the O. J. Simpson case depict him boasting that on at least one occasion, he and other policemen had a "kill party" to celebrate a police shooting. The detective, Mark Fuhrman, also declares that there is "nothing better" than "a good beating."</p>
        <p>"That's when everybody wants to get some beer," said Mr. Fuhrman, who found many pieces of evidence in the Simpson case, and whose racial and ethical attitudes now dominate the trial. He continued, according to a transcript obtained by The New York Times: "It's like the end of a football game. You just won the championship. And you're on the real high. You're dominant. You're powerful. You're unbeatable."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Transcripts of taped interviews with the former police detective who is a central prosecution witness in the O. J. Simpson case depict him boasting that on at least one occasion, he and other policemen had a "kill party" to celebrate a police shooting. The detective, Mark Fuhrman, also declares that there is "nothing better" than "a good beating."</p>
        <p>"That's when everybody wants to get some beer," said Mr. Fuhrman, who found many pieces of evidence in the Simpson case, and whose racial and ethical attitudes now dominate the trial. He continued, according to a transcript obtained by The New York Times: "It's like the end of a football game. You just won the championship. And you're on the real high. You're dominant. You're powerful. You're unbeatable."</p>
        <p>He declares later: "Most real good policemen understand that they would just love to take certain people and just take them to the alley and just blow their brains out. All gang members for one. All dope dealers for two. Pimps, three."</p>
        <p>Testimony in the trial plodded along today until an 11th-hour disclosure by Dr. Henry Lee, the head of the crime laboratory of the Connecticut State Police and a much-heralded expert on crime scene collection and analysis. Dr. Lee said he found what could be a second type of bloody shoeprint -- one inconsistent with the shoes prosecutors say Mr. Simpson wore on the night of the killings -- on the walkway, a piece of paper and an envelope found near the bodies of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald L. Goldman.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lee's findings could suggest either that a second attacker was at the crime scene or that the police walked willy-nilly over evidence. If left uncontradicted, either point would be powerful evidence for the defense. Dr. Lee said the imprint on the paper, which the police photographed but failed to collect, was beneath blood rather than above it.</p>
        <p>The defense is clearly not through quizzing Dr. Lee on the subject. But even before he elaborates, Tom Lange, one of the two police detectives who headed the investigation, hinted that there was less to Dr. Lee's testimony than meets the eye. "Stay tuned," Mr. Lange said.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors face not only the testimony of an eminent expert, but also the comments that Mr. Fuhrman made to Laura Hart McKinny, a North Carolina college professor and screenwriter, during at least 13 hours of interviews taped from 1985 to 1994. Ms. McKinny was working on a screenplay on tensions between the men and women of the Los Angeles Police Department, and at times in the transcript it is unclear whether Mr. Fuhrman is describing something he actually witnessed or is helping construct a scene.</p>
        <p>Defense lawyers want the jury to hear nearly 60 snippets from the tapes, in which Mr. Fuhrman either calls blacks "niggers" or hints at his own misconduct as a police officer. The judge is considering whether to allow any of the excerpts.</p>
        <p>The interview bounces back and forth between fiction and reality, with the borders often indistinct. There are repeated references, for example, to fictional characters: when they should be killed and how.</p>
        <p>The transcript says Mr. Fuhrman told Ms. McKinny that Men Against Women, a clandestine police group to which he apparently belonged, had held one kill party, and he suggested that it was a more regular occurrence. "M.A.W. had a kill party," he said. "We'll have it a couple of days after we're -- you know -- like the day after. Like the day after the shooting, it'll be in the paper."</p>
        <p>But when he elaborated on what such an event is like, filled with beer drinking and manly backslapping, it was not clear which hat, police memoirist or fiction writer, he was wearing, or whether he was speaking from experience or concocting hyperbolic tales for a screenplay. That is also true when he speaks of how a policeman must cover his face when shooting someone in the temple to keep bone fragments out of his eyes.</p>
        <p>The tape excerpts that the defense wants the largely minority jury to hear are potentially potent tools to convince jurors that Mr. Fuhrman is a bigot and liar capable of planting incriminating evidence.</p>
        <p>Judge Lance A. Ito told the defense lawyers this morning: "What you have presented to me with regards to these tapes and transcripts is a very prodigious task. You should not anticipate a ruling on this issue this week."</p>
        <p>In the transcript, Mr. Fuhrman said he had "beaten a lot of people real bad." He also said that shooting suspects was "highly pleasurable," but that the best police officers do not have to use their guns. And he rhapsodizes about a culture built on protecting one another, fearlessness, loyalty to colleagues and male bonding -- or, as he put it, drinking tequila straight in the kitchen while womenfolk sit in the living room.</p>
        <p>"They love to drink beer," he said of his police fraternity. "They love cowboy boots. They like good music. A dirty bar. Loose women. They are all Republicans. Most of them are veterans. They believe in going to war. They're very patriotic. They are the same kind of guy that they get all choked up when they hear the National Anthem. They're the same guy who stands up with their hand over their heart at a baseball game. Those are just the kind of people that policemen have been since policemen have been policemen."</p>
        <p>In court today, Christian Reichardt, a Los Angeles chiropractor, testified that although Mr. Simpson had been intermittently depressed in the months before Mrs. Simpson and Mr. Goldman died, he was "more relaxed than usual" and "very jovial" during a telephone conversation roughly 90 minutes before the killings.</p>
        <p>Judge Ito earlier ruled that Mr. Reichardt, who spoke with a slight German accent and came to court wearing a pony tail, earring and "Hamsters USA" button, could not testify about the drug use of Faye Resnick, his former girlfriend and one of Mrs. Simpson's best friends.</p>
        <p>Deputy District Attorney Christopher A. Darden tried to show that the witness was beholden to Mr. Simpson, who had thrown business and pleasure trips his way. "Are you here to help the defendant?" Mr. Darden asked at one point.</p>
        <p>"Nope," replied Mr. Reichardt, who sometimes smiled mockingly at the prosecutor's questions while looking at the jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darden pressed Mr. Reichardt, largely without success, to concede that Mr. Simpson was despondent and angry when Mrs. Simpson left him for good.</p>
        <p>The defense handed Judge Ito a new motion on the Fuhrman tapes this morning, presumably purged of the erroneous page citations that prompted the Judge's ire Monday, listing those portions that it wants to introduce in evidence. The motion was supplemented by what Mr. Simpson's lead lawyer, Johnnie L. Cochran Jr., said were 10 additional references to "niggers" lifted off a previously untranscribed tape.</p>
        <p>Moments later, Mr. Simpson's lawyers tried to ask Larry Ragle, a crime-scene specialist highly critical of police work in the Simpson case, about his encounter on Monday with Philip Vannatter, who with Mr. Lange headed the investigation. Defense lawyers say Mr. Vannatter refused to shake Mr. Ragle's extended hand, calling him "a traitor." That, they said, reflects the "conspiracy of silence" to cover up misconduct.</p>
        <p>Deputy District Attorney Marcia Clark said the attempt to recall Mr. Ragle left her speechless, only to start on a long verbal assault on Mr. Ragle and the defense team.</p>
        <p>"These people want to put on everything they can to slime the Police Department," Ms. Clark said angrily, accusing Mr. Ragle of "basically lying on the witness stand."</p>
        <p>Judge Ito cut her off. But Ms. Clark persisted, maintaining that "there might be one or two others in this country" who shared Mr. Vannatter's low opinion of Mr. Ragle.</p>
        <p>The reference to the audience outside the courtroom provoked Judge Ito's long-simmering resentment of the camera to his left. "That causes me to believe that the lawyers are pandering to the cameras, and that causes me to believe that I probably ought to pull the plug on the cameras," he warned.</p>
        <p>Judge Ito has made such threats before, and no one expected him to follow through.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
