<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confused Atop a Mountain Peak? Clues to Cognitive Losses Found</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="784305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOUNTAIN CLIMBING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RUNNING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OXYGEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT EVEREST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PIKES PEAK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIEBERMAN, PHILIP (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOOD, STEVEN (DR)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mountain Climbing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DE1E3EF930A1575BC0A963958260" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confused Atop a Mountain Peak? Clues to Cognitive Losses Found</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASED on experiments done on Mount Everest and Pikes Peak, researchers are discovering why many mountain climbers make mistakes and why women tend to adapt to high altitudes better than men.</p>
        <p>The new findings apply not only to elite athletes and mountain climbers, the researchers said, but to summer vacationers who climb popular spots like Mount Rainier in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASED on experiments done on Mount Everest and Pikes Peak, researchers are discovering why many mountain climbers make mistakes and why women tend to adapt to high altitudes better than men.</p>
        <p>The new findings apply not only to elite athletes and mountain climbers, the researchers said, but to summer vacationers who climb popular spots like Mount Rainier in Washington.</p>
        <p>The acute effects of mountain sickness are well known, said Dr. Philip Lieberman, a neuroscientist at Brown University who is interested in how the brain is affected by high altitudes. Some people get headaches and vomit in reaction to high altitudes, he said, but less has been known about the cognitive effects of climbing 14,000-foot peaks.</p>
        <p>When climbers get to very high altitudes, Dr. Lieberman said, "even experienced people do crazy things," like ignoring the risk of avalanches.</p>
        <p>To find out why, in 1993 Dr. Lieberman set up a small laboratory at a base camp 17,500 feet above sea level, in the shadow of Mount Everest. He enlisted five male members of an American expedition that was on its way to Everest's 29,000-foot summit.</p>
        <p>Ensconced at the base camp, the researcher stayed in radio contact with the climbers as they rested at camps 20,800 feet, 23,600 feet and 26,400 feet above sea level.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lieberman based his experiment on a theory that lack of oxygen selectively impairs a part of the brain involved in sequencing movements, including the motions made by the tongue, lips and larynx during speech. When this area, called the basal ganglia, is deprived of oxygen, he said, people have trouble with the complex syntax of spoken language and with making judgments.</p>
        <p>To measure these effects, Dr. Lieberman read sentences to the climbers while they looked at simple pictures in a test booklet. Their task was to match a picture with a sentence. At the highest camp, the climbers took 50 percent longer to comprehend sentences that a typical 6-year-old could understand, Dr. Lieberman said.</p>
        <p>He also asked the climbers to answer questions like "Which letter does not belong -- A, a or b?" Such questions have two correct answers, Dr. Lieberman said. It can be "b" because it is the only "b" or "A" because it is the only capital letter. As climbers went higher, he said, they found it increasingly difficult to see the problem in two ways.</p>
        <p>Finally, Dr. Lieberman asked the climbers to read a list of simple words. He then measured the timing of their speech and found that the higher they climbed, the more difficulty they had with making simple sounds.</p>
        <p>For example, to produce a "buh" sound, a climber had to vibrate his vocal cords within 20 thousandths of a second after opening his lips. But he needed to wait 40 thousandths of a second to make a "puh" sound. The climbers mistimed the movements of their lips and vocal cords so that "buh" and "puh" sounded the same, Dr. Lieberman said. "Their speech got very sloppy," he said, and their judgment deteriorated.</p>
        <p>On the Everest expedition, one climber whose "buhs" and "puhs" overlapped wanted to leap over a wide crevasse, Dr. Lieberman said. "He was dressed in heavy boots and could never have made it," he said, "but a Sherpa stopped him in time." In other research carried out on mountaintops, Dr. Steven Wood, a physiologist at the East Carolina School of Medicine in Greenville, N.C., examined the blood of runners competing in the 1993 and 1994 annual races up Pikes Peak in Colorado.</p>
        <p>The race covers 13.2 miles beginning in Manitou Springs (6,800 feet) and ends at the summit of Pikes Peak (14,100 feet). "Average running time is equal to most marathons," Dr. Wood said, "but the race covers half the distance. The altitude gain slows people down. It's very stressful."</p>
        <p>When researchers examined the runners' blood, they found no change in the women's blood, but the men's blood had become sticky, like ketchup.</p>
        <p>"In most parts of the body, blood flows continuously," Dr. Wood said.  "But heart and skeletal muscles contract, squeezing off all blood flow. Then they relax, so blood can start flowing again. But if blood becomes too much like ketchup, then you have a potentially dangerous situation. There may not be enough pressure to get the blood going again."</p>
        <p>This may explain why more men than women drop dead while running, Dr. Wood said. But at this point "it's only speculation," he said, and the effects seen in the runners on Pikes Peak are not life threatening, he added.</p>
        <p>Blood becomes more ketchup-like if it has too many red blood cells, Dr. Wood said, and it is known that testosterone promotes the growth of red blood cells. Could this be what happened to the male runners?</p>
        <p>Probably not, Dr. Wood said, because the number of red blood cells was the same before and after the race. But it could involve female hormones.</p>
        <p>A likely candidate is progesterone, Dr. Wood said. Females rats are better able to breathe in low oxygen than male rats, especially when their progesterone levels are highest. The hormone has been shown to stimulate breathing capacity in pregnant women, who produce high amounts of progesterone, and who tend to hyperventilate. More progesterone means they can take more oxygen into their blood, he said.</p>
        <p>Thus a woman running up Pikes Peak or climbing Mount Everest might have an advantage over her male companions, Dr. Wood said. In sitting around campfires, climbers often note that women seem to do well at high altitudes, but the stories so far are anecdotal, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
