<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Blues: Here More, There Less</title>
    <meta content="14BLUE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="JAZZ REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="JAZZ REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blues Music Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">King, B B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EEDE143AF937A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Blues: Here More, There Less</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews Blues Music Festival at Radio City Music Hall, with B B King and others; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blues resists definition. It doesn't always fit the well-known three-chord, 12-bar structure, or any other one. It does involve blue notes, and a tone that can be despairing, stoic, wry, lusty, sullen and resilient, all at once. Yet even if it can't be precisely delineated, the blues means something, despite the tendency to apply the term to any American music that's not trying to be trendy.</p>
        <p>The blues was the kind of music B. B. King performed on Wednesday night, headlining the Blues Music Festival at Radio City Music Hall, a five-hour quadruple bill that was only about 40 percent blues. The night before, Keb' Mo' performed at the Bottom Line in a set that borrowed blues techniques while skirting the blues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blues resists definition. It doesn't always fit the well-known three-chord, 12-bar structure, or any other one. It does involve blue notes, and a tone that can be despairing, stoic, wry, lusty, sullen and resilient, all at once. Yet even if it can't be precisely delineated, the blues means something, despite the tendency to apply the term to any American music that's not trying to be trendy.</p>
        <p>The blues was the kind of music B. B. King performed on Wednesday night, headlining the Blues Music Festival at Radio City Music Hall, a five-hour quadruple bill that was only about 40 percent blues. The night before, Keb' Mo' performed at the Bottom Line in a set that borrowed blues techniques while skirting the blues.</p>
        <p>Mr. King, who turns 71 on Monday, performed with plenty of shtick: kissing his guitar, Lucille; mock-sobbing and sniffling; demanding sing-alongs. With a big band behind him, his repertory touched on jazz and rhythm-and-blues, but his singing and guitar solos were unadulterated blues, moving within one line from quiet misery to fury to laughter, making a guitar phrase sigh and then sting. ''When new gets old,'' Mr. King sang, ''I'll still be around,'' and no listener could doubt it.</p>
        <p>Sharing the bill, the Neville Brothers played down their greatest strength, their mastery of New Orleans rhythm, and slighted their own repertory to act like the world's most overqualified cover band. Even Aaron Neville's supernal falsetto wore thin after one too many ballads.</p>
        <p>Delbert McClinton, a Texas honky-tonk singer, sounded as if he had a sore throat. And Kenny Wayne Shepherd played showy, repetitious hard-rock blues guitar, aiming for Jimi Hendrix and Stevie Ray Vaughan and reaching toward Robin Trower. During intermission a disk jockey promoted new albums at top volume, earning no friends for the record store that sponsored the intrusion.</p>
        <p>With his fedora, his sepia-toned clothes and a shiny steel guitar in his lap, Keb' Mo' (short for Kevin Moore) was the image of an old-fashioned bluesman when he performed at the Bottom Line. He also had a bluesman's skills: the syncopated ragtime finger picking, the husky voice that sounded both experienced and amused, like a younger Taj Mahal. But the image didn't tell the right story.</p>
        <p>Keb' Mo' is a folky songwriter who touches down now and then in the blues. But he's closer to Tracy Chapman, Lyle Lovett, Bill Withers or Bonnie Raitt than he is to Robert Johnson or the Rev. Gary Davis. His songs are often good-natured psychobabble; one answers blues predicaments (no lover, no job) with the assurance, ''You can love yourself.'' Often, his performance improves on his material. But at times, as in ''Standin' at the Station'' and ''Mama, Where's My Daddy,'' he approached the core of the blues, facing down desolation with a grin.</p>
        <p>JAZZ REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
