<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Urges Doctors to Fight Surgical Pain (and Myths)</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAIN-RELIEVING DRUGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NURSING AND NURSES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, LOUIS W (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pain-Relieving Drugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DA1531F935A35750C0A964958260" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Urges Doctors to Fight Surgical Pain (and Myths)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Government recommended today that doctors provide painkillers swiftly and aggressively to patients after surgery to decrease suffering and speed recovery.</p>
        <p>Federal health officials said myths about pain and its management cause half of the patients who undergo surgery in more than 23 million procedures each year to suffer unrelieved, unnecessary pain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Government recommended today that doctors provide painkillers swiftly and aggressively to patients after surgery to decrease suffering and speed recovery.</p>
        <p>Federal health officials said myths about pain and its management cause half of the patients who undergo surgery in more than 23 million procedures each year to suffer unrelieved, unnecessary pain.</p>
        <p>"We can do more, and we can do better, to control pain after surgery," the Health and Human Services Secretary, Dr. Louis W. Sullivan, said at a news conference. "This guideline discusses the actual physical damage which a patient can sometimes suffer as a result of pain, and it shows that inadequately managed pain can inhibit recovery, prolong hospitalization and thus potentially contribute to higher-than-necessary costs." Talks With Patients Urged</p>
        <p>In the first of a series of nonbinding medical care guidelines, the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research, a new agency mandated by Congress, called on doctors and nurses to take more time to monitor and measure pain and to treat it aggressively with drugs, relaxation therapy and other means.</p>
        <p>It is no longer sufficient to give pain medication "as needed," or only after the patient complains, said the guidelines. Doctors should work with patients before and after surgery to plan medication and other treatment to keep patients as pain-free as possible, they said. To aid in this, doctors should make it common practice to have patients rate their pain, such as using a simple 10-point scale, to track progress in managing it, the guidelines said.</p>
        <p>The guidelines said numerous studies show it is easier to control pain before it starts, or when it is at a low level, than to wait until the patient is suffering. "Prevention is better than treatment," said the guidelines. "Pain that is established and severe is difficult to control."</p>
        <p>"When doctors simply call for injections of such painkillers as morphine and codeine 'as needed,' the results are often undermedication and unnecessary pain in roughly half the patients," said Dr. James O. Mason, head of the Public Health Service, of which the new agency is a component.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mason said part of the problem was myths about pain "that have become part of our culture" -- such notions that pain is necessary to build character, that infants do not feel pain, that elderly patients have a higher pain tolerance and that narcotics used for postoperative pain are often addictive.</p>
        <p>The postoperative pain guidelines are the first of many planned by the new health policy and research agency, which is charged with developing advice for doctors and other professionals concerning health practices that may be the center of uncertainty, and improving the quality and efficiency of patient care.</p>
        <p>Unlike similar consensus conferences on health issues sponsored by other government agencies and private groups, the new agency's work focuses on more extensive examinations of medical literature concerning practices that are in wide use, said Dr. J. Jarrett Clinton, administrator of the agency. After gathering further information from other sources, such as public meetings and interviews, expert panels assembled by the agency develop treatment guidelines.</p>
        <p>Dr. Clinton said a big difference between these guidelines and those from other groups is that they have been tested at hospitals and clinics before they are released. In coming months, the agency hopes to release similar sets of guidelines concerning such problems as treating cancer pain, senility, urinary incontinence and patients who are infected with the virus that causes AIDS but who have not yet developed symptoms.  Not Trying to Dictate</p>
        <p>Dr. Mason said that the guidelines were voluntary and were not an attempt by the Government to dictate medical practice. The guidelines should be viewed like those on immunization or AIDS care issued by the Federal Centers for Disease Control, or the recommendations of panels from the National Institutes of Health, which are generally accepted by doctors nationwide, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Todd, executive vice president of the American Medical Association, and Dr. Barbara Redman, executive director of the American Nurses Association, immediatedly endorsed the pain guidelines.</p>
        <p>"They do not dictate treatment and must never be viewed as 'cookbook medicine,' " Dr. Todd said at the news briefing. "These are guidelines, which we prefer to called parameters because they define a range of options available for doing something. It's still individual care."</p>
        <p>To study pain, the agency brought together an 18-member panel that included specialists in pediatrics, neurology, physical therapy, pharmacy and medical ethics, nurses, pain experts and a consumer representative. The panel, headed by Dr. Daniel B. Carr of Massachusetts General Hospital and Dr. Ada K. Jacox, a registered nurse and sociologist with the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, began working on the guidelines in 1990. Use of Morphine Discussed</p>
        <p>The panel's recommendations, which also cover pain management for trauma and certain diagnostic procedures, discusses types of drugs that should be used, from narcotics to aspirin, dosages and dose schedules. For instance, the guidelines recommend using morphine first, instead of meperidine or Demerol as is common now, for managing severe postoperative pain because morphine is easier to use for continuous dosing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jacox noted that doctors and patients have been reluctant to use morphine because of fears of addiction, but several good studies indicate this risk is very small, occurring in less than 0.04 percent of cases.</p>
        <p>The panel also issued these recommendations and findings regarding pain:</p>
        <p>*Newborn infants, especially those born prematurely, require special pain treatment, and adequate relief is necessary for medical and ethical reasons.  Recent studies do not support the belief that painkillers dangerously depress infant breathing.</p>
        <p>*Relaxation techniques such as breathing exercises, as well as such nondrug methods as applying heat, cold or massage can help decrease postoperative pain.</p>
        <p>*Patients, particularly the elderly who may have misguided ideas about stoicly enduring it, should be encouraged to report pain.</p>
        <p>*People with well-controlled pain, such as those who self-medicate through metered intravenous infusion pumps, tend to be discharged earlier and may suffer fewer chronic pain problems later.</p>
        <p>The Health and Human Services Department said the guidelines would be distributed to doctors, nurses, professional medical societies, health care schools, insurers and consumer groups. An abbreviated version for patients, now in English and soon in Spanish, will also be available.</p>
        <p>The entire practice guide for professionals, quick reference guides for pain management in adults or children, and the patient guide are available without cost from the AHCPR Publications Clearinghouse, P.O. Box 8547, Silver Spring, Md. 20907, or by calling a toll-free telephone number, 800-358-9295.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
