<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqi Leader Sees Arabs' Meeting As a Spur for His Regional</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BAGHDAD (IRAQ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUSSEIN, SADDAM (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D81030F93BA15756C0A966958260" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqi Leader Sees Arabs' Meeting As a Spur for His Regional</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: On the broad highway at Baghdad's approaches, a sculpture depicts two monumental hands holding aloft crossed swords in soaring, heroic splendor. The swords symbolize the victory that Iraq says it won in the war with Iran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: On the broad highway at Baghdad's approaches, a sculpture depicts two monumental hands holding aloft crossed swords in soaring, heroic splendor. The swords symbolize the victory that Iraq says it won in the war with Iran.</p>
        <p>On the broad highway at Baghdad's approaches, a sculpture depicts two monumental hands holding aloft crossed swords in soaring, heroic splendor. The swords symbolize the victory that Iraq says it won in the war with Iran.</p>
        <p>The sculpture was shaped from moldings taken, according to diplomats here, of President Saddam Hussein's hands.</p>
        <p>The message, reflecting a personality cult that has sustained 12 years of autocratic rule, is that the Iraqi leader delivered not only his own nation but also the entire Arab world during the eight years of conflict with Iran, which ended in a cease-fire in August 1988.</p>
        <p>Leaders Gather in Baghdad</p>
        <p>But as Arab leaders - kings, presidents and emirs - arrived here today for an emergency meeting starting tomorrow, the supposition among Western and Arab diplomats was that President Hussein was seeking to turn his battle against the Iranians into an acknowledged role as a leader and forceful spokesman of the Arabs.</p>
        <p>With his one-million-strong army still largely deployed on the Iranian front, and his oratory increasingly anti-American and anti-Israeli, the question that preoccupies some delegates and diplomats in this hot city on the Tigris River is: How will he achieve that?</p>
        <p>The answer, for some, is that the Iraqi leader - long perceived by Arab and Western outsiders as bellicose and harsh in both language and action -will use the gathering as a platform to remold the image of his regime.</p>
        <p>If the tactics succeed, Western diplomats contend, President Hussein will broaden his range: The warrior will become the warrior statesman.</p>
        <p>Image Could Be Bolstered</p>
        <p>''If he comes out of this with a well-run summit and resolutions that make some sense, he'll come out with his reputation more enhanced,'' a Western envoy said.</p>
        <p>At the very least, Arab and Western diplomats said, the Iraqi leader will mark out a constituency, making himself the spokesman of those Arabs who have become increasingly frustrated with the inability of the United States, Egyptians and Palestinians to draw Israel into talks on the status of the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>The summit talks, promoted by President Hussein and the Palestine Liberation Organization's chairman, Yasir Arafat, have been called with two principal aims: to register Arab concern at the implications of large scale Soviet Jewish immigration to Israel and to support the Iraqi leader in his contest with the West over effort to acquire advanced weaponry.</p>
        <p>Concern on Occupied Lands</p>
        <p>Arab nations, and the P.L.O. in particular, are concerned that Israel will settle some of the tens of thousands of Soviet Jews in the occupied lands.</p>
        <p>As a comprehensive expression of Arab sentiment, the Baghdad gathering could well prove to be imperfect because Syria's President, Hafez al-Assad - the most militant of Arab leaders sharing a border with Israel -has not so far agreed to attend.</p>
        <p>Syria and Iraq are the Arab world's most bitter adversaries - divided by personality conflicts and ideological disputes between their leaders and by recent memories of Syria's support for Iran in the war with Iraq.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, as Arab foreign ministers prepared for the meeting, some strands of thought became clear.</p>
        <p>During the course of last week, Iraq publicized details of what Western diplomats said was a leaked American State Department briefing paper, circulated to American embassies in the Arab world. The document urged the nations at the conference to avoid inflammatory rhetoric and said the United States would not take the gathering seriously if it engaged in specific attacks on Washington.</p>
        <p>The purported document incensed delegates, Arab diplomats said.</p>
        <p>Yet, allies of the United States, notably Egypt and Saudi Arabia, obtained a commitment from the Arab foreign ministers - not binding on the summit meeting - to avoid naming specific countries in their resolutions.</p>
        <p>Aimed at Bush and Gorbachev</p>
        <p>The resolutions are supposed to offer a summary of Arab thinking to be considered this week by President Bush and President Mikhail S. Gorbachev of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the foreign ministers agreed to support demands for Arab rights to acquire advanced technololgy. The resolution supports Iraq's protests over recent United States and British actions to prevent the shipment of nuclear triggers and components for a cannon capable of firing rocket-boosted shells over long distances.</p>
        <p>The ministers, however, failed to agree on an Egyptian proposal that the Middle East be declared an area free of weapons of mass destruction. This idea was aimed as much at Israel's nuclear capability as at Iraq's stockpiling and development of advanced chemical weapons.</p>
        <p>The easiest issue for the leaders, and one of the most emotional, is Soviet Jewish resettlement in Israel. This is the issue that persuaded Mr. Arafat to press for the talks. According to Palestian officials, the P.L.O. leader helped persuade some reluctant Arab leaders to attend a conference to back Iraq in return for support against Soviet Jewish immigration.</p>
        <p>Conciliatory Gestures</p>
        <p>As he maneuvered in advance of the gathering, President Hussein sent signals to various adversaries, seemingly to promote a new image. He sent a senior official to Damascus to present an invitation to President Assad. And he offered face-to-face talks with President Hashemi Rafsanjani of Iran.</p>
        <p>''They can either reject him and look silly or accept him and look small,'' a Western diplomat said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, the Iraqi leader has been strongly critical of the United States - his leading trading partner - and has said that if Israel attacks his country with nuclear weapons he will respond by destroying half of Israel with poison gas. The statements drew widespread support in the Arab world for a figure perceived as ready and able to stand up to Israel.</p>
        <p>''Saddam Hussein has been very skillful in finding a gap in Arab politics,'' a Western diplomat said. ''There is terrific frustration and he stepped in and reaped the fruits.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
