<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weicker as an Independent: Low-Key, Out in Front</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="357123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVO, NICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEICKER, LOWELL P JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROWLAND, JOHN G (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRISON, BRUCE A (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DF1639F93BA15756C0A966958260" item-length="1398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weicker as an Independent: Low-Key, Out in Front</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK RAVO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVO, NICK</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gone is the big white Winnebago-like bus covered with campaign banners. So is the endless entourage wearing ''Nobody's Man But Yours'' T-shirts. Even the trademark jar-grippers that Lowell P. Weicker Jr. passed out across Connecticut during his four Senate races have disappeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gone is the big white Winnebago-like bus covered with campaign banners. So is the endless entourage wearing ''Nobody's Man But Yours'' T-shirts. Even the trademark jar-grippers that Lowell P. Weicker Jr. passed out across Connecticut during his four Senate races have disappeared.</p>
        <p>Gone is the big white Winnebago-like bus covered with campaign banners. So is the endless entourage wearing ''Nobody's Man But Yours'' T-shirts. Even the trademark jar-grippers that Lowell P. Weicker Jr. passed out across Connecticut during his four Senate races have disappeared.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. Weicker's campaign - a surprisingly credible independent bid for governor - is being propelled by a sedate Dodge minivan marked with the name of his new political affiliation, A Connecticut Party, and the state's understated unofficial symbol, the Charter Oak.</p>
        <p>''The jar-grippers we can't use because they all say Senate on them,'' Mr. Weicker said last week, while decompressing between campaign stops with a bourbon on the rocks in the dark and comfortable environs of the Quinnipiack Club.</p>
        <p>The cosmetic differences between Mr. Weicker's current campaign and those of the past are emblematic of personal change in the bumptious and bombastic former Senator, who relished his role as a liberal and a loner in the Republican Party.</p>
        <p>This, say his aides, is ''the new Weicker'' or ''a laid-back Weicker.'' Some even call him ''the humble Weicker,'' citing his narrow defeat in the 1988 Senate race by Joseph I. Lieberman, then the Attorney General.</p>
        <p>''I think being free of the shackles of Republican dogma and being free to express my feelings makes a big difference,'' Mr. Weicker said of his more low-key style.</p>
        <p>This is also, at least this early in the campaign, an astoundingly successful Weicker. A poll conducted by the University of Connecticut in mid-May and released by The Hartford Courant last week showed him with a substantial lead over both the Republican front-runner, Representative John G. Rowland of Waterbury, and the front-running Democrat, Representative Bruce A. Morrison of Hamden. The survey of more than 500 randomly selected residents, which has a margin of error of 5 percent, gave 41 percent of the vote to Mr. Weicker, 14 percent to Mr. Rowland and 9 percent to Mr. Morrison.</p>
        <p>''We are all very interested and very impressed,'' said James W. Dull, a former journalist who once covered Mr. Weicker and is now the chairman of the political science department at the University of New Haven. ''It is audacious that he is taking on both political parties without a base to try to become governor.''</p>
        <p>Charles E. Cook Jr., editor of The Cook Political Report, a newsletter published in Washington, said: ''The conventional wisdom remains that Weicker is a solid favorite.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weicker's lead appears to be based mostly on his high name recognition and his long-standing popularity in the state: he served in Congress from 1969 to 1989 and is the only Republican to win statewide office since 1970.</p>
        <p>His supporters have also detected a large degree of sympathy for Mr. Weicker after his upset loss to Mr. Lieberman. They note, too, a high level of overall voter discontent.</p>
        <p>Votes From Both Parties</p>
        <p>''People are generally dissatisfied with the two political parties,'' said Thomas J. D'Amore Jr., a former state Republican chairman who is Mr. Weicker's campaign manager. ''They say the parties don't work or they're exclusive little clubs.''</p>
        <p>Both major political parties stand to lose votes to Mr. Weicker, a Greenwich resident and heir to the Squibb pharmaceutical fortune who has remained a registered Republican.</p>
        <p>In the past, Mr. Weicker, who still receives praise for his role on the Senate Select Watergate Committee 17 years ago, has attracted wide support among Democrats and independents, as well as among liberal and moderate Republicans. The state has about 660,000 registered Democrats, 450,000 Republicans and 550,000 unaffiliated voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weicker's decision to run as an independent came after Republican leaders, long irritated by his liberal positions, showed no interest in reviving his political career.</p>
        <p>Richard Foley, the Republican state chairman, said he was ''not terribly worried'' about the polls because it is so early. Mr. Morrison's campaign manager, Thayer Baldwin, said he did not expect the polls to change significantly until Labor Day.</p>
        <p>'Cult of Personality'</p>
        <p>Officials in both parties have also dismissed Mr. Weicker's current popularity as a ''cult of personality'' or ''celebrity status.'' Few Rowland or Morrison backers, however, foresee Mr. Weicker's candidacy fading completely, as many third-party bids do as the election nears.</p>
        <p>''He's a strong enough candidate to maintain a significant presence in the campaign,'' Mr. Baldwin said.</p>
        <p>Independents or third-party candidates have rarely won election as governors in this century. Excluding territorial elections, only three have done it since 1930. The last independent to win a governorship was James B. Longley of Maine, a little-known insurance executive who defeated a Democrat and Republican in 1974, a year when voter discontent with politics soared because of the Watergate scandal and the resignation of President Nixon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook said that ''anti-politician'' attitudes are prevalent nationally this year. But he called the current trend unusual because, unlike attitudes in 1974, it seems to be mainly an anti-Congress feeling directed equally at both parties. Citing several recent scandals and the Congressional pay-raise issue, he said the parties are being viewed increasingly as mechanisms for getting and keeping personal power.</p>
        <p>Climbing Up the Ballot</p>
        <p>''There is a growing cynicism out there,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Weicker has run into few technical difficulties with his independent candidacy. By April, he had received commitments from about 1,000 volunteers and had collected the 9,937 signatures needed to be on the ballot. He also announced that his candidacy would be called ''A Connecticut Party'' to meet a state requirement that any independent bid have a name. The name Independent Party had been taken by a small political group in the state. The article ''A'' was used to secure the place on the ballot directly below the Democratic and Republican candidates.</p>
        <p>''This really is a grass-roots effort,'' Mr. D'Amore said. ''It has to be, out of necessity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weicker, who is 59 years old, has insisted that he is running to win, not as a Quixotic quest or as possible revenge against Republicans who abandoned him in his failed re-election bid.</p>
        <p>He has raised about $300,000 for his campaign and expects to raise about $2 million. He has been endorsed by a prominent Republican, the State Senate Minority Leader, Reginald J. Smith of New Hartford, and two lesser known lawmakers, State Senator Emil V. Benvenuto, Republican of Greenwich, and Representative Edith G. Prague, Democrat of Columbia.</p>
        <p>Decision on Running Mates</p>
        <p>He has also contacted numerous state leaders, including a female Republican, First Selectwoman Jacqueline Durrell of Fairfield, and two black Democrats, Mayor Carrie Saxon Perry of Hartford and State Senator Bruce L. Morris of New Haven, about serving as his running mate for lieutenant governor. He expects to make a decision within the next 10 days.</p>
        <p>''With the possible exception of Chris Dodd, I don't think anyone else in the state could do something like this,'' Mr. Dull said.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amore said building an independent candidacy had been easier than expected. He also said Mr. Weicker's name recognition and the extensive news media coverage he receives partially offsets any difference in campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>''Our need for dollars is less because we have something they don't have,'' Mr. D'Amore said of Mr. Morrison and Mr. Rowland. ''Nobody knows who they are.''</p>
        <p>Although the state's declining fiscal health will likely become the dominant issue of the campaign, no candidate has presented any specific remedies or discussed in detail how they would change state government. Mr. Weicker, like Mr. Morrison, has said that he would not rule out a state income tax. Mr. Rowland opposes such a tax. Mr. Weicker, however, has been aggressive in his remarks about his opponents, particularly Mr. Rowland, a conservative whom the former Senator has called a ''flip-flop artist'' on the abortion issue. Mr. Rowland became a supporter of abortion rights last year.</p>
        <p>He also took a backhanded swipe at the youth of Mr. Rowland, who is 33 years old. ''I don't think John Rowland is too young,'' Mr. Weicker said. ''I think John Rowland is too devoid of substance to be governor.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
