<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rheingold Returns With a Family Link</title>
    <meta content="RHEIN.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1014213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rheingold Brewing Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitaro, Michael H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebman, Walter H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DA143EF930A35756C0A96E958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rheingold Returns With a Family Link</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on revival of Rheingold Brewing Co by new owner Michael H Mitaro and Walter H Liebman, whose family once owned original brewery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WALTER H. LIEBMAN had let go of his dream by the time the phone rang last September. Mr. Liebman, head of public affairs at Purchase College, had long hoped to revive his family's beer company, Rheingold, but the idea grew dimmer each year. Then he heard Michael H. Mitaro's voice, and the dream blazed anew. Mr. Mitaro, a former executive with Labatt U.S.A., introduced himself as the new owner of Rheingold, which had languished since 1976. The beer that once filled more glasses in New York than any other could be No. 1 again, Mr. Mitaro said. The time was right. Nostalgia was in. Moreover, the microbrewery madness was over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitaro, 43, had acquired Rheingold's trademark through a licensing agreement with its most recent owner, the Stroh Brewing Company. He and Mr. Liebman, 67, known as Terry, formed the new Rheingold Brewing Company, opened an office here and recently held a news conference at Gallagher's Steak House in Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WALTER H. LIEBMAN had let go of his dream by the time the phone rang last September. Mr. Liebman, head of public affairs at Purchase College, had long hoped to revive his family's beer company, Rheingold, but the idea grew dimmer each year. Then he heard Michael H. Mitaro's voice, and the dream blazed anew. Mr. Mitaro, a former executive with Labatt U.S.A., introduced himself as the new owner of Rheingold, which had languished since 1976. The beer that once filled more glasses in New York than any other could be No. 1 again, Mr. Mitaro said. The time was right. Nostalgia was in. Moreover, the microbrewery madness was over.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitaro, 43, had acquired Rheingold's trademark through a licensing agreement with its most recent owner, the Stroh Brewing Company. He and Mr. Liebman, 67, known as Terry, formed the new Rheingold Brewing Company, opened an office here and recently held a news conference at Gallagher's Steak House in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Introducing three former Miss Rheingolds, winners of the contest that riveted popular attention on the company in the 1950's and early 60's, Mr. Mitaro tapped into the current revival craze. ''Why bring back Rheingold?'' he asked. ''Why are they restoring Grand Central? Why the redevelopment of Times Square? Rheingold brings back all the deep, heartfelt memories of New York.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitaro, the company's president, said he remembers the beer well, having reached legal drinking age just before national brewers like Anheuser-Busch, Schlitz and Miller drove regional operations like Rheingold out of the market. Calling the beer ''the gem of the old brands,'' he said, ''it fell fast in the 1970's, but its image never got tarnished.''</p>
        <p>Rheingold sold a yearly 50 million cases of its extra dry lager at the company's height in the 1960's, and the brand accounted for one out of every three beers sold around New York City. Mr. Liebman, a descendant of Samuel Liebmann, the German immigrant who founded the brewery in 1837, worked there from 1955 until 1961, eventually becoming assistant vice president and merchandising director.</p>
        <p>He oversaw the Miss Rheingold contest -- which was established by Phillip Liebmann, his cousin and boss -- arranging for ballot boxes in bars, restaurants and grocery stores and supervising the annual election. The popular contest drew 25 million ballots each year, all of which were hand counted, Mr. Liebman said. Voters chose from five candidates, professional models who embodied an all-American wholesomeness. Posters of the winners showed Miss Rheingold bowling, gardening or skiing, wearing sporty clothes and a sparkling, straightforward smile.</p>
        <p>Then there was the jingle. Borrowed from a waltz by Emil Waldteufel, a French composer born the year Samuel Liebmann founded his brewery, the lilting melody became nearly ubiquitous. The jingle -- ''My beer is Rheingold, the dry beer. Think of Rheingold whenever you buy beer'' -- has been brought back intact, along with the identical red, white and black label of the old days.</p>
        <p>''It harkens back to a simpler time,'' Mr. Mitaro said. He said the company plans to woo the younger generation with a ''back to basics'' theme, now that the infatuation with microbreweries has died down. ''There's little brand loyalty,'' he said. ''People are looking for a new beer to call their own.''</p>
        <p>At the news conference, Mr. Mitaro introduced Dr. Joseph Owades, a former Rheingold brewmaster who is estimated to have brewed more than 500 million cases of the beer. Dr. Owades will resurrect the original Rheingold formula, which will be brewed in Utica. Other beers on Dr. Owades's long resume include Gablinger's, a low-calorie beer that later became Miller Lite, Tuborg and New Amsterdam. As an independent consultant, he developed Samuel Adams.</p>
        <p>Another major element in Rheingold's success was its sponsorship of the New York Mets The company will once again sponsor the team, serving as the exclusive domestic beer sponsor of all Mets radio broadcasts on WFAN (660 AM) this season. Two promotions will be held at Shea Stadium:  Rheingold beach towels will be given out on July 18, and on July 31 each of four randomly picked contestants will have the chance to win $1 million by throwing three consecutive strikes from the pitcher's mound. ''We want someone to win,'' Mr. Mitaro said.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, amid the nostalgia and toasts, the three former Miss Rheingolds stood in the strobe lights at Gallagher's and relived the glory days, when their faces were familiar to millions through billboards and other advertising.  Anne Hogan Davis, Miss Rheingold 1952, is now the mother of 6 and the grandmother of 10 who lives in Purchase. Her poster shows her waving from a ski lift, poles draped casually across her lap. That picture, she said, took two weeks to shoot, a far cry from her usual modeling work. ''I was used to moving fast,'' she said.  ''With this, you smiled for five hours.''</p>
        <p>She recalled Rheingold as a gracious company, which gave her a baby carriage when her first child was born. Single and 21 when she won the contest, she said the money was the best part: $10,000 in one lump sum. She questioned whether the contest would be viable today, not because attitudes toward women have changed but because of the expense involved. Mr. Mitaro, however, said the company planned to revive the Miss Rheingold competition in some form, possibly next year.</p>
        <p>The partners have set out to make Rheingold a strong regional beer, pricing it about 50 cents higher for a six pack than Budweiser beer, an Anheuser-Busch brand. The higher price is meant to avoid pricing wars and to distinguish Rheingold from other beers.</p>
        <p>Speaking in his office here, Mr. Liebman said he would remain at Purchase through June and then help the new company as its managing director. ''This is like a time warp,'' he said. ''I'm thrilled.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
