<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="03MSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1014463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D6113EF930A35756C0A96E958260" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-20</p>
        <p>European Nations Accept Currency Despite Snag  Eleven European nations approved a plan to begin a common currency, and after bitter disagreements selected Wim F. Duisenberg of the Netherlands as president of the new European central bank for half of the eight-year term, when he will be succeeded by a French banker. 1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-20</p>
        <p>European Nations Accept Currency Despite Snag  Eleven European nations approved a plan to begin a common currency, and after bitter disagreements selected Wim F. Duisenberg of the Netherlands as president of the new European central bank for half of the eight-year term, when he will be succeeded by a French banker. 1</p>
        <p>Peace a Tough Sell in Dublin  In contrast to Northern Ireland, every major party in the Irish Republic supports the peace agreement. Now the trick is to turn out the vote. That is a surprisingly daunting challenge, and backers are commissioning polls, enlisting celebrities, and using focus groups. 1</p>
        <p>Fears Grow in Georgia  Politicians in Georgia have concluded that Russia is determined, by whatever means, not to allow the country to slip out of its orbit. 20</p>
        <p>Myanmar Has Addicts, Too  Myanmar, the world's foremost exporter of opium, has developed its own domestic heroin habit, and now has the world's highest rate of H.I.V. infection and AIDS contracted from dirty needles. 9</p>
        <p>Clinton Reversal on Mines  Having rebuffed a treaty banning land mines, the Clinton Administration is now scrambling to repeal a one-year moratorium on the use of antipersonnel mines. Military commanders never supported the law in the first place. 4</p>
        <p>Uruguay Welfare State Tested  Uruguay's welfare state is resistant to the market forces sweeping through Argentina, Brazil and much of Latin America. But a fight is brewing over a plan to let private companies generate electricity. 3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL 26-42</p>
        <p>Air Safety Board Taking Longer On Investigations  The National Transportation Safety Board is taking twice as long to investigate plane crashes as it did five years ago, primarily because of the efforts it is still devoting to the daunting mysteries of the crashes of T.W.A. Flight 800 and a USAir flight near Pittsburgh. 36</p>
        <p>Cancer Drugs Raise Hopes  Two new drugs that can eradicate any type of cancer, with no obvious side effects and no drug resistance have been successful -- in mice. Some cancer researchers say the drugs are the most exciting treatment that they have ever seen. But they temper their enthusiasm with caution. 1</p>
        <p>Reno Aide Urged Counsel  The Justice Department's top prosecutor for campaign-finance abuses told Republican Senators that he had urged the Attorney General to seek an independent prosecutor to investigate President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore, but was rebuffed by Ms. Reno and other advisers, law enforcement-officials said. 1</p>
        <p>Spain in West, 400 Years  On April 30, 1598, Don Juan Onate and 500 colonists from Mexico crossed the Rio Grande at El Paso and embarked on a journey that ultimately established the first European settlements in the American West, predating the first permanent English settlement in the present United States, Jamestown in Virginia, by almost a decade. 26</p>
        <p>Gingrich on The Attack  Speaker Newt Gingrich invoked comparisons between President Clinton's actions in office and the forces that led the Roman republic toward ruin. 30</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION 43-51</p>
        <p>The $66 Million Fugitive  In February, BankBoston realized that $66 million had been fraudulently lent out of its New York office. That same month, one of its bankers, Ricardo S. Carrasco, disappeared, and so did the money. A native of Uruguay with ties to many foreign clients, the authorities admit that, even with the Federal Bureau of Investigation chasing him, Mr. Carrasco could be almost anywhere. 43</p>
        <p>The Fresh Air Fund  For 122 years, the Fresh Air Fund has been sending poor urban children to camp or to families living in the country. This year, it will enable 3,000 children to attend camp and 7,000 to stay with families in about 300 rural towns, from Virginia to Maine and southern Ontario, Canada. 43</p>
        <p>Tobacco's Deep Pockets  Facing immense legislative stakes and suffering from a battered public image, the tobacco industry has rained contributions on almost every incumbent in Congress, dispensing special largesse to proven allies while still giving generously to occasional adversaries, according to a study of donations given to members of Congress from the Metropolitan area commissioned by The New York Times. 46</p>
        <p>Backlash on Budget  Gov. George E. Pataki's vetoes on more than $1.5 billion in state spending have angered people in depressed upstate cities like Niagara Falls, where many community programs rely almost entirely on state aid. Even politically conservative residents are livid, saying the vetoes will lead many to vote against Mr. Pataki this fall. 43</p>
        <p>Broadway's No. 1 Fan  The talk-show host Rosie O'Donnell has become to Broadway what Oprah Winfrey is to books: a big-time celebrity with a hit television show and a largely female following who has made it her mission to breathe new life into a corner of American culture that badly needs help. 1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES 52-53</p>
        <p>Rev. Frederic Gehring  The World War II Navy chaplain who was known as the Padre of Guadalcanal was 95. He plunged into jungle combat with the First Marine Division in 1942 and came out with a battle-scarred little Chinese girl who became an inspiring symbol of hope at a time of national despair. 53</p>
        <p>Maria Torok  A psychoanalyst in France whose rejection of Freud's ideas was welcomed in feminist circles, she  was 72. 53</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote 51  Weather 51  TV Update 52</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
