<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's All a Matter of Balance</title>
    <meta content="07TVKIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="55" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1540919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gustines, George Gene</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Xiaolin Showdown (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DF103AF934A35751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's All a Matter of Balance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George Gene Gustines</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gustines, George Gene</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Xiaolin Showdown is animated children's series that incorporates history of Shaolin temple, said to be birthplace of kung-fu; characters are on quest for sacred objects and must race through mystical obstacle courses; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE teachings of an ancient order of monks are at the heart of ''Xiaolin Showdown,'' an animated series that had its premiere last month as part of the Kids WB programming block on Channel 11.</p>
        <p>Shown on Saturday mornings at 9:30, ''Xiaolin Showdown'' incorporates the history of the Shaolin Temple, said to be the birthplace of kung-fu. In the series, Omi, a young monk, is joined by three travelers as he searches for the Shen Gong Wu, a collection of sacred objects. Jack Spicer, an evil boy genius, and Wuya, an ancient witch, are also seeking the objects. When a member of each side gets to one of the Shen Gong Wu simultaneously, they must race through a mystical obstacle course to win it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE teachings of an ancient order of monks are at the heart of ''Xiaolin Showdown,'' an animated series that had its premiere last month as part of the Kids WB programming block on Channel 11.</p>
        <p>Shown on Saturday mornings at 9:30, ''Xiaolin Showdown'' incorporates the history of the Shaolin Temple, said to be the birthplace of kung-fu. In the series, Omi, a young monk, is joined by three travelers as he searches for the Shen Gong Wu, a collection of sacred objects. Jack Spicer, an evil boy genius, and Wuya, an ancient witch, are also seeking the objects. When a member of each side gets to one of the Shen Gong Wu simultaneously, they must race through a mystical obstacle course to win it.</p>
        <p>''I grew up with the whole martial arts genre of entertainment,'' said Christy Hui, the creator and a producer of the series. ''In America, kids read comic books. In Asia, we read martial arts novels,''</p>
        <p>''I also have a thing about Shaolin monks,'' said Ms. Hui, who was born in Canton, China, and moved to the United States in the late 1970's. ''They have a code of ethics that are really great principles in life. Shaolin monks are very highly regarded. They have integrity. They are honorable people. It's their code that draws me to the whole Shaolin monk warrior clan.''</p>
        <p>The collected wisdom of the monks shapes the character of Master Fung, the head of the Xiaolin Temple and mentor to the four adventurers.</p>
        <p>One of the great things about martial arts, said Ms. Hui, is that it is ''the teaching of body, mind and spirit.''</p>
        <p>''It's about balancing all of that within oneself,'' she continued. ''That's what Master Fung teaches to all the kids: it's the balance.''</p>
        <p>As the series progresses, the need for that balance becomes evident in the personality and abilities of each team member.</p>
        <p>Omi (front, above and below), who is traveling outside the temple for the very first time, has an elemental link to water: normally as tranquil as a pond, he becomes a raging tsunami in battle. Kimiko, the quartet's only girl, keeps up on the latest trends and high-tech gadgets and is very protective of Omi. Her element is fire and she is quick to anger. Clay, a cowboy represented by the earth, is incredibly trustworthy. While his teammates think he's slow to react, he simply believes in thorough analysis. And Raimundo is linked to the wind. Although loyal to the team, he has a devil-may-care attitude, and Omi is a frequent target of his jokes.</p>
        <p>Humor is also supplied by Dojo, a 1,500-year-old, fire-breathing, shape-changing dragon who, like a divining rod, can sense the location of the Shen Gong Wu.</p>
        <p>''There's a kind of comedy that when it's done right -- no matter where you're from -- people will find funny,'' said Ms. Hui.</p>
        <p>In one episode, Omi visits Clay's ranch. (''Just imagine this kid trying to milk a cow,'' said Ms. Hui.) Then there's the trip to New York, where a showdown takes place on a basketball court in an episode titled -- what else? -- ''Omi, My Homey.''</p>
        <p>George Gene Gustines</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
