<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liggett's Tobacco Settlement In Danger of Coming Undone</title>
    <meta content="07CIGS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="875673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Class-Action Suits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Liggett Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Liability for Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DE143BF934A3575AC0A960958260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liggett's Tobacco Settlement In Danger of Coming Undone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Liggett Group, which stunned and infuriated its larger rivals in tobacco industry in March by agreeing to settle lawsuits, is negotiating to avoid being dragged back into the litigation; Liggett's initial settlement agreements have already resulted in first damage payments ever by a tobacco company--$1 million to five of the states that sued the industry seeking compensation for smoking-related health care expenditures (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Liggett Group, which stunned and infuriated its larger rivals in the tobacco industry in March by agreeing to settle lawsuits that involved all the companies, is negotiating to avoid being dragged back into the litigation, lawyers involved in the talks say.</p>
        <p>Liggett's initial settlement agreements have already resulted in the first damage payments ever by a tobacco company -- $1 million to five of the states that sued the industry seeking compensation for smoking-related health care expenditures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Liggett Group, which stunned and infuriated its larger rivals in the tobacco industry in March by agreeing to settle lawsuits that involved all the companies, is negotiating to avoid being dragged back into the litigation, lawyers involved in the talks say.</p>
        <p>Liggett's initial settlement agreements have already resulted in the first damage payments ever by a tobacco company -- $1 million to five of the states that sued the industry seeking compensation for smoking-related health care expenditures.</p>
        <p>But neither the agreement with the states nor the second settlement with lawyers who filed a class action on behalf of smokers nationwide won final court approval. The future of both is now unclear.</p>
        <p>At the time of the settlements in March, Bennett S. LeBow, chairman of Liggett's parent, the Brooke Group, argued that they opened a new path for the industry to begin putting tobacco litigation behind it. He hoped the settlements would attract support from shareholders of RJR Nabisco, the parent of R. J. Reynolds Tobacco, the nation's second-largest tobacco company after Philip Morris. Mr. LeBow was seeking control of RJR to force the immediate spinoff of its Nabisco food business and the eventual merger of its highly profitable tobacco operations with the struggling Liggett, and the settlement terms included provisions for bringing RJR into the deals.</p>
        <p>But the strategy backfired. RJR shareholders sided with management, which said the settlement would be too expensive for RJR and was riddled with loopholes that could attract more lawsuits. The class action settlement, for example, covered only lawsuits based on a theory that cigarettes are addictive.</p>
        <p>''The concept of a settlement was fine, but it has to be more comprehensive,'' said Gary Black of Sanford Bernstein. ''They only took out 2 percent of the ways you could sue the industry.''</p>
        <p>Since then, the outlook has become especially murky for the class action settlement, which would have required Liggett to pay up to $50 million over 25 years toward smoking cessation programs. That agreement was based on the assumption that a Mississippi lawsuit called Castano would be approved as a national class action lawsuit. But the Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit agreed with the industry in May that there was no national class of smokers, making it uncertain whether the Castano lawyers could settle on behalf of anyone except the Castano family.</p>
        <p>Liggett and the plaintiffs' lawyers are now exploring two strategies, according to people familiar with the talks. One involves asking the courts overseeing Castano to rule that even where there are too many differences among smokers to treat them as a group in a trial, they can be regarded as a class in a voluntary settlement. The simpler approach, lawyers say, might be to file a new class action lawsuit in another state against Liggett alone.</p>
        <p>Mr. LeBow declined to characterize the talks but said: ''We intend to settle this as a class action in some jurisdiction. As of right now, the terms are the same, word for word.''</p>
        <p>Liggett also intends to pursue its agreement with the states; that agreement requires it to pay between 2 percent and 7 percent of pretax income for 24 years to the settling states in addition to its initial payments to the five original states: Florida, Massachusetts, Mississippi, West Virginia and Louisiana.</p>
        <p>The settlement allows Liggett to withdraw if too few other states join in. So far, none have, although people familiar with the situation say several states have been talking about joining in the next few weeks. Mr. LeBow suggested that the company might be willing to make modest payments beyond those required in the agreement to encourage them, the equivalent of a signing bonus for an athlete or executive.</p>
        <p>''Liggett just can't afford a scorched-earth litigation policy,'' Mr. LeBow said. ''One major judgment against Liggett would put us out of business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. LeBow added that he thought that his wealthier rivals were underestimating the risks of litigating every case instead of seeking global settlements. Philip Morris and RJR both declined to comment on Liggett's continuing settlement efforts.</p>
        <p>One settlement Liggett cannot afford is the recently floated proposal for a deal in which Congress would impose a settlement on the entire industry. While no such deal is anywhere near being struck, the outlines of the initial proposals made known late last month would require payments based on market share rather than on profits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
