<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Military Police Begin Patrolling Streets</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713894"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="MISSION TO HAITI: IN HAITI"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAITI-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CEDRAS, RAOUL (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, MICHAEL (COL)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHELTON, HENRY M (LT GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANCOIS, MICHEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KIFNER, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E7DA153AF937A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Military Police Begin Patrolling Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KIFNER, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti, Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American military police began their first road patrols in the Haitian capital today, as their commander worked on a plan to station M.P.'s in local police precincts.</p>
        <p>Col. Michael Sullivan, commander of the 16th Military Police Brigade, met for a second time today with the Haitian police commander, Lieut. Col. Michel Francois, who is widely held responsible for much of the violence that the Haitian police and military have inflicted on the population over the past three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American military police began their first road patrols in the Haitian capital today, as their commander worked on a plan to station M.P.'s in local police precincts.</p>
        <p>Col. Michael Sullivan, commander of the 16th Military Police Brigade, met for a second time today with the Haitian police commander, Lieut. Col. Michel Francois, who is widely held responsible for much of the violence that the Haitian police and military have inflicted on the population over the past three years.</p>
        <p>Perhaps even more important in the web of terror that has held Haiti in thrall, he is said to be a major force in arming and financing the attaches, the civilian gunmen who enforce the military government's will .</p>
        <p>Although American officials here are currently concentrating their efforts on the uniformed, official forces that have been agents of repression, the "attaches" and other unofficial groups were given thousands of new M-16 rifles, Uzi machine-guns and other weapons in the period before the Americans arrived. They have melted away, presumably lying in wait to reassert their grip on power when an opportunity arises.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, Colonel Sullivan described his meetings as "courteous, professional, quite cordial." He said he and his officers had held two additional meetings with Haitian police officials.</p>
        <p>American military policemen are to be stationed in 6 to 10 police precincts around the capital, perhaps as early as next week. Presumably, they are to monitor the performance of the Haitian police, which has hitherto largely consisted of taking bribes and beating people.</p>
        <p>Colonel Sullivan's brigade currently has about 500 M.P., and as the American buildup continues, is expected to grow to about 1,000. The former New York City Police Commissioner, Raymond Kelly, is a leading candidate to direct training of the Haitian police under a civilian Government, White House officials said this week.</p>
        <p>One goal of the American effort would be to professionalize the police force to create civil order that would allow the exiled President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, to return, form a functioning Government and hold new elections.</p>
        <p>Although American officials here constantly talk in terms of "restoring" democracy, there has been precious little democracy in Haiti's history. And, indeed, the dictatorship throughout most of this century has been largely enforced by a military created by an earlier American intervention, that of the U.S. Marines in 1915.</p>
        <p>Colonel Francois is part of the ruling triumvirate of officers -- the others are the army commander, Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras and his Chief of Staff, Brig. Gen. Philippe Biamby -- that the United States military intervention was designed to oust.</p>
        <p>But, under the terms of the last-minute agreement worked out by former President Jimmy Carter, the American military has entered into an uneasy partnership with the three men on the presumption that they will leave office after being given amnesty by the Parliament, or no later than Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>Lieut. Gen. Hugh Shelton of the XVIII Airborne Corps, the overall American commander on the ground, summoned General Cedras this morning to General Shelton's new headquarters in a tightly guarded industrial park by the airport.  The airport is now bristling with a massive display of American troops and equipment, including water purification trucks, huge electrical generators, portable pontoon bridges, shallow-draft river boats and vehicles on which an intimidating array of weaponry is mounted.</p>
        <p>As the supplies poured in, American soldiers and convoys became more and more evident on the streets of the capital, shuttling equipment between the airport and their other bases at the port.</p>
        <p>The military police, in their dark-green Humvee all-terrain vehicles, began their first road patrols from the southeast corner of the airport, an uneventful run to show their presence and assess the immediate neighborhood.  MISSION TO HAITI: IN HAITI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
