<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Belfast Journal; When It Comes to Peace, You Spell It B-I-N-G-O</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BINGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE STYLES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHERN IRELAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BELFAST (NORTHERN IRELAND)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">IRISH REPUBLICAN ARMY (IRA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARITY, JAMES F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland/Belfast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life Styles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3DA153AF937A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Belfast Journal; When It Comes to Peace, You Spell It B-I-N-G-O</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES F. CLARITY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLARITY, JAMES F</byline>
      <dateline>BELFAST, Northern Ireland, Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three weeks after the start of the Irish Republican Army cease-fire, the signs of peace in Belfast are as easy to find as the New Vic Bingo Hall downtown.</p>
        <p>Vera Gormley, who sells betting cards there, says the cease-fire is encouraging more and more people to come into the bingo hall at night to try their luck now that it seems unlikely that I.R.A. bombs will still be exploding from time to time next door at the Grand Opera House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three weeks after the start of the Irish Republican Army cease-fire, the signs of peace in Belfast are as easy to find as the New Vic Bingo Hall downtown.</p>
        <p>Vera Gormley, who sells betting cards there, says the cease-fire is encouraging more and more people to come into the bingo hall at night to try their luck now that it seems unlikely that I.R.A. bombs will still be exploding from time to time next door at the Grand Opera House.</p>
        <p>"The old folks are coming out at night again," said Mrs. Gormley. "They wouldn't come when the bombs went off. They ran out of here. Now we're seeing faces we haven't seen in years."</p>
        <p>The bingo surge is one of the early signs that the people of Belfast are adjusting well and quickly to the disappearance of I.R.A. bombings and shootings.</p>
        <p>The Protestant paramilitaries have continued sporadic attacks on Catholics in the predominantly Protestant British province of Ulster, but in Belfast, there is a palpable sense of relief. Ordinary people wonder how peace will affect them, if a peace economy will hurt civilians who benefited from the years of strife. Politicians concentrate on the war of words instead of the violence that has killed 3,170 people since 1969.</p>
        <p>Taxi drivers say they no longer sit idle on Saturdays, but are busy with shoppers coming to town on weekends for the first time in years. The fashionable Culloden Hotel, in the eastern suburbs, now permits cars and cabs to pull up to the front door, no longer stopping them outside a high steel gate. Checkpoints with police and soldiers have virtually disappeared from the streets. The reduced number of soldiers on patrol now wear regimental berets and ribboned caps rather than helmets. Gone are the security guards who checked the bags of people entering the Castlecourt shopping mall.</p>
        <p>And instead of attending funerals of I.R.A. victims and denouncing I.R.A. brutality, Protestant political leaders are focusing on what they see as the accelerating political campaign to create an Ireland free of British control and ending eventually in union with the Irish Republic to the south, something they fear and oppose.</p>
        <p>In recent days, the British Prime Minister, John Major, has promised that any political settlement reached with the I.R.A. and its political wing, Sinn Fein, will be submitted to a referendum in the north, where the majority is Protestant, and opposed to a united Ireland.</p>
        <p>And Prime Minister Albert Reynolds of Ireland, stating what most people consider obvious, said that he did not expect to see a united Ireland in his generation.</p>
        <p>"It's all choreographed to reassure Protestant unionists," said Paul Arthur, a political science professor at Ulster University in Belfast. "To reassure them that no secret deals have been done with the I.R.A. or anyone else."</p>
        <p>Ian Paisley Jr., an official of the Democratic Unionist Party run by his father, the fundamentalist hard-line preacher, said the promise of a referendum meant that "the government has come back down to earth." But he still feels that "the British will with pleasure withdraw from Northern Ireland and eventually agree to a united Ireland." In language reflecting his father's scathing style, he described a scenario involving Ireland, America and Britain: "The Micks push the Yanks push the Brits and the Unionists, anything to embarrass Britain."</p>
        <p>Mr. Paisley said that Ireland and Britain were clearly trying to bypass his father by dealing with the mainstream Ulster Unionist Party of James Molyneux. "But they have to remember," he said, "there is only one unionist leader who can sell any agreement reached to the unionist people, and that's Ian Paisley."</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Donaldson and a delegation of Ulster Unionist Party officials, Rev. Paisley's chief rivals, met on Thursday with Vice President Al Gore in Washington and emerged saying they were satisfied that their view were being given a fair hearing in Washington. One of the Ulster Unionists' principal demands is that the I.R.A. surrender its arsenal of weapons and explosives, which he estimated at 100 tons, before it be given a place at a negotiating table with Britain and Ireland, an event not expected before next spring at the earliest.</p>
        <p>Gerry Adams, the I.R.A.'s political leader, said that Mr. Major had been a "tomfool" to propose the referendum, which he characterized as a "con trick," attempting to dictate he means of public approval of settlement as a precondition for peace talks. Mr. Adams is also preparing to visit the United States, including Washington.</p>
        <p>At Debenham's department store at Castlecourt , the sole security guard on a recent afternoon was a young woman who would identify herself only as Kelly. She said that nine security guards had been laid off since last Saturday, and that shoppers now entered the store without being searched. Some of the former guards hoped to be rehired as salesmen and women to handle the increase in business, she said.</p>
        <p>"But I'd rather have peace than me job," she said, in a clipped Belfast accent. "Anyone'll tell you that."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
