<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health</title>
    <meta content="16LOSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DC1738F935A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health article discusses factors common among formerly obese people who have succeeded in losing and keeping off significant weight; notes most modified both eating and exercise habits and developed ways to deal with cravings and stress that enabled them to stick to diets; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PROFESSIONAL beliefs about the possibility of long-term weight loss by those who have a lot to lose have not changed much since 1958, when the renowned obesity specialist Dr. Albert J. Stunkard of the University of Pennsylvania said: ''Most obese persons will not stay in treatment. Of those who stay in treatment, most will not lose weight, and of those who do lose weight, most will regain it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PROFESSIONAL beliefs about the possibility of long-term weight loss by those who have a lot to lose have not changed much since 1958, when the renowned obesity specialist Dr. Albert J. Stunkard of the University of Pennsylvania said: ''Most obese persons will not stay in treatment. Of those who stay in treatment, most will not lose weight, and of those who do lose weight, most will regain it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stunkard may be right about ''most obese persons.'' But what about the uncounted thousands who do manage to lose many pounds, sometimes a third or half of their original weight, and also manage to keep it off -- not just for a year or two, but for life? Might not their success stories be a better example for those struggling to lose weight?</p>
        <p>Weight Loss Is Possible</p>
        <p>Anne M. Fletcher, a registered dietitian who has counseled hundreds of overweight patients, thought so when she wrote the inspiring and informative book ''Thin for Life'' (Chapters, 1994; in paperback,  Houghton Mifflin, $13). In it, she distills 10 secrets of success from the stories of 160 ''masters of weight control,'' defined as people who have managed to keep off at least 20 pounds for a minimum of three years.</p>
        <p>Actually, the average weight loss for her subjects was 63 pounds. Seventy percent lost 40 pounds or more, more than half lost 50 pounds, and most have been maintaining their losses for five or more years. And they did it without appetite-suppressing drugs, the long-term safety of which is now very much in question. Yesterday the Food and Drug Administration asked manufacturers of two of the most popular diet drugs -- Redux, the trade name for dexfenfluramine, and Pondimin, or fenfluramine, half of the fen-phen combination -- to withdraw the drugs because they have been linked to heart damage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fletcher also explodes many of the prevailing myths about weight loss, like, ''If you've been overweight since childhood, it's next to impossible to lose weight and keep it off,'' and, ''If you've dieted and failed many times before, there's little hope of ever licking your weight problem.'' Close to half of Ms. Fletcher's ''masters'' had been heavy since childhood, and nearly 60 percent had tried to lose weight at least five times before they finally succeeded.</p>
        <p>Debunking other myths, Ms. Fletcher says her masters do not eat like birds or exercise fanatically to maintain their losses. Most eat several meals a day, including snacks and an occasional high-calorie treat. And while most exercise much more than typical Americans, 60 percent of whom do not exercise at all, few overdo it. About 70 percent exercise three or more times a week, but only 16 percent do so daily. Walking, not running, is their leading activity.</p>
        <p>Lest you think Ms. Fletcher's subjects are an aberration, the National Weight Control Registry, an ongoing study, has just published an analysis of 629 women and 155 men who lost an average of 66 pounds and have maintained at least a 30-pound loss for five or more years. They reduced their body weight by 29 percent, on average, successfully moving to a normal weight range. Ms. Fletcher's conclusions are corroborated by that study, which was conducted by Dr. Mary L. Klem and her colleagues at the University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine and the University of Colorado Health Sciences Center in Denver and published in August in The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition.</p>
        <p>Most of the registry's participants had been overweight since childhood, nearly half had one overweight parent, and more than a quarter had two overweight parents. Their genes may have predisposed them to obesity, but their sustained weight losses prove that heredity need not confer a lifelong destiny.</p>
        <p>How They Do It</p>
        <p>To lose weight, about 55 percent of the registry study participants used a formal program or professional assistance, like Weight Watchers, Overeaters Anonymous or sessions with a psychologist or registered dietitian. The remaining 45 percent did it on their own. Nearly 90 percent modified both their eating and their exercise habits, reducing the amount and kind of calories consumed and increasing the number of calories expended. Only 10 percent used diet alone to shed those unwanted pounds, and only one in five used a liquid diet formula. Fewer than 6 percent used medication or surgery to lose weight.</p>
        <p>The most popular diet strategy, used by nearly 90 percent of participants, was to restrict the intake of certain types or amounts of foods. Forty-three percent counted calories, a third limited their fat intake, and a quarter counted fat grams. More than 44 percent ate the same foods they had been eating but limited amounts.</p>
        <p>As for exercise, 92 percent exercised at home, and about a third regularly exercised with a group or a friend. The women primarily chose walking and aerobic dancing for exercise, while the men tended to choose competitive sports and weight-lifting.</p>
        <p>More than three-fourths of the study participants said their successful weight loss had been prompted by a particular event. Many were motivated by health problems -- like  varicose veins, low back pain, sleep apnea or fatigue -- or emotional factors.</p>
        <p>One woman, for example, said that she had lost weight after her lawyer told her that her husband had left her because she was too fat. Another said she wanted to look good for her approaching 25th anniversary. But many others reported that the trigger, according to the research team, was simply ''ongoing discontent'' and the decision to ''just do it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fletcher's subjects also reported that something had prompted them, as she put it, ''to take the reins.'' She added, ''They stopped looking to others for all the answers and decided to lose weight for no one other than themselves.''</p>
        <p>Try, Try Again</p>
        <p>More than 90 percent of the registry study participants had tried several times to lose weight before they were successful, shedding, on average, a total of 53 to 487 pounds in the course of their lives. They said their efforts had worked this time because they had greater social or health reasons for losing weight.</p>
        <p>More than 80 percent said they had been more committed to making behavioral changes, 81 percent said they had exercised more than in past attempts, and 63 percent said they had used a stricter diet. They also developed ways to deal with cravings and stress that enabled them to stick to their diets.</p>
        <p>The people interviewed by Ms. Fletcher likewise learned from past mistakes. They became more realistic about their weight goals, staying within a range that they could maintain without having to go to painful extremes. They learned to monitor their weight (most of the registry study participants weighed themselves more than once a week) to keep within a 10-pound range. Most had plans of action ready when their weight began to creep up -- stopping snacks, increasing exercise or reducing portions until they returned to their desired weight.</p>
        <p>The masters at weight control have made gradual but total changes in how they eat and exercise and do not think of themselves as on a diet. They have accepted the fact that they cannot go back to their old eating habits. As one woman put it, ''I'd like to be eating hot fudge sundaes or brownies, but for me, the weight is more important.''</p>
        <p>Much of their resolve stems from the fact that they find life is simply better when they are thinner. At least 85 percent of the study participants reported that their lives had improved since losing weight. The benefits included gaining self-confidence, getting jobs, becoming more involved in their communities and cultivating a fulfilling social life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
