<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citing Fraud in Home Care, Clinton Halts New Permits</title>
    <meta content="T16FRAU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E4DE1438F935A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citing Fraud in Home Care, Clinton Halts New Permits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, citing discovery of widespread fraud, says he will bar home health agencies from Medicare program for at least six months while Federal Government develops more stringent standards against fraud; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton said today that he would bar new home health agencies from the Medicare program for at least six months while the Federal Government develops more stringent standards against fraud.</p>
        <p>More than 3.8 million of the 38 million Medicare beneficiaries receive services from 10,000 home health agencies, and the Federal Government pays $19 billion a year for those services. The number of such agencies in the program has increased 75 percent since 1990. Mr. Clinton said today that Federal investigators had found evidence of widespread fraud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton said today that he would bar new home health agencies from the Medicare program for at least six months while the Federal Government develops more stringent standards against fraud.</p>
        <p>More than 3.8 million of the 38 million Medicare beneficiaries receive services from 10,000 home health agencies, and the Federal Government pays $19 billion a year for those services. The number of such agencies in the program has increased 75 percent since 1990. Mr. Clinton said today that Federal investigators had found evidence of widespread fraud.</p>
        <p>In a speech at a conference of the Service Employees International Union, Mr. Clinton said: ''Home health care is one of the country's fastest growing industries. We want more people to be cared for at home, if they can properly be cared for at home. Every month, nearly a hundred home health providers, new ones, enter the Medicare program, but there is still too much evidence of widespread fraud and abuse.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he was determined to ''keep scam and rip-off artists'' out of the program.</p>
        <p>Accordingly, he said: ''I am declaring an immediate moratorium on the admission of new home health agencies to Medicare. During this moratorium, we'll develop tough new regulations to insure that no fly-by-night providers enter or remain in the Medicare program.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he would require home health agencies to reapply to the Medicare program every three years, so the Government could be sure they were complying with the new standards.</p>
        <p>In addition, the President said, ''we will double the number of audits of home health agencies currently involved in the Medicare program.'' The number of comprehensive audits will rise to 1,800 a year, from 900.</p>
        <p>White House officials said that auditors would review 250,000 claims a year, up from the current 200,000.</p>
        <p>A recent report by the General Accounting Office, the Congressional watchdog agency, said: ''Controls over the Medicare home health benefit remain essentially nonexistent. Few home health claims are subject to medical review, and most claims are paid without question.''</p>
        <p>The Government reviewed 60 percent of claims filed 10 years ago, but only 2 percent of those filed last year. The money for such reviews has lagged far behind the increase in the number of claims.</p>
        <p>The total number of home health visits financed by Medicare doubled from 1992 to 1996, reaching 280 million last year. The people who receive home health services are typically women older than 75. But many are disabled people younger than 65.</p>
        <p>Leslie G. Aronovitz, an associate director of the General Accounting Office, said tonight, ''We were heartened by the President's actions, which are very much in line with what we recommended at a Congressional hearing on July 28.''</p>
        <p>But Mark J. Biros, a Washington lawyer who has represented home health agencies, said: ''The moratorium is a drastic action. It's an admission that the Government may not have the program under control. It will hurt bona fide providers even as it stops a small percentage of alleged fraud.''</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration will require home health agencies to submit detailed financial information on all their subsidiaries and related businesses. Unscrupulous operators have conducted business through ''front companies'' that did not really exist.</p>
        <p>Under the old procedures, Ms. Aronovitz said, it was ''simply too easy'' for home health agencies to be certified for Medicare.</p>
        <p>In one case, she said, ''an individual with no experience in health care started a Texas home health agency in the pantry of her husband's restaurant.'' Federal investigators found that the company had hired home health aides on the condition that they recruit patients. The agency was suspected of providing unnecessary services and was cited for violating Federal standards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
