<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Met Is Delighted by New Russian Link</title>
    <meta content="16OPER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Opera</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kirov Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gergiyev, Valery</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levine, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Picker, Tobias</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tan Dun</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EEDA1738F935A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Met Is Delighted by New Russian Link</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Metropolitan Opera general manager, Joseph Volpe, names Valery Gergiyev as company's main guest conductor; Gergiyev will also conduct Kirov Opera at Met; Volpe says Met expects $1 million deficit this season; he and artistic director, James Levine, report commissioning new operas from Tobias Picker and Tan Dun (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph Volpe, the general manager of the Metropolitan Opera, formally announced the appointment of Valery Gergiyev as the company's principal guest conductor yesterday at a news conference.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Gergiyev at his left and James Levine, the Met's artistic director, at his right, Mr. Volpe also discussed the Met's financial projections, which include a deficit of $1 million this season (compared with a surplus of $117,000 last season), as well as several changes in the management hierarchy. He and Mr. Levine also announced the commissioning of new operas from Tobias Picker and Tan Dun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joseph Volpe, the general manager of the Metropolitan Opera, formally announced the appointment of Valery Gergiyev as the company's principal guest conductor yesterday at a news conference.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Gergiyev at his left and James Levine, the Met's artistic director, at his right, Mr. Volpe also discussed the Met's financial projections, which include a deficit of $1 million this season (compared with a surplus of $117,000 last season), as well as several changes in the management hierarchy. He and Mr. Levine also announced the commissioning of new operas from Tobias Picker and Tan Dun.</p>
        <p>Mr. Volpe noted that the relationship between the Met and Mr. Gergiyev extends back around five years, to when Mr. Gergiyev first brought the Kirov Opera to the Met for a series of summer performances. Since then, Mr. Gergiyev has conducted at the Met, starting with an ''Otello'' in 1994, and the Met began an arrangement with the Marinsky Theater in St. Petersburg, which Mr. Gergiyev directs, in which the Met provided sets and costumes from productions it had replaced. The Marinsky Theater is the home of the Kirov Opera and the Kirov Ballet.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Gergiyev as principal guest conductor, the flow of productions may work both ways. Mr. Levine acknowledged yesterday that Mr. Gergiyev's expertise in the Russian repertory would help the Met expand into an area where Mr. Levine could not as easily lead it, and Mr. Volpe suggested that elements of the Kirov's productions -- and certainly some of its singers -- would find their way into the Met's Russian opera stagings. There could also be co-productions, shared by both companies.</p>
        <p>''I'm in heaven,'' Mr. Volpe said, ''just to think what can be accomplished with everything Jim and I have tried to do, and now with Valery coming on and adding what he can do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gergiyev is scheduled to conduct eight productions at the Met over the next five seasons. He will also conduct the Kirov Opera in 13 performances at the Met next April and May.</p>
        <p>Besides the appointment of Mr. Gergiyev, Mr. Volpe elevated three members of the Met staff to assistant manager positions. Joe Clark, the company's technical director, remains in charge of the technical side of the Met's productions. Stewart Pearce was appointed assistant manager in charge of planning and marketing, and Smeeta Sharon was appointed assistant manager in charge of business.</p>
        <p>Explaining the expected loss of $1 million on this year's budget of $160 million, Mr. Volpe said that he considered the current Met season experimental in the sense that the company is not presenting certain of its staples, most notably ''La Traviata,'' ''Le Nozze di Figaro,'' ''Aida'' and ''Tosca.'' The budget projection may also reflect Mr. Volpe's policy of presenting more operas with fewer repeat performances. This season the repertory includes 25 works, up from 23 last season (not counting the ''Ring'' cycle, for which the company adds extra performance weeks). Mr. Volpe said that box-office sales for the season were expected to be 91 percent, down 1 percent from last season.</p>
        <p>In announcing the commissions from Mr. Tan and Mr. Picker, Mr. Levine and Mr. Volpe said that it was too early to discuss subjects, collaborators or scheduling details, but that  both operas were to be performed before 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
