<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late-Night Clubs, Bars and Restaurants Renew White Plains</title>
    <meta content="NITELI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="941878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Area Planning and Renewal</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">White Plains (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowe, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0D61530F935A35754C0A961958260" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late-Night Clubs, Bars and Restaurants Renew White Plains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA ROWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rowe, Claudia</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on renewal of night life in downtown White Plains, NY, in nine months since opening of new bars, lounges and restaurants; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Benjamin Feder was a child in the 60's, his parents called this city's downtown Little Fifth Avenue. Fancy shops flourished alongside high-end department stores, customers strolled the main streets and money flowed.</p>
        <p>Over the last 10 years, Mr. Feder -- who is one of several new bar and club owners in the area -- watched the neighborhood decay into a dead zone where 99-cent shops sprouted like weeds and streets were deserted by nightfall. But, like the trendy, microbrewed beer he sells at the Westchester Brewing Company, all things have a time to shine. Mamaroneck Avenue's time may be now.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Benjamin Feder was a child in the 60's, his parents called this city's downtown Little Fifth Avenue. Fancy shops flourished alongside high-end department stores, customers strolled the main streets and money flowed.</p>
        <p>Over the last 10 years, Mr. Feder -- who is one of several new bar and club owners in the area -- watched the neighborhood decay into a dead zone where 99-cent shops sprouted like weeds and streets were deserted by nightfall. But, like the trendy, microbrewed beer he sells at the Westchester Brewing Company, all things have a time to shine. Mamaroneck Avenue's time may be now.</p>
        <p>In the last nine months, the buzz created with the Brewing Company's October 1996 debut has reverberated across the street to the Lazy Boy Saloon, where the owner, J. R. Cavallaro, has expanded his selection to include 300 brands of bottled beer and 35 on tap. In November Mr. Cavallaro, 30, also opened the White Plains Tobacconist, a fancy cigar store two doors down. A few yards away, Esy's restaurant plans to fill summer nights with live jazz, and one block north Emanon nightclub keeps revelers busy until 4 A.M., which is the legal closing time.</p>
        <p>The Fireworks Brewery is scheduled to open nearby in a few months on Martine Avenue. Construction is under way at Laguna restaurant on Waller Avenue, and parking gets tight in the neighborhood on Saturday nights.</p>
        <p>''It's great.'' said Maria Garcia, 30, of White Plains as she sipped a cocktail at Emanon's marble-top bar on a recent Friday evening. ''There has been nothing to do around here for so long, and now all this! We've been craving something like this for years. Have you seen the cigar room upstairs? It's beautiful. It's like a little part of New York City in Westchester.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Garcia's enthusiasm echoed all the way to City Hall, where Mayor S. J. Schulman was remembering a recent party at Emanon. The club -- which is ''no name'' spelled backward -- features a huge selection of single-malt Scotches and top-shelf Cognacs served in a cigar lounge with cedar-lined humidors and leopard-print upholstery.</p>
        <p>''It's really something,'' the Mayor said. ''It's very elegantly appointed, and it shows a real investment of real dollars. That's no hot dog stand.''</p>
        <p>But to hear the new bar and club owners tell it, White Plains was not always so friendly to late-night businesses. At first, city officials did not understand what Mr. Feder and his partners meant when they said they wanted to open an upscale brew pub.</p>
        <p>''There was some concern in the Building Department when they heard 'microbrewery' that it was going to be an industrial firm with fumes and deliveries and everything,'' said Commissioner Joseph R. Potenza of the Planning Department.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Feder and his partners, Benn Lewis and Jeffrey Reed, chauffeured the bureaucrats down to Manhattan for a night at the fashionable Zip City bar and brewery to illustrate what they were aiming for. Relations soon improved.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Schulman acknowledges the once-hostile atmosphere between White Plains and its business owners. When he took office three years ago, he said, it quickly became obvious that the city would have to encourage more night life downtown. Malls like The Westchester on Bloomingdale Road were taking over retail businesses, and the area was becoming empty after dark.</p>
        <p>To turn things around, officials rewrote some zoning laws, added hundreds of parking spaces and allowed bars like the Lazy Boy and the Westchester Brewing Company to keep their sidewalk cafes open past midnight. The restaurants, nightclubs and pubs that followed led Mr. Schulman to describe the burgeoning scene as ''a controlled New York City.''</p>
        <p>The reaction from residents has been positive, the Mayor said. Daniel Hickey, deputy commissioner for public safety, said there had been 14 calls complaining about noise on Mamaroneck Avenue, no robberies, but 10 arrests associated with the night-time businesses from June 1996 to June 1997. Those figures compare with 15 noise complaints and 1 robbery the previous year.</p>
        <p>John Jordan, 26, contracts manager for Aerotek Data Services in White Plains, said he preferred to unwind on Mamaroneck Avenue after work rather than heading to Manhattan for fun. ''You don't have the driving time,'' he said. ''You don't have all the havoc and hassles of the city life. It's a lot easier to hang around up here and have a good time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan's boss, Rex Salter, agreed: ''The scene here? It's great. We need this, but even more -- times eight. If I really want to go out, I still go to the city, but I like it up here. In the city, you've got to cab it or drive around. It's expensive. You've got to stand in line to get in places. It's a hassle. Here, it's a lot easier, a lot more casual.''</p>
        <p>By 9 P.M. the two were shooting pool around a crowded table at the Lazy Boy as dozens of other customers downed oysters at the raw bar and quaffed raspberry beers from Belgium. ''This is kind of quiet!'' yelled Mr. Cavallaro, the owner, over the din. ''We get a lot of people who travel here for the beers. People from New York City, people from upstate New York.''</p>
        <p>Emanon is also beckoning the after-work crowd with its patio bar, which recently opened and offers Colossal Corporate Happy Hours.  ''We've got this beautiful, romantic outdoor area right in the heart of White Plains, right in the heart of the city,'' Daniel Devlin, the 34-year-old owner, said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feder at the Brewing Company said things really rock and roll on Saturday nights. ''The thought has crossed my mind that it would have been nice to have done this 10 years ago -- before I had a wife and family,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
