<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oscar Style: All Polished, Pretty and Banal</title>
    <meta content="28DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards/Academy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0D71E3DF93BA15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1426" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oscar Style: All Polished, Pretty and Banal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>WEST HOLLYWOOD, Calif., March 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses various fashions worn at Academy Awards; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On her way into the Vanity Fair Oscar party early this morning, Queen Latifah did what any celebrity might do when told she cannot bring her bodyguard into the hottest party in town -- and it's 1 a.m., too late, practically speaking, for a snit. She stripped off the several million dollars' worth of borrowed Harry Winston jewels she had on and handed them to the bodyguard, right on the curb. Like they're loose change or something.</p>
        <p>Then she sailed past the paparazzi gathered five deep behind the rope line and into Morton's restaurant, where Brad Pitt, Jennifer Aniston, Tom Cruise, Nicole Kidman, Hilary Swank, Chloe Sevigny, Matt Damon, Winona Ryder, Faye Dunaway, Jane Fonda -- well, everyone who is anybody -- were already engaged in the frenetic business of being a star on Oscar night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On her way into the Vanity Fair Oscar party early this morning, Queen Latifah did what any celebrity might do when told she cannot bring her bodyguard into the hottest party in town -- and it's 1 a.m., too late, practically speaking, for a snit. She stripped off the several million dollars' worth of borrowed Harry Winston jewels she had on and handed them to the bodyguard, right on the curb. Like they're loose change or something.</p>
        <p>Then she sailed past the paparazzi gathered five deep behind the rope line and into Morton's restaurant, where Brad Pitt, Jennifer Aniston, Tom Cruise, Nicole Kidman, Hilary Swank, Chloe Sevigny, Matt Damon, Winona Ryder, Faye Dunaway, Jane Fonda -- well, everyone who is anybody -- were already engaged in the frenetic business of being a star on Oscar night.</p>
        <p>How can one describe the scene inside Morton's except to say that it was strangely, marvelously surreal? Walter Cronkite was talking to Steven Tisch, the entertainment executive. Bob Colacello, a Vanity Fair writer who is working on a book about Ronald Reagan, was saying something to Connie Wald, widow of the producer Jerry Wald, who made ''Johnny Belinda'' and ''Key Largo.'' She looked fabulous in a black taffeta couture skirt with a black Gap T-shirt she had thoughtfully adorned with a Mongolian lamb cowl and jeweled earrings.</p>
        <p>They had all been there since 5 p.m. So had Tony Curtis, Billy Wilder, Steve Martin, David Geffen, Fran Lebowitz, Penny Marshall, Regis Philbin and Kelly Lynch, about 150 people in all invited by Graydon Carter, the magazine's editor, to watch the Academy Awards on big-screen televisions as they ate grilled ahi tuna with baby bok choy and warm chocolate truffle cake.</p>
        <p>Unless one was an Oscar nominee or a presenter, or decided to stay at home, as Rita Wilson and her husband, Tom Hanks, did (''I'll be in my sweats,'' Ms. Wilson said happily on Saturday at the lunch Barry Diller, the former Paramount chief, gave at his house for several hundred people), the place to be on Oscar night was at one of the half dozen or so parties that now seem to rival the awards themselves for sheer star power. DreamWorks and Miramax had their parties, so did the Elton John AIDS Foundation (with In Style magazine). And there were the private affairs held in the days leading up to the Oscars, like the dinner on Saturday night that the agent Ed Limato had.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to seeing all those familiar faces, and debating the merits of who wore what -- which has become a kind of ruthless sport at Oscar time -- the Vanity Fair party was by far the most elegant cattle call in town.</p>
        <p>Although only 150 people could be invited to the dinner, nearly 1,000 started pouring into Morton's when the awards show ended at 10:30 p.m. Within 30 minutes, when Mr. Cruise and Ms. Kidman arrived, the area in front of the bar was so jammed that when someone suggested everyone move into the tent, which had been set up in the back of the restaurant, for dancing and just sitting around, Mr. Cruise became a kind of ring leader. ''Hey, let's go back,'' he called out above the roar. ''We're moving in the back.''</p>
        <p>In the back, Ms. Kidman, who had on a gold silk Dior dress, let out a sigh. ''I think we're just going to stay at this party,'' she said, adding that she planned to leave at midnight for a flight to Australia, where she is filming ''Moulin Rouge.'' Someone had stepped on the train of her dress and put a tear in it. ''It's madness,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Hugh Hefner was in a booth with a pride of four blondes, including a pair of bosomy twins, and people came over just to gawk. Cher, who had changed from her black Oscar gown into an ensemble of sequins with a denim jacket, immediately spotted the dress designer Diane Von Furstenberg.</p>
        <p>''Oh, how are you,'' Cher said to Ms. Von Furstenberg. ''I see your stuff on QVC sometimes. One day I watched it for 45 minutes.''</p>
        <p>Morton's was throbbing with people. Mr. Carter was on the dance floor with Minnie Driver. Ms. Lebowitz, meanwhile, spent most of the night, until after 1 a.m., reclining on a sofa, with her high heels dangling on the arm rest and a carton of Marlboro Lights next to her. ''I have my drink and my cigarettes,'' she said. ''I'm just waiting for the pizza to be delivered.''</p>
        <p>Just then somebody brought over Heidi Fleiss, the former Hollywood madam, to meet Ms. Lebowitz, and after Ms. Lebowitz introduced another guest to Ms. Fleiss, who had on a velvet, fur-trimmed coat she described as ''hooker-rock star,'' Ms. Lebowitz beamed. ''That's the best introduction I've made since I introduced Liberace to Michael Graves,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Pitt, who was a presenter, made his way into the tent, he was asked what he thought of this year's Oscar fashion, which many thought was a mixed bag. Mr. Pitt grinned. ''That's a woman thing,'' he said. ''You don't ask a guy that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Aniston, his girlfriend, gave him a look. ''Oh now, ask a guy,'' she said. ''He knows.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pitt shrugged handsomely. ''Everybody was dressed, and I was happy they were,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Aniston, who was wearing a black halter-style dress by Lawrence Steele, continued: ''You know the thing that burns me the most? It's that people can't try something without going on trial or getting ridiculed. It's that Joan Rivers and Melissa thing.'' She was referring to the E! Entertainment channel's fashion critics.</p>
        <p>The thing is, the fashion that comes down the red carpet has become almost too banal to even comment upon. Actresses like Charlize Theron, who had on a Vera Wang gown with Fred Leighton diamond dress clips, and Ashley Judd, who wore lavender Valentino with her hair in Southern ringlets, looked pretty. So did Ms. Sevigny in a Madame X gown by Saint Laurent.</p>
        <p>But there was little surprise. No outrageous examples of bad taste (unless you count Angelina Jolie's get-up, which was spooky). Even the sexier clothes, like the Versace dresses worn by Cameron Diaz and Lucy Liu, seemed somehow predictable.</p>
        <p>''I call it the beauty-pageant parade of Barbie doll dresses,'' said Randolph Duke, who scored something of a coup by designing Ms. Swank's ball gown, made from 1950's French silk, which he called a homage to Charles James. ''The risk-takers were fewer this year,'' he added. ''These girls get so many opinions: publicist, manager, husband, mother. It's a committee decision, and you know what you get with a committee decision.''</p>
        <p>Asked for an opinion, Lisa Eisner, the fashion muse and stylist, said, ''I hate when young girls try to dress like older women.'' She mentioned the big gold hoop earrings that Uma Thurman wore with her Alberta Ferretti dress, which she suggested were better than aging diamonds.</p>
        <p>But who can say in Hollywood? There was Connie Wald, a doyenne, in her Gap T-shirt. ''Nothing has changed in Hollywood, basically,'' she said sweetly. ''It's all the same -- still cutthroat, still competitive. Only the faces have changed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
