<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amendment Would Let State Name Sex Offenders Online</title>
    <meta content="28MEGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1187421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DD1F3DF93BA15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amendment Would Let State Name Sex Offenders Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, March 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Governor Christine Todd Whitman, frustrated that state courts have prevented Megan's Law from reaching into cyberspace, introduces legislation that would amend State Constitution to allow officials to post convicted sex offenders' names on Internet site (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frustrated that New Jersey courts have prevented Megan's Law from reaching into cyberspace, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman introduced legislation today that would amend the State Constitution to allow officials to post convicted sex offenders' names on an Internet site.</p>
        <p>New Jersey began a national movement in 1995, when legislators reacted to the outrage surrounding the murder of 7-year-old Megan Kanka by enacting the nation's first law allowing the police to notify residents when a paroled sex offender moves into their community.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frustrated that New Jersey courts have prevented Megan's Law from reaching into cyberspace, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman introduced legislation today that would amend the State Constitution to allow officials to post convicted sex offenders' names on an Internet site.</p>
        <p>New Jersey began a national movement in 1995, when legislators reacted to the outrage surrounding the murder of 7-year-old Megan Kanka by enacting the nation's first law allowing the police to notify residents when a paroled sex offender moves into their community.</p>
        <p>All 50 states now have similar statutes, and 16 states list the names and addresses of paroled sexual predators on Web sites. But New Jersey's  Supreme Court, which has a history of judicial activism, has demanded sharp limits on who can be notified, citing concerns about vigilantism and parolees' privacy rights.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey General Assembly passed a bill today to post sexual predators' names and addresses on the Internet, but Governor Whitman said she believed that law would be struck down by the courts, so she proposed the bold step of circumventing the courts by changing the State Constitution. ''We're always sensitive to the privacy rights of individuals,'' Mrs. Whitman said. ''But we are more sensitive to the rights of the community.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey's Constitution has been amended more than 150 times since it was adopted in 1947, usually for bond initiatives and other minor matters. The last time an amendment was used to challenge a State Supreme Court ruling was in 1992, when voters and legislators reaffirmed that the death penalty was constitutional.</p>
        <p>A constitutional amendment would need the approval of two-thirds of lawmakers in both houses of the Legislature, and would then be put on the ballot for voters in November. Even if the measure wins approval, however, it could face a challenge in federal court, because several recent rulings have raised concerns that Internet sex-offender registries may go too far.</p>
        <p>Deborah Jacobs, executive director of the New Jersey chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union, said her group was likely to challenge the proposed amendment because it would subject convicted sex offenders to punishment even after their prison terms ended. Under the state's current policy, which notifies only those who live near a sex offender, there have been some incidents of housing discrimination and physical threats, Ms. Jacobs said, including one 1998 case in which five gunshots were fired into a parolee's home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jacobs said the new measure could also deter sexual assault victims from reporting abuse by relatives, for fear that their families might be subjected to public humiliation. ''One reason attacks are not reported is the shame,'' she said. ''These laws will do more to discourage people from reporting.''</p>
        <p>But Governor Whitman and many other New Jersey officials said they believed that the benefits of publicizing sex offenders' whereabouts far outweighed any drawbacks. The governor said the state police had taken aggressive steps to prevent any vigilante attacks and would intensify their efforts if the information was made more widely available.</p>
        <p>The Senate president, Donald T. DiFrancesco, said he supported the governor's initiative because it would allow New Jersey voters to decide whether widespread notification was appropriate. The Assembly speaker, Jack Collins, whose support would be necessary for any constitutional amendment to win approval, said he was open to the proposal, but stopped short of endorsing it.</p>
        <p>Since states began posting sex offenders identities' on the Internet, there have been some problems, but no reports of vigilante attacks related to the Web sites, said Scott Matson, a research associate at the Center for Sex Offender Management. The most serious complaints in other states have involved incorrect addresses being posted or juvenile offenders' names being included with those of adults, Mr. Matson said.</p>
        <p>''There have been cases where people whose house was incorrectly listed on the Web site end up getting harassed when they have no criminal record at all,'' Mr. Matson said.  ''It's mostly labeling and verbal abuse, where they get called names.''</p>
        <p>In those states that have set up Internet registries, many criminal justice experts have warned residents not to be lulled into the false belief that they are fully apprised of the danger around them. ''Up to 80 percent of sex offenders have never been caught, so these Web sites have to be careful not to create a false sense of security,'' Mr. Matson said. ''We try to remind people that they still have to teach their children how to protect themselves and watch for the warning signs.''</p>
        <p>But opponents of New Jersey's plan for an Internet registry say that if state officials truly wanted to protect the public, they would provide funding for mandatory psychiatric treatment for paroled sex offenders.</p>
        <p>''Knowing where the offender works and lives is a false security statement,'' said Assemblywoman Nia Gill. ''When they are allowed to leave jail, what do you do to substantively ensure the safety of our children? We have to make sure these people are in treatment.''</p>
        <p>In a sign of the political volatility of the issue, however, even Assembly  members who opposed the measure today did not vote no: the final vote count was 55 yes votes, zero no votes and 17 abstentions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
