<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook;   British Playwrights Look Toward an Era After Thatcherism</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARE, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLANNERY, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">RACING DEMON (PLAY)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SINGER (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Critic's Notebooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D8113AF93AA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook;   British Playwrights Look Toward an Era After Thatcherism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICH, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: What will the left-wing playwrights of England do when they don't have Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher to kick around anymore? While Mrs. Thatcher is still very much on the scene, the possibility of her political exit in a year or two, as predicted by public opinion polls, may already be sapping the energy from a theater whose most inventive recent writing has often been in red-hot opposition to her policies and values.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: What will the left-wing playwrights of England do when they don't have Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher to kick around anymore? While Mrs. Thatcher is still very much on the scene, the possibility of her political exit in a year or two, as predicted by public opinion polls, may already be sapping the energy from a theater whose most inventive recent writing has often been in red-hot opposition to her policies and values.</p>
        <p>What will the left-wing playwrights of England do when they don't have Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher to kick around anymore? While Mrs. Thatcher is still very much on the scene, the possibility of her political exit in a year or two, as predicted by public opinion polls, may already be sapping the energy from a theater whose most inventive recent writing has often been in red-hot opposition to her policies and values. In postwar Britain, at least, Conservative Governments seem to raise the creative fevers of British playwrights, while Labor leadership tends to still the waters. Should the blandly liberal Laborite Neil Kinnock come to power, one could more easily imagine his ascendancy inspiring a nostalgic Terence Rattigan revival than inciting a new generation's anti-establishment ''Look Back in Anger'' or ''Top Girls.''</p>
        <p>David Hare's ''Racing Demon'' and Peter Flannery's ''Singer,'' the two most critically celebrated plays in London right now, and certainly the most fascinating, are both the work of leftist dramatists who seem to be wrestling with the anticipated transition to a new political era. Each writer tries to shift the focus of his ideological ire away from Thatcherism per se, if not always with success. At their impressive best, Mr. Hare and Mr. Flannery even leave the vicissitudes of present-day Britain behind entirely and go after God, an authority figure whose tenure even Mrs. Thatcher cannot outlast. ''Racing Demon'' is in repertory at the National Theater with ''The Crucible,'' and, like Arthur Miller's play, it dramatizes a violent spiritual division within a parish. In Mr. Hare's case, the parish is a poor Anglican one in contemporary South London where the presiding vicar, a theological doubter and political liberal, finds his leadership under challenge from a young evangelical curate. The vicar, Lionel (Oliver Ford Davies), believes that the Church of England's mission among inner-city blacks and immigrants begins with the practical good deeds of social work. The curate, Tony (Adam Kotz), insists that Lionel's ''fiddle-faddle'' only sows confusion and that people instead need a firm faith in redemption, as achieved by the rituals and rules set down in The Book.</p>
        <p>Sometimes ''Racing Demon'' can be funny about its clerics, most notably when they are having one tequila sunrise too many at the Savoy. Sometimes the battle between Lionel and Tony sounds like a disguised replay of the secular debates in Mr. Hare's other plays, including the recent ''Secret Rapture,'' in which the equivalent antagonists, two sisters, were an idealistic artist and an evangelically capitalist Thatcher minister. As always, Mr. Hare balances his dueling partners. For all of Lionel's enlightened humanism, he is often as paralyzed and befuddled by doubt as his adversaries paint him to be, an ineffectual liberal of the type who earned Mr. Hare's disdain in ''Plenty'' and ''Pravda.'' Tony, in contrast, delivers his extreme fundamentalist views with a boyish vigor that makes him the sexiest figure on stage and the one natural leader among the many clergymen in view.</p>
        <p>What finally makes the play deeply upsetting is Mr. Hare's ruthless demolition of the sincere spiritual credos of both men. When Tony becomes so eager to sell religious miracles that he asserts an AIDS patient has been cured by the power of prayer, his exploitation of human suffering for his polemical cause seems obscene. But the kindly Lionel becomes just as appalling. He is so infatuated with his own humble conscience that he fails to notice the tragedies of two intimates, his lonely, neglected wife (Barbara Leigh-Hunt) and a loyal gay minister (Michael Bryant) who is being hounded out of England by the gutter press. ''God, where are you?'' Lionel asks in the play's very first line, and the question hangs in the air throughout the evening. As impeccably directed by Richard Eyre on a stark crucifix-shaped set floating in the vast space of the National's Olivier stage, ''Racing Demon'' usually seems suffused with God's troubling silence, no matter who the worshiper.</p>
        <p>It's only when Mr. Hare drags on a superfluous character to fill that silence that he betrays his play's Shavian eloquence for tedious didacticism. An attractive advertising woman keeps popping up unconvincingly in both Lionel and Tony's lives, whenever the playwright needs a convenient mouthpiece for either his plot exposition or his own stand on the issues (''I like the idea of justice better than God''). But even this role is well acted (by Stella Gonet), and the rest of the cast is superb, with Miss Leigh-Hunt and Mr. Bryant proving especially touching as mere mortals trapped innocently in an earthly web of domestic injustices. The existence of a divine plan is under equally fierce attack in ''Singer,'' in which Mr. Flannery charts the postwar adventures of his title character, an Auschwitz survivor played with an incandescent mixture of malignant energy and feral charm by the great actor Antony Sher. ''When someone builds a machine the size of half a continent, employing a cast of thousands, just to make you into soap, it's hard to take entirely seriously the idea of progress,'' says Mr. Sher's Peter Singer, voicing the play's particular agnosticism. ''But it's necessary to go on trying.''</p>
        <p>Actually, the playwright doesn't try that hard. This epic drama, which evokes Jacobean tragicomedy and sends four decades of English life sprawling over the Royal Shakespeare Company's main stage at the Barbican Center, reveals history not as progress but as a vicious circle, endlessly repeating itself. As an immigrant in London, Singer tries to obliterate his Auschwitz memories by restlessly remaking himself into an amoral slumlord exploiting the poor and helpless; ''Singerism'' soon becomes a notorious national synonym for ''wickedness, greed, evil.'' After faking suicide in 1960, an atoning Singer re-emerges in ''sackcloth and ashes'' in 1968 as a do-gooder among the homeless, succumbing to a survivor's guilt as fervently as he once tried to deny it. Either way, his life is imprisoned in the shadow of the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>Though diffuse and repetitive and no more convincing at creating female characters than Mr. Hare's play, ''Singer'' is admirable for its daring ambitions and extravagant theatricality. Mr. Flannery manages to mix such diverse historical and cultural phenomena as a Shakespearean Chorus (played by the excellent Joe Melia), a parody of a 1960's hippie musical, and fictionalized biographies of both Primo Levi (another good performance, by Mick Ford) and the infamous real-life Harold Macmillan-era scoundrels Peter Rachman and John Profumo. The issues at the play's core include, most pressingly, the question of how history's past atrocities can be remembered by a world ''where people can't remember what they had for breakfast.'' Even so, Mr. Flannery has been accused by a critical minority of two separate but related offenses in ''Singer'' - of practicing anti-Semitism and of trivializing the Holocaust. The charge of anti-Semitism seems absurd unless one believes that any portrayal of a greedy Jewish character is anti-Semitic; besides, Mr. Sher's animalistic magnetism makes Singer, however grasping, not a caricature but a sympathetic and irresistible man with a ''talent for life,'' trying to defy a Nazi-ordained fate any way a hostile society will allow. But the second charge is harder to deflect, largely because the writer has been unable to resist the temptation to inject the Great Housekeeper, as he scathingly refers to Mrs. Thatcher, into the politics of ''Singer.''</p>
        <p>The problem develops late in the production when the play's nightmarish opening tableau, a smoky evocation of Auschwitz hell brilliantly staged and lighted by Terry Hands, is repeated almost identically. In its Act II replay, however, the sequence is no longer set in World War II but in present-day London, with the walking cadavers now representing homeless people reduced to camping out by the South Bank. Is Mr. Flannery likening the plight of the neglected poor in Mrs. Thatcher's Britain to that of victims of Nazism? It would seem so, especially when Singer is soon after recruited by the present power elite to help build disciplinary internment camps in the British countryside for the homeless and ''social misfits.''</p>
        <p>In response to his critics, Mr. Flannery has denied that he is equating today's Britain with Hitler's Germany, but whom should the theatergoer believe, the playwright or his own eyes? ''Singer'' is finally so distorted by its author's passionate but inappropriately superimposed political agenda that Nazi crimes are robbed of their specificity and the play ends up contributing to the very process of historical amnesia it previously condemned. After watching a writer as gifted as Mr. Flannery completely lose control of ''Singer,'' even one who shares the anti-Thatcherism of the English theater may wonder if the Great Housekeeper might yet drive her opponents mad before they can sweep her out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
