<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Papal Statement Could Shake the Church</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRTH CONTROL AND FAMILY PLANNING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POPE (JOHN PAUL II)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINFELS, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birth Control and Family Planning</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D61E3BF93AA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1127" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Papal Statement Could Shake the Church</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER STEINFELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINFELS, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Pope John Paul II is completing a major statement on Roman Catholic moral teaching that is already generating rumors and anxiety among Catholic theologians. Some suggest - and a leading Vatican official denies - that it will declare the church's condemnation of contraception to be infallible teaching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Pope John Paul II is completing a major statement on Roman Catholic moral teaching that is already generating rumors and anxiety among Catholic theologians. Some suggest - and a leading Vatican official denies - that it will declare the church's condemnation of contraception to be infallible teaching.</p>
        <p>Pope John Paul II is completing a major statement on Roman Catholic moral teaching that is already generating rumors and anxiety among Catholic theologians. Some suggest - and a leading Vatican official denies - that it will declare the church's condemnation of contraception to be infallible teaching.</p>
        <p>Other theologians expect a broader and more theoretical document that will not deal explicitly with contraception but will nonetheless reflect the Pope's determination to bolster the church's teaching against it.</p>
        <p>The issue of birth control has emerged as a central one for the papacy of John Paul II and has put the Vatican at odds with many leading theologians as well as lay people.</p>
        <p>The new statement will almost certainly heighten the impression among Catholics, particularly in the United States, that the church is making the issue a touchstone that guides its actions on questions from the naming of bishops to other theological issues.</p>
        <p>Warning From Theologians</p>
        <p>A spokesman at the Vatican press office confirmed yesterday that the Pope was preparing a major statement, to be issued by the end of the year as a papal encylical or in the slightly less solemn form of an apostolic letter. But he said he had no information on its contents.</p>
        <p>Last month 22 European theologians, including Hans Kung and Edward Schillebeeckx, signed a declaration warning that a document elevating the ban on birth control to the status of infallible teaching ''would intensify to a catastrophic degree the polarization within our church and accelerate the church's loss of credibility.''</p>
        <p>But on July 20 a Swiss Catholic news agency quoted Joseph Cardinal Ratzinger, head of the Vatican office that oversees doctrine, as saying he had no reason to believe that the document would invoke infallible teaching in regard to birth control.</p>
        <p>The claim that a doctrine is taught infallibly by the church or the Pope means that it is taught with a God-given assurance of its truth. Doctrines can also be taught ''authoritatively,'' leaving open the possibility that further theological discussion will find them partly or wholly erroneous.</p>
        <p>Many theologians say the Pope's statement, even if highly technical, could shake up theological scholarship and eventually the church.</p>
        <p>Some expect that the statement will simply contain a general pronouncement on morality and infallibility. While not explicitly declaring the ban on contraception to be infallible, such a statement would strengthen the hand of church officials who say it is.</p>
        <p>A number of theologians also foresee a papal rejection of a form of moral analysis that enjoys wide support among Catholic theologians, including those critical of the birth-control teaching.</p>
        <p>They expect the Pope to uphold the traditional position that important moral principles, like the one against ''directly'' taking the life of an innocent person, have no exceptions.</p>
        <p>Such acts are considered intrinsically immoral and are absolutely forbidden, regardless of the consequences. Only when an act is not intrinsically immoral can one weigh good consequences against bad ones and choose the lesser of two evils.</p>
        <p>But many Catholic moralists say such teaching ignores the context of actions, including both intentions and consequences. Compared with traditional moralists, they look not so much to an act's intrinsic character as to the proportion of good and evil involved in it.</p>
        <p>Exceptions to absolute norms may need to be made in extremely hard cases, they say; for example, an abortion that is necessary to save the life of a pregnant woman should be judged differently from one that is not. This proportional approach has also been applied in discussions of civilian casualties in warfare, surgical sterilization and some sexual issues. A Slippery Slope?  More traditional Catholic moralists object that in practice this approach will open the door to more exceptions than its supporters acknowledge. If a theologian says a norm has exceptions, said Germain Grisez, a professor of Christian ethics at Mount St. Mary's college in Emmitsburg, Md., ''he might as well have said that there is no norm at all.''</p>
        <p>Opponents of the proportional approach say it undermines the theological argument that contraception is intrinsically immoral.</p>
        <p>If the Pope reasserts absolute norms or condemns the proportional approach, the reaction among theologians will depend greatly on the terms he uses. Advocates of the proportional approach differ among themselves on many details and do not constitute a neatly defined school of thought.</p>
        <p>But the Rev. Richard A. McCormick, a professor at the University of Notre Dame and a leading exponent of proportional teaching, argues that whatever the specific language of the Pope's statement, it ''will put a majority of moral theologians under a cloud.''</p>
        <p>The papal statement may also take a position on the theological debate about what kind of moral norms can be infallibly taught by the church or Pope.</p>
        <p>Theologians Are Divided</p>
        <p>Catholic theologians remain divided over what matters properly fall within the scope of infallibility, especially in the area of morality.</p>
        <p>Some say the church can invoke infallible teaching only regarding broad moral principles, of the sort expressed in the Ten Commandments, or other norms clearly stated in Scripture.</p>
        <p>These theologians argue that although very specific teachings, like the church's teaching on just and unjust wars or its teaching on birth control, may be authoritative, they cannot be taught infallibly because they are not matters of divine revelation but depend on changeable factual judgments or philosophical concepts.</p>
        <p>Other theologians argue that the church and the Pope have a wide scope to interpret moral teachings infallibly, no matter how specific or distantly related to Scripture.</p>
        <p>Some of these theologians, including Mr. Grisez and officials close to the Pope, have argued that the condemnation of contraception should be considered infallible teaching because it was almost universally held by Catholic officials before the disputes of the 1960's.</p>
        <p>Their position would be strengthened by any papal statement that supported the wider intepretation of infallibity in the area of morality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grisez said he did not believe that the papal statement would silence many moralists of other views. But he added, ''Something like this helps a number of young people who are confused.''</p>
        <p>Father McCormick disagreed, saying the consultations preceding such papal documents had become limited to a narrow circle of theological views. ''If they had a full, open discussion and then if they concluded that approaches I favor don't sit well with a full Christian life, I'd say, 'O.K.,' '' he said. ''But it doesn't work that way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
