<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warning Strikes Hit 10 Cities in East Germany</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="380256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GERMANY, REUNIFICATION OF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DD153AF93AA1575BC0A966958260" item-length="377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warning Strikes Hit 10 Cities in East Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>EAST BERLIN, Aug. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: About 45,000 municipal workers in several East German cities walked off their jobs for a few hours today in warning strikes for better wages and job security in a united Germany.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: About 45,000 municipal workers in several East German cities walked off their jobs for a few hours today in warning strikes for better wages and job security in a united Germany.</p>
        <p>About 45,000 municipal workers in several East German cities walked off their jobs for a few hours today in warning strikes for better wages and job security in a united Germany.</p>
        <p>Nurses, secretaries, bus drivers, garbage-haulers and other employees stopped working for up to two hours in at least 10 cities.</p>
        <p>Demonstrations and rallies were held in a number of cities, with workers demanding job protection and pay increases in a united Germany. There are about 1.6 million municipal workers in East Germany.</p>
        <p>The workers are demanding compensation for higher prices that have resulted from the economic merger July 1 of the two Germanys. They also demand that East German income taxes not be immediately raised to West German levels.</p>
        <p>In Potsdam outside Berlin, buses and street cars were idle for two hours, according to the official East German news agency. Streetcars blocked main avenues in Magdeburg, and dozens of garbage trucks hindered access to the city's main department store.</p>
        <p>Operations at Magdeburg's Elbe River harbor were temporarily crippled by the walkout, the news agency said. Short strikes were also staged in Halle, Sonneberg, Schwerin, Frankfurt an der Oder, Chemnitz, Zwickau, Plauen and Schonberg.</p>
        <p>In Bonn, the West German Government said Western investors' interest in East Germany is starting to pick up. The West German Government had hoped for large-scale investment in East Germany once the two nations merged their economies.</p>
        <p>Tomatoes Hurled at Kohl</p>
        <p>HALLE, East Germany, Aug. 28 (Reuters) - Leftist protesters hurled tomatoes and eggs at West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl at a rally in East Germany today, but security men used umbrellas to shield the Chancellor.</p>
        <p>About 100 Communists and other leftists in a crowd of 5,000 drowned out Mr. Kohl with whistles and shouts complaining about the high cost of German unification.</p>
        <p>East Germany is to merge with West Germany on Oct. 3, and Mr. Kohl had expected a warm welcome.</p>
        <p>Today's throng in Halle's medieval square was tiny compared with the 150,000-strong crowds that cheered him when he barnstormed through the country to back local candidates for free elections last March.</p>
        <p>Since then, unemployment has soared from next to nothing to about 350,000 in August.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
