<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Are Quick to Line Up Coaching Candidates</title>
    <meta content="25GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="897540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Chiefs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reeves, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bugel, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schottenheimer, Marty</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Arizona Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Kansas City Chiefs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E1D71E31F936A15751C1A960958260" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Are Quick to Line Up Coaching Candidates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants move to find replacement for Coach Dan Reeves, getting permission to talk with Jim Fassel, offensive coordinator of Arizona Cardinals, and Joe Bugel, assistant head coach and offensive coordinator of Oakland Raiders; plan to talk with others and are reportedly very interested in Coach Marty Schottenheimer of Kansas City Chiefs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Giants General Manager George Young said he was not going to waste any time searching for a head coach to replace Dan Reeves. He wasn't kidding. About 15 minutes after Monday's news conference to announce the firing of Reeves, Young called the Arizona owner, Bill Bidwill, to seek permission to speak to Jim Fassel, the Cardinals' offensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Young has been given permission by Oakland to talk to Joe Bugel, the Raiders' assistant head coach and offensive coordinator.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Giants General Manager George Young said he was not going to waste any time searching for a head coach to replace Dan Reeves. He wasn't kidding. About 15 minutes after Monday's news conference to announce the firing of Reeves, Young called the Arizona owner, Bill Bidwill, to seek permission to speak to Jim Fassel, the Cardinals' offensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Young has been given permission by Oakland to talk to Joe Bugel, the Raiders' assistant head coach and offensive coordinator.</p>
        <p>Young plans to fly to Arizona tomorrow to meet with Fassel and will probably interview Bugel late this week or early next week.</p>
        <p>Fassel, who will also draw interest from the Detroit Lions if they dismiss Wayne Fontes, released a statement yesterday saying he was given permission to speak with teams and will meet with the Giants in the near future. Young had no comment on the meeting.</p>
        <p>The Giants also plan to interview Sherman Lewis, the Green Bay offensive coordinator; Emmitt Thomas, the Philadelphia defensive coordinator, and Nick Saban, the Michigan State University head coach.</p>
        <p>There were rumors that the Giants had requested permission to speak to Marty Schottenheimer, the Kansas City Chiefs' coach, and that they were told that they could not because he is under contract with the team for another year. But several people within the Kansas City organization strongly denied that the Giants had called. Still, there is no question that the Giants are extremely interested in Schottenheimer.</p>
        <p>Reeves, who was fired on Monday by the Giants after four seasons as head coach, left with a 31-33 overall record.</p>
        <p>The next Giant head coach will have to know that the team's management system is going to remain intact and that he will have to work within it, something that Reeves was unable to do.</p>
        <p>Both Fassel, who was on the Giants' staff as the quarterbacks coach in 1991 and '92, and Bugel believe not only that they can work under those conditions but that the Giants have enough talent to win.</p>
        <p>Fassel is considered a rising star by many in the National Football League, and he has earned a reputation as a skilled worker with offenses and quarterbacks. Quarterback Boomer Esiason struggled in his last years with the Jets, but then he went to the Cardinals, worked with Fassel and had a great year. (This season, Esiason threw for more than 500 yards against Washington.)</p>
        <p>Reeves cut Kent Graham when he was with the Giants and signed Tommy Maddox, who was cut in the last preseason and is still out of the National Football League.</p>
        <p>Graham went to Detroit and sat on the bench. Then he went to the Cardinals, worked with Fassel and improved dramatically. Graham was told this week by the Arizona head coach, Vince Tobin, that he would be the starter going into next season.</p>
        <p>''I completely trust Jim,'' Graham said, ''and I think that trust is important in a coach-quarterback relationship. The Giants would be doing themselves a huge favor if they hired him.''</p>
        <p>Could the Giants, in hiring Fassel, get the next great offensive head coach? Is Fassel in the mold of Green Bay's Mike Holmgren (13-3 this year), Denver's Mike Shanahan (13-3), Washington's Norv Turner (9-7) and Cincinnati's Bruce Coslet (7-2)? The combined record of these coaches this season is 42-15.</p>
        <p>Bugel has a solid reputation, too. He is considered great with offensive lines, gaining that reputation while working with the Hogs of the Redskins in the 1980's. He is smart and knows how to handle the news media.</p>
        <p>If the Giants want to get Bugel, they may have to act quickly because is reportedly a candidate for the Raiders' head coaching job, vacated by Mike White yesterday. However, Bugel has had his differences with the Raiders' owner, Al Davis.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>GEORGE YOUNG had a final meeting with the assistant coaches on Monday and made it clear to many of them that they still are under contract with the team until another coach is hired and that teams will have to get permission from the Giants to speak with them.</p>
        <p>One last thing about the Giants' regular-season finale against New England. Running back DAVID MEGGETT, a former Giant and current Patriot, was in the Giants' locker room for almost an hour before Saturday's game, talking with players and others. He told them he wanted to come back to the Giants, whom he left for a multiyear contract with New England. But that will not happen.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
