<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sad Parade To Paradise In the Bronx</title>
    <meta content="25ABOU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="About New York" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="897551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="About New York"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DF1F31F936A15751C1A960958260" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sad Parade To Paradise In the Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE door to Chago's wooden shack, a tumbledown place where he sometimes slept, was slightly ajar. A candle flickered inside, illuminating the cramped space with slow-motion flares that glowed, then faded. Outside, the family garden plots lay in hibernation, awaiting next year with its promise of fragrant blossoms and fat tomatoes.</p>
        <p>A sign tied to the chain-link gate declared this corner of East 182d Street in the Crotona section of the Bronx to be the  ''Garden of Paradise.'' For Chago, it might as well have been the portal to the hereafter: he was shot to death inside his shack this month. His neighbors aren't sure why, since the 52-year-old man was a gentle character, the kind who would help people carry their groceries or pass the time with his friends slapping down dominoes on a table set up around the corner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE door to Chago's wooden shack, a tumbledown place where he sometimes slept, was slightly ajar. A candle flickered inside, illuminating the cramped space with slow-motion flares that glowed, then faded. Outside, the family garden plots lay in hibernation, awaiting next year with its promise of fragrant blossoms and fat tomatoes.</p>
        <p>A sign tied to the chain-link gate declared this corner of East 182d Street in the Crotona section of the Bronx to be the  ''Garden of Paradise.'' For Chago, it might as well have been the portal to the hereafter: he was shot to death inside his shack this month. His neighbors aren't sure why, since the 52-year-old man was a gentle character, the kind who would help people carry their groceries or pass the time with his friends slapping down dominoes on a table set up around the corner.</p>
        <p>His death, coming as it did during this sacred season, jarred the neighborhood. Yet, it also reminded the Rev. John Flynn and Lucy Laboy about the last year's relative tranquillity.</p>
        <p>It hasn't been like other times when Father Flynn was all too busy keeping track of the funeral Masses he had to say at St. Martin of Tours Roman Catholic Church for victims of violence, drugs or both. In the seven years he has been in the parish, he has seen death surround the church literally, with homicides being committed on the four streets that border it.</p>
        <p>''This year, I can't remember when we had the last,'' he said. ''In the last six months, we haven't had serious youth deaths.''</p>
        <p>He turned to Ms. Laboy, a parish volunteer, but she couldn't remember, either.</p>
        <p>''It was cool, thank God,'' she said. ''Oh, Father, it's been a long time. It's been peaceful.''</p>
        <p>THIS year, Father Flynn noticed something. He likes to ask the children in the parochial school how they feel about their community. What do they think about their borough? Like Mikey's stunned pals in those old cereal commercials, Father Flynn repeated their answer: They like it.</p>
        <p>''Once, young people never thought they would grow up to be old,'' he said. ''That's not been the case recently.''</p>
        <p>He left the rectory and walked, retracing a path on which he led his congregation recently during a prayer-and-song procession to the Garden of Paradise. People took candles, which they left behind in Chago's shack. It was an act of consecration.</p>
        <p>''We think God's cathedral is the world,'' he explained. ''We bless the whole thing with holy water and rededicate the world to the things that create. Like gardens, or houses. I think there are houses going up there.''</p>
        <p>Houses have already sprung up a few blocks away on East 179th Street, red-brick homes decorated with Santa faces, snowmen and blinking lights. Inside one lives Francisco Lopez, a veteran of some of Father Flynn's processions.</p>
        <p>This is his family's first Christmas in their new home. In 1994, just a few days before the Feast of the Three Kings on Jan. 6, which for many Hispanic families marks the true culmination of the season, a fire broke out in their old apartment building. Rumors were that it was drug-related.</p>
        <p>''The fire started right next door,'' said his son, Frankie Jr. ''They poured gasoline on the roof of the lady next door.''</p>
        <p>THE Lopez family ended up moving in with relatives for a while, until the building was repaired. But they never felt the same, and began applying for one of the new homes being built nearby. On June 27, they closed on the house and moved in. The same day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez and his wife, Lucy, now talk about organizing a block association, so the neighbors can look out for one another. They have fixed up their house -- a tidy, if modest, legacy for their children -- with a Christmas tree, holiday cards and a string of window lights. But Mr. Lopez still recalls the memory of the holiday season when he found himself burned out of his home. They lost everything, even the gifts they had exchanged the week before.</p>
        <p>''Today, the spirit of the holiday has been given almost a pagan meaning again when all we do is prepare by buying gifts,'' he said. ''The Holy Family had no place to go, either. They had no refuge. Nowhere for their child to be born. If we remember that, we could change.''</p>
        <p>Last night, the Lopez family went from their new home to Mass at St. Martin's. They heard the Gospel of St. Luke, in which shepherds beheld angelic heralds who shone in heavenly glory. On the streets of Crotona -- glorious by its very existence -- lights shone in many houses and one shack.</p>
        <p>About New York</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
