<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Lust and Honor Turn to Dust, Just Party On</title>
    <meta content="14SINS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1046428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CITY OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weill, Kurt (1900-50)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orff, Carl (1895-1982)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2D81531F937A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Lust and Honor Turn to Dust, Just Party On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews New York City Opera double bill of Kurt Weill's Seven Deadly Sins and Carl Orff's Carmina Burana; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In both message and structure, Kurt Weill's ''Seven Deadly Sins'' and Carl Orff's ''Carmina Burana,'' which returned to the New York City Opera repertory in a double bill on Saturday, are ideal companions. Weill's work, with its satirical libretto by Brecht, follows a young girl from Louisiana through the full cycle of sins and skewers the pieties of her family, who warn her against these evils but happily accept the money she makes along the way. The Orff, using bawdy Latin texts based on a collection composed by medieval German monks, wonders fleetingly about mortality, concludes that it doesn't matter, and leaps blithely into a celebration of hedonism.</p>
        <p>Each work begins with an arresting musical motif -- a jazzy one in the Weill, a pompously orchestrated magnification of ancient chant in the Orff -- that returns emphatically at the end. Between those bookends, each composer offers a set of slim, colorfully illustrated volumes on misbehavior. There is one jarring historical note. Brecht and Weill composed ''Sins'' in Paris in 1933, having just fled Hitler's Germany; Orff, a favorite and beneficiary of the Nazi regime, composed ''Carmina Burana'' in Germany in 1937. Oddly, that uneasy link supports the contention, shared by Brecht and the monks, that there is no profit in honor; that in the end, all is dust, the moral no less than the amoral.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In both message and structure, Kurt Weill's ''Seven Deadly Sins'' and Carl Orff's ''Carmina Burana,'' which returned to the New York City Opera repertory in a double bill on Saturday, are ideal companions. Weill's work, with its satirical libretto by Brecht, follows a young girl from Louisiana through the full cycle of sins and skewers the pieties of her family, who warn her against these evils but happily accept the money she makes along the way. The Orff, using bawdy Latin texts based on a collection composed by medieval German monks, wonders fleetingly about mortality, concludes that it doesn't matter, and leaps blithely into a celebration of hedonism.</p>
        <p>Each work begins with an arresting musical motif -- a jazzy one in the Weill, a pompously orchestrated magnification of ancient chant in the Orff -- that returns emphatically at the end. Between those bookends, each composer offers a set of slim, colorfully illustrated volumes on misbehavior. There is one jarring historical note. Brecht and Weill composed ''Sins'' in Paris in 1933, having just fled Hitler's Germany; Orff, a favorite and beneficiary of the Nazi regime, composed ''Carmina Burana'' in Germany in 1937. Oddly, that uneasy link supports the contention, shared by Brecht and the monks, that there is no profit in honor; that in the end, all is dust, the moral no less than the amoral.</p>
        <p>City Opera's stagings present this unedifying message for what it is. In ''Sins,'' the central character, Anna, is split in two: Anna I, who sings, is essentially Anna's conscience, although she is more practical than angelic; Anna II, who dances and speaks, is Anna's more purely physical, instinctive side. As Anna travels through America, Anna II gets caught up in the various sins -- Lechery in Boston, Avarice in Baltimore, Envy in San Francisco -- and Anna II leads her out of them. The family, gathered in a corner of the stage, comments on Anna's progress.</p>
        <p>James Schuette's costumes -- garish, clashing colors for the city dwellers, staid black for the family -- together with John Conklin's virtually bare sets, convey several varieties of emptiness. Anne Bogart's direction has the wit to make Anna seem both vulnerable and brazen, victim and victimizer. The vocal writing isn't strenuous, but Emily Golden sang Anna I's music vividly, and Ellen Lauren, as Anna II, danced with an energy that matched Ms. Golden's singing.</p>
        <p>With no characters, no plot and sparse solo singing, ''Carmina Burana'' is more cantata than opera. City Opera presents it as a ballet, its various misdeeds -- orgies, gang brutality and shooting up with heroin, among the most memorable -- staged graphically by Donald Byrd. Virginia Grasso, soprano, John Daniecki, tenor, and John Hancock, baritone, sang the solo lines ably. The principal dancers were Tom Gold, Fabrice Lemire and Marie-Christine Mouis. Nancy Brous gave the dancers colorful and often scant costumes; the chorus, seated in a pair of rolling galleries, wears monklike hoods.</p>
        <p>In the pit, Derrick Inouye got a suitably cabaret-like sound from the orchestra in the Weill. The Orff, conducted by Stewart Robertson, was strangely tepid. Greater emphasis on the score's faux grandeur would give it the edge it needs.</p>
        <p>CITY OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
