<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Emmys Go to 'Practice' and 'Frasier' as Top Series</title>
    <meta content="14EMMY$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980917T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1046511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emmy Awards</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braugher, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lahti, Christine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sterngold, James</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Practice, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frasier (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emmy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emmy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED91231F937A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Emmys Go to 'Practice' and 'Frasier' as Top Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sterngold, James</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Emmy Awards ceremonies held; winners include The Practice (Drama Series), Frasier (Comedy Series), Andre Braugher (Leading Actor in Drama Series) and Christine Lahti (Leading Actress in Drama Series); other winners listed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an evening that emphasized the nostalgia of the past rather than the immense uncertainty of the future of television, there were a number of surprise winners in the Emmy Awards here tonight and further signs that cable channels are making increasing creative inroads against the traditional broadcast networks.</p>
        <p>A new show, ''The Practice,'' the tale of a tough, young law firm, won as best drama series, a marked instance of new blood in this category. In the comedy-series category, ''Frasier,'' about an earnest radio therapist, Dr. Frasier Crane, set a record in taking the Emmy. It was the fifth consecutive Emmy for the show, the first time any show has won so many of the statuettes, breaking a record that had seemed as unassailable as Roger Maris's single-season home-run mark. Four shows had tied for the record, including ''Cheers,'' from which ''Frasier'' had been spun off.''Frasier,'' which runs on NBC, has won every year it has been on the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an evening that emphasized the nostalgia of the past rather than the immense uncertainty of the future of television, there were a number of surprise winners in the Emmy Awards here tonight and further signs that cable channels are making increasing creative inroads against the traditional broadcast networks.</p>
        <p>A new show, ''The Practice,'' the tale of a tough, young law firm, won as best drama series, a marked instance of new blood in this category. In the comedy-series category, ''Frasier,'' about an earnest radio therapist, Dr. Frasier Crane, set a record in taking the Emmy. It was the fifth consecutive Emmy for the show, the first time any show has won so many of the statuettes, breaking a record that had seemed as unassailable as Roger Maris's single-season home-run mark. Four shows had tied for the record, including ''Cheers,'' from which ''Frasier'' had been spun off.''Frasier,'' which runs on NBC, has won every year it has been on the air.</p>
        <p>In addition, Kelsey Grammer, who plays Frasier, and David Hyde Pierce, who plays his stuffy, emotionally repressed brother, Miles, took the Emmys as best lead actor in a comedy series and best supporting actor in a comedy series, respectively. Helen Hunt won her third Emmy as best lead actress in a comedy, for ''Mad About You,'' and best supporting actress went to Lisa Kudrow, the not always coherent Phoebe in ''Friends.''</p>
        <p>The best lead actor in a drama award went to Andre Braugher, who won his first Emmy in his last season as a tough detective in ''Homicide: Life on the Street.'' The Emmy for best lead actress in a drama went to Christine Lahti, a surgeon in ''Chicago Hope.'' This was the 50th anniversary of the telecast of the Emmys, which are presented by the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences. The ceremony was held at the Shrine Auditorium near downtown Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The program this year was heavier on nostalgia than usual, with a series of clips and moments commemorating people like the Marx Brothers and Ed Sullivan, and shows like ''Gunsmoke,'' ''Father Knows Best'' and ''American Bandstand.'' There was a long standing ovation when Bob Hope, Milton Berle and Sid Caesar appeared together onstage. The presenters also showed the moment when it was revealed who shot J. R. on ''Dallas'' 18 years ago.</p>
        <p>The academy and television executives were eager to focus on creative achievements rather than the uncertainty of the future of a medium being fragmented by many new channels and squabbles that have taken place behind the scenes for several years.</p>
        <p>They were pleased that a number of new shows won nominations and that first-time actors took some of the Emmys. Several people also noted that, in addition to ''Frasier's'' setting a record, the writer and producer David E. Kelley also came close to setting one. He was the first producer ever to have two shows, one drama, ''The Practice,'' and one comedy, ''Ally McBeal,'' nominated for best series in their categories. Though just one of the shows won the award, it was regarded as a striking creative achievement and a sign of the vibrancy of the medium.</p>
        <p>But there were reminders of simmering resentments within the industry.</p>
        <p>One of the more striking victories was in the mini-series category, long dominated by the broadcast networks. This year four of the five Emmy nominees were from cable channels.</p>
        <p>The winner, the 12-part, hugely expensive ''From the Earth to the Moon,'' was produced by HBO and had stirred up a bitter debate even before the ceremony.</p>
        <p>Some network executives had complained that the program, of which Tom Hanks was executive producer, did not technically qualify as a mini-series, but those charges were rejected by the academy. The only network nominee this year was NBC's ''Merlin.''</p>
        <p>HBO also continued its streak in the original movie category. The channel won in this category for the sixth consecutive year for ''Don King: Only in America.'' That movie also won for best writing, with a script by Kario Salem.</p>
        <p>Last year, some network executives had pushed to have the cable channels placed in a separate original-movie category because of allegations that they could spend more money than the broadcast networks on their films. The academy also rejected that campaign.</p>
        <p>NBC received some consolation in the fact that it took more Emmys, 18, than any other company. ABC trailed with 16 and HBO came in third with 14.</p>
        <p>Camryn Manheim, the earnest lawyer, Ellenor Frutt, in ''The Practice,'' took the Emmy for best supporting actress in a drama series. In one of the more memorable acceptance speeches of the evening, the heavyset Ms. Manheim thanked her friends and supporters, asked if she could get the autographs of her fellow nominees, then shouted, ''This is for all the fat girls!''</p>
        <p>The Emmy for best supporting actor in a drama went to Gordon Clapp, Detective Greg Medavoy in ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.'' It was Ms. Manheim's first time nominated and Mr. Clapp's second.</p>
        <p>Peter Tolan and Garry Shandling took the honor as best writers in a comedy series for ''The Larry Sanders Show.'' It was the first Emmy Mr. Shandling had won after having garnered 19 nominations over the years.</p>
        <p>Similarly, ''Late Show With David Letterman'' won the Emmy for best variety, music or comedy series, the first time it has taken an Emmy after 19 fruitless nominations in various categories.</p>
        <p>The Emmy for best actor in a movie or mini-series went to Gary Sinise for ''George Wallace.'' He had been nominated previously for his role as Harry Truman in ''Truman.'' The Emmy for best actress in a movie or mini-series went to Ellen Barkin for her role in ''Before Women Had Wings.''</p>
        <p>Winners of the 1998 Emmy Awards</p>
        <p>Drama series:</p>
        <p>''The Practice,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Comedy series:</p>
        <p>''Frasier,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Mini-series:</p>
        <p>''From the Earth to the Moon,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Variety, music or comedy series:</p>
        <p>''Late Show With David Letterman,'' CBS</p>
        <p>''Variety, music or comedy special:</p>
        <p>''The 1997 Tony Awards,'' CBS</p>
        <p>Made-for-television movie:</p>
        <p>''Don King: Only in America,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Leading actor, drama series:</p>
        <p>Andre Braugher, ''Homicide,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Leading actress, drama series:</p>
        <p>Christine Lahti, ''Chicago Hope,'' CBS</p>
        <p>Leading actor, comedy series:</p>
        <p>Kelsey Grammer, ''Frasier,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Leading actress, comedy series:</p>
        <p>Helen Hunt, ''Mad About You,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Leading actor, mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>Gary Sinise, ''George Wallace,'' TNT</p>
        <p>Leading actress, mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>Ellen Barkin, ''Before Women Had Wings,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Supporting actor, drama series:</p>
        <p>Gordon Clapp, ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Supporting actress, drama series:</p>
        <p>Camryn Manheim, ''The Practice,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Supporting actor, comedy series</p>
        <p>David Hyde Pierce, ''Frasier,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Supporting actress, comedy series:</p>
        <p>Lisa Kudrow, ''Friends,'' NBC</p>
        <p>Supporting actor, mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>George C. Scott, ''12 Angry Men,'' Showtime</p>
        <p>Supporting actress, mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>Mare Winningham, ''George Wallace,'' TNT</p>
        <p>Performance in a variety or music program:</p>
        <p>Billy Crystal, ''The 70th Annual Academy Awards,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Directing, drama series:</p>
        <p>Mark Tinker, ''Brooklyn South: Pilot,'' CBS, and Paris Barclay, ''N.Y.P.D. Blue: Lost Israel, Part II,'' ABC (tie)</p>
        <p>Directing, comedy series:</p>
        <p>Todd Holland, ''The Larry Sanders Show: Flip,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Directing, variety or music program:</p>
        <p>Louis J. Horvitz, ''The 70th Annual Academy Awards,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Directing, mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>John Frankenheimer, ''George Wallace,'' TNT</p>
        <p>Writing, drama series:</p>
        <p>Nicholas Wootton and David Milch, ''N.Y.P.D. Blue: Lost Israel, Part II,'' ABC</p>
        <p>Writing, comedy series:</p>
        <p>Peter Tolan and Garry Shandling, ''The Larry Sanders Show: Flip,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Writing, variety or music program:</p>
        <p>Eddie Feldmann, Dennis Miller, David Feldman, Leah Krinsky, Jim Hanna, David Weiss and Jose Arroyo, ''Dennis Miller Live,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Writing for a mini-series or movie:</p>
        <p>Kario Salem, ''Don King: Only in America,'' HBO</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 17, 1998, Thursday  A list of this year's Emmy Awards on Tuesday and in some copies on Monday omitted one of those honored for writing for a drama series.  Along with Nicholas Wootton and David Milch, Bill Clark received the Emmy for work on an episode of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 17, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>A list of this year's Emmy Awards on Tuesday and in some copies on Monday omitted one of those honored for writing for a drama series.  Along with Nicholas Wootton and David Milch, Bill Clark received the Emmy for work on an episode of ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
