<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prospect Park's Ravine Inching Closer to Past</title>
    <meta content="14RAVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1046489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Prospect Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olmsted, Frederick Law (1822-1903)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vaux, Calvert (1824-1895)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E1DB1231F937A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prospect Park's Ravine Inching Closer to Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Prospect Park's Ravine as one of New York City's most intriguing works in progress; its long-envisioned reconstruction began three years ago and it may not be regularly open to public for a decade but on tightly controlled basis, people are beginning to see results of ambitious restoration of landscape designed by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, project that has already cost $4.5 million and is likely to cost at least that much more; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prospect Park's Ravine is one of the city's most intriguing works in progress. Its long-envisioned reconstruction began three years ago, and it may not be regularly open to the public for a decade.</p>
        <p>But on a tightly controlled basis, people are starting to see the results of the ambitious restoration of a landscape designed by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, a project that has already cost $4.5 million and is likely to cost at least that much more. Beginning with members of the Brooklyn park's committee of community advisers on Saturday, and continuing with twice-daily tours for the general public on weekends through November, people will witness the revival of a manmade landscape that had almost died through years of neglect and mismanagement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prospect Park's Ravine is one of the city's most intriguing works in progress. Its long-envisioned reconstruction began three years ago, and it may not be regularly open to the public for a decade.</p>
        <p>But on a tightly controlled basis, people are starting to see the results of the ambitious restoration of a landscape designed by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux, a project that has already cost $4.5 million and is likely to cost at least that much more. Beginning with members of the Brooklyn park's committee of community advisers on Saturday, and continuing with twice-daily tours for the general public on weekends through November, people will witness the revival of a manmade landscape that had almost died through years of neglect and mismanagement.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing how long it needs to be closed,'' said Julia Kristella, a magazine editor who took her 10-year-old son, Sam, through the project. ''But when my son is 20, it will be wonderful. This will be a legacy for our kids.''</p>
        <p>The Ravine is the spine of Prospect Park, a park whose design Olmsted and Vaux considered superior to their plan for Central Park.</p>
        <p>Beginning with a waterfall just south of the park's Long Meadow, it has a meandering stream, steep gorges and glistening pools -- all intended to give the impression of a walk in the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>Like the Ramble in Central Park, the Ravine is the dark, secluded, mysterious counterpoint to adjacent open vistas. All this was fashioned in the 1860's and 1870's from nondescript farmland.</p>
        <p>''Though you hate to say it, Olmsted and Vaux might have been the first Walt Disney,'' said Tupper W. Thomas, the administrator of Prospect Park.</p>
        <p>''They created an experience of nature that was not natural. Originally, there were just kettle ponds here. They made lakes, rivers and springs. They made a forest.''</p>
        <p>But their achievement inexorably deteriorated. Within a few decades their delightful rustic bridges and shelters, built with rough-hewn logs, were battered by overuse; ultimately they were replaced with utilitarian concrete. The steep mountainlike slopes fostered terrible erosion, as hillsides became rock-hard. Some of the exotic plants chosen by Olmsted to give the area a tropical feel proved disastrous. A 1960's policy of removing ground cover and smaller vegetation and planting grass instead hastened the erosion.</p>
        <p>The restoration has so far involved the planting of 7,000 shrubs, 12,000 trees and 161,000 smaller plants. More intriguingly, steps, waterfalls and streams were painstakingly reconstructed. Since the park's original plans were destroyed in the 1930's, this had to be done on the basis of historical photographs. Each rock, from huge boulders to smaller stones, was numbered. Beyond this, the preservationists read essays and other writings by Olmsted and Vaux, trying to fathom their intentions.</p>
        <p>''On the eve of the 21st century, this is bringing the 19th century back to Prospect Park,'' said Henry J. Stern, the Parks Commissioner. ''It's retro, but beautiful.''</p>
        <p>Now, nature is being asked to take its course. Since last spring, verdant shrubbery around waterfalls has made them almost exactly resemble 19th-century photographs of the park.</p>
        <p>This is the landscape people are beginning to visit. Tours will be at 1 and 3 P.M. on Saturdays and Sundays through November, and if the weather is warm, into December. Then, the area will be closed again. Maybe there will be more tours in the spring.</p>
        <p>The ongoing work is being financed principally by Howard Golden, the Brooklyn Borough President. He suggested the current viewings will build further support.</p>
        <p>''Now, after more than two years behind closed fences, the forest has been reopened so the millions of visitors to the park each year can see what the visionaries planned: an oasis of nature and wildlife in the heart of Brooklyn for all to enjoy.''</p>
        <p>On Saturday's tour, evidence of progress ranged from the bulldozers being used on the latest stage of major restoration to the new wildflowers waving in the breeze next to the stream. Children thrilled to count 16 frogs on the side of a lake that had been in danger of vanishing beneath erosion and invasive weeds.</p>
        <p>''I was so surprised to see how deep the ravine went,'' said Laurie Chin, one of the adults on the tour. Until recently, it had been almost completely filled in.</p>
        <p>Some seemed lost in the moment, saying they almost felt they were time-traveling. ''You have a sense of refuge; at the same time you lose your sense of place,'' said Curtis Cravens, a photo editor who was pushing his 3-year-old daughter in a stroller.</p>
        <p>A high point of the trip was meeting Dennis Madge, who is building a rustic shelter atop the hill overlooking the largest waterfall. Mr. Madge, a craftsman from Cleveland, N.Y., is hewing cedar and tamarack logs into a hexagonal structure, with financing in part from the State Parks Department. The roof will be open and there will be four benches inside. Almost all of his hand tools are traditional. He is building the shelter to be especially sturdy, because he is positive that children will climb it.</p>
        <p>On top of Mr. Madge's hill, it is quiet and nothing is visible but the scene dreamed by Olmsted and Vaux. ''You certainly don't feel you're in the middle of New York City,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As the walk progressed, children were transfixed by a large hole in a hillside that Ms. Thomas said had long been a mystery. Many people, she said, thought trolls lived inside.</p>
        <p>An explicit message is that time will change everything. Vistas will disappear and views will change dramatically, as shrubs and trees fill in gaps and reach outward and upward. Nobody feels the living nature of the creation more than the volunteers -- a couple of dozen each weekend and thousands over the course of a year -- who work in the woodlands, building cribs, dumping wood chips and mulch, and pulling weeds.</p>
        <p>''I feel virtuous when I see a tree growing we planted,'' said Bill Miller, a history professor at the State University of New York at Stonybrook who visits each week to work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
