<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Groups Ask F.C.C. To Reconsider NBC Ruling</title>
    <meta content="20TUBE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/20/business/media/20tube.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1575573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Profanity</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bono (Musician)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Profanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Communications Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040420T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DA1E3BF933A15757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Groups Ask F.C.C. To Reconsider NBC Ruling</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Media Groups Ask F.C.C. to Reconsider NBC Ruling</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group representing 24 media organizations and individual performers asks FCC to reconsider its ruling against NBC for violating decendy standards; charges that politically tinged campaign against indecency is having chilling effect on television and radio programming; NBC files separate petition seeking to overturn decision, which found that NBC had run afoul of federal decency standards by broadcasting a single vulgarity by singer Bono during live awards program; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charging that a politically tinged campaign against indecency is having a chilling effect on television and radio programming, a group representing 24 media organizations and individual performers filed a petition yesterday asking the Federal Communications Commission to reconsider its ruling against NBC for violating decency standards.</p>
        <p>NBC filed a separate petition yesterday seeking to overturn the decision, which found that NBC had run afoul of federal decency standards by broadcasting a single vulgarity by the singer Bono during a live awards program. The actions, which were first reported in The Wall Street Journal, were mere formalities for a court challenge. In neither case do the petitioners, who include Viacom, the News Corporation and the American Civil Liberties Union, hold out much hope that the F.C.C. will reverse the decision although it must review it. But as the case is expected to be appealed in court on First Amendment grounds, the court cannot be brought in until the reconsideration is decided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group representing 24 media organizations filed a petition asking the Federal Communications Commission to reconsider its ruling against NBC for violating decency standards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charging that a politically tinged campaign against indecency is having a chilling effect on television and radio programming, a group representing 24 media organizations and individual performers filed a petition yesterday asking the Federal Communications Commission to reconsider its ruling against NBC for violating decency standards.</p>
        <p>NBC filed a separate petition yesterday seeking to overturn the decision, which found that NBC had run afoul of federal decency standards by broadcasting a single vulgarity by the singer Bono during a live awards program. The actions, which were first reported in The Wall Street Journal, were mere formalities for a court challenge. In neither case do the petitioners, who include Viacom, the News Corporation and the American Civil Liberties Union, hold out much hope that the F.C.C. will reverse the decision although it must review it. But as the case is expected to be appealed in court on First Amendment grounds, the court cannot be brought in until the reconsideration is decided.</p>
        <p>David Fiske, a spokesman for the F.C.C., said the commission never comments on reconsideration petitions.</p>
        <p>The case involves a comment made by Bono after winning a Golden Globe Award in 2003, when he used a vulgarity as an adjective to express his elation. Initially the F.C.C. ruled that this was not a violation, but that decision outraged some viewers who flooded the commission with letters of protest. Last month, the F.C.C. reversed course -- and only rejected ordering a fine be levied against NBC by the margin of one vote.</p>
        <p>Executives involved in the petitions claimed that the ''political climate'' was responsible for what they labeled a broad and hopelessly vague standard for decency in programming, which has driven broadcasters to take drastic steps to limit the content of programs they broadcast. Awards programs, including the Academy Awards, have been put on delays; some songs long played on the radio, like ''Who Are You'' by the Who, have been removed because they contain vulgarities.</p>
        <p>Robert C. Wright, the chairman of NBC, who wrote an op-ed column on the subject in The Wall Street Journal yesterday, said in an interview that his goal in challenging the F.C.C. decision was ''to get some people thinking about this issue.'' He noted that in its 75 years, NBC has never been fined for any reason.</p>
        <p>F. William LeBeau, the senior regulatory counsel for NBC, called the change signaled by the F.C.C. decision in this case ''sweeping and unprecedented in the annals of First Amendment law.''</p>
        <p>The groups taking part in the separate petition include the biggest union representing television performers, the three Hollywood guilds representing actors, directors and writers, and even individual entertainers like the comedian Margaret Cho and the magicians Penn and Teller.</p>
        <p>Robert Corn-Revere, the lawyer who filed the petition on behalf of the non-NBC groups, said the F.C.C. decision had moved the policing of offensive speech away from what previous court decisions had intended. ''It was meant to be cautious; now it's become expansive and draconian.''</p>
        <p>He said the decision left open the possibility that any live news event, like a war protest at one of the political conventions this year where someone utters a vulgarity, or any live sports event where fans hold up signs containing objectionable words, could leave a broadcaster subject to serious fines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fiske of the F.C.C. said on the issue of live news and sports coverage: ''I don't think the commission addressed it. Maybe there would be a distinction for news or sports.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corn-Revere said the decision also made it possible for a politically motivated government ''to go after a speaker they don't like.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corn-Revere, who is a First Amendment lawyer, would not say which organization initially engaged him to pursue the petition, saying, ''Anyone who stands alone risks the wrath of the government.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
