<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Memorial That's True to 9/11</title>
    <meta content="19FISC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/19/opinion/19FISC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1544298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Op-Ed Contributor"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischl, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D8173FF93AA25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Memorial That's True to 9/11</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Memorial Thats True to 9/11</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Fischl</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischl, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Eric Fischl, artist, on what constitutes appropriate expression for tragedy of 9/11; says none of designs he has seen for memorial at World Trade Center site reflect tragedy of that day or inspire us to confront it; says these sanitized designs fail to capture destruction and injustice of that day; says each design puts too much emphasis on towers themselves and not on victims; says perhaps not enough time has passed to absorb tragedy and come to terms with our loss (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like many people touched by 9/11, I'm still mourning the loss of a dear friend who worked on the 106th floor of one of the twin towers. Last year, to honor my friend's memory and those of the thousands of others who died, I created a sculpture titled ''Tumbling Woman,'' a bronze statue of a naked woman in perpetual free fall. If it sounds familiar, that's probably because you remember the fuss it caused. About a week after it was installed at Rockefeller Center, the sculpture was removed. ''Too soon to be seen'' is what I was told as the piece was being draped with a cloth and taken away. Perhaps.</p>
        <p>As you can imagine, the experience led me to think about what constitutes an appropriate expression for tragedy. As an artist and an American, one question still preoccupies me: if we cannot face what happened, how can we move past it?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>None of the memorial proposals reflect the tragedy of that day or inspire us to confront it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like many people touched by 9/11, I'm still mourning the loss of a dear friend who worked on the 106th floor of one of the twin towers. Last year, to honor my friend's memory and those of the thousands of others who died, I created a sculpture titled ''Tumbling Woman,'' a bronze statue of a naked woman in perpetual free fall. If it sounds familiar, that's probably because you remember the fuss it caused. About a week after it was installed at Rockefeller Center, the sculpture was removed. ''Too soon to be seen'' is what I was told as the piece was being draped with a cloth and taken away. Perhaps.</p>
        <p>As you can imagine, the experience led me to think about what constitutes an appropriate expression for tragedy. As an artist and an American, one question still preoccupies me: if we cannot face what happened, how can we move past it?</p>
        <p>At any moment the decision will be made as to who will design the memorial at the World Trade Center site. Based on what I have seen, none of the proposals will reflect the tragedy of that day or inspire us to confront it. They do not speak of the cruelty and the horror, of the vulnerability and desperation, of the valor and sacrifice. Above all, they fail to capture the destruction and injustice. In fact, these sanitized designs could be memorials to anything almost anywhere.</p>
        <p>Maybe the finalists who designed the proposals were overwhelmed by the success of the Vietnam Memorial, or maybe their modernist sensibilities could not tolerate the messiness of what happened that day. Maybe it was because the bodies of most of the victims vanished in the destruction. That might help explain why each design puts too much emphasis on the towers themselves. By trying to honor the buildings' footprints, and by placing the intimate and sacred memorial spaces underground, covered with a false sense of tranquillity, they are regrettably doing what the attack did to the people inside: making them disappear. Not only is the coffin being put in the ground, the tombstone is being buried along with it.</p>
        <p>We need to learn how to tell the story of 9/11. After all, a memorial should be more than a marker at a grave site. It should be a narrative. Imagine if the Gettysburg battlefield were a sound and light show, or if the Alamo were a park with reflecting ponds instead of the remains of the old structure. Narratives help keep the meaning and significance of great historical events vital. They inspire us in their retelling. They reinforce our resolve.</p>
        <p>Ground zero is big enough to contain several memorials. Reconstruct the twisted and charred steel facade of One World Trade, return the battered bronze globe that now sits in Battery Park to the center of the plaza where it once stood, and keep the slurry wall exposed. We need to allow space for monuments that capture the drama, images that haunt us and objects that carry the scars of their survival. In other words, we need to memorialize what really happened on Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>Part of the outcry I heard against my sculpture last year was that it was art, and art belongs in museums, not public spaces. But what, then, is the purpose of art? Art has always served to bring form to what is experienced but cannot be seen. It recreates things that have happened and moves them forward into a new light. It brings order to chaos and clarity to confusion. Let us hope that the memorial will seek to include true artistic expression in its final configuration.</p>
        <p>In the end, I'm not sure we are ready to finalize the design of the memorial. Perhaps not enough time has passed to absorb the tragedy and come to terms with our loss. In a few brutal seconds, the collapsing towers robbed us of family members, friends and fellow citizens. We can't allow a memorial to do the same.</p>
        <p>Op-Ed Contributor Eric Fischl is an artist. His paintings are collected in ''Eric Fischl, 1970-2000.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Fischl is an artist. His paintings are collected in ''Eric Fischl, 1970-2000.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
