<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Not Done, Even With Cameron</title>
    <meta content="19METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/19/sports/baseball/19METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1544353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duquette, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cameron, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Cameron, Mike</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Duquette, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1DC143FF93AA25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Not Done, Even With Cameron</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Not Done, Even With Cameron</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets general manager Jim Duquette says Mets' acquisition of center fielder Mike Cameron is not likely to be final move before next season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Mike Cameron rotated from one television interview to another, with Shea Stadium's field as a backdrop beyond the Diamond Club windows, Jim Duquette addressed a crowd of reporters yesterday near a small stage. Duquette, the Mets' general manager, had little time to boast about how Cameron completed the team's defense.</p>
        <p>With Cameron officially signed, Duquette has moved onto Saturday's deadline for teams to offer contracts to players, referred to as nontenders, who are eligible for arbitration and can become free agents if they remain unsigned. Working with a payroll of about $80 million for next season, Duquette said it was a long shot for the Mets to lure any of the premier free agents like Vladimir Guerrero. So, Duquette is poised to fill the Mets' remaining holes -- starting pitcher, closer and right fielder -- around those nontenders. It is a modest route to compete with the Phillies, who Duquette called the division's most improved team, and the Braves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Mike Cameron officially signed, General Manager Jim Duquette is poised to fill the Mets remaining holes: starting pitcher, closer and right fielder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Mike Cameron rotated from one television interview to another, with Shea Stadium's field as a backdrop beyond the Diamond Club windows, Jim Duquette addressed a crowd of reporters yesterday near a small stage. Duquette, the Mets' general manager, had little time to boast about how Cameron completed the team's defense.</p>
        <p>With Cameron officially signed, Duquette has moved onto Saturday's deadline for teams to offer contracts to players, referred to as nontenders, who are eligible for arbitration and can become free agents if they remain unsigned. Working with a payroll of about $80 million for next season, Duquette said it was a long shot for the Mets to lure any of the premier free agents like Vladimir Guerrero. So, Duquette is poised to fill the Mets' remaining holes -- starting pitcher, closer and right fielder -- around those nontenders. It is a modest route to compete with the Phillies, who Duquette called the division's most improved team, and the Braves.</p>
        <p>Duquette said a lot can happen between now and Saturday's deadline. ''If not, then I'll be patient enough for the nontender list to be filed,'' he said. ''I believe there is a lot of quality that's going to be nontendered.''</p>
        <p>Reliever Scott Williamson could be set free, and Duquette spoke with the Red Sox at last week's winter meetings about trading for him to be the Mets' closer. Duquette said yesterday that he came close to trading for a closer on Wednesday night before the deal fell through, and a baseball official familiar with those discussions indicated it was for Williamson.</p>
        <p>Williamson saved 21 games for Cincinnati last season before being traded to Boston in July and becoming their setup man. Keith Foulke signed this month to be the Red Sox's closer, making Williamson a luxury.</p>
        <p>Duquette is also carrying on the Mets' yearlong quest to trade Roger Cedeño, whom the Mets project as a $5 million reserve outfielder. The Mets may be forced to pay part of Cedeño's contract, or take on more salary in return in a Cedeño trade.</p>
        <p>Duquette spoke with the Indians after the season about trading Cedeño for the former Met Matt Lawton, who will earn $7 million and $7.75 million the next two seasons. But Cleveland refuses to do an even exchange because Cedeño is not as good a player as Lawton and the savings would have to be reinvested into recouping Lawton's production.</p>
        <p>Without knowing who will playing next to him in right field, Cameron expects a big turnaround from the Mets. He chose them over the Padres and the Athletics, who offered four-year deals worth at least $20 million. Cameron met with the three teams last Friday in New Orleans during the winter meetings. Cameron, who has co-authored a motivational book for children, ''It Takes a Team,'' which includes a top-10 list on how to be a good teammate, sold himself to the Mets chief operating officer, Jeff Wilpon, who authorized raising the Mets' $18 million, three-year offer to $19.5 million with a club option.</p>
        <p>Cameron, 30, weighed the mixed reviews of New York he had heard last season in the Mariners' clubhouse from the former Mets John Olerud (positive) and Armando Benitez and Rey Sanchez (not positive) with the endorsements of Mets pitchers Tom Glavine, Al Leiter and John Franco. He chose the Mets because New York is about an hour and a half flight from his home outside Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Cameron's contract is for $4 million next season and $6 million in 2005 and 2006, with a $3 million signing bonus and a $500,000 buyout. With the recently signed shortstop Kazuo Matsui and with José Reyes's moving to second base, the Mets have ''one of the strongest defensive middles in the game,'' Duquette said.</p>
        <p>Cameron earned his second Gold Glove last season and is second to Atlanta's Andruw Jones in putouts by a center fielder over the last five seasons. ''I don't walk on the field and proclaim to be the best center fielder that ever played the game,'' Cameron said. ''I just play, man, I just play, and I have confidence in what I can do with the glove.''</p>
        <p>A career .250 hitter, Cameron struck out 137 times in 534 at-bats last season while hitting .253 with 18 home runs, 76 runs batted in and 17 stolen bases.</p>
        <p>Cameron attributes his low average to his troubles seeing the baseball amid the glare at Safeco Field in Seattle. Beginning in 2000, Cameron hit .223 with 30 homers, a .328 on-base percentage and a .373 slugging percentage at home and .286 with 57 home runs, a .370 on-base percentage and a .514 slugging percentage on the road. The Mariners addressed the problem by covering the batter's eye beyond the center-field fence with a black honeycomb surface during the All-Star Game break last July.</p>
        <p>Shea Stadium and its windswept outfield is more friendly to pitchers than hitters, but Cameron said he was happy to make it home. In the coming days, Duquette hopes to give him some help in right field.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
