<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Tiger Man to Sharp-Dressed Man for His Day in Court</title>
    <meta content="19TIGE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/19/nyregion/19TIGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1544357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saulny, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yates, Antoine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDC143FF93AA25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Tiger Man to Sharp-Dressed Man for His Day in Court</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">From Tiger Man to Sharp-Dressed Man for His Day in Court</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antoine Yates, who is accused of keeping tiger in Harlem (NYC) apartment and reckless endangerment, appears in court and faces seven years in prison if convicted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Antoine Yates, the person who has come to be known as Tiger Man for housing his 400-pound Bengal tiger in a Harlem apartment, showed up at Manhattan Criminal Court yesterday in high style.</p>
        <p>In his last court appearance, he looked bedraggled in white sweat pants and a sling, but this time Mr. Yates's outfit consisted of a striking monochromatic white shirt-and-tie combination under a dark suit. He topped the look with a hat, a black bowler, and a splash of color -- a red feather, to match his red earring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Antoine Yates, the person who has come to be known as Tiger Man for housing his 400-pound Bengal tiger in a Harlem apartment, showed up at Manhattan Criminal Court yesterday in high style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Antoine Yates, the person who has come to be known as Tiger Man for housing his 400-pound Bengal tiger in a Harlem apartment, showed up at Manhattan Criminal Court yesterday in high style.</p>
        <p>In his last court appearance, he looked bedraggled in white sweat pants and a sling, but this time Mr. Yates's outfit consisted of a striking monochromatic white shirt-and-tie combination under a dark suit. He topped the look with a hat, a black bowler, and a splash of color -- a red feather, to match his red earring.</p>
        <p>Then there was the entourage, consisting of a state assemblyman, a defense lawyer from a high-profile Manhattan firm and a special assistant for the assemblyman. Then there was the private security team, consisting of beefy bodyguards clearing a path from car to courtroom, one in a full-length fur coat.</p>
        <p>People going about their business inside the court building, at 100 Centre Street, wondered about the identity of the man and clamored for a better look. It seemed clear that Mr. Yates, jobless and homeless, had, with the help of his handlers, made a savvy transition from oddball defendant to celebrity-in-waiting.</p>
        <p>Reporters chatted up his team. Newspaper photographers snapped his picture.</p>
        <p>''Antoine is, despite his characterization, not a kook,'' said the assemblyman, Keith L. T. Wright, who represents the 70th District in Harlem. ''I'm here to show support as his assemblyperson, to help him find a job, possibly with animals.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yates, 37, was arrested in October on charges of reckless endangerment and the possession of a wild animal.</p>
        <p>He could face seven years in prison if convicted on the charges, which stemmed from the discovery of Ming, his tiger, in his apartment in a public housing complex.</p>
        <p>The case came to light after Mr. Yates called police claiming to have been bitten by a pit bull. They managed to remove Ming after a sharpshooter shot him with tranquilizer darts.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Yates said that he was keeping the tiger ''to show the whole world that we could all get along.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yates's lawyer, Ray Colon, is a member of the Cochran Firm, which was founded by the noted lawyer Johnnie L. Cochran Jr. He is handling the case without a fee. Yesterday, he said he was ready for trial, but Mr. Yates has not yet been indicted.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the Manhattan district attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau, said the case was still under investigation. Mr. Colon said he ''can't speculate about what their case is.''</p>
        <p>A reporter suggested that the case was about keeping a dangerous animal in a housing complex.</p>
        <p>The reporter then asked Mr. Colon what his defense strategy might be.</p>
        <p>''The Constitution is our defense,'' he said. ''The onus is on the district attorney. We're ready to go to trial.''</p>
        <p>For all the fanfare of Mr. Yates's appearance, it was a routine court appointment that turned out to be much ado about nothing, since the case was adjourned without action until April 7.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
