<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Peace Talks in Geneva, a Few Scraps of Hope</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GENEVA (SWITZERLAND)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SARAJEVO (BOSNIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIDING, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland/Geneva</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DC173CF931A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Peace Talks in Geneva, a Few Scraps of Hope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIDING, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Aug. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bosnian Muslim leaders boycotted peace talks again today to protest the Serbian seizure of two strategic mountains outside Sarajevo, but evidence that Serbian troops were at last withdrawing raised hopes that negotiations would resume on Thursday.</p>
        <p>President Alija Izetbegovic of Bosnia, who heads the Muslim delegation, told reporters that there were "some signs" that the Serbs were pulling back, but "we insist they withdraw completely."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bosnian Muslim leaders boycotted peace talks again today to protest the Serbian seizure of two strategic mountains outside Sarajevo, but evidence that Serbian troops were at last withdrawing raised hopes that negotiations would resume on Thursday.</p>
        <p>President Alija Izetbegovic of Bosnia, who heads the Muslim delegation, told reporters that there were "some signs" that the Serbs were pulling back, but "we insist they withdraw completely."</p>
        <p>A United Nations spokesman said the international mediators, Lord Owen for the European Community and Thorvald Stoltenberg for the United Nations, also told the Serbian leader, Radovan Karadzic, "in very clear terms" that the withdrawal must be completed by mid-morning Thursday. Moving In the U.N. Troops</p>
        <p>"United Nations troops will then monitor and report any effort by Bosnian Government forces to return," the spokesman, John Mills, said. "President Izetbegovic said his troops will not enter the areas vacated by Serbian forces. This situation will be reviewed tomorrow morning with a view to restarting negotiations."</p>
        <p>Mr. Izetbegovic withdrew from the talks on Aug. 1 after Bosnian Serbs seized Mount Igman and Mount Bjelasnica, at the southern entrance to the capital. Since then, he has met almost daily with the mediators but not with Dr. Karadzic or the Bosnian Croat leader, Mate Boban.</p>
        <p>Before the suspension, however, the parties agreed on the constitutional framework of a new "union" of three autonomous ethnic republics, and United Nations officials are confident they can pick up where the talks left off. An Agreement in Sarajevo</p>
        <p>Lord Owen and Mr. Stoltenberg were also cheered by a broad military agreement reached early today in Sarajevo by the commanders of the three sides, covering the withdrawal of troops and heavy weapons, the clearing of mines and international monitoring of compliance.</p>
        <p>"This agreement," Mr. Mills said, "means that the current peace process until now has achieved agreement with the political and military leadership of the three parties on all aspects of the settlement except for the map."</p>
        <p>But agreement on the map involves defining how much territory will be assigned to each group and assuring communication between Muslim enclaves and Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>The status of Sarajevo must also be worked out. The Serbs have proposed dividing the city; the Muslims insist that it remain united. The mediators say some temporary solution in which the city would remain a United Nations-protected "safe area" may be necessary for a year or more. A Whiff of Optimism</p>
        <p>Despite these obstacles and the long record of cease-fire violations since the Bosnian war began 16 months ago, United Nations officials dared to be optimistic about a settlement.</p>
        <p>Reflecting the belief that the talks are reaching a watershed, the special United States envoy for the former Yugoslavia, Reginald Bartholomew, and his newly named successor, Charles E. Redman, met today with the mediators and with the leaders of the Bosnian delegations.</p>
        <p>At a meeting Tuesday with Dr. Karadzic, Mr. Redman gave him a copy of the statement issued Monday in Brussels after NATO approved the use of military force -- specifically air strikes -- to prevent Sarajevo from being strangled by Serbian forces.</p>
        <p>Dr. Karadzic, who has accused President Izetbegovic of stalling in the hope of a NATO air strike on Serbian positions, has warned that any attack on his forces would lead to a rapid widening of the war.</p>
        <p>He also angrily denied reports late Tuesday that Serbian forces on Mount Igman were being reinforced, saying one Serbian unit had been replaced "because they were wet and tired" and asserting that Bosnian Muslims had delayed the withdrawal by taking over areas abandoned by the Serbs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
