<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; A Little Girl With a Big Talent, and How She Grew</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JEFFERSON, MARGO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARLAND, JUDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHIPMAN, DAVID</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">JUDY GARLAND: THE SECRET LIFE OF AN AMERICAN LEGEND (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDA1730F931A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; A Little Girl With a Big Talent, and How She Grew</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO JEFFERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JEFFERSON, MARGO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Judy Garland The Secret Life of an American Legend By David Shipman Illustrated. 540 pages. Hyperion. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Judy Garland said movie and television moguls wanted her to be "sort of the girl next door." But, she added, "they couldn't find the right house or the right door." Neither could she, and that's why the House of Garland turned into such a scary place. Go through one door and you'd find the plucky, sweet-faced girl with the tear in her voice. Go through another and you'd find a cursing maniac addicted to vodka, barbiturates, amphetamines, crash diets and wrist slashing. Go through a third and you'd find a performing genius. She knew every show-business technique there was, from hokum to hysteria to pure joy, and she managed to leave her mark on almost every kind of performer, from rock star to drag queen to summer-stock and church-choir ingenues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Judy Garland The Secret Life of an American Legend By David Shipman Illustrated. 540 pages. Hyperion. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Judy Garland said movie and television moguls wanted her to be "sort of the girl next door." But, she added, "they couldn't find the right house or the right door." Neither could she, and that's why the House of Garland turned into such a scary place. Go through one door and you'd find the plucky, sweet-faced girl with the tear in her voice. Go through another and you'd find a cursing maniac addicted to vodka, barbiturates, amphetamines, crash diets and wrist slashing. Go through a third and you'd find a performing genius. She knew every show-business technique there was, from hokum to hysteria to pure joy, and she managed to leave her mark on almost every kind of performer, from rock star to drag queen to summer-stock and church-choir ingenues.</p>
        <p>Garland died in 1969, and the books have been piling up ever since. There are memoirs, film histories, biographies and biomythographies, most flaunting titles like "Weep No More, My Lady," "A Mortgaged Life" and "Rainbow's End." David Shipman can't resist subtitling his book "The Secret Life of an American Legend," but he does resist the breathless, insinuating prose such titles usually inspire. He is a hard-working, unsentimental researcher whose books include "The Story of Cinema" (St. Martin's Press, 1986) and a three-volume work, "The Great Movie Stars" (DaCapo, 1985).</p>
        <p>Mr. Shipman is willing to sort through family genealogies, rambling interviews, press clips, studio memos and all previous works on Garland. When he finds several accounts of the same incident, he lays them all out, on the sensible ground that when you're dealing with a legend, four versions may be more truthful than one. The times also allow him to be direct where his predecessors had to be circumspect. "The most contentious matters in most biographies are the sexual ones," he notes, "and I can only say that of all the people I spoke to who knew Garland and Vincente Minnelli" -- Garland's second husband -- "only one did not take it for granted that I already knew of Minnelli's homosexuality." Likewise the bisexuality of Garland and of her father, Frank Gumm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shipman begins with Garland's roots in the South and the Midwest. She was born in 1922 and named Frances Ethel (Baby) Gumm. Her unhappily married parents were minor but passionate vaudevillians and theater managers, and Baby took her first bow at the age of 2 1/2, after singing "Jingle Bells" on a stage in Grand Rapids, Minn. The family eventually settled in California, and she was a contract player by the age of 13.</p>
        <p>Thanks to "The Wizard of Oz," she was a star at 15, and she was still a star at 28, when M-G-M dumped her: a star, a survivor of several nervous collapses and a drug addict, thanks to her continued abuse of the pills the studio had blithely prescribed to make sure she slept at night, rose early each morning and stayed thin, thin, thin. From then on, her life became a series of comebacks, occasionally on film, more often on stage. The first time she was asked to carry a show all by herself, she snapped, "Who do you think I am, Aimee Semple McPherson?" That's exactly who she was: a show-business faith healer who could turn a theater into a camp meeting or a group therapy session.</p>
        <p>Garland's public saw through the press-release euphemisms. They knew and loved knowing that a report of influenza probably meant she had had her stomach pumped again, or that a much-needed rest was probably a much-needed stay in a sanitorium. In 1964 she told an interviewer she had had so many comebacks that every time she returned from the bathroom, it was seen as a comeback. Five years later, at the age of 47, she locked herself into a bathroom and died of an overdose.</p>
        <p>Her secret life's no secret anymore. But there is still one secret Mr. Shipman can't penetrate and that is the secret of Garland's talent. He assesses each film performance briefly and quotes liberally from reviews. But he makes no sustained attempt to get at the heart of the trouper who lived with, and on, the rage, the hysteria and the incandescence. Post-modernists love to talk about there being no real barriers between high and popular art. But popular entertainers still get the short end of criticism's stick: few of their biographers manage to join the steamy passion of fans' worship to the stern passion of criticism.</p>
        <p>What are we to make of the performing selves of Judy Garland? In her girlish days, her sunny, virginal air gave way to a voice that both ravished and fulfilled. (Who can forget her singing "You Made Me Love You" to Clark Gable, and why does Mr. Shipman call it "Let's Fall in Love"?) In her middle years she became a kind of Horatio Alger for the movie masses, using film after film to mythologize her own modest American origins, her unquenchable gifts, and her triumph through hard work and trueheartedness.</p>
        <p>Her material stayed grounded in earlier times (the styles of Al Jolson and Helen Morgan; the songs of Irving Berlin and Harold Arlen). But the last years -- the mood swings, the high-strung hands and manic vibrato, the tension and the self-destruction -- exposed her bond to the rebel underside of the culture. James Dean and Montgomery Clift perfected Method acting, Lenny Bruce perfected Method stand-up, and Judy Garland perfected Method vaudeville. Of course Elvis Presley was a fan. Of course Janis Joplin owed as much to Garland as to Bessie Smith. And of course, with her androgynous face, her butch-gamine hair and her way of looking sexier in a tux and a fedora than in chiffon or lame, she was the girl and boy next door.</p>
        <p>Judy Garland was quick-witted, tough, damaged and utterly self-obsessed. "There wasn't a thing that that gal couldn't do -- except take care of herself," said Bing Crosby (whose biographers make it clear that taking care of himself was about the only thing he chose to do). She was a child star, and child stars learn early that their talent can thrill and manipulate others. Very few seem able to learn that when they grow up, that same talent can thrill and nurture and even save them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
