<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A.C.L.U. Fights Plan For a New Caller ID</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVACY, RIGHT OF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IDENTIFICATION DEVICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BELL ATLANTIC CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NEWMAN, GENE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DC1531F935A15751C0A963958260" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A.C.L.U. Fights Plan For a New Caller ID</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GENE NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NEWMAN, GENE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEVEN years after Bell Atlantic brought the nation's first statewide Caller ID service to New Jersey, the company wants to go itself one better. It has petitioned the Board of Public Utilities for permission to offer a program that shows telephone callers' names, as well as their numbers, on a recipient's display unit.</p>
        <p>But the plan is being fought by the American Civil Liberties Union of New Jersey, representing groups ranging from the New Jersey Coalition for Battered Women and the Coalition Against Sexual Assault to the hundreds of thousands of New Jerseyans with unlisted numbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEVEN years after Bell Atlantic brought the nation's first statewide Caller ID service to New Jersey, the company wants to go itself one better. It has petitioned the Board of Public Utilities for permission to offer a program that shows telephone callers' names, as well as their numbers, on a recipient's display unit.</p>
        <p>But the plan is being fought by the American Civil Liberties Union of New Jersey, representing groups ranging from the New Jersey Coalition for Battered Women and the Coalition Against Sexual Assault to the hundreds of thousands of New Jerseyans with unlisted numbers.</p>
        <p>In comments filed with the utilities board on Feb. 6, the A.C.L.U. said that adding automatic name delivery "would pose a widespread and substantial threat to the privacy rights and safety of the public at large."</p>
        <p>The organization asked the board to impose safeguards on the Bell Atlantic plan. One would enable subscribers to demand that the company, without charge, automatically block the showing of their names and telephone numbers on display units. As a result of an earlier A.C.L.U. campaign, callers can now block the display of their numbers to a Caller ID box by dialing *67 before each call.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic said it expected a first-year revenue gain of $6.2 million with the new program it calls Caller ID Deluxe. More than 250,000 of the company's 3.5 million New Jersey customers now take Caller ID, which provides a caller's telephone number only.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic opposes the A.C.L.U. position. James W. Carrigan, a company spokesman, said the interests of the callers and the recipients of calls were now balanced by the *67 blocking option and by a service called Anonymous Call Rejection, which keeps blocked calls from ringing on phones with Caller ID.</p>
        <p>Caller ID costs residential customers $6.50 a month. The new version would be $7.50 a month. Most display units bought within the last year can be activated to display names as well as numbers. Display units start at about $35.</p>
        <p>The A.C.L.U. says many of the problems inherent in Caller ID are increased by adding the names of telephone subscribers to their telephone numbers. Bruce Marvin, a lawyer on the A.C.L.U. staff, said, "There are legitimate safety issues for victims of domestic abuse and confidentiality issues for unlisted number subscribers who've paid a premium to be unlisted, and here the phone company basically eviscerates that protection and puts the burden on the caller to protect his privacy."</p>
        <p>Undercover police officers and informants could inadvertently give themselves away in calls to criminal contacts, the A.C.L.U. argued. An employee who wanted to keep his visits to a psychiatrist confidential could give himself away in a call from the doctor's office. Abused women who have taken refuge in the homes of friends or relatives could give away their locations. After a 1993 agreement won by the A.C.L.U., shelters for battered women have been provided with full-time call blocking.</p>
        <p>In its comments to the Board of Public Utilities, the A.C.L.U. contended that the new service would not only reduce the job of geographically locating an abuse victim to "a matter of minutes" if she neglects to dial *67, but also "provide the abuser with a new target -- the subscriber," since the display will show the account name for the calling phone.</p>
        <p>Margaret Gardner, Bell Atlantic's director of Value Added Services, said many Caller ID customers also have unlisted numbers. "We have found no diminution in subscribership for nonpublished service after the introduction of Caller ID either in New Jersey or elsewhere," she said. "To say that Caller ID has caused nonpublished customers a problem or diminished the value of their service has not proved true in the marketplace. We've also received very few complaints from nonpublished customers."</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic says Caller ID has significantly reduced threatening and obscene calls. The recipient of such calls can turn the caller's number over to the police. Caller ID has also improved the response times of emergency service units and reduced the number of fraudulent orders to takeout food shops.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gardner said Bell Atlantic's Annoying Call Bureau has had a 57 percent reduction in new cases since Caller ID was introduced.</p>
        <p>Another benefit was suggested by a Morris County woman who took Caller ID because of incessant calls from an elderly relative. "She called us 15 times a day because she forgot each call right after she made it," the woman said. "It worked, but I found I still had to run to the phone to see who it was. It kept ringing and ringing."</p>
        <p>The woman then bought a service known as Call Block, whereby her phone was programmed so that certain numbers could not get through; it costs $4 a month. "That solved it," she said, and added, "Still, I kind of liked Caller ID, so I kept it."</p>
        <p>The A.C.L.U. has asked the board to require that commercial Caller ID Deluxe subscribers indicate in the White and Yellow Pages that they use the service and that Bell Atlantic distribute English and Spanish explanations of available call blocking options in bill inserts and directories. In addition, the A.C.L.U. is calling for the distribution of 80,000 Caller ID Deluxe warning notices each year for five years to courts and domestic violence agencies.</p>
        <p>Eric Neisser, a Rutgers law professor and a volunteer lawyer for the A.C.L.U., said in a recent interview that of the 24 states that already have Caller ID Deluxe, 11 permit subscribers to have their names and numbers automatically blocked full time from being shown on display boxes.</p>
        <p>The A.C.L.U. has asked the utilities board to consolidate Bell Atlantic's petition with that of the Warwick Valley Telephone Company, the state's smallest telephone company, which serves Vernon and Upper Greenwood Lake.</p>
        <p>Starting April 15, in line with a Federal Communications Commission order, long-distance carriers will be required to pass numbers to Caller ID display units nationwide.  Name displays will still be limited to calls from local calling areas.</p>
        <p>Jason Ford, a spokesman for the utilities board, declined to provide a timetable for the board's decision. Asking Someone Who Owns One</p>
        <p>BELL ATLANTIC has already introduced the new Caller ID Deluxe in Virginia, West Virginia and Maryland. The service, now proposed for New Jersey, shows callers' names as well as their phone numbers on a recipient's display unit.</p>
        <p>Margaret Gardner, Bell Atlantic's director of Value Added Services, said a survey of subscribers to the new service in the Richmond area indicated almost 100 percent customer satisfaction. "It was probably the most positive survey I've ever seen on a new product in a long time," she added.</p>
        <p>That reaction was echoed in a handful of calls by a reporter to Virginia Caller ID Deluxe customers.</p>
        <p>"I wouldn't trade it for any amount of money," said William H. Hall Jr., a retired financial manager. He previously had Caller ID, he said, and scared off an obscene caller with it. "Then as soon as I found out they had one that produced a name on the screen, I said, 'That's for me.' You know as we grow older, remembering numbers can be a problem."</p>
        <p>Leroy Harris, a retired optician, said he was very pleased with Caller ID Deluxe. He said he has fun surprising his friends with his "ESP" when they call and he addresses them by name before they speak.</p>
        <p>A divorced mother who insisted on anonymity said of the service, "I think it's one of the best things I could have provided for this house."</p>
        <p>As a former battered wife, she said, she fears for her own and her children's safety, adding: "I tell them if they see their own last name on the screen, they shouldn't answer."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
