<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isles Outplay Penguins After Losing Kasparaitis</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PENGUINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DE103AF935A15751C0A963958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isles Outplay Penguins After Losing Kasparaitis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If tonight was any indication, having to say goodbye to Darius Kasparaitis for the rest of the season does not necessarily mean saying goodbye to the season itself.</p>
        <p>The Islanders announced before tonight's game against the league-leading Pittsburgh Penguins that a doctor's examination on Thursday had disclosed a torn anterior cruciate ligament in Kasparaitis's right knee. The hard-hitting 22-year-old defenseman will have surgery next week and miss the rest of the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If tonight was any indication, having to say goodbye to Darius Kasparaitis for the rest of the season does not necessarily mean saying goodbye to the season itself.</p>
        <p>The Islanders announced before tonight's game against the league-leading Pittsburgh Penguins that a doctor's examination on Thursday had disclosed a torn anterior cruciate ligament in Kasparaitis's right knee. The hard-hitting 22-year-old defenseman will have surgery next week and miss the rest of the year.</p>
        <p>That is bad news, indeed, for a team with a depleted defense corps. And with the high-scoring Penguins coming to town, things looked pretty ominous before game time.</p>
        <p>So, what happened?</p>
        <p>Tommy Soderstrom stood on his head at one end, stopping 26 shots, while the explosive Jaromir Jagr was held in check. At the other end, the Islanders got goals from Ray Ferraro, Marty McInnis and Steve Thomas (the same Steve Thomas who had not scored in 11 games). And surprise! A 3-1 Islander victory before a season-high crowd of 15,673 at Nassau Coliseum two nights after a depressing home thrashing at the hands of Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>"That's a good question," said Islander Coach Lorne Henning when asked which performance was more indicative of his team. "But out of the last eight games, we've played seven pretty solid ones. So I guess you've got to throw that Tampa one out."</p>
        <p>The Islanders are now 7-8-3 over all, plodding along like most of the rest of the Eastern Conference. Pittsburgh, which opened the season 13-1-2, has lost 2 games in a row, but the Penguins are still tied for the league lead in points.</p>
        <p>The Islanders had to be as concerned with their depleted defense as they were with their opponent, though.</p>
        <p>Kasparaitis had injured the knee at Montreal last Monday night when the Canadiens' Ed Ronan fell on his leg. What was originally diagnosed as a bruise was discovered to be a tear Thursday.</p>
        <p>"I was shocked," Kasparaitis said. "I felt like I was going to be able to play at the end of the week."</p>
        <p>Instead, he will likely be out from 9 to 11 months.</p>
        <p>"Darius is a pretty big part of what we're trying to build here," General Manager Don Maloney said before the game. "I hate to keep making excuses. I've been promising to make changes around here. Right now, it's going to be very difficult, when you look at our blue line, to do a major reshuffle. We're a little thin there."</p>
        <p>Dean Chynoweth (bruised left knee) and Rich Pilon (sore groin) are also out. Bob Beers (facial fractures) has yet to play, although he may be ready Tuesday. And Scott Lachance sprained his left ankle with two minutes to play and likely will miss Tuesday's game.</p>
        <p>Tonight, that did not matter much. For just the third time this season, the Islanders were ahead after the first 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>As usual, their opponents scored the opening goal -- the 15th consecutive time and 17th in 18 games this season. This time, it was the Penguins' Tomas Sandstrom at 11:30 on a 2-on-1 with Martin Straka.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh's lead lasted all of 30 seconds. From the slot, Ferraro used a screen and wristed a quick shot over Wendell Young, starting in place of Ken Wregget, who had played every minute for the Penguins before tonight. For Ferraro, it was his 10th of the season.</p>
        <p>Less than four-and-a-half minutes later, Dennis Vaske drove the puck around the left boards and Thomas was the first to reach it. He wheeled and fired cross-ice to McInnis cutting to the net. McInnis completed the bang-bang play past Young and it was, 2-1, Islanders at 13:22.</p>
        <p>Soderstrom, meanwhile, was making save after acrobatic save, often meandering way out of his crease in traffic. By the end of two periods, he had stopped 20 of 21 shots. The Islanders had just 4 shots on goal in the second 20 minutes. But the Islanders just knew it was going to be their night when Thomas, who was pulling the trigger from just about every angle imaginable, broke his goal-scoring drought on one of them at 8:19 for a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>With Young flopped down on his back in the crease, Thomas lifted the puck over him for his fourth goal of the season and his first since Jan. 31.</p>
        <p>"I really did feel like someone got a crane out and pulled a piano off on my back," said Thomas, who was playing on a new line for much of the game.</p>
        <p>As he celebrated, the right wing appeared to scream out, "Finally!" On the day the Islanders received their worst news of the season and then went out and earned their biggest victory, they all should have been thinking the same thing.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
