<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Higher Jobless Rates Likely in New Survey</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PART-TIME EMPLOYMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATISTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LABOR DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Time</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB1030F937A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Higher Jobless Rates Likely in New Survey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in 25 years, the Labor Department is revamping its monthly employment survey, and initial tests of the new questionnaire indicate that the United States has hundreds of thousands of people now listed as full-time workers who in fact hold only part-time jobs.</p>
        <p>The tests also suggest that once the new survey replaces the present one, starting in January 1994, the unemployment rate may rise slightly. That is partly because unemployment is probably greater than the current survey can capture, and the new, more accurate one is likely to capture at least some of the additional unemployment, Government officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time in 25 years, the Labor Department is revamping its monthly employment survey, and initial tests of the new questionnaire indicate that the United States has hundreds of thousands of people now listed as full-time workers who in fact hold only part-time jobs.</p>
        <p>The tests also suggest that once the new survey replaces the present one, starting in January 1994, the unemployment rate may rise slightly. That is partly because unemployment is probably greater than the current survey can capture, and the new, more accurate one is likely to capture at least some of the additional unemployment, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>"The results of our testing are very, very preliminary, and I would be more comfortable not saying it, but it looks like unemployment could be higher when the new survey is used," said Anne E. Polivka, an economist at the Labor Department's Bureau of Labor Statistics, who is helping to develop the new survey.  Impact on Policy</p>
        <p>Apart from the unemployment issue, the new survey will produce information not now available that could have an impact on Government policies. It might, for example, encourage the Federal Reserve to raise or lower interest rates sooner than it might otherwise act as a result of the labor force data now gathered each month in the Current Population Survey, run by the Census Bureau in collaboration with the Bureau of Labor Statistics.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department will distinguish each month between people holding full-time jobs and those who now seem to be full-timers because they put together two or three part-time jobs, or some overtime hours, to work a full 35-hour week or more. Some 95 million people were listed as full-timers late last year because they worked the requisite 35 hours in the week before a monthly survey.</p>
        <p>But the initial testing of the new format, with its more detailed questions, indicated that 2 percent of these "full-timers" -- 1.8 million people -- held dual part-time jobs. An additional 5.3 million people held a full-time job and also moonlighted in a second job, another distinction not currently captured in the monthly surveys. Part-time jobs generally do not pay as well or offer as comprehensive benefit packages as full-time jobs, so that a labor force composed of a rising number of part-time workers is probably less well off than one composed of more full-time workers.</p>
        <p>With the new information, if the Federal Reserve sees that people are losing their second jobs or their pay from moonlighting over a period of several months, it might decide that the economy is weakening and lower interest rates to stimulate economic growth. The nation's forecasters would also incorporate such data into their latest predictions.</p>
        <p>"The degree to which people are able to get multiple jobs to make up for a shortage of hours in their primary employment is an indication of the strength and flexibility of our economy," said Glen Cain, a University of Wisconsin labor economist who participated last week in a discussion of the new survey at a meeting of the American Economic Association.</p>
        <p>Or a rise in dual job-holding may be an early signal that the economy is getting stronger, and higher interest rates may be in order to slow growth.  This could happen even while the total number of people holding jobs, now about 118 million, and the unemployment rate, now 7.3 percent, remain unchanged.</p>
        <p>In the current survey, anyone holding any job for any number of hours in the week before the survey is listed as employed. Now people will also be asked whether they regularly work full time or part time or hold two jobs, questions currently posed only in surveys conducted every year or two. The last was in 1991.</p>
        <p>This is the fourth major revision of the monthly Current Population Survey since it was begun in 1940 to estimate the unemployment rate and to collect other work-force data. Some 65,000 households, a cross section of the national population, are interviewed each month, and this number will remain unchanged in the new survey. But for the first time since 1967, the questions are being revised and labor economists familiar with the changes generally welcome them.</p>
        <p>In the 1960's, men still dominated employment and full-time jobs were the norm. The new questions are intended to capture more accurately such changes as the huge rise in part-time work and multiple job holders, the rise in the number of people now counted as employed who in fact work without wages in small family businesses, and the rise in the number of mothers who work part time rather than full time because they lack child-care assistance.</p>
        <p>Preliminary tests of the new survey suggest that roughly 900,000 additional people now recorded as wage earners should in fact be listed as working in family businesses without pay. And nearly two million women consider themselves forced to work part time because they lack child-care help. That is a breakdown not captured in current data.</p>
        <p>Planning for the revised Current Population Survey began in the late 1980's and the new questions were tested in 1990 and 1991 in focus groups and in random telephone polling. Since last July, the survey has been tested monthly among 15,000 representative households. The Census Bureau, which conducts the monthly survey and the Bureau of Labor Statistics, which interprets the data, are just beginning to release information about the revisions and the test results, and more is to be disclosed starting next month.</p>
        <p>Some questions might tend to lower the unemployment rate. In the new survey, reading classified want ads, by itself, no longer constitutes active job-hunting, a condition for being counted as unemployed.</p>
        <p>But other changes in the survey could push up the unemployment rate, Ms. Polivka said. Rather than record their answers on paper, the interviewers in the new system are equipped with laptop computers.</p>
        <p>When interviewers revisit the same households, they can call up on their computers the previous month's answers. That is likely to encourage people to be more consistent and precise in their new answers. Greater accuracy in turn tends to push up the unemployment rate, officials say.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
