<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Attacks Policy Curbing Plea Bargains</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLEA BARGAINING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, IAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, BURTON B (JUSTICE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, ROBERT T (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DD143AF937A25752C0A965958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Attacks Policy Curbing Plea Bargains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, IAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new policy against plea bargaining in the Bronx has begun to burden the borough's court system, increasing the usual caseload and swelling an already huge backlog of felony cases, the Bronx's top judge, Burton B. Roberts, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>But the Bronx District Attorney, Robert T. Johnson, said the policy, which he announced abruptly in November, was not to blame and has in fact begun to work as he intended. In an interview yesterday, Mr. Johnson also appeared to step back from what had seemed a hard-line policy, saying his office would still allow defendants to plead guilty to lesser charges in some cases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new policy against plea bargaining in the Bronx has begun to burden the borough's court system, increasing the usual caseload and swelling an already huge backlog of felony cases, the Bronx's top judge, Burton B. Roberts, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>But the Bronx District Attorney, Robert T. Johnson, said the policy, which he announced abruptly in November, was not to blame and has in fact begun to work as he intended. In an interview yesterday, Mr. Johnson also appeared to step back from what had seemed a hard-line policy, saying his office would still allow defendants to plead guilty to lesser charges in some cases.</p>
        <p>"I would like to think there is always flexibility," he said. "The system cannot deal with absolutes. Each case is individual. I understand that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson angered judges and defense lawyers when he announced an end to plea bargains in felony cases, a decision that critics said would overwhelm a justice system that depends heavily on plea bargains. Last year, 84 percent of all felony cases in the Bronx ended in a plea bargain, in which suspects plead guilty, often to a lesser charge, in exchange for leniency. More Backlogged Cases</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Justice Roberts, the state administrative judge in the Bronx, said the policy had increased the number of cases by 107, from 4,388 before the policy was announced.</p>
        <p>More significantly, he said the number of backlogged cases -- those in the system longer than six months -- rose to 56 percent of the total, up from 53 percent in November. This was the highest percentage of backlogged cases since 1983, he said.</p>
        <p>The increase translates into only four more cases for each of the 33 trial judges. But Justice Roberts said that the judges -- who now average 134 active cases each -- were already overburdened and that the new policy meant that more cases would go to trial, which takes much longer than a guilty plea.</p>
        <p>"If this continues, we are going to be in trouble," Justice Roberts said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson said it was too early to assess the policy, but he added that in his view it showed early signs of success. Though critics had accused the District Attorney of devising the policy rashly in anger at one judge, he said the policy would bolster public confidence in the judicial system and would allow prosecutors to concentrate on major cases. Measure of Success</p>
        <p>One measure of the policy's success, he said, is that State Supreme Court indictments were down 19 percent in December, compared with the total for the corresponding period the preceding year, and that plea bargains before indictment were up 41 percent.</p>
        <p>He said those numbers were consistent with the policy's goal of prosecuting only the strongest cases and permitting plea bargains of weaker cases before indictment in State Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson also said that contrary to earlier statements, his policy was not a blanket ban on all plea bargains after indictment but was meant to end the institutionalized haggling over charges and sentences. He will continue to allow plea bargains in cases where the evidence is weak or a defendant seems to deserve mercy, he said.</p>
        <p>Marvin Ray Raskin, head of the criminal committee of the Bronx County Bar Association, welcomed this flexibility in the policy, which he said he had not heard of. But on a practical level he said he doubted that many assistant district attorneys would be willing to negotiate.</p>
        <p>"The soldiers love to please the general, and they are not going to want to plea," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
