<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warning to Broadcasters That Renege on Running HDTV</title>
    <meta content="Y15TUBE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">High-Definition Television (Hdtv)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pay Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sinclair Broadcast Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television Sets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DB1638F936A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warning to Broadcasters That Renege on Running HDTV</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leading members of Congress threaten retribution against broadcasters who they say hoodwinked Congress by promising to broadcast high-definition television on their new digital channels, then reneged once new channels were in hand; although law allows television stations to use their new channels as they please, Sen John McCain and other members say Congress ageed to loan valuable spectrum only after broadcasters promised to use it for HDTV at least part of time; ABC has already said it was leaning toward using its new channels to broadcast lower-resolution, pay-television programs, instead of single high-definition TV show, as has Sinclair Broadcasting Group; both say they see no easy way to make money from high-definition broadcast; Sen McCain schedules hearing of his Senate Commerce Committee on matter (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leading members of Congress are threatening retribution against broadcasters who say they might not offer high-definition television on their new digital channels.</p>
        <p>These lawmakers, including chairmen of important House and Senate committees, are saying in essence that the broadcasters hoodwinked Congress by promising to broadcast HDTV when the award of their digital channels was in doubt, then reneged once the new channels were in hand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leading members of Congress are threatening retribution against broadcasters who say they might not offer high-definition television on their new digital channels.</p>
        <p>These lawmakers, including chairmen of important House and Senate committees, are saying in essence that the broadcasters hoodwinked Congress by promising to broadcast HDTV when the award of their digital channels was in doubt, then reneged once the new channels were in hand.</p>
        <p>Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona and chairman of the Senate Commerce Committee, has scheduled a hearing on Wednesday, when he plans to question the broadcasters about their plans. ''It's so disillusioning,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''It is a clear revocation of a commitment that was irrefutably made.''</p>
        <p>Last month, Preston Padden, president of the ABC television network, said ABC was leaning toward using its new channels to broadcast several lower-resolution, pay-television programs instead of a single high-definition TV show. At the same time, the Sinclair Broadcasting Group, which owns or provides programming for 29 television stations nationwide, announced that it would forgo HDTV and offer several channels of pay TV instead.</p>
        <p>While the law allows television stations to use their new channels more or less as they please, Mr. McCain and other members say Congress agreed to loan the valuable spectrum -- worth as much as $10 billion if auctioned -- after the broadcasters promised that they would use it for HDTV at least part of the time.</p>
        <p>''The whole idea was that they would exchange one channel for another channel to broadcast HDTV,'' said Representative W. J. (Billy) Tauzin, the Louisiana Republican who heads the House telecommunications subcommittee. ''I don't think Congress will let the decision not to use HDTV pass without some serious debate and discussion. There will be a quid pro quo.''</p>
        <p>Representative Michael G. Oxley, an Ohio Republican and a subcommittee member, added, ''If this was a trial balloon sent up by ABC, I would suggest that it's made of pure lead, if my discussions with my colleagues are any indication.''</p>
        <p>Executives from both ABC and Sinclair were quick to point out that they had never absolutely forsworn any intention to broadcast high-definition programming. Instead, both had said they saw no easy way to make money by offering it. The Government's rules allowed them to choose their own approach. And so, the executives added, they had merely talked about their likely strategies for putting the digital airwaves to profitable use, primarily by using over-the-air television for pay-TV services.</p>
        <p>At both companies, executives are explaining themselves again, or back-pedaling. In August, David Smith, Sinclair's president, was dismissive of HDTV, saying he saw no way to make money from broadcasting it.</p>
        <p>Last week, Nat Ostroff, a Sinclair vice president, said the company still believed that HDTV was a money loser. But in an interview, he added: ''We really don't see the basis for the Congressmen's reaction. We have not ruled out HDTV. I can see broadcasting it on an occasional basis, with the occasions increasing as the population of TV receivers able to receive it increase.''</p>
        <p>Moments later, he said: ''We are prepared to commit that we are going to do some HDTV. We have to find out if the public wants it.''</p>
        <p>In meetings with several lawmakers and in a later interview, Mr. Padden stressed that ''no one at ABC has ever said we would not do HDTV.'' He said his comments in August were preliminary. And in fact, his first remark that day was, ''I am not here to announce any settled strategy.''</p>
        <p>Both he and Mr. Smith of Sinclair are scheduled to testify before Mr. McCain's committee on Monday. So is Reed E. Hundt, outgoing chairman of the Federal Communications Commission. He has never been a fan of HDTV and disagrees with Mr. McCain and Mr. Tauzin. In fact, shortly after Mr. Padden's and Mr. Smith's announcements last month, he sent letters to both broadcasters lauding them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tauzin, however, warned that broadcasters who chose not to offer HDTV might face steep fees, onerous new public service obligations or even spectrum auctions.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Oxley said: ''It's important to note that it was the broadcasters, now some 10 years ago, who asked to pursue HDTV, lest the Japanese best us in this area. In 1987, they told us that they would become a second-class service unless they were given the tools to pursue HDTV capability.''</p>
        <p>High-definition television signals fill the entire space on the airwaves occupied by a television channel, while lower-resolution signals fill less space. And ''if there is no HDTV,'' Mr. Tauzin said, ''then the question becomes, how much spectrum do you need to do a digital broadcast? We could take back the rest and auction it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tauzin's remarks were particularly notable because he is regarded as a reliable ally of the broadcasting industry. ''I think they need to hear from me because I am a friend,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>Ken Johnson, an aide to Mr. Tauzin, said the Congressman was speaking out in part because ''we don't want to be blindfolded and shot by the people who have called this whole thing a spectrum giveaway.</p>
        <p>''Billy is saying this is not going to be a giveaway,'' Mr. Johnson added. ''They are going to live up to their promises.''</p>
        <p>Broadcasters do not consider Mr. McCain a friend. He opposed the award of the second channels from the beginning, saying they ought to be auctioned. But he was outvoted.</p>
        <p>Now, he says: ''We need to find out why segments of the broadcast industry, after absolutely promising to use this spectrum, which they got for free, to make the transition to HDTV, are now reneging on that promise and planning to use this spectrum, which they got for free, for money-making endeavors instead.</p>
        <p>''I think the spectrum issue ought to be revisited,'' he added.</p>
        <p>NBC, CBS and PBS all are promising to broadcast high-definition programming, primarily during evening hours, while experimenting with other services at other times of the day, while Fox has not said what it intends to do. And some executives from the other networks see the whole debate as an embarrassment -- or worse.</p>
        <p>''This public-relations nightmare and congressional-relations nightmare is very harmful to the industry and to the general public,'' Michael Jordan, chairman of CBS's parent company, Westinghouse Electric, said in an interview. ''To Congress and to the public, we look somewhat irresponsible and tremendously disorganized.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. McCain acknowledged that he was not sure how easy it might be to penalize broadcasters who choose not to offer high-definition television.</p>
        <p>''It depends on the mood of Congress and the power of the broadcast industry,'' he said. ''As you know, my contests with them are unblemished by victory.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
