<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaky After 100 Million Years</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, DAVID RAINS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCPHEE, JOHN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ASSEMBLING CALIFORNIA (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DF173DF934A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaky After 100 Million Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Rains Wallace;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, DAVID RAINS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASSEMBLING CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>By John McPhee. Illustrated. 304 pp. New York:  Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $21.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASSEMBLING CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>By John McPhee. Illustrated. 304 pp. New York:  Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux. $21.</p>
        <p>THE last of the four-volume "Annals of the Former World," John McPhee's "Assembling California" is a popular account of the plate tectonics revolution in geology that the author began chronicling in 1981. Mr. McPhee has used an effective and rather innovative way of interpreting the science of plate tectonics, the wandering around the world of the great plates that form the surface of the earth. He has told the story through the articulate geologists he has befriended, with each volume built around the experience and insights of one individual. The series also centers on the geology along Interstate 80, the main east-west road across the United States, another way of bringing a vast subject to manageable dimensions.</p>
        <p>The earlier volumes dealt with geologists working in the Great Basin, the Appalachians and the Rockies. The latest deals with California through the work of Eldridge Moores, a geologist at the University of California at Davis, who specializes in one of the more advanced and problematic aspects of plate tectonics, ophiolites. Mr. Moores travels the world in search of ophiolites, the deep ocean rocks that have become part of continental mountains through sea floor spreading, crustal plate subduction, continental suturing and other tectonic processes.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Moores and his colleagues, California did not exist until the latter half of the dinosaur age, and has been "assembled" as the result of a series of sea floor eruptions, called "island arcs," that collided with North America's western margin and added vast quantities of rocks to it. Many of these rocks can be identified as ophiolites because they contain layers of the same materials that make up today's deep ocean floors. Mr. Moores takes Mr. McPhee to see ophiolites in California's Sierra Nevada and Coast Range, and also in Cyprus and Macedonia.</p>
        <p>This theme -- that the state of California was assembled over the last hundred million years -- is clear. Others are less so, which is not Mr. McPhee's fault. "Nature is messy," Mr. Moores tells the author. "Don't expect it to be uniform and consistent." A secondary theme is that California now is being torn apart along a series of "transform faults" caused by longitudinal motions of the crustal plates underlying the West Coast. The most famous of these is the San Andreas, along which the great 1906 earthquake occurred. If the faulting continues, Los Angeles and San Diego will eventually be part of Alaska, as Southern California is rafted toward the Bering Strait.</p>
        <p>So, after 200 million years of assemblage, California also is being disassembled. Such twists make reading "Assembling California," along with the "Annals" -- "Rising From the Plains" (1986), "In Suspect Terrain" (1983) and "Basin and Range" (1981) -- like field trips through typically messy and inconsistent natural landscapes. Subjects arise, sometimes refer to subjects in previous volumes, segue into historical dissertations or paleontological reflections, and so on. (An index for each volume would help, and one wonders at their absence.)</p>
        <p>Mr. McPhee varies his discussion of plate tectonics with lively excursions into the California gold rush and the Napa Valley wine country, and reaches a climax in an account of the 1989 Loma Prieta earthquake, California's latest demonstration of its disassembling. "At the University of California, Santa Cruz," he writes, "three first-year students from the East Coast sit under redwood trees on the forest campus. As the shock waves reach them and the trees whip overhead, the three students leap up and spontaneously dance and shout in a ring." There'll always be a California -- somewhere.</p>
        <p>"Assembling California" is a good book, like all of Mr. McPhee's works, but not quite as good as earlier volumes of the "Annals." Ophiolites and transform faults</p>
        <p>are</p>
        <p>technical, and the author's writing sometimes seems subducted by them. For example: "The Philippine Plate, largest of the microplates, is surrounded by ocean trenches six and seven miles deep. On the east, Pacific crust is going under the Philippine Plate. On the west, Asian crust is going into the Manila Trench, where melting has produced the West Luzon arc, and where Taiwan is docking with mainland China. That much is straightforward compared with the many smaller microcontinents and minor ocean basins that are also in the region."</p>
        <p>Mr. McPhee does not bring Eldridge Moores's character to life as much as he did the characters of scientists in previous volumes. This is not for lack of erudition and wit on Mr. Moores's part, but his personality is tuned to a lower key than those voluble "originals" Mr. McPhee depicts so well. Mr. McPhee is a romantic about things like frontier life and hard-rock mining, and Mr. Moores is not, having grown up on an Arizona back-country mine and decided when he was 10 years old: "I've had it! If I never do another thing, I'm going to go out of here." Mr. Moores went into geology partly as an excuse for globe-trotting, and Mr. McPhee seems a little disoriented as he follows him about the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>MR. MCPHEE maintains a certain ironic detachment toward the environmental issues that often arise with geology. In 1993, this attitude begins to seem anachronistic. Urban sprawl has turned the westernmost 50 miles of Interstate 80 into an almost continuous traffic jam, but Mr. McPhee apparently does not notice the change from 1981. He also sometimes seems casual to the point of myopia about what lives</p>
        <p>on</p>
        <p>his rocks. One reason California has one of the highest biodiversity levels in the United States is that many rare plants grow on ophiolitic landscapes, but this also escapes notice.</p>
        <p>"Assembling California" closes with what seems to be an affirmation. Mr. McPhee meets a fisherman where the San Andreas Fault intersects the Pacific, who tells the author that he has caught salmon there, although not recently. "But someday they come. They always come," the fisherman concludes.</p>
        <p>California's salmon have dwindled alarmingly since 1981, however, and may not "always come," so the affirmation has a hollow ring. Perhaps Mr. McPhee meant it so. The turbulent new vision of the past that he has presented so well certainly does not support blind faith in civilization's future.</p>
        <p>David Rains Wallace is the author of "The Klamath Knot: Explorations in Myth and Evolution" and "The Quetzal and the Macaw: The Story of Costa Rica's National Parks."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Rains Wallace is the author of "The Klamath Knot: Explorations in Myth and Evolution" and "The Quetzal and the Macaw: The Story of Costa Rica's National Parks."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
