<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Author! Author!</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sophisticated Traveler Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="102" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sophisticated Traveler Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF103AF934A35750C0A965958260" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Author! Author!</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. I've seen the Atlantic: pretty but frantic. / I've faced the Pacific: nothing specific. / As for the continent, I'm not yet on to it. 2. Any noun on which my eyes rested, a hill across the harbor, a lane between the fishermen's shacks, silently returned two sounds, one the patois, the other English. 3. It seemed a haunted land. I thought of witches, of the kingdom of Medea. 4. But as I walk the streets of San Francisco, many of them have, for me, a familiar ring: Kearny, O'Farrell, Larkin, Geary, McAllister -- obviously some of my countrymen have left their mark here. 5. Off the packed trail we experience the miracle of corn snow, skiing atop the crust, like skiing on an eggshell that has been sprinkled with sugar. 6. Recently I returned to the old migration route of the Kiowas. I had in me a need to behold again some of the principal landmarks of that long, prehistoric quest, to descend again from the mountain to the plain. 7. There was a time when senescent gentlemen and ladies, down by the seawall, used to walk their dogs at the cocktail hour with leash in one hand and a martini in the other. 8. When the spirit of adventure invades the historical process -- when states or their leaders or representatives go adventuring -- the results are usually catastrophic. 9. One morning in Stockholm, after rain and just before November, a mysteriously translucent shadow began to paint itself across the top of the city. 10. For the Rock and the desert are not nullities. They have astonishing beauty and subtle habits, the desert seeming to overflow with an Old Testament plenty, the Rock shedding its skin evenly, through the process called spalling, like a live serpent. 11. But Salem is a different matter. It takes its name from no English county or cathedral town, and one comes to it without the weight of nostalgic associations. 12. Paris with its long humanistic tradition, as a city known to value and respect those who create, was for the Tournon Crowd both a cultural and racial haven. 13. The sally is the first tree to green and the first to wither; the rowan berries are an incredible orange in the light from the lakes each September. 14. Parisian gloom is not simply climatic, it is a spiritual force that acts not only on building materials, on walls and rooftops, but also on your character, your opinions and judgments. 15. Like the Pharoahs, the landscape itself is dead, enlivened only by the tourists who lend some movement and color to a barren and mortuary area. 16. The next time I look, the sky above the far peaks has been painted with broad streaks of brilliant orange on a ground of cerulean, the last stars are fading overhead, and the bay is silent. Then the voices of the waking birds begin. 17. Speaking of venison, I do remember my first haunch. 18. It isn't necessarily the great and famous beauty spots we fall in love with. As with people, so with places: Love is unforeseen, and we can all find ourselves affectionately attached to the minor and the less obvious. 19. From the coastal bluffs to the north, I now realize, I could easily watch Kurile seals cut the wild, jade-green water of the ocean. Such animals draw a visitor quickly out of himself and into the land -- the sight of them alone is exhilarating. 20. We have watched the Nakhi women coming down from the Snow Range, with their bundles of pine and artemisia; and one old woman with a bamboo winnowing basket on her back, and the sun's rays passing through it. BRIAN MOORE SUSAN MINOT SAUL BELLOW SALMAN RUSHDIE N. SCOTT MOMADAY MARY LEE SETTLE W.S. MERWIN LEON EDEL WILLIAM GOLDING CYNTHIA OZICK P.D. JAMES PAULE MARSHALL JOHN MCGAHERN DEREK WALCOTT JULIA CHILD JOSEPH BRODSKY MURIEL SPARK BARRY LOPEZ BRUCE CHATWIN THOMAS KENEALLY The 20 quotations above have been garnered from a decade of Sophisticated Travelers; the names in the center column are those of some of the distinguished writers whose work has appeared in these pages. Match the quotation with the author to prove your literary acumen (or to show off your long-term memory). No prizes are offered, but give yourself extra credit if you can identify those writers who have also won the Nobel Prize in Literature. (Hint: there are four.) Answers appear on Page 100</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. I've seen the Atlantic: pretty but frantic. / I've faced the Pacific: nothing specific. / As for the continent, I'm not yet on to it. 2. Any noun on which my eyes rested, a hill across the harbor, a lane between the fishermen's shacks, silently returned two sounds, one the patois, the other English. 3. It seemed a haunted land. I thought of witches, of the kingdom of Medea. 4. But as I walk the streets of San Francisco, many of them have, for me, a familiar ring: Kearny, O'Farrell, Larkin, Geary, McAllister -- obviously some of my countrymen have left their mark here. 5. Off the packed trail we experience the miracle of corn snow, skiing atop the crust, like skiing on an eggshell that has been sprinkled with sugar. 6. Recently I returned to the old migration route of the Kiowas. I had in me a need to behold again some of the principal landmarks of that long, prehistoric quest, to descend again from the mountain to the plain. 7. There was a time when senescent gentlemen and ladies, down by the seawall, used to walk their dogs at the cocktail hour with leash in one hand and a martini in the other. 8. When the spirit of adventure invades the historical process -- when states or their leaders or representatives go adventuring -- the results are usually catastrophic. 9. One morning in Stockholm, after rain and just before November, a mysteriously translucent shadow began to paint itself across the top of the city. 10. For the Rock and the desert are not nullities. They have astonishing beauty and subtle habits, the desert seeming to overflow with an Old Testament plenty, the Rock shedding its skin evenly, through the process called spalling, like a live serpent. 11. But Salem is a different matter. It takes its name from no English county or cathedral town, and one comes to it without the weight of nostalgic associations. 12. Paris with its long humanistic tradition, as a city known to value and respect those who create, was for the Tournon Crowd both a cultural and racial haven. 13. The sally is the first tree to green and the first to wither; the rowan berries are an incredible orange in the light from the lakes each September. 14. Parisian gloom is not simply climatic, it is a spiritual force that acts not only on building materials, on walls and rooftops, but also on your character, your opinions and judgments. 15. Like the Pharoahs, the landscape itself is dead, enlivened only by the tourists who lend some movement and color to a barren and mortuary area. 16. The next time I look, the sky above the far peaks has been painted with broad streaks of brilliant orange on a ground of cerulean, the last stars are fading overhead, and the bay is silent. Then the voices of the waking birds begin. 17. Speaking of venison, I do remember my first haunch. 18. It isn't necessarily the great and famous beauty spots we fall in love with. As with people, so with places: Love is unforeseen, and we can all find ourselves affectionately attached to the minor and the less obvious. 19. From the coastal bluffs to the north, I now realize, I could easily watch Kurile seals cut the wild, jade-green water of the ocean. Such animals draw a visitor quickly out of himself and into the land -- the sight of them alone is exhilarating. 20. We have watched the Nakhi women coming down from the Snow Range, with their bundles of pine and artemisia; and one old woman with a bamboo winnowing basket on her back, and the sun's rays passing through it. BRIAN MOORE SUSAN MINOT SAUL BELLOW SALMAN RUSHDIE N. SCOTT MOMADAY MARY LEE SETTLE W.S. MERWIN LEON EDEL WILLIAM GOLDING CYNTHIA OZICK P.D. JAMES PAULE MARSHALL JOHN MCGAHERN DEREK WALCOTT JULIA CHILD JOSEPH BRODSKY MURIEL SPARK BARRY LOPEZ BRUCE CHATWIN THOMAS KENEALLY The 20 quotations above have been garnered from a decade of Sophisticated Travelers; the names in the center column are those of some of the distinguished writers whose work has appeared in these pages. Match the quotation with the author to prove your literary acumen (or to show off your long-term memory). No prizes are offered, but give yourself extra credit if you can identify those writers who have also won the Nobel Prize in Literature. (Hint: there are four.) Answers appear on Page 100</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
