<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; They Support Free Trade, Except in the Case of . . .</title>
    <meta content="16ROSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/16/weekinreview/16ROSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1535775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenbaum, David E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DB1338F935A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; They Support Free Trade, Except in the Case of . . .</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">They Support Free Trade, Except in the Case of . . .</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenbaum, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Free trade is difficult issue for politicians, who cannot help be swayed by fact that people harmed by trade expansion have names and faces, whereas those who benefit often do not even know it; dilemma for Democratic presidential candidates seeking union support discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLITICAL candidates who stand on the ideological scale between Ralph Nader on the left and Patrick J. Buchanan on the right tend to accept, in the abstract, the conventional view of economists: International trade helps many more people than it hurts.</p>
        <p>But on the campaign trail, politicians cannot help but be swayed by the fact that people who are harmed by trade expansion have names and faces -- and votes -- and that the people who benefit often do not even know it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the volatile issue of international trade, many politicians, especially those on the campaign trail, are looking for wiggle room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLITICAL candidates who stand on the ideological scale between Ralph Nader on the left and Patrick J. Buchanan on the right tend to accept, in the abstract, the conventional view of economists: International trade helps many more people than it hurts.</p>
        <p>But on the campaign trail, politicians cannot help but be swayed by the fact that people who are harmed by trade expansion have names and faces -- and votes -- and that the people who benefit often do not even know it.</p>
        <p>This is leading many politicians, including most of the main Democratic candidates for president, to abandon the emphasis on globalization that was a cornerstone of the Clinton presidency.</p>
        <p>Free trade is easy to justify when times are good, as they were in the Clinton years. Workers who lost jobs when factories closed often found better ones. But when the economy took a turn for the worse, the theory that more trade would lead to more prosperity began to influence politicians less than workers' real-world concerns about their own jobs.</p>
        <p>The Democratic presidential candidates wrestle with the issue daily. They need support from organized labor, which generally opposes any expansion of trade that might threaten existing jobs.</p>
        <p>''I found this to be the most wrenching and agonizing issue I dealt with in my eight years in the White House,'' said Gene Sperling, a top economic and political strategist in the Clinton White House who was instrumental in developing its free market approach.</p>
        <p>The Republicans are not immune to the issue either, as the Bush administration's experience last week with steel tariffs illustrated.</p>
        <p>President Bush presents himself as a committed advocate of free trade. But last year, hoping to strengthen his position in politically crucial steel-producing states like Pennsylvania and West Virginia, the president imposed tariffs that raised the price of imported steel as much as 30 percent.</p>
        <p>Last week, the World Trade Organization, the international arbiter of trade laws, ruled that these tariffs were illegal, opening the way to retaliatory sanctions by European countries against American goods unless Mr. Bush relents.</p>
        <p>Now, in a hint that the president may reverse course, the White House has let out the word that Mr. Bush's political advisers believe the tariffs may actually have lost the president more support from executives and workers in steel-dependent industries like automobiles than he gained from those in the steel industry.</p>
        <p>A recent study by two trade economists, Gary Clyde Hufbauer and Ben Goodrich, bolsters that view. They calculated that the tariffs might have saved 3,500 steel jobs but might have cost several times that many jobs in industries that buy steel.</p>
        <p>Among the Democratic presidential candidates, only Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut continues to emphasize the advantages of removing trade barriers around the world.</p>
        <p>Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri has made a career of opposing trade pacts and of wooing organized labor, and that is one of the main elements of his campaign this year.</p>
        <p>And the other main candidates, to one degree or another, say they favor the expansion of trade. This establishes that they cannot be called know-nothing protectionists.</p>
        <p>Then come the caveats. They would re-examine existing trade agreements to make sure American workers are not put at a disadvantage. And they would sign no new pacts that did not require trading partners to adopt much stricter standards for workers' rights and environmental protection.</p>
        <p>To the unions, these are code words. China, Mexico and the countries in South America, where American factories and jobs might move, are unlikely to adopt the kind of collective bargaining and minimum wage requirements that prevail in the United States and Europe. Nor are they likely to impose the same kind of environmental regulations on their factories.</p>
        <p>Stanley B. Greenberg, who was the pollster for Mr. Clinton in his first presidential campaign and who is unaligned with any current campaign, said he thought this was a politically effective stand.</p>
        <p>''It's a tough issue,'' Mr. Greenberg said. ''The public supports trade restrictions by a large majority. But if the candidate seems to be inward-looking, he does less well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt portrays his opponents as Johnnies-come-lately in their qualms about free trade. He notes that he led the fights in Congress against the North American Free Trade Agreement and increased trade with China, and argues that the world needs ''fair trade, not just free trade.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gephardt had hoped his record on trade would translate into united support from labor unions. Indeed, he has won the endorsement of 21 unions, including the Teamsters and most of the large industrial unions. But his campaign suffered a blow last week when two of the largest unions, the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees and the Service Employees International Union, announced their endorsement of Howard Dean.</p>
        <p>Because trade has never seriously affected their jobs, the public employees and service workers do not feel the loyalty to Mr. Gephardt that manufacturing workers do. And Dr. Dean, who as governor of Vermont was an advocate of free trade, has turned around and taken positions that approach Mr. Gephardt's in their intensity.</p>
        <p>In a debate in September, Dr. Dean said he had supported trade pacts in the past because ''we benefited in Vermont from trade.'' But campaigning around the country, he said, he saw how ''our manufacturing jobs are hemorrhaging'' and decided that ''we have to go back and revise every single trade agreement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sperling said the challenge for Democrats was to find a way to ''embrace the benefits of trade'' without allowing ''all the downsides to be dumped on the few who are in the wrong industry in the wrong city at the wrong time.''</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, said he expected the whole calculus of trade as a political issue to change. ''It's always been a wedge issue for Democrats and blue-collar workers,'' he said. But now, he went on, white-collar jobs in banks, telemarketing, software programming and other fields are increasingly moving overseas. And the two regions harmed most by factory closings are the Southeast, a Republican stronghold, and the Midwest, which has several swing states that could decide the presidential election.</p>
        <p>''The way this issue is growing all around the country,'' Mr. Schumer concluded, ''I think it could be the sleeper in the election this year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
