<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Without Will P., Giants' Focus Turns to Will A.</title>
    <meta content="16GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/16/sports/football/16GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1535795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zinser, Lynn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Will</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Allen, Will</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D61338F935A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Without Will P., Giants' Focus Turns to Will A.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Without Will P., Giants Focus Turns to Will A.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants and cornerback Will Allen prepare to face Philadelphia Eagles; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Will Allen is used to being half of a tandem, rarely mentioned in a sentence without his counterpart. His teammates and coaches rarely utter his last name. Among the Giants, he is known as Will A., the perfect counterbalance to his fellow cornerback, Will P.</p>
        <p>Allen and Peterson are friends. They share a position. They were drafted together. Their lockers are next to each other.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Will Allen and Will Peterson share a position. For the past four weeks, though, Will A. has been going it alone following Will P.s back injury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Will Allen is used to being half of a tandem, rarely mentioned in a sentence without his counterpart. His teammates and coaches rarely utter his last name. Among the Giants, he is known as Will A., the perfect counterbalance to his fellow cornerback, Will P.</p>
        <p>Allen and Peterson are friends. They share a position. They were drafted together. Their lockers are next to each other.</p>
        <p>For the past four weeks, though, Will A. has been going it alone. Will P. suffered a back injury, leaving the Giants with one Will. The injuries have not stopped there, and now, facing a crucial game at Philadelphia, Allen is the last veteran cornerback still standing. Placed on injured reserve this week, Peterson no longer comes to practice.</p>
        <p>If Allen needed any further reminder of the burden he carries in this secondary, not seeing Peterson next to him every day provides a poignant one. Allen is 25, with two full seasons of experience, and suddenly he is asked to hold up a significant portion of the Giants' defense on his own. ''The situation we're in right now, I have no choice,'' Allen said. ''I definitely feel like one of the key guys out there. Knowing that, you step into that role.''</p>
        <p>Being the only Will means not being allowed to make mistakes. It means covering the opponent's top receiver without faltering. It means being the one his teammates can count on while they fret over everyone else.</p>
        <p>It meant helping Ralph Brown adjust to the starting job after Peterson's injury. Now Brown is out three to four weeks with a separated shoulder, and starting at corner is Frank Walker, a rookie. The Giants had to sign cornerback Ike Charlton this week out of sheer desperation.</p>
        <p>''It's tough,'' Brown said. ''Will has to make sure he's doing his job. If we match him up on somebody and he's not doing his job, who else are we going to look to? We've got a rookie over here and we're already helping him out on a lot of coverages. If Will's not doing his job, we're really in trouble.''</p>
        <p>The last time the Giants played the Eagles, it was Will A.'s first game without Will P. The Eagles made that transition look easy: quarterback Donovan McNabb tried to complete only two passes to James Thrash while Allen was covering him, and Allen intercepted one of them.</p>
        <p>Allen also picked off a pass by McNabb, his former Syracuse teammate, in their first meeting as pros, in 2001. But what Allen remembers from that day is giving up a touchdown to Thrash and yielding another big catch by Thrash. ''That,'' Allen said, ''wasn't acceptable.''</p>
        <p>It is that attitude that has smoothed Allen's ascension to most valuable cornerback. Now, the details matter as much to the rest of the team as they do to him.</p>
        <p>''We're short out there,'' Allen said. ''We've got a lot of guys that aren't accustomed to playing. That changes a lot of things. It's like, Will Allen can't be out there making mistakes. Will Allen can't be out there giving up stuff. You have to leave some room for the guys who are just getting out there.''</p>
        <p>Never was that role more obvious than when Allen drew the job of covering Randy Moss of the Vikings. He broke up one long pass to Moss but gave up two others, both in the first half. In the second half, he held Moss to two catches for 4 yards.</p>
        <p>''Him being the healthiest guy around, he's accepting the challenge,'' the secondary coach, DeWayne Walker, said. ''I was teasing him, telling him that's why we pay him the big bucks. From my perspective it's his job, and I think he looks at it that way, too.''</p>
        <p>His job, though, has been more than just shutting down whichever receiver he covers. He has to shepherd his teammates through the process. Allen has to make sure his counterpart lines up on the correct receiver. Against the Jets two weeks ago that communication failed, and Walker ended up covering Santana Moss on several plays. With Peterson on the other side of the field, those things weren't an issue. Will P. and Will A. were considered equals. Either could take on the top receiver.</p>
        <p>Without half of the duo, the spotlight falls only on Allen. For the rest of this season anyway, he has a name of his own.</p>
        <p>''With Will P. gone, there's no more two Wills, but it's not like that's gone forever,'' Allen said. ''That's the identity of our secondary. People say, 'They have two decent corners, both named Will,' so we're the two Wills. That's never going to go away.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Giants waived kicker BRETT CONWAY on Saturday and signed tight end DARNELL DINKINS off their practice squad for Sunday's game against the Eagles. MATT BRYANT, out for the past five weeks with a hamstring pull, will resume the kicking duties. The team also signed center SCOTT PETERS off their practice squad and waived center OMAR SMITH, who had played only on special teams.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
