<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>St. Petersburg</title>
    <meta content="WDSTPETE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/16/travel/16wdstpete.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1535605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Petersburg (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Sara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/St. Petersburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DA1638F935A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>St. Petersburg</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In St. Petersburg, Fla.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Sara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column on upcoming events, sightseeing, lodging and restaurants in St Petersburg, Fla; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>St. Petersburg's skyline is newly muscular, with high-rise luxury condos, the $40 million BayWalk shopping and entertainment complex and a growing assortment of gleaming hotels and offices.</p>
        <p>The transformation of the city from a dowdy Florida retirement haven started modestly 10 years ago, and gradually gained momentum; since 1998, St. Petersburg has logged six consecutive years of the busiest construction activity in its history, with more than $1.5 billion in development projects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Salvador Dalí, rock shows and a childrens museum cut the sedateness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>St. Petersburg's skyline is newly muscular, with high-rise luxury condos, the $40 million BayWalk shopping and entertainment complex and a growing assortment of gleaming hotels and offices.</p>
        <p>The transformation of the city from a dowdy Florida retirement haven started modestly 10 years ago, and gradually gained momentum; since 1998, St. Petersburg has logged six consecutive years of the busiest construction activity in its history, with more than $1.5 billion in development projects.</p>
        <p>The city's sudden awakening has been aided by the influx of high-tech firms staffed with young employees (the median age of its residents went from a high of 48.1 in 1970 to 39.3 in 2000), and the handiwork of local entrepreneurs -- including restaurateurs and innkeepers -- who found potential in its gentle climate, pedestrian-friendly ambience and carefully preserved seven-mile stretch of verdant parkland facing Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>St. Pete's new streetscapes include orange-haired skateboarders, jumping late-night clubs and sidewalks crowded on weekends with shoppers and diners. But it retains the perfumy drawl and relaxed Southern charm that for decades has drawn vacationers to its tree-lined streets and to 35 miles of broad, sandy beaches 20 minutes west of downtown.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The city has a special attraction for art lovers: the Salvador Dalí Museum, 1000 Third Street South, (727) 823-3767, www.salvadordalimuseum.org, whose 1,500 works of art (including 95 oil paintings) is the most comprehensive collection of Dalí's work in the world. The museum is planning a special exhibition in honor of the 100th anniversary of the artist's birth next year: from Jan. 9 to August, ''Dalí Centennial: An American Collection'' will feature objects from its collection never displayed before, new acquisitions and two stereoscopic paintings on loan from the Teatro-Museo Dalí in Figueres, Spain. During the year, the museum also will present original works of poetry, music and dance in Dalí's memory. Open daily; general admission, $12.50.</p>
        <p>The rock act Alkaline Trio performs at 8 p.m., Nov. 17, at Jannus Landing Courtyard, 220 First Avenue North, (727) 896-1244, and www.jannuslanding.net. Tickets are $14.99 in advance or $17 the day of the show. The Landing, dating from 1888, is billed as the oldest outdoor concert venue in Florida, and is host to varied musical acts -- from rock to rap, punk, rockabilly and jazz.</p>
        <p>The 26th annual in-water Fall Boat Show features more than 700 boats, Nov. 20 to 23 at the Bayfront Center, 400 First Street South, (800) 874-9015, www.stpete.org/bayfront.htm; admission, $7.</p>
        <p>The Bayfront Center includes the 2,000-seat Mahaffey Theater for the Performing Arts, where theater, music and other entertainment events are held. On Dec. 15, Skitch Henderson leads the Florida Orchestra through a program of holiday favorites with guest vocalists and a choral ensemble at 8 p.m. Tickets are $21 to 45. Information: (800) 874-9015, www.stpete.org/mahaffey.htm.</p>
        <p>The 21st annual Boley Centers' Jingle Bell Run will start at 7:30 p.m. on Dec. 10 at the Pier, 800 Second Avenue NE. The event -- over one- and three-mile courses along the waterfront -- is less sport and more evening holiday party, as runners bring dogs and babies and wear bells, illuminated necklaces and goofy hats sparkling with Christmas ornaments. Registration is $15, or $18 on race day. Information: (727) 821-4819 and www.boleycenters.org.</p>
        <p>Glass sculptures of Dale Chihuly are the subjects of a joint show at the Museum of Fine Arts St. Petersburg, 255 Beach Drive NE, (727) 896-2667, www.fine-arts.org, and the Orlando Museum of Art from Jan. 18 to May 30. General admission, $12. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Set among a connected series of keys at the mouth of Tampa Bay, Fort DeSoto Park, 3500 Pinellas Bayway South, Tierra Verde, (727) 582-2267, www.fortdesoto.com, has 1,136 serene acres encompassing miles of frothy surf and perfect sand, two fishing piers, paved bike and skate trails, a dog park and beach, picnic areas, nature trails and campgrounds. Numbered signs along the shore mark a kayak trail through Mullet Key Bayou, teeming with dolphins, manatees and water birds. Single kayaks rent for $15 an hour, $35 a day; canoes, $17 an hour, $40 a day (cash only) at the Fort DeSoto Canoe Outpost in the park, (727) 864-1991, www.canoeoutpost.com.</p>
        <p>The Pier, 800 Second Avenue NE, (727) 821-6164, www.stpete-pier.com, sits a quarter-mile out in Tampa Bay, crowned with a five-story, upside-down pyramid. It has 16 shops and galleries, restaurants, dolphin sightseeing cruises, surrey bike rentals and a small aquarium.</p>
        <p>In 1999, the city spent $3 million to buy and renovate a vintage Florida attraction, Sunken Gardens, 1825 Fourth Street North, (727) 551-3100, www.stpete.org/sunken.htm. The four-acre plot -- as much as 10 feet below street level -- is again lush with more than 500 species of plants, and its original 1926 historic building has been restored to its elegant Mediterranean Revival glory, painted pastel yellow. Open daily; general admission, $7.</p>
        <p>Next to the garden (and sharing the same entrance) is Great Explorations, the Children's Museum, (727) 821-8992, and at www.greatexplorations.org, which moved there this year. Kids love its laser harp, which has diode lasers instead of strings that youngsters touch to create synthesized music; a new exhibit is Great Splash, with a pinball machine that teaches about the water cycle. Open daily; $8, ages 3 to 11 $7. Joint admission to the gardens and the museum, $12.75 and $8.50.</p>
        <p>Haslam's Book Store, 2025 Central Avenue, (727) 822-8616 and www.haslams.com, now in the fourth generation of the same family, bills itself as Florida's largest new and used bookstore. It has more than 300,000 volumes, including rare titles, and antiquaria jammed into 30,000 square feet. Closed Sunday.</p>
        <p>The BayWalk shopping and entertainment complex opened three years ago at 125 Second Avenue North, (727) 895-9277, www.baywalkstpete.com, with a pretty outdoor courtyard, where bands play alfresco on the weekends, attracting big, noisy crowds. On its second floor is the popular Martini Bar, owned by former Miami Dolphins football star Dan Marino, always rocking with young patrons, who also patronize the state-of-the-art, 20-screen movie theater, and other dozen bars, shops and restaurants.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>The peak season typically runs from November through May.</p>
        <p>An unusually fancy Hampton Inn and Suites, 80 Beach Drive NE, (727) 892-9900, fax (727) 892-9205, www.stpetehamptonsuites.com, complements the city's Mediterranean Revival architectural style. The hotel has 61 rooms and 30 suites, and public areas are planted with bougainvillea. There are shops at street level and a secluded heated pool and patio on the second floor. Doubles cost $119 to $154, suites $139 to $169, depending on the season; Continental breakfast is included.</p>
        <p>Mansion House Bed and Breakfast, 105 Fifth Avenue NE, (800) 274-7520, fax (727) 821-6906, www.mansionbandb.com, has 12 tidy rooms, each with different décor and a dataport and Wi-Fi, in two houses dating to the early 1900's, a courtyard garden and swimming pool. Doubles: $99 to $220, with hot breakfast in the bright, pretty dining room.</p>
        <p>Budget: The 1926 Martha Washington Hotel was a popular winter resort for decades before its acquisition in 1986 by Holiday Inn. Renamed the Heritage Holiday Inn, 234 Third Avenue North, (800) 283-7829, fax (727) 823-1644, www.theheritagehi.com, it features 10 suites and 61 rooms decorated in blues and burgundies, with rates from $89.95 to $169; a small pool; and a shady patio. The $6.95 breakfast buffet in the lobby is prepared by a chef at Julian's Restaurant next door, who often includes thin crepes or eggs Benedict.</p>
        <p>With a knockout view of the steamy bay and whipped-cream clouds, Grayl's Hotel, 340 Beach Drive NE, (888) 508-4448, fax (727) 502-0920, www.graylshotel.com, has 25 remarkably tidy rooms and suites, each done in a different hue, priced at $89 to $175, with Continental breakfast. The hotel is within 10 minutes of more than 40 restaurants.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The queen of downtown is the Renaissance Vinoy Resort and Golf Club, 501 Fifth Avenue NE, (888) 303-4430, fax (727) 894-2270, www.renaissancehotel.com/tpasr. Its fanciful turrets and exotic, 1925-era Italian marble front desk, cypress ceiling beams and glazed quarry tile were preserved during a recent renovation. There are 360 guest rooms and 15 suites, many with spectacular water views. The hotel also has a spa, a big pool with a waterfall, five restaurants, tennis courts, an 18-hole golf course and a marina. Doubles, $199 to $249; suites, $300 to $600.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Skyway Jack's Restaurant, 2795 34th Street South, (727) 867-1907, is a funky local institution with a breakfast menu featuring, among other things, sweetbreads, orange pecan French toast, chipped beef on toast and eggs any style you can imagine. Its clientele ranges from women in Chanel suits to pierced punk rockers to fishermen on their way home from the docks. Open for breakfast and lunch daily; breakfast for two, $12.</p>
        <p>The chef Christopher Ponte trained at Taillevent in Paris, and then moved to New York to work with Daniel Boulud and François Payard. But Ponte and his wife, Jennifer, yearned for their own restaurant, and they now have it: Cafe Ponte, 13505 Icot Boulevard in Clearwater, northwest of St. Pete; (727) 538-5768. Lunch is a deal: Duck egg roll with apricot sauce is $6, a grilled sirloin steak sandwich $7.50, and the passion fruit taster $7. Open for lunch weekdays, and dinner Tuesday to Saturday. Dinner for two with wine, $100.</p>
        <p>The food at Mattison's, an American Bistro, 111 Second Avenue NE, (727) 895-2200, is tasty, if not trendy. You can start with lobster ravioli; follow that with filet mignon with sautéed mushrooms, mashed potatoes, vegetables and creamy béarnaise sauce; and finish with chocolate macadamia nut tart. Lunch weekdays, dinner Tuesday to Saturday. Dinner for two with wine, up to $100.</p>
        <p>The crowd turns up late at Pacific Wave Restaurant, 211 Second Street South, (727) 822-5235, to nibble on fare like Laos spring roll filled with Thai basil, mango and marinated grilled prawns and served with bird's eye chili and cashew dipping sauce, or to have a late dinner of mixed grill of shrimp, scallops and fresh Hawaiian fish with chipotle grits and three sauces. Dinner for two with wine, $120. Dinner Monday to Saturday.</p>
        <p>An excellent seafood restaurant is the Maritana Grille at the Don CeSar Resort and Spa, 3400 Gulf Boulevard, St. Pete Beach, (727) 360-1881, which is famous for dishes like horseradish-crusted Atlantic salmon with shrimp. Hidden in a service area just off the kitchen is the Chef's Table, where the executive chef, Eric Neri, takes up to eight people through six courses of his staff's most creative new dishes, like toasted bread rounds lavished with crème fraîche and caviar; pan-seared scallops with yellowtail snapper, sweet corn and English peas; and a chocolate tower imprinted with gold leaf. These meals are offered Wednesday to Sunday for $125 a person, not including wine. The main dining room is open daily for dinner, which runs about $160 for two with wine.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN SARA KENNEDY lives in Tampa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SARA KENNEDY lives in Tampa.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
