<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="16LIGUID" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1535852"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1038F935A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The Oyster Bay Historical Society today opens ''The Art of Oyster Bay,'' a show honoring the town's 350th anniversary and promoting a campaign to build a new library for the society.</p>
        <p>The exhibition features works by 35 local artists. The artists have donated the pieces, which are devoted to some aspect of life in the area. Some of the works are for sale; others will be sold at an auction on Dec. 6 at the home of Henry Luce 3rd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The Oyster Bay Historical Society today opens ''The Art of Oyster Bay,'' a show honoring the town's 350th anniversary and promoting a campaign to build a new library for the society.</p>
        <p>The exhibition features works by 35 local artists. The artists have donated the pieces, which are devoted to some aspect of life in the area. Some of the works are for sale; others will be sold at an auction on Dec. 6 at the home of Henry Luce 3rd.</p>
        <p>The society is planning to build a fireproof repository for its collection of historic records, photographs, art, books and artifacts -- including many from or about Theodore Roosevelt. The items are currently housed in the Earle-Wightman House, circa 1720.</p>
        <p>Painters, sculptors and photographers contributing works to the show include Elizabeth Roosevelt, a distant cousin of Theodore Roosevelt; George Gach; Nan Coffey; Carol Kingston; Franklin Hill Perrell; Trixie Taylor; and Mort Kunstler.</p>
        <p>The exhibition takes place at the Earle-Wightman House on Summit Street. Information: (516)922-5032.</p>
        <p>Light 10 Candles</p>
        <p>The Long Island Children's Museum in Garden City is celebrating its 10th birthday. To mark the occasion, it has put together an eight-day event that ends next Sunday with a party, complete with cake and entertainment.</p>
        <p>Other special events this week include Louie Miranda's ''Louie Show,'' at 1 and 3 p.m. today; a film festival, from 2 to 5 p.m. on Wednesday; and ''Stories and Song Day'' by Tom Callinan and Ann Shapiro, at 1 and 3 p.m. on Saturday and next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The museum is on Davis Avenue. Information: (516)224-5800.</p>
        <p>Beethoven Today</p>
        <p>Two chamber music concerts today feature Beethoven.</p>
        <p>At Tilles Center on the C.W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville, ''Music at Hillwood'' continues its yearlong salute to ''Beethoven: Genius, Revolutionary, Hero, Symbol of Freedom.''</p>
        <p>The concert is narrated by the actor Jake Robards and features the Shanghai String Quartet playing works by Barber and Bach, along with Beethoven's Quartet, Op.132. Caroline Stoessinger is the host.</p>
        <p>The performance begins at 3 p.m. Information: (516)299-3100.</p>
        <p>At the nearby Brookville Country Club on Cherry Valley Road in Glen Head, Chamber Players International begins its ''Musical Cuisine'' season with Anna Rabinova, violinist, and Jeffrey Biegel, pianist, offering an all-Beethoven program that includes the Violin Sonata, No.5 in F major, Op.24, ''Spring.''</p>
        <p>There is a Champagne brunch buffet at noon, followed by the music at 2 p.m. Information: (877)444-4488.</p>
        <p>Always in Style</p>
        <p>The Long Island Philharmonic turns its attention to ''Classic Masterworks'' by Debussy, Mozart, Grieg and Dvorak for its latest outing.</p>
        <p>The orchestra will be joined by Angela Brown, soprano; Abel Moeng, bass-baritone; and the Long Island Philharmonic Chorus, directed by Frances C. Roberts. The program includes Dvorak's ''Te Deum,'' Op.103.</p>
        <p>The concert takes place on Saturday at Staller Center in Stony Brook and at 7 p.m. next Sunday at Tilles Center in Brookville. Information: (631)293-2222.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Olga Vinokur, a pianist, will play works by Chopin, Mozart and Rachmaninoff at 2:30 p.m. at the Freeport Library on West Merrick Road. Information: (516)379-3274. Strike the Bell, a group singing sea chanteys, will perform at 2 p.m. at the Sachem Library on Holbrook Road in Holbrook. Information: (631)588-5024.</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- The Dongnae Yaryu Masked Dance-Drama Preservation Society, a 27-member troupe that performs Korean folk theater, visits the Wang Center on the Stony Brook campus of the State University of New York at 2 p.m. Information: (631)632-6353.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- To open its season, the Bay Area Symphony and Chorus perform works by Beethoven, Puccini, Mozart and Tchaikovsky at 8 p.m. The concert takes place at the Young Middle School on Sylvan Avenue in Bayport. Information: (631)281-6243.</p>
        <p>Catrin Finch, a Welsh harpist who is the royal harpist to the Prince of Wales, performs at 8 p.m. at the Port Washington Library on Library Drive. Information: (516)883-4400.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
