<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Give 2 Young Backs a Crack at Starting</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGRIGGS, LAMAR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPARKS, PHILLIPPI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DA163BF934A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Give 2 Young Backs a Crack at Starting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 26.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Giants' starting lineup when they take on the Dolphins in Miami Saturday night will basically be the same starting lineup that will begin the regular season against the Bears in Chicago eight days later. So said Coach Dan Reeves today, and that bodes well for two defensive backs, Lamar McGriggs and Phillippi Sparks.</p>
        <p>Sparks, a second-round draft choice out of Arizona State in 1992, will start at right cornerback on Saturday. He has been battling veteran Perry Williams for a starting role after spending most of last season as a nickel back and special-teams player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Giants' starting lineup when they take on the Dolphins in Miami Saturday night will basically be the same starting lineup that will begin the regular season against the Bears in Chicago eight days later. So said Coach Dan Reeves today, and that bodes well for two defensive backs, Lamar McGriggs and Phillippi Sparks.</p>
        <p>Sparks, a second-round draft choice out of Arizona State in 1992, will start at right cornerback on Saturday. He has been battling veteran Perry Williams for a starting role after spending most of last season as a nickel back and special-teams player.</p>
        <p>McGriggs, an eighth-round draft choice out of Western Illinois in 1991, will start at free safety against the Dolphins. The third-year Giant -- an eighth-round pick out of Western Illinois -- started 10 games last season after Myron Guyton was sidelined with a back injury. He and Guyton have been battling for a starting job.</p>
        <p>Reeves, of course, didn't guarantee that Saturday's starters will be the starters on Sept. 5. But, he said, "I don't see a lot of changes." Offensive Line Shapes Up</p>
        <p>When the Giants start the season in Chicago, Doug Riesenberg will be beginning his fifth season as the starting right tackle and as one of the more anonymous Giant regulars.</p>
        <p>A sixth-round draft choice from California in 1987, Riesenberg has started every game except one for the Giants since 1989, the exception coming two years ago when an ankle injury briefly sidelined him.</p>
        <p>He is ready for this season, he thinks. "It's going to be interesting, a challenge," he said with regard to the new attitudes and schemes of a new coaching staff.</p>
        <p>Bob Kratch will be the right guard in the absence of Eric Moore, whose suspension, growing out of a case involving steroid possession, will keep him out of the first four regular-season games. Bart Oates remains a fixture at center and two other veterans, William Roberts and Jumbo Elliott, will start on the left side at guard and tackle, respectively. So the offensive line, so much of a concern this summer because of Roberts's irregular heartbeat and Elliott's holdout, is coming together just in time for a final rehearsal.</p>
        <p>That is good news for the 37-year-old quarterback, Phil Simms, who was especially sharp today as the Giants buzzed through a no-contact, 90-minute workout featuring the passing game.  Taylor Isn't Kicking; Or Is He?</p>
        <p>Lawrence Taylor, in a group interview after practice, said he was feeling fine, looking forward to the season and definitely not looking back. "I don't even think about last year," he said. "That was a sad period in Giant history."</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
