<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Community Reinvestment Is Right and It Pays</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MORTGAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMUNITY REINVESTMENT ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URBAN AREAS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURD, MAUDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D91E3BF934A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Community Reinvestment Is Right and It Pays</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Fresh Money for Poor Communities" (editorial, Aug. 13) promotes several harmful myths about community reinvestment lending.</p>
        <p>First, low-income borrowers are not necessarily "credit-risky." Available data from private mortgage insurance companies suggest that low-income homeowners are far less likely to default on mortgages than high-income borrowers, in part because low-income borrowers view homeownership as shelter, rather than investment. And, after a decade of record losses on speculative investments in commercial real estate, we have yet to see a bank or savings and loan institution go belly up because of too much lending to poor people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Fresh Money for Poor Communities" (editorial, Aug. 13) promotes several harmful myths about community reinvestment lending.</p>
        <p>First, low-income borrowers are not necessarily "credit-risky." Available data from private mortgage insurance companies suggest that low-income homeowners are far less likely to default on mortgages than high-income borrowers, in part because low-income borrowers view homeownership as shelter, rather than investment. And, after a decade of record losses on speculative investments in commercial real estate, we have yet to see a bank or savings and loan institution go belly up because of too much lending to poor people.</p>
        <p>Second, notwithstanding a dangerous campaign for "regulatory relief" by the banking industry, the Community Reinvestment Act is not a source of massive paperwork burdens for banks. The act has only three minor technical requirements, and the policy of bank regulatory agencies is that lenders need not keep any special documentation for the act's purposes. A 1991 Office of Management and Budget survey found the act to be the least burdensome consumer protection law on the books.</p>
        <p>Finally, the act is not the utter failure you portray. Nearly $35 billion has been lent in low- and moderate-income neighborhoods as a result of the act. Many lenders, working with the very community development organizations you praise, have developed precisely the expertise in community lending whose lack you bemoan. And the best Community Reinvestment Act performers have found that community reinvestment lending is not just good social policy, but good business as well.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the act has not met its potential to revitalize neighborhoods. But the real problem is a scandalous record of enforcement by the four Federal banking agencies under 12 years of hostile administrations. Nearly 90 percent of lenders get "satisfactory" grades, and less than a dozen merger applications have ever been denied because of this law, despite abundant evidence of redlining.</p>
        <p>As Senator William Proxmire, the author of the act, observed several years ago: "Regulators seem to think that we're all living in Lake Wobegone. Like the children of the fictional village, United States lenders are all above average. Almost all get high ratings year after year, and almost none is ever held back. . . . And I ask myself, how is it that so many neighborhoods are continuing to fail, while so many lending institutions are continuing to pass?" Perhaps the Administration's review of the act will reverse this outrageous record.</p>
        <p>Your suggestion that banks be allowed to "buy out" of the act through contributions to community development banks is seriously wrongheaded and smacks of the creation of a "separate and unequal" banking system, one for minorities and the poor, and another for everyone else. Turning the tide of despair in low-income neighborhoods requires more than token charitable contributions from the banking industry. We need mainstream lenders to view community reinvestment as a business proposition and to put the ingenuity of the market to work there.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government confers on lenders a host of advantages -- public charters, taxpayer-backed deposit insurance at a discounted price and access to the discount window at the Fed. After having spent hundreds of billions of dollars to bail out these lenders, we have learned that all this public largess is not without fiscal consequence. Surely, the least we can expect in return is a banking system that fairly serves the needs of all Americans.  MAUDE HURD  Natl. President, Assn. of Community Organizations for Reform Now Boston, Aug. 17, 1993</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
