<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel Steps Up Its Security In Fear of New Bombings</title>
    <meta content="04MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="948403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hamas (Islamic Fundamentalist Movement)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DC133DF937A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel Steps Up Its Security In Fear of New Bombings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israel steps up security nationwide amid signs that Islamic militants may be planning more attacks following recent suicide bombings in Jerusalem; deploys thousands of army troops, police officers and paramilitsry forces, nearly doubling number on streets of Jerusalem alone; move adds to sense of unease and leaves buses mostly empty and shopping centers nearly deserted; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As relations between the Israeli and Palestinian leaders continued to fray, a reinforced army of security forces fanned out across Israel today in the face of new signs that Islamic militants may be planning more attacks after a suicide bombing last week.</p>
        <p>The huge deployment, which included thousands of army troops, police officers and paramilitary forces, nearly doubled the number of heavily armed police on the streets of Jerusalem alone and added to a sense of unease that left buses mostly empty and shopping centers nearly deserted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As relations between the Israeli and Palestinian leaders continued to fray, a reinforced army of security forces fanned out across Israel today in the face of new signs that Islamic militants may be planning more attacks after a suicide bombing last week.</p>
        <p>The huge deployment, which included thousands of army troops, police officers and paramilitary forces, nearly doubled the number of heavily armed police on the streets of Jerusalem alone and added to a sense of unease that left buses mostly empty and shopping centers nearly deserted.</p>
        <p>A threat issued in the name of Hamas, the militant group blamed by the authorities for the suicide attack that killed 13 Israelis in a crowded Jerusalem market on Wednesday, warned of further action if Palestinian prisoners were not freed by 9 tonight. The deadline expired without incident.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials have said they do not know whether the warning, posted in in the West Bank town of Ramallah the same day as the bombing, was credible. But the chief of the Israeli police, Assaf Hefetz, said the authorities had learned of ''a series of details'' pointing to the possibility of renewed violence.</p>
        <p>And in a sign of the potential for retaliatory strikes, the Israeli authorities said a Palestinian man in his 50's or 60's was found shot dead near the Jewish settlement of Carmel in the West Bank this evening. They said Palestinian witnesses had reported that he had been shot from a passing car. Israel's Channel 2 television quoted one witness as saying that the car bore the yellow license plates issued to Israelis.</p>
        <p>The dark mood today was underscored by a stern declaration from Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, who told his Cabinet during a daylong meeting that Israel would no longer honor its agreements with Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, unless Mr. Arafat did more to crack down on Islamic militants in territory under Palestinian control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu and Mr. Arafat have adopted an increasingly venomous tone in recent days, accusing each other of bad faith. Today the Prime Minister suggested that the consequences of a breakdown in relations between the two sides could be drastic.</p>
        <p>''If Arafat honors his commitments in the agreement, chiefly to fight terrorism, the agreement will survive,'' Mr. Netanyahu said of the interim peace accords that Israel first concluded with the Palestinians four years ago. ''If he doesn't, we will not keep up our part of the bargain unequivocally.''</p>
        <p>In the four days since the bombing, Israel has responded with harsh measures including sealing off the Palestinian territories and suspending plans for peace talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu has also said Israel will halt payment of the taxes and customs fees that it owes the Palestinian Authority, including a $25 million allotment that it was to have turned over on Friday. That sum alone accounts for more than half of the monthly Palestinian budget.</p>
        <p>Together with Israel's decision to close the Palestinian territories, the suspension of payments is bound to exert immediate and severe economic hardship.</p>
        <p>There were reports that some of the more right-wing members of the Israeli Cabinet, including Agriculture Minister Rafael Eitan, had urged Mr. Netanyahu to take even harsher action by dispatching troops into the cities now under Palestinian control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu has warned that he would consider such a step, but there has been no indication that he is preparing to take it. His Government today also backed away from an earlier threat to jam Palestinian radio broadcasts, a move that officials said had proven technically and financially unfeasible.</p>
        <p>Some 15 suicide bombers have killed at least 140 people in Israel in the last three and a half years. In contrast to nearly all previous attackers, the two men who blew themselves up in the produce market on Wednesday still have not been identified, adding to the mystery surrounding the event.</p>
        <p>Several previous suicide bombers recorded videotapes before their attacks to boast of their plans for martyrdom, and the deaths of others have been openly mourned by family members in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip. The identities of others, including the Palestinian man who carried the bomb that killed three people in a Tel Aviv coffee house in March, have been quickly traced by the Israeli authorities.</p>
        <p>But in the latest attack, the Israeli authorities say no one has stepped forward to identify the bombers. Some officials suggested today that the attackers might have come to Israel from an Arab country, but they acknowledged that they had no evidence to support the theory.</p>
        <p>One reason that no one has stepped forward to identify the suicide bombers, some officials suggested, may be that the Palestinian Authority, under pressure from the Israeli Government, has begun to deal increasingly severely with the relatives and associates of those who carry out suicide attacks.</p>
        <p>Another reason, the Israeli officials said, may be emerging disagreements within the Islamic militant group Hamas about the wisdom of resorting to violent action.</p>
        <p>But even though Israeli forces arrested 37 more Palestinians overnight Saturday, bringing to 117 the number taken into custody since the attack, the police said such sweeps had been little more more than trolling expeditions.</p>
        <p>''In my opinion, we still don't have a lead,'' Mr. Hefetz, the police chief, said.</p>
        <p>Police officials said their forensic experiments had concluded that the explosive used in the two devices was TNT, the material most frequently used by Islamic militants operating from the West Bank and Gaza. The officials said they were confident that the bombs had contained no sophisticated plastic explosives, which might have suggested a connection to radical groups like the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, which has used such materials extensively in the past.</p>
        <p>As the investigation continued, Palestinian officials renewed their charges that Palestinians were being unfairly and collectively punished for a terrorist action beyond their control.</p>
        <p>The latest Israeli closing of the West Bank and Gaza Strip has been the most severe, with military checkpoints and dragon-teeth barriers stretched across even back roads that Palestinians once used to evade Israeli scrutiny.</p>
        <p>The closing has kept tens of thousands of Palestinians from reaching their jobs in Israel and halted deliveries of newspapers and virtually all other goods from Israel into Palestinian-controlled areas, driving some prices to extraordinarily high levels.</p>
        <p>Even the crossing points to Jordan and Egypt have been closed to Palestinians, leaving hundreds stranded on both sides of the borders. And because those prevented from leaving the West Bank and Gaza include some people who are critically ill, the Palestinian Authority issued an appeal for international help in urging Israel to ease its restrictions.</p>
        <p>''We are in a big, unjust prison,'' said Fraij al-Khairy, the Palestinian Authority's deputy minister of civil affairs.</p>
        <p>A young Palestinian bride, Ruba Musa, who was trying to make her way to her wedding in the West Bank village of Abud, said she had been turned away at seven checkpoints as she tried to leave her home city of Ramallah by various routes. ''It is low of them to stop a bride at a checkpoint,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In Israel, too, some citizens chafed at the inconveniences imposed by Israel's restrictions and worried that more might follow.</p>
        <p>On roadways, buses and even shopping streets, paramilitary police officers halted cars and pedestrians to inspect citizens' identification papers.</p>
        <p>The officers responded to more than 200 calls from jittery civilians who reported finding suspicious packages. None turned out to be explosive devices, but several were detonated, including two at Jersusalem's central bus station, where even policemen who have grown accustomed to suicide bomb attacks appeared unusually tense.</p>
        <p>Security officials from Israel and the Palestinian Authority met on Saturday night to discuss their troubled relationship, but both sides said little progress had been made.</p>
        <p>Ami Ayalon, director of Shin Bet, the Israeli domestic intelligence service, was reported to have complained after the meeting that Mr. Arafat had failed to respond to last week's attack with the vigor he showed in 1996 after a series of suicide bomb attacks.</p>
        <p>For his part, Jibril al-Rajoub, the head of the Palestinian preventive security force in the West Bank, went out of his way to specify that the meeting did not constitute a renewal of security cooperation between the two sides.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
