<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frist Isn't Following Republicans on Criticism of Judges</title>
    <meta content="06CONG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/06/politics/06cong.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1662766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Separation-of-Powers Doctrine</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frist, Bill (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delay, Tom (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiavo, Terri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Frist, Bill</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Schiavo, Terri</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EED61F3FF935A35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frist Isn't Following Republicans on Criticism of Judges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Frist Isn't Following Republicans on Criticism of Judges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Bill Frist, majority leader, breaks with fellow Republicans calling for new judicial accountability after Terri Schiavo's death; Democrats accuse Republicans of undermining separation of powers; Frist, disagreeing with Tom DeLay, House majority leader, says he sees no need to examine why federal judges chose not to intervene in Schiavo's case after Congress had passed emergency law that let them do so; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The struggle over the relationship between Congress and the courts intensified on Tuesday as Senator Bill Frist, the majority leader, broke with fellow Republicans calling for new judicial accountability after Terri Schiavo's death. Democrats accused Republicans of undermining the separation of powers.</p>
        <p>Disagreeing with Representative Tom DeLay, the Texas Republican who is the House majority leader, Dr. Frist said he saw no need to examine why federal judges chose not to intervene in Ms. Schiavo's case after Congress had passed an emergency law that let them do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Senate majority leader broke with fellow Republicans, calling for new judicial accountability after Terri Schiavo's death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The struggle over the relationship between Congress and the courts intensified on Tuesday as Senator Bill Frist, the majority leader, broke with fellow Republicans calling for new judicial accountability after Terri Schiavo's death. Democrats accused Republicans of undermining the separation of powers.</p>
        <p>Disagreeing with Representative Tom DeLay, the Texas Republican who is the House majority leader, Dr. Frist said he saw no need to examine why federal judges chose not to intervene in Ms. Schiavo's case after Congress had passed an emergency law that let them do so.</p>
        <p>''I believe we have a fair and independent judiciary today,'' said Dr. Frist, who declined to comment directly on Mr. DeLay. ''I respect that.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Frist, of Tennessee, moved quickly to separate the emotionally charged case of Ms. Schiavo from the politically charged possibility of a showdown over Democratic filibusters against President Bush's judicial nominees. Opponents are linking the two, calling them examples of how Republicans, stymied by resistance, take extreme steps to advance their ideology. That tie could complicate Dr. Frist's push to change Senate rules.</p>
        <p>The Senate Democratic leader, Harry Reid of Nevada, said the Republicans were guilty of an ''arrogancy of power.''</p>
        <p>''The Republican legislative leaders in Congress have forgotten what our Constitution's all about,'' Mr. Reid said. ''If they don't get what they want, they attack who's ever around. Now they're after the courts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid cited Mr. DeLay's comments last week that suggested potential retribution against the judges, as well as a speech on Monday by Senator John Cornyn, Republican of Texas and a former state judge. In his remarks on the Senate floor, Mr. Cornyn said he wondered whether recent court-related violence could be connected to public frustration with an unaccountable judiciary.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Cornyn said that he did not share Mr. DeLay's view on examining the judges and that his own comments were being misconstrued for political reasons. He also said judges should expect to have their work scrutinized.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the judiciary is immune from criticism when they decide cases in a way that reflects more of an ideology or political agenda,'' Mr. Cornyn said.</p>
        <p>Democrats condemned Mr. Cornyn's comments, coupling them with Mr. DeLay's, and said Republicans were determined to curb the independence of the judiciary.</p>
        <p>''The presumption that somehow we are going to threaten judges or demand certain outcomes from judges is antithetical to a free people under law,'' said Representative Steny H. Hoyer of Maryland, the No. 2 Democrat in the House.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay's office said he would have no comment on Dr. Frist's statement. His spokesman, Dan Allen, also said too much was being made of the majority leader's comments last week.</p>
        <p>''House Republicans feel that the courts ignored the clear intent of the legislation, and at this point in time, we feel that we should look into why they did so,'' Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frist's comments were similar to a view expressed last week by Vice President Dick Cheney, who told the editorial board of The New York Post that he did not believe retribution against judges for their decisions was a good idea.</p>
        <p>Mr. DeLay has for years been outspoken in criticizing what he sees as judicial activism, and he has led legislative efforts to limit the jurisdiction of federal judges in some areas. Before he changed plans to attend the pope's funeral, Mr. DeLay had been scheduled to be a headline speaker this week at a conservative conference, ''Confronting the Judicial War on Faith,'' sponsored by the Judeo-Christian Council for Constitutional Restoration.</p>
        <p>According to its organizers, potential steps to be discussed are impeaching federal judges who let personal values influence decisions, reducing or eliminating court financing, and giving Congress and the states the power to vacate Supreme Court rulings.</p>
        <p>''This is going to be an action-oriented conference,'' said a meeting planner, Don Feder.</p>
        <p>The tone of the criticism aimed at the judiciary after the death of Ms. Schiavo, whose feeding tube was removed, has drawn the attention of the American Bar Association. In an e-mail message on Friday to the bar's membership, its president, Robert J. Grey Jr., said lawyers and others who work with the law needed to respond to what he described as decreasing respect for the courts.</p>
        <p>''As the voice of the legal profession,'' Mr. Grey wrote, ''we must not allow those among us who would do harm, in any form, to destroy the very freedoms our legal system is entrusted to protect.''</p>
        <p>As interest groups stepped up their lobbying, the political parties continued maneuvering in advance of a potential Senate vote to bar the filibusters. Mr. Reid said he was willing to consider ways to avoid a floor fight.</p>
        <p>''Let's just calm down and see where the American people are on this issue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Republicans say it is Democrats who are stirring up the issue, noting they have established a special political strategy office, under Mr. Reid's control, on the filibuster fight. The Republicans say that Dr. Frist is facing increasing pressure from Republican senators to move forward and that his options are diminishing.</p>
        <p>''We will reach a point where negotiations, I guess, will have to end, because they will be fruitless, and then votes will have to be cast,'' said Senator Rick Santorum of Pennsylvania, the No. 3 Republican.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
