<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Build Those Houses</title>
    <meta content="02SAFI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Essay" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="912819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Essay"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D91131F931A35750C0A961958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Build Those Houses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire Op-Ed column says that if Israel were to defer to Palestinian demand that houses for Jews not be built in Jerusalem, it would put city's status 'in play,' and raise Arab expectations to heights that would make peace settlement impossible; sees affirmation of Israeal's intent to keep capital whole; urges Pres Clinton to make clear to Yasir Arafat what Palestinians can realistically expect, and not pump him up with false hopes (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Palestinian Arabs are calling on the world to stop Israel from building houses for Israelis inside the city limits of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>That presents the Palestinian claim to sovereignty over part of what Israel dares to consider its capital in the starkest of terms. If Jews were to defer to this demand, that would automatically put the status of today's undivided Jerusalem ''in play'' -- and raise Arab expectations to heights that would make a negotiated settlement impossible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Palestinian Arabs are calling on the world to stop Israel from building houses for Israelis inside the city limits of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>That presents the Palestinian claim to sovereignty over part of what Israel dares to consider its capital in the starkest of terms. If Jews were to defer to this demand, that would automatically put the status of today's undivided Jerusalem ''in play'' -- and raise Arab expectations to heights that would make a negotiated settlement impossible.</p>
        <p>Realistic expectations on both sides are the keys to peace.</p>
        <p>Last month, after the Likud-approved withdrawal from Hebron, even the most hard-line Israelis grasped the reality that a large portion of disputed West Bank land would be turned over to Palestinian self-rule -- and that the resulting ''entity,'' to use the word rejectionist Arabs long applied to Israel, would have many attributes of a nation.</p>
        <p>Many Israelis never expected that. The prospect of a Palestinian nation on the border took a lot of hard swallowing. Now that its likelihood is realized, Prime Minister Netanyahu must negotiate limits on Palestine's coming sovereignty to protect Israel's airspace, water supply, and population.</p>
        <p>This month, we have the test of the realism of Palestinian expectations. Do those include the partition, euphemized as ''sharing,'' of Jerusalem?  Such a demand would be a deal-breaker; to insist on creating a foreign island inside Jerusalem would be as provocative as Israeli annexation of the entire West Bank.</p>
        <p>Israel just had a free election about the future of its capital, and 56 percent  of Israel's Jews supported Netanyahu; one cause of that landslide among non-Arab Israelis was a conviction that he would be the most certain to preserve Jerusalem's unity.</p>
        <p>That is why this construction of homes in the neighborhood called Har Homa -- which Arabs see as on the pathway from their future state to East Jerusalem -- is no mere tacking to the right. It is an affirmation of Israel's intent to keep its capital whole. Netanyahu, having waited until the Supreme Court approved the legality of building on the land, showed an interest in amity by providing half again as many homes inside Jerusalem for Arab families.</p>
        <p>Within Israel, a consensus has been struck accepting a half-the-West-Bank state with its capital outside Jerusalem. Some of Labor's ardent doves, including Oslo architect Yossi Beilin, joined Likud leaders in an informal manifesto that included maintaining undivided sovereignty in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>In that remarkable embrace of realism, Israelis of left and right supported special status for holy places and local power-sharing in Arab neighborhoods, but the unofficial coalition's central message to the Arabs and the world was plain: Most Israelis envision a final settlement that respects the unity of Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>''You cannot make peace on the outside if you cannot make peace on the inside,'' Netanyahu told Sir David Frost the other night. Israelis are making peace with each other on the inside about territory, despite the fiercest rows about politics; now the challenge to the Palestinians is to make their internal peace as well, which calls for getting their expectations in line with reality.</p>
        <p>When Yasir Arafat arrives at the White House tomorrow morning (sorry, that bedroom is booked) President Clinton should make clear what Palestinians can realistically expect: a state with a flag and a U.N. seat but limits on air and water rights; half the arable land of the West Bank, made contiguous around Israeli settlements through the most creative gerrymandering; and economic opportunity linked to democratic progress.</p>
        <p>How should Clinton and his James Baker-trained advisers help negotiations move ahead?</p>
        <p>Not by pumping up false hopes for certain letdown; not by tolerating crowd-pleasing hate rhetoric; not by failing to press for arrests of Arab terrorists; and surely not by tut-tutting at Israel for making clear that Jerusalem is not on the table for sectioning into competing capitals.</p>
        <p>The clear signal Israel sends now about the inviolability of Jerusalem makes final settlement more likely later. U.N. or U.S. pressure on Israel to delay sending any signal at all, or to show by silence or inaction any weakness of resolve, would invite unrealistic expectations by Palestinians and thus subvert a final agreement.</p>
        <p>Essay</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
