<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Pressure Cited in Case Against Marines</title>
    <meta content="Y21CAB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cable Cars and Trams</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marine Corps (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ashby, Richard J (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schweitzer, Joseph (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seagraves, Chandler (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raney, William 2d (Capt)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1DA1E3CF932A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="490" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Pressure Cited in Case Against Marines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>CAMP LEJEUNE, N.C., April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyer for pilot of US Marine Corp jet fighter that clipped cable of ski gondola cable in Italy, killing 20 people, says political pressure led to charges against four-man crew, who face charges of involuntary manslaughter and negligent homicide; four identified as Capt Richard J Ashby, Capt Joseph P Schweitzer, Capt Chandler P Seagraves and Capt William L Raney 2d; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lawyer for the pilot of a Marine jet that clipped a ski gondola cable in Italy, killing 20 people, said today that political pressure had led to charges against the four-man crew.</p>
        <p>The most serious charges brought against the four are 20 counts of involuntary manslaughter and negligent homicide. Charged last month were the pilot, Capt. Richard J. Ashby, and Capt. Joseph P. Schweitzer, Capt. Chandler P. Seagraves and Capt. William L. Raney 2d.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lawyer for the pilot of a Marine jet that clipped a ski gondola cable in Italy, killing 20 people, said today that political pressure had led to charges against the four-man crew.</p>
        <p>The most serious charges brought against the four are 20 counts of involuntary manslaughter and negligent homicide. Charged last month were the pilot, Capt. Richard J. Ashby, and Capt. Joseph P. Schweitzer, Capt. Chandler P. Seagraves and Capt. William L. Raney 2d.</p>
        <p>The four men appeared here today with their lawyers at an administrative phase of an Article 32 hearing, the military equivalent of a grand jury hearing. At today's procedure, Lieut. Col. Ronald L. Rogers decided to hold two Article 32 hearings, in May and in June, to determine if the four men will be tried by a court martial. Each involuntary manslaughter specification carries a maximum sentence of 10 years in prison. Each negligent homicide charge carries a maximum of 3 years.</p>
        <p>The four crewmen, based at nearby Cherry Point air station, said little other than to respond to questions from Colonel Rogers or their lawyers.</p>
        <p>At a news conference after the hearing, Frank Spinner, the pilot's civilian lawyer, said he was concerned that the crewmen, not only his client, faced the same charges.</p>
        <p>''There is certainly enough to indicate at this point that what has happened thus far has been a function of political pressure,'' said Mr. Spinner, who represented First Lieut. Kelly Flinn of the Air Force on adultery charges. Mr. Spinner said, ''For decades military members have been involved in training exercises which have resulted in death and in many of those cases there have been acts of negligence and perhaps even recklessness, and yet there does not appear to be anyone court-martialed previously in similar circumstances.''</p>
        <p>The crewmen did not speak at the news conference.</p>
        <p>Marine Corps lawyers representing the Government requested a joint hearing for the men, but Colonel Rogers agreed to a request by lawyers for Captain Seagraves that separate hearings be held. Capt. Paul E. Kaplan, a Marine Corps lawyer, argued that his client and Captain Raney were in the back seats of the EA-6B Prowler aircraft with different duties and different range of visibility when the incident occurred, on Feb. 3, near Cavalese, Italy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
