<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agreement Will Spare Historic Site</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="861920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FREDERICKSBURG (VA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WAL-MART</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">KENMORE FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON, GEORGE (1732-99)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia/Fredericksburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4D71339F931A35754C0A960958260" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agreement Will Spare Historic Site</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second time in two years, efforts by historians and preservation groups have saved what they regard as a hallowed piece of American history.</p>
        <p>Just as the Disney Company was discouraged in 1994 from building a giant history theme park near Civil War battlefields in Northern Virginia, Wal-Mart Stores, the giant Arkansas retailer, said today that it would be willing to abandon plans to construct a store on property that was once part of George Washington's boyhood home along the Rappahannock River near Fredericksburg, Va.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second time in two years, efforts by historians and preservation groups have saved what they regard as a hallowed piece of American history.</p>
        <p>Just as the Disney Company was discouraged in 1994 from building a giant history theme park near Civil War battlefields in Northern Virginia, Wal-Mart Stores, the giant Arkansas retailer, said today that it would be willing to abandon plans to construct a store on property that was once part of George Washington's boyhood home along the Rappahannock River near Fredericksburg, Va.</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart agreed that if a deal could be completed that would repay the company its development costs so far, it would buy another site in Stafford County to build a store that could be even larger than the 93,000-square-foot one planned for the original site. The owners of the original site also agreed to the plan.</p>
        <p>"I've thought all along that it's amazing what you can do if you don't mind who gets the credit," said Bill Beck, president of the Historic Fredericksburg Foundation, referring to local and national efforts to fight commercial development of the site. "I'm know I'm going to go to bed tonight pleased that we have gotten this far."</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart's willingness to consider an alternative site emerged from an offer  by the Kenmore Foundation of Fredericksburg to buy two tracts, a 15-acre site where the Washington farm stood and the adjacent 30-acre property that was also  part of the farm and was where Wal-Mart had planned to build. The Kenmore Foundation is a nationwide group that oversees Kenmore Mansion, the restored home of George Washington's sister, Betty Washington Lewis, and her husband, Fielding Lewis, who supplied ammunition to American forces in the Revolutionary  War.</p>
        <p>If the Kenmore Foundation can raise about $3 million and commit to buy the land by Aug. 15, Wal-Mart will develop the alternate site, about a half mile east of the Washington farm, known locally as Ferry Farm, according to the new plan.</p>
        <p>In addition to repaying Wal-Mart's costs and its local representative, the Richmond Group, the money go to the Warren family of Northern Virginia, which has owned the land for years.</p>
        <p>Charles L. Cabell, a lawyer for the Richmond Group, predicted that the deal would be successful. "I think it will happen," Mr. Cabell said. "The Warrens want to close, and Wal-Mart wants a store in the area."</p>
        <p>Wal-Mart's commitment to the area has come as heartening news to Stafford County officials, relieved that they escaped the loss of jobs and development Prince William County felt when Disney pulled out of the theme park plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck said that Kenmore officials were also excited about the possibility  of having four George Washington-related attractions in the Fredericksburg area. In addition to Kenmore Mansion, the foundation also runs the house where the first President's mother, Mary Baldwin Washington, lived, and a tavern once owned by his brother, Charles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
