<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cause Unknown for Fatal Pipe Rupture</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="569763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STEAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASBESTOS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSOLIDATED EDISON CO OF NY INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MURTHA, EUGENE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCTIGUE, MARTIN (CAPT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asbestos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DF1F3FF931A25752C1A964958260" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cause Unknown for Fatal Pipe Rupture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consolidated Edison officials said yesterday that they did not know how a pipe burst on Tuesday night, letting loose a blast of 500-degree steam that killed a utility mechanic and gravely injured two other men at a Manhattan power station on the East River.</p>
        <p>A thorough examination of the 40-year-old steel pipe will be delayed while contractors clean up asbestos that the steam spread over a courtyard and driveway opening onto First Avenue at the end of East 39th Street. A preliminary examination showed that the half-inch-thick steel of the pipe had been peeled back by the rush of steam to create a four-foot oval gash. No one was working on the pipe at the time, Con Ed officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consolidated Edison officials said yesterday that they did not know how a pipe burst on Tuesday night, letting loose a blast of 500-degree steam that killed a utility mechanic and gravely injured two other men at a Manhattan power station on the East River.</p>
        <p>A thorough examination of the 40-year-old steel pipe will be delayed while contractors clean up asbestos that the steam spread over a courtyard and driveway opening onto First Avenue at the end of East 39th Street. A preliminary examination showed that the half-inch-thick steel of the pipe had been peeled back by the rush of steam to create a four-foot oval gash. No one was working on the pipe at the time, Con Ed officials said.</p>
        <p>Several days ago, Con Ed closed a pipe that connects the north half of the Waterside plant to the pipes that carry steam under the streets, for maintenance. Then the utility detoured the steam, which heats buildings in Manhattan, through the south half of the plant. It was the pipe that connects the halves that ruptured.  Air Samples Taken</p>
        <p>The company initially said it did not believe that the explosion had spread any asbestos at the Waterside plant, but the city Department of Environmental Protection said that some asbestos had escaped onto First Avenue. Air samples taken by the city during the steam release showed no abnormal asbestos levels, said Babu Thomas, director of enforcement in the Department of Environmental Protection's asbestos control program.</p>
        <p>The dead man was identified by Con Edison as Eugene Murtha, 58 years old, of Bensonhurst, Brooklyn.  Mr. Murtha, who started with Con Ed in 1966, had been working on an electric fan on the seventh level of the plant. His body was found on the ninth level.</p>
        <p>In the roaring, blinding scene of confusion that followed the pipe break, five firefighters who arrived at 9:17 P.M., 10 minutes after the break, were erroneously told that people were still trapped in the plant and set out to find them. One of the firefighters, a captain now in critical condition at the burn unit of New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center, suffered extensive burns internally and externally when the straps of his air pack became tangled in a stairwell. Four others suffered burns as they took turns trying to pull the captain to safety.</p>
        <p>"The rescuers became the rescued," said Lieut. Andrew Clark, a spokesman for the Fire Department.</p>
        <p>The captain, Martin McTigue, 48 years old, of Rescue Company 4, Woodside, Queens, was listed in critical but stable condition yesterday, said a hospital spokeswoman. Also listed as critical but stable was Bogdan Puchalski, 37, an employee of the Ogden Corporation, who was at the plant removing asbestos under contract with Con Ed. Mr. Puchalski also had internal and external burns.</p>
        <p>Mayor David N. Dinkins went to the hospital to visit the firefighters, and met with Captain McTigue's wife, Patricia, and their four daughters, Mary, 20, Jean, 19, Christine, 16, and Bridget, 14.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cleon W. Goodwin, director of the burn center, said that breathing tubes had been inserted in the two men to prevent throat tissue from swelling and choking them. There is no direct treatment for internal burns, he said.</p>
        <p>"If you take 100 patients who have these large burns and steam inhalation, approximately half will not survive an injury like this," he said. He added that the extent of their injuries was not yet clear. The two men are on morphine but are conscious, he said.</p>
        <p>A second firefighter, William Boltja, 35, was also in the burn unit with a back injury and second-degree burns on his legs. Three others who had facial burns spent the night at the burn unit but were discharged yesterday morning. Workers Thought to Be Inside</p>
        <p>Lieut. Jack Duggan said that when the team arrived from Queens, filling in for a Manhattan unit that was busy elsewhere, "there was a sign-in sheet of Con Ed indicating that there were 14 to 16 people still in the building."</p>
        <p>"They were in there, doing their search, when their position became untenable and he became entangled in an iron railing in a stairwell," Lieutenant Duggan said, referring to Captain McTigue, a 23-year veteran firefighter.</p>
        <p>There was no one home at the Murtha home yesterday. Mr. Murtha's family arrived at Waterside at 1:45 A.M. Wednesday to identify his body.</p>
        <p>Executives at Mr. Puchalski's company, Ogden, were not able to provide any information about the injured worker.</p>
        <p>The Waterside plant, opened in 1901, is the oldest in the city that is still in use, but nearly all the equipment in the red-brick building is far younger. The age of the 40-year-old pipe is not unusual, said Dan Walden, a Con Ed spokesman. He said some pipes in the system, which serves Manhattan south of 96th Street, are nearly 100 years old. "The one thing that's unusual about this pipe is it is not underground," Mr. Walden said.</p>
        <p>The pipe, which generally carries 400,000 pounds of steam an hour at 500 degrees, will be examined by outside experts, including metallurgists, he said. Waterside, which burns gas or oil and is used to make electricity in peak periods, was producing only steam at the time of the accident, and only two of its four boilers were in use. Because the weather is not especially cold, the company said, it would have no trouble meeting steam demand using other plants on the system.</p>
        <p>Around the country, ruptures of steam pipes are not infrequent. Sometimes they are caused by chemical reactions that gradually wear away pipe walls. Sometimes they are caused by water moving through the system and slamming into weak spots.</p>
        <p>In this case, the break occurred on the inside edge of a 90-degree bend, near the top surface, according to the company.</p>
        <p>Yesterday afternoon workers with paintbrushes, in anti-contamination suits and respirators, painstakingly swept asbestos from the driveway that leads from the courtyard where the pipe burst onto First Avenue.</p>
        <p>Con Edison said that Waterside was structurally sound and that workers were checking electrical components for moisture. It could be restarted in a few days, the company said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
