<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Are Killed In 2 Car Thefts In Newark</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="569816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERRY, BETTY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, QSAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDF1E31F931A25752C1A964958260" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Are Killed In 2 Car Thefts In Newark</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH F. SULLIVAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Nov. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This city's nightly ritual of joy riding by teen-age car thieves left four people dead this morning.</p>
        <p>In one collision, a woman was killed when a stolen car that was being followed by the police rammed the car in which she was a passenger. The second accident involved the fiery crash of a stolen car carrying six teen-agers; it went out of control while traveling at speeds up to 95 miles an hour, killing the driver and two passengers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This city's nightly ritual of joy riding by teen-age car thieves left four people dead this morning.</p>
        <p>In one collision, a woman was killed when a stolen car that was being followed by the police rammed the car in which she was a passenger. The second accident involved the fiery crash of a stolen car carrying six teen-agers; it went out of control while traveling at speeds up to 95 miles an hour, killing the driver and two passengers.</p>
        <p>The toll was the highest of any night this year during an epidemic of car theft, which the authorities had thought they were beginning to curb because of publicity about harsh new punishments.</p>
        <p>Throughout the spring and summer, teen-agers were stealing an average of 40 cars a night in what has become a rite of passage, spinning them in tight circles called "doughnuts," racing through the streets and trying to disable police cars. Accidents and confrontations between officers and the thieves have resulted in death and injury, sometimes to bystanders. 'We've Been Trying to Tell Him'</p>
        <p>"Apparently, the youngsters have not heard the hue and cry coming from the community, telling them to stop stealing autos and engaging in high-speed chases," said Glenn Grant, the city's Business Administrator. "We'll have to redouble our efforts."</p>
        <p>As friends gathered this afternoon to mourn Qsan Williams, the driver of the car that went up in flames, one said: "We've been trying to tell him for seven years, but he'd go out all the time, stealing cars." And other teen-agers in the group said the deaths today would not stop them from stealing, either.</p>
        <p>One of the harsher new punishments enacted this year is a 10-year prison sentence for causing the death of another while trying to elude the police. James F. Mulvihill, the Acting Essex County Prosecutor, said the 16-year-old driver of the car that fatally injured Betty Perry, 38 years old, of 24 17th Avenue, would probably be charged under that law.</p>
        <p>The police say that the first accident involved a gray Honda Accord that was stolen Tuesday from the street in the city's Ironbound section. About 12:30 A.M. today the driver tried to ram a police car near the Hillside border, and then sped off. Officer Avoids Being Rammed</p>
        <p>Two hours later Police Captain Alan Marion saw the Honda speeding with another blue car, also believed to have been stolen. Captain Marion said the Honda suddenly headed in his direction and he avoided being rammed by throwing his police cruiser into reverse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulvihill said Captain Marion called for reinforcements and did not try to arrest the driver of the Honda, who he said obeyed all traffic lights and stop signs.</p>
        <p>At Bergen Street and Hawthorne Avenue, the Honda sped into the intersection as the light was turning red and rammed the Oldsmobile in which Ms. Perry was riding, flipping the car over on its side. Mr. Mulvihill said Ms. Perry suffered "massive internal injuries" and died nine hours later at University Hospital. The driver of the car she was in, Mamie Branch, 41, of 83 Treacy Avenue, was treated at Beth Israel Hospital for cuts and a bruised shoulder and held for observation. Tom Casey, a hospital spokesman, said she was in satisfactory condition but had no memory of the accident or of being pulled from the wreckage.</p>
        <p>All five youths in the car were arrested and charged with receiving stolen property, eluding police and attempted assault on the two officers.</p>
        <p>The most seriously injured teen-ager was Colon Sowell, 18, of Fairview Avenue, who suffered a broken pelvis and shoulder. He was a passenger, as were Malik Yarrell, 18, of West Kinney Street, a 15-year-old and a 17-year-old. The driver was 16; his name was withheld because of his age. A grand jury will be asked to investigate the accident, Mr. Mulvihill said.</p>
        <p>In the second accident a 1992 Acura Legend was found in flames shortly after 5 A.M. near 14th Avenue and South 12th Street.</p>
        <p>The car, which had been reported stolen from Jersey City on Tuesday, had been seen traveling at speeds approaching 100 miles per hour along 12th Street, with six teen-agers inside, said Police Chief Thomas O'Reilly.</p>
        <p>"The car apparently hit a pothole or an object in the street and became airborne," Chief O'Reilly said. "It then hit a traffic light at the corner, sending it over a 10-foot fence, and tore a seven-foot section out of a wooden utility pole before landing farther down the street."</p>
        <p>Residents who heard the crash pulled three passengers from the car before it burst into flames, with three still inside. Identification of the victims will be made through dental records by the state Medical Examiner, Mr. Mulvihill said.</p>
        <p>Two of the victims were 14 years old. The third, identified as Qsan Williams, 18, of 420 South Seventh Street, was the driver, the police said.</p>
        <p>One of those pulled from the car was identified as Timothy Johnson, 18, of 425 15th Avenue. He had compound fractures of both legs and a broken ankle and was listed in satisfactory condition at University Hospital. The other survivors, ages 14 and 17, had only minor cuts and bruises.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
