<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Museum for Self-Taught Artists</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN VISIONARY ART MUSEUM (BALTIMORE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOFFBERGER, REBECCA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DE1039F936A15752C1A963958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Museum for Self-Taught Artists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first clue that something has changed along the southern edge of the Inner Harbor in Baltimore is the huge, colorful contraption of spinning ice-cream scoops, milkshake canisters, air-filter cups and who knows what else,  twirling in the wind just east of Federal Hill.</p>
        <p>But with its whimsical parts dancing every which way and back again, the "Whirligig" created by Vollis Simpson, a 76-year-old mechanic from North Carolina, is more than a fresh landmark. It is also an invitation to the equally joyous works on exhibit just beyond, in the American Visionary Art Museum, a museum that opens to the public on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first clue that something has changed along the southern edge of the Inner Harbor in Baltimore is the huge, colorful contraption of spinning ice-cream scoops, milkshake canisters, air-filter cups and who knows what else,  twirling in the wind just east of Federal Hill.</p>
        <p>But with its whimsical parts dancing every which way and back again, the "Whirligig" created by Vollis Simpson, a 76-year-old mechanic from North Carolina, is more than a fresh landmark. It is also an invitation to the equally joyous works on exhibit just beyond, in the American Visionary Art Museum, a museum that opens to the public on Friday.</p>
        <p>Unlike other forms of expression, visionary art -- often called outsider art -- knows no boundary, genre or style, only the defining rule of art by artists who are entirely self-taught. It differs from folk art in that folk artists generally follow well-known and long-practiced norms, with less of the spontaneity or whimsy that seems so apparent among the unschooled.</p>
        <p>While these eccentric creators have won notice for decades, mostly in European settings like the Musee de l'Art Brut in Lausanne, Switzerland, founded by the French artist Jean Dubuffet, American audiences have been slower to appreciate the same kind of work.</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, scattered exhibitions began appearing around the country, but  now the muses that drive Mr. Simpson and other experts in tinkering, carving and thatching have a three-story home of their own, with initial plans by museum officials to change exhibits every six months, each new presentation in keeping with some overarching theme.</p>
        <p>The opening exhibition, "The Tree of Life," features nearly 400 works, most expressed through materials of trees, including wood, roots, leaves, twigs, branches and nuts and their byproducts. A model of the luxury liner Lusitania, by Wayne Kusy, a Chicago artist, is made of 192,000 toothpicks.</p>
        <p>"This is art that is very spontaneous," said Roger Manley, a visionary-art expert and author from North Carolina chosen to be curator of the opening show.  "Often, the people who make it are even mysteries to their own families. In art, these people are out there on the edge of the bell curve."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the opening show features many artists once known to their friends and relatives for activities wholly apart from artistic endeavor. There are works by Herbert Singleton, whose violent exploits in New Orleans made the state prison in Angola, La., his home address for more than a decade, and Michael Dennis, a Harvard-trained neurobiologist in California, who abandoned his medical research to sculpture giant logs on an island off British Columbia, where he now lives.</p>
        <p>Their works, like others in the museum, reflect an intense spiritual presence, much of it projected through storytelling. Mr. Singleton captures the  searing pain blacks once experienced in the Deep South with a carved wooden door that shows cotton picking and Ku Klux Klan lynchings. It is called "The Way We Was." Another is a carved scene of the funeral of someone he obviously held in low regard. Its title is "Glad You Dead, You Rascal, You."</p>
        <p>Dr. Dennis's work, shown in the museum's adjacent building, a former whisky warehouse now called the Tall Sculpture Barn, includes "The Ancestors," a collection, or perhaps a family, of 10 outsize tree trunks, charred and sculptured into vaguely human form. It's only your imagination that they whisper secrets to one another and move about when no one is looking.</p>
        <p>The founder of the museum, Rebecca Hoffberger, 43, is a Baltimorean who has spent the past decade planning and raising money to build it. The land, the main building (a former paint company) and the sculpture barn were donated by the city. Private donations of $7 million covered design costs, construction and interior renovations that are still under way.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more than anything else, the American Visionary Art Museum stakes out its fanciful place in the cultural landscape less for celebrating unusual creations than for their unusual creators, artists of disparate backgrounds who  have wandered down their own paths of spirit and interpretation.</p>
        <p>"For the most part," Mrs. Hoffberger said, "these people don't think of themselves as artists. They are just people absorbed in what they're doing, which is often spiritual, between just them and God. It may not be practical, but to them, it's deeply fulfilling. They are not driven by the need to please someone else, only themselves."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
