<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate G.O.P. Seeks Tax Cuts In Stalled Talks On State Budget</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="843947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAO, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6D71139F936A25757C0A960958260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate G.O.P. Seeks Tax Cuts In Stalled Talks On State Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAO, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the surest sign yet that slow-moving talks over the New York State budget  are finally turning serious, the Republican leadership of the State Senate plans to unveil an ambitious proposal this week to cut an array of business taxes by $75 million this year and much more in future years.</p>
        <p>Though the Republicans say the plan would take a relatively small bite out of the $63 billion 1996-97 state budget now under negotiation, it would have a significant effect on future spending plans because it would grow in value to almost $1 billion by fiscal year 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the surest sign yet that slow-moving talks over the New York State budget  are finally turning serious, the Republican leadership of the State Senate plans to unveil an ambitious proposal this week to cut an array of business taxes by $75 million this year and much more in future years.</p>
        <p>Though the Republicans say the plan would take a relatively small bite out of the $63 billion 1996-97 state budget now under negotiation, it would have a significant effect on future spending plans because it would grow in value to almost $1 billion by fiscal year 2000.</p>
        <p>Critics say it is irresponsible for the Senate Republicans to propose new tax cuts in a year in which the Governor and legislative leaders are already considering deep spending cuts in education, health care and welfare programs to close a projected $4 billion budget shortfall.</p>
        <p>But Senate leaders said they believed that enough money was available to soften some spending cuts in Gov. George E. Pataki's proposed budget while also  cutting new taxes. They also asserted that additional tax cuts would promote job growth and lead to higher tax revenues in the long run.</p>
        <p>The Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, a Rensselaer County Republican,  said in an interview that cuts in personal and corporate taxes over the last two years had spurred the state's economy. "If you are doing something right, why not continue it?" he said.</p>
        <p>But the Senate proposal is also a political manifesto for this fall's campaigns, in which all 211 seats in the Legislature will be up for election. The Senate Republicans have traditionally run on a tax-cutting platform, and having Mr. Bruno bring a tax-reduction package to the budget table would allow Republican candidates to say they had pushed for tax cuts this year, whether they win them or not.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has said in the past that he supports aspects of the Senate plan,  but he has also raised questions about whether this is the right year to do it,  given the state's fiscal problems. "We'll look at it," his spokeswoman, Zenia Mucha, said of Mr. Bruno's plan.</p>
        <p>Major elements of the Senate plan are likely to face significant opposition in the Democratic-controlled Assembly, where many members wanted to delay a personal income tax cut that took effect on April 1 as a way to avoid spending reductions. Those Democrats are sure to oppose several of the Senate's new tax cuts, particularly one intended to help the real-estate industry.</p>
        <p>Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, did not return telephone calls seeking reaction to the Senate proposal.</p>
        <p>The budget for the 1996-97 fiscal year that began on April 1 is now two weeks late, making this the 12th consecutive year that the Legislature has failed to enact a spending plan on time. Until now, the budget talks have been proceeding  at an unusually slow pace while legislative leaders have waited for Congress to  pass a Federal budget.</p>
        <p>But the state is operating on a 30-day spending plan that runs out on April 30. For that reason, the Legislature is under pressure to enact a budget in the  coming weeks to avoid disruptions in state payments to public employees, community groups, local governments and school districts.</p>
        <p>The Senate proposal calls for cutting or eliminating about a dozen business taxes over the coming four years. The plan also would restore some of Mr. Pataki's proposed cuts in education and health care programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno said his top priority would be to eliminate in the coming year a 10 percent gains tax on real estate transfers worth more than $1 million -- derisively named by Republicans the "Cuomo tax" for the former Governor who signed it into law in 1983. New York is the only state to have such a gains tax, which last year generated $106 million for the state.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno said that the tax had stifled the real estate market, prevented renovations on aging buildings and discouraged out-of-state financiers from investing in the city. Citing a study prepared for the Real Estate Board of New  York and the Rent Stabilization Association of New York, the city's two major landlords, organizations, Mr. Bruno said elimination of the tax would trigger $7.7 billion in real estate transfers and create 6,900 new jobs, mostly for renovation work.</p>
        <p>The study contends that the spurt in real-estate sales would provide $215 million to the city and $62 million to the state in revenue from other taxes on  property transfers. Mr. Bruno suggested that that windfall could be calculated as part of the state's overall aid package to the Giuliani administration this year.</p>
        <p>First Deputy Mayor Peter J. Powers said that Giuliani administration officials would probably support repeal of the tax because they believed it deterred real estate transfers. Rescinding the tax, he said, "may create more money than it taxes away."</p>
        <p>The real estate industry has been a major campaign contributor in the last year, particularly to Republicans. In 1995, the Real Estate Board, the Rent Stabilization Association and the Realtors Political Action Committee gave a total of $8,000 to Mr. Bruno, $106,000 to the Republican Senate Campaign Committee, $62,500 to the State Republican Committee and $6,750 to Mr. Pataki. In the same period, the three groups gave $2,400 to Mr. Silver and $13,600 to the Democratic Assembly Campaign Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno denied that campaign contributions played a role in his decision to push for eliminating the real estate gains tax. "We receive money from every walk of life," he said. "Does that mean that you can't legislate because you'll  be in conflict?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Bruno's plan will also call for the gradual elimination of the gross receipts tax on energy and telecommunications companies, which is passed through to customers in utility bills. Democrats and Republicans agree that lower-income people pay a disproportionately high percentage of the tax.</p>
        <p>And the plan will call for reducing estate taxes and taxes paid by farmers and beer and soda bottlers and on diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>Critics said eliminating the real estate gains tax would benefit only the wealthy and do little to fuel economic growth. "This is a very specific tax cut aimed at a few people," said Robert Lynch, an associate professor of economics at the State University of New York at Cortland, who has studied state tax issues. "Why it would promote economic activity is beyond me."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
