<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Troops Wrap Up Evacuation Operation in Liberia</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="843941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LIBERIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MONROVIA (LIBERIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Liberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Liberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D71139F936A25757C0A960958260" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Troops Wrap Up Evacuation Operation in Liberia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>MONROVIA, Liberia, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After six days of hectic operations, an American evacuation effort from this  embattled and badly looted city to neighboring countries wound down today with a final trickle of traumatized foreigners being flown out of Liberia.</p>
        <p>After racing through the previous two evenings to complete an operation that  involved round-the-clock,two-way radio monitoring to pinpoint stranded Americans and daring rescue missions by diplomatic security people, a few families of Lebanese and Indian immigrants went aboard large GH-53 helicopters for a 90-minute flight to Freetown, Sierra Leone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After six days of hectic operations, an American evacuation effort from this  embattled and badly looted city to neighboring countries wound down today with a final trickle of traumatized foreigners being flown out of Liberia.</p>
        <p>After racing through the previous two evenings to complete an operation that  involved round-the-clock,two-way radio monitoring to pinpoint stranded Americans and daring rescue missions by diplomatic security people, a few families of Lebanese and Indian immigrants went aboard large GH-53 helicopters for a 90-minute flight to Freetown, Sierra Leone.</p>
        <p>Many of the last refugees to make their way out of the country were so badly shaken that they wept uncontrollably as they made their way to the American Embassy's seaside landing pad.</p>
        <p>"If you could see the dead bodies we passed on the streets on our way here,"  said Comfort Sannoh, a Sierra Leone mother who flew out with her three small children, all of them American citizens. "They are all over the place."</p>
        <p>Officials at the embassy said there were known to be about 30 more Americans  in various points around Monrovia, and final efforts to locate them were being made today. Officials allowed for the possibility that more citizens of other countries might show up at the embassy later, but said the large-scale evacuation had ended.</p>
        <p>As the operation closed down, attention here turned to Liberia's political and relief emergencies, each of which looms as large as it did at the start of the country's latest crisis, with the ferocious renewal last weekend of a seven-year-old civil war.</p>
        <p>The streets of the city were quieter today than they had been since the outbreak of the fighting. With less gunfire and looting by fighters, large numbers of people wandered as far from their homes as they felt safe in an increasingly desperate search for food and water in a country where virtually no store remains intact.</p>
        <p>After talks with leaders of several of Liberia's warring militias, a high-level Ghanaian delegation that left here today spoke with renewed confidence about the chances of a cease-fire that was declared on Friday but was quickly and repeatedly broken.</p>
        <p>"I think obtaining from Taylor and Kromah an agreement to halt their assault  on the Barclay Training Center opens up a lot of options," said Mohammed Ibn Chambas, Ghana's Deputy Foreign Minister.</p>
        <p>The reference was to two of the conflict's most powerful warlords, Charles Taylor and Al Haji G. V. Kromah, who have traditionally been bitter rivals, but  who in the recent violence have joined forces to wage urban warfare against D. Roosevelt Johnson, a self-styled general who has emerged as the leader of a militia composed of fighters from his Krahn ethnic group.</p>
        <p>There were also reports that Mr. Johnson had agreed to a truce. But with all  of the country's radio stations and newspapers knocked out of service and with Mr. Johnson still lying low, this could not be confirmed.</p>
        <p>All three men are members of a now-fractured Government that emerged in October from peace talks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chambas said a West African peacekeeping force -- which has been deployed in Liberia for the last five years, but has been completely ineffectual in the latest round of fighting -- would gradually begin taking up positions around the city and "clearing out central Monrovia of various factional fighters."</p>
        <p>Other diplomats, however, said they remained extremely wary of Mr. Taylor, who has expressed a determination to capture at all costs the Barclay Training Center, the sprawling former barracks of the national army in the central city. There Mr. Johnson's fighters are holed up with thousands of other Liberians and several Lebanese and West Africans being held hostage.</p>
        <p>"Taylor talks reasonably on this subject at the outset, saying he wants a society of laws and not of men," a diplomat said. "But after a while, his talk about Johnson degenerates into talk about the Krahn -- these people this, and these people that."</p>
        <p>With the Krahn fighters backed into a corner, perhaps awaiting reinforcement  that could arrive from the group's homeland in southeastern Liberia, diplomats said the conflict had again begun to resemble the vicious ethnic polarization and violence that swept Liberia at the start of the war.</p>
        <p>Liberia's civil war began in 1989, when Mr. Taylor invaded from the neighboring Ivory Coast with a small force drawn from border-region tribes that  had been severely persecuted by the dictator Samuel K. Doe.</p>
        <p>The early part of the war involved vicious attacks and reprisals between Mr.  Doe's ethnic group, the Krahn, and members of northeastern tribes recruited by Mr. Taylor. Mr. Doe was captured and tortured to death in 1990 by another rebel  leader, and Liberia's war has become a steadily more fragmented conflict ever since.</p>
        <p>If Liberia's latest reported halt to the fighting does not hold, and Mr. Taylor's forces mount a full assault on the Barclay Training Center, as they have threatened, the United States would quickly be confronted with an awkward predicament, officials here acknowledged.</p>
        <p>A heavily armed, ship-borne United States Marine contingent, complete with landing craft and attack helicopters, is due here late in the week, and will replace about 1,000 troops from the Army Special Forces who have been protecting the American Embassy and running the evacuation.</p>
        <p>If the Taylor forces attacked the Barclay Center after the new contingent of  marines arrived, Washington would have to decide quickly whether to stand back and watch a fierce battle that could quickly kill thousands of innocent hostages, or to use its newly deployed strength to stop the assault.</p>
        <p>Even if Washington opted for inaction, diplomats here say, the risk is great  that Krahn fighters, fanning out of their doomed downtown base, would head toward the American Embassy, thus bringing the war to the doorstep of the country's last remaining safe haven.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, with a World Food Program vessel sailing from Freetown to Monrovia with emergency food supplies and with groups like Doctors Without Borders requesting help in returning to Liberia to mount a relief effort, pressure is already building on Washington to extend its involvement here beyond a simple evacuation exercise.</p>
        <p>"I am eternal optimist," said the Roman Catholic Archbishop of Monrovia, Michael Kpakala Francis, a prominent figure in the settlements of all of Liberia's recent crises, who was one of the last people to fly out of the country today. "But if nothing is done here in the next few weeks, there will be mass starvation in Liberia."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
