<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Pain, No Gain For Marbury And Knicks</title>
    <meta content="14knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/14/sports/basketball/14knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746774"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Nuggets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Howard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Denver Nuggets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Coney Island (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Marbury, Stephon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Larry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEED81031F937A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Pain, No Gain For Marbury And Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">More Pain, No Gain for Marbury and Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Denver Nuggets defeat New York Knicks, 108-96; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephon Marbury and Larry Brown have coexisted for six months and 45 losses, but with only weeks left in the Knicks' season, they still appear to be operating in different universes. They talk around and past each other, pursuing different visions on the court and offering divergent views of what went wrong off it.</p>
        <p>Their uneasy partnership took another bad turn over the weekend when Marbury declared he would play his own way next season and Brown responding with measured bemusement. As the tension sparked again yesterday, the Knicks were routed by the Denver Nuggets, 108-96, at Madison Square Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stephon Marbury and Larry Brown's uneasy partnership took another bad turn over the weekend, and the Knicks were routed Monday by the Nuggets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stephon Marbury and Larry Brown have coexisted for six months and 45 losses, but with only weeks left in the Knicks' season, they still appear to be operating in different universes. They talk around and past each other, pursuing different visions on the court and offering divergent views of what went wrong off it.</p>
        <p>Their uneasy partnership took another bad turn over the weekend when Marbury declared he would play his own way next season and Brown responding with measured bemusement. As the tension sparked again yesterday, the Knicks were routed by the Denver Nuggets, 108-96, at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to go back to playing the way how I normally play,'' Marbury said yesterday morning, reiterating comments he made in The Star-Ledger of Newark on Sunday. ''It isn't about control. It's about going out and playing the style that I play. I mean, I think Coach knew my style of play before I got here. So I felt like my game and the way how he wanted me to play should be intertwined together. It shouldn't just be one way.''</p>
        <p>The sentiments were not new. Marbury has chafed, often publicly, all season about trying to play Brown's way. Accustomed to being a scorer first and a passer second, Marbury has unhappily attempted to invert those roles, as per Brown's preferences. He is on pace for a career low in assists (6.6 a game) and his lowest scoring average (17.2 points) since 1999. And the Knicks are on pace for their worst season in franchise history.</p>
        <p>''I went into this year trying to do something, to put myself in a situation where we can win, O.K.? To help the team win games,'' Marbury told The Star-Ledger. ''Unfortunately, that didn't happen. So, what do I do now, as far as the way I play? I go back to playing like Stephon Marbury, a k a Starbury. I haven't been Starbury this year. I've been some other dude this year.''</p>
        <p>After Saturday's loss at Charlotte, Marbury made a point of how much freedom Raymond Felton, the Bobcats' rookie guard, is afforded by Coach Bernie Bickerstaff. Referring to that comment, Marbury said yesterday: ''No, I don't have that type of freedom. Yeah, it's a problem.''</p>
        <p>Brown, who coached the freewheeling Allen Iverson for six years, responded: ''I've never given a guard more freedom than Stephon Marbury in my life. And he has the ball all the time.''</p>
        <p>Generally, however, Brown tried to deflect the issue. While Marbury, who scored 25 points and had 7 assists last night, clearly was making a plea for more control of the offense, Brown tried to recast the issue. He noted that Marbury has been playing with a sprained left shoulder, ''so I would assume that's what he means.''</p>
        <p>''If you're the best player on a team that's struggling and you say you're not playing like you're capable of playing, I think he's probably saying, 'I've got to step up.' So let's hope he steps up,'' Brown said.</p>
        <p>It is possible that Marbury will get the freedom he wants, but somewhere else. The Knicks, having acquired Steve Francis last month, are expected to aggressively shop Marbury this summer. With three years and $60.3 million left on his contract, however, Marbury is possibly untradeable. Waiving him would be both financially and politically unpalatable, given how much the Knicks -- particularly the team president, Isiah Thomas -- have invested in Marbury as the face of the team. But Brown is under contract for four more years, and the Knicks will consider all options.</p>
        <p>Asked if he and Marbury are compatible, Brown offered a tepid: ''We'll see. The way I interpret it is, he's going to step up.''</p>
        <p>Marbury, a Coney Island native who has said he wants to finish his career here, gave a more optimistic view.</p>
        <p>''For sure, I can definitely work with Coach,'' Marbury said. ''I don't got no problem with him. I'm just saying, he just has to understand how I feel and I understand how he feels. I'm willing to bend. I proved that at the beginning of the year. I came in completely vulnerable. I said basically do whatever you want me to do and I'm going to do it. But by us losing, I can't deal with that.''</p>
        <p>For a time, Marbury and Brown found harmony. The Knicks opened January with six straight victories, with Marbury averaging 23.3 points and 9.3 assists a game during the streak. Brown showered him with praise, saying, ''He's playing like a point guard.''</p>
        <p>But Marbury injured his left shoulder a short time later, ''and when I came back things weren't the same,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Marbury said he was allowed to call most of the plays during that January run. Lately, Brown has taken more control of the offense. After a recent loss to Chicago, Brown complained that the team failed to run four plays down the stretch.</p>
        <p>''If we was winning and I was playing the way I was playing, I would be as happy as anybody in this world,'' Marbury said. ''But we're not winning.''</p>
        <p>The Brown-Marbury rift has undermined the Knicks all season, but it might not even rank in the top five of the team's greatest problems.</p>
        <p>''We're losing games because we're not guarding, we're not sharing the ball, we're not taking care of the ball and we're putting people on the free-throw line,'' Brown said. ''And I didn't have that problem in Philly, I didn't have that problem in Detroit, I didn't have that problem in Indiana, I didn't have that problem in San Antonio, I didn't have that problem with the L.A. Clippers, I didn't have that problem with the New Jersey Nets.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Eddy Curry missed the game because of a stomach virus. Jerome James started in his place, forming the Knicks' league-high 36th different starting lineup. James scored 11 of the Knicks' first 14 points, all within the first four minutes. He had 8 points in his last eight games combined and had not scored more than 9 points in any game this season.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
