<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Harder Line On Driving While Drunk</title>
    <meta content="14drunk" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/14/nyregion/14drunk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Kathleen (Dist Atty)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver-Greenberg, Jessica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plea Bargaining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Rice, Kathleen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E0D91031F937A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Harder Line On Driving While Drunk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Harder Line on Driving While Drunk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JESSICA SILVER-GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Silver-Greenberg, Jessica</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, N.Y., March 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dist Atty Kathleen Rice pledges to crack down on drunk drivers in Nassau County by seeking tougher penalties against many first-time offenders; says those arrested with blood alcohol of 0.13 percent or higher will no longer be allowed to negotiate plea bargains; pledges to recommend jail time for any driver who is arrested for dunken driving twice in five years; will push for passage of bill that would require repeat offenders to serve at least five days in jail (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In her first policy initiative since taking office in January, the Nassau County district attorney, Kathleen Rice, pledged on Monday to crack down on a ''drunk driving epidemic'' by seeking tougher penalties against many first-time offenders.</p>
        <p>Those arrested with blood-alcohol levels of 0.13 percent or higher will no longer be allowed to negotiate plea bargains, she said, and will face a misdemeanor charge of driving while intoxicated. Under former District Attorney Denis Dillon, who lost to Ms. Rice in November, drivers with blood-alcohol levels of up to 0.15 percent could strike a plea bargain and plead guilty to driving while impaired. Ms. Rice said that was the equivalent of a speeding ticket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>MINEOLA, N.Y., March 13  In her first policy initiative since taking office in January, the Nassau County district attorney, Kathleen Rice, pledged on Monday to crack down on a</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In her first policy initiative since taking office in January, the Nassau County district attorney, Kathleen Rice, pledged on Monday to crack down on a ''drunk driving epidemic'' by seeking tougher penalties against many first-time offenders.</p>
        <p>Those arrested with blood-alcohol levels of 0.13 percent or higher will no longer be allowed to negotiate plea bargains, she said, and will face a misdemeanor charge of driving while intoxicated. Under former District Attorney Denis Dillon, who lost to Ms. Rice in November, drivers with blood-alcohol levels of up to 0.15 percent could strike a plea bargain and plead guilty to driving while impaired. Ms. Rice said that was the equivalent of a speeding ticket.</p>
        <p>She said that had her policy had been in place in 2005, about 900 more drivers would have faced charges of driving while intoxicated. Mr. Dillon could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>''Today is Day 1 in our assault on drunk driving in Nassau County,'' said Ms. Rice, who was flanked by other Nassau County law enforcement officials. ''It will be a long and hard process, certain to create opposition from the other side of the courtroom, but this step, and the steps that will follow, must be taken before more innocent lives are lost.''</p>
        <p>In 2005, 23 people were killed by drunken drivers in Nassau County and there were 4,100 drunken-driving arrests. Under New York State law, drivers with a 0.07 percent blood-alcohol level or higher are considered impaired.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice said the new policy was aimed at reducing the rate of recidivism by escalating the penalties for repeat offenders. Of the 1,300 drunken driving cases pending in Nassau County District Court, more than 300 are cases of repeat offenders.</p>
        <p>''There was a trickle-down effect where you could get caught with a 0.15 B.A.C. level six times in a row, and since you were always right below the threshold, you could take a plea bargain and leave,'' said Eric Phillips, the director of communications for the district attorney's office, referring to blood-alcohol content.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rice also pledged on Monday to recommend jail time for any driver who is arrested for drunken driving twice in five years. She also said she would push for passage of a bill introduced by State Senator Charles J. Fuschillo Jr., a Republican who represents Nassau County, that would require that repeat offenders serve at least five days in jail. The proposal would also allow judges to issue consecutive sentences to drunken drivers who were also convicted of more than one count of manslaughter.</p>
        <p>An assistant district attorney, Maureen McCormick, who previously worked as a prosecutor in Brooklyn, told of a second-degree manslaughter case she prosecuted two years ago in which an off-duty police officer, Joseph Gray, killed four people while driving drunk and received 5 to 15 years in prison, the maximum. She said she felt Mr. Gray should have received consecutive sentences.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
