<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Equitable Real Estate Unit Is Vulnerable but Confident</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="398531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PENSIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MORTGAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">EQUITABLE REAL ESTATE INVESTMENT MANAGEMENT INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HYLTON, RICHARD D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1F38F935A35752C1A966958260" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Equitable Real Estate Unit Is Vulnerable but Confident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD D. HYLTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HYLTON, RICHARD D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cracks are starting to appear in the portfolio of the nation's largest investor of real estate assets for pension funds. Equitable Real Estate Investment Management Inc., a unit of the Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States, is grappling with rising withdrawals of pension money from its managed funds and, like others in the industry, faces growing delinquency rates in its mortgage portfolio.</p>
        <p>At a time when mortgage delinquencies are expected to begin rising sharply, Equitable Life has about $12.1 billion invested in commercial real estate mortgages for its own account, a major portion of its $44.9 billion in assets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cracks are starting to appear in the portfolio of the nation's largest investor of real estate assets for pension funds. Equitable Real Estate Investment Management Inc., a unit of the Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States, is grappling with rising withdrawals of pension money from its managed funds and, like others in the industry, faces growing delinquency rates in its mortgage portfolio.</p>
        <p>At a time when mortgage delinquencies are expected to begin rising sharply, Equitable Life has about $12.1 billion invested in commercial real estate mortgages for its own account, a major portion of its $44.9 billion in assets.</p>
        <p>On top of that, Equitable Life is already struggling with the debacle of the high-interest investment securities it sold throughout the 1980's. The fall in interest rates has hurt the insurance giant's ability to make enough money to cover those commitments and it will probably lose more than $1 billion as it continues to make those payments. In addition, potential losses on the company's $3.9 billion portfolio of "junk bonds" could add to its troubles.</p>
        <p>Even so, none of Equitable Life's problems are likely to affect its ability to meet insurance policy claims. Equitable Life is one of the nation's remaining mutual insurance companies. It is owned by its policyholders rather than public shareholders.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Equitable Real Estate raised eyebrows when it put a partnership in which it was the general partner into bankruptcy. That prompted speculation in the industry that the move signified the beginning of an aggressive housecleaning.</p>
        <p>According to the real estate unit's top management, the bankruptcy of this partnership was an isolated incident. "That is the only tax-oriented, high-leverage partnership transaction of its kind in our portfolio," said George R. Puskar, chairman of Equitable Real Estate, referring to changes in the tax law in 1986 that made real estate partnerships less attractive. "After that investment was made, many of the senior people made a conscious decision that we would not pursue that kind of business and so it was a stand-alone situation."</p>
        <p>The company says neither the recent sales or planned sales of some of its properties nor the bankruptcy filing should be construed as a sign that it is tightening oversight, but that its portfolio review process is functioning as usual.</p>
        <p>"The current market conditions are no surprise to us," Mr. Puskar said. "We started sending the caution signals in 1986, and we have been culling out problems in our equity portfolio for some time now."</p>
        <p>Many industry experts say that in all likelihood Equitable Real Estate will weather the industry turbulence.</p>
        <p>With more than $35 billion in assets under management, Equitable Real Estate, which is based in Atlanta, is the leading manager of pension fund money invested in real estate and is one of the biggest sources of financing for the nation's developers.</p>
        <p>$24 Billion in Investments</p>
        <p>The company's nearly 550 professionals manage a portfolio of $24 billion in equity real estate investments and more than $11 billion in mortgages. It has equity interests in about 800 properties, including about 51 million square feet of industrial space, 76 million square feet of office space, 63 million square feet of retail space and nearly 20,000 hotel rooms.</p>
        <p>Although its insurance parent has been struggling to cut costs and improve its profit, the real estate unit, which generated a modest 8 percent increase in pretax profits in 1989, has been spared along with the other investment subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>"Our business is growing," Mr. Puskar said. "We have not had to cut on the people side of the equation, but we have made cuts on the overhead and expense side."</p>
        <p>Still, like every other major investor in the country's faltering real estate market, the Equitable unit is vulnerable. Only weeks ago, John Portman, a large developer, was forced to give up control of Peachtree Center, a huge office and retail complex in Atlanta, after he failed to make payments on a $333 million Equitable mortgage.</p>
        <p>The company's main investment fund, the $3.8 billion Prime Property Fund, has already refunded $140 million to investors this year and 33 investors recently asked to redeem an additional $330 million.</p>
        <p>Prime, which invests in regional shopping malls, industrial projects and office space, does not have enough cash on hand to meet those requests, and company executives estimate that it will take about 12 months before it can meet them.</p>
        <p>Equitable Real Estate executives say the company's delinquency rate on commercial mortgages has remained stable at about 1 percent for the last few years and they do not expect it to rise sharply.</p>
        <p>A Growing Problem</p>
        <p>But delinquencies among commercial mortgages, the underwriting standards on many of which deteriorated during the building boom of the mid-1980's, are expected to pose a growing problem for insurance companies over the next three or four years. Falling real estate values and rental incomes can make it impossible for developers to make their debt payments. And if the market value of these properties falls below the value of the underlying mortgage, developers may be tempted to simply hand over the deeds to the mortgage holders instead of making payments, as is allowed under their contracts.</p>
        <p>The problem could be exacerbated if interest rates rise. Billions of dollars of such mortgages will mature over the next several years, and if they are rolled over at a higher rate buildings will face an even tougher time meeting mortgage payments.</p>
        <p>Equitable Real Estate says it is cutting its ties with troublesome projects. "We are actively going over these loans and asking ourselves whether we want to roll them over," Mr. Puskar said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
