<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holdover From Solid South Tries to Defy G.O.P.'s Tide</title>
    <meta content="16FRIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Carolina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Ernest F. Hollings</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollings, Ernest (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Inglis, Bob (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D7103AF935A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="1749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holdover From Solid South Tries to Defy G.O.P.'s Tide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>GREENVILLE, S.C., Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ernest Hollings, silver-haired incumbent from South Carolina and only remaining Southern Democrat of his era in Senate, campaigns for re-election to sixth full term; 76-year-old Senator is only statewide-elected Democrat left in his state; old 'Solid South' has been transformed from Democratic stronghold into Republican fortress; there are only 7 Democrats in Senate from 11 states of old Confederacy, down from 16 in 1980; Hollings holds slight lead over Republican Repr Bob Inglis; photos; he points to his seniority, while Inglis crusades against pork-barrel politics and Hollings' tart tongue and reputation for aloofness; critics say Inglis is moralistic and works against state's interests; one voter likens him to fourth-grader who reminded teacher when she didn't collect homework (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is, quite simply, the last of his kind.</p>
        <p>Senator Ernest F. Hollings of South Carolina, his hair so white that it emits a translucent glow, is the only Southern Democrat of his era remaining in a chamber once distinguished by the breed. For 32 years, he has survived by knowing which backs to slap, which arms to twist and which chits to call in the service of winning highway funds and military appropriations for a desperately needy state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is, quite simply, the last of his kind.</p>
        <p>Senator Ernest F. Hollings of South Carolina, his hair so white that it emits a translucent glow, is the only Southern Democrat of his era remaining in a chamber once distinguished by the breed. For 32 years, he has survived by knowing which backs to slap, which arms to twist and which chits to call in the service of winning highway funds and military appropriations for a desperately needy state.</p>
        <p>For most of that period, South Carolinians were grateful for any morsels dropped from Washington's table. But South Carolina, like the rest of its region, has been transformed over the years, from a dependent economy into an assertive one, and from a Democratic stronghold into a Republican fortress.</p>
        <p>As the 76-year-old Mr. Hollings runs for re-election to a sixth full term, the question is whether the state he has served for 50 years -- as legislator, Lieutenant Governor, Governor and Senator -- will finally leave him behind. Other than the Comptroller General, Mr. Hollings is the only statewide-elected Democrat left in South Carolina.</p>
        <p>And thus this year's Senate campaign between Mr. Hollings and his Republican opponent, Representative Bob Inglis, serves as something of a referendum on whether any role remains in the state, and in the South, for a party that went all but unchallenged in the early days of Mr. Hollings's career.</p>
        <p>There are now 7 Democrats in the Senate from the 11 states of the old Confederacy, down from 16 in 1980.</p>
        <p>''So much rides on this race as far as the South is concerned,'' said Charles W. Dunn, a Clemson University political scientist. ''If the Democrats can't save this seat, what seat can they save and how can they recruit candidates? If Hollings loses, it's almost like Sherman has finished his march.''</p>
        <p>Polls show the race to be tight, with Mr. Hollings holding a slight lead of 49 percent to 42 percent in a Mason-Dixon survey taken two weeks ago. While political analysts generally commend Mr. Hollings's campaign strategy and work ethic, they note that the Senator failed to put his underfinanced opponent away in September, when he had the advertising airwaves to himself.</p>
        <p>They also said that the outcome could be influenced by a number of outside forces. In the race for governor, a surprisingly competitive effort by Jim Hodges, the Democratic challenger to Gov. David M. Beasley, seems to be exciting the Democratic base, a benefit to Mr. Hollings. But Mr. Inglis, a member of the Judiciary Committee who has demanded President Clinton's resignation, may be aided by strong sentiment in South Carolina about the White House sex scandal.</p>
        <p>The choice for South Carolinians could not be starker. While Mr. Hollings is best known for his commitment to deficit reduction, he remains an advocate of Federal activism in areas like education, housing and the arts. Mr. Inglis, on the other hand, typifies the South's new Republicanism and its anti-Government leanings.</p>
        <p>At 39, Mr. Inglis, a three-term Congressman, is barely half Mr. Hollings's age. He is a father of five who sleeps on an air mattress in his Congressional office. While Mr. Hollings hails from Charleston, the static old seaport of elegant homes and Democratic faith, Mr. Inglis represents the burgeoning Greenville-Spartanburg metropolitan area, which is infused with new foreign investment and fervent Christian conservatism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hollings speaks in a mumbled, sometimes unintelligible drawl, and his acerbic wit has produced a compendium of impolitic comments. The bookish, bespectacled Mr. Inglis, by contrast, reveals virtually no accent and lectures with the measured deliberateness of an economics professor.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Hollings campaigns on his ability to get things done, Mr. Inglis rejects the very premise of pork barrel politics and has shaped his campaign around the preachy theme of ''principle over politics.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Inglis has hindered his own campaign by refusing to accept contributions from political action committees, limiting his projected budget to about $2 million, a third less than Mr. Hollings has already spent. And in a state with more seniority in the Senate than any in history -- 74 years between Mr. Hollings and his 95-year-old colleague, Strom Thurmond -- Mr. Inglis argues that tenure counts for little in today's Republican Congress. He has vowed to serve only two terms, just as he promised to serve only three in the House.</p>
        <p>''If principle doesn't win in politics, then I'm not very interested in winning,'' he said in an interview. ''Before, we were the redheaded stepchild of the nation and we needed anything we could get to lift us out of this desperate poverty we were in. Now what South Carolinians are realizing is they that prefer free enterprise opportunity to a Government guarantee.''</p>
        <p>Where was the value of seniority, Mr. Inglis asked, when the Federal Government recently closed military bases in Charleston and Myrtle Beach and eliminated thousands of jobs at the Savannah River Site nuclear plant?</p>
        <p>''It's not an attack on the Senator's effectiveness,'' he said, noting that the Pentagon's base closure commission has usurped the seniority spoils system. ''It's not that he was asleep at the switch. It's that the world has changed, for the better.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hollings, the highest-ranking Democrat on the Commerce Committee and one of the most senior members on Appropriations, scoffs at this notion. The value of seniority, he said, can be seen in his ability to place other Federal agencies at the Charleston base after the Navy withdrew.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, Mr. Hollings said in a debate in Greer on Tuesday night that Mr. Inglis will be ''a lame duck by the time he gets up there with this silly term limits thing.''</p>
        <p>''He won't even get a good committee,'' the Senator said. ''He won't be a voice. He'll be hardly a whisper from South Carolina.''</p>
        <p>After listing a number of interstate highway projects that he helped secure for South Carolina, Mr. Hollings added: ''He continues to call it pork. This is Government. This is the way it works.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Inglis has crusaded against pork, a sustaining staple of South Carolina politics, with both his words and his votes. In the House, he opposed Federal financing for an interstate highway connector in his home district and for a badly needed bridge in Charleston. He did so, he said, because the money was being earmarked for politically influenced projects that bypassed the state's priority list. Instead, a toll road is being built to connect the Interstates in Greenville, prompting Mr. Hollings to refer to his opponent as ''Toll Road Bob.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Inglis's stands may seem noble to those who do not spend rush hours stalled on Interstate 385, said Marc T. Belk, a store manager in Greenville who confronted Mr. Inglis at a campaign stop here this week. ''This fellow here is going to Washington and voting against our interests,'' Mr. Belk said. ''He's like the guy in fourth grade who reminded the teacher when she didn't collect the homework.''</p>
        <p>If South Carolinians perceive Mr. Inglis as moralistic, he does not seem to mind. His strategy centers on making the campaign a referendum on Mr. Hollings, and if his style draws a contrast with that of the tart-tongued incumbent, all the better.</p>
        <p>Mr. Inglis regularly asserts that South Carolinians should expect more civility from their representatives. He travels the state in a red motor home emblazoned with the slogan: ''Finally, someone's listening!'' His aides at headquarters answer the telephone by saying, ''It's a great day at Inglis for Senate.'' At the debate in Greer, as at most appearances, Mr. Inglis said that South Carolinians should ''expect a senator to be civil to you, expect him to listen, expect him not to denigrate you, not to humiliate you.''</p>
        <p>Such comments are a reference to Mr. Hollings's reputation for aloofness and arrogance. To reinforce that point, the State Republican Party recently broadcast an advertisement that included footage of Mr. Hollings giving a speech on election night in 1992. Thinking that he had run his last race, and perhaps bruised by his narrow victory margin of three percentage points, Mr. Hollings blurted: ''I don't have to get elected to a blooming thing. And I don't have to do things that are politically correct. The hell with everybody.'' Then he added: ''I'm free at last.''</p>
        <p>Six years later, Mr. Hollings cannot seem to mask his indignation at being challenged by Mr. Inglis, whom he dismisses as a hypocrite. And in recent days, the Senator has played willingly into Mr. Inglis's strategy. In an interview on Wednesday with The Herald of Rock Hill, S.C., Mr. Hollings mocked Mr. Inglis as ''so oozing and goozing and such a nice little choirboy and so pleasant, and everybody's rude, and he wants to be courteous. He is a goddamn skunk. I can tell you that right now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Inglis responded: ''I guess he's right about me being a choirboy. That's not my style to use that kind of language.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hollings is capable of joking about his style, telling a big crowd at a Democratic fish fry in Fair Lawn on Monday night that he and his wife, Peatsy, get along so well because they are ''both in love with the same fella.'' But he also said in an interview that his arrogance pales compared to Mr. Inglis's.</p>
        <p>''Here's a fellow that rode in on the Christian right in the big wave we had in '92, done nothing for anybody and all of a sudden he's going to change and give us a new setup,'' Mr. Hollings said. ''Now if you talk about arrogance, egads. I can be a little arrogant, but he's big arrogant. He wins first prize on arrogance.''</p>
        <p>Defiantly unreconstructed to the end, Mr. Hollings said he was running one more time to stem the Republican tide. On Nov. 3, voters will decide whether his era will end on his own terms.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
