<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Absentee Balloting Threatened By Delays Over Stadium Vote</title>
    <meta content="16STAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: THE BALLOT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Absentee Voting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yankee Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6D7103AF935A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Absentee Balloting Threatened By Delays Over Stadium Vote</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of New York City voters could lose chance to vote in Nov 3 election because court battle over referendum on Yankee Stadium delays printing of absentee ballots (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of New York City voters could lose the chance to vote in the Nov. 3 election because the court battle over a referendum on Yankee Stadium has delayed the printing of absentee ballots, the president of the Board of Elections said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mail ballots are sometimes decisive in close elections, and because the city vote tends to be Democratic, reduced balloting could conceivably affect a tight statewide contest like the Senate race between Alfonse M. D'Amato and Charles E. Schumer, said the board president, Douglas A. Kellner, who is a Democrat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of New York City voters could lose the chance to vote in the Nov. 3 election because the court battle over a referendum on Yankee Stadium has delayed the printing of absentee ballots, the president of the Board of Elections said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mail ballots are sometimes decisive in close elections, and because the city vote tends to be Democratic, reduced balloting could conceivably affect a tight statewide contest like the Senate race between Alfonse M. D'Amato and Charles E. Schumer, said the board president, Douglas A. Kellner, who is a Democrat.</p>
        <p>The problem could also prompt lawsuits seeking to postpone the election, to extend the deadline for returning ballots or to challenge the election results. ''Anything is conceivable,'' said Mr. Kellner, who has joined a Federal suit seeking to force distribution of the absentee ballots.</p>
        <p>But Republicans on the Board of Elections -- which has five Democratic and five Republican members -- said the board could not approve a ballot until the referendum dispute was resolved. And they took issue with Mr. Kellner's assertions about how many voters could be affected by the problem.</p>
        <p>By law, the board was supposed to have mailed out the absentee ballots starting Oct. 1. So far about 36,000 voters have requested such ballots, Mr. Kellner said, and experience suggests the total will reach 70,000. Absentee ballots are given to people who are ill, disabled, out of town or in the military.</p>
        <p>But this year's ballots have not even been printed yet -- a process that normally takes six days -- pending the outcome of litigation on whether the ballot should include the Yankee Stadium referendum, which is sponsored by Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone,  or another referendum on campaign-financing rules backed by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>''We have never had anything of this nature ever happen before,'' said the elections board's spokeswoman, Naomi R. Bernstein.</p>
        <p>The dispute over the stadium referendum, which would ask voters whether tax money should be spent for a new home for the Yankees in Manhattan, was heard yesterday by the Appellate Division of State Supreme Court. The appellate panel did not issue an immediate ruling, and although the case is being expedited, whichever side loses this latest round is expected to take the issue to the Court of Appeals, which will take more time.</p>
        <p>The election is now just 18 days away. To be counted, mail ballots must completed and returned by hand no later than Election Day or by mail with a postmark by the midnight before Election Day.</p>
        <p>''Every day we get closer, the number losing their right to vote rises dramatically,'' said Darrell L. Paster, a lawyer for the Democrats. ''I have a couple getting married this week and going on a safari in Zimbabwe. I had a woman call today from Australia. I have a couple who are going to Hong Kong this evening, then to a cruise ship to Bali.</p>
        <p>''It's doubtful we'll get ballots to people in nuclear submarines and on aircraft carriers in the middle of the Indian Ocean.''</p>
        <p>The issue has split the elections board along strict party lines.</p>
        <p>The Democrats have accused the Republicans of deliberately holding back the ballots to keep the city vote low to help Senator D'Amato. But the Republicans vehemently deny it. ''That's ludicrous,'' said Ronald D'Angelo, the Republican elections commissioner for Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>He said the Republicans were simply following the law and could not approve a paper ballot until the courts resolved the issue of which referendum would appear on it. The Republicans on the board also disputed how many people might be precluded from voting, and said they would use every means possible, including Federal Express delivery of ballots to overseas voters, once the ballot question was settled.</p>
        <p>The ballot problem arose after the City Council authorized a referendum to decide whether public money could be used to help build a new stadium for the Yankees if they leave their current city-owned site in the Bronx when their lease expires in 2002.</p>
        <p>Speaker Vallone pushed for the referendum and is making it a theme issue in his Democratic candidacy for Governor. Republicans have labeled it a political ploy to spark a big voter turnout in the city that might help Mr. Vallone.</p>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani vehemently opposes the stadium referendum, arguing that its passage would tie his hands in negotiating with the Yankee's owner, George M. Steinbrenner 3d. To block the stadium referendum, the Mayor convened a commission to draft unrelated revisions in the City Charter to be placed on the ballot. Under state law, Charter revisions proposed by a Mayoral commission bump off the ballot any other proposal.</p>
        <p>Then the Democrats sued, contending that the Mayoral referendum was a ruse and that his commission had failed in its legal duty to review the entire Charter. Last week a State Supreme Court judge in the Bronx agreed and ruled that the Mayor's referendum be struck from the ballot and the stadium referendum restored. The Mayor's lawyers immediately appealed.</p>
        <p>In a related case, Mr. Kellner and other Democrats asked a Federal District Court judge this week to compel the mailing of the ballots under an earlier bipartisan elections board compromise to include both referendum questions on the ballot and simply count the votes on the one that the courts ultimately approved.  The Federal judge, Robert P. Patterson Jr., so far has declined to grant the Democratic request, voicing reluctance to intervene while the dispute is in the State courts.</p>
        <p>THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: THE BALLOT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
