<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dance in Review</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19911126T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="489558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JENNIFER MULLER/THE WORKS DANCE COMPANY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DE173FF936A15752C1A967958260" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dance in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jennifer Muller/The Works  Joyce Theater Through Sunday</p>
        <p>Known especially for choreography that flings sleek, polished dancers into the air, Jennifer Muller has often used energy with less dramatic edge than keen kinetic sense. The second of the three programs in the current season of her modern-dance company, Jennifer Muller/The Works, offers a surprise in this respect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jennifer Muller/The Works  Joyce Theater Through Sunday</p>
        <p>Known especially for choreography that flings sleek, polished dancers into the air, Jennifer Muller has often used energy with less dramatic edge than keen kinetic sense. The second of the three programs in the current season of her modern-dance company, Jennifer Muller/The Works, offers a surprise in this respect.</p>
        <p>The bill on Thursday night consisted of "Refracted Light" and "Righteous About Passing (on the Left)," both from 1990, and the New York premiere of a Muller work created for the Ballet Stagium troupe in Sao Paulo, Brazil, in April.</p>
        <p>"Woman With Visitors at 3 A.M.," as that piece is called, is a welcome return to the stronger emotional imagery that colored Miss Muller's early choreography. Like most of her pieces, the work does not justify its length, but its images engage the eye and the mind through an implied narrative power.</p>
        <p>Lana Cantrell is the woman who tosses on a bed as phantoms in gray street dress (designed by Donna Larsen) hover over her. At the other end of the stage, Michael Jahoda, a superlative dancer of great speed and nuance, is atypically cast as dazed zombielike figure.</p>
        <p>The flashbacks that follow suggest that Mr. Jahoda's character was beaten by bullies who rose from their swivel chairs in an office. As projections of the heroine's mind, this suite is too ordered to be properly dreamlike, and it falls into the enigmatic.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the effect is more tantalizing than irritating, although some episodes are more clearly explained than others. The heroine possibly relives her youth. A family grouping has Mignon Gillen as Girl With a Hole in Her Heart, exasperating her parents. Keith Jarrett's music, with added wind chimes to the piano solos, loses its new-age cool for a jazziness that accompanies a strange, surrealist image for a woman in a red cloche and red dress standing behind a man on a park bench.</p>
        <p>The possible painterly inspiration behind the piece is not identified in the program. After so much angst, the ultimate family reconciliation, which seems more like wishful thinking on the heroine's part, seemingly derives more from pictorial than psychological sources.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the choreography itself fits the general idea, conveyed by the cast, which includes Leda Meredith, Ricardo Sarcos, Karen Lynn Hirschfield, John Brooks, Maria Naidu, Yasushi Tanaka and Edgar Duprat.</p>
        <p>"Righteous" is more of a one-image piece, built about Miss Muller's stylization of break-dancing, to rap music by Eric B. and Rakim. Mr. Jahoda, with a lightness that makes him look as if he barely touches the floor in his leaps, is downright terrific here.</p>
        <p>In "Refracted Light" the dancers smear themselves with blue paint to Tibetan chants in what may or may not be a story of plague and survival. It is that kind of piece.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 26, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A brief dance review yesterday about the Jennifer Muller/The Works troupe at the Joyce Theater misidentified the dancer who portrayed the heroine on Thursday in the premiere of "Woman With Visitors at 3 A.M." She was Lana Carroll, not Lana Cantrell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 26, 1991, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A brief dance review yesterday about the Jennifer Muller/The Works troupe at the Joyce Theater misidentified the dancer who portrayed the heroine on Thursday in the premiere of "Woman With Visitors at 3 A.M." She was Lana Carroll, not Lana Cantrell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
