<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Movies</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="455889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN GELDER, LAWRENCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOMFIELD, NICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCAREY, LEO</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DARK OBSESSION (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLOODY SUNDAY (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC1138F93BA15755C0A967958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Movies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Van Gelder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VAN GELDER, LAWRENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Documentarian Returns</p>
        <p>More than 20 years ago, when Nick Broomfield was studying law, he knew what he liked best. "What I most enjoyed in law was case history," he said, "learning stories from reality."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Documentarian Returns</p>
        <p>More than 20 years ago, when Nick Broomfield was studying law, he knew what he liked best. "What I most enjoyed in law was case history," he said, "learning stories from reality."</p>
        <p>So it was no surprise that after he decided to give up law and go to Britain's National Film School, he would turn to documentaries, collaborating with Joan Churchill on such films including "Tattooed Tears," a study of the California prison system, and "Soldier Girls," about women Army recruits at Fort Gordon, Ga.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Broomfield is turning to fictional features, but reality is never far away. In his first feature, the well-received "Dark Obsession," Gabriel Byrne plays an English aristocrat, Sir Hugo Buckton, who, out with some male friends, hits a woman with his car one night and leaves her to die. Mr. Broomfield said real-life models for Sir Hugo were not hard to find.</p>
        <p>"I think an awful lot of men, particularly in England, because of their education and upbringing, are very out of touch with their emotions and have an enormous problem relating to the opposite sex and are far more comfortable in the company of men," said Mr. Broomfield, a Briton who now lives in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>For his next film, he is revisiting his past as a documentary film maker to create a fictional work titled "Bloody Sunday." Twenty-two years ago, when he was in film school, he went to Northern Ireland to make a documentary about a Protestant family and a Roman Catholic family. He was in Northern Ireland when British paratroopers opened fire in Londonderry, killing a dozen people and triggering the latest round of sectarian violence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Broomfield described the film as being "kind of like 'Platoon' set in Northern Ireland." The film follows a group of British paratroopers through the six months leading up to what has come to be called Bloody Sunday.</p>
        <p>He and Danny Boyle, who wrote the screenplay, worked with a former paratrooper who helped with their research and led them to some of the paratroopers who had been present that day in Londonderry.</p>
        <p>"I've always been quite interested in the way people's characters change and the consequences that follow," Mr. Broomfield said. "I think the military extracts an enormous change in the individual in the way in which it shapes the individual into the unit and produces somebody who, because of the esprit de corps and the bonding that takes play within a platoon, would do things they would never do in civilian life."</p>
        <p>Mr. Broomfield said he hoped to begin filming "Bloody Sunday" in September in England. As soon as it is finished, he said, he plans to start work on "Listening Post," another film inspired by real events. In this instance, the case involves an airman at a British base in Cyprus during the time United States forces were deployed at Beirut airport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Broomfield has just finished editing a film adaptation of Spalding Gray's theater piece "Monster in a Box." And while the film maker has begun to color fact with fiction, he hasn't abandoned the documentary. Recently he made "The Leader, His Driver and the Driver's Wife," a documentary set in South Africa that Mr. Broomfield describes as "a black comedy about the white right."</p>
        <p>He added: "I would love to dip back into doing documentaries from time to time, because they're enormous fun. It's just a delight to go off with a camera and probably two other people and poke around wherever you want to and ask the questions probably no one else has the right to ask." Laughing With Leo</p>
        <p>Comedy was Leo McCarey's stock in trade. Beginning July 6, the achievements of the director, writer and producer will be commemorated by the American Museum of the Moving Image with what is described as his first comprehensive museum retrospective.</p>
        <p>The series, "Leo McCarey: The King of Comedy," is to run for six weeks and include all 23 surviving McCarey features, his two 1950's television films, and a selection of the silent shorts that McCarey, who died in 1969, directed for Hal Roach in the mid-1920's.</p>
        <p>Among the films to be shown are "The Kid From Spain," starring Eddie Cantor; "Duck Soup," with the Marx Brothers; "Ruggles of Red Gap," with Charles Laughton and Mary Boland; "The Awful Truth," with Irene Dunne and Cary Grant; "Going my Way," with Bing Crosby and Barry Fitzgerald, and "The Bells of St. Mary's," with Bing Crosby and Ingrid Bergman.</p>
        <p>The museum is at 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
