<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Signs of Waning Recession in May Consumer Data</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="455960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASAR, SYLVIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD7153DF93BA15755C0A967958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Signs of Waning Recession in May Consumer Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIA NASAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASAR, SYLVIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consumers apparently had the wallet and the will to spend their way out of recession last month, a Government report issued yesterday said.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department report showing that consumer spending surged 1.1 percent in May prompted the President's chief economic adviser, Michael J. Boskin, to declare again, less equivocally than he had in the past, that the recession was over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consumers apparently had the wallet and the will to spend their way out of recession last month, a Government report issued yesterday said.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department report showing that consumer spending surged 1.1 percent in May prompted the President's chief economic adviser, Michael J. Boskin, to declare again, less equivocally than he had in the past, that the recession was over.</p>
        <p>"These figures are further evidence that a recovery is under way," Mr. Boskin said.</p>
        <p>The level of consumer spending in May was $41.8 billion, the highest monthly amount since last fall. The increase, to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $3.8 trillion, followed a revised four-tenths of 1 percent contraction in April.</p>
        <p>Consumer spending accounts for about two-thirds of the nation's economy, which fell into recession according to traditional definitions when the gross national product registered two straight quarters of contraction -- a 1.6 percent drop in the fourth period of 1990 and a 2.8 percent decline in the first period of 1991.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's Commerce Department report also showed that Americans' personal incomes before taxes rose one-half of 1 percent in May, to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $4.78 trillion. It was the biggest monthly advance this year and the fourth straight monthly gain since January.</p>
        <p>The income advance cheered private economic forecasters, who took it as a sign that the rebound in consumer spending would continue.</p>
        <p>"A virtuous cycle has set in," said Robert Giordano, director of economic research at Goldman Sachs &amp; Company. "Income growth will tend to support spending by stimulating more production."</p>
        <p>The burst of spending was broad-based, encompassing everything from clothes to cars to services.</p>
        <p>The stronger car buying followed a decline in April that dragged total consumer spending down by $15.2 billion in the month. Robert Dennis, an economist at the Congressional Budget Office, said he thought car buying would show another rise in June. Sales of new cars in the first 20 days of this month are running ahead of the May level.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's report also showded that the savings rate of consumers fell in May to 3.6 percent of after-tax income, from 4 percent in April. The decline was the fourth since January, when the rate was 4.5 percent, and the May rate was the lowest since September, when it was 3.5 percent.</p>
        <p>But economists took the lower savings rate as a positive sign.</p>
        <p>"That suggests that consumers are confident and that they feel better about their balance sheets, especially home prices," said Mr. Dennis of the Congressional Budget Office.</p>
        <p>A Labor Department report yesterday also showed that intial claims for unemployment insurance fell in the second week of June, to 431,000, after an increase in the previous week.</p>
        <p>The recession will not be declared officially over by the Business Cycle Dating Committee of the National Bureau of Economic Research for months to come. But Mr. Boskin cited encouraging "coincident indicators" that the committee usually uses to help mark the end of recessions.  Some Turning Points</p>
        <p>For example, the number of Americans on payrolls, Mr. Boskin said, reached its low point in April; industrial production and store and factory sales touched bottom in March, and, according to today's report, Americans' incomes reached a trough in February.</p>
        <p>The data could yet be revised, which is one reason the business cycle committee holds off its final pronouncement for a time. But Mr. Boskin's analysis of the current data suggests that the recession may have ended in April or May.</p>
        <p>Since the recession of 1990-91 was more shallow than most, Mr. Boskin said, the recovery is likely to be modest by past standards. The next indicator of the recovery's momentum will come a week from Friday, when the Labor Department will report on the number of jobs gained or lost and hours worked in June, which is the first clue of whether incomes rose or fell in the month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
