<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>War-Mood Metrics</title>
    <meta content="11wwln--essay" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="42" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/12/11/magazine/11wwln_essay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1723809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 12-11-05: ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feldman, Noah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/National Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDD1331F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>War-Mood Metrics</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">War-Mood Metrics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Noah Feldman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feldman, Noah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Noah Feldman essay holds that last year's irrational optimism over Iraq has been replaced by unjustified pessimism; says it is example of one ideological standpoint giving way to another; blames deteriorating security situation and rising opposition to war in US for fueling pessimistic view; cites examples of significant progress being made; contends societies can survive protracted terrorist violence against civilian targets and emerge intact; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A little less than a year ago, in the aftermath of the first Iraqi elections, the most irresponsible thing being said in Washington was that everything was going to be fine. Now, with the next set of elections scheduled for Dec. 15, the new irresponsibility is the increasingly respectable assertion that the war has already been lost. Irrational optimism has been replaced by unjustified pessimism. This is not some triumph of experience over idealism. One a priori ideological standpoint is simply giving way to another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is today's home-front pessimism about Iraq any more rational than yesterday's optimism?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A little less than a year ago, in the aftermath of the first Iraqi elections, the most irresponsible thing being said in Washington was that everything was going to be fine. Now, with the next set of elections scheduled for Dec. 15, the new irresponsibility is the increasingly respectable assertion that the war has already been lost. Irrational optimism has been replaced by unjustified pessimism. This is not some triumph of experience over idealism. One a priori ideological standpoint is simply giving way to another.</p>
        <p>The last, bloody year in Iraq has seen an uninterrupted stream of insurgent attacks on U.S. soldiers and Iraqi security forces. Civil strife between Shiites and Sunnis has escalated. The jihadist wing of the insurgency has made civilians into primary targets, which in turn has encouraged Shiite militias, working closely with the government, to use outrageous tactics -- including torture and targeted assassination -- in the fight against those insurgents. Meanwhile, ordinary Iraqis, acting as if they expect a civil war, are moving out of mixed towns to safer, more homogeneous communities. You can hardly blame them, seeing that the United States has not managed to provide security and that denominational tensions have continued to mount.</p>
        <p>The deteriorating security situation, coupled with rising opposition to the war in the United States, has fueled the view that the game is up. Yet there has also been significant progress toward Sunni participation in the political process. Before the elections last January, no one in the world (outside the senior levels of the Bush administration) expected Sunnis to turn out in more than token numbers. Since the constitutional referendum in October, though, several Sunni political parties have formed to contest this week's elections. These parties may soon represent the first organized, credible voice for Sunnis in the new Iraq. They can be expected to seek their fair share of the political spoils in the new Parliament -- but to get them, they will have to offer something, beginning with a drawing down of violence on the part of the ex-Baathist, ex-military wing of the insurgency. In return, they may obtain a reduced role for the de-Baathification commission so unpopular with their constituents and perhaps some flexibility from Shiite leaders on the degree of autonomy to be sought by the oil-rich south.</p>
        <p>Of course, even if the insurgency diminishes, jihadist terror will remain. But lest we forget, societies can survive protracted terrorist violence against civilian targets. Israel has been living with such attacks for decades. Tragic, costly and debilitating, terrorism nonetheless can coexist with ordinary politics and ordinary lives.</p>
        <p>It is an uncomfortable truth that American forces in Iraq have come to provide a motivation for terrorist violence. It is equally uncomfortable to acknowledge that with each day that it cannot defeat the insurgency, the United States loses credibility as a military power able to achieve its objectives through force. In the near term, however, if the Iraqis are to reach a political agreement that holds, they cannot do it without U.S. troops as guarantors of any pact. For all their complaints about occupation, the new Sunni politicians understand this. Instead of calling for immediate withdrawal, they are urging a timetable for a phased pullout -- a request to which Shiite and Kurdish leaders are ready to acquiesce. The willingness of Iraqi leaders to reach such a consensus suggests that, for them at least, the construction of a functioning postwar Iraqi state is not yet out of the question.</p>
        <p>This latest effort at pact-making could well fail. Elected Sunnis could prove unable to deliver a reduction in insurgent violence, and the civil war could go into high gear. Lebanon-in-Vietnam -- a rough approximation of the horror that would follow -- really would mark a defeat for the United States, one that would leave many thousands dead and probably could not be cabined within the borders of Iraq. Unbearably enough, such a catastrophe would look like the kind of situation that often leads humanitarians in the United States to call for intervention.</p>
        <p>But it is indefensible to claim that this disastrous outcome is inevitable and ethically obtuse to use such a prediction to justify doing nothing to prevent it. All is not well in Iraq. But all is not lost, either.</p>
        <p>THE WAY WE LIVE NOW: 12-11-05: ESSAY Noah Feldman is a contributing writer for the magazine and a law professor at New York University. He was a senior adviser to the Coalition Provisional Authority in Iraq.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Noah Feldman is a contributing writer for the magazine and a law professor at New York University. He was a senior adviser to the Coalition Provisional Authority in Iraq.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
