<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not-So-Hidden Treasures At Museum Gift Shops</title>
    <meta content="11ctmuseum" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1724251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT AT ITS BEST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0D61131F932A25751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not-So-Hidden Treasures At Museum Gift Shops</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GORDON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSEUM shops offer a welcome shortcut to gift givers. Their managers have done the legwork -- calling or traveling all over the state, the country or even the world to find what you would have picked out had you jumped on a plane to, say, Turkey. And they offer a route away from the same old gifts for the same old season: another sparkly candle, another bottle of wine. As a bonus, many of the museums feature special events during December. Here are a few of the best shops.</p>
        <p>PEABODY MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY -- Anyone who has ever read anything about the museum knows that it is best known for its collection of dinosaurs. It also has one of the best museum shops in the state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSEUM shops offer a welcome shortcut to gift givers. Their managers have done the legwork -- calling or traveling all over the state, the country or even the world to find what you would have picked out had you jumped on a plane to, say, Turkey. And they offer a route away from the same old gifts for the same old season: another sparkly candle, another bottle of wine. As a bonus, many of the museums feature special events during December. Here are a few of the best shops.</p>
        <p>PEABODY MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY -- Anyone who has ever read anything about the museum knows that it is best known for its collection of dinosaurs. It also has one of the best museum shops in the state.</p>
        <p>Whoever sets out the merchandise at the Peabody knows how to lure people in. On a recent Saturday, an assorted mix of chunky inexpensive bracelets ($12.95 to $14.95) hung in a display right by the entrance. Women crowded around, jockeying for position as they tried them on. Equally popular were the dozens of small square bins of kids' toys in the center of the shop. (The contents range from 50 cents to $4.) One bin contained rectangles that connected to make a bouncing ball.</p>
        <p>But trinkets are just the beginning. One wall has been devoted this season to pieces from Peru, connected to the current exhibition, ''Machu Picchu: Unveiling the Mystery of the Incas.'' They include thick sweaters, hats, Peruvian crafts, art quilts and folk art. Give a kid the pan flute ($19.95) and you'll have to wrest it away later. (Or buy it to avoid a meltdown.)</p>
        <p>The really good stuff is in the section marked with a sign warning children not to move any closer without an adult. Silver jewelry in interesting, elaborate designs is well priced; a heavy necklace adorned with silver beads is one of the most expensive pieces at $180. Gleaming handmade silk scarves, pottery and dozens of other items prompt a shopper to stand and stare off into space, wondering, ''Who can I buy this for?''</p>
        <p>Peabody Museum of Natural History, 170 Whitney Avenue, New Haven; (203) 432-5050, www.peabody.yale.edu.</p>
        <p>Open 10 a.m. to 4:45 p.m. Mondays through Saturdays, noon to 4:45 p.m. Sundays.</p>
        <p>THE FLORENCE GRISWOLD MUSEUM -- Florence Griswold, the soul of the Impressionist Old Lyme Art Colony, might have been pleased with the thought and care displayed in the shop at the museum that bears her name. It has long had an excellent reputation for its offerings, which take a welcome leap from typical museum fare into the artistic and inventive.</p>
        <p>Although the shop is small by big-museum standards, each piece in it is jewel-like, from the artists' tools showcased in a bookcase to the right of the shop, including ragg-paper books ($13), Cretacolor drawing sets ($25), watercolor travel sets ($29.95) and miniature colored pencils ($4), to the inventive handmade jewelry kept in a case by the front desk. Bracelets include a translucent wire and bead piece that looks like a mesh over the skin ($50).</p>
        <p>For the holidays, trees full of ornaments stood like bejeweled sentries in the center of the space, and shelves spilled over with Christmas-themed books and gifts. Collectors from throughout the area come to find Robert Sabuda's latest pop-up book, in this case ''The 12 Days of Christmas'' ($19.95). Those who think pop-ups are for kids will think again when they see this work of art, which requires close inspection to adequately admire the handiwork.</p>
        <p>Other mainstays include art books that focus on the Connecticut shoreline, along with cards, posters and papers. The shop also carries an instrument called the Music Maker ($35), a small harplike gadget that allows the user to slip a song sheet under the strings, pluck them and make even the tone-deaf sound musical.</p>
        <p>The Florence Griswold Museum, 96 Lyme Street, Old Lyme; (860) 434-5542. www.flogris.org.</p>
        <p>Open 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tuesday to Saturday and Monday through Jan. 2, from 1 to 5 p.m. Sunday.</p>
        <p>THE MARK TWAIN HOUSE AND MUSEUM -- Mark Twain is Connecticut -- well, and Hannibal, Mo., and he did live in Europe after he lost his fortune. But no matter, because this is the house he decorated with the money he made from his books, and it is the place he is said to have loved best. The house proves that Mr. Twain was probably ahead of his time in many ways, including in the hiring of Louis Comfort Tiffany to design some of his interiors before Mr. Tiffany made a name for himself in art glass.</p>
        <p>Art glass is a theme in this museum shop, where Tiffany reproductions are sold, but even more compelling are the modernist creations of the California art-glass maker Lundberg Studios. These are high-end gifts (a small vase costs $190), but for anyone who collects art glass, they are an especially attractive present.</p>
        <p>The standard museum-store offerings such as hats, notepads and book bags are easily overlooked for things that Mr. Twain would have appreciated, including miniatures of a Ferris wheel, a carousel ($100 each) and a circus ($125) that are intricate and amusing.</p>
        <p>Possibly even better, although tucked far back and too high for a child to find, is a copy of an 1894 book, ''Children's Singing Games,'' edited by Alice B. Gomme, with black-and-white pictures by Winifred Smith ($24.75). The book comes complete with music and instructions. For those determined to lure the kids away from video games, TV and the computer this season, it may help to have something like this on hand.</p>
        <p>There's also quite a collection of everything Huckleberry on bookshelves at the front of the store. Wild huckleberry cordials, chocolate bars, gummi bears, jelly beans, tea and taffy are among the offerings. Victoriana is also a continuing theme, evidenced by scarves and purses of the era, pocket watches by Jules Jurgensen, and an entire section devoted to calligraphy that includes instruction books, ink and pens.</p>
        <p>Mark Twain House and Museum, 351 Farmington Avenue, Hartford; (860) 247-0998 or on the Web at www.marktwainhouse.org.</p>
        <p>Open 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Monday to Saturday, noon to 5:30 p.m. Sunday.</p>
        <p>MYSTIC SEAPORT MUSEUM STORE -- This is by far the biggest museum store in the state, a two-story house that stands alone on Route 27 with its own parking lot. Besides an abundance of gifts, the store has a cafe where tired visitors can take a break. After a respite, they go back to shopping, because this store is a destination unto itself.</p>
        <p>Within the cafe are food gifts that include jars of apple crisp, apple butter, soup mixes, oatmeal, marinades, nuts, candies and more, most with a distinctly New England flavor. Move on to the decorated Christmas trees. One is hung with hammered tin ornaments ($7.95 to $9.95), another with Kitras art-glass balls, which glow in the light, with the iridescence and wavy colors of a blown bubble ($15.95 to $20.95).</p>
        <p>Most of the items in the shop have a maritime theme, including a cocktail shaker in the form of an oil lamp ($165), a silver serving dish shaped like a shell ($50), Nantucket baskets ($250) and a miniature of the U.S.S. Constitution ($325).</p>
        <p>The sheer amount of merchandise is remarkable, with whole sections devoted to children's items, clothing, jewelry and clocks of all types. To keep the kids busy, a puzzle called ''The Best of Connecticut'' has 1,000 pieces ($14.95). Books fill the second floor, filed in categories such as Military History and Sea Stories. After checking out all the items in this store, shoppers can head over to the Maritime Gallery, which sells marine art, ship models, scrimshaw and sculpture.</p>
        <p>Mystic Seaport Museum Store, Route 27, Mystic; (800) 331-2665, www.mysticseaport.org.</p>
        <p>The shop is open 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. daily. The cafe is open 8 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>MYSTIC AQUARIUM AND INSTITUTE FOR EXPLORATION -- This is one shop that is almost exclusively for children; once kids get inside they don't want to leave. Ashley Boyle, 10, and her sister, Kasey, 11, of Wolcott were admiring a $395 bronze seal sculpture displayed in a window of the shop on a recent Sunday. (Ashley's verdict: ''I think it's neat.'') A few feet away, a display table overflowed with stuffed penguins of varying sizes ($5 to $30), their renewed popularity courtesy of the film ''March of the Penguins.''</p>
        <p>Fish figures, games, key chains, puzzles, jewelry: If it has something to do with children and fish or fishing, the store has it. There is also merchandise geared to adults, including a mermaid weathervane, at $69.99. But the kids come first here, and as one father said as he struggled to keep three children from spending his entire Christmas budget in one place: ''There's a lot of stuff here for under $5. Go and find it.''</p>
        <p>Mystic Aquarium and Institute for Exploration, 55 Coogan Boulevard, Mystic; (860) 572-5955 or visit www.mysticaquarium.org.</p>
        <p>Open 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. daily.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT AT ITS BEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
