<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rise in Chinese Textile Imports Prompts Inquiry in Europe</title>
    <meta content="23TEXT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/23/business/worldbusiness/23textiles.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1666928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meller, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mendelson, Peter (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Quotas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Europe</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D81431F930A15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rise in Chinese Textile Imports Prompts Inquiry in Europe</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rise in Chinese Textile Imports Prompts Inquiry in Europe</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL MELLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meller, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, April 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Commission, following surge in textile imports in first quarter 2005 and fierce lobbying by European textile manufacturers, will begin inquiry on whether import controls should be reimposed on China; early numbers and anecdotal evidence shows sharp increase in Chinese textile imports to Europe since start of year, when 40-year-old quota system was lifted; European Trade Comr Peter Mandelson, citing need for more evidence of harm caused by imports, has hesitated to take any retaliatory action against China; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Commission will begin an inquiry Monday to see whether import controls should be reimposed on China, after a surge in textile imports during the first three months of this year.</p>
        <p>Claude Veron-Reville, the spokeswoman for the European trade commissioner, Peter Mandelson, said Friday that after analyzing customs data for the first quarter, the commission had enough evidence to justify an investigation. European textile manufacturers have been lobbying fiercely for new import limits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Commission will begin an inquiry to see whether import controls should be reimposed on China, after a surge in textile imports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Commission will begin an inquiry Monday to see whether import controls should be reimposed on China, after a surge in textile imports during the first three months of this year.</p>
        <p>Claude Veron-Reville, the spokeswoman for the European trade commissioner, Peter Mandelson, said Friday that after analyzing customs data for the first quarter, the commission had enough evidence to justify an investigation. European textile manufacturers have been lobbying fiercely for new import limits.</p>
        <p>Early numbers and anecdotal evidence have pointed to a sharp increase in Chinese textile imports to Europe since Jan. 1, when a 40-year-old quota system was lifted. Mr. Mandelson hesitated to take any retaliatory action against China, the European Union's second-biggest trading partner after the United States, saying he needed more evidence of the harm caused by the sharp rise in imports.</p>
        <p>He will attend an informal dinner Sunday with trade ministers from the 25 countries in the union to discuss the Chinese textile imports. Though a majority supports the investigation, there is no consensus.</p>
        <p>France, Portugal and Italy, which all have important textile industries, are expected to push for the quickest possible action against China.</p>
        <p>Others, however, like Sweden, are opposed to any process that could lead to restrictions on China, as some of Europe's retailers have benefited from the sharp decline in prices of certain clothes. These ministers are unlikely to dissuade the commission from opening an inquiry as the commission takes the lead on all trade issues.</p>
        <p>Imports of Chinese tights and pantyhose into the union skyrocketed 1,940 percent by value in January and February, compared with a year earlier, Euratex, the textile industry association, said. The value of imports of pullovers and jerseys from China jumped 893 percent, while imports of trousers more than tripled, Euratex said.</p>
        <p>The increases in supply have caused prices to fall, Euratex said. While this is good news for the profit margins of retailers and for some consumers, European textile manufacturers are suffering, the trade group said.</p>
        <p>An official investigation would involve informal discussions with the Chinese government. If China failed to curb the surge during over a two-month period, the union would have to choose between imposing so-called safeguard measures or opening a formal three-month-long consultation with the Chinese government.</p>
        <p>The Chinese premier, Wen Jiabao, said Thursday that the increase in textile exports to Europe followed changes in international trading rules, and that his government had taken action to control the surge, according to The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
