<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man in the News; A Marine on Message -- Peter Pace</title>
    <meta content="23PACE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/23/politics/23pace.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1666950"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Peter Pace</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cloud, David S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pace, Peter (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Man in the News (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Joint Chiefs of Staff</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pace, Peter</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EED81431F930A15757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man in the News; A Marine on Message -- Peter Pace</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Marine on Message</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID S. CLOUD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cloud, David S</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Man in the News profile of Marine Gen Peter Pace in view of Pres Bush's decision to nominate him to be chairman of Joint Chiefs of Staff; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In April 2003, as American troops were entering Baghdad and looters roamed the streets, Gen. Peter Pace was asked in a television interview what the United States military could do to help democracy take root in Iraq.</p>
        <p>''What we can help do,'' General Pace replied, ''is provide a stable environment inside of which you can rebuild your schools, you can have your electricity turned back on, the water and humanitarian aid can continue to flow, and the people can meet publicly and decide for themselves what kind of government they want.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gen. Peter Pace's effectiveness as a communicator who stays on message is one of the factors that led President Bush to nominate him to be chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In April 2003, as American troops were entering Baghdad and looters roamed the streets, Gen. Peter Pace was asked in a television interview what the United States military could do to help democracy take root in Iraq.</p>
        <p>''What we can help do,'' General Pace replied, ''is provide a stable environment inside of which you can rebuild your schools, you can have your electricity turned back on, the water and humanitarian aid can continue to flow, and the people can meet publicly and decide for themselves what kind of government they want.''</p>
        <p>That was a precise description of the Bush administration's hopes for quick results in Iraq, delivered with utter confidence by a marine who looks as if he came from central casting. Two years later, with stability in Iraq still elusive, General Pace's effectiveness as a communicator who sticks to the administration's message is one of the factors that led President Bush to nominate him on Friday to be chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
        <p>General Pace, vice chairman since late 2001, has long been considered the likely successor to the current chairman, Gen. Richard B. Myers, who retires in September. His new role, which requires Senate confirmation, appears likely to be defined in good part by the effort to extricate the military from Iraq.</p>
        <p>The main question concerning General Pace, current and former Pentagon officials say, is whether as chairman he will be willing to take on Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld and other administration officials in private when disagreements on strategy or other matters arise.</p>
        <p>''The issue is whether General Pace will offer his best military advice, even if it goes against the individual views of the secretary of defense,'' said one general, now retired, who worked under General Pace on the Joint Staff. This general, who would speak only anonymously because his current job requires him to maintain his contacts at the Pentagon, said he doubted that General Pace would be an assertive chairman.</p>
        <p>Others who know him describe him as efficient and unflappable, skilled at managing complex initiatives while also attentive to the needs of enlisted personnel.</p>
        <p>General Pace's management style has been built over 38 years in a career that began with graduation from the Naval Academy and has included postings in Vietnam, Somalia, Japan and Korea, as well as studies at George Washington University, where he earned a master's degree in business administration, and Harvard.</p>
        <p>Peter Pace, the son of an Italian immigrant, was born in Brooklyn on Nov. 5, 1945, and raised in Teaneck, N.J. At Teaneck High School, he played soccer, ran track and was vice president of the senior class. The entry by his name in his senior yearbook reads, ''Leadership, modesty, reliability and character are all qualities that personify Pete.''</p>
        <p>Jacqueline Kates, a high school classmate who is now mayor of Teaneck, said, ''Pete seems to be absolutely professional, but he also brings compassion and humanity.''</p>
        <p>Soon after graduating from the Naval Academy in 1967, he was sent to Vietnam and assumed leadership of a rifle platoon. After the Tet Offensive of 1968, his unit fought to retake the citadel at Hue from the North Vietnamese Army. That battle, one of the toughest of the war, took the lives of five of the platoon's members. Even today, he keeps a picture of the first, Lance Cpl. Guido Farinaro, on his desk at the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>A quarter-century later, Brigadier General Pace was the second-ranking officer in a task force that President Bill Clinton sent to Somalia after the fiasco, later portrayed in the movie ''Black Hawk Down,'' in which 18 American soldiers were killed.</p>
        <p>In 1994, still unable to bring peace to a Somalia torn by militia violence, the United States withdrew. Years later, General Pace would say that expanding the American mission, from humanitarian aid to include disarming Somali militias, had been a mistake.</p>
        <p>After Somalia, he was promoted to major general and made deputy commander of United States forces in Japan, where he worked under General Myers, an Air Force officer.</p>
        <p>Promoted to lieutenant general in 1996 and four-star rank in 2000, he took over the Southern Command, overseeing all American forces in the Caribbean and Latin America. Less than a year later, he was named vice chairman of the Joint Chiefs, serving again under General Myers.</p>
        <p>Though General Pace would be the first marine to become chairman of the Joint Chiefs, for most of the last 18 years he has held posts taking him beyond the corps, to responsibilities overseeing multiple military services.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
