<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Soviets Near Settling Arms Pact Dispute</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="447359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7D71539F930A15756C0A967958260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Soviets Near Settling Arms Pact Dispute</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>ST. PAUL, Minn., May 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States and the Soviet Union today moved toward agreement on resolving differences over a treaty cutting non-nuclear armed forces in Europe.</p>
        <p>The disagreements have prevented the pact from taking effect and have blocked the scheduling of the next superpower summit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States and the Soviet Union today moved toward agreement on resolving differences over a treaty cutting non-nuclear armed forces in Europe.</p>
        <p>The disagreements have prevented the pact from taking effect and have blocked the scheduling of the next superpower summit.</p>
        <p>In St. Paul to promote his education program, President Bush expressed hope that the differences over the treaty could be ironed out this week. And in Washington, the chief of the Soviet general staff suggested that he had accepted a compromise plan offered by the United States. 'It Went Very Well'</p>
        <p>"We don't have all the results yet," said Mr. Bush, adding, "As far as I'm concerned, it went very well."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spent 15 minutes at the White House on Tuesday with Gen. Mikhail A. Moiseyev, the Soviet officer. General Moiseyev, who met with other senior American officials on Monday and Tuesday, had been seen by Washington as the leader of hard-line military officers who opposed the terms of the conventional arms treaty. But he indicated in a statement to reporters that the Soviet Union had agreed to abide by the overall limits set by the treaty, which was signed in Paris last year but not ratified.</p>
        <p>American charges that the Soviet Union has reneged on some of its commitments under the treaty have stalled efforts to conclude another agreement, which would reduce long-range nuclear weapons. That in turn has prevented the final scheduling of a Soviet-American summit meeting that is supposed to be held in Moscow this year.</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union had been insisting that its naval infantry units and coastal defense forces should not be counted toward the treaty's ceilings, while the United States had suggested that Moscow keep those units intact if it so desired but eliminate a corresponding number of other ground forces so that the overall ceiling set by the pact would not be violated. Accord Possible This Week</p>
        <p>"The naval infantry armaments and the armaments of the coastal defense will be counted against those overall ceilings," General Moiseyev said in Washington.</p>
        <p>He said it was "quite possible" that a final agreement on the treaty could be reached this week. "What is left is not of great importance," he said.</p>
        <p>Although the general's comments were not definitive, David Shorr, associate director of the British American Security Council, a group that closely monitors conventional arms reduction, said: "Moiseyev seems to be ready to meet the concerns that the U.S. has been expressing. He seems ready to count everything we want counted under the limits."</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters aboard Air Force One en route to St. Paul, Mr. Bush called "totally erroneous" a report in The New York Times and some other newspapers today that he opposed inviting President Mikhail S. Gorbachev to London in July for a meeting of the leaders of the seven most powerful industrial democracies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said, "No decisions have been taken on that," but he declined to say whether he indeed favored inviting Mr. Gorbachev to the meeting in London. "If his coming there could help with the reform, genuinely help reform, that would be a very, very important matter," he said.</p>
        <p>Administration officials who had said on Tuesday that Mr. Bush did not want Mr. Gorbachev invited to London said today that while no formal answer had been sent to Mr. Gorbachev, the United States did not want to include him in the meeting this year because the extent and nature of economic assistance that Washington is ready to offer the Soviet Union remains unsettled.</p>
        <p>They said Mr. Bush was irked that discussions about the meeting had appeared in news reports before a diplomatic accommodation had been reached and a final decision announced. The articles also came as General Moiseyev was in town for delicate discussions in which the Bush Administration has a large stake.</p>
        <p>Moreover, in his dealings with Mr. Gorbachev, Mr. Bush tries to strike a careful, diplomatic tone that does not embarrass the Soviet leader publicly. Administration officials said today that it was still possible that some face-saving convention might be found in place of Mr. Gorbachev attending the London conference, for instance having Moscow send a lower-level delegation to consult with officials of the countries meeting there.</p>
        <p>Administration officials have been placing great importance on General Moiseyev's visit to the United States because he had been perceived in Washington as a leading figure among conservative military officers who thought the conventional arms treaty cut too deeply into Soviet military strength in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's comments today seemed to be a signal that the Administraation has concluded that the military, or at least General Moiseyev, was no longer blocking final agreement.</p>
        <p>"One thing I came away with is that they genuinely want to resolve both these matters," he said. "There was some question as to whether the Soviets wanted a deal, or whether we did. The answer is that we both do."</p>
        <p>General Moiseyev said: "The ceiling for the Soviet Union which is envisaged by the treaty signed in Paris will remain the same for the Soviet Union. It will not be exceeded."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush declined to provide any details of the discussions. "We're at the stage where we need confidential discussions going on," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
