<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="707958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E3D81539F930A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOOTBALL  Bears Edge Chiefs  Steve Walsh hit Tyrone Williams with a 32-yard touchdown pass with 3 minutes 7 seconds left last night, lifting the visiting Chicago Bears over Kansas City, 21-18, before the Chiefs' biggest preseason crowd in 20 years. Walsh drove the Bears (3-0) 80 yards in just four plays, aided by two penalties. After the touchdown, Walsh hit Ryan Wetnight with a 2-point conversion pass.</p>
        <p>The Chiefs (2-2) then zipped downfield behind Steve Bono and had a 1st-and-goal from the 4-yard line. But on fourth down from the 2, the Chiefs passed up the expected overtime-causing field goal and tried to pass. But Bono tripped coming out from center when his own lineman stepped on his foot and was ruled sacked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOOTBALL  Bears Edge Chiefs  Steve Walsh hit Tyrone Williams with a 32-yard touchdown pass with 3 minutes 7 seconds left last night, lifting the visiting Chicago Bears over Kansas City, 21-18, before the Chiefs' biggest preseason crowd in 20 years. Walsh drove the Bears (3-0) 80 yards in just four plays, aided by two penalties. After the touchdown, Walsh hit Ryan Wetnight with a 2-point conversion pass.</p>
        <p>The Chiefs (2-2) then zipped downfield behind Steve Bono and had a 1st-and-goal from the 4-yard line. But on fourth down from the 2, the Chiefs passed up the expected overtime-causing field goal and tried to pass. But Bono tripped coming out from center when his own lineman stepped on his foot and was ruled sacked.</p>
        <p>Joe Montana threw the only touchdown pass completed against the Chicago defense in the preseason as the Chiefs built a 15-3 lead. Montana, playing only the first half, was 13 for 20 for 141 yards and an 8-yard touchdown strike to J. J. Birden, who caught 3 passes for 39 yards in the 12-play, 92-yard drive. Bono then came in for the Chiefs (2-2) and tossed to Jimmy Johnson the first 2-point conversion ever scored against the Bears, who had surrendered only two field goals in their first two preseason games.</p>
        <p>The crowd of 75,114 was the largest preseason gathering for the Chiefs home or away since August 1973. Mark Collins, replacing Albert Lewis at cornerback, intercepted an Erik Kramer pass with 41 seconds left in the first half and sped 30 yards for a touchdown, giving the Chiefs a 15-3 halftime lead.</p>
        <p>"I think we were in sync to a certain degree," Montana said.</p>
        <p>Deion Sanders watched the game upstairs at Arrowhead Stadium. The unrestricted free agent cornerback has been shopping his services to National Football League teams he believes will contend for the Super Bowl. (AP) TRACK AND FIELD Christie Meets Expectations  The world champion sprinter Linford Christie was billed as the star of the Commonwealth Games in Victoria, British Columbia, and, after a leisurely first race, he lived up to expectations yesterday. The 1992 Olympic gold medalist at 100 meters had the slowest winning time of all the first-round heats, then came back to tie his own games record with a sizzling 10.02-second quarterfinal victory. His time matched the record he set four years ago in Auckland, New Zealand. Frankie Fredericks of Namibia, the world champion at 200 meters, won his quarterfinal heat in 10.04, his fastest of the year, as the competition began in cool, damp weather. (AP) TENNIS  For Berasategui, No. 36 on Clay  Top-seeded Alberto Berasategui defeated Herbert Wiltschnig of Austria, 6-2, 7-5, yesterday in the $400,000 Croatian Open, a clay-court tournament in Umag. For the 21-year-old Berasategui, ranked 10th in the world, it was his 36th clay-court victory of the year. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
