<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utilities Say '81 New York Law Is Proving Costly</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536469"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D7153DF935A25755C0A964958260" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utilities Say '81 New York Law Is Proving Costly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State consumers will pay $4.5 billion or more in extra costs in the 1990's, according to the state's utilities, because of a law passed in Albany at the tail end of the last energy crisis.</p>
        <p>The law was intended to nurture competition in electricity generation and improve efficiency by offering a minimum price to independent producers. Now those prices look extremely generous because of an unexpected drop in utilities' own costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State consumers will pay $4.5 billion or more in extra costs in the 1990's, according to the state's utilities, because of a law passed in Albany at the tail end of the last energy crisis.</p>
        <p>The law was intended to nurture competition in electricity generation and improve efficiency by offering a minimum price to independent producers. Now those prices look extremely generous because of an unexpected drop in utilities' own costs.</p>
        <p>The Cuomo administration is seeking a repeal of the law. But the industry that the law helped to create, independent power production, is lobbying hard to keep its provisions, at least for the time being. Changing Conditions</p>
        <p>The conflict illustrates the pitfalls of long-term energy policy, with a law enacted at a time of high fuel prices and perceived shortages creating unexpected problems a decade later, after the energy market took an unexpected turn toward cheaper, more abundant supplies.</p>
        <p>The law was meant to incubate small projects that use "renewable" fuels or that use oil and gas efficiently. It promised entrepreneurs who built generating stations that they could sell to utilities for a minimum price of 6 cents a kilowatt-hour. The utilities would then resell the electricity to their own customers.</p>
        <p>The Consolidated Edison Company, which won its first rate increase in a decade in April, said one reason it needed to charge more was the expense of buying power from independent generators, even though its peak demand for power was falling.</p>
        <p>The recession and an unexpected dip in fuel costs have left New York with a surplus of electricity and produced a crash in the wholesale price. Consequently, the utilities now say that they are required to pay 6 cents for power from the independents that they could make themselves for 3.</p>
        <p>"We're being locked into contracts well above market levels," said Richard M. Flynn, the chairman of the New York Power Authority, who has been lobbying for a repeal. "The law was enacted back in 1981, and it was a different world in those days. We projected then that electricity prices would continue to rise."</p>
        <p>Carol E. Murphy, the executive director of the Independent Power Producers of New York, a lobbying group in Albany, acknowledged that future projects should not be guaranteed 6 cents. But if existing contracts were abrogated, she said, no one would ever build another independent plant in New York. And the new plants are cleaner than the cheaper older ones owned by utilities, she said.</p>
        <p>Still, the Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation, which serves a huge area of upstate New York, says that its deals with the independents will cost its customers an extra $3 billion. Customers of Con Edison, which serves New York City and most of Westchester, may pay $1 billion more and customers of the Long Island Lighting Company may pay $500 million, by those companies' estimates.</p>
        <p>About 1,900 megawatts of independent power production is now on line, with another 4,700 megawatts under contract, according to Ms. Murphy, at a cost of about $10.6 billion. The total capacity of these plants is roughly 10 times the size of the abandoned Shoreham nuclear plant.  Demand Is Down</p>
        <p>One reason for the utilities' saying that the cost is excessive is that the demand for power is stable or shrinking because of the recession and because of aggressive promotion of conservation by utilities.</p>
        <p>If demand was rising, then the choice would be between new capacity built by the utilities or by the independent producers. But the utilities say that currently if it were not for distortions of the energy market caused by public policy, no new capacity would have to be built at all.  Ms. Murphy, speaking for the independent producers, said "what we have here is a very temporary energy glut." She added, "If you assume that some part of the utility system is going to have to be shut down or retired, the best guess of everyone is that we're going to need more power by the end of the century."</p>
        <p>Ms. Murphy's position is that the cost of complying with the Federal Clean Air Act amendments of 1990 will sharply raise the utilities' cost estimate of 3 cents a kilowatt-hour. She added that the public would probably be willing to pay a premium for cleaner power. "If you ask people if they'd rather spend 6 cents for hydropower or 5 cents for a coal burner or a foreign-oil burner, most people would probably pick 6 cents," she said.</p>
        <p>Nearly 500 megawatts of the 8,500 megawatts of existing and planned capacity is hydroelectric. Most of the rest is fired by natural gas, often generating steam for industrial use along with electricity, raising total efficiency. Under a Federal law, the Public Utilities Regulatory Policy Act of 1978, such co-generators and generators using clean sources have a guaranteed market for their power with the utilities.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is convinced that the state contracts are such a bad deal for consumers. Another analyst, Christopher O. Ward, the assistant commissioner of energy policy and programs in New York City's Department of Telecommunications and Energy, said that the independent projects had another advantage, providing diversity of fuel in the electric system. He added that in utility planning, because of continuously changing circumstances, "you can't not take a risk." Proposing Changes</p>
        <p>Mr. Flynn, however, said he would like a reorganized system for signing contracts, with the price not being set until late in the process, and a requirement that construction start soon after the contract is signed, to reduce the risk posed by changing conditions.</p>
        <p>For her part, Ms. Murphy said that without a firm price in hand, financing such a project would be impossible. The utilities, she said, have never liked independent generators, and Mr. Flynn, she added, wanted to scuttle the contracts in retaliation for the demise of his agency's contract to buy power from Hydro-Quebec.</p>
        <p>That contract was canceled as uneconomic earlier this year, an action the independent producers had lobbied for. Mr. Flynn said that just as the Hydro-Quebec contract had been canceled as uneconomic, other such contracts should be terminated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
