<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Digest</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="829761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK, NY, USA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1DE1239F930A25751C0A960958260" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Digest</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK CITY</p>
        <p>Crew Seizes Bronx Districts</p>
        <p>Saying he suspected widespread corruption, Dr. Rudy Crew, the New York City Schools Chancellor, announced that he had seized control of two Bronx school districts that are among the lowest-performing in the city and would soon order  an investigation of at least 10 of the city's 30 other districts. [Page A1.] Change in Foster Placements</p>
        <p>Three boys, one 15, the others 16, are accused of walking out of their foster-care group home on Staten Island, breaking into the house of a 71-year-old man and killing him. Now, bowing to public outrage, the city's child welfare agency has agreed to stop the emergency placement of foster children in  group homes on Staten Island. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Crisis at a Pet Hospital</p>
        <p>The Animal Medical Center, a nine-story complex on East 62d Street, is facing "a very difficult fiscal crisis." The hospital reported an operating loss of $3  million last year, double that of five years ago, as a result of sharply rising  costs, an inability to push fees any higher and, most important, problems with people who do not paying their bills. [B1.]</p>
        <p>A Question of Privilege?</p>
        <p>As state legislators moved faster than a three-card monte player to override  the Governor's veto of a sensitive labor bill, they affirmed that New York's police officers and firefighters are special, deserving enhanced arbitration privileges even though Mayor Giuliani says the changes may break the bank. The way the police in particular have thrown their weight around in Albany raises the issue of just how special they think they are. NYC by Clyde Haberman. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Police Admit Error in Shooting</p>
        <p>The first thing Lebert Folkes says he wants to know is why Officer Christopher Strom, a nine-year police veteran, shot him after ordering him out of his car in front of his Queens home. Then, he says, he wants to know where to find a good lawyer.  "Obviously, an error was made by the New York City Police Department," the commander of Queens detectives said. [B3.]</p>
        <p>Editors, Authors and Joan</p>
        <p>The contract dispute between Random House and Joan Collins, the actress-author, sheds light on just how much editors -- unknown, uncelebrated -- often do to make their authors' books read well. Or at least sell well. Reporter's Notebook. [B3.]</p>
        <p>Arrest in Torah Burglaries</p>
        <p>A burglar who preyed on synagogues and a man accused of being his fence were  charged in the theft of at least $100,000 in sacred Torahs and other religious objects, the police said.  [B2.]</p>
        <p>Rohatyn Offers to Withdraw</p>
        <p>Felix G. Rohatyn, the New York investment banker who has lobbied heavily to get the No. 2 seat on the Federal Reserve Board, drafted a letter to President Clinton, withdrawing himself from consideration after concluding that his nomination would face insurmountable opposition from Senate Republicans, senior  Administration officials said. Business Day. [D1.]</p>
        <p>REGION</p>
        <p>Legislature Overrides Veto</p>
        <p>The New York State Legislature voted to override Governor Pataki's veto of a  bill that will help New York City's police and firefighters win larger pay raises, utterly rejecting the pleas of Mayor Giuliani and his ally on this issue, Mr. Pataki. [A1.]</p>
        <p>By overriding Governor Pataki's veto of the police bill, the Legislature seemed  to signal that it had little regard for Mayor Giuliani and his lobbying strategy in the capital. [B5.]</p>
        <p>History shows how difficult it is to override a veto in Albany. [B5.]</p>
        <p>Handling Engineers' Errors</p>
        <p>Seeking to prevent just the sort of collision that occurred on Friday in New  Jersey, Federal regulators imposed stiff penalties five years ago on violations  by railroad engineers, including the kind of error that put two blots on the record of one of the engineers killed Friday. [B1.]</p>
        <p>The usually bustling 7:58 New Jersey Transit local was a different trip on the first workday after a crash. Many regulars were conspicuously absent, leaving the others to wonder: Did they skip the train? Or did something happen to them in the crash? [B6.]</p>
        <p>Assault Rocks Hasidim</p>
        <p>A Hasidic mother of seven children who had been given an order of protection  from her husband was found lying in her bedroom, her face covered in blood. The  police are trying to question her estranged husband.  Although an arrest warrant has not been issued, the police described the case as attempted murder. [B6.]</p>
        <p>Man Charged as Peeping Tom</p>
        <p>A man described by the police in Mineola, L.I., as a "high-tech peeping Tom," was charged with burglary for breaking and entering with an electronic surveillance device. The police say he used a two-way mirror and video equipment to spy on a young female tenant. [B6.]</p>
        <p>Abuse Secrecy Laws Loosened</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki signed legislation to loosen laws requiring secrecy in child  abuse investigations. The measure had won overwhelming approval in both the Senate and the Assembly, despite civil-liberties advocates' complaints that it would violate privacy rights. [B5.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
