<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Girl Is Raped In Bias Case, Police Report</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="500420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLATBUSH (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLATLANDS (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB123AF936A25752C0A964958260" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Girl Is Raped In Bias Case, Police Report</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what the police have classified as a bias-related incident, a 15-year-old high school girl was abducted from a bus stop in the Flatbush-Flatlands section of Brooklyn yesterday morning, had her eyes taped shut and was driven to another location and raped, the police said.</p>
        <p>The case was deemed bias-related because ethnic remarks were used by the two abductors, the police said. The victim is white and the abductors are black.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what the police have classified as a bias-related incident, a 15-year-old high school girl was abducted from a bus stop in the Flatbush-Flatlands section of Brooklyn yesterday morning, had her eyes taped shut and was driven to another location and raped, the police said.</p>
        <p>The case was deemed bias-related because ethnic remarks were used by the two abductors, the police said. The victim is white and the abductors are black.</p>
        <p>Last night, after meeting with the victim's family, Mayor David N. Dinkins and Police Commissioner Lee P. Brown held a news conference at the 63d Precinct station house in Flatbush. Calling the incident "heinous" and referring to the assailants as "urban terrorists," the Mayor said the city would pay a $10,000 reward for information leading to the conviction of the attackers. The victim's father said he would match that reward. Rewards Are Offered</p>
        <p>The attack is another in a recent string of bias crimes that have stunned the city and once again strained race relations.</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins yesterday also announced $5,000 rewards for information in two bias cases in the Bronx, including the Jan. 6 attack on two black children who were sprayed with white liquid that appears to have prompted at least some of the incidents that followed.</p>
        <p>Inspector William Wallace, commander of the Police Department's citywide Bias Incident Investigation Unit, said it was "very unusual" for a rape to be classified as bias-related. In the 11-year history of his unit, the inspector said, there has never before been such a case.</p>
        <p>The authorities would not say what racial remarks were made during the attack. But the girl's father, a data processor for a company on Wall Street, said: "They threw her in the car, pressed her in the back seat and they said, 'We're taking you to see somebody.' She asked, 'Who are you taking me to see?' And then they proceeded to force her to remove her clothing and taped her eyes with black electrical tape. 'Why are you doing this to me?' she asked. And one of the men replied, 'Because you are white and perfect.'</p>
        <p>"And then one of them proceeded to ask, 'Have you kissed a black man before?' And she said, 'Yes.' "</p>
        <p>At his news conference, Mr. Dinkins, when asked if he was concerned about individuals or groups seeking revenge, said vigilantism "will not help the cause."</p>
        <p>"It is said that an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth will leave every one blind and toothless," he added.</p>
        <p>The attack began at 6:55 A.M. near East 38th Street and Avenue S in the Flatbush-Flatlands section, a police spokesman, Sgt. Nicholas Vreeland, said. The girl was waiting for a bus to take her to her high school, the sergeant said, when a black man, described as about 6 feet tall, heavily built and between 25 and 30 years old, approached her. Waiting Alone at Stop</p>
        <p>Commissioner Brown said at the news conference that the girl -- a sophomore honors student at Midwood High School -- had apparently missed her regular school bus and was waiting alone at the stop.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Vreeland said the man, who had a mustache and was wearing black jeans, a gray hooded sweatshirt and a black jacket with a hood, "engaged the girl in conversation."</p>
        <p>"What was said at that point, we don't know," he said.</p>
        <p>"The victim attempted to move on and the man grabbed her around the neck and stated he had a gun," the sergeant continued. "She never actually saw the gun." The girl was then forced into the rear seat of what turned out to be a rented, white Toyota Camry. The car had been stolen.</p>
        <p>"The victim's head was forced face down against the floorboards, so she couldn't see where she was going," Sergeant Vreeland said. "As the car was being driven, the suspect fondled her."</p>
        <p>Another man -- described as in his 20's, also about 6 feet tall, but of slighter build -- was driving the car and proceeded to another location, where the girl was forced to engage in sexual intercourse with one of the men, the sergeant said. She was sodomized as well as raped, he said.</p>
        <p>At about 8:15 A.M., the police said, the abductors released the girl at Flatlands Avenue and East 40th Street. From there, she telephoned her mother, who soon arrived and took her to a hospital. A Major Clue</p>
        <p>A major clue in the case came from the victim, who managed to memorize the license plate numbers of the car driven by her abductors before they pulled her into the car and taped her eyes, her cousin said.</p>
        <p>Using those numbers, the police traced the car to a rental agency. They then went to the agency and discovered that the car had been stolen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins said he would go to Albany to press for legislation that would increase penalties for people who commit bias-related crimes and crimes that involve two or more attackers. "All of us in some way or other have to find some way to deal with this senseless violence," he said.</p>
        <p>The police have set up a phone number, (718) 287-0311, for anyone with information about the case.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
