<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Re-enactment Tape Is Allowed in Officer's Trial</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="500414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOOTINGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIDEOTAPE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MANSLAUGHTER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TEANECK (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PANNELL, PHILIP C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPATH, GARY (POLICE OFFICER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Manslaughter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA153AF936A25752C0A964958260" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Re-enactment Tape Is Allowed in Officer's Trial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>HACKENSACK, N.J., Jan. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The judge in the manslaughter trial of a white Teaneck police officer accused of killing a black teen-ager in 1990 today accepted into evidence an unusual videotaped re-enactment that indicates that the victim's arms had been raised above his head at the moment the fatal shot was fired.</p>
        <p>The hourlong film provides the prosecution with a graphic, full-color tool to support at least three eyewitnesses who are expected to testify that the youth had his hands up when he was shot in the back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The judge in the manslaughter trial of a white Teaneck police officer accused of killing a black teen-ager in 1990 today accepted into evidence an unusual videotaped re-enactment that indicates that the victim's arms had been raised above his head at the moment the fatal shot was fired.</p>
        <p>The hourlong film provides the prosecution with a graphic, full-color tool to support at least three eyewitnesses who are expected to testify that the youth had his hands up when he was shot in the back.</p>
        <p>But for lawyers representing the officer, 31-year-old Gary Spath, the videotape poses a problem seldom encountered by defense lawyers in criminal cases in New Jersey. To the degree that it buttresses the prosecution's argument in a pivotal issue in the case -- the position of the youth's arms -- the tape offers visual refutation of Officer Spath's contention that the youth, Philip C. Pannell, was reaching for the handgun that was in his parka pocket when he was shot.  Use of Tape Denounced</p>
        <p>Officer Spath's lawyers, who argue that he shot in self-defense, objected vehemently to the tape's introduction during a two-day pretrial hearing that ended today in New Jersey Superior Court here. They denounced the tape as scientifically unreliable and irrelevant and, therefore, inadmissible as evidence.</p>
        <p>But Judge Charles R. DiGisi called the videotape an "absolutely valuable aid" to help the jury understand the testimony of the prosecution expert who prepared it -- Lucien C. Haag, a forensic scientist from Phoenix.</p>
        <p>Aides to New Jersey's Attorney General, Robert J. Del Tufo, said they believed it was the first time the state had used such a video as a tool to demonstrate evidence in a criminal prosecution.</p>
        <p>In the past, they said, videotapes have been most commonly used in court to show crimes in progress: bribes and pay-offs, environmental pollution and the release of hostages or kidnapping victims. In addition, the aides said, tapes have been used to re-enact auto crashes in civil and criminal cases.</p>
        <p>The shooting, which occurred on April 10, 1990, led to a night of street disorders in Teaneck and a deep split in the suburb's carefully cultivated image of racial harmony. The trial is viewed by many Teaneck residents as a test of the town's effort to repair that fabric.  An All-White Jury</p>
        <p>Opening arguments are scheduled for Wednesday morning. The case will be heard by an all-white jury of 11 men and 5 women -- a racial composition that had disturbed supporters of the Pannell family.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haag crafted the videotaped demonstration last July to determine what body movements would reproduce the circumstances of the shooting in which a single bullet pierced Mr. Pannell's bulky red parka and entered his back, just to the right of his left shoulder blade. A man matching Mr. Pannell's height and weight -- 5 feet 9 inches tall and 146 pounds -- was used. In the film, a white circle marked the hole in the parka and a red dot from a laser beam represented, on the parka, the location of the entry wound.</p>
        <p>When the model stood normally, with his hands at his sides, the bullet hole in the jacket was eight inches diagonally below the bullet hole in the victim's back. Mr. Haag's objective was to find the bodily stance in which the two holes were on top of each other. In one scene, when the model raised both arms nearly straight up and turned his upper torso slightly to the left, the patch and dot were only about an inch apart. In another scene, the same alignment occurred when only the left arm was raised.</p>
        <p>Officer Spath and his partner, Wayne Blanco, have said Mr. Pannell was reaching toward his left pocket and turning to his left when he was shot. When Mr. Haag had the model move in that manner, the white patch and red dot appeared to be about three inches apart.</p>
        <p>Officer Spath's co-counsel, Philip DeVencentes, ridiculed Mr. Haag's work as an "invidious home movie" and said judges have been cautious about admitting filmed reenactments in previous criminal cases.  Expert Witness Cited</p>
        <p>In his ruling, Judge DiGisi called the videotape "carefully prepared" and held that it was not intended to convey the actual circumstances of the shooting. He noted that another prosecution witness, Dr. Michael Baden, former Chief Medical Examiner of New York City, had testified here that Mr. Haag's "general procedure" was accepted within the forensic community, though Dr. Baden did not know of any other case in which this exact approach had been used. The judge also said reliability and relevance were questions for the jury to decide.</p>
        <p>Two defense experts, Henry C. Lee, chief forensic scientist for the Connecticut State Police, and Dr. Dominick J. DiMaio, a former Chief Medical Examiner of New York City, are expected to testify that the crime scene was too dynamic, with too much movement by principals, to permit an accurate re-enactment.</p>
        <p>In a victory for the defense this afternoon, Judge DiGisi rejected a prosecution effort to bar testimony from Mr. Pannell's friends that the youth had brandished a handgun in the afternoon, before a police dispatcher told Officer Spath of a resident's report of a youth with a gun near the shooting scene. The judge said that testimony showed that the youth had a gun and "did not hestitate" in removing it from his pocket. Excluding that information would be unfair to Officer Spath, Judge DiGisi said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
