<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>302 Queries for Simpson Panelists</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JURY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMPSON, O J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGOLICK, DAVID  ORENTHAL JAMES 'O J' SIMPSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jury System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DA1439F932A35753C1A962958260" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>302 Queries for Simpson Panelists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MARGOLICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARGOLICK, DAVID  ORENTHAL JAMES 'O J' SIMPSON;</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Do they own any special knives, like hunting knives or pen knives? Have they  ever seen O. J. Simpson on television selling orange juice or Hertz rental cars, and what kind of impression did he make? What do they think about the news media? About DNA evidence? About the level of racial discrimination in Southern  California? About Nicole Brown Simpson?</p>
        <p>Those questions, plus 296 others on topics like divorce, domestic violence and the stress of jury duty, are on the 80-page laundry list of questions completed by 304 potential jurors in Mr. Simpson's murder trial. From the answers they provide -- including their choice of words, spelling, punctuation,  penmanship, even whether they use a pen or a pencil -- opposing lawyers can begin to select the 12 men and women who will determine the defendant's fate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Do they own any special knives, like hunting knives or pen knives? Have they  ever seen O. J. Simpson on television selling orange juice or Hertz rental cars, and what kind of impression did he make? What do they think about the news media? About DNA evidence? About the level of racial discrimination in Southern  California? About Nicole Brown Simpson?</p>
        <p>Those questions, plus 296 others on topics like divorce, domestic violence and the stress of jury duty, are on the 80-page laundry list of questions completed by 304 potential jurors in Mr. Simpson's murder trial. From the answers they provide -- including their choice of words, spelling, punctuation,  penmanship, even whether they use a pen or a pencil -- opposing lawyers can begin to select the 12 men and women who will determine the defendant's fate.</p>
        <p>This could very well set a record," Robert Hirschhorn, a jury consultant in Galveston, Tex., said of the Simpson survey. "The DeLorean questionnaire was 50  pages, the Branch Davidian went about 80 questions over 18 pages, William Kennedy Smith was 15 pages and 94 questions, maybe 120 with subparts. They don't ask that many questions on the S.A.T. They are literally getting the book on that jury."</p>
        <p>The questionnaire was released late today by Judge Lance A. Ito after the last jury candidates filled it out. Judge Ito had put together the questionnaire after consultations with Mr. Simpson's defense team and prosecutors from the office of the Los Angeles County District Attorney.</p>
        <p>For the next two weeks, the opposing counsel will scrutinize the completed forms as if they were Rorschach inkblots, conducting separate, highly psychoanalytical searches for sympathizers. They may even put the questionnaires through sophisticated machinery that can read handwriting, organize data and cough out on demand those who, based on previously determined criteria, most closely approximate the ideal juror for their side.</p>
        <p>The forms will help lawyers frame the additional questions that they will ask jury candidates in one-on-one interviews scheduled to begin Oct. 12. And they will help weed out jurors who seek to cash in, like various knife salesmen, waiters and limousine drivers, on their sudden, accidental connection to the most widely followed murder trial in history.</p>
        <p>"What do you think about a juror writing about his/her experience on a case?" one question asks.</p>
        <p>Several questions deal with Mr. Simpson's fame before June 12, when the bodies of his former wife and a friend, Ronald L. Goldman, were found outside Mrs. Simpson's home in the Brentwood section of Los Angeles. Jury prospects are  asked whether they ever saw Mr. Simpson in person, on television, in movies like "Naked Gun 2 1/2," playing football or doing sports commentary. Then the questionnaire examines how their attitudes have changed since a wayward dog led  a neighborhood couple to the two bloody bodies.</p>
        <p>"What was your first reaction to hearing that O. J. Simpson was a suspect in  this case?" states another question. "Do you think you may find it more difficult to believe the evidence presented to you if it conflicts with your beliefs about O. J. Simpson?"</p>
        <p>The jury candidates are pressed for their impressions, if any, of various people in the case: Jose Camacho, who sold Mr. Simpson a knife before the killings; Allan Park, who drove Mr. Simpson to the airport soon after the murders; Mr. Simpson's house guest, Brian (Kato) Kaelin, and various waiters and bartenders at Mezzaluna, where Nicole Simpson ate dinner the night she died. Are the prospective jurors fans of the University of Southern California Trojans (Question 265) or the Buffalo Bills (No. 267)? Do they watch "Monday Night Football" (No. 269)?</p>
        <p>Question 154 concerns a 1989 incident in which Nicole Simpson called 911 for  protection against her husband, an event returned to 12 questions later: "Have you ever called the police on your spouse or significant other?"</p>
        <p>"Does the fact that O. J. Simpson excelled at football," Question 147 asks, "make it unlikely in your mind that he could commit murder? Why or why not?"</p>
        <p>Question 151 asks jury candidates whether they watched Mr. Simpson's now famous flight in the white Ford Bronco. No. 151A asks how long they watched; 151B wants to know what they think of what they watched. And No. 152 asks whether they actually watched any of the chase in person.</p>
        <p>For each side, certain issues will be red flags. For instance, jury prospects, particularly black prospects, who express skepticism of or hostility  toward law-enforcement authorities will be anathema to the prosecution. Similarly, defense lawyers are likely to veto candidates who say they have been  victims of domestic violence or who acknowledge any discomfort with interracial  marriage.</p>
        <p>But other insights may lurk between the lines. Word choice, Mr. Hirschhorn observed, is one factor. Mr. Simpson's preferred jurors, he said, should be more cerebral than visceral, more prone to poking holes and finding reasonable doubt  than to going with their gut. "I'd look for 'as I see it' instead of 'in my opinion,' and 'I think' rather than 'I feel,' unless they say, 'I feel O. J. Simpson is getting a raw deal,' and then I'd sign them up," he said.</p>
        <p>Amy Singer, a jury consultant in Miami, said other clues lay in the handwriting, the jury candidates' use of the allotted space, the choice of writing implement and even the color of ink. She recalled, for example, a potential juror in another case whose long answers partly obliterated the questions and were written in red. "You don't have to be Sigmund Freud to figure out this was an opinionated lady who would disregard whatever anybody said," she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Singer said Mr. Simpson's lawyers and his jury consultant, Jo-Ellan Dimitrius, should look for people who write distinctively, boldly and at length  -- qualities, she said, that suggest independence and intelligence. Both she and Mr. Hirschhorn said the Simpson lawyers should want jurors who write neatly and  without mistakes. People who insist on crossed t's and dotted i's in their own handwriting, they explained, will hold prosecutors to a similarly high standard.</p>
        <p>"Because the police officers' carelessness is an issue in this case, I would  look for someone who didn't misspell a single word and wrote legibly," Mr. Hirschhorn said. "Anyone who hurried through the questionnaire could relate to sloppy police work. They could also hurry through deliberations and find O. J. guilty."</p>
        <p>Ms. Singer said the defense should stay away from people whose script is timid and terse, although she warned that terseness could be common in responses to the questionnaire. So anxious are people to serve on the Simpson jury, she said, that even loquacious candidates will muzzle themselves.</p>
        <p>"Generally people are honest, because they sign their names under penalty of  perjury," she said. "But in this case, it's tough, tough, tough, because people  have an agenda. They want to be on this jury, so they're motivated to be very vanilla. Once they stick out, someone is going to scream."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
