<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weighing a New Murder Trial for Rabbi</title>
    <meta content="15RABB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/15/nyregion/15RABB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1343117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Fred J (Rabbi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Camden (NJ)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Neulander, Fred J</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3D9163BF936A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weighing a New Murder Trial for Rabbi</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Weighing a New Murder Trial for Rabbi</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>CAMDEN, N.J., Nov. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Day after mistrial is declared in case of Rabbi Fred J Neulander, prosecutors vow to press ahead with case, although several long-range issues remain unresolved before new trial begins on charges that rabbi arranged murder of his wife (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after a mistrial was declared in the case of Rabbi Fred J. Neulander, prosecutors vowed today to press ahead with the case, although several long-range issues remain unresolved before a new trial begins on charges that the rabbi arranged the murder of his wife.</p>
        <p>The questions include the site of a new trial, Rabbi Neulander's legal representation, and the end of the term of the Camden County prosecutor, Lee A. Solomon, who has directed the case since he was appointed in 1997; he leaves the post next June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAMDEN, N.J., Nov. 14  A day after a mistrial was declared in the case of Rabbi Fred J. Neulander, prosecutors vowed today to press ahead with the case, although several long-range issues remain unresolved before a new trial begins on charges that the rabbi arranged the murder of his wife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after a mistrial was declared in the case of Rabbi Fred J. Neulander, prosecutors vowed today to press ahead with the case, although several long-range issues remain unresolved before a new trial begins on charges that the rabbi arranged the murder of his wife.</p>
        <p>The questions include the site of a new trial, Rabbi Neulander's legal representation, and the end of the term of the Camden County prosecutor, Lee A. Solomon, who has directed the case since he was appointed in 1997; he leaves the post next June.</p>
        <p>The mistrial was declared on Tuesday because the jury was deadlocked on all three charges against Rabbi Neulander. Mr. Solomon said his office would again seek conviction on the same charges -- murder, felony murder and conspiracy -- and would ask a new jury to return the death penalty on grounds that in 1994 the rabbi, now 60, offered to pay an accomplice $30,000 to kill his wife, Carol, 52. ''Nothing about this case has changed,'' Mr. Solomon said on Tuesday after the mistrial was declared.</p>
        <p>The first discussions about a second trial will be held in a hearing scheduled for Dec. 10 before the trial judge, Linda G. Baxter of New Jersey Superior Court. But whether a second trial will start before Mr. Solomon's five-year term expires next June 27 is uncertain. Mr. Solomon is a Republican, and he has no guarantee that New Jersey's incoming governor, James E. McGreevey, a Democrat, will reappoint him. New Jersey governors customarily select county prosecutors from their own political party when openings occur.</p>
        <p>Should a new trial start before Mr. Solomon's term expires, it is considered likely that any new prosecutor would continue it. But if the trial does not start before Mr. Solomon leaves office, the decision to proceed will fall to his successor, said Greg Reinert, a spokesman for Mr. Solomon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solomon offered no hints on Tuesday about possible changes in strategy in a second trial, including relying again on its chief witness against the rabbi, Leonard Jenoff, 55, a recovering alcoholic who confessed in April 2000 to participating in Mrs. Neulander's murder and accused the rabbi of hiring him for $30,000 to commit the crime.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander's lawyers, Dennis Wixted and Jeffrey Zucker, portrayed Mr. Jenoff as a liar throughout the trial and argued that the state had little evidence against the rabbi except Mr. Jenoff's statement.</p>
        <p>The issues that troubled the jury and produced the deadlock after 43 hours of deliberation over seven days remained a mystery today. The panel's numerical split on the three charges also remained unknown publicly. In an unusual step, Judge Baxter issued a court order barring reporters from asking the jurors about their deliberations. The judge first issued the order in August.</p>
        <p>Last week, a lawyer for NBC, Carolyn P. Short of Philadelphia, filed a motion to end the prohibition, arguing that the First Amendment gave news organizations the right to contact jurors after the trial. But Judge Baxter rejected the motion today. She said she did so to protect Rabbi Neulander's rights to a fair trial in the future.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander's lawyers, Mr. Zucker and Mr. Wixted, argued in support of the ban on press contacts today. The trial prosecutor, James Lynch, took no position.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Zucker and Mr. Wixted said they planned to stay on as the rabbi's lawyers, at least through the Dec. 10 hearing. They also said they planned to start financial talks soon about representing him throughout a second trial. ''We're committed to our client,'' Mr. Zucker said.</p>
        <p>The lawyers declined to say whether they would ask that the second trial be transferred from Camden County.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander has been in jail, without bail, since he was indicted on the murder-for-hire charge, a capital offense, in June 2000. The two defense lawyers plan to ask Judge Baxter to set a bail during a hearing scheduled for Friday morning. Mr. Wixted said defendants in capital cases typically are not allowed bail if prosecutors can show a likelihood that they will be convicted and that the death sentence will be imposed.</p>
        <p>''If the state can't prove guilt in the first trial, how can they argue there's a reasonable prospect the death sentence will be imposed on a second trial?'' Mr. Wixted asked.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
