<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. JUDGE BLOCKS 25~ FARE INCREASE: SEES POSSIBLE BIAS</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="807823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS ANDVERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBWAYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPANISH-SPEAKING GROUPS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL RIGHTS ACT OF 1964</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBURBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ-PENA, RICHARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATTERSON, ROBERT P JR (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CONWAY, E VIRGIL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spanish Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DB1439F93AA35752C1A963958260" item-length="1534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. JUDGE BLOCKS 25~ FARE INCREASE: SEES POSSIBLE BIAS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEREZ-PENA, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ruling that the planned fare increases for the region's mass transit system appeared to discriminate against black and Hispanic riders in New York City, a Federal judge yesterday blocked a 25-cent increase in subway and bus fares that  was scheduled to take effect Sunday.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Transportation Authority quickly appealed the ruling, and the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit granted an emergency hearing, to be held today, on whether to reverse the order.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ruling that the planned fare increases for the region's mass transit system appeared to discriminate against black and Hispanic riders in New York City, a Federal judge yesterday blocked a 25-cent increase in subway and bus fares that  was scheduled to take effect Sunday.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Transportation Authority quickly appealed the ruling, and the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit granted an emergency hearing, to be held today, on whether to reverse the order.</p>
        <p>Even so, transit officials appeared to be hedging their bets. Yesterday afternoon, the Transit Authority, the arm of the M.T.A. that runs the city's subways and buses, stopped selling the new $1.50 tokens and began buying them back from riders.</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. chairman, E. Virgil Conway, warned in a statement that without the added $5.25 million a week the extra 25 cents was expected to bring in, there would be "deteriorating and increasingly unreliable service." But he and other M.T.A. officials did not offer specific proposals for coping with the loss of income.</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. board voted last month to increase the price of a token by 20 percent, to $1.50, while raising fares for the Metro-North commuter line and the Long Island Rail Road by an average of 9 percent. The New York Urban League and  the Straphangers Campaign, a riders' group, sued the M.T.A. and the state, which helps subsidize the authority, charging that the disparity violated the 1964 Civil Rights Act because a majority of transit riders in the city are black and  Hispanic, while suburban railroad users are overwhelmingly white.</p>
        <p>The Civil Rights Act says, in part, that no one, on the basis of race, can be "subjected to discrimination under any program or activity receiving Federal financial assistance," a description that fits the M.T.A. Courts have ruled that to win suits brought under the law, the plaintiffs do not have to show an intent to discriminate by race, only a racially discriminatory result.</p>
        <p>The preliminary injunction by Judge Robert P. Patterson Jr., of Federal District Court in Manhattan, created widespread uncertainty for millions of subway and bus riders. Some, unaware of his decision, continued to buy new tokens -- more than a million have been sold -- until sales were suspended about five hours after the ruling. With the M.T.A.'s appeal pending and with only four days remaining before the scheduled increase, it was anyone's guess whether passengers' best strategy would be to keep any new tokens they had or sell them  back.</p>
        <p>Still, transit officials, who in the last few weeks have removed large numbers of $1.25 tokens from circulation and in some cases limited the number of tokens passengers could buy, said they would replenish the supplies at stations  around the city.</p>
        <p>In the injunction, Judge Patterson said the plaintiffs had presented enough of a case to show that they were likely to succeed at trial, the legal standard  they had to meet to get a court order. "The plaintiffs have demonstrated a likelihood of success on the merits, and the defendants have not shown any legitimate nondiscriminatory justification or any business necessity for the fare increase as proposed," he wrote.</p>
        <p>The judge will hold a trial to settle the question, but unless the injunction is overturned on appeal, his ruling yesterday would bar the increase until then. The ruling does not affect commuter rail fares, which are still scheduled to rise on Sunday, though the majority of riders who use monthly passes would not see the increase until Dec. 1.</p>
        <p>In court papers and in a hearing last Thursday, the M.T.A. and the state argued that the plaintiffs were using the wrong measures to gauge the relative subsidies to the Transit Authority and the commuter railroads. And underlying their arguments about fairness was the contention that the state was free to distribute money according to purely political considerations, to favor one area over another, regardless of fairness.</p>
        <p>The ruling was met with elation -- and no small measure of surprise -- by the plaintiffs and their allies.</p>
        <p>"We had a rough chance," said Dennis M. Walcott, president of the New York Urban League. "I mean, we were really going uphill."</p>
        <p>Gene Russianoff, staff lawyer for the Straphangers Campaign, said: "My own view of this has been manic depressive, like, 'We're going to win, we're going to lose, we're going to win, we're going to lose.' "</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, one of the defendants, declined to comment on the substance of the ruling, saying only that there had been no intent to discriminate. "I expect the M.T.A. had plans in place to deal with this," he said.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani flirted publicly with the possibility of joining in the suit, then decided not to, saying that the city's lawyers considered the legal arguments weak and that he thought it wrong to inject race into the debate over fares.</p>
        <p>But yesterday the Mayor said: "I think it's the right result. I would like to see the fare hike held up so that the M.T.A. had more time to do restructuring so that either a fare increase could be avoided" or lessened.</p>
        <p>Riders, too, approved of the decision. "Glad to hear it," said Joe Sheldrick, an executive from Long Island who was waiting for a No. 3 train yesterday at Times Square. He was among those who bought 10-packs of the new tokens in anticipation of the fare increase.</p>
        <p>"I just try to make my life as convenient as possible," he said, "and I didn't want to stand in line for these new tokens. I guessed wrong in this one."</p>
        <p>Lawsuits like the one before Judge Patterson have been tried in a few other cities, with mixed results. An attempt to block a fare increase in Philadelphia  failed. But in Los Angeles last year, a judge issued an injunction prohibiting the county transportation authority from raising fares and eliminating discount  monthly passes for bus riders. In an interim settlement five months later, the fare increase was allowed but the monthly passes were saved pending the final outcome of the suit.</p>
        <p>In New York, the state cut aid to the Transit Authority this year by $86 million, while increasing it for every other public transportation system in the state. The state also took $220 million that had accumulated in an account fed by local and state taxes and had been earmarked for the M.T.A.</p>
        <p>And under Mr. Conway's financial plan for 1996 and beyond, the Transit Authority would take $125 million a year out of its operating fund and put it toward capital rebuilding costs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conway has defended the disparity in fare increases between the city transit system and the commuter railroads, saying that the subway and bus system was expected to end this year $45 million in the red and that it faced much larger budget deficits in future years than the commuter railroads.</p>
        <p>But Judge Patterson wrote that if it were not for the state's and the M.T.A.'s decisions on transit financing, "there would be no year-end deficit and no increase in fares would be required at this time."</p>
        <p>Various surveys and studies have estimated that between 54 and 60 percent of  the Transit Authority's riders are nonwhite, while more than 80 percent of the commuter railways' users are white.</p>
        <p>The plaintiffs asserted that the Transit Authority has 81 percent of the state's mass transit riders, but gets 63 percent of the state subsidies. They said city transit riders' fares pay 59 percent of the day-to-day operating costs for the subways and buses, compared to 52 percent at Metro-North and 44 percent  at the L.I.R.R., and the fare increase would push the city figure up to 69 percent.</p>
        <p>At last Thursday's hearing, Gary Caplan, the M.T.A. budget director, argued that the plaintiffs' calculation was inaccurate because it did not include interest payments, depreciation, police costs and other expenses. When those are factored in, he said, riders' share of the burden is similar on the city and suburban systems.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Caplan acknowledged that once the fare goes to $1.50, by his own calculations, city transit riders would pay 61 percent of the total costs, compared with 50 percent at Metro-North and 41 percent at the L.I.R.R. His testimony led one lawyer for the plaintiffs to quip that Mr. Caplan had been their best witness.</p>
        <p>If, after a trial, the fare increase is still blocked, the state and the M.T.A. would have several options. The M.T.A. could simply slash services to keep the fare down, or it could raise commuter railroad fares 20 percent to match the increase at the Transit Authority.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
