<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WELFARE DEBATE WILL RE-EXAMINE OLD ASSUMPTIONS</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="734596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD STAMPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Fitness and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Stamps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D8133BF931A35752C0A963958260" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WELFARE DEBATE WILL RE-EXAMINE OLD ASSUMPTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A great debate is about to begin over one of the major premises of America's social welfare policy: that low-income people are legally entitled to Government aid guaranteeing a minimum standard of living.</p>
        <p>Many of the Republicans who will take control of Congress on Wednesday contend that welfare, Medicaid and food stamps should be stripped of their status as open-ended "entitlements." Instead, they say, Congress should appropriate fixed amounts of money each year for those programs, whose size would no longer increase automatically when, for example, a recession put more people out of work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A great debate is about to begin over one of the major premises of America's social welfare policy: that low-income people are legally entitled to Government aid guaranteeing a minimum standard of living.</p>
        <p>Many of the Republicans who will take control of Congress on Wednesday contend that welfare, Medicaid and food stamps should be stripped of their status as open-ended "entitlements." Instead, they say, Congress should appropriate fixed amounts of money each year for those programs, whose size would no longer increase automatically when, for example, a recession put more people out of work.</p>
        <p>Neither Democrats nor Republicans are proposing significant changes in the largest entitlement program, Social Security, or withdrawing the entitlement status of Medicare, although the money spent on those two programs dwarfs the spending on welfare and food stamps.</p>
        <p>Instead, the battle lines have been drawn over the use of entitlements to guarantee a minimum standard of living for the poor. That struggle transcends the debate over specific Republican proposals that would, for example, increase the use of orphanages, impose stringent work requirements on welfare recipients and eliminate aid to the children of young unmarried women.</p>
        <p>Here is the outlook:</p>
        <p>*The Clinton Administration is reassessing the whole question of entitlements, is receptive to some changes and has not decided on a strategy for dealing with Republican proposals to restructure welfare.</p>
        <p>*Nonpartisan experts believe that Congress may, for the first time, limit Federal Medicaid spending, which has doubled in four years, reaching $82 billion in 1994. Medicaid provides health care for 33 million low-income people; Medicare finances health care for 36 million people who are elderly or disabled.</p>
        <p>*Congress will consider giving states a lump-sum payment, or block grant, to help poor people now entitled to benefits under the main cash welfare program, Aid to Families with Dependent Children. Block grants would be a radical departure because they would eliminate individual entitlement to benefits and would give states more flexibility in deciding how to use the money.</p>
        <p>*The food stamp program is perhaps the most secure of the major programs for poor people. House Republicans want to put it into a block grant with other food and nutrition programs, but they expect resistance because food stamps have support from a middle-class constituency that includes farmers, grocers and the food industry generally.</p>
        <p>The struggle will challenge Democrats, in the Administration and in Congress, to explain why entitlement programs were created and why they should be continued.</p>
        <p>Representative Christopher Shays, a Connecticut Republican on the Budget Committee, said: "We have to get these programs off autopilot. They should be subject to annual appropriations. Entitlements have taken away the power of the people, through Congress, to decide where money is spent each year." Congress would need more control over spending to comply with a proposed constitutional amendment that would require a balanced Federal budget, he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Democrats say the welfare and food stamp programs serve a valuable economic purpose, infusing money into a state when recession hits, unemployment rises and more families need assistance.</p>
        <p>Representative Sander M. Levin of Michigan, a member of the Ways and Means Committee who is trying to coordinate the Democratic strategy on welfare legislation, said he strongly believed that states should have more flexibility in designing programs, but he worried about Republican efforts to replace entitlement programs. "What would happen in times of recession?" he asked in an interview. "You can't repeal economic cycles."</p>
        <p>Another Democrat, Robert Greenstein, director of the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, said entitlement programs responded automatically to economic and demographic changes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shays countered, "That's a good argument, but in the process we're going bankrupt."</p>
        <p>In an entitlement program, the Government has a legal obligation to pay benefits to all applicants who meet criteria set by Federal law. The formulas for deciding who gets how much stay the same from year to year unless Congress votes to change them. If the demand for aid exceeds expectations, Congress must somehow come up with more money, by borrowing, raising taxes or cutting other items in the budget.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Congress appropriates specific amounts each year for discretionary spending programs, which include defense, medical research, law enforcement, Head Start and job training.</p>
        <p>Entitlement programs account for slightly more than half of all Federal spending, roughly $800 billion of $1.5 trillion last year. The large middle-class entitlements, Social Security and Medicare, which pay benefits regardless of financial need, dwarf the programs for low-income people -- the Government spent $475 billion on Social Security and Medicare in 1994, compared with $125 billion on Aid to Families with Dependent Children, food stamps and Medicaid. But Social Security, which both parties have found to be a volatile issue, is off the table, and Congress is not considering changing the entitlement status of Medicare.</p>
        <p>The roots of these programs run deep. Welfare, under the name Aid to Dependent Children, was part of the Social Security Act in 1935. President Lyndon B. Johnson signed the Food Stamp Act in 1964. Medicaid and Medicare were created in 1965.</p>
        <p>While committed to the overall goals of those programs, the Clinton Administration has not decided whether or how to defend their status as entitlements. White House officials are mulling that question as they prepare for a conference on welfare with governors and members of Congress from both parties in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said President Clinton, a former governor, was sympathetic to the governors' pleas for more flexibility in using Federal money.</p>
        <p>Asked if she would defend the entitlement status of welfare and Medicaid, Avis LaVelle, an Assistant Secretary of Health and Human Services, said: "No, I can't. There is a re-evaluation going on throughout the department as to the whole concept of entitlement programs. It's just not smart for us to take an advocacy position one way or another. The ground is shifting under our feet."</p>
        <p>Representative Levin said Democrats in Congress and the Administration had "no clear strategy" for dealing with the Republican proposals at this time. "It's important for us to develop one quickly," he said.</p>
        <p>Robert D. Reischauer, director of the Congressional Budget Office, said that if lawmakers wanted to slow the growth of welfare programs, they could do so without eliminating the entitlement to benefits. For example, he said, Congress could restrict eligibility or make benefits less generous. Such changes could save substantial amounts of money, but the Government would still have a legal obligation to pay benefits to any applicants who met the criteria.</p>
        <p>There is fierce competition for money among domestic programs, and it is likely to intensify this year. Current law imposes an annual limit on all discretionary spending through 1998, and President Clinton says he wants to maintain the ceiling at current levels in 1999 and 2000. Representative John R. Kasich of Ohio, the Republican in line to become chairman of the House Budget Committee, says he wants to reduce the spending limits.</p>
        <p>If a benefit program loses its status as an entitlement, it would have to compete with all the other domestic programs for money. And that, many Republicans say, is exactly what should happen.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
