<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON NOMINEES WILL BE SCREENED FOR ILLEGAL HIRING</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930210T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="589163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIDES AND EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATTORNEYS GENERAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL SECURITY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ILLEGAL ALIENS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND EMIGRATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOMESTIC SERVICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BABY SITTERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE (IRS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEPHANOPOULOS, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAIRD, ZOE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, RONALD H (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SKAGGS, DAVID E (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOOD, KIMBA M (JUDGE)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF113EF93AA35751C0A965958260" item-length="2677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON NOMINEES WILL BE SCREENED FOR ILLEGAL HIRING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All candidates for the hundreds of Government jobs subject to Senate confirmation are now being asked if they had hired illegal aliens or violated tax laws on household workers, Clinton Administration officials said today, and at least a dozen people have been dropped from consideration over those issues.</p>
        <p>Use of the new questions follows an uproar over the nomination of Zoe Baird to be Attorney General and the withdrawal of another candidate for the same job, Federal District Judge Kimba M. Wood of New York. George Stephanopoulos, the White House spokesman, said that in view of those events candidates for Presidential appointments in the Clinton Administration would probably be disqualified if they had hired illegal aliens in the last six years. New Standards Imposed</p>
        <p>The hiring of illegal aliens was prohibited by a law adopted in November 1986. Asked if President Clinton would appoint any people who have employed illegal aliens since then, Mr. Stephanopoulos said, "I think it would make it very difficult, and it would probably be disqualifying, yes." Administration officials said Mr. Clinton would probably not nominate individuals who hired illegal aliens before November 1986 because people would find it difficult to distinguish between the two situations in political debate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All candidates for the hundreds of Government jobs subject to Senate confirmation are now being asked if they had hired illegal aliens or violated tax laws on household workers, Clinton Administration officials said today, and at least a dozen people have been dropped from consideration over those issues.</p>
        <p>Use of the new questions follows an uproar over the nomination of Zoe Baird to be Attorney General and the withdrawal of another candidate for the same job, Federal District Judge Kimba M. Wood of New York. George Stephanopoulos, the White House spokesman, said that in view of those events candidates for Presidential appointments in the Clinton Administration would probably be disqualified if they had hired illegal aliens in the last six years. New Standards Imposed</p>
        <p>The hiring of illegal aliens was prohibited by a law adopted in November 1986. Asked if President Clinton would appoint any people who have employed illegal aliens since then, Mr. Stephanopoulos said, "I think it would make it very difficult, and it would probably be disqualifying, yes." Administration officials said Mr. Clinton would probably not nominate individuals who hired illegal aliens before November 1986 because people would find it difficult to distinguish between the two situations in political debate.</p>
        <p>The White House imposed the new standards three weeks after it had said that Ms. Baird's employment of illegal immigrants as household help should not disqualify her from becoming Attorney General. Mr. Clinton later withdrew the nomination under pressure from Capitol Hill and public opinion.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how the new standards will apply to people already in office. Current officeholders are being urged to comply with all relevant laws, Mr. Stephanopoulos said. He went on to say there was no reason for Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown to step down, even though Mr. Brown had said he failed to pay Social Security taxes for a household worker.  Under Criticism by Women</p>
        <p>Announcing the new test today, the White House seemed eager to rebut criticism of its decision to drop two women considered for Attorney General. The White House was also trying to counter accusations by women's groups like the National Organization for Women that it had been unfairly harsh on Ms. Baird and Judge Wood, or that there was a double standard working against women.</p>
        <p>The more rigid standards -- routinely violated by hundreds of thousands of families and enforced only sporadically by the Government -- apply to candidates for hundreds of powerful posts, most notably the assistant secretaries who run Cabinet agencies day to day.</p>
        <p>More than 1,100 Presidential appointments are subject to Senate confirmation, with about 680 being for full-time jobs. The rest are for boards and commissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephanopoulos did not say whether these candidates would automatically be disqualified if they had failed to pay Social Security taxes for household workers. But White House officials said questions about compliance with immigration and tax laws were now being routinely asked of all candidates for Cabinet and sub-Cabinet positions.</p>
        <p>So far, White House officials said, at least a dozen people have been dropped from consideration because their answers were deemed unsatisfactory. White House officials refused to identify the candidates, but said they had been considered for jobs at the Interior Department, the Treasury and the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>President Clinton said today that he had not used a double standard in disqualifying Judge Wood.</p>
        <p>"I think Judge Wood has been somewhat unfairly treated inasmuch as what happened to her happened in the ordinary course of the vetting process," Mr. Clinton said. "It's happened to many other people in the months that we have been working on this." He said all other nominations were being handled in an "even-handed" manner. Differences Are Noted</p>
        <p>Even as the White House announced the new standard, it was somewhat imprecise about the effect of the new rules. Mr. Stephanopoulos said the cases of Mr. Brown and Judge Wood "aren't comparable in any way."</p>
        <p>In describing his situation on Sunday on the NBC program "Meet the Press," Mr. Brown said, "I never employed any illegal aliens." But he said he did not pay Social Security taxes for a household employee until last month, when he said "most people found out that there was an obligation" to make such payments. The employee, he said, cleaned his home for three hours a week over the last four or five years.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baird, who employed two illegal aliens as household workers and failed to pay their Social Security taxes, asked the President to withdraw her nomination as Attorney General after a public furor. Judge Wood, who was on the verge of being nominated for the same job, was pressured into withdrawing after the White House learned that she had hired an illegal alien as a baby sitter in March 1986, although that was not illegal at the time.</p>
        <p>What is the distinction between Mr. Brown and Judge Wood? In the screening process for Presidential nominees, Mr. Brown was not asked about his compliance with immigration and tax laws. By contrast, Judge Wood was asked several times, and "she was not completely forthcoming," Mr. Stephanopoulos said.</p>
        <p>Judge Wood said that she was asked if she had a "Zoe Baird problem" and that she interpreted that to mean had she ever hired an illegal alien when it was against the law and not paid Social Security and other taxes for that worker, as Ms. Baird had. She said she had replied truthfully that she had not.  'Everybody Complies With It'</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephanopoulos said the new test was being applied impartially to all candidates of both sexes. "All people who are nominees now are being asked the question," he said. "Since we became aware of this situation, we are insuring that everybody complies with it."</p>
        <p>In deciding that the questions are relevant to all high-level Government positions, the Administration is going far beyond the criteria that the White House and Congress used in Ms. Baird's case.</p>
        <p>Critics of Ms. Baird said that violating the law disqualified her to be Attorney General, the nation's highest law enforcement officer, and that the hiring of an illegal alien was relevant because the Attorney General supervises the Immigration and Naturalization Service. But Ms. Baird committed only civil offenses, not a crime.</p>
        <p>Donald D. Roberts, a spokesman for the Internal Revenue Service, estimated that 75 percent, or 1.5 million, of the 2 million households that employ domestic workers fail to pay the required taxes.</p>
        <p>Some of those 1.5 million households include those of members of Congress. Representative David E. Skaggs, Democrat of Colorado, said: "After the Baird case, I was amazed to learn that parents owe Social Security taxes whenever they pay a baby sitter more than $50 in three months. This means I should have paid Social Security taxes on occasional baby-sitting for which I've paid, on average, a few hundred dollars a year. I'm in the process of computing the taxes and interest I owe and will pay that amount promptly."</p>
        <p>A 34-year-old White House aide said he thought he was coming to Washington to work on the President's domestic policy, but found to his dismay that he was spending more time answering questions about his own "domestics policy."</p>
        <p>Astrid E. Merget, chairwoman of the National Academy of Public Administration, a Congressionally chartered group of 350 government scholars, said the new test was "an overreaction in the wake of the Zoe Baird phenomenon."  Underground Child Care</p>
        <p>"Given the particular situation of most professional women and professional couples, it's probably common for people to hire child-care workers through the underground economy and not pay Social Security taxes," said Ms. Merget, a professor of public policy and management at Ohio State University, in Columbus. "That practice is troubling but common, and symptomatic of the problem of child care for working professionals."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephanopoulos said he did not know if Clinton appointees had complied with all tax and immigration laws in the past, but he promised that President Clinton would enforce compliance in the future. "The policy of the White House is very clear," he said. "All the Cabinet officers are supposed to comply with the law."</p>
        <p>G. Calvin Mackenzie, a professor of government at Colby College in Waterville, Me., who has studied the Presidential appointment process for many years, said he saw nothing inherently unreasonable in the new test.</p>
        <p>"It is reasonable to ask people if they've obeyed the law," he said. "But there is no objective standard of reasonableness here. Presidents live in a political world, and they have to play within the parameters of that world."</p>
        <p>"The reason the Senate has a role in this process is that the people who wrote the Constitution could not write an objective standard," said Mr. Mackenzie. "They left the Senate to be the judge of fitness. Nowadays that means that if you have domestic help, you better pay their Social Security taxes."</p>
        <p>Edward R. Meyers, program director of Citizens for Tax Justice, a coalition of labor unions and public interest groups, said: "It is not outrageous to expect people to abide by the law. Until the law is changed, people should comply with it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stephanopoulos said people who belatedly paid taxes for their maids might still, in some cases, qualify for Government jobs. "A lot of people were not aware of all the implications of the law relating to Social Security taxes prior to the Zoe Baird case," he said. "But now we are aware of it, and Cabinet officials are expected to comply."</p>
        <p>In response to inquiries by The New York Times, Clinton Administration officials and members of Congress generally said they had not knowingly hired illegal aliens in recent years. Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bensten "has never knowingly hired any illegal aliens," said his spokesman, H. Christopher Peacock.  Many Say They Complied</p>
        <p>Henry G. Cisneros, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, said he "did have occasional household help over the years." But he said, "We made sure they were properly documented and paid Social Security."</p>
        <p>Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt said he had felt a special obligation to obey tax and immigration laws because he was Attorney General of Arizona as well as its Governor.</p>
        <p>Carol M. Browner, the head of the Environmental Protection Agency, said she had never employed undocumented aliens, "never had any regular household help" and sent her 5-year-old son to community day-care centers.</p>
        <p>Donna E. Shalala, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, never had occasion to violate the law, an aide said, because her housing and household workers were provided to her by her last two employers: the University of Wisconsin at Madison, where she was chancellor, and Hunter College in New York, where she was president.</p>
        <p>Sam Bernsen, a lawyer who worked at the Immigration and Naturalization Service from 1939 to 1977, said tonight: "If an undocumented alien was hired before Nov. 6, 1986, clearly there was no violation of the law by the employer. It was not illegal, immoral or unethical. If the hiring occurred after Nov. 6, 1986, it was a violation of the law."</p>
        <p>"But this law is making lawbreakers out of hundreds of thousands of people who are otherwise law-abiding citizens," said Mr. Bernsen. CONGRESS AND ITS HOUSEHOLD HELP</p>
        <p>SENATE:</p>
        <p>Of 100 Senators, 89 responded through either their press secretaries or other aides to questions asked by the New York Times.  89 said the Senator had not employed any illegal alien since 1986.  88 said the Senator had never employed anyone without paying Social Security tax for the worker. The remaining Senator, Patty Murray, Democrat of Washington, said she had used numerous baby sitters over the years without paying Social Security taxes for them.</p>
        <p>Senate offices refused to answer the questions:</p>
        <p>Jeff Bingaman, New Mexico</p>
        <p>Dale Bumpers, Arizona</p>
        <p>Carl Levin, Michigan</p>
        <p>Ted Stevens, Alaska</p>
        <p>Senate offices did not returned several calls:</p>
        <p>Barbara Boxer, Democrat of California</p>
        <p>Alphonse A. D'Amato, Republican of New York</p>
        <p>Lauch Faircloth, Republican of North Carolina</p>
        <p>Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina</p>
        <p>John Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts</p>
        <p>Barbara A. Mikulski, Democrat of Maryland</p>
        <p>Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES:</p>
        <p>Of 435 Representatives, 406 responded to questionnaires, mainly through press secretaries or other spokesmen.</p>
        <p>406 said the Representative had not employed any illegal alien since 1986.</p>
        <p>398 said the Representative had never employed anyone without paying Social Security taxes for the worker.</p>
        <p>8 said 'Yes,' 'Don't know' or a qualified 'no' to the question of paying Social Security taxes:</p>
        <p>Tom Bevill, Democrat of Alabama: "Don't know." "Impossible to answer because over the years people have cut his grass or done yard work or baby sat for his children. Is the question addressed to these circumstances?"</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Furse, Democrat of Oregon: "Yes." She has a small farm and hires two 'contract' grape workers each year for two days; they take care of their own taxes.</p>
        <p>Nancy L. Johnson, Republican of Connecticut: "Yes." She employed someone who cleaned her house once every two weeks.</p>
        <p>Pete Peterson, Democrat of Florida: "Yes." Domestic help.</p>
        <p>J.J. Pickle, Democrat of Texas: "Yes." Occasionally he hires a housecleaner and is not sure if this exceeds the $50-a-quarter limit. He does not pay Social Security taxes on these wages.</p>
        <p>David E. Skaggs, Democrat of Colorado: "Yes." Mr. Skaggs faxed the following response: "After the Baird case, I was amazed to learn that parents owe Social Security taxes whenever they pay a baby sitter more than $50 in three months. This means I should have paid Social Security taxes on occasional baby sitting for which I've paid on average a few hundred dollars a year. I'm in the process of computing the taxes and interest I owe and will pay that amount promptly."</p>
        <p>Olympia J. Snowe, Republican of Maine: "No." She has hired 'LBJ' interns without withholding Social Security taxes, but she did not think this was a violation of House rules.</p>
        <p>Maxine Waters, Democrat of California: "Yes." "Twenty-five or 30 years ago when I had kids my neighbors worked as baby sitters"</p>
        <p>9 Representatives' offices refused, for various reasons, to answer the questions:</p>
        <p>Peter Hoagland, Democrat of Nebraska: "We don't respond to surveys."</p>
        <p>David L. Hobson, Republican of Ohio: Refusal</p>
        <p>Paul E. Kanjorski, Democrat of Pennsylvania: "We don't do surveys of any kind."</p>
        <p>John W. Olver, Democrat of Massachusetts: 'We don't participate in polls from organizations outside our district."</p>
        <p>David R. Obey, Democrat of Wisconsin: Usually does not participate in surveys.</p>
        <p>Nydia M. Velazquez, Democrat of New York: Refusal</p>
        <p>Robert S. Walker, Republican of Pennsylvania: Office policy is not to respond to polls.</p>
        <p>Craig Washington, Democrat of Texas: "I don't think that's anyone's business even if I did. That's not the way the nation is governed."</p>
        <p>Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California: Does not participate in surveys.</p>
        <p>18 offices have not responded:</p>
        <p>Herbert H. Bateman, Republican of Virginia</p>
        <p>Xavier Becerra, Democrat of California</p>
        <p>Anthony C. Beilenson, Democrat of California</p>
        <p>George E. Brown Jr., Democrat of California</p>
        <p>Richard J. Durbin, Democrat of Illinois</p>
        <p>Bob Filner, Democrat of California</p>
        <p>Richard A. Gephardt, Democrat of Missouri</p>
        <p>Henry B. Gonzalez, Democrat of Texas</p>
        <p>Bill Gradison, Republican of Ohio</p>
        <p>Ralph M. Hall, Democrat of Texas</p>
        <p>Alcee L. Hastings, Democrat of Florida</p>
        <p>William J. Jefferson, Democrat of Louisiana</p>
        <p>Jay C. Kim, Republican of California</p>
        <p>William O. Lipinski, Democrat of Illinois</p>
        <p>William H. Natcher, Democrat of Kentucky</p>
        <p>Nancy Pelosi, Democrat of California</p>
        <p>Bill Thomas, Republican of California</p>
        <p>Sidney R. Yates, Democrat of Illinois</p>
        <p>2 House seats are open.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 10, 1993, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the screening of Clinton Administration job candidates to determine if they had hired illegal immigrants or violated household employment tax laws referred incompletely in some copies to the most recent candidate for Attorney General. She is Judge Kimba M. Wood.</p>
        <p>Because of another editing error, the article also referred ambiguously to Judge Wood's tax history. She did pay such taxes for her domestic help.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 10, 1993, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the screening of Clinton Administration job candidates to determine if they had hired illegal immigrants or violated household employment tax laws referred incompletely in some copies to the most recent candidate for Attorney General. She is Judge Kimba M. Wood.</p>
        <p>Because of another editing error, the article also referred ambiguously to Judge Wood's tax history. She did pay such taxes for her domestic help.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
