<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Readies a Made-for-TV Convention</title>
    <meta content="08TEEV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="POLITICS: THE CONVENTION" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="870250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: THE CONVENTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7D9153EF93BA3575BC0A960958260" item-length="1459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Readies a Made-for-TV Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Aug. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans plan upcoming four-day National Convention in San Diego to maximize favorable television exposure; join communications technology to new sophistication about network news, infomercials and entertainment in planning tightly disciplined, fast-paced television variety show; paradox is that Bob Dole, more than any other major-party candidate in recent memory, disdains set pieces of television politics; question remains whether networks will broadcast much of it for them; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Planning even for the networks' commercial breaks, Republicans here have scripted a four-day political television program, which they are calling a convention. Now the question is whether the networks will broadcast it for them.</p>
        <p>For at least two decades, the high points of political conventions have been foregone conclusions, plotted as much for television viewers as for the delegates. This year, though, the delegates themselves seem like afterthoughts, or perhaps props. The Republicans have joined communications technology to new sophistication about network news, infomercials and entertainment to plan a tightly disciplined, fast-paced television variety show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Planning even for the networks' commercial breaks, Republicans here have scripted a four-day political television program, which they are calling a convention. Now the question is whether the networks will broadcast it for them.</p>
        <p>For at least two decades, the high points of political conventions have been foregone conclusions, plotted as much for television viewers as for the delegates. This year, though, the delegates themselves seem like afterthoughts, or perhaps props. The Republicans have joined communications technology to new sophistication about network news, infomercials and entertainment to plan a tightly disciplined, fast-paced television variety show.</p>
        <p>''Instead of putting on a news event they hope the networks will cover, they have come to the point where they're putting on a TV program, hoping they can get much of it past TV journalists, unfiltered,'' said Tom Hannon, the political director for CNN.</p>
        <p>The paradox is that the Republicans have planned all this for the greater glory of Bob Dole, who, more than any other major-party candidate in recent memory, disdains the scripts and the set pieces of television politics.</p>
        <p>From his skybox facing the podium, Paul J. Manafort, the political consultant who has masterminded  convention preparations for Mr. Dole, will have direct telephone lines to the officials on the platform, to keep them moving through their brief, tightly scheduled speeches. He will also have direct lines to each state delegation.</p>
        <p>''I want to move Governor Whitman from New Jersey over to California, so that CBS can do a picture,'' Mr. Manafort said by way of example, waving toward the floor while touring his box this afternoon. ''I'll ring down, she'll get the message, we'll have somebody there to escort her.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the customary challenge of whipping delegates into line, Mr. Manafort added, ''If there are any political issues, which there won't be in this convention, I'll also have the capacity to do that from here.''</p>
        <p>Such thorough programming is risky. By planning so carefully and transparently, the planners could prompt restless journalists to pounce on any deviation from the program, like delegates' grumbling  over abortion.</p>
        <p>''They just need to keep in mind,'' said Mr. Hannon, of CNN, ''that we're producing our coverage and they're not, and they're managing their convention and we're not.''</p>
        <p>But the planners are managing their convention for Mr. Hannon's audience. In a reflection of how little emphasis has been placed on those actually attending the convention,  the cramped hall here is, as one Republican official put it, ''the worst place in America to watch it.'' More than 7,000 Republicans with convention passes are expected to sit in rooms outside the hall and watch the proceedings on television.</p>
        <p>From the platform itself, Haley Barbour, the Republican national chairman, will be able to monitor coverage of the proceedings on a five-inch RCA set mounted in his desk.</p>
        <p>The gray, muslin-covered podium is flanked by 15-foot-square ''video walls,'' which will offer carefully produced presentations of speakers  and scenes from across America.  Convention planners want those screens to function like Trojan television sets: they hope the networks will happily haul the video presentations into living rooms nationwide, so that millions of viewers will watch what the delegates watch.</p>
        <p>The networks say they have no intention of simply retransmitting what Mr. Barbour has taken to calling ''a festival of Republican ideas.''</p>
        <p>''We're not there to be an unmediated conduit for their promotions,''  said Jeff Gralnick, vice president of ABC News and executive producer of that network's convention coverage.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Manafort predicted that the networks would carry many video presentations, saying those videos were integral to the convention's messages. ''There's a moral responsibility to at least allow us to communicate with the American people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Network producers say they have a public-interest duty to convey the kickoff of the Presidential campaign to the public. The networks fulfill that duty with thorough coverage of both parties' conventions, ''to help people to form opinions in choosing their President,'' said Steve Jacobs, executive producer of special events for CBS News.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Jacobs said it was ''longstanding CBS policy not to carry the infomercials, like the eight-minute biographies that parties make of their candidates.'' He said he hoped to get advance copies of the Republicans' videos, to evaluate each for news value.</p>
        <p>For example, Mr. Jacobs is eager  to review a videotape about Ronald Reagan, planned for showing in the hall at the convention's opening session, on Monday night. The public has seen so little of Mr. Reagan recently, he said, that ''it probably represents news'' and is ''not a political commercial.''</p>
        <p>Having studied the practices of network news, the Republicans have included some video presentations that they expect the networks not to carry. That filler material is intended to provide time for commercials and such.</p>
        <p>''We analyzed television coverage of the conventions over the last 20 years,'' Mr. Manafort said, ''and there is a pattern as to when the anchors would be on the air, when they would do cut-aways to commercials, when they would go to correspondents on the convention floor. It averages about 15 to 16 minutes'' an hour.</p>
        <p>In between, Mr. Manafort has scheduled 45 minutes an hour of programming he wants the networks to feature.</p>
        <p>While convention planners have long worried about television angles and whether delegates' signs should look homemade, conventions until now abided by some pre-television rituals. That meant long-winded speeches that pushed the schedule so late that notable speakers -- the nominee, say -- were addressing prime-time viewers only in Guam.</p>
        <p>This time the Republicans have not only selected a roster of moderate speakers, many of them women, but also limited almost every speechmaker to less than five minutes. Each speaker is to address one subject, as part of an 8-to-12-minute  ''issues segment'' on that topic, whether crime, welfare or some other matter.</p>
        <p>To insure that the message gets out unfiltered, the Republicans are covering their convention with their own cable production company. The coverage will be shown on two cable networks: the Family Channel and the USA Network. Those telecasts are being paid for by the San Diego Convention and Visitors Bureau,  partly with $1.3 million from the Amway Corporation.</p>
        <p>But much of the fare is also likely to prove irresistible to the other networks, said Roderick P. Hart, professor of communications and government at the University of Texas at Austin. ''What would television want but good television?'' Professor Hart said. ''It will be attracted to the bauble.''</p>
        <p>POLITICS: THE CONVENTION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
