<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Human Sharks Feeding in an Animated Hollywood Aquarium</title>
    <meta content="19gate" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/19/arts/television/19gate.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1695763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greg the Bunny (Tv Program)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hopeless Pictures (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5D7133EF93AA2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Human Sharks Feeding in an Animated Hollywood Aquarium</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Human Sharks Feeding in an Animated Hollywood Aquarium</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates reviews premiere of IFC animated television series Hopeless Pictures and Greg the Bunny; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The danger in making a television show about unlikable people is that viewers will find them unlikable, too. The trick is to make viewers want to spend time with them anyway. Bob Balaban partly succeeds with ''Hopeless Pictures,'' the undeniably clever animated series that begins tonight on IFC.</p>
        <p>As the premiere episode begins, Mel Wax (the voice of Michael McKean), head of Hopeless Pictures, is on the freeway and on his cellphone, talking (through the magic of what must be four-way call-waiting) to his psychiatrist, his wife, a publicist and Isaac Mizrahi, who wants to make a movie of the Liza Minnelli-Chita Rivera stage musical ''The Rink.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>IFC's undeniably clever animated series features unlikable people from Hollywood that viewers may want to spend time with anyway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The danger in making a television show about unlikable people is that viewers will find them unlikable, too. The trick is to make viewers want to spend time with them anyway. Bob Balaban partly succeeds with ''Hopeless Pictures,'' the undeniably clever animated series that begins tonight on IFC.</p>
        <p>As the premiere episode begins, Mel Wax (the voice of Michael McKean), head of Hopeless Pictures, is on the freeway and on his cellphone, talking (through the magic of what must be four-way call-waiting) to his psychiatrist, his wife, a publicist and Isaac Mizrahi, who wants to make a movie of the Liza Minnelli-Chita Rivera stage musical ''The Rink.''</p>
        <p>Mel has problems. Last night's screening of the film ''Dirty Feet'' was a disaster, the crazy Swedish director of a Hopeless film being shot in Zagreb is way over budget, and his wife (Lisa Kudrow) has found lingerie in his car. He tells Dr. Stein (Jonathan Katz, formerly of ''Dr. Katz, Professional Therapist'') about these developments while he juggles the other calls.</p>
        <p>He tries to convince his wife that the undergarment is a gift for her and the letter she found from Jessica is really a movie pitch by a male writer who uses a female nom de plume. Mel tells Mr. Mizrahi he'll ''set something up.'' And he praises the publicist (Peggy Siegel, the real-life publicist doing a voice cameo as herself) for her brilliant idea for the next screenings.</p>
        <p>And all of this happens before Mel breaks a molar and moves heaven and earth to get an appointment with the celebrity dentist of the moment, Dr. Glimmerglass. The one person who may be able to make that happen, unexpectedly, is Sam (Mr. Balaban), the ''idiot nephew'' on Mel's payroll.</p>
        <p>Hollywood is a killer environment, and death is as arbitrary in ''Hopeless Pictures'' as on ''Six Feet Under.'' The three in the premiere episode all take place in the background of other scenes: Dr. Stein's patient goes out a high-rise window, the star of the Zagreb film throws a small dog against a wall and Peggy Siegel's houseboy is eaten by a shark.</p>
        <p>The likability factor is upped by Traci, one of Mel's six-figure-salaried executives, who also consults Dr. Stein constantly. She's happy with her Scarlett Johansson haircut, sculptured eyebrows, collagen job and new breasts (''I've been getting a lot of compliments on them'') and just wonders if she should sleep with the writer she's about to have lunch with.</p>
        <p>The writer turns out to be pitching ''Death of a Saleslady,'' a murder mystery set at Bloomingdale's. He's fully aware of the title's similarity to another work. ''There might be references to the Arthur Miller play, of course, which I'm dying to read,'' he says. ''I've heard that it's incredible.''</p>
        <p>Traci (the impossibly perfect Jennifer Coolidge) doesn't read, she says. But she's pretty sure that Arthur Miller is still around and is Ann Miller's husband.</p>
        <p>''Hopeless Pictures'' runs 20 minutes. The half-hour is filled out by the welcome return of ''Greg the Bunny'' to prime time, Greg being a scruffy but fabulous puppet with the voice of Dan Milano.</p>
        <p>Greg's 2002 Fox series didn't work out well, possibly because his puppet brilliance was immersed in contrived situations and surrounded by largely unnecessary puppet companions. So he has gone back to what he does best: movie parodies.</p>
        <p>Tonight's is ''Bunnie Hall,'' in which Greg plays the Woody Allen role. ''I've been very sad since I broke up with Petunia,'' he tells the camera. ''If only I could go back in flashbacks and watch it all unfurl before my eyes.''</p>
        <p>Greg has Mr. Allen's voice and style down pat. And with his button eyes, unmoving mouth, expressive paws and ever-present tremble, he gets away with jokes like: ''I have a strict rule. I'm not dating marionettes. There's too many strings attached.'' (The best-friend Tony Roberts character, played by Warren the Ape, has just offered to fix him up.)</p>
        <p>It is a little strange that during the lobster-at-the-beach-house scene in ''Bunnie Hall'' our hero tosses his girlfriend into the pot and falls in love with the lobster instead. He and the lobster have picturesque urban dates and strange sex, but to be true to herself, she must return to the sea. And he can never leave New York.</p>
        <p>Hopeless Pictures  IFC, tonight at 10, Eastern and Pacific times; 9, Central time.</p>
        <p>Directed, produced and written by Bob Balaban; Adam Kassen and Mark Kassen, producers; for IFC, Debbie DeMontreux and Evan Shapiro, executive producers; Susan Heimbinder, supervising producer.</p>
        <p>WITH: Michael McKean (Mel Wax), Jennifer Coolidge (Tracy/Nina Boroslova), Jonathan Katz (Dr. Stein), Bob Balaban (Sam) and cameos by Lisa Kudrow, Isaac Mizrahi and Peggy Siegel.</p>
        <p>Greg the Bunny  IFC, tonight at 10:20, Eastern and Pacific times; 9:20, Central time.</p>
        <p>Dan Milano, Spencer Chinoy and Sean Baker, creators. Debbie DeMontreux and Evan Shapiro, executive producers; Jessica Wolfson, supervising producer.</p>
        <p>WITH: Dan Milano (Greg the Bunny) and Warren DeMontague (Warren the Ape).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
