<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fresh Air Fund's Treat: 2 Weeks at Beach</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="760867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRESH AIR FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARUOLO, JOSEPH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARUOLO, LOUISE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PULITZER, LISA BETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDE133DF934A35756C0A963958260" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fresh Air Fund's Treat: 2 Weeks at Beach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BETH PULITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PULITZER, LISA BETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE many Manhattanites, Eric Thomas looks forward to spending his two-week vacations at his summer home on Long Island, where he can ride his bicycle to the beach, soak up the sun and run barefoot through the sand.</p>
        <p>He does not own a home. Nor does he rent a share in a glamorous Hamptons beach house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE many Manhattanites, Eric Thomas looks forward to spending his two-week vacations at his summer home on Long Island, where he can ride his bicycle to the beach, soak up the sun and run barefoot through the sand.</p>
        <p>He does not own a home. Nor does he rent a share in a glamorous Hamptons beach house.</p>
        <p>Eric is a Fresh Air Fund youth from East Harlem. And for four years he has visited the Paruolo family at their house in Oyster Bay Cove.</p>
        <p>When he first arrived at the two-story brick colonial in July 1991, the 14-year-old said that he was a little nervous. But after a few days Eric felt at ease eating ham-and-cheese sandwiches, playing video games and discussing mathematics with the Paruolos' children, Derek and Stephanie.</p>
        <p>"Basically, I would say that Eric just makes himself at home," said Joseph Paruolo, a retired biology teacher from East Meadow High School who is an interior decorator.  "I think he's grown three inches in the last six months. When he got off the train I didn't recognize him at first."</p>
        <p>He and his wife, Louise, have participated in the Fresh Air Fund for 15 years. Before Eric, the couple sponsored other children, including two sisters who continue to stay in touch with the family. But the Paruolos said they have a special attachment to Eric, who not only visits for two weeks every July, but also spends New Year's Eve and winter weekends at their home.</p>
        <p>"He just fit right in," Mrs. Paruolo, a travel agent, said. "He has a very good personality and he's a lot of fun. He got very comfortable very quickly. We didn't feel like we had to entertain him. We do the same things we always do, but they feel more special when he's with us."</p>
        <p>Derek, 13, said when Eric first arrived, he went out of his way to plan activities that they could enjoy together. But the boys quickly realized that it was all right to do some things on their own.</p>
        <p>"Now, we're like brothers," Derek, a seventh grader at Vernon Middle School in Oyster Bay, said. "We do our own stuff sometimes. If I'm out on my bike he might be inside playing video games."</p>
        <p>Stephanie, who is younger, said she liked to race on bicycles and watch movies with Eric.</p>
        <p>Fresh Air host families open their homes to disadvantaged children for two weeks or more every July.  "Families come in all different configurations, and everyone is eligible," said Jenny Morgenthau, executive director of the fund.</p>
        <p>The fund began in 1877, when the Rev. Willard Parsons, a minister in Sherman, Pa., asked his congregation to provide country vacations for children from New York tenements.</p>
        <p>More than 10,000 children enjoy the free programs yearly. They are selected on the basis of financial need. All are from low-income families, with most receiving welfare.</p>
        <p>This year close to 7,000 children will visit host families in rural and suburban areas across 13 states, from Virginia to Maine. About 2,900 children will attend five Fresh Air camps on a 3,000-acre site in Fishkill, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Two hundred families in Nassau and Suffolk will be hosts for Fresh Air Fund children this summer. But Mrs. Paruolo, a volunteer leader for the fund, said more families were needed.</p>
        <p>"There is an overabundance of kids and not enough families to host them," she said. "If you have a couple of kids, one more child is not a problem."</p>
        <p>For Eric, the best part about visiting Long Island is summer camp at East Woods School in Oyster Bay, which he free. This year he hopes to become a counselor in training.</p>
        <p>"I try to get a lot of people from my neighborhood to sign up for the Fresh Air Fund," said Eric, who has persuaded a cousin to join. "It's not as noisy out on Long Island as it is in my neighborhood."</p>
        <p>Eric, a ninth grader at Intermediate School 44 on West 77th Street in Manhattan, said that after high school he would like to attend a police academy on Long Island.</p>
        <p>There are no financial requirements for to be a host family. Most families simply want to share their homes. Hosts can state their preferences on sex and age of the children whom they wish to sponsor. The fund also has a program for placing children who have special physical or emotional needs.</p>
        <p>The fund depends primarily on contributions. Donations may be sent to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10018. Families who would like to be hosts can call (800) 367-0003.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
