<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="761063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENT STABILIZATION CODE (NYS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROZHON, TRACIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D61230F934A35756C0A963958260" item-length="2670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline/>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROZHON, TRACIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Pam and Kevin Wolf spent $250,000 to completely renovate their rent-stabilized three-bedroom duplex apartment on Park Avenue six years ago, some of their friends questioned their sanity.</p>
        <p>"They told us we were crazy to spend that much money fixing up a rental," Mrs. Wolf said, gazing across the grand gallery the couple created -- and which they will vacate in August. "But we planned on staying here for at least 20 years. Everybody else who lives here has been here that long. And we thought, where else could we get a 2,800-square-foot duplex on Park Avenue for $250,000?"</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Pam and Kevin Wolf spent $250,000 to completely renovate their rent-stabilized three-bedroom duplex apartment on Park Avenue six years ago, some of their friends questioned their sanity.</p>
        <p>"They told us we were crazy to spend that much money fixing up a rental," Mrs. Wolf said, gazing across the grand gallery the couple created -- and which they will vacate in August. "But we planned on staying here for at least 20 years. Everybody else who lives here has been here that long. And we thought, where else could we get a 2,800-square-foot duplex on Park Avenue for $250,000?"</p>
        <p>But the Wolfs guessed wrong. Rent controls for apartments renting for $2,000 or more a month that are occupied by tenants whose household income was more than $250,000 for two years running were effectively lifted in 1993. For tenants of such apartments who either voluntarily acknowledge they make that much money or are found to make that much, the choice is unpleasantly clear: either move out, stay temporarily through a series of appeals and delays, or try to negotiate a deal with the owner.</p>
        <p>For those who move out, finding a comparable apartment at a price near to what they were paying is close to impossible, according to real-estate brokers who cite the hot rental market as one factor. For some grand eight- or nine-room prewar apartments that may have rented for several thousand dollars to rent-regulated tenants, market rents may now be "way over $10,000, maybe $15,000 a month," said Dolly Lenz, Sotheby's top-selling agent.</p>
        <p>Cathy Blau, a broker on the Upper West Side, cited the case of one older couple whose rent skyrocketed. "They had a three-bedroom, three-bath apartment in a great prewar," she said. "Now they're looking at a one- or two-bedroom with one-and-a-half baths in a postwar in an entirely different location. They're scaling down everything." Ms. Blau said she had suggested to families with children in private schools that they look at houses in Riverdale.</p>
        <p>In TriBeCa, Barrie Mandel of the Corcoran Group said that one couple to whom she is currently showing apartments could have bought the 3,000-square-foot loft they are now renting back in 1980 or 1981 for $50,000. They gambled, and kept paying the rent, which has risen to over $2,000. "The rent will now shoot up to $5,000 a month," Ms. Mandel said. "If they bought it then -- with the tax deductions -- they would have paid the equivalent of maybe six months rent." If they want to buy their loft now, it's on the market for $895,000.</p>
        <p>Throughout Manhattan, where most of the decontrol is taking place, deals are being made. Some landlords in buildings that have been converted to co-ops and condominiums, but in which some apartments are still occupied by rent-regulated tenants, are offering to sell apartments to well-off renters at less than market prices. If that fails, sometimes they offer cash incentives to leave, according to high-end brokers like Ms. Lenz, who says that 30 percent of her sales in the last nine months have been to "luxury-decontrol people."</p>
        <p>AT 40 Central Park South and its sister building, at 41 West 58th Street, both of which were constructed in the 1940's, 18 of 200 apartments were decontrolled because of the high-rent, high-income decontrol law. Tenants in 15 of the apartments have already negotiated higher rents. Neither side will give specific numbers, but the landlord said the deals were a compromise between the old rent and the market rent.</p>
        <p>The landlord, H. Dale Hemmerdinger of ATCO Properties, said that as a result of the decontrol of the apartments, he would spend $8 million on renovations and was using his prediction of more forced vacancies in the coming years to borrow from banks. "We're fighting over the timetable," he said, "because nobody really knows exactly how many apartments will turn over in a given year." He estimated there would be at least 10 a year in the buildings.</p>
        <p>In one complicated negotiation involving 20 apartments at a magnificent old landmark building on the Upper West Side, tenants negotiated a "lifetime tenancy" deal with the landlord, according to the group's lawyer. The rents will be keyed to existing rents but will rise by amounts negotiated between the landlord and the tenants hit or likely to be hit by the decontrol provisions.</p>
        <p>In other buildings, landlords have given tenants 5- or 10-year leases at a compromise rent. "Say if they were paying $2,500 and the market is $5,000, they'll start at $3,500 or $4,000, to be brought up to market over the time of the lease," said Samuel J. Himmelstein, a Manhattan lawyer who frequently represents tenants. Mr. Himmelstein said he was not talking about the half-dozen luxury decontrol cases his firm was handling, but cases he had been told about.</p>
        <p>While 869 decontrol orders had been issued by April 28, notifying renters that their apartments are no longer subject to rent regulation -- rulings that may be appealed -- an untold number of renters "saw the writing on the wall," as one tenant put it, and left.</p>
        <p>Although no governmental agency is tracking these people, real estate brokers report they are showing up in ever-increasing numbers at open houses and making appointments to view co-ops and condos. One such couple, a plastic surgeon and his lawyer wife, bought a carriage house on the Upper East Side, one broker said. The surgeon will use the downstairs for his office, perhaps even reducing his monthly expenses.</p>
        <p>Some of these tenants say that they are unable to buy. Mary Vetri, a rental agent for William B. May's downtown office, said many affected young people were not moving from their old apartments, even though the rent will rise. "They'll stay because they're in a bind: they're making a lot of money, but they don't have any down payment to buy," Ms. Vetri said.</p>
        <p>She said that many such renters are "young Wall Street types" who may have rented an apartment for $2,100 a month a couple of years ago and whose rent has risen to a market level of perhaps $2,400, nothing like the huge increase that someone who had lived in a regulated apartment for 10 or 20 years would encounter.</p>
        <p>Renters in large, prewar buildings -- often already converted to co-ops or condominiums -- who have lived in their apartments for years have received the biggest financial shock. One such tenant who, like the Wolfs, spent a large amount of money to on improvements, and who would speak only on condition of anonymity, called the law "brutally unfair."</p>
        <p>"It protects rent-controlled tenants paying almost nothing who are in a far better economic situation that I am," he said. "I felt that we have been taken advantage of." Since he moved into his nine-room apartment in 1985, he said, his rent had gone from $2,200 to $3,250. If he had not made a deal with his landlord -- a deal he refused to discuss -- the rent would have gone up to $7,000, he said.</p>
        <p>Another lawyer who specializes in tenant representation, Steven Smollens, criticized what he termed the "illogic and unfairness of a law that allows a man making $1 million a year to keep his $500-a-month apartment, but takes away the apartment of a husband and wife with four children in private school, with barely a dollar for a pizza tip."</p>
        <p>The high-rent, high-income decontrol law was approved by the State Legislature two years ago after a bitter struggle. Both landlord and tenant representatives predict that when the rent-regulation laws come up for the required renewal by the Legislature in 1997, with a Republican administration in office in Albany, there will be another battle.</p>
        <p>THE final report of Gov. George E. Pataki's Transition Committee on Housing and Community Development, dated Dec. 13, 1994, recommends phasing out rent regulations completely through vacancy decontrol -- the lifting of controls on all apartments as they become vacant.</p>
        <p>A similar vacancy-decontrol policy was in effect from 1971 to 1974, resulting in the decontrol of 388,000 apartments, or about a third of the city's rent-regulated stock, according to the New York State Division of Housing and Community Renewal. About 90 percent of those apartments were reregulated in 1974 with the passage of the Emergency Tenant Protection Act, after a report by the Temporary State Commission on Living Costs and the Economy noted that rents had jumped precipitously on turnover. There were also complaints of tenants being harassed by landlords -- charges that were denied.</p>
        <p>Currently apartments renting for more than $2,000 a month are, under the 1993 law, decontrolled when they become vacant.</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki's transition committee for housing was headed by Charles J. Urstadt, the real-estate executive who was the architect of the first vacancy decontrol when he was Housing Commissioner under another Republican Governor, Nelson A. Rockefeller. The committee's report also recommends extending decontrol to current tenants with household incomes over $150,000 who live in apartments renting for more than $1,500 a month.</p>
        <p>Tenant and landlord groups are already gearing up for the legislative struggle to come.</p>
        <p>Michael McKee, development director of the New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition, said he would join other tenant advocates on May 16 in chartering a series of buses bound for Albany, in the first tenant rally since Governor Pataki took office.</p>
        <p>ON the other side, Steven Spinola, president of the Real Estate Board of New York, said that his group had already begun lobbying legislators.</p>
        <p>"There's going to be a major battle in 1997, but that doesn't mean we're not doing anything now," said Mr. Spinola. "I don't think we'll be able to reduce the limits this year -- we'll try -- but I think maybe this year we'll be able to pass a law putting rent that's being withheld into escrow."</p>
        <p>Mr. Spinola and his group contend that the escrow measure is necessary because some tenants, faced with a decontrol order, would unfairly claim "diminution of services" and not send in their rent. "After about eight months -- long enough to see they're not going to win -- they'll just run out without paying," said Mr. Hemmerdinger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hemmerdinger said that he was making renovations at his two back-to-back postwar apartment buildings -- 40 Central Park South and 41 West 58th Street -- that he would not have undertaken without luxury decontrol. He has hired two noted interior designers, Jed Johnson and Alan Wanzenberg, to draw up plans for elaborate granite and bronze lobbies in both buildings and for renovations to the entrance on Central Park South.</p>
        <p>He said that he would redo the elevators at both and that he had spent in "six figures" resurrecting the garden courtyard between the buildings. He said he was installing an elaborate plastic-key and card security system that will restrict even the tenants to certain floors. He is replacing the buildings' old balconies with stainless steel ones.</p>
        <p>"Like any landlord, you let the carpet get threadbare, let the elevators look seedy," said the outspoken developer and landlord. "Now I have motivation: I can't get the higher market rents unless my halls look good."</p>
        <p>THE first step in high-rent, high-income decontrol involves a questionnaire. Under the system, landlords may send income questionnaires to anyone who pays rent of $2,000 a month or more. If the tenant replies that gross household income has not totaled more than $250,000 in each of the last two years, or if the questionnaire is not returned, an income check is run through the New York State Department of Taxation and Finance. If the tenant answers yes, or if the income check reveals that the household is "over income," a decontrol order is issued.</p>
        <p>At this point, negotiations often begin. The landlords interviewed all agreed that their first choice was to keep the sitting tenant -- but at a higher rent. Tenants can appeal decontrol orders, as landlords can appeal denials. The decontrol orders do not become effective until the expiration of the lease.</p>
        <p>Until recently, Doug Oliver was a rent-stabilized tenant in an 11-room, high-ceilinged prewar apartment at 21 East 66th Street, a building that was converted to a condominium six years ago. Mr. Oliver was paying $2,700 a month when he received the decontrol questionnaire. Some of his friends in the neighborhood are paying that much for a one-bedroom apartment, he freely concedes.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Oliver received the questionnaire, he decided that his days as a $2,700-a-month renter were numbered -- despite the fact, he said, that his highly variable yearly income as a commercial real estate broker had been over the threshold in only one of the two preceding years.</p>
        <p>"The first year I had tremendous losses," he said. "But my second year was great. So even though I didn't qualify then, they can send these questionnaires out every year and I knew it wouldn't be long before I did."</p>
        <p>At first, Mr. Oliver's instinct was to fight, and to drag the procedure out as long as possible, continuing to pay the $2,700 rent "probably until the year 2000." He called lobbying groups and "rushed down to Mike McKee's office and gave him a check for $5,000 to go to Albany and do something. I paid another $3,000 for old ladies to go picket. I gave a couple of Councilpeople contributions."</p>
        <p>But then he and the conversion sponsor worked out a compromise: the sponsor would sell him the 11-room apartment, with three exposures, 28 windows and three fireplaces, for $1.23 million. The apartment has been appraised for more than double that figure, he said. As part of the deal, the condominium's sponsor required that if Mr. Oliver sold within three years of the purchase -- a process known as "flipping" the apartment -- Mr. Oliver would pay him a set sum, which he declined to disclose. With the mortgage and maintenance, Mr. Oliver said, he now pays about $15,000 a month before taxes -- more than five times his former rent. At market value the apartment might rent for between $18,000 and $20,000 a month, according to Ms. Lenz.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH the apartment appears to be a sound financial investment, Mr. Oliver said that he made the decision at least partly because "once I got into a real out-and-out battle, they were right that someday they'd get it back, and I didn't want to live in my house under that threat; my home was in jeopardy."</p>
        <p>Pam and Kevin Wolf, after their initial shock on receiving a questionnaire, also felt that their home was in jeopardy. In doing their $250,000 renovation six years ago, they had combined two rental apartments in the postwar white-brick building at 920 Park Avenue, at 80th Street. Their total rent was $4,100 a month. They said that with the landlord's permission they put in new windows, central air-conditioning and heat, some slate floors, Jacuzzis and an elegant winding staircase. They had remodeled every room.</p>
        <p>When they move out this August, at the end of their lease, the rent on their apartment, they said, is scheduled to go up to $7,500 a month. "It sounds outrageous, but according to people who have been looking, the landlord will probably get it," Mrs. Wolf said. "This apartment works well for people who want to live on Park Avenue but can't pass stringent co-op rules."</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Oliver, the Wolfs decided to buy -- but not in the same building. (The building at 920 Park is all rental, so they did not have the option.)</p>
        <p>They declined to give the exact address or the price they are paying for their new apartment, but Mrs. Wolf deemed the monthly after-tax expenses "comparable" to the $7,500 they would have had to pay to stay where they are.</p>
        <p>She said she felt that the new building, a landmark on Central Park West, would be more conducive to raising their two children, Jessica, 3, and Jared, 2.</p>
        <p>"We're leaving the East Side for the West Side, for a more family-oriented building, where the children can Rollerblade in the lobby," Mrs. Wolf said. "Here one of the tenants once asked the doorman if the children and I couldn't ride in the freight elevator."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
