<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On More and More Routes, Only Propeller Planes Fly</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="723120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN EAGLE (AIRLINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, ADAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E1D8153EF936A35752C1A962958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On More and More Routes, Only Propeller Planes Fly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BRYANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although many passengers express concern over flying in propeller-driven planes -- and some liken such flights to "riding on the back of a mosquito" -- a growing number of people are finding that propeller aircraft are the only type of planes flying to their destinations.</p>
        <p>Major airlines are replacing jets with propeller planes on more and more routes as a way to cut costs in an industry that lost $12.8 billion over the last four years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although many passengers express concern over flying in propeller-driven planes -- and some liken such flights to "riding on the back of a mosquito" -- a growing number of people are finding that propeller aircraft are the only type of planes flying to their destinations.</p>
        <p>Major airlines are replacing jets with propeller planes on more and more routes as a way to cut costs in an industry that lost $12.8 billion over the last four years.</p>
        <p>But they are not very popular with passengers, many of whom complain about the noise and the bumpy rides associated with propeller planes. Travel agents say that some people go out of their way to avoid the smaller planes, even driving to nearby cities that have jet service.</p>
        <p>"I'll never take them again if I have a choice," said Karen Beaurigard, an administrator with the state of Michigan who flew, in a propeller-driven plane, through the same storm in which the American Eagle Flight 4184 crashed on Monday in Roselawn, Ind., killing all 68 people aboard.</p>
        <p>"When I came in Monday night, it was harrowing," she said. "I prayed all the way."</p>
        <p>To some degree, concerns about the safety record of propeller aircraft are justified. Although there are no direct comparisons of the safety records of jet aircraft and propeller planes, industry executives generally agree that the rate of fatal accidents has been two to three times higher on propeller planes than it is on jets. Generally, smaller propeller planes have a higher accident rate than the larger ones.</p>
        <p>The American Eagle ATR-72 that crashed on Monday was among the largest of the commercial propeller planes.</p>
        <p>The number of passengers boarding propeller planes each year more than doubled in the last 10 years, to 52 million, according to the Regional Airline Association in Washington.</p>
        <p>While the propeller planes are the only choice available at about 7 of every 10 airports in the United States, they are also being used to fly more short routes from big hub airports.</p>
        <p>Since 1988, for example, departures on commuter airlines from hub airports has grown 73 percent, while the number of jet departures on short routes has increased only 3 percent, according to statistics compiled by Samuel C. Buttrick, an airline stock analyst at Kidder, Peabody in New York.</p>
        <p>Some city officials believe that without jet service, their communities appear second-rate to outsiders. So in cities like Amarillo, Tex., officials have agreed to guarantee profits to an airline to provide jet service.</p>
        <p>Travel agents say that customers sometimes switch their vacation plans once they learn they have to board a propeller aircraft to get to their destination.</p>
        <p>Estelle Lessack, president of Travel Trends, an agency in Fort Lee, N.J., said she has some customers who fly on turboprops when they travel alone, but refuse to do so when traveling with their children. "Many people are fatalists," she said. "They just don't want be fatalists with their families."</p>
        <p>Yet, despite such concerns, the American Eagle crash does not appear to have changed many travelers' minds about flying on turboprops. American Eagle, other regional airlines and travel agents said yesterday that they had seen no measurable decline in reservations since Monday. By comparison, USAir estimated that its two jet crashes this year prompted many travelers to switch airlines, which cost the company about $40 million in lost revenue.</p>
        <p>Industry experts said that passenger traffic on turboprops held steady this week because many passengers have no choice but to fly the smaller planes unless they want to drive to another airport. And they said that many travelers appeared to have decided long ago whether they would fly on the smaller aircraft, and the recent crash has not changed their mind.</p>
        <p>Some people even enjoy flying on smaller planes. "The pilots are friendlier and you can see out the front window," said Shelley Ruckel, a travel agency manager in Lansing, Mich.</p>
        <p>Linda Hargreaves of Louisville, Ky., said that flying in a turboprop rather than a jet was "like the difference between a motorcycle and a Mercedes." She added that she felt comfortable flying in the smaller planes. 'It's a tested means of transportation," she said as she waited Thursday in Miami International Airport to board a USAir turboprop for a flight to Key West.</p>
        <p>Although many travelers see propeller planes as an older technology than jets, the nation's fleet of passenger-carrying turboprops is somewhat younger than the jet fleets, with an average age of 9.4 years in 1993, compared with 10.8 years for jets.</p>
        <p>Since April, the National Transportation Safety Board has been studying the safety of the commuter airline industry, looking at issues that include pilots training. Its report is due this month.</p>
        <p>The International Airline Passengers Association, an organization in Washington that monitors air safety in foreign countries, said that travelers should fly on propeller planes only in good weather and in daylight hours to minimize the change of accidents.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
