<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's a Lack of Control For Penn State in Polls</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="723113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORAN, MALCOLM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D8153EF936A35752C1A962958260" item-length="649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's a Lack of Control For Penn State in Polls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORAN, MALCOLM</byline>
      <dateline>BLOOMINGTON, Ind., Nov. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The process goes on, week by week, as Penn State attempts to build a case for a national championship. The Nittany Lions are schooled to concentrate on the opponents across the line of scrimmage, but with just one serious challenge left on their schedule, they are aware of another competition.</p>
        <p>Penn State will meet Indiana here on Saturday and will then contend with Nebraska on Sunday. That is how the next few weekends should go for the teams that share the No. 1 positions in the two polls that attempt to determine a national championship in the absence of a playoff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The process goes on, week by week, as Penn State attempts to build a case for a national championship. The Nittany Lions are schooled to concentrate on the opponents across the line of scrimmage, but with just one serious challenge left on their schedule, they are aware of another competition.</p>
        <p>Penn State will meet Indiana here on Saturday and will then contend with Nebraska on Sunday. That is how the next few weekends should go for the teams that share the No. 1 positions in the two polls that attempt to determine a national championship in the absence of a playoff.</p>
        <p>The Lions will cope with the beauty pageant segment of their schedule as they sweep through their second Big Ten season. It is a time to impress voters and create statistical advantages, even as they go about their work. It can also be a frustrating time, as it was last weekend when a more-than-convincing 63-14 victory over Ohio State could not prevent Nebraska from gaining the No. 1 position in the USA Today/CNN poll of coaches. Penn State was first in the Associated Press writers' poll and in the New York Times computer ranking.</p>
        <p>Last weekend's outcome raised a real possibility that Penn State (7-0) could complete a perfect season without any national-championship credentials, a painful scenario experienced by Lion teams of a generation ago.</p>
        <p>"It hurt us a little bit," said tailback Ki-Jana Carter earlier this week. "We beat them convincingly. I don't know what else we can do."</p>
        <p>Nebraska (9-0) will meet Kansas (5-3) on Saturday, and the possible Orange Bowl opponent of the Huskers, the Miami Hurricanes, could take an important step toward a Big East championship. Miami and Syracuse, two once-beaten teams, will meet at the Carrier Dome. Alabama, which has won all eight of its games but remains on the outside of the championship picture, could come within one victory of clinching first place in the West Division of the Southeastern Conference with a victory at Louisiana State on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Next week, Penn State will play at Illinois in a meeting considered the last serious challenge of its regular season. Here, against Indiana (5-3), Penn State will meet a team that has lost three of its last five games. But the Lions are just a year removed from a home game against the Hoosiers in which they lost a 14-point lead and needed a 45-yard touchdown pass from Kerry Collins to Bobby Engram in the fourth quarter for a 7-point victory.</p>
        <p>Collins has since developed into a quarterback with a chance to establish national records in pass efficiency and completion percentage. His rating of 194.75 is ahead of the 176.9 established by Jim McMahon of Brigham Young in 1980. Collins has completed 69.9 percent of his passes, a mark just 0.4 less than the record set by another Brigham Young star, Steve Young, in 1983.</p>
        <p>But the need for continued progress goes well beyond a place among individual records. Penn State's play in the next few weeks will determine not only whether the Lions reach the Rose Bowl, but also how: as a No. 1 team capable of holding the position with a solid performance, or a No. 2 team that may require a Nebraska defeat in order to win.</p>
        <p>Coach Joe Paterno has continued to avoid direct comments on the polls. But when asked if he had said anything to his players about trying to ignore the weekly votes, his feelings came through.</p>
        <p>"I'll tell you exactly what I tell them," Paterno said. "I tell them, 'The media and a lot of other people take a lot of fun out of the season you are having. You are playing really well, have worked hard, achieved some things, and you have four games left to play and enjoy them. Don't get caught up in a lot of talk and debate about something you can't do anything about. Think about how you are going to play, and when you are winning, enjoy it. Don't let anybody take any of the enjoyment away from you.' "  FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
