<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jobless Rate in Connecticut, At 5.6%, Tops U.S. Average</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA163EF931A25755C0A966958260" item-length="382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jobless Rate in Connecticut, At 5.6%, Tops U.S. Average</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Connecticut's unemployment rate rose to 5.6 percent in April, from 5 percent in March, exceeding the national average for the first time since May 1977.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Connecticut's unemployment rate rose to 5.6 percent in April, from 5 percent in March, exceeding the national average for the first time since May 1977.</p>
        <p>Connecticut's unemployment rate rose to 5.6 percent in April, from 5 percent in March, exceeding the national average for the first time since May 1977.</p>
        <p>A year ago Connecticut had one of the lowest unemployment rates in the nation, at 3.3 percent. The national seasonally adjusted jobless rate was 5.4 percent in April.</p>
        <p>Economists said the new figure confirmed a sharp slowdown in the state's once-booming economy. But several said the greater significance was in the pattern of joblessness rather than the number of jobless workers.</p>
        <p>The number of people employed in construction, one of the most depressed areas, rose by 6.8 percent, to 69,500 jobs from 65,100 in March. That increase was countered by declines in manufacturing, which employed 800 fewer workers, and by growth that was slower than expected across a spectrum of businesses.</p>
        <p>'This Is Not Texas'</p>
        <p>''The ultimate good news is that Connecticut's economy is not so dependent on any one sector - this is not Texas,'' said Richard H. Mattoon, an economist for the Connecticut Business and Industry Association. ''The bad news is that it's a broad-based decline.''</p>
        <p>Figures from the State Labor Department show that the total number of people employed in non-agricultural jobs rose slightly, to 1.671 million from 1.668 million in March and 1.669 million in April 1989.</p>
        <p>The number of people listed as actively seeking work also declined, to 91,600 in April from 93,000 in March.</p>
        <p>The higher jobless rate, the experts said, arose because the traditional spring increase in the number of jobs did not materialize with anywhere near the usual vigor.</p>
        <p>Possibility of Revision</p>
        <p>''One month does not a recession make,'' a professor of economics at Fairfield University, Edward J. Deak, said. ''But this is certainly different from what the state was experiencing in 1987 and 1988.''</p>
        <p>Deputy Labor Commissioner Lawrence S. Fox said preliminary figures for last month showed a decline in the number of people receiving unemployment benefits. He speculated that the jump in April might have been a ''fluky'' result that could be revised as additional information arrives.</p>
        <p>New York had a 4.9 percent unemployment rate in April and 5.1 percent last month. The New Jersey rate in April was 4.9 percent, falling to 4.8 in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
