<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roll Call in House on Vote on a Tax Package Sponsored by the Democrats</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="515649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAPITAL GAINS TAX</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Gains Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DF1E3BF932A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roll Call in House on Vote on a Tax Package Sponsored by the Democrats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is the roll-call vote of 211 to 189 by which the House approved a Democratic-sponsored tax bill today that would cut taxes for the middle class and raise them for the wealthy. A "yes" vote is a vote to approve the bill. Voting for the bill were 209 Democrats, 1 Republican and 1 independent. Voting against it were 40 Democrats and 149 Republicans. X denotes those not voting. There are no vacancies in the 435-member House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is the roll-call vote of 211 to 189 by which the House approved a Democratic-sponsored tax bill today that would cut taxes for the middle class and raise them for the wealthy. A "yes" vote is a vote to approve the bill. Voting for the bill were 209 Democrats, 1 Republican and 1 independent. Voting against it were 40 Democrats and 149 Republicans. X denotes those not voting. There are no vacancies in the 435-member House.</p>
        <p>ALABAMA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Bevill, Y; Browder, Y; Cramer, Y; Erdreich, Y; Harris, Y.  Republicans -- Callahan, X; Dickinson, X. ALASKA</p>
        <p>Republican -- Young, N. ARIZONA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Pastor, Y.  Republicans -- Kolbe, N; Kyl, N; Rhodes, N; Stump, N. ARKANSAS</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Alexander, Y; Anthony, Y; Thornton, Y.  Republican -- Hammerschmidt, N. CALIFORNIA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Anderson, Y; Beilenson, N; Berman, Y; Boxer, Y; Brown, Y; Condit, N; Dellums, Y; Dixon, Y; Dooley, Y; Dymally, X; Edwards, Y; Fazio, Y; Lantos, Y; Lehman, N; Levine, X; Martinez, Y; Matsui, Y; Miller, X; Mineta, Y; Panetta, Y; Pelosi, Y; Roybal, Y; Stark, N; Torres, Y; Waters, Y; Waxman, Y.  Republicans -- Campbell, X; Cox , N; Cunningham, N; Dannemeyer, X; Doolittle, N; Dornan, N; Dreier, N; Gallegly, N; Herger, N; Hunter, N; Lagomarsino, N; Lewis, N; Lowery, N; McCandless, N; Moorhead, N; Packard, N; Riggs, N; Rohrabacher, N; Thomas, X. COLORADO</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Campbell, Y; Schroeder, Y; Skaggs, X.  Republicans -- Allard, N; Hefley, N; Schaefer, N. CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>Democrats -- DeLauro, Y; Gejdenson, Y; Kennelly, Y.  Republicans -- Franks, N; Johnson, N; Shays, N. DELAWARE</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Carper, N. FLORIDA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Bacchus, Y; Bennett, Y; Fascell, Y; Gibbons, Y; Hutto, N; Johnston, Y; Lehman, X; Peterson, Y; Smith, Y.  Republicans -- Bilirakis, N; Goss, N; Ireland, N; James, N; Lewis, N; McCollum, N; Ros-Lehtinen, N; Shaw, N; Stearns, N; Young, N. GEORGIA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Barnard, X; Darden, Y; Hatcher, X; Jenkins, Y; Jones, N; Lewis, Y; Ray, N; Rowland, Y; Thomas, X.  Republican -- Gingrich, X. HAWAII</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Abercrombie, Y; Mink, Y. IDAHO</p>
        <p>Democrats -- LaRocco, Y; Stallings, N. ILLINOIS</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Annunzio, Y; Bruce, X; Collins, X; Costello, Y; Cox , Y; Durbin, Y; Evans, Y; Hayes, Y; Lipinski, X; Poshard, Y; Rostenkowski, Y; Russo, X; Sangmeister, Y; Savage, Y; Yates, Y.  Republicans -- Crane, N; Ewing, N; Fawell, N; Hastert, N; Hyde, N; Michel, N; Porter, N. INDIANA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Hamilton, N; Jacobs, Y; Jontz, Y; Long, N; McCloskey, Y; Roemer, N; Sharp, Y; Visclosky, Y.  Republicans -- Burton, N; Myers, N. IOWA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Nagle, Y; Smith, Y.  Republicans -- Grandy, N; Leach, N; Lightfoot, N; Nussle, N. KANSAS</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Glickman, Y; Slattery, N.  Republicans -- Meyers, N; Nichols, N; Roberts, N. KENTUCKY</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Hubbard, Y; Mazzoli, Y; Natcher, Y; Perkins, Y.  Republicans -- Bunning, N; Hopkins, N; Rogers, N. LOUISIANA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Hayes, X; Huckaby, X; Jefferson, Y; Tauzin, N.  Republicans -- Baker, X; Holloway, X; Livingston, X; McCrery, N. MAINE</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Andrews, Y.  Republican -- Snowe, Y. MARYLAND</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Byron, Y; Cardin, Y; Hoyer, Y; McMillen, N; Mfume, Y.  Republicans -- Bentley, N; Gilchrest, N; Morella, N. MASSACHUSETTS</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Atkins, Y; Donnelly, Y; Early, N; Frank, Y; Kennedy, Y; Markey, Y; Mavroules, Y; Moakley, Y; Neal, Y; Olver, Y; Studds, Y. MICHIGAN</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Bonior, Y; Carr, N; Collins, Y; Conyers, Y; Dingell, Y; Ford, Y; Hertel, Y; Kildee, Y; Levin, Y; Traxler, Y; Wolpe, Y.  Republicans -- Broomfield, N; Camp, N; Davis, N; Henry, N; Pursell, X. Upton, N; Vander Jagt, N. MINNESOTA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Oberstar, Y; Penny, Y; Peterson, N; Sabo, Y; Sikorski, Y; Vento, Y.  Republicans -- Ramstad, N; Weber, N. MISSISSIPPI</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Espy, Y; Montgomery, N; Parker, N; Taylor, N; Whitten, X. MISSOURI</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Clay, Y; Gephardt, Y; Horn, Y; Skelton, N; Volkmer, Y; Wheat, Y.  Republicans -- Coleman, N; Emerson, N; Hancock, N. MONTANA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Williams, Y.  Republican -- Marlenee, X. NEBRASKA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Hoagland, Y.  Republicans -- Barrett, N; Bereuter, N. NEVADA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Bilbray, Y.  Republican -- Vucanovich, N. NEW HAMPSHIRE</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Swett, N.;  Republican -- Zeliff, N. NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Andrews, N; Dwyer, N; Guarini, Y; Hughes, N; Pallone, N; Payne, Y; Roe, N; Torricelli, Y.  Republicans -- Gallo, N; Rinaldo, N; Roukema, N; Saxton, N; Smith, N; Zimmer, N NEW MEXICO</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Richardson, Y.;  Republicans -- Schiff, N; Skeen, N. NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Ackerman, Y; Downey, Y; Engel, Y; Flake, Y; Hochbrueckner, Y; LaFalce, Y; Lowey, Y; Manton, X; McHugh, Y; McNulty, Y; Mrazek, X. Nowak, Y; Owens, Y; Rangel, Y; Scheuer, Y; Schumer, Y; Serrano, Y; Slaughter, Y; Solarz, Y; Towns, Y; Weiss, Y.  Republicans -- Boehlert, N; Fish, N; Gilman, N; Green, N; Horton, N; Houghton, N; Lent, N; Martin, N; McGrath, N; Molinari, N; Paxon, N; Solomon, N; Walsh, N. NORTH CAROLINA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Hefner, Y; Jones, Y; Lancaster, Y; Neal, Y; Price, Y; Rose, Y; Valentine, Y.  Republicans -- Ballenger, N; Coble, N; McMillan, N; Taylor, N. NORTH DAKOTA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Dorgan, Y. OHIO</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Applegate, Y; Eckart, Y; Feighan, Y; Hall, Y; Kaptur, Y; Luken, Y; Oakar, Y; Pease, Y; Sawyer, Y; Stokes, Y; Traficant, N.  Republicans -- Boehner, N; Gillmor, N; Gradison, N; Hobson, N; Kasich, N; McEwen, N; Miller, N; Oxley, N; Regula, N; Wylie, X. OKLAHOMA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Brewster, Y; English, N; McCurdy, N; Synar, Y.  Republicans -- Edwards, X; Inhofe, N. OREGON</p>
        <p>Democrats -- AuCoin, Y; DeFazio, Y; Kopetski, Y; Wyden, Y.  Republican -- Smith, N. PENNSYLVANIA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Blackwell, Y; Borski, Y; Coyne, Y; Foglietta, Y; Gaydos, Y; Kanjorski, Y; Kolter, Y; Kostmayer, Y; Murphy, Y; Murtha, Y; Yatron, Y.  Republicans -- Clinger, N; Coughlin, N; Gekas, N; Goodling, N; McDade, N; Ridge, N; Ritter, N; Santorum, N; Schulze, N; Shuster, N; Walker, N; Weldon, N. RHODE ISLAND</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Reed, Y.  Republican -- Machtley, N. SOUTH CAROLINA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Derrick, Y; Patterson, N; Spratt, Y; Tallon, Y.  Republicans -- Ravenel, N; Spence, N. SOUTH DAKOTA</p>
        <p>Democrat -- Johnson, Y. TENNESSEE</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Clement, Y; Cooper, N; Ford, Y; Gordon, Y; Lloyd, N; Tanner, Y.  Republicans -- Duncan, N; Quillen, N; Sundquist, N. TEXAS</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Andrews, Y; Brooks, Y; Bryant, Y; Bustamante, Y; Chapman, Y; Coleman, Y; de la Garza, Y; Edwards, Y; Frost, Y; Geren, N; Gonzalez, Y; Hall, N; Laughlin, X; Ortiz, Y; Pickle, Y; Sarpalius, N; Stenholm, Y; Washington, Y; Wilson, Y.  Republicans -- Archer, N; Armey, N; Barton, N; Combest, N; DeLay, N; Fields, N; Johnson, N; Smith, X. UTAH</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Orton, X; Owens, N.  Republican -- Hansen, N. VERMONT</p>
        <p>Independent -- Sanders, Y. VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Boucher, Y; Moran, Y; Olin, Y; Payne, Y; Pickett, N; Sisisky, N.  Republicans -- Allen, N; Bateman, N; Bliley, N; Wolf, N. WASHINGTON</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Dicks, Y; Foley, Y; McDermott, Y; Swift, Y; Unsoeld, Y.  Republicans -- Chandler, X; Miller, N; Morrison, X. WEST VIRGINIA</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Mollohan, Y; Rahall, Y; Staggers, Y; Wise, Y. WISCONSIN</p>
        <p>Democrats -- Aspin, Y; Kleczka, Y; Moody, Y; Obey, Y.  Republicans -- Gunderson, N; Klug, N; Petri, N; Roth, N; Sensenbrenner, N. WYOMING</p>
        <p>Republican -- Thomas, N.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
