<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Montgomerie Changes His Tune, and So Does His Gallery</title>
    <meta content="16links" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/06/16/sports/golf/16links.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1769502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Montgomerie, Colin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE1131F935A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Montgomerie Changes His Tune, and So Does His Gallery</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Montgomerie Changes His Tune, and So Does His Gallery</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK, N.Y., June 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Freckled and often heckled, red faced and often the runner-up, Colin Montgomerie spent the 1990's chasing a major championship in the United States, with results that left him stomping mad.</p>
        <p>Montgomerie lost a playoff for the United States Open title in 1994 and was defeated in another playoff at the 1995 P.G.A. Championship. At the 1997 United States Open, he was again second.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cooler heads prevail, on the greens and in the gallery at the U.S. Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Freckled and often heckled, red faced and often the runner-up, Colin Montgomerie spent the 1990's chasing a major championship in the United States, with results that left him stomping mad.</p>
        <p>Montgomerie lost a playoff for the United States Open title in 1994 and was defeated in another playoff at the 1995 P.G.A. Championship. At the 1997 United States Open, he was again second.</p>
        <p>In time, he became the preferred target among the hecklers in American golf galleries: easily recognized, almost like family, except that ''Monty'' was everyone's favorite taunt.</p>
        <p>Entering this year's Open, the Scottish-bred Montgomerie was viewed as neither contender nor bait for the grandstand.</p>
        <p>''They have forgotten about me,'' Montgomerie said Thursday. ''In more ways than one, I suspect.''</p>
        <p>In Thursday's first round at the taxing Winged Foot West Course, Montgomerie walked with applause at his back and, in the end, with the swagger of someone who was again a candidate for the Open championship. He concluded his day with a one-under-par 69, atop the leader board as the only player in the field under par. Leaving the 18th green, Montgomerie was cheered.</p>
        <p>It is not just the fans who have appeared to mellow. Montgomerie said he had changed, too.</p>
        <p>''I am more relaxed on the course than I ever was before,'' Montgomerie, 42, said. ''I came here for the majors in the 1990's with very high expectations, and I put too much pressure on myself. I wanted it a little bit too much then. That often doesn't work for you.</p>
        <p>''And since it didn't work, I've decided to try a new method. I can say that I swing more freely now. The attention isn't on me and the conversation isn't about me, and I can play with a little more calm spirit.''</p>
        <p>Calm spirit was a necessary attribute to survive the arduous conditions at Winged Foot on Thursday. Like his fellow competitors, Montgomerie could have made disastrous numbers on several holes, but he escaped with only three bogeys. His best moments may have been difficult sand saves from deep greenside bunkers on the 10th and 13th holes.</p>
        <p>Montgomerie closed by making a curling 25-foot, right-to-left putt for birdie on the 17th, and though he missed a five-footer for another birdie on the 18th, he did not seemed bothered.</p>
        <p>''Oh, that putt broke a mile,'' he said. ''I can't be worried about that. I was still enjoying the putt on the 17th. I hit that putt and about halfway to the hole I thought, 'Well, that has no chance.' But it kept curling and it went in.''</p>
        <p>Montgomerie spent more than an hour talking with reporters after the round, joking about his past misfortunes in major championships in the United States.</p>
        <p>When a questioner inevitably mentioned the near misses, Montgomerie smiled and said, ''Thanks for reminding me of those -- as if I didn't remember them.''</p>
        <p>But he conceded it was a vexing quest at times.</p>
        <p>''It was my goal to win one, and I had a go at it and came quite close,'' he said. ''I feel good that I never gave up or backed away. In every case, someone just did something exceptional to win it from me. But there was a lot of pressure, and I did much of that to myself.</p>
        <p>''I do feel the difference here this week, nine years since I last contended for one of these championships. And so far, the results are pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Montgomerie said he believed he could remain in contention because Winged Foot called for accurate second shots to devilish greens.</p>
        <p>''Some golf courses are set up to put an emphasis on putting,'' he said. ''Here, the emphasis is on getting it to the green in the right place. I've always been good at getting it there and never been very good when I got there. But if I can putt safely, I have a chance this week.''</p>
        <p>Montgomerie was once so berated by American fans that Golf Digest felt compelled to launch a ''Be Nice to Monty'' campaign, which included the distribution of buttons bearing that slogan. But Montgomerie said he was never heckled Thursday.</p>
        <p>''There were no troubles or problems,'' he said. ''I didn't need my Golf Digest buttons.''</p>
        <p>Asked if winning the Open would mean as much to him as it did in the 1990's, Montgomerie answered quickly.</p>
        <p>''Oh, yes,'' he said. ''It would probably mean more now. I figure I've got another four or five years left at this level. Although I'm not thinking of it that way. There's pressure in that, you know.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
