<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry Into Ambush Opens; Iraqi Forces Feared Infiltrated</title>
    <meta content="26IRAQ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/26/international/middleeast/26iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1622235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: THE OCCUPATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppel, Richard A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DD143DF935A15753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry Into Ambush Opens; Iraqi Forces Feared Infiltrated</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Inquiry Into Ambush Opens; Iraqi Forces Feared Infiltrated</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD A. OPPEL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oppel, Richard A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Tuesday, Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraqi officials open investigation into role played by infiltrators in ambush that left 49 Iraqi National Guard trainees dead; there are growing indications that insurgents are being given inside information about movements of Iraqi security forces; United States military officials have long been skeptical of loyalty of Iraqi security forces, having seen some American-trained Iraqi soldiers take up arms against occupation forces during fighting in Apr; now even senior Iraqi government officials concede possibility that insurgents staged attack with help from members of Iraqi security forces; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iraqi officials opened an investigation on Monday into the role played by infiltrators in the ambush on Sunday that left 49 Iraqi National Guard trainees dead in the face of growing indications that insurgents are being given inside information about the movements of Iraqi security forces.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, fresh violence in Baghdad struck troops from Estonia and Australia, two countries that had largely managed to avoid bloodshed during the occupation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are growing indications that insurgents are being given inside information about the movements of Iraqi security forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iraqi officials opened an investigation on Monday into the role played by infiltrators in the ambush on Sunday that left 49 Iraqi National Guard trainees dead in the face of growing indications that insurgents are being given inside information about the movements of Iraqi security forces.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, fresh violence in Baghdad struck troops from Estonia and Australia, two countries that had largely managed to avoid bloodshed during the occupation.</p>
        <p>United States military officials have long been skeptical of the loyalty of the Iraqi security forces, having seen some American-trained Iraqi soldiers take up arms against occupation forces during fighting in April. But on Monday, even senior Iraqi government officials conceded that it was very possible that insurgents staged the attack with help from members of the Iraqi security forces. One adviser to the interim prime minister, Ayad Allawi, said that as many as 5 percent of the Iraqi government's troops are insurgents who have infiltrated the ranks or their sympathizers.</p>
        <p>''It's quite possible they were involved in this and other incidents,'' said Aqil al-Saffar, an Iraqi national security aide. Suspicions of infiltration have arisen in part because the victims were unarmed and did not have armed escorts even though they were traveling in an area where insurgent attacks are frequent. That issue will be examined in the inquiry, an Iraqi official said.</p>
        <p>Defense Ministry officials said Monday that the attack happened at 8 p.m. Saturday, and that 3 civilian drivers were killed in addition to the 49 guardsmen, who were ''on leave heading to their families.'' The ministry promised ''to make the criminal terrorists get the fair punishment for their crimes against our people'' and vowed that ''these cowardly and treacherous actions will not stop our fighters of the courageous army from carrying on to purify the soil of Iraq from the criminal and terrorism groups.''</p>
        <p>Evidence of infiltration has been steadily growing. One month ago, an Iraqi National Guard commander who was one of five candidates nominated to become the provincial commander in Diyala -- the region where the ambush occurred Saturday -- was arrested by American officials for ''having associations with known insurgents.'' The commander, Brig. Gen. Talib Abid Ghayib al-Lahibi, was in charge of Iraqi guardsmen providing security in the region and had been a senior commander under Saddam Hussein's government.</p>
        <p>The deputy governor of Diyala Province, Aqil Hamid al-Adili, who said he believed that the travel plans of the slain National Guard troops had probably been leaked to insurgents, told Agence France-Presse on Monday that the government investigation ''will explore whether elements of the police or the National Guard had any contact with terrorists.''</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials also point to another very demoralizing attack on Iraqi forces one week ago, when insurgents fired mortar shells, perfectly timed and well aimed, at an Iraqi National Guard outpost north of Baghdad. The attack, which killed 4 and wounded 80, came just as the guardsmen were gathering for a ceremony, leading some in the Pentagon to suggest that insurgents had inside information about the event.</p>
        <p>''Iraqi security forces have been infiltrated,'' a Pentagon official said on Monday. ''The goal of attacks on them is to break morale and effectiveness.''</p>
        <p>Insurgents have increasingly sought to defeat the occupation by killing members of the Iraqi security forces; American officials are hoping that those forces will soon be capable of playing a far larger role in stabilizing the country. Insurgents have targeted the police, National Guardsmen and others they deem ''collaborators'' by exploding car bombs at recruiting stations and cafes patronized by the Iraqi police and killing translators who work with American forces. By some accounts, almost 800 members of the Iraqi police have been slain this year.</p>
        <p>A group led by the Jordanian militant Abu Musab al-Zarqawi took responsibility for the killings in Diyala. American officials say Mr. Zarqawi has been behind many of the car-bombings and beheadings that have taken place in Iraq.</p>
        <p>On Monday, another group linked to Mr. Zarqawi took credit for an attack near the Australian Embassy. Early Tuesday, the United States military said that a strike on a safe house in Falluja had killed an aide to Mr. Zarqawi.The blast at the embassy happened at about 8 a.m. in a wealthy district of Baghdad, killing three Iraqis and wounding three Australian soldiers.</p>
        <p>After the bomb exploded, American tanks and other vehicles arrived and set up a cordon around the scene. American soldiers trained their rifles at Iraqis who came to the scene in the aftermath of the bombing, some still wearing pajamas. One soldier told a photographer: ''I suggest you stay back. We can't have any photos of this. If you don't, then I'm talking about your cameras being taken and thrown on the ground.''</p>
        <p>In Canberra, the Australian capital, a military spokesman, Mike Hannan, said the attack occurred when ''a security detachment patrol of armored vehicles was engaged by an improvised explosive device that was hidden in a vehicle,'' according to Agence France-Presse. ''We know that two of the three Australian vehicles were damaged and three of our people suffered non-life-threatening injuries,'' Mr. Hannan said.</p>
        <p>About three hours later, an Estonian soldier was killed and five others were wounded in western Baghdad when their convoy was attacked with a homemade bomb perched in the roadside.</p>
        <p>The Estonian prime minister, Juhan Parts, in an interview with Reuters, said he believed the attack was part of an effort by insurgents to destabilize Iraq before national elections in January. But he said it was ''extremely important to continue the determined work of the international coalition to guarantee the victory of democracy and human rights in Iraq and the security of all Iraqis.''</p>
        <p>In other violence on Monday, a city council leader in Mahmoudiya, an insurgent stronghold just south of Baghdad, was slain in a drive-by shooting. And insurgents in the northern Iraqi city of Mosul bombed a government compound, killing three and injuring one, according to The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: THE OCCUPATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
