<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Burmese Protests, Capital Is Tense</title>
    <meta content="09BURM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Myanmar</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yangon (Myanmar)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Myanmar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7DA133FF93AA35751C1A960958260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Burmese Protests, Capital Is Tense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>BANGKOK, Thailand, Dec. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Streets of Yangon are quiet but tense as hundreds of policemen block parts of Burmese capital to prevent demonstrations by angry students; move follows week of largest student demonstration since army killed hundreds in pre-democracy uprising in 1988; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The streets of Yangon were quiet but tense today as hundreds of policemen blocked off parts of the Burmese capital to prevent demonstrations by angry students.</p>
        <p>The move came after a week that saw the largest student demonstrations since the army killed hundreds of people in crushing a peaceful pro-democracy uprising in 1988. The demonstrations have brought a new threat of instability to the military Government, which is struggling to neutralize the democracy movement of Daw Aung San Suu Kyi.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The streets of Yangon were quiet but tense today as hundreds of policemen blocked off parts of the Burmese capital to prevent demonstrations by angry students.</p>
        <p>The move came after a week that saw the largest student demonstrations since the army killed hundreds of people in crushing a peaceful pro-democracy uprising in 1988. The demonstrations have brought a new threat of instability to the military Government, which is struggling to neutralize the democracy movement of Daw Aung San Suu Kyi.</p>
        <p>The police, using truncheons and fire hoses, broke up the protests, arresting hundreds of students who had staged sit-ins, thrown rocks and marched through the streets carrying banners reading, ''We want freedom'' and ''Give us human rights.''</p>
        <p>The police also erected roadblocks to insure that the students would not approach the house of Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi, and they confined her to her house, temporarily reinstating the house arrest that ended after six years in mid-1995.</p>
        <p>Since September, the authorities have prevented her from making her regular weekend addresses to thousands of supporters, the country's only forum for free speech.</p>
        <p>Col. Kyaw Win, deputy director of military intelligence, told reporters last week that those meetings would no longer be allowed. He said she would be free to meet with supporters inside her compound, but she has said that is not acceptable.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi said that she had no links with the students but that they appeared to share her anger at the military junta that has ruled the country since the crackdown in 1988.</p>
        <p>''What I understand is that they were demonstrating against police brutality and injustice,'' she told reporters. ''We're against police brutality and injustice too, so I could say that we are all on the same side.''</p>
        <p>Colonel Kyaw Win said he believed that ''political infiltration'' had been involved in the student demonstrations and that ''there may be a threat to political stability.''</p>
        <p>The unrest comes at a difficult moment for the Government. It is eager to be accepted next year as a full member of the Association for Southeast Asian Nations, the region's political and economic grouping.</p>
        <p>Membership would bring some measure of international respectability to a government that is widely condemned in the West for its human-rights violations and for canceling the results of an election in 1990 that was won by Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi's party.</p>
        <p>At a conference in Indonesia a week ago, leaders of the association, known as Asean, met with Gen. Than Shwe, head of the junta, but left unclear whether they were ready to embrace his Government.</p>
        <p>In an ambiguous statement, they said Myanmar would be accepted as a full member simultaneously with Laos and Cambodia, which are also waiting to be elevated from the status of observers.</p>
        <p>Thailand, the Philippines and Singapore have expressed concerns over the situation in Myanmar, formerly called Burma. But other nations, led by Malaysia, are eager to induct all three countries by next July, when Asean will mark its 30th anniversary.</p>
        <p>The grouping insists that one of its tenets is ''noninterference'' in one another's internal affairs. In addition, some members are offended by the insistence of the United States and other nations on the importance of human rights.</p>
        <p>After the meeting, Myanmar's Foreign Minister, Ohn Gyaw, said no one had talked to him about human rights.</p>
        <p>''There was no suggestion or advice that 'If you want to join Asean, you should do this or that,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>While cracking down on the pro-democracy movement, the junta has also attempted to open up the country in a demonstration of normalcy, inviting reporters to monthly briefings and opening its doors to tourists with the start of ''Visit Myanmar Year'' last month.</p>
        <p>Campus unrest is particularly worrisome to the junta because it was student demonstrations in 1988 that led to the collapse of the 30-year authoritarian regime of Ne Win and set off the democratic uprising that sent the country into chaos.</p>
        <p>The current campus turmoil carries remarkable parallels to 1988. In both cases, it was set off by a violent confrontation at a tea house and escalated as students grew angry over their treatment by authorities.</p>
        <p>The incident this time came in October, when three students were severely beaten by the police after a dispute with a tea-house owner. Determined not to let the incident escalate, the Government arrested two police officers and sentenced them to two-year prison terms.</p>
        <p>But the students were not mollified. In their first demonstration last week, on Monday, a group of up to 1,000 presented officials with a list of demands including a complete accounting of the tea-house incident, release of students arrested in a protest that followed it and an investigation into the distribution on campus of leaflets telling them to calm down and concentrate on their studies.</p>
        <p>In addition, they called for the creation of an independent student union, a highly symbolic demand.  The student union was abolished and its historic building was destroyed in 1962, shortly after Mr. Ne Win came to power in a coup.</p>
        <p>The demands were rejected on the spot, and later in the night, several hundred students marched from the glowing, golden stupa of the giant Shwedagon Pagoda through the  streets of the city, chanting their demands. Before the authorities dispersed them, they marched past the smaller Sule Pagoda, where on Aug. 8, 1988, tanks and soldiers opened fire on student demonstrators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
