<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Canada's Dollar Weak Shoppers Snub U.S. Stores</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="583885"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL MONETARY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DE143CF93BA25752C0A965958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Canada's Dollar Weak Shoppers Snub U.S. Stores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>ST. CATHARINES, Ontario</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charmaine Morrison, eight months pregnant, and her husband, Dale, are scouting the big Zellers discount store here at the Fairview Mall for baby clothes and diaper-changing pads. Mr. Morrison's mother, Shirley Trento, is looking at garbage bags and a wood cutting board, while his stepfather, John Trento, inspects paints for the hobby horses he builds in his spare time.</p>
        <p>A few months back they would have gone on a shopping expedition across the border, into the malls of Buffalo or Niagara Falls, N.Y. "Now, it's just not worth it," Mr. Morrison, 32, the comptroller at a local auto parts company, said recently. "With the Canadian dollar down so much, you'll break even at best."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charmaine Morrison, eight months pregnant, and her husband, Dale, are scouting the big Zellers discount store here at the Fairview Mall for baby clothes and diaper-changing pads. Mr. Morrison's mother, Shirley Trento, is looking at garbage bags and a wood cutting board, while his stepfather, John Trento, inspects paints for the hobby horses he builds in his spare time.</p>
        <p>A few months back they would have gone on a shopping expedition across the border, into the malls of Buffalo or Niagara Falls, N.Y. "Now, it's just not worth it," Mr. Morrison, 32, the comptroller at a local auto parts company, said recently. "With the Canadian dollar down so much, you'll break even at best."</p>
        <p>The Canadian dollar has fallen 13 percent against the American dollar since late 1991, when it was worth about 90 United States cents. Now it is worth 78 cents.</p>
        <p>Millions of Canadians, who until a few months back were denuding shelves in American malls and wholesale outlets along the 3,000-mile border, are increasingly finding that the bargains are a lot less attractive.</p>
        <p>As a result, the number of same-day car trips by Canadians to and from the United States has been declining all year, the Government's statistics agency reported. In November, the latest month for which figures are available, they were off nearly 20 percent from November 1991 to the lowest level in two years.</p>
        <p>"Business is awful," said Don Powell, 32, who sells T-shirts from a kiosk in the Rainbow Center Mall in Niagara Falls. "Most of the people coming to this mall are Canadians, and they're not coming the way they used to."</p>
        <p>Robert Joseph, also 32, who owns two shops in the same mall, one selling sunglasses and the other moccasins, said volume was down 20 percent from a year earlier in both stores.</p>
        <p>On the Canadian side, stores have cut prices and aggressively tried to keep their customers at home. The magnitude of recent price changes has even prompted some border-hopping by Americans, searching for bargains in Canada. The Retail Council of Canada, which represents 6,000 merchants, says it has had reports over the last two months that Americans have been picking up woolens, china and housewares and even some food items like baked goods. But no figures are available. 'Dash' Shoppers Disappear</p>
        <p>Other border regions are in similar straits. Convenience centers, usually consisting of a grocery store and specialty retailers, at Blaine, Lynden and Sumas in Washington, just south of Vancouver, reported to the Chamber of Commerce in Bellingham, Wash., that business over Christmas was down 18 to 20 percent from a year before, said Mike Brennan, vice president of the Bellingham chamber.</p>
        <p>"We're no longer getting the dash shoppers -- those who come ripping across the line to fill up their tank with gasoline and their back seats with milk and other dairy products," Mr. Brennan said.</p>
        <p>But what is bad news for American retailers is good news for Canadian store owners, who deserve some of the credit for luring the shoppers back.</p>
        <p>"Our merchants sharpened their pencils, particularly in those goods like food, clothing, electronics and appliances that were cross-border-shopped," said Alasdair McKichan, president of the Canadian retail council.</p>
        <p>Canadian retail sales were up 3.5 percent in October to $15.5 billion, the latest month for which figures are available, and most analysts expect further gains when the numbers are tallied for the Christmas season. At its peak, economists estimated that cross-border shopping drained the Canadian economy of $5 billion a year. Canadian Retailers Happy</p>
        <p>"Canadian retailers couldn't be happier," said Catherine Swift, senior vice president and chief economist of the Canadian Federation of Independent Businesses. Merchants represent 20 percent of the federation's membership of 83,000 small- and medium-size enterprises.</p>
        <p>The phenomenon has eased the sting of the severe Canadian recession. "Retailers are not the only ones smiling," Ms. Swift said, "but distributors and manufacturers as well, since the pace of the entire economy is quickened by higher retail sales."</p>
        <p>A $2 box of garbage bags in a Niagara Falls, N.Y., supermarket now costs the equivalent of $2.26 for the Canadian who buys American greenbacks at the border. Should the bags be found in a local market for around $2.50 Canadian, nothing is saved crossing the border after gasoline consumption and bridge tolls are added.</p>
        <p>As they saw their trade headed south, Canadian merchants complained loudly to Ottawa. Some merchants and officials went so far as to call cross-border shopping unpatriotic.</p>
        <p>The border hopping, spurred by high exchange rates and unpopular consumption-tax increases, became an incendiary political issue. The Government responded with further tariff cuts. Duties were slashed on many Japanese-made electronics goods, which were among the more popular cross-border purchases. Many Canadian duties had been twice as high as the American tariffs. Tougher Customs Inspections</p>
        <p>Ottawa also enforced more rigorous customs inspections. Fines were stiffened. Canadians are allowed to bring in $20 duty free on single-day trips to the United States. If they are away 48 hours or more, the limit rises to $100.</p>
        <p>Paul Walters, president of the 272-store Zellers Inc. chain, which likes to call itself the Canadian Wal-Mart, had one of the sharpest pencils.</p>
        <p>"At Zellers the lowest price is the law," he said, citing company policy to beat prices in other Canadian stores.</p>
        <p>The Montreal-based chain, owned since 1979 by the 323-year-old Hudson's Bay Company, delivers circulars on its promotions sometimes twice a week to 7.5 million households, effectively the bulk of the country.</p>
        <p>For Canadians shopping in the United States, the most popular items remain those that are most highly taxed in Canada, including gasoline, tobacco and alcoholic beverages, which still cost more than twice as much as in the United States. But customs officials enforce strict limits on the quantities of these products that can be brought in.</p>
        <p>Even if the Canadian dollar should bounce back up, Canadian merchants predict that cross-border shopping will not again become the economic drain and political lightning rod that it had been until a few months ago, because of adjustments in Canadian prices and improved marketing practices.</p>
        <p>"Canadians now realize the grass is not as green as they thought it was in the other pasture," said Mr. McKichan of the retail council.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
