<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faltering Companies Seek Outsiders</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="583919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXECUTIVES AND MANAGEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOARDS OF DIRECTORS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDE133EF93BA25752C0A965958260" item-length="1748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faltering Companies Seek Outsiders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When John F. Akers announced last month that the International Business Machines Corporation would cut 25,000 more jobs in 1993, he acknowledged what management experts say is the biggest conundrum for reviving any stumbling giant: speeding its response to changing markets and technology.</p>
        <p>But there is an emerging view among business scholars and management consultants suggesting that loyal "company men" like Mr. Akers, I.B.M.'s chairman and chief executive since 1986 and a 33-year I.B.M. employee, are ill-equipped to lead faltering corporations through painful recoveries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When John F. Akers announced last month that the International Business Machines Corporation would cut 25,000 more jobs in 1993, he acknowledged what management experts say is the biggest conundrum for reviving any stumbling giant: speeding its response to changing markets and technology.</p>
        <p>But there is an emerging view among business scholars and management consultants suggesting that loyal "company men" like Mr. Akers, I.B.M.'s chairman and chief executive since 1986 and a 33-year I.B.M. employee, are ill-equipped to lead faltering corporations through painful recoveries.</p>
        <p>They say that such insiders are often too slow to disrupt the corporate cultures that brought them to power even in the face of mounting financial crises. Indeed, directors at a growing number of corporations are bringing in leaders with fewer ties to the companies and more urgent plans to correct festering troubles -- although there is such a thing as being too urgent, as shown by the recent turmoil at the Sunbeam-Oster Company. Though the chairman, Paul B. Kazarian, turned the company around after bankruptcy, his hard-driving style caused a mutiny among his managers that resulted in his ouster.  "To really see the need for a major cultural change, and then to have the will to make it happen despite the pain, you need a kind of outsider's perspective," said John P. Kotter, a Harvard professor of leadership who studied 11 companies that successfully streamlined operations and gained market share in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>He found that none of the revivals were led by people who had climbed the traditional corporate ladders. Two of the brightest corporate success stories of the 1980's, General Electric and Xerox, were planned and executed by people outside the traditional corporate paths to power, Mr. Kotter said. And similar revivals appear to be under way at Compaq Computer and at Tenneco Inc., which recently replaced their chiefs.</p>
        <p>Stan Davis, an author and consultant in Boston, said company men often become too ensnarled in the politics of sustaining an oversized organization to react quickly to changing technologies and consumer demands.</p>
        <p>"It's a recipe for disaster," Mr. Davis said. "Whether it's General Motors, or I.B.M. or Sears, the only way that they will survive would be in a very radically transformed way that would take a lot of hardship, heartache, turmoil and pain." Upheaval at Highest Levels</p>
        <p>Some of the biggest business stories in 1992 have been chronicles of huge financial losses accompanied by upheaval at the highest levels of troubled corporations. General Motors' directors picked the chief of the successful European operation, John F. Smith Jr., to replace Robert C. Stempel in October after just 27 months as G.M.'s chief executive. Directors at Digital Equipment forced Kenneth H. Olsen into retirement after the computer giant's founder had run the company for 35 years, and chose a relative newcomer, Robert B. Palmer, who joined Digital in 1985.</p>
        <p>One candidate to replace James D. Robinson 3d, who is being ushered out by the board after 15 years as chief at American Express, is Harvey Golub, a former management consultant who until a year ago headed the financial company's IDS Financial Services unit in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Akers has hardly been a passive chief executive at I.B.M. During his tenure, he has cut I.B.M.'s work force by 28 percent and a year ago set in motion a companywide reorganization to split I.B.M. into smaller, better-focused businesses.</p>
        <p>"You could make the case that the only effective agent of change is somebody who doesn't come with all the history and trappings of the enterprise," Mr. Akers said through a spokesman. "The critical issue is whether management is truly willing to make the changes that are necessary. I believe we are demonstrating our willingness to make the fundamental changes."</p>
        <p>Last year, he brought in John Kotter to address senior management about the need for change. "When he was finished, I asked him what we should be doing that we're not doing," Mr. Akers said. "His only advice was to do it with a real sense of urgency. That's exactly what we're doing."</p>
        <p>Yet I.B.M. directors clipped some of Mr. Akers's power in recent weeks, recalling two retired senior executives, including a former rival of Mr. Akers, to help run the company.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, the independent thinkers who are now in vogue are often the first to be stymied or driven out by the bureaucratic cultures that grow out of industry dominance. That may make it difficult for leaders like Mr. Smith at G.M. and Mr. Akers to find the types of managers needed to jolt their bloated, tradition-bound organizations into a crisis mode. Pockets of Innovation</p>
        <p>But even within bureaucracies, there are pockets of innovation and success. In fact, many of the leaders now being tapped by boards come from star units within otherwise troubled corporations. John F. Welch, the head of G.E., made his mark as head of the company's plastics group, far afield from the traditional training grounds for a chief executive: light bulbs and washing machines.</p>
        <p>Dozens of factors have turned the tried-and-true management practices of the past into sure-fire formulas for failure. Among them are the accelerating pace of product design changes, shifting consumer tastes, the push for manufacturing efficiencies and competition on a global scale.</p>
        <p>Rest-on-your-laurels attitudes are why many huge organizations slip from their perches. Of the 500 companies that Fortune magazine included on its first list of the nation's largest industrial companies in 1955, only 35 percent remain on the list. And only 40 percent of the 500 industrial giants on the 1970 list were included in 1985.</p>
        <p>Even so, directors rarely challenge experienced chief executives until the damage has cut deeply into revenues and profits. That, critics say, stems in part from the tradition in most companies of having the chief executive also rule as chairman of the board -- a tradition that G.M., for one, finally broke recently by giving the job of chairman to John G. Smale, a retired head of Procter &amp; Gamble. Picking an Outsider</p>
        <p>At Compaq, the jobs of chairman and chief executive have been separate since the company was founded 10 years ago. Ben Rosen, the investor whose firm helped Compaq get off the ground, has been chairman from the start.</p>
        <p>He and other nonmanagement directors concluded a year ago that Compaq was losing touch with customers, and took the first step to rectify the problem by replacing the popular chief and co-founder, Joseph (Rod) Canion, with Eckhard Pfeiffer, the German-born longtime head of Compaq's European operations.</p>
        <p>In picking an outsider, Compaq has followed a formula that worked at Xerox, Tenneco and First Chicago, among others. David Kearns, who awoke Xerox to the threat of Japanese copy-machine makers, went to the company from I.B.M. at age 41 and was named chief executive at 52. Barry Sullivan, chief executive at First Chicago, was recruited by directors in 1980 from Chase Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In May, Tenneco's directors replaced James L. Ketelsen, the company's leader since 1978, with Michael H. Walsh, 50, a former Government prosecutor who had never managed a business until he was 38. He came from the Union Pacific Railroad, where he won high marks for improving efficiency and profits while slashing both white- and blue-collar jobs as chief executive between 1985 and 1991.</p>
        <p>What is it about these rebels plucked from within the corporate hierarchy or recruited from other companies that makes them better prepared for administering the necessary tough medicine? Fresh View of Problems Needed</p>
        <p>Professor Kotter said one answer was the intuitive ability to continually view problems in fresh ways and to identify ineffective operating practices and traditions.</p>
        <p>Noel M. Tichy, a professor at the University of Michigan whose new book on the Welch era at G.E., "Control Your Destiny or Someone Else Will" (Doubleday), said Mr. Welch of G.E. viewed business as a fast-moving, free-flowing sport like hockey, which he played at the University of Massachusetts, where he was captain of the team.</p>
        <p>"Hockey shaped Welch psychologically," Professor Tichy said. "He was a tough blue-collar kid who developed this informal, ad hoc, but disciplined style. And he wants to win, win, win. Performance means everything to him, with no compromises."</p>
        <p>General Electric's transformation under Mr. Welch is perhaps the classic contemporary case of a successful revolution led from within an aging corporate giant.</p>
        <p>Although G.E. was prosperous when Mr. Welch took command in 1981, at age 45, he created a crisis among senior managers with an edict that any business not ranking first or second in its global market would be overhauled or sold -- one reason he gave for recently merging its aerospace unit with Martin Marietta's. Previously, a G.E. division manager's job was regarded as safe if sales grew at least as fast as the United States economy. Mr. Welch decided that was a formula for failure in the global economy, since markets in Europe and Asia were growing more rapidly than in America. Gain in Efficiency</p>
        <p>G.E.'s sales this year will exceed $65 billion, compared with $27 billion in 1981 -- a stunning gain in efficiency considering that it now employs far fewer people. It eliminated about 124,000 jobs during the 1980's. Another 37,000 jobs will be trimmed through the Martin Marietta deal, bringing total employment to 240,000 by year end.</p>
        <p>Mr. Welch gained attention after he was given control in 1968 of G.E.'s plastics department, with sales of less than $100 million. Today it has more than $5 billion in sales. "He would do radical stuff to trick the bureaucracy," Mr. Tichy said. "The only reason he survived is because his sales were growing at 30 percent a year and his unit was making a lot of money. People thought he was a wild man, but he became bulletproof because his performance won out."</p>
        <p>Mr. Walsh of Tenneco said Mr. Smith's initial moves at G.M. to promote younger executives into top positions was a sign that he understood the importance of finding talented allies within the vast G.M. organization.</p>
        <p>"In a hierarchical organization, bosses don't do much work," Mr. Walsh said. "They just preside and take all the credit. It's criminal. A lot of good young people are buried down there, and their bosses are happy to keep them buried."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
