<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tech Notes; In Search of Sailboat Speed</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="704708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRIFOILER INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLOYD, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED81031F934A3575BC0A962958260" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tech Notes; In Search of Sailboat Speed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LLOYD, BARBARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR sailors, the 50-knot speed barrier is a goal that keeps getting closer but has not been attained. Yet the quest for that speed -- 57.5 miles an hour, to landlubbers -- has spawned technology that is available on a recreational sailboat.</p>
        <p>More water bug than boat, the 29-foot vessel is called a Trifoiler. It looks like a trimaran, a boat with three hulls. But when the wind blows at 10 miles an hour or more, all three fiberglass structures rise out of the water, and the craft rides on L-shaped foils that work like underwater airplane wings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR sailors, the 50-knot speed barrier is a goal that keeps getting closer but has not been attained. Yet the quest for that speed -- 57.5 miles an hour, to landlubbers -- has spawned technology that is available on a recreational sailboat.</p>
        <p>More water bug than boat, the 29-foot vessel is called a Trifoiler. It looks like a trimaran, a boat with three hulls. But when the wind blows at 10 miles an hour or more, all three fiberglass structures rise out of the water, and the craft rides on L-shaped foils that work like underwater airplane wings.</p>
        <p>Capable of speeds up to about 35 m.p.h., or 30 knots (a knot is equal to 1.15 m.p.h.), the boat carries one or two people. They sit in a center cockpit, like pilots in a fighter jet.</p>
        <p>The Trifoiler has two sails, one on each of the boat's outriggers, or amas (pronounced AH-mahs), which resemble small surfboards. Sensor paddles reach out in front of the amas to regulate the angle of the in-water foils, which provide lift and stability as the boat flies about a foot above the surface.</p>
        <p>Trifoiler Inc., a privately held manufacturer in Lakewood, Calif., has sold eight of the $11,900 hydrofoil boats since introducing the craft earlier this year. Greg Ketterman, an engineer from Long Beach, Calif., and the founder of the company, said it had five more ready to deliver and a backlog of eight orders that it hoped to fill by the end of the summer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ketterman designed the vessel, and he and his brother, Dan, have refined it for several speed-record attempts by Russell Long, a former America's Cup skipper.</p>
        <p>The prototype model, using lighter-weight materials and a different design than the Trifoiler that is available commercially, reached a speed of 43.55 knots in 1992. The current sailboat speed record -- 46.52 knots -- was set earlier this year, by a custom-built Australian hydrofoil boat, "Yellow Pages Endeavour."</p>
        <p>While other companies are at work on boats with hydrofoils, the Trifoiler model is the only production sailboat on the market that uses them.</p>
        <p>The Trifoiler performs best on flat water. It will sail in rough seas, Mr. Ketterman said, but waves of more than three feet slow it down. The outrigger design gives the Trifoiler a stability that makes it unlikely to flip over even at high speed, he said.</p>
        <p>Randy McMillan, a recreational sailor from Suttons Bay, Mich., bought one of the first production models last month and has been sailing on the bays of Lake Michigan.</p>
        <p>"When you're going 25 to 35 m.p.h. in a sailboat," he said, "it's a real rush. The feeling when the boat is up on foils is like being in an airplane."</p>
        <p>But it is not a boat for light winds, he said, because at low speeds it is just like a regular sailboat. "You want to be up on the foils, or you don't want to sail," he said. BARBARA LLOYD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
