<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Yankees' Biggest Task: Neutralize Brown</title>
    <meta content="17YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD SERIES PREVIEW: YANKEES VS. PADRES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Diego Padres</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wells, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E4DC1E3AF934A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Yankees' Biggest Task: Neutralize Brown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees biggest task in World Series against San Diego Padres will be to beat Padres pitcher Kevin Brown; Brown will go against David Wells in Game 1; charts; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe Torre carried a thick red binder through the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday, holding it against his hip, like mother and child. The binder, as thick as any Yellow Pages, contained the Yankees' scouting report of the San Diego Padres, intelligence to be used in the World Series that begins tonight at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>A section of the report addressed the performances of Torre's hitters against the San Diego pitchers -- such as Kevin Brown, who will throw against the Yankees' David Wells in Game 1. Torre could not have been encouraged by numbers that illuminate Brown's dominance. Bernie Williams, the Yankees' cleanup batter, has just 4 hits in 17 career at-bats against Brown, for a .235 average. Chili Davis is a career .170 hitter against the San Diego right-hander, Tino Martinez .118.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe Torre carried a thick red binder through the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday, holding it against his hip, like mother and child. The binder, as thick as any Yellow Pages, contained the Yankees' scouting report of the San Diego Padres, intelligence to be used in the World Series that begins tonight at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>A section of the report addressed the performances of Torre's hitters against the San Diego pitchers -- such as Kevin Brown, who will throw against the Yankees' David Wells in Game 1. Torre could not have been encouraged by numbers that illuminate Brown's dominance. Bernie Williams, the Yankees' cleanup batter, has just 4 hits in 17 career at-bats against Brown, for a .235 average. Chili Davis is a career .170 hitter against the San Diego right-hander, Tino Martinez .118.</p>
        <p>The Yankees faced Brown when he pitched in the American League from 1986 to 1995, before he made improvements. The only regular with a career average over .300 against Brown is third baseman Scott Brosius at .409.</p>
        <p>''He throws a sinking fastball at about 97 m.p.h.,'' Brosius said drolly. ''That would make him a pretty good pitcher.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees, coming off a season in which they won 114 games and had playoff victories against Texas and Cleveland, are strong favorites in this four-of-seven-game series; their lineup is deeper, and they have more depth in their pitching rotation and in their bullpen. If the World Series extends to seven games, four of those will be played in the Stadium, where the Yankees are 66-20 this year.</p>
        <p>But Brown, who is a sturdy 6 feet 4 inches and 200 pounds and is a C.I.A.-serious competitor, could be the great equalizer; if the Padres beat the Yankees and prevent Torre's team from assuming its place in baseball history, Brown will presumably play a major role. Brown, perhaps baseball's most durable pitcher, could pitch Games 1, 4 and 7, and in spite of their dubious personal records against him, the Yankees will probably need to neutralize or beat him at least once to win this series.</p>
        <p>Since he left the Baltimore Orioles after the 1995 season, Brown has learned how to better control his emotions and has added a four-seam fastball (which sails high in the strike zone) and a darting, diving forkball to a repertory that already included a sinking fastball with stunning movement. He went 18-7 with a 2.38 earned run average for the Padres this season and is 2-1 with a 1.44 e.r.a. in the post-season.</p>
        <p>''I knew he'd make a difference,'' said Bruce Bochy, the Padres' manager. ''I didn't know he'd make this big of an impact over our year. He's made a huge difference.''</p>
        <p>Torre said: ''Pitchers can dominate a game, no question. We know Kevin Brown is a good pitcher. Roger Clemens is a good pitcher. Pedro Martinez is a good pitcher. We just go out and try to do our thing. Hopefully, if he makes mistakes, we can take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>In the past, Brown has sometimes been his own worst enemy, with a tendency to try too hard and overthrow after he allows one or two cheap hits or somebody behind him makes an error.</p>
        <p>''For a guy with stuff like that,'' one A.L. executive said, ''a lot of times something seems to happen to keep him from winning.''</p>
        <p>Brown will be facing the major leagues' most potent lineup: the Yankees averaged six runs per game and, with their experienced, patient hitters, they will force Brown to throw strikes. Torre made two adjustments to his starting lineup that seemed to be a reaction to Brown. Brosius, who has batted eighth or ninth virtually the entire season, was bumped up to seventh, to a position where he has a better chance to drive in runs; and Ricky Ledee, a rookie, was inserted in the ninth spot and will start in left field to give the Yankees six left-handed hitters. Against Brown this year, left-handed batters hit 20 percentage points higher than right-handed batters did.</p>
        <p>Bochy said that Andy Ashby would pitch Game 2 and Sterling Hitchcock Game 3. He did not announce his starters for subsequent games, leaving the option to use Brown on three days' rest in Game 4. Torre, on the other hand, is committed to four starters -- Wells in Games 1 and 5, Orlando Hernandez in Games 2 and 6, David Cone in Games 3 and 7 and Andy Pettitte in Game 4.</p>
        <p>Torre acknowledged that he essentially shaped the back end of his rotation around Cone's needs: the right-hander has sometimes struggled in cold weather, and by starting in Game 3 on Tuesday, Cone will throw in the warmth of San Diego. Should the Series go to seven games, however, Cone would pitch on a late October night in New York, and the weather could become a factor.</p>
        <p>Hernandez pitched seven shutout innings against Cleveland in Game 4 of the American League Championship Series -- and for that he earned a promotion in the World Series. Pettitte pitched poorly in his only start in the league championship series, and he is now also coping with his father's recovery from heart surgery. Pettitte is in Texas, away from the Yankees, and Torre is not sure when the left-hander will rejoin the team.</p>
        <p>WORLD SERIES PREVIEW: YANKEES VS. PADRES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
