<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A handful of marketers get personal, summoning consumers by name with customized ads on the Internet.</title>
    <meta content="28ECOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/28/technology/28ecom.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1592853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="E-Commerce Report"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">About.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lycos Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dotomi Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldfinger, Yair</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/E-Commerce</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/E-Commerce Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Outdoor Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">About.com</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D81738F93BA15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A handful of marketers get personal, summoning consumers by name with customized ads on the Internet.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Web Marketers Get Personal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Tedeschi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Visitors to Web sites like About.com, Lycos and nytimes.com will soon be shown customized ads that will address them by name, mention some of their past purchases at site and urge them to return; ads will be seen only by people who have agreed to receive electronic messages from companies they have done business with; analysts and industry executives say new approach will offer online sellers new and inexpensive way to retain customers they have spent heavily to acquire; company behind new ads is Dotomi, brainchild of Yair Goldfinger, who created technology that eventually became AOL's instant messaging service and who sees his 'direct messaging' system as kind of commercial analog to instant messaging; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the 2002 movie ''Minority Report,'' the character played by Tom Cruise, John Anderton, darted through a city in which electronic billboard advertisements spoke to him by name.</p>
        <p>The next wave of Internet advertising could make John Andertons of us all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A handful of marketers are getting personal, summoning consumers by name with customized ads on the Internet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the 2002 movie ''Minority Report,'' the character played by Tom Cruise, John Anderton, darted through a city in which electronic billboard advertisements spoke to him by name.</p>
        <p>The next wave of Internet advertising could make John Andertons of us all.</p>
        <p>Starting next week, a handful of marketers in the United States will begin sending customized ads to Internet users who land on About.com, Lycos and nytimes.com, among other Web sites. So, instead of seeing a random advertisement for the Audio Book Club or the e-travel agencies Orbitz and Priceline, you might see ads addressing you by name, mentioning some of your past purchases at the site and urging you to return.</p>
        <p>(The idea sounds spookier than it is. Only those who have agreed to receive electronic messages from companies they have done business with will see the ads.)</p>
        <p>Analysts and industry executives say this new approach offers online sellers a new and inexpensive way to retain customers they have spent heavily to acquire. In recent years, marketers have mainly used e-mail messages to persuade users to return, but spam filters now block many legitimate commercial e-mail messages and spam-weary consumers are less inclined to open commercial messages that make it to their in-boxes.</p>
        <p>The company behind the new ads, Dotomi, is the brainchild of Yair Goldfinger, who created the technology that eventually became AOL's instant messaging service. According to John Federman, Dotomi's chief executive and the former publisher of PCWeek, Mr. Goldfinger developed Dotomi's ''direct messaging'' system as a kind of commercial analog to instant messaging.</p>
        <p>''This lets you create, in effect, a marketer buddy list,'' Mr. Federman said, borrowing a phrase known to instant messaging system users as the list of people who have permission to contact them. ''You're enabling a group of marketers with whom you have a stated affinity to send you electronic communications.''</p>
        <p>The publishers' technology systems will be set up to recognize when a user arrives, and will then retrieve an ad that has been built especially for that user. Just as Web sites like Amazon and others place cookies, or tiny text files containing identification numbers, onto their customers' computers so they can recognize them when they return, so, too, will Dotomi's publishing clients use cookies to spot customers of Dotomi's advertisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Federman said Dotomi tested the service last year in Israel, where the company's technology team is based. Customers were initially seduced by the novelty of being summoned by name to click on an ad, and they did so at a rate of 34 percent. (The average click rate for a so-called banner ad in the United States is less than a half of a percent.) Once the novelty wore thin, the click rates settled at 7 to 12 percent -- still a rate many advertisers would pay dearly for.</p>
        <p>Dotomi's 70 Israeli clients, who include Burger King, American Express and Holiday Inn, use the ads in several ways. El Al, the Israeli airline, sends out birthday messages to its customers. Other companies remind users to catch the sunset at a specific time, since they know where their customers live. Some companies send special offers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Federman said four marketers have signed up for the service in the two months since Dotomi began offering it in the United States: Orbitz, Audio Book Club and two other advertisers whose names will not be disclosed until ads begin running. Another five, Mr. Federman said, are about to sign agreements. After a test period, Dotomi will charge $20 for every 1,000 displayed.</p>
        <p>By comparison, some Web sites can charge $40 to $100 for 1,000 displays on popular pages -- those that attract car buyers, for instance, said Charlene Li, an advertising analyst with Forrester Research. But for ads that run without regard to a highly targeted audience, publishers typically charge about $2 per 1,000.</p>
        <p>In turn, Dotomi will pay publishers an undisclosed premium above what it would cost to place ads, in exchange for the publishers overseeing a slightly more complicated advertisement delivery method. Mr. Federman said that 70 percent of Internet users in the United States visit at least one of the publishers Dotomi has signed up to run the ads.</p>
        <p>According to executives at MediaBay, which markets audio books and vintage radio broadcasts through its catalog and online businesses, Audio Book Club and Radio Spirits, the Dotomi ads are a cheap alternative to the company's paper-based ads. ''Based on Dotomi's average click rates and our traditional rates, we believe we can lower our cost per order up to 50 percent,'' said Magnus Gustafsson, MediaBay's senior vice president for marketing.</p>
        <p>The ads, which MediaBay will start running next month, will incorporate the names and past purchases of the roughly 130,000 people who have given the company its e-mail address. For instance, if a customer purchased all of John Grisham's older novels through Audio Book Club, the company will send them an ad promoting the new Grisham releases on whatever Dotomi-affiliated Web site they happen to be visiting.</p>
        <p>Initially, not every advertisement will contain an offer created exclusively for them. Rather, MediaBay will create a handful of offers for broader customer segments -- say all the people who bought Walter Isaacson's Benjamin Franklin biography -- then simply affix a name to each offer and keep it ready for when a customer lands in Dotomi's Web.</p>
        <p>MediaBay will obtain permission, via e-mail message, to send the ads. It will also promote the ads in its catalog mailings and during the checkout process on its Web sites.</p>
        <p>Publishers, meanwhile, will welcome the chance to run Dotomi's ads, said Craig Swerdloff, the vice president for national direct marketing sales at MaxOnline, which places ads on a network of more than 1,500 Web sites like Billboard.com, CheapTickets.com, EdgarOnline and DilbertZone.com.</p>
        <p>Because Dotomi is paying publishers more than what typical advertisers would pay, ''most publishers will say 'Sure, let's see how our visitors take to this,''' Mr. Swerdloff said. ''If customers start complaining, sites can always turn it down.''</p>
        <p>Even privacy-sensitive consumers will have little cause to worry, though, said Fran Maier, president of TrustE, a nonprofit privacy certification program for Web sites.</p>
        <p>''Our concern was that people would see these ads and think, 'Oh my God, my information is being taken and used,''' she said. ''But this is completely opt-in, so customers should know what they're getting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Federman, of Dotomi, also said the company lacks the willingness or technological ability to track a consumer's behavior across different Web sites to, say, display an auto ad when it determines a customer has been surfing car-buying sites.</p>
        <p>Analysts suggest that if Dotomi can prepare consumers well enough to minimize the spook factor of personalized ads, it could create a lucrative market. But Denise Garcia, an online advertising analyst with Gartner, a technology consulting firm, noted that marketers have to persuade a significant number of consumers to agree to the ads before it's worth their while to embark on such campaigns.</p>
        <p>''And until a lot of marketers are doing this,'' Ms. Garcia said, ''it won't be a huge money maker.''</p>
        <p>Sarah Fay, president of Carat Interactive, a Boston-based advertising firm, predicted that advertisers would work hard to make customers comfortable with such ads.</p>
        <p>''Loyalty marketing is becoming one of the top ways to increase sales,'' Ms. Fay said. ''You see it with catalogers, and how sophisticated they are about mining their e-mail databases. This gives you a new way to touch people who really have a relationship with your company.''</p>
        <p>E-Commerce Report</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
