<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices Decline Case on Race and School</title>
    <meta content="21SCOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1185643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E1D7113AF932A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices Decline Case on Race and School</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court passes up chance to clarify law on use of race as factor in assigning or admitting students to public schools; lets stand, without comment, ruling by federal appeals court in Richmoned, Va, which found Washington suburb of Montgomery County, Md, was improperly taking race into account in deciding which students could transfer from one school to another; accepts appeal from state of Washington stemming from 1997 court decision on treatment of violent sex offenders, which upheld constitutionality of program that made offenders who complete criminal sentences subject to subsequent open-ended civil commitment; will decide whether federal courts should enforce arbitrator's judgment reinstating worker dismissed for failing drug test (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court today passed up its latest opportunity to clarify the law on the use of race as a factor in assigning or admitting students to public schools.</p>
        <p>Without comment, the justices let stand a ruling by the federal appeals court in Richmond, Va., which found last year that the Washington suburb of Montgomery County, Md., was improperly taking race into account in deciding which students could transfer from one school to another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court today passed up its latest opportunity to clarify the law on the use of race as a factor in assigning or admitting students to public schools.</p>
        <p>Without comment, the justices let stand a ruling by the federal appeals court in Richmond, Va., which found last year that the Washington suburb of Montgomery County, Md., was improperly taking race into account in deciding which students could transfer from one school to another.</p>
        <p>The school district generally did not permit transfers that would decrease racial or ethnic diversity. It was sued by the parents of a white kindergartener who was denied a transfer from his neighborhood school, where the white population was small and declining rapidly, to a math and science ''magnet'' program at another elementary school with a majority of white students.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit said that even if the school district had a ''compelling'' interest in preserving racial diversity -- a question the appeals court did not decide -- it could not achieve that goal through a policy that amounted to ''mere racial balancing in a pure form.''</p>
        <p>The case had been watched closely in the world of public education, where school boards and administrators have been troubled by lower court rulings making them legally vulnerable for diversity policies that, not many years ago, were welcomed as creative strategies addressing white flight and segregated housing patterns. The Fourth Circuit's decision ''puts school districts in the untenable position of contributing to racial isolation,'' the Montgomery County board told the justices in its appeal, Montgomery County Public Schools v. Eisenberg, No. 99-1069.</p>
        <p>The National School Boards Association filed a brief supporting the district's appeal, joined by other education groups including the Council of the Great City Schools, a coalition of the country's 57 biggest urban school systems. ''The Fourth Circuit gave no attention whatsoever to the positive attributes of diversity, the views of local educators, or diversity as a positive academic strategy,'' the brief said.</p>
        <p>The school boards association said today it was ''profoundly disappointed'' that the justices would not hear the case, adding that ''education attorneys advising the 15,000 school districts across the country still remain in the dark as to what constitutional standard applies when dealing with this issue.''</p>
        <p>With the growth of magnet-school and school-choice programs, the question of student assignment is receiving renewed attention across the country. In one case, the federal appeals court in Boston invalidated a preferential admissions policy for the Boston Latin School, a prestigious public school, in a 1998 ruling that Boston school officials decided not to appeal for fear of inviting an adverse Supreme Court ruling that would be binding nationwide.</p>
        <p>Nearly simultaneously with its Montgomery County decision, the Fourth Circuit in a separate case from Arlington County, Va., invalidated a weighted lottery plan that school officials used to ensure minority attendance at a kindergarten magnet school. The suburban Virginia county has appealed to the Supreme Court, but the justices are not scheduled to consider the case until next month.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Eisenberg, the father of the plaintiff in the Montgomery County case, who also served as a lawyer for his son, told the court in his brief that the case was correctly decided and there was no need to review it. ''A denial of the petition will give a powerful incentive to those school districts seeking to promote diversity to begin at the earliest possible date to devise lawful policies to achieve this worthy goal,'' the brief said.</p>
        <p>It has been 22 years since the court, in the Bakke case, ruled that while quotas were unconstitutional, diversity was a permissible goal to be taken into account in public university admissions. Not only is it unclear how that ruling applies outside the context of higher education, but the viability of the Bakke decision itself is in considerable doubt. In a case the justices declined to review four years ago, a federal appeals court struck down a minority admissions program at the University of Texas Law School and declared that Bakke was no longer good law.</p>
        <p>There were these other developments at the court today:</p>
        <p>Sex Offenders</p>
        <p>The justices accepted an appeal from the state of Washington stemming from a 1997 Supreme Court decision on the treatment of violent sex offenders.</p>
        <p>In a case from Kansas three years ago, the court upheld the constitutionality of a program that made violent sex offenders who have completed their criminal sentences subject to a subsequent, open-ended civil commitment, with the goal of protecting the public and treating the offender. Because the aim was treatment and not punishment, the court said then in Kansas v. Hendricks, the additional confinement was neither double jeopardy nor an imposition of a new penalty for an old offense.</p>
        <p>The Kansas program was modeled on one adopted by the state of Washington under a 1990 law, the Sexually Violent Predator Statute, which the Washington Supreme Court had upheld and which appeared safe from challenge under the 1997 Kansas ruling.</p>
        <p>But last year, acting on a petition for a writ of habeas corpus from a convicted rapist who has been held under the law for nine years following his release from prison, the federal appeals court in San Francisco found that if the actual conditions of the offender's confinement appeared to be punitive rather than therapeutic, the extra time could raise double jeopardy and new-penalty problems despite the ''civil'' designation.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit held that Andre Brigham Young was entitled to a chance to prove his contentions that he was not receiving treatment and that conditions at the state's Special Commitment Center were equivalent to prison or worse.</p>
        <p>In its appeal, Seling v. Young, No. 99-1185, Washington State is arguing that the decision undercut the 1997 ruling and opened similar programs to court challenges as conditions of confinement fluctuate. Twenty-three states joined Washington's appeal.</p>
        <p>Drug Testing</p>
        <p>The court agreed to decide whether federal courts should enforce an arbitrator's judgment reinstating a worker who has been dismissed for failing a drug test.</p>
        <p>Many labor contracts provide for grievance and arbitration of such dismissals. Arbitrators' awards are usually enforced by courts, but not if the award is found to be against public policy. The lower federal courts are sharply divided on how to define this exception, both in general and in the context presented here: a worker who has failed a drug test and has been ordered reinstated to a job in which an impaired employee could imperil public safety.</p>
        <p>In this case, a man who drove a West Virginia coal company's truck was dismissed for failing a drug test for the second time but was ordered reinstated by an arbitrator. The Fourth Circuit upheld the judgment, finding that an arbitration award was contrary to public policy only if it required the performance of an illegal act. The company would violate no law by keeping the driver on the job, the appeals court said.</p>
        <p>Other courts have ruled that there is a general public policy, even if no specific law, against employing drug users in inherently dangerous jobs. The justices accepted the appeal, Eastern Associated Coal Corp. v. United Mine Workers, No. 99-1038.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
