<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Dr. Irwin Redlener; Making Health Care Better for Children</title>
    <meta content="16KIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1168860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Children's Health Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Redlener, Irwin (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Donna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EFDE163AF935A25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Dr. Irwin Redlener; Making Health Care Better for Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA GREENE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greene, Donna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Irwin Redlener, president and co-founder of Children's Health Fund and president of Children's Hospital at Montefiore Medical Center in Bronx, answers questions on efforts to improve children's health care services in Westchester County, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR more than three decades, Dr. Irwin Redlener of New Rochelle, president of the Children's Hospital at Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx, has worked on behalf of children who, usually because of their economic circumstances, are underserved by the health care system.</p>
        <p>Frustrating? Yes, he admits, but he hopes that today's prosperity will result in policies that will help the 20 million or so American children who are without health insurance or otherwise have problems obtaining health care.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR more than three decades, Dr. Irwin Redlener of New Rochelle, president of the Children's Hospital at Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx, has worked on behalf of children who, usually because of their economic circumstances, are underserved by the health care system.</p>
        <p>Frustrating? Yes, he admits, but he hopes that today's prosperity will result in policies that will help the 20 million or so American children who are without health insurance or otherwise have problems obtaining health care.</p>
        <p>Dr. Redlener is president and co-founder of the Children's Health Fund, a philanthropic organization, which he and the singer Paul Simon established in 1987 to support health care programs for children. He is also professor of pediatrics at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine and a lecturer in pediatrics at Harvard Medical School. His wife, Karen, with whom he works on many of his projects, is director of the New York Children's Health Project.</p>
        <p>Here are excepts from a recent conversation with Dr. Redlener:</p>
        <p>Q. With a hospital being built at Montefiore and another at the Westchester Medical Center, will there not be too many children's units in this region?</p>
        <p>A. We are so far behind when it comes to children's hospitals that we could actually probably use, besides the two you mentioned, one in southern Manhattan or Brooklyn. In terms of pure need, let me give you an idea of what it is: in Philadelphia, where there are about 200,000 children, there are three children's hospitals. In the Bronx alone there are almost 400,000 children, and with southern Westchester over 400,000 children,  and there has never been a children's hospital in the Bronx even though it is the largest and most medically undeserved urban area in the United States.</p>
        <p>So I'm not the slightest bit concerned about too much in the way of children's services.</p>
        <p>Q. Why has health care not gotten better for poor children?</p>
        <p>A. The reason is that the prosperity we are enjoying, if you start looking at the figures, is one that is exaggerating the extreme wealth at the upper end of the economic scale and so far not doing much at the lower and middle-lower ends of the economic scale. We have had what I consider to be an intractable level of child poverty in this country that hovers between 20 and 25 percent of American children living in poverty. It has been that way without change for basically more than a decade.</p>
        <p>One of the problems is that we have not provided the basic elements needed to get out of poverty -- making sure that people are healthy, especially in early childhood, and that the educational system is top notch. Health care and early health services -- and I mean physical and emotional health and stability -- are the absolute essential building blocks for making people into adults who will be productive. If they're not healthy, they will do poorly in school. They're both chronically ill and under educated, and this has a profound effect on the general economic level in the United States and on the ability of people currently in poverty to get out of poverty.</p>
        <p>Q. Is it frustrating to realize that so little has been accomplished when you have talked about the need for better health care for 30 years?</p>
        <p>A. It is definitely frustrating, and it is difficult to understand why it takes so long to change this. People say that it took a long time for it to get the way it is, and it's not going to change overnight. But I think 30 years is beyond overnight already. I am frustrated, but I do think there is a sense of hopefulness now. In 1997, for example, the federal government passed the State Child Health Insurance Program, providing $24 billion over five years to expand health insurance. This was out of the blue and sponsored by Senators Edward M. Kennedy and Orrin Hatch, representing two different parties, and very strongly pushed by President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore. It has taken a long time to get implemented, but we're really starting to roll on this. We've had about two million kids now enrolled on it.</p>
        <p>The other thing is that the children themselves are awesome in their ability to inspire hopefulness. People always ask me, Is it depressing to work with kids who are under the duress of the adverse conditions that they live in? I and my wife, Karen, have worked together on this since 1971 when I ran a medical firm in Arkansas and she was a Vista volunteer. While we feel frustrated, we are  hopeful about the future. The new children's hospital is not going to be just a hospital but a whole new child health system. We expect to be seeing 5,000 to 6,000 inpatients and more than 100,000 outpatients a year, and another couple of hundred thousand children will be using various elements of this child health network that we're establishing. There are going to be no financial barriers whatsoever to get into this hospital and its whole system.</p>
        <p>Q. You mentioned the support of Senator Hatch, a Republican, for the children's health insurance program. Does that give you the hope that children's health care will not be a Democratic issue only?</p>
        <p>A. Yes. The fact that he was involved as a true partner with Senator Kennedy in 1997 is a hopeful sign. Many of us have been pleasantly shocked to see health care back on the agenda in the presidential campaign. Although right now it has been a Democratic dynamic, I'm sure Republicans area going to be asked to state their views clearly about how they think we're going to solve some of these enormous health care challenges. Some of us are going to be measuring candidates on how they approach children's issues in general. My wish is that everybody push these candidates to focus on the health care, educational and social needs of children. There is no greater gift that we can give the country.</p>
        <p>Q. As a health care advocate, what is your involvement with Paul Simon?</p>
        <p>A.  In 1985 through 1987, I was involved with U.S.A. for Africa, which did the ''We Are the World'' song, and I was involved with the very significant Ethiopian famine relief. And Paul Simon was one of the singers on the song, and I was director of grants and medical director for the organization. Paul got very interested in the problems of the homeless in New York. As it turns out, 10 percent of the money raised by U.S.A. for Africa was designated to remain in the U.S. to deal with hunger and homeless issues.</p>
        <p>So Paul asked the organization if he could get some help with doing something for homeless children in New York. And he was referred to me. Paul and I took what turned out to be a fateful tour of some of the facilities that were taking care of homeless families. And we walked into the Martinique Hotel in Manhattan in the fall of 1986, where there were 1,000 children and their families, warehoused in a squalid tower in New York City. The needs of these kids was pretty overwhelming.</p>
        <p>So I developed the New York Children's Health Project, and it was about setting up a mobile health care program for homeless children in the city. I recruited Karen to get involved in this, and she did a lot of research about the health care needs of kids. Paul got very involved with all of this. He basically paid for the first mobile unit of the New York Children's Health Project, which is  custom designed, and he built the 35-foot-long, fully equipped rolling pediatric clinic. We now have five of them in New York, now all affiliated with Montefiore Medical Center. They comprise the largest health care program for homeless kids in the United States.</p>
        <p>Then Paul and I set up a foundation called the Children's Health Fund, and Karen is involved, and we have been developing this model, which we have now spread to 15 communities around the United States. All of them use mobile units and other means to provide what we believe is high-quality medical care to medically underserved children.</p>
        <p>Q. Who is financing the New York Children's Health Project now?</p>
        <p>A. My foundation, and by the way two-thirds of the money we raise, which is between $5 million and $6 million a year, is from corporate partnerships.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
