<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Visions of Food, Food and More Food</title>
    <meta content="16PLAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1168976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Repertory Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wodehouse, P G (1881-1975)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vaughan, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Angela</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Play's the Thing, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6153AF935A25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Visions of Food, Food and More Food</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>LONG BRANCH</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews New Jersey Repertory Co's production of P G Wodehouse's 1926 adaptation of The Play's the Thing, starring Stuart Vaughan and Angela Roberts, and directed by Vaughan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REFLECTING upon ''The Play's the Thing'' after last Sunday's matinee at the New Jersey Repertory Company's Lumia Theater here stirs dangerous culinary notions into a theater critic's notebook. Instead of providing food for thought, Stuart Vaughan's undernourished staging of what ought to be a delectable trifle summoned thoughts of food. Imagine the joys of writing about the joys of eating.</p>
        <p>There are heavyweight questions to ponder. Does evaluating an art form diminish the enjoyment of it? Or is appreciation enhanced and pleasure intensified after knowledge and experience? And what on earth do food dreams have to do with theater reviewing?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REFLECTING upon ''The Play's the Thing'' after last Sunday's matinee at the New Jersey Repertory Company's Lumia Theater here stirs dangerous culinary notions into a theater critic's notebook. Instead of providing food for thought, Stuart Vaughan's undernourished staging of what ought to be a delectable trifle summoned thoughts of food. Imagine the joys of writing about the joys of eating.</p>
        <p>There are heavyweight questions to ponder. Does evaluating an art form diminish the enjoyment of it? Or is appreciation enhanced and pleasure intensified after knowledge and experience? And what on earth do food dreams have to do with theater reviewing?</p>
        <p>In this case, everything. For it is clear that in Long Branch, the chow's the thing. The play is not. Nor is the direction or the acting. Mr. Vaughan is the director. Mr. Vaughan acts the leading role. These are issues.</p>
        <p>Fully craving the sustenance for the soul that only a live performance can bestow, and leaving (2 hours 35 minutes later) on empty, one professional theatergoer found satisfaction just across the parking lot. The out-of-the-way storefront restaurant is named, aptly, Heart and Soul, and its owners serve soul food with the dedication and brio of artists.</p>
        <p>Such are the byways of life: unexpected letdowns, substitute thrills, sudden discoveries. For Long Branch habitues and foodies, it is essential to mention Max's (best hot dogs, but the restaurant is seasonal) and Barbeque Churrasqueira (it's Portugese) -- both in the midst of Lucky Cheung-Jade Garden variety fast food Chinese and pizzerias by the dozen, not to mention America's omnipresent mecca crowned by the yellow arch.</p>
        <p>Oh yes, the play. Even though P. G. Wodehouse wrote the adaptation of Ferenc Molnar's 1926 comedy about artifice and illusion, it takes supreme stylists to put the wit back into the adapter's lines and the playwright's conceits.</p>
        <p>No question, it is time for another adaptation. No wonder Tom Stoppard seized the war horse, originally titled ''Play in the Castle,'' and turned it into ''Rough Crossing'' in 1984, transported the characters from a palace on the Italian Riviera to a luxury liner named the Dodo and transposed a staid operetta (the composing of which concocts the plot) into a dopey musical comedy. It's been a rough crossing indeed for Molnar, Stoppard style, but it now has a happening place in regional theaters. A McCarter Theater staging in Princeton was buoyed by a front-line cast and precise direction in 1994.</p>
        <p>While ''Rough Crossing'' appears regularly -- Hartford Stage in Connecticut has it scheduled May 25 to June 24 -- productions of ''The Play's the Thing'' pop up less regularly, most recently, to no avail, at the Roundabout Theater on Broadway in 1995.</p>
        <p>Molnar (1878-1952), often referred to as the Budapest boulevardier, is also well known for ''The Guardsman,'' which was seen in a musical version, ''Enter the Guardsman,'' last season at the New Jersey Shakespeare Festival in Madison, and is now being booked, odddly enough, onto cruise ships. How Molnar floats. And, of course, the playwright's not-so-funny ''Liliom'' inspired Rodgers and Hammerstein to write ''Carousel'' for eternity.</p>
        <p>''The Play's the Thing'' is, lovingly, about theater, blending satirical musings on the mechanics of playwriting and theater shop talk -- ship talk in Stoppard's variation -- with the contrivances of a sex farce. An overheard bedroom indiscretion, between the prima donna and an actor, replete with her protestations ''Hands off'' and ''Don't bite,'' is incorporated, word for word, by an ingenious playwright, Sandor Turai, into a script for a late-night divertissement to be performed in that grand castle with the paper-thin walls. Turai's life-saving motivation: to make sure the prima donna's eavesdropping lover, the  composer, doesn't walk.</p>
        <p>The infidels learn the script, but given the theatrical necessity of staged readings nowadays, that would hardly be necessary. And the playwright did not even take notes. There's a trick, but there goes the play if you let modern real life get in the way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vaughan does not allow real acting style to get in the way. His approach desperately needs less matter and more mirth. Turai's playwritiing partner, Mansky (William Shust) appears as more of a commandeering critic than a collaborator. Joseph Culliton, actor and lover, lurches a lot, being as bad onstage as he is behind the wall. Lurching is as much an acting manner as a body tic here; Angela Roberts, the actor's inamorata, lurches, too.</p>
        <p>Back to food. Turai's copious breakfast order is a laugh-getter. But it is generic cheese, ham, eggs and chicken he's asking for.</p>
        <p>Think Hungarian savories, creamy paprika potatoes, all that. Or Italian Riviera specials -- biscotti all'anice or biscottini al limone. Or bolt across the parking lot and order smothered pork chops, barbecued ribs, collard greens, peach cobbler.</p>
        <p>THE PLAY'S THE THING  New Jersey Repertory Company  Lumia Theater, 179 Broadway, Long Branch</p>
        <p>Through Sunday. Performances  today and Sunday at 2 p.m., Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>(732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
