<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3d Graders Improve Test Scores In Reading</title>
    <meta content="18SCHO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, Richard P (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DD1F38F93BA25754C0A961958260" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3d Graders Improve Test Scores In Reading</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Education Commissioner Richard P Mills releases results of statewide reading tests; figures show that reading scores of third-graders in New York City's most troubled schools showed their greatest gain in eight years; overall scores of city's third-grade students also inches up, reversing three-year decline; however, scores for students and sixth and eighth grades declined slightly, by less than 1 percentage point for sixth graders and by 1.5 percentage points for eighth graders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reading scores of third-grade students in New York City's most troubled schools showed their greatest gain in eight years, according to the results of state reading tests released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The overall scores of the city's third-grade students also inched up, reversing a three-year decline, according to the figures released by the State Education Commissioner, Richard P. Mills. But the scores for students in the sixth and eighth grades declined slightly, by less than 1 percentage point for the sixth graders and by 1.5 percentage points for the eighth graders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The reading scores of third-grade students in New York City's most troubled schools showed their greatest gain in eight years, according to the results of state reading tests released yesterday.</p>
        <p>The overall scores of the city's third-grade students also inched up, reversing a three-year decline, according to the figures released by the State Education Commissioner, Richard P. Mills. But the scores for students in the sixth and eighth grades declined slightly, by less than 1 percentage point for the sixth graders and by 1.5 percentage points for the eighth graders.</p>
        <p>The third graders' results on the state test, which was given in May, mirror the performance on another reading test given by the city school system in April. That test also showed an increase in their scores, though the results fell far short of the goals set by the Schools Chancellor, Rudy Crew, who has made improvement of third-grade reading scores a top priority.</p>
        <p>On the state reading examinations, nearly 67 percent of third graders met the minimum standards, compared with about 63 percent last year. But the schools on the state's list of failing schools reported the biggest increase: more than 54 percent of the third graders met minimum standards, up nearly 10 percentage points from last year.</p>
        <p>State education officials said they were heartened by the progress and noted that a dozen of those 87 schools had raised their scores enough that they could be removed from the failing list. ''After a long period of time, New York City has some good news, and New York City has some good news in some of the most challenging schools,'' Mr. Mills said yesterday. ''They have proved they can turn things around.''</p>
        <p>However, in a letter to Dr. Crew on Tuesday, Mr. Mills also identified four schools in New York City where test scores continued to sharply decline. Those schools, he said, suffered from a lack of sufficient textbooks, qualified teachers and effective leadership.</p>
        <p>The four schools are in a special district under the direct control of the Schools Chancellor. Three of them -- Public School 157 in Longwood, the Bronx; Intermediate School 111 in Bushwick, Brooklyn, and I.S. 193 in East Tremont, the Bronx -- have been in the Chancellor's District since last fall. The fourth -- I.S. 74, in Hunts Point, the Bronx -- was placed in the district two months ago.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Chancellor's spokeswoman, Chiara Coletti, noted that the nine schools in the special district were ones that needed the greatest attention. ''Within one school year, turning around each of the nine schools in the Chancellor's District would have been impossible,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Math scores on the state tests also showed improvement. More than 91 percent of third graders met minimum standards this year, compared with 88 percent last year, and nearly 87 percent of sixth graders met the standards, compared with 83 percent last year.</p>
        <p>More students with limited English skills were exempted from both the state and city tests this year; in order to make valid comparisons, city officials said they readjusted last year's data to exclude those students.</p>
        <p>Terry Astuto, a New York University education professor, applauded the improvement in scores but warned that it could be, in part, because teachers tailor their classes to the test. ''These are high-stakes tests,'' she said, ''for kids, teachers and schools.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
