<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Columbia/HCA Inquiry Is Said To Produce Evidence of Fraud</title>
    <meta content="18CARE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia/hca Healthcare Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichenwald, Kurt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DE1F38F93BA25754C0A961958260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Columbia/HCA Inquiry Is Said To Produce Evidence of Fraud</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eichenwald, Kurt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal prosecutors in investigation of Columbia/Healthcare Corp reportedly have obtained evidence that certain hospital executives responsible for obtaining reimbursement from Medicare submitted false information to Government; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors in the investigation of the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation have obtained evidence that certain hospital executives responsible for obtaining reimbursement from Medicare submitted false information to the Government, people with knowledge of the effort said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The first indictments based on that evidence are expected to come in as little as a few months in Florida, charging that those executives played roles in submitting reports to the Government that improperly inflated hospital costs, people with knowledge of the investigation said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal prosecutors in the investigation of the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation have obtained evidence that certain hospital executives responsible for obtaining reimbursement from Medicare submitted false information to the Government, people with knowledge of the effort said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The first indictments based on that evidence are expected to come in as little as a few months in Florida, charging that those executives played roles in submitting reports to the Government that improperly inflated hospital costs, people with knowledge of the investigation said.</p>
        <p>Those cost reports, which are submitted by virtually every hospital and other health care providers, are used to calculate Federal payments that bring hundreds of millions of dollars to Columbia each year. Medicare reimburses hospitals for certain costs, and uses the cost reports in calculating certain payment rates. The cost reports also help determine total compensation on outpatient services like home care.</p>
        <p>If brought, such charges would constitute the first indictments in the Columbia investigation. But, people with knowledge of the inquiry said, the investigation is continuing and may extend further.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, law enforcement officials served search warrants and removed documents from Columbia hospitals and offices in six states. Since then, an additional search was also conducted in Georgia for documents relevant to the inquiry, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>The searches continued yesterday, with agents of the Federal Bureau of Investigation seizing older hospital records maintained at certain warehouses, people with knowledge of the investigation said.</p>
        <p>More searches of Columbia's hospitals and offices are expected to continue for several days, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>''We're still putting out more search warrants,'' said June Gibbs Brown, Inspector General at the Department of Health and Human Services, following a Congressional hearing on Medicare fraud.</p>
        <p>Columbia stock dropped 93.75 cents a share yesterday, to $33.25, on the New York Stock Exchange; it was the Big Board's most actively traded stock, with 12.5 million shares changing hands. On Wednesday, word of the searches sent the stock tumbling $4.75 a share, or more than 12 percent.</p>
        <p>Grand juries in several states are investigating possible fraud in Columbia's cost reporting. Already, the Government has obtained the cooperation of several informants, including current and former employees of the company's hospitals.</p>
        <p>Those informants, along with information obtained during the last three years in a civil inquiry by the Inspector General of the Department of Health and Human Services, have allowed prosecutors to move far along with the investigation even before this week's searches, people with knowledge of the investigation said.</p>
        <p>Some of the Government's critical evidence comes from second sets of cost reports and worksheets maintained at Columbia hospitals that contained significantly lower expenses than in those reports submitted to the Government, people with knowledge of the investigation said.</p>
        <p>Investigators were said to believe that these second reports, known as reserve cost reports, along with the worksheets, provided evidence that at least some hospitals were knowingly inflating the numbers reported to the Government in the cost report to improperly raise total compensation.</p>
        <p>Reached for comment, Columbia officials yesterday referred to statements Wednesday by Samuel A. Greco, the company's senior vice president of financial operations.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Greco said that the company was unaware of a connection between the searches and any allegations about cost reports. He added that the company and its hospitals, relying on advice from accountants and other consultants, do their best to submit complete and accurate cost reports.</p>
        <p>''We hold ourselves to the highest standards,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Columbia investigation is multifaceted, and while cost-reporting is its centerpiece, the inquiry is also touching on other matters.</p>
        <p>People with knowledge of the inquiry said the investigation was also examining whether unnecessary blood tests were being regularly conducted at Columbia hospitals when doctors ordered diagnostic work-ups of patients.</p>
        <p>In particular, the investigation is examining the use of tests known as complete blood counts that were billed to Medicare, people with knowledge of the inquiry said.</p>
        <p>The kinds of charges that are typically brought in cost reporting cases include mail fraud and making a false statement to the Government. In criminal cases, mail fraud has a statute of limitation of five years. That means that cost reports dating back for half of the life of Columbia, which was founded in 1987, are relevant in the criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>The Federal precedents in Florida regarding cost-reporting fraud are particularly strong. A critical case on such crimes was decided last October by the Federal Court of Appeals in Atlanta, whose rulings are binding on the entire 11th Circuit, which covers Georgia, Florida and Alabama.</p>
        <p>In that decision, the appeals court affirmed the conviction of John E. Calhoon, a former executive with the Charter Medical Corporation, for cost reports he helped prepare for six different Georgia hospitals operated by Charter. Mr. Calhoon was convicted of mail fraud and making a false statement to the Government.</p>
        <p>According to the decision, Mr. Calhoon instructed subordinates to include expenses on the cost report that he did not believe could be properly reimbursed under the Federal Medicare system. But Mr. Calhoon told the subordinates to list those amounts on separate, reserve cost reports, as likely to be disallowed by the Government if they were audited. Such audits take place rarely.</p>
        <p>Those actions closely mirror what the Government is said to believe occurred at some Columbia hospitals, with hospital executives submitting costs that they expected would not be reimbursed if the submitted report was audited, and accounting for them as such on the reserve cost reports.</p>
        <p>Mr. Calhoon's conviction for misrepresenting certain expenses -- in that case, advertising costs as being expenditures for ''outreach'' -- was also affirmed by the court. During his trial, one of Mr. Calhoon's subordinates testified that the outreach account was created so that there would be no ''red flag'' alerting Medicare auditors to the non-reimbursable advertising expenses.</p>
        <p>The appeals court also held that the Government need not have been defrauded of any money for Mr. Calhoon's conviction to be upheld. In other words, even if auditors caught the improper cost items, Mr. Calhoon could be convicted of fraud.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
