<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daughter, Father and the Flag</title>
    <meta content="PLEDGE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="914388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oath of Allegiance</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Waterbury (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Howard, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byars, Tisha</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Byars, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flags, Emblems and Insignia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D91330F93AA35750C0A961958260" item-length="1410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daughter, Father and the Flag</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID HOWARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Howard, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tisha Byars, senior at Wilby High School in Waterbury, Conn, has set off intense debates about American flag and its symbolic value by refusing to stand and recite Pledge of Allegiance at start of each school day; her father, Dennis, believes African-Americans never got their freedom and are still slaves; Wilby's officials, rankled by Byars refusal to say the pledge, responded by segregating her in school's homeroom for the school year; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TISHA BYARS is an unlikely teen-age rebel. She scrunches her nose disapprovingly at pictures displayed in her family's Waterbury home and grins coyly when her parents divulge her fondness for the telephone. Ms. Byars, 17, is a tutor in her spare time and plans to teach elementary school. She hardly seems the greatest threat to the American way since Vietnam War protesters torched the American flag.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Byars, a high school senior, set off intense debates about the flag and its symbolic value by refusing to stand and recite the Pledge of Allegiance at the start of each school day. In the process, she awakened some of Waterbury's dormant racial tensions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TISHA BYARS is an unlikely teen-age rebel. She scrunches her nose disapprovingly at pictures displayed in her family's Waterbury home and grins coyly when her parents divulge her fondness for the telephone. Ms. Byars, 17, is a tutor in her spare time and plans to teach elementary school. She hardly seems the greatest threat to the American way since Vietnam War protesters torched the American flag.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Byars, a high school senior, set off intense debates about the flag and its symbolic value by refusing to stand and recite the Pledge of Allegiance at the start of each school day. In the process, she awakened some of Waterbury's dormant racial tensions.</p>
        <p>Her father, Dennis Byars, is the source of the silent protest. He believes the pledge falsely promises liberty and justice for all, and forbade his children from participating in the 30-word ceremony as early as the first grade. At a time when most children are concerned with Disney characters and Sesame Street, Tisha Byars' head was filled with stories of African slave ships and human bondage.</p>
        <p>''We still never got our freedom, even to this day,'' Mr. Byars said. ''We're still slaves, because we never got the equality we fought for. This country has never done anything for us.''</p>
        <p>The family's beliefs sparked howls of outrage from residents devoted to the flag's symbolic value. Richard LeBlanc, for example, whose brother was killed in action in Vietnam, said he is offended. ''These flags are presented to the mothers when these boys come home,'' Mr. LeBlanc said. ''They come right off the coffin. That's what the flag is all about.''</p>
        <p>Discussion on airwaves and in newspapers about patriotism and the cost of citizenship quickly led to angry words about race and the history of blacks in the United States.</p>
        <p>In a letter to The Waterbury Republican-American, Thomas E. DiMaio referred to Ms. Byars' ''rebellion against the country'' and went on to ask ''Will she be consistent with her principles and reject Government aid programs that provide benefits because of her race and gender? Will she refuse to benefit from government-mandated affirmative action programs? I think not.''</p>
        <p>Others encouraged the family to leave the United States for other parts of the world, like Africa.</p>
        <p>Many members of the African-American community rallied around the family. ''This is not about the pledge,'' said James L. Griffin, a black activist. ''A lot of people of all ethnic backgrounds have problems with saluting the flag for their own personal reasons. This is about bigots, claiming to be patriots, attacking a young girl to legitimize their attack on the black community.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the family's beliefs would never have been talk-show fodder if not for a flap over corn chips and the National Honor Society. It wasn't until Ms. Byars transferred to Wilby High School in Waterbury before her sophomore year that officials questioned the pledge protest.</p>
        <p>The Constitutional right to freedom of expression prohibits schools from forcing students to say the Pledge of Allegiance, even if school policy calls for a daily recitation. But in this case, Tisha Byars faced consequences for her protest, she and her parents say.</p>
        <p>Wilby officials, rankled by her refusal to say the pledge, responded by segregating her in the school's office during homeroom for the school year, the Byars family said.</p>
        <p>And the following year, Wilby officials blackballed Ms. Byars from the school's National Honor Society chapter, the girl's parents charge.</p>
        <p>School officials said they assigned Ms. Byars to the office for homeroom because her decision to remain seated during the pledge was disruptive and the Pledge of Allegiance issue never was a factor for the honor society's selection committee, said the school's principal, Martin Galvin.</p>
        <p>Ms. Byars, ranked 11th in her class, was rejected from the honor society because she was disciplined for eating chips in class during her junior year, he said. The school's policy has always been to refuse membership to students with even a single disciplinary referral, though juniors are given a chance to apply as seniors if they keep their record clean, Mr. Galvin said.</p>
        <p>''Those are the issues, and they've gotten lost, unfortunately,'' the principal said.</p>
        <p>When the Byars family filed the first known appeal of the National Honor Society selection process in the city's history, the Superintendent of Schools, Roger Damerow, formed a seven-member panel to hear arguments. That body rejected the Byars' appeal on Jan. 29. The family is now consulting with lawyers from the American Civil Liberties Union to decide whether to pursue the issue further.</p>
        <p>But it's the pledge issue that remains the most-debated aspect of the controversy.</p>
        <p>Waterbury excuses students from the pledge if they bring a note from their parents, expressing religious reasons for not reciting the pledge. Mr. Byars says he did send a note. Mr.Galvin said the note was initially honored but that the student was removed from homeroom for trying to persuade other students not to recite the pledge.</p>
        <p>In any case, Waterbury's policy goes a step beyond Connecticut's other big-city districts. Officials in Hartford, New Haven and Bridgeport said no policy exists for the recitation of the pledge in their schools, and no incidents have arisen. It's really at the teachers' discretion, said Webster Brooks, a Hartford administrator.</p>
        <p>Some in Waterbury believe the pledge should be mandatory at all functions.</p>
        <p>Waterbury veterans said the pledge is an appropriate way to pay homage to those who died for the country.</p>
        <p>''We feel we have one of the greatest countries in the world, and therefore give it its proper respect,'' said John G. Chiarella, spokesman for the Waterbury Veterans Memorial Committee. ''You have to know the proper means of respect. Everybody can do their own thing, but what we learned in the military is, if you don't have order, if you don't have certain codes of conduct for people to follow, what you have is a mob.''</p>
        <p>But to others, the pledge -- particularly in the context of Waterbury's sharply ethnic neighborhoods -- is inextricably connected to racism. How else to explain the caustic reaction toward a schoolgirl? After all, residents last summer warmly greeted former Mayor Joseph J. Santopietro when he was released from Federal prison pending an appeal of convictions of corruption charges, Mr. Griffin pointed out. ''They gave Santopietro a hero's welcome home after he ripped off the city,'' he charged, ''but here's a little girl who has a problem saluting the flag, and all these people are attacking her.''</p>
        <p>When the bi-weekly Waterbury Observer featured Ms. Byars on its cover, businesses in one neighborhood threatened to withdraw their advertisements, the paper's publisher, John Murray, said. An African-American activist, David Gilmore, then suggested organizing a boycott of the businesses that pulled advertising from the newspaper.</p>
        <p>The case has raised parenting questions as well. Some, including members of the black community, wondered whether Mr. Byars was right to impose his beliefs on a child, knowing they will create controversy at her expense.</p>
        <p>James Thompson of Waterbury, a member of a black family who grew up a Jehovah's Witness, was forbidden as a child from rising from his seat for the pledge or the National Anthem. But as an adult he rejected his parents' beliefs.</p>
        <p>''Being a Jehovah's Witness was, 'do this, do that, don't do this.' So you go through your life doing what you're told, but you don't know why you're doing it,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''You're living a life your parents want you to live.'' That, he said, was what Mr. Byars did to his daughter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byars said he has passed on to his daughter the strength and self-confidence she needs to excel in a world where racism still exists.</p>
        <p>''You have to bring about change with your children,'' he said. ''You can only change one person at a time. She has to stand with her head up and not be subservient. You can be respectful without being subservient.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
