<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fox Expected to Start Naming Cabinet Today in Mexico</title>
    <meta content="Y22FOX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/22/world/22FOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Editors' Note Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001123T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1249414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cabinets and Sub-Cabinets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castaneda, Jorge G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gil Diaz, Francisco</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5DD143AF931A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fox Expected to Start Naming Cabinet Today in Mexico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thompson, Ginger</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexican Pres-elect Vicente Fox Quesada is expected to start naming his cabinet; aims to shatter strength of old-boy networks that dominate politics; is expected to name Jorge G Castaneda foreign minister and economist Francisco Gil Diaz treasury secretary; selections follow extraordinary nationwide search that involved input from head hunters and advice from his rivals; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At last Vicente Fox Quesada is expected to begin announcing the choices for his cabinet, on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>With the announcements, Mr. Fox, who as the first person in 71 years to defeat the Institutional Revolutionary Party becomes president in 10 days, aims to shatter the strength of the old-boy networks that dominated politics. He has pledged to chose men and women from a variety of viewpoints and party affiliations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At last Vicente Fox Quesada is expected to begin announcing the choices for his cabinet, on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>With the announcements, Mr. Fox, who as the first person in 71 years to defeat the Institutional Revolutionary Party becomes president in 10 days, aims to shatter the strength of the old-boy networks that dominated politics. He has pledged to chose men and women from a variety of viewpoints and party affiliations.</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Mr. Fox is generally expected the appoint a leftist academic, Jorge G. Castaneda, as foreign minister and will try to keep Wall Street calm by selecting an eminent economist as treasury secretary. He is Francisco Gil Diaz, who is committed to upholding the free-market changes made by the departing president, Ernesto Zedillo.</p>
        <p>The selections are a result of an extraordinary nationwide search that involved as much input from head hunters and advice from Mr. Fox's rivals as it did from leaders of his own conservative National Action Party. The process has been subject to numerous delays and intense competition on the transition team.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Fox is known as more of a pragmatist than a party stalwart, members of his party have been quietly nervous about whether their leaders would be given prominent positions. Women's groups have pressured Mr. Fox to include a respectable number of their leaders.</p>
        <p>Leftist leaders of the Democratic Revolutionary Party refused to accept any positions in the cabinet.</p>
        <p>A number of those expected to be chosen will be longtime allies. But it appears that Mr. Fox will fulfill his promise to build a pluralistic government by appointing lawyers, academics, economists and business leaders with little government experience and just tenuous ties to his campaign.</p>
        <p>The diversity reflects not only Mr. Fox's pledges to voters and promises of change. It also demonstrates his pragmatism. Because he will be president without a majority in Congress, it is crucial to build bridges in many camps if he is to win approval for the unpopular programs that he hopes to undertake, including reforming the tax structure and privatizing electricity.</p>
        <p>Although experts praise the variety, others wonder whether people with such vast ideological differences will be able to work together. Some experts wonder whether a team of unknowns will be able to live up to the high expectations for reinventing how Mexico is governed.</p>
        <p>''I think it just might work,'' said a political expert, Gabriel Guerra. ''Having a plural cabinet diminishes the resistance that he is going to have on all fronts. And it is a much better alternative than if he had put together a highly ideological team.''</p>
        <p>In the clearest sign of Mr. Fox's commitment, he will pick Mr. Castaneda, a polemicist, as foreign minister. Mr. Castaneda, a left-wing writer who teaches at New York University, is a son of one of the most distinguished foreign ministers in Mexico's recent history. But in the eyes of many, Mr. Castaneda lacks diplomatic experience.</p>
        <p>A writer of numerous books on Mexican politics, including ''Perpetuating Power, How Mexican Presidents Were Chosen,'' which is being released this week in New York, Mr. Castaneda has intellectual admirers around the world. But he recently enraged the Mexican press by writing a haughty newspaper column that scolded journalists as unsophisticated and unprofessional.</p>
        <p>And as a strident leftist, Mr. Castaneda has often been a harsh critic of United States policy in Latin America and has made a number of enemies among Republicans in Congress, particularly Senator Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Castaneda acknowledged that there had been unfavorable rumblings about the prospect of his appointment from Mr. Helms and from staff members at the Senate Foreign Relations Committee. But Mr. Castaneda said he had good relations with an overwhelming majority of Republican leaders, especially among those working with Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''When we went to the United States,'' Mr. Castaneda, said, ''Fox saw that I have solid relationships with people close to Gore and Bush, that I have relationships at high-levels in the Clinton administration. And so there will be no real problems. Now we may not always agree on every issue, but there is an openness to negotiate and work out our differences.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox is scheduled to give the names of his cabinet in three separate announcements over the next week. Among the cabinet members he is widely expected to announce on Wednesday are Mr. Gil and Luis Ernesto Derbez as secretary of the new economy ministry, which will take over the duties formerly handled by the commerce secretary. Neither are members of Mr. Fox's party, the PAN.</p>
        <p>Mr. Derbez, 53, has been a chief architect of Mr. Fox's economic plans throughout his campaign and in the five-month transition since the elections in July. A former World Bank economist who has spent most of the last decade outside Mexico, he was generally considered too unknown and inexperienced to be treasury minister.</p>
        <p>His admirers say he knows how to build relationships with those who disagree with him. And Mr. Derbez has shown intense interest in strengthening industry, which he says has been neglected in favor of foreign investment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gil, 57, (pronounced heel) is general director of a long-distance telephone company, Avantel. He worked as a deputy governor at the Bank of Mexico and was chief tax collector under President Carlos Salinas de Gortari.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gil, one of the nation's most eminent economists, personifies the philosophies of his old professor, Milton Friedman at the University of Chicago. Although Wall Street would be pleased by Mr. Gil's appointment, many here say his tough convictions might make him a poor negotiator.</p>
        <p>For the treasury secretary, a major task will be to help Mr. Fox win approval for tax changes aimed at increasing government revenue. Mr. Gil's appointment may also stir apprehensions among dominant businessmen like Carlos Slim, president of Telmex and the nation's wealthiest man. As head of Avantel, Mr. Gil worked to break up Telmex's near monopoly over telecommunications.</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  November 23, 2000, Thursday  An article yesterday about the new cabinet taking form in Mexico described the incoming foreign minister, Jorge G. Castaneda, as a ''strident leftist.'' While he has taken leftist positions, his views are not doctrinaire; he should not have been described that way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: November 23, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the new cabinet taking form in Mexico described the incoming foreign minister, Jorge G. Castaneda, as a ''strident leftist.'' While he has taken leftist positions, his views are not doctrinaire; he should not have been described that way.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
