<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Forget the Bumblebees and Other Allies</title>
    <meta content="WCGARDEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1019383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="IN THE GARDEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faust, Joan Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD61039F937A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Forget the Bumblebees and Other Allies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Faust, Joan Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Lee Faust gardening column on bumblebees and other garden insects; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIMES gardeners are so busy planting and tending, they forget that there are other things going on about them. But some curious little events recently bore this out. Along the front walk one recent nippy morning, there appeared what seemed to be a dead bumblebee. But closer inspection proved it was not the case. The tiny creature seemed to be somewhat stunned in the coolness. Since all seemed well with the bumblebee, it was carefully bypassed. It seemed the sun would soon warm the day and the tiny insect would be on its way.</p>
        <p>The next morning proved to be warmer, but the bumblebee was there again. This time, however, the insect appeared to be quite busy checking things on the ground. The bumblebee was making a crawling, rather than a flying, inspection of the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIMES gardeners are so busy planting and tending, they forget that there are other things going on about them. But some curious little events recently bore this out. Along the front walk one recent nippy morning, there appeared what seemed to be a dead bumblebee. But closer inspection proved it was not the case. The tiny creature seemed to be somewhat stunned in the coolness. Since all seemed well with the bumblebee, it was carefully bypassed. It seemed the sun would soon warm the day and the tiny insect would be on its way.</p>
        <p>The next morning proved to be warmer, but the bumblebee was there again. This time, however, the insect appeared to be quite busy checking things on the ground. The bumblebee was making a crawling, rather than a flying, inspection of the area.</p>
        <p>The next day was it was time to mow the lawn, and what should appear in true flying fashion? The bumblebee. The fat, furry insect hovered above the lawn and made several passes, each about a foot above the grass. It seemed to be following the path of the mower and the circular flight pattern was fascinating to watch. Also, by this time anthropomorphism was setting in and the bumblebee seemed to have become a friend. The busy flyer provided ceaseless fascination as it circled over the mowed grass in what appeared to be a rather undisturbed manner.</p>
        <p>The mowing chore was finished in due time. But there was no more bumblebee to be seen.</p>
        <p>Of course, this is no attempt to make serious observations of the insect world; that has been done many times over by experts. Especially appealing are the personal documentations made by Edwin Way Teale in his delightful book, ''The Strange Lives of Familiar Insects.'' Yet, watching what goes on outside does peak curiosity and spur learning in many other realms.</p>
        <p>What was probably going on in the life of the bumblebee was none other than springtime nest hunting by a queen bumblebee. This insect is known to nest underground, quite often in the abandoned den of a mouse or other subterranean creature. Underground, the queen bumblebee lays her eggs and the process of continuing the life cycle of the  colony begins. The only one to survive the winter will be a queen bumblebee who will hibernate and begin the cycle again the following year.</p>
        <p>According to most entomologists, the caste system of the beehive is the same for the bumblebee clan as for the honeybee. One curious point, however, is that the bumblebee has an extra long tongue that permits it to pollinate some of the more demanding flowers that the honeybees cannot reach.</p>
        <p>Another curious observation is one made by Edwin Way Teale. He learned that bumblebees sleep. In his book he writes, ''I once found scores of bumblebees bedded down for the night in the crevices of the bark of a scarlet oak. Usually, when a bumblebee does not return to the nest during summer nights, it sleeps clinging to the underside of a leaf.''</p>
        <p>Insects are so maligned by gardeners that it is rare to be able to say something good about any of them. Yet there are scores of beneficial insects that help those who grow plants. These are allies to be encouraged when encountered.</p>
        <p>Possibly the one most familiar to all is the ladybug or more correctly, the convergent lady beetle. This little feeder relishes many of the garden's troublemakers including aphids, mealybugs and scales. Not every species feeds on all pests, but suffice it to say that the lady beetle is definitely a friend. So, too, is the ground beetle. Those who work in the soil often respond to this beetle with a quick stomp. But it would be better to use restraint; this is a predatory beetle that feeds on certain mites, thrips and many kinds of caterpillars.</p>
        <p>Lacewings are not only lovely to look at but also voracious feeders on aphids as well as mealybugs, white flies, leafhoppers, mites and certain scales. This is an insect that appears especially beautiful if its pairs of wings are backlighted by the sun. The tiny wings are held above the body and have a transparent lacy appeal. The larval stage of the insect suggests a tiny alligator and it feeds on many soft-bodied pests by piercing them with its needlelike mouth parts.</p>
        <p>The lacewing should not be confused with a pesky species called the lacebug, which has become a serious predator on andromeda. The lacebug's damage causes stippled marks on the leaves and can be a difficult problem to bring under control.</p>
        <p>Finally, the chief of all the predatory insects is the praying mantis. This insect can grow to such size that it may even suggest a small bird, although its closest insect relative is the grasshopper. Mantises have been known to kill tiny frogs as well as lizards. But their favorite prey are the soft-bodied insects they can grasp in lightning speed with extended legs.</p>
        <p>Though to a gardener, plants may be the thing, it is clear to observers of nature that other creatures are just as important.</p>
        <p>IN THE GARDEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
