<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Separate Missions for 2 Americans</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="844769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="GYMNASTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GYMNASTICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAWES, DOMINIQUE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAMORTE, CHRIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D91E39F93AA25757C0A960958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Separate Missions for 2 Americans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
      <dateline>SAN JUAN, P.R., April 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Dominique Dawes, the road to success in Atlanta may begin here at the world gymnastics championships. For Chris LaMorte, the road ends here. But even  though Dawes and LaMorte will not be Olympic teammates this summer, they are both wearing red, white and blue in San Juan, and in today's first session, both Americans qualified for Friday's eight-gymnast finals.</p>
        <p>Dawes, the lithe and explosive 19-year-old from Gaithersburg, Md., qualified  on the uneven bars by finishing second in the semifinals with a score of 9.8. She also qualified on the balance beam by finishing fifth with a 9.787. LaMorte, a 21-year-old from Lake Ronkonkoma, Long Island, qualified on the rings by finishing in a tie for sixth with a score of 9.65.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Dominique Dawes, the road to success in Atlanta may begin here at the world gymnastics championships. For Chris LaMorte, the road ends here. But even  though Dawes and LaMorte will not be Olympic teammates this summer, they are both wearing red, white and blue in San Juan, and in today's first session, both Americans qualified for Friday's eight-gymnast finals.</p>
        <p>Dawes, the lithe and explosive 19-year-old from Gaithersburg, Md., qualified  on the uneven bars by finishing second in the semifinals with a score of 9.8. She also qualified on the balance beam by finishing fifth with a 9.787. LaMorte, a 21-year-old from Lake Ronkonkoma, Long Island, qualified on the rings by finishing in a tie for sixth with a score of 9.65.</p>
        <p>Dawes, a 1992 Olympian and former world silver medalist, is accustomed to succeeding at this level, even though she missed last year's worlds because of injuries. But LaMorte has never competed internationally until now, which makes  his performance in San Juan all the more remarkable.</p>
        <p>"I never thought I'd be on the same floor with some of these guys," said LaMorte, who in 1993, while attending the University of New Mexico, became the first freshman to win the National Collegiate Athletic Association rings title and then defended his title as a sophomore.</p>
        <p>Those performances certainly turned heads in Albuquerque, N.M., but they turned few heads in the rarefied world of elite gymnastics. And when LaMorte began performing his routine in practice earlier this week, Italy's Yuri Chechi, the three-time-defending world rings champion, was taken by surprise.</p>
        <p>"I had never seen or heard of him before, and I was quite impressed," Chechi  said. "He can do very well."</p>
        <p>LaMorte's routine is packed with the same sorts of strength moves that Chechi favors. But only Chechi, who had the top score today on rings (9.775), will be in Atlanta this summer. Only all-around gymnasts capable of performing on all six apparatus make the American Olympic team. LaMorte competes on rings and nothing but rings: the result of three operations on his left wrist and two on his right ankle.</p>
        <p>"Basically, rings is the only thing that doesn't hurt," he said.</p>
        <p>Despite today's fine score on the bars, Dawes has to be happy this is not her Olympics. Mistakes in her floor routine on Wednesday kept her from making the final 16 in that event. She admits that she has been battling nerves all week. And even though she placed second behind the defending world bars champion Svetlana Chorkina of Russia today, Dawes had to alter her routine on the fly after a 1 1/2-turn pirouette she was planning on top of the highest bar came up  a half rotation short. She recovered quite nicely, however.</p>
        <p>"It feels good that I finally did a set that I'm proud of here," Dawes said.</p>
        <p>Fellow American Jaycie Phelps also did fine sets today, qualifying for the finals on the bars and beam, finishing third (9.837) in the beam.</p>
        <p>The last time Dawes performed at this level was in November 1994 at the world team championships in Dortmund, Germany. That was the same year she swept to victory in all five events at the United States Championships and became one of  the American athletes to watch closely as Atlanta approached. But her 1995 season was considerably less successful, largely because of a stress fracture in her wrist that led to shoulder problems.</p>
        <p>At 19, she is now a senior citizen in women's gymnastics terms. But she and Coach Kelli Hill still felt it was important for the international judges to see her again before Atlanta (assuming she qualifies at the United States Trials in  June).</p>
        <p>"I think everyone was kind of curious why I wasn't in Sabae, and I want to show them I'm in really good shape if not better shape than I was before," Dawes said.</p>
        <p>DISMOUNTS</p>
        <p>The only other American to reach a final was CHAINEY UMPHREY, who finished sixth on the high bar with a score of 9.65. VITALY SHCHERBO of Belarus, winner of six gold medals at the 1992 Olympics, qualified for four finals: high bar, pommel horse, vault and floor exercise, where he was the leading qualifier with  a 9.712.</p>
        <p>GYMNASTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
