<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Researcher Falsified Data in Breast Cancer Study</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940316T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="674323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BREAST</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FALSIFICATION OF DATA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAMOXIFEN (DRUG)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUGS (PHARMACEUTICALS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POISSON, ROGER (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Breast Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Tamoxifen (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Breast</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDC133DF937A25750C0A962958260" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Researcher Falsified Data in Breast Cancer Study</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALTMAN, LAWRENCE K</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Federal investigation has found that a Canadian researcher falsified data in a study that helped change the way breast cancer is treated. The study concluded that full mastectomies were not always necessary to prevent the spread of early forms of the disease.</p>
        <p>The implications of the investigative finding for the treatment of breast cancer are not immediately clear. Cancer experts, moving to reassure women today, said there were other studies that supported the original research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Federal investigation has found that a Canadian researcher falsified data in a study that helped change the way breast cancer is treated. The study concluded that full mastectomies were not always necessary to prevent the spread of early forms of the disease.</p>
        <p>The implications of the investigative finding for the treatment of breast cancer are not immediately clear. Cancer experts, moving to reassure women today, said there were other studies that supported the original research.</p>
        <p>And the University of Pittsburgh, which was the organizing center of the federally financed study of breast surgery, issued a statement saying that the conclusions of the studies remained the same when the Canadian data were excluded. Women treated "as a result of this research can be assured of the appropriateness of their therapy," Pittsburgh officials said.</p>
        <p>In the Federal investigation, first reported today in The Chicago Tribune, officials found that the Canadian researcher had enrolled some women in at least one part of the study who did not fit the criteria for inclusion. The investigation found that organizers of the study have known of the resulting faulty data for two years and have not moved to clarify the subject publicly.</p>
        <p>And a year ago, in a confidential memorandum, a Government research official recommended that the Pittsburgh scientist who headed the project should publish a new analysis of the data as a way of restoring public confidence.</p>
        <p>In addition to the finding of falsification in part of the breast-surgery study, the Food and Drug Administration disclosed that in May 1991 the Canadian researcher, Dr. Roger Poisson of St. Luc's Hospital in Montreal, acknowledged that he had falsified results of other research studies.</p>
        <p>Those studies involved the drug tamoxifen, which is used as a supplement in treating breast cancer, the document said. In a disciplinary agreement, the F.D.A. indefinitely prohibited Dr. Poisson from participating in studies involving experimental drugs.</p>
        <p>The study on breast surgery began more than a decade ago and its findings were made public in 1989 in the New England Journal of Medicine. It found that in many women with early breast cancer a partial mastectomy, which is also called a lumpectomy, plus radiation therapy, is as effective in preventing recurrences and in survival as the more disfiguring procedure of a full mastectomy.</p>
        <p>The Federal investigation was a cooperative effort that involved the National Institutes of Health, the National Cancer Institute, the Office of Research Integrity, and the Food and Drug Administration.</p>
        <p>The inquiry by Federal agencies followed an internal review by Dr. Bernard Fisher, the University of Pittsburgh scientist who headed a federally financed group that organized the study involving more than 5,000 doctors and 484 medical centers. Dr. Poisson was one of those participating.</p>
        <p>The investigation found at least 115 falsifications, and those falsehoods have been known to the organizers of the study for two years.</p>
        <p>In February 1993, Dr. Lyle W. Bivens, the acting chief of the Office of Research Integrity, the Federal agency that looks for misconduct in Government-sponsored health research, wrote to Dr. Samuel Broder, the head of the National Cancer Institute, and recommended that Dr. Fisher publish a re-analysis of the data, excluding the falsified Canadian information, "to restore public confidence in the conclusions of the studies."</p>
        <p>Dr. Bivens also criticized Dr. Fisher for delayed reporting to the National Institutes of Health, saying the initial discovery of falsification of a report "should have triggered a more immediate and clear response" by the group. Report Planned for June</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher said in a telephone interview today that his team was preparing a report to be published in June and a commentary that is due to appear in April.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fisher said his team had acted with urgency within established rules and procedures after it detected the data irregularities in February 1991. Dr. Poisson was immediately suspended from entering new patients into studies.</p>
        <p>During the investigations, Dr. Fisher's team was "prohibited from any public discussions or scientific publication related to this issue" until the Office of Research Integrity reported its findings in April 1993, according to a statement issued by Dr. Fisher's group at the University of Pittsburgh today.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh officials said that statisticians from the National Cancer Institute had confirmed that none of the conclusions of the study had been altered by removing the data submitted by Dr. Poisson.</p>
        <p>In its article today, The Chicago Tribune said that about 16 percent of the patients in the study came from Dr. Poisson's research in Montreal.  Beginning in 1977, the newspaper said, he enrolled at least 100 patients who should have been ineligible on medical, technical or consensual grounds.</p>
        <p>Regarding the the second, unrelated disciplinary action involving Dr. Poisson, the scientist's lawyer, William Brock of Montreal, said in a telephone interview today that Dr. Poisson had "no other alternative" than to sign the Government paper that found fault with his procedures. He faced financial ruin from years of litigation if he wanted to fight in court, the lawyer said. To the extent that there were any discrepancies in data, Dr. Poisson did not believe that they were serious enough to warrant such a harsh penalty, Mr. Brock said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Poisson "does not believe he did anything wrong," Mr. Brock said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jerome Kassirer, the editor of The New England Journal of Medicine, said today that it would be premature to say anything about changes in the treatment of breast cancer as a result of the disclosures of falsifications.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kassirer said his journal did not know about the falsifications until last week. He said that he was surprised that Dr. Fisher had not reported the irregularities sooner and that he had asked Dr. Fisher to write a letter for publication in the journal reporting the new data and explaining the circumstances. Dr. Fisher agreed to do so, Dr. Kassirer said.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether data from the remaining centers that took part in the study have been scrutinized as throughly as those submitted by Dr. Poisson. If the Pittsburgh team's initial review did not detect the falsifications from Dr. Poisson, it could also have missed irregularities from other institutions. A thorough review by researchers and institutions not connected with the original study may be needed to assure women of the validity of the findings, experts said.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, the Michigan Democrat who is chairman of the House Commerce Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, has made a number of telephone calls to the Office of Research Integrity and National Institutes of Health in the last two months and has met with officials from the Federal agencies on the topic of the breast cancer research, a subcommittee staff member said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 16, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front-page article on Monday about a Federal investigation of a study of breast cancer treatments referred incorrectly in some copies to the extent of wrongdoing found. Data were falsified, but there was no finding of fraud. The article also misstated the year of the study's publication in The New England Journal of Medicine. It was 1985, not 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 16, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, a front-page article on Monday about a Federal investigation of a study of breast cancer treatments referred incorrectly in some copies to the extent of wrongdoing found. Data were falsified, but there was no finding of fraud. The article also misstated the year of the study's publication in The New England Journal of Medicine. It was 1985, not 1989.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
