<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Shakespeare's Quarterback Finally Wins the Biggest Game</title>
    <meta content="26ANDE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Broncos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Bay Packers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elway, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DB103BF935A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Shakespeare's Quarterback Finally Wins the Biggest Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses performance of Denver Broncos quarterback John Elway in defeating Green Bay Packers to win Super Bowl; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN he walked up the stairs to the platform near the huge balloon replica of the Super Bowl trophy, he smiled when he heard the ''El-way, El-way'' chant. And when Pat Bowlen accepted the silver Vince Lombardi Trophy, the Broncos' president lifted it and yelled, ''This one's for John.''</p>
        <p>In what might have been his last stand, John Elway was finally the winning Super Bowl quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN he walked up the stairs to the platform near the huge balloon replica of the Super Bowl trophy, he smiled when he heard the ''El-way, El-way'' chant. And when Pat Bowlen accepted the silver Vince Lombardi Trophy, the Broncos' president lifted it and yelled, ''This one's for John.''</p>
        <p>In what might have been his last stand, John Elway was finally the winning Super Bowl quarterback.</p>
        <p>''Other than my wife and my four kids, there's nothing better than this,'' he would say. ''So many things going against us, the N.F.C., the A.F.C., all types of things, it's unbelievable. We did it the hard way. But for all the Bronco fans who never had this feeling, we finally got it done.''</p>
        <p>He is 37 years old. If the Broncos had lost last night, he might never have had another chance.</p>
        <p>''You wonder if you're going to run out of years,'' he said. ''But fortunately, I hung on.''</p>
        <p>In recent weeks Elway has hinted that if the Broncos were to win this Super Bowl, he might consider retiring even though he has three years remaining on his contract. And when he was asked if he might retire now, he sidestepped the question.</p>
        <p>''I'll talk to my wife and family and see how the body heals up,'' he said. ''I'll also talk to Mr. Bowlen.''</p>
        <p>When he was much younger, when John Elway was still hoping to lift the Broncos into the Super Bowl someday, he acknowledged his ambition as a football player.</p>
        <p>''My goal is to beat Terry Bradshaw,'' he said, referring to the former Pittsburgh Steelers quarterback. ''He won the Super Bowl four times. I want to win it five times.''</p>
        <p>But now John Elway has finally won it one time.</p>
        <p>If Shakespeare had ever written a Super Bowl play, Elway would have been his tragic figure who finally succeeded even though he completed only 12 of 22 passes for 123 yards.</p>
        <p>But that's the perception of the quarterback position.</p>
        <p>People think of Bradshaw or Joe Montana having won the Super Bowl four times. Or of Jim Kelly having lost it four times. Or of Fran Tarkenton having lost it three times.</p>
        <p>But when people think of John Elway now, they'll think mostly of the one time he won, rather than the three times he didn't.</p>
        <p>They'll think of him holding both hands high as Terrell Davis hurried into the end zone virtually untouched for the 1-yard touchdown that provided the winning margin in the 31-24 victory over the Green Bay Packers. In that moment, Eugene Robinson, the Packer safety who had snatched Elway's pass in the end zone earlier in the final quarter, walked up to him.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Congratulations, John,' '' Robinson said later. ''I know how this feels.''</p>
        <p>People will also think of Elway holding both hands high again minutes later when Brett Favre's fourth-down pass bounced off the grass of Qualcomm Stadium at Jack Murphy Field with 28 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>But they'll think mostly of his 8-yard scramble late in the third quarter that set up Davis's 1-yard touchdown for a 24-17 lead, a scramble on a third-and-6 from the Packer 12-yard line.</p>
        <p>Taking the snap in the shotgun formation, Elway retreated beyond the 20-yard line as he searched for a receiver. Finding none open, he moved upfield, then to the right as he crossed the 10-yard line. In another situation, he might have slid, as quarterbacks usually do.</p>
        <p>Instead he dived for the first down as safety Leroy Butler and linebacker Brian Williams converged on him. With that dive, he sprawled at the 4-yard line. Two plays later, he handed off to Davis, who barreled for the 1-yard touchdown and a 24-17 lead.</p>
        <p>At a brawny 6 feet 3 inches and 215 pounds, Elway has been able to absorb the punishment and see his receivers beyond the pass rushers and the blitzers. He has an arm that slings arrows. He has the legs to move around when he must. He's boyishly handsome. He's also wealthy.</p>
        <p>In his four Super Bowl appearances, only once was Elway on the favored team. Against the Redskins in Super Bowl XXII, the Broncos were a 3 1/2-point choice, but lost, 42-10.</p>
        <p>But the Broncos were underdogs to the Giants by 9 1/2 points before losing, 39-20, in Super Bowl XXI, and underdogs to the 49ers by 7 points before being routed, 55-10, in Super Bowl XXIV. And yesterday the Broncos were underdogs to the Packers by 11 1/2 points before dethroning them.</p>
        <p>''The time kind of eases some of the pain,'' Elway said during the week. ''It was really rough when we were there three out of four years.</p>
        <p>''It was right there in the back of your mind, and it was tough to get rid of it. But now, having been so long ago, it has healed some of the wounds.''</p>
        <p>And now even the scars from those wounds have disappeared.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
