<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.M.F. Votes to Enhance Power of China and Others</title>
    <meta content="19fund" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/19/business/worldbusiness/19fund.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1791204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boards of Directors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <org class="online_producer">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Paulson, Henry M Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wolfowitz, Paul D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DC1031F93AA2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.M.F. Votes to Enhance Power of China and Others</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">I.M.F. Votes to Enhance Power of China and Others</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN R. WEISMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weisman, Steven R</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE, Sept. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Member states of the International Monetary Fund, yielding to demands from China and leading Western countries, voted Monday to adopt a disputed plan to modify the fund's power structure and take steps to expand the voice of China and other rapidly developing nations.</p>
        <p>The modification of the governance of the fund, the international agency that monitors the global economy and rescues countries from insolvency, was widely described as the biggest step since the fund was established in the 1940's, the era when the victors of World War II created the vast cooperative superstructure for the world economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Member states of the International Monetary Fund voted to adopt a disputed plan to modify the fund’s power structure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Member states of the International Monetary Fund, yielding to demands from China and leading Western countries, voted Monday to adopt a disputed plan to modify the fund's power structure and take steps to expand the voice of China and other rapidly developing nations.</p>
        <p>The modification of the governance of the fund, the international agency that monitors the global economy and rescues countries from insolvency, was widely described as the biggest step since the fund was established in the 1940's, the era when the victors of World War II created the vast cooperative superstructure for the world economy.</p>
        <p>China's share of the votes at the monetary fund, which has 184 members, would go up only slightly, to 3.719 percent, from 2.98 percent. The shares of South Korea, Turkey and Mexico, the other countries that gained more power from the vote on Monday, also rose a similarly modest amount. But the change was hailed by the United States and other nations as a decisive reform.</p>
        <p>''It looks like a small step forward, but it's a large step,'' said Henry M. Paulson Jr., the United States Treasury secretary, who was here for the annual meeting of the monetary fund and the World Bank and participated in morning-until-night sessions assessing the global economy and possible steps to assure its health.</p>
        <p>The proposal passed with 90.6 percent of the total vote, the fund said. The names of the dissenting countries were not released. But the opposition had been led by Brazil, Argentina, India and Egypt, which had worried that they would be left with a diminished role at the bank. In a separate development, a committee of finance ministers that oversees the World Bank endorsed in principle a plan by Paul D. Wolfowitz, the bank president, to crack down on corruption in the bank's lending, but not unreservedly. The ministers added a proviso that the bank's board of executive directors, a separate group that oversees the day-to-day bank operations on behalf of donor and recipient nations, be able to override the way Mr. Wolfowitz carries out the plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz, a conservative intellectual who was an architect of the Iraq war as deputy secretary of defense in President Bush's first term, has stirred unease in the bank with his corruption policy. Many directors fear that it may be overly punitive and lead to cuts in aid to poor countries.</p>
        <p>The finance ministers' committee also raised concerns, Mr. Wolfowitz said, about the standards to apply to various countries and the question of how much of the bank's resources should go to anticorruption plans.</p>
        <p>The finance ministers' committee issued a statement that supported the anticorruption campaign but with what seemed to be muted wording. It supported the bank's ''engagement'' on the issue but demanded further information on how it would be carried out , and in a suggestion of unhappiness, ''stressed the importance of board oversight of the strategy.''</p>
        <p>Some officials here indicated that the wording of the committee's statement reflected discomfort with Mr. Wolfowitz. But Mr. Wolfowitz said he was pleased the board had given him a green light to proceed with what has become a signature issue for him in his 15 months at the bank.</p>
        <p>Throughout the meetings the last few days in Singapore, much of the criticism from participating countries has focused less on the World Bank than on the overhaul of the monetary fund. The fund vote needed 85 percent of the 184 member countries' voting shares to be adopted.</p>
        <p>The United States has about 17 percent of the vote and Europe, in aggregate, about 23 percent. Mr. Paulson and his European counterparts have spent much of their time here lobbying other countries to agree to the change. Japan has a 6.1 percent share.</p>
        <p>The vote was not much in doubt, but many countries that voted in favor said they did so under protest. They signaled that in a second round of discussions, scores of countries, including many poor African nations, would be demanding a bigger voting share for themselves. The change in the fund governance was advocated by the United States and many European countries as a way of getting China and other developing countries to feel more invested in the international economic system.</p>
        <p>The monetary fund is one of many institutions that American and European officials say are in need of change. After the collapse of trade talks this summer, there are fears of disaffection with the World Trade Organization, the successor of a global trade regime set up 60 years ago.</p>
        <p>Western leaders also want to change the composition of the United Nations Security Council, adding some countries to the roster of five permanent veto-bearing members. But they have been unable to agree on which countries to add. The United States wants to add Japan and one of several developing countries seeking membership.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfowitz has said that the World Bank also needs to change its governance to give more say to China and other fast-growing countries in the developing world.</p>
        <p>Under the surface of the monetary fund vote was another objective of the United States: to engage China in the fund as the fund expands its role in monitoring currency flows and exchange rates. Washington hopes that the fund will become another voice urging China to let its currency fluctuate more freely in relation to the dollar.</p>
        <p>If there was one overriding consensus among European and American finance ministers, it was that China was artificially keeping the value of its currency low in relation to the dollar, and that this is an unhealthy pattern also being followed by Japan and other Asian nations.</p>
        <p>The net effect, economists say, is that Chinese exports are cheaper than they should be, and its imports are more costly than they should be, aggravating the huge American trade and current-account deficits that have turned the United States into the world's biggest debtor nation. But Mr. Paulson said again in Singapore that a ''strong dollar'' remains in the United States' interest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
