<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mali's Democracy</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="847114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MALI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MALI</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Mali</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDF1739F93AA15757C0A960958260" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mali's Democracy</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While hardly anybody was watching, the people of Mali were burning some 3,000 firearms in a March ceremony meant to mark the end of a five-year conflict between Tuareg nomad rebels and the Malian Army. These "flames of peace" are a salutary augury for Africa, and a pointed reminder for Washington. Mali has moved without fanfare from 35 years of single-party rule and 23 years of military dictatorship to a multi-party democracy. This feat might be better known if a single high-level American official had troubled in recent years to visit Bamako, Mali's capital.</p>
        <p>Much of the credit for these gains belongs to President Alpha Oumar Konare, the victor in Mali's first free elections, in 1992. "The single-party system was a total failure in all countries which practiced it," Mr. Konare recently declared. "The logic of 'shut up and obey' gives immediate results, but offers no tomorrow." He is careful to add that it will take years of calm, openness and rule of law to consolidate free government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While hardly anybody was watching, the people of Mali were burning some 3,000 firearms in a March ceremony meant to mark the end of a five-year conflict between Tuareg nomad rebels and the Malian Army. These "flames of peace" are a salutary augury for Africa, and a pointed reminder for Washington. Mali has moved without fanfare from 35 years of single-party rule and 23 years of military dictatorship to a multi-party democracy. This feat might be better known if a single high-level American official had troubled in recent years to visit Bamako, Mali's capital.</p>
        <p>Much of the credit for these gains belongs to President Alpha Oumar Konare, the victor in Mali's first free elections, in 1992. "The single-party system was a total failure in all countries which practiced it," Mr. Konare recently declared. "The logic of 'shut up and obey' gives immediate results, but offers no tomorrow." He is careful to add that it will take years of calm, openness and rule of law to consolidate free government.</p>
        <p>But under this 49-year-old historian, Mali, once a French colony, has made an impressive start. The former dictator, Gen. Moussa Traore, who was ousted in  1991, is being tried for the killing of 100 students during riots that year, but his execution is ruled out. "I hope that Moussa Traore and his friends will live as long as possible so that they may see democracy flourish in Mali," says Mr. Konare, who opposes capital punishment. A free press, unknown in Mali until restrictions were lifted in 1992, already flourishes as 20 newspapers supplant a state monopoly. Mali, parting company with most African countries, condemned Nigeria for its execution of Ken Saro-Wiwa and other activists.</p>
        <p>All this is happening in one of the world's 20 poorest countries, sandy and landlocked, whose eight million inhabitants are dependent on the River Niger, which flows through the heart of Mali. But the country's economy is percolating, at a 6 percent growth rate, which is partly a result of privatization and other free-market reforms. This success was recognized by the International Monetary Fund, which recently approved a three-year $91 million loan to Mali.</p>
        <p>What is needed along with the money is attention and recognition. Spotlighting Mali's turn to democracy, and its efforts to integrate Tuareg refugees, can powerfully bolster an innovative leadership. The people of Mali will obviously be the final arbiters of this promising experiment, but showing that the world cares can improve the odds. That is something Washington might keep in mind the next time a top Government official goes to Africa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
