<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Weighs Return of Control Over Some Services to 5 Boroughs</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOROUGH PRESIDENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY CHARTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOROUGH PRESIDENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CITY CHARTERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA1231F930A15751C1A965958260" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Weighs Return of Control Over Some Services to 5 Boroughs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, ALISON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani suggested yesterday that he was willing to return to the five boroughs some of City Hall's control over service delivery, and said he had asked the borough presidents to draft plans for an experiment in such decentralization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he would consider decentralization in areas like sanitation, road maintenance and repair, parks and environmental protection, and he pointed out that the Parks Department already has borough-level commanders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani suggested yesterday that he was willing to return to the five boroughs some of City Hall's control over service delivery, and said he had asked the borough presidents to draft plans for an experiment in such decentralization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he would consider decentralization in areas like sanitation, road maintenance and repair, parks and environmental protection, and he pointed out that the Parks Department already has borough-level commanders.</p>
        <p>He said that once he received the plan, which is to be drawn up by Borough Presidents Guy V. Molinari of Staten Island and Claire Shulman of Queens, he could determine what could be done quickly by executive order and what could be authorized by the City Council, without having to go through a revision of the City Charter.</p>
        <p>"It might allow us to define the mayoralty more sensibly," Mr. Giuliani said. "It may be that you really should have less than all that power because you can't do all of that well." He said some areas recommended by the borough presidents could be tried out "as an experiment and see if it works." Political Significance</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's examination of ways to give the boroughs renewed influence is part of his often-stated goal of streamlining municipal government and making delivery of services more efficient. But the move also has political significance for him since he rolled up his largest percentages of support in Staten Island and Queens, where many residents view City Hall as aloof and Manhattan-oriented. Staten Islanders voted in November in favor of outright secession from the city, a move that could threaten Mr. Giuliani's re-election prospects.</p>
        <p>The proposal to hand back powers to the boroughs would reverse a trend that has been taking place gradually for the last century. In 1961 voters approved a charter revision proposed by Mayor Robert F. Wagner to strip the borough presidents of their substantial control over such functions as street and sewer repairs. The move also reduced the political patronage jobs controlled by the county Democratic organizations.</p>
        <p>In 1989 another City Charter change weakened the borough presidents further by eliminating the Board of Estimate, which had been declared unconstitutional. The board, which had been made up of the five borough presidents, the City Council president, the comptroller and the mayor, had voted on contracts and franchises, decided matters of land use and shared budgetary power with the Council. Secession Movements</p>
        <p>Since then, discontent in the boroughs has shown itself in Staten Island's vote for secession in November and a more muted secession movement in Queens.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shulman and Borough President Ruth W. Messinger of Manhattan proposed earlier this year that the Board of Education be split into five separate borough boards. And Howard Golden, the Brooklyn Borough President, called unsuccessfully for the State Legislature to create a commission to study ways to give the boroughs a stronger role in service delivery, planning and budgeting.</p>
        <p>The 1989 charter revision, however, also strengthened the role of the City Council, and the Council is unlikely to look favorably at any move to reduce those powers again through decentralization.</p>
        <p>"You'd have to look at the specific proposals, but we'd certainly be very hesitant," said Peg Breen, a spokeswoman for Council Speaker Peter F. Vallone of Queens. "The whole idea of charter reform is that we are one city represented by a legislative body and an executive, and I think we would be very cautious about anything that started decentralizing and just putting things back into the boroughs."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, in an interview with editors and reporters of The New York Times, called the Staten Island secession movement a "valuable wake-up call" that showed that Staten Island residents were alienated from the centralized municipal government. "They are complaining they have a government they can't touch, feel, and that isn't responsible to them," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani has political as well as policy reasons to try to prevent the secession of Staten Island, where he won overwhelming electoral support. But he said more borough control should extend as well to Manhattan, Brooklyn, Queens and the Bronx. "If I do it for Staten Island, I'll do it for each one of the boroughs," he said. Drafting Proposals</p>
        <p>Mr. Molinari said senior aides to all five borough presidents had already met at Staten Island's Borough Hall earlier this month to start drafting proposals and hoped to have a complete plan by late January.</p>
        <p>Among the areas where various borough presidents said they would like more control over service delivery are sanitation, transportation, police, parks and city planning. Mr. Molinari said the borough presidents were also examining ways to create a larger role for themselves in budgeting, capital construction, management, awarding contracts and land-use decisions -- in essence, all the areas in which the borough presidents had broad powers before the 1989 revision of the City Charter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani did not make clear whether he was speaking of more power specifically for the borough presidents or for borough-level commissioners who would report back to commissioners at City Hall. But Ms. Shulman left no no doubt that she wanted to see the agencies create "borough commissioners that respond to borough presidents."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani did not say whether he supported another full-fledged exercise in revising the City Charter. But in a letter sent earlier this month to Mr. Golden, he said a proposal by the Brooklyn Borough President to create a new Charter Revision Commission "is important to me." Another Appointment</p>
        <p>In another development, Mr. Giuliani is expected today to appoint one of his closest aides, Randy M. Mastro, to serve as his chief of staff at City Hall, aides to his transition said.</p>
        <p>As chief of staff, Mr. Mastro would oversee Mr. Giuliani's mayoral staff at City Hall, and as a close adviser to Mr. Giuliani, he would also be part of the new Mayor's inner circle on policy and decision making.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani is also expected shortly to appoint Elliot Sander, a state transportation official, as Commissioner of the city's Department of Transportation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
