<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans, Ending a Delay, Approve Soviet Technical Aid</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SOVIET TURMOIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB153EF936A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans, Ending a Delay, Approve Soviet Technical Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL L. MONTGOMERY,</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, Sept. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European Community approved $11.8 million in technical assistance for the Soviet Union today, the first installment of a long-delayed $1.062 billion program.</p>
        <p>The aid package, to be spent by the end of 1992, was allocated by the 12-nation group last December but was then blocked, first in retaliation for repression by Moscow in the Baltic republics and later by jurisdictional disputes. The purpose of the technical assistance program is to prepare the Soviet markets for reform.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European Community approved $11.8 million in technical assistance for the Soviet Union today, the first installment of a long-delayed $1.062 billion program.</p>
        <p>The aid package, to be spent by the end of 1992, was allocated by the 12-nation group last December but was then blocked, first in retaliation for repression by Moscow in the Baltic republics and later by jurisdictional disputes. The purpose of the technical assistance program is to prepare the Soviet markets for reform.</p>
        <p>By negotiating largely with the individual republics rather than with the central authorities, the European Commission, the executive body of the community, found ways to assure that the money would go for reform rather than the status quo.</p>
        <p>The initial grants will be spread through the republics, and are largely intended to set up structures to make sure that needy areas get the aid.  Britons to Provide Advice</p>
        <p>For example, executives of 30 large supermarket chains in Britain are to meet next week to try to advise Soviet representatives on the storage, distribution and marketing of perishable food.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the technical assistance, the European Commission said in a statement today, is to train people and provide capital so that the distribution system can respond with speed and flexibility to crises. The community's food aid is handled separately from technical assistance, with a separate budget, but a major concern for the winter is distribution of emergency supplies.</p>
        <p>The community is already distributing some emergency aid, primarily infant formula and medicine, but is contemplating a bigger program for the winter. The community, which pays large price supports to its farmers, has accumulated vast stores of beef, butter, lamb, grain, vegetable oil and other food. In grain alone, the community has 30 million tons of surplus in its warehouses and is accumulating more from this year's bumper harvest.  Hungary Gets $5.9 Million</p>
        <p>Where possible, the community is providing credits for goods in Eastern Europe that will be sent to the Soviet Union and elsewhere as aid. This gives hard currency to the panting East European economies while producing food where there are shortages.</p>
        <p>This week, for example, the community advanced $5.9 million to Hungary, which has had a big 1991 harvest, so that it can send 45,000 tons of wheat to Albania as part of an aid program. Previously, the community had sent 50,000 tons of wheat from its own stores.</p>
        <p>Frans Andriessen of the Netherlands, the European Commissioner in charge of the East European aid program, said Albania's need for food aid was critical. He said Albania was, per capita, the leading consumer of bread in Europe and would need at least 50,000 tons of wheat a month until the harvest this time next year.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Kohl Cautions on Soviet Aid</p>
        <p>BONN, Sept. 4 (AP) -- Chancellor Helmut Kohl said today that the West should stop expecting Germany to be the Soviet Union's leading benefactor.</p>
        <p>In a parliamentary address, Mr. Kohl also said he would press for cuts in short-range nuclear weapons in American and Soviet arsenals. Thousands of the American missiles are based on German soil.</p>
        <p>In a suggestion that the United States may have a different view, NATO commanders said this week that the recent Soviet coup attempt could lead the Western security alliance to rethink its current cuts in military forces in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohl said Germany's partners and allies should do more to help the Soviet Union financially because it was in their interest that the troubled union remain stable.</p>
        <p>"This huge task cannot be left to us Germans alone, or just to the Europeans," he said. "Every country -- and I mean every country -- must carry a fair share of this joint responsibility, corresponding to its abilities."</p>
        <p>Some of the biggest industrial countries, including the United States, Japan and Canada, have expressed reluctance to increase direct financial aid to the Soviet Union until the Soviets do more to create a market economy.</p>
        <p>SOVIET TURMOIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
