<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INVESTING WITH: Anton V. Schutz; Burnham Financial Services Fund</title>
    <meta content="16INVO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/16/business/yourmoney/16INVO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1465341"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="Investing With Anton V. Schutz"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mendon Capital Advisers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Burnham Asset Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Investing With</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E6D9123AF935A25751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INVESTING WITH: Anton V. Schutz; Burnham Financial Services Fund</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Burnham Financial Services Fund</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carole Gould profile of Burnahm Financial Services fund and Anton V Schutz, president of Mendon Capital Advisors, which runs fund for Burnahm Asset Management; photo; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANTON V. SCHUTZ, who runs the $90 million Burnham Financial Services fund, has invested nimbly in a sector whose many components respond very differently to the same economic conditions.</p>
        <p>One part of the financial services industry is savings institutions, which have had the wind at their sails despite the weak economy. That is because the Federal Reserve has been lowering interest rates in recent years, reducing their cost of money, Mr. Schutz said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NTON V. SCHUTZ, who runs the $90 million Burnham Financial Services fund, has invested nimbly in a sector whose many components respond very differently to the same economic conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANTON V. SCHUTZ, who runs the $90 million Burnham Financial Services fund, has invested nimbly in a sector whose many components respond very differently to the same economic conditions.</p>
        <p>One part of the financial services industry is savings institutions, which have had the wind at their sails despite the weak economy. That is because the Federal Reserve has been lowering interest rates in recent years, reducing their cost of money, Mr. Schutz said.</p>
        <p>But asset managers, another part of the sector, have been hurt as the stock market has slumped, he said, and many consumer finance companies have suffered because their customers have defaulted on loans.</p>
        <p>''You have some haves and some have-nots in one sector,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His fund returned 36.2 percent a year, on average, for the three years through Thursday, placing first among 77 financial services funds tracked by Morningstar Inc. The group returned 5.1 percent a year, on average, during that time, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index lost 15 percent, on average.</p>
        <p>The fund returned 12.1 percent in the last 12 months, versus losses of 15.7 percent for its group and 25.7 percent for the index.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schutz, 38, is based in Rochester and is president of Mendon Capital Advisors, which runs the fund for Burnham Asset Management in New York. The fund's Class A shares, sold with a 5 percent load, or sales charge, through brokers and financial advisers, are available without a load through fund supermarkets like those operated by Charles Schwab and Fidelity Investments.</p>
        <p>To pick the 50 to 70 stocks in the fund, Mr. Schutz starts by evaluating interest rates, earnings, global events and other macroeconomic factors. The overall economy is now very murky, he said.</p>
        <p>''It's not easy to see whether the U.S. economy will be recovering soon or falling into an abyss,'' he said. ''Then there's a question about Iraq.''</p>
        <p>His macro analysis is largely keeping him away from savings institutions, where the easy money has already been made, he said, and pointing him toward life insurers and broker-dealers, which are trading at low prices because of the weak economy.</p>
        <p>Next, he reviews company-specific factors. Among life insurers, for example, he reviews the types of products they sell and the companies' own investment portfolios.</p>
        <p>In October, he began buying shares of Federated Investors, the asset management company based in Pittsburgh. The stock trades for about 12 times the company's projected 2003 earnings, he said, compared with a multiple of 16 for its group. Mr. Schutz said investors believe that because about one-third of Federated's revenue comes from its money market funds, the company will miss an upturn in the stock market. But the company is introducing more stock mutual funds and managed accounts, he said, and is a good acquisition target.</p>
        <p>He paid $25.99, on average, for his shares; they now trade at $24.68.</p>
        <p>Another holding is First Niagara Financial, a savings institution based in Lockport, N.Y. The company has an unusually strong balance sheet, Mr. Schutz said; its ratio of equity to assets is 20 percent, versus 8 percent for its competitors.</p>
        <p>First Niagara's management has much commercial banking experience, he said, and its earnings from high-yielding business loans have made it less vulnerable to interest rate shifts. He first bought shares in January 2001, paying $8.16, on average; they now trade at $11.11.</p>
        <p>ANOTHER holding is Prudential Financial, the insurer and money manager based in Newark. The company is working to shed Prudential's losing operations and to cut costs, Mr. Schutz said, to increase its return on equity and earnings. In December, Prudential announced its acquisition of the American operations of Skandia; the deal is expected to close by June. Because Skandia has a big business in variable annuities, the move will give Prudential more exposure to a recovery in the capital markets, Mr. Schutz said.</p>
        <p>He bought shares starting in December 2001, paying $30.52, on average. They now trade at $30.72.</p>
        <p>Investing With Anton V. Schutz</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
