<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Brokers Peace Accord In the Aegean</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="826788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AEGEAN SEA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREECE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREECE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES) WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL'CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DE1739F932A05752C0A960958260" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Brokers Peace Accord In the Aegean</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN ENGELBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ENGELBERG, STEPHEN;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to the entreaties of President Clinton and other senior American officials, Greece and Turkey late this evening pulled back from a military confrontation over a tiny, uninhabited island in the Aegean.</p>
        <p>A State Department official said that a "mutually acceptable agreement" under which the two countries withdrew their forces and stopped unfurling flags over the 1,000-square-yard rocky outcropping came shortly before midnight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to the entreaties of President Clinton and other senior American officials, Greece and Turkey late this evening pulled back from a military confrontation over a tiny, uninhabited island in the Aegean.</p>
        <p>A State Department official said that a "mutually acceptable agreement" under which the two countries withdrew their forces and stopped unfurling flags over the 1,000-square-yard rocky outcropping came shortly before midnight.</p>
        <p>The official said that both sides had agreed to return to "the status quo ante" under which neither Greece nor Turkey asserted sovereignty over the island.</p>
        <p>"Greek and Turkish forces are withdrawing at this time," the official said, reading from a prepared statement. "The United States will monitor the withdrawal."</p>
        <p>The announcement brought to an end one of the more peculiar chapters in NATO  history, a moment when two members of the alliance edged close to hostilities over an utterly unstrategic piece of land.</p>
        <p>It began as a typical Greek-Turkish dispute over territory, and was initially treated by the Clinton Administration as a minor imbroglio. Diplomatic notes were delivered by American officials in Ankara and Athens this week urging both  sides to reconsider their stands.</p>
        <p>But American officials became alarmed this morning when they saw intelligence reports that the two sides were headed toward a military confrontation. A contingent of 12 Greek commandos was holding the island, and had unfurled the blue and white Greek flag above it. The Turks had plans to overrun the Greeks. Both sides had warships and airplanes poised over the tiny island, which is four miles off the Turkish coast near the city of Bodrum.</p>
        <p>The reports set off alarm bells across Washington. President Clinton called the Prime Ministers of both countries and the Turkish President, Suleyman Demirel. American officials said all three leaders assured Mr. Clinton that they did not want to see hostilities erupt.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Warren Christopher, Secretary of Defense William Perry, Gen. John Shalikaskvili, the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and Anthony  Lake, the national security adviser, all worked the phones to their Greek and Turkish counterparts, urging them to back down from the ultimatums they had been trading in recent days.</p>
        <p>The incident over the island came at a sensitive moment for both countries..</p>
        <p>In Turkey, Prime Minister Tansu Ciller heads a caretaker Government and handed in her resignation last month after an Islamic party finished first in her country's elections, defying a secular tradition that has been a cornerstone of Turkish Government for seven decades.</p>
        <p>In Greece, the Government has drifted for months during the illness of Prime  Minister Andreas Papandreou. This month, Mr. Papandreou was replaced by Costas Simitis, whose Government faces its first vote of confidence in the Greek Parliament this week.</p>
        <p>The disputed territory, called Imia by the Greeks and Karnak by the Turks, is home only to several dozen goats.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, it became a flash point for tensions between the two longtime adversaries, with newspapers in both countries egging on their leaders. Over the weekend, several reporters from the Turkish daily Hurriyet rode a helicopter to  the rocks, took down the blue and white Greek flag and raised the red and white  Turkish flag.</p>
        <p>That prompted the Greeks to dispatch the small force of commandos and to raise their own flag again.</p>
        <p>The dispute arose last month when a Turkish ship ran aground on the island. According to various reports, the Turkish captain refused assistance from the Greeks. Soon, both sides were lodging protests and exchanging angry diplomatic notes.</p>
        <p>Sovereignty over the island has long been in question. The Turks insist that  the island is theirs; Greeks say that it was given them by the Italians in 1947.</p>
        <p>"All of this is obviously a function of absentee civilian leaders," said one  senior official. "You have a classic situation in which the military is disproportionately influential, and their inherent hostility toward each other just exploded."</p>
        <p>Ms. Ciller said on Monday in Ankara that her country was ready "to take all necessary measures" if the Greeks did not withdraw their troops from the island. Earlier, she said she would not permit the Greeks to create a "fait accompli" over the issue, and said that the issue could only be resolved through international negotiations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Simitis did little more to defuse tensions. "We do not accept any question on our national sovereignty," he said recently. "In defending this, we have the means and will make use of them without hesitation. Turkey should not kid itself."</p>
        <p>All of this was viewed as a tempest in a teapot by Washington, until the two  militaries began to spar with each other.</p>
        <p>A clash between Greece and Turkey could split NATO. The two countries have fought over control of the Aegean for millenia and nearly went to war over Cyprus in 1974.</p>
        <p>"It sounds incredible that they could go to the brink of military action -- I don't want to say war -- over a little piece of land smaller than the State Department," said Richard C. Holbrooke, the Assistant Secretary of State for European Affairs. "But this is serious."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
