<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.T.C. Rejects Sale of Seagram To Diageo And Pernod</title>
    <meta content="24DRIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/24/business/worldbusiness/24DRIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1336595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rum</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Diageo Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pernod Ricard</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Universal Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pillsbury Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Mills Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapner, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muris, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Diageo Plc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bronfman, Edgar Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFDA1431F937A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.T.C. Rejects Sale of Seagram To Diageo And Pernod</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">F.T.C. Rejects Sale of Seagram to Diageo and Pernod</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN with SUZANNE KAPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Kapner, Suzanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Trade Commission seeks court order to block $8.15 billion sale of Seagram Co's wine and spirits business to Diageo and Pernod Ricard of Europe, arguing that sale would give Diageo stranglehold on US market for rum; commission director Joseph Simons says sale would create dangerous likelihood of reduced competition and higher prices; Diageo plans to continue discussions with commission in hopes of reaching settlement; Seagram's owner, Vivendi Universal, also says it is committed to deal; Diageo's proposed sale of its Pillsbury food business to General Mills $10.5 billion is allowed to proceed after commission's chairman Timothy J Muris recuses himself from vote (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>United States regulators moved yesterday to block the sale of the Seagram wine and spirits business to Diageo and Pernod Ricard of Europe, the first major deal to be rejected by the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>But another controversial deal, Diageo's proposed sale of its Pillsbury food business to General Mills, was allowed to proceed after the top regulator recused himself from a vote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>United States regulators moved on Tuesday to block the sale of the Seagram wine and spirits business to Diageo and Pernod Ricard of Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>United States regulators moved yesterday to block the sale of the Seagram wine and spirits business to Diageo and Pernod Ricard of Europe, the first major deal to be rejected by the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>But another controversial deal, Diageo's proposed sale of its Pillsbury food business to General Mills, was allowed to proceed after the top regulator recused himself from a vote.</p>
        <p>In a unanimous decision, the Federal Trade Commission agreed to seek a court order to block the $8.15 billion sale of Seagram, arguing that the sale would give Diageo a stranglehold on the United States market for rum.</p>
        <p>''The proposed merger would consolidate the second- and third-largest U.S. rum producers, leaving only two large sellers of rum in the United States,'' said Joseph  Simons, director of the commission's bureau of competition. Seagram, the No. 2 company, has Captain Morgan rum, and Diageo is No. 3 with the fast-growing Malibu Caribbean white rum. Combined, they would be a stronger force against Bacardi, the nation's largest seller of rum.</p>
        <p>The sale would ''create a dangerous likelihood of reduced competition and higher prices for consumers,'' Mr. Simons said.</p>
        <p>Diageo said late yesterday that it planned to continue discussions with the commission in hopes of reaching a settlement. Seagram's owner, Vivendi Universal, also said it was committed to a deal.</p>
        <p>''The question is not if the transaction will close,'' said Edgar Bronfman Jr., executive vice chairman of Vivendi Universal. ''It is a matter of when, which in any case is no later than Dec. 31, 2001. We remain completely confident that the specific issues raised by the commission will be resolved in a timely fashion.''</p>
        <p>One possibility would be for Diageo to divest itself of Malibu, a proposal that has gained some credence in recent days. Some people close to the F.T.C. said such a move could lead to approval of the Seagram sale.</p>
        <p>The trade commission's staff had recommended that the Seagram deal be blocked, as the full commission did. But it had also recommended that the $10.5 billion sale of Pillsbury be halted. The Pillsbury acquisition was allowed to proceed after the commission's chairman, Timothy J. Muris, recused himself. Two commissioners voted in favor, and two  against. A recent recusal by Mr. Muris in a similar case let Pepsi's acquisition of Gatorade go forward despite the agency staff's opposition and a deadlocked vote by the panel.</p>
        <p>Diageo, the world's largest producer of spirits, with brands like Smirnoff, Johnnie Walker and Tanqueray, sees the acquisition of Seagram's drink business as important to future growth. If regulatory concerns stop this deal, they could stymie future acquisitions as well.</p>
        <p>Halting the deal would also be a major setback for Pernod Ricard, a French company that would have risen from No.  5 to become the third-largest maker of spirits in the world.</p>
        <p>Pernod's chairman, Patrick Ricard, said he was resolute. ''We remain confident that this transaction will be brought to a successful conclusion,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Vivendi Universal, which acquired  the Seagram Company in June 2000, never intended to keep to the spirits business. It was interested solely in Seagram's entertainment assets, including Universal Studios and Polygram Records, and it began looking for a buyer almost immediately.</p>
        <p>The original bidders for Seagram included Allied Domecq, and an alliance between Bacardi and Brown-Forman, both of which would probably bid again if a settlement is not reached.</p>
        <p>Diageo and Pernod Ricard could agree to sell certain brands or to split them differently to reach a settlement with the commission. Under the proposal, Diageo was to get Captain Morgan, Crown Royal and V.O. Canadian whiskeys, while Pernod was to get Chivas Regal, Martell Cognac, Seagram's Extra Dry gin, Glen Grant, Royal Salute and Glenlivet whiskeys, as well as Seagram's Scotch whiskey manufacturing and bottling plants in Scotland.</p>
        <p>The auction of the Seagram business was considered a special opportunity for liquor companies. At a time when sales of spirits have been sluggish, some hot brands presented a chance to accelerate sales growth. Both Captain Morgan and Crown Royal are growing at 5 percent a year, while another brand for which Seagram had distribution rights, Absolut, has annual sales growth of 10 percent.</p>
        <p>General Mills' acquisition of Pillsbury will increase concentration in the baking goods market. Commissioner Mozelle W. Thompson voted against the combination. ''The proffered recipe is clearly missing vital ingredients,'' he said, adding, ''The voluminous evidence reviewed by staff indicates that the proposed transaction offers few, if any, consumer benefits.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
