<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Langenbrunner Celebrates, and the Devils Tag Along</title>
    <meta content="26DEVI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/26/sports/hockey/26DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1378981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Panthers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Panthers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Langenbrunner, Jamie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D7123BF935A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Langenbrunner Celebrates, and the Devils Tag Along</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Langenbrunner Celebrates, and the Devils Tag Along</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., March 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils defeat Florida Panthers, 3-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jamie Langenbrunner celebrates each goal with a cockeyed grin, as if he has surprised himself. His goals do not usually include pirouettes or shots that reach triple digits on a radar gun. He scuffles for everything he gets.</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner scuffled to score his 12th goal of the season tonight, and it was a big one for the Devils. Eighteen seconds into the third period, he broke a tie by slapping in the rebound of a shot by Patrik Elias, and the Devils defeated the Florida Panthers, 3-1, before 15,014 at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eighteen seconds into the third period, the Devils' Jamie Langenbrunner scored to break a tie and beat the Florida Panthers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jamie Langenbrunner celebrates each goal with a cockeyed grin, as if he has surprised himself. His goals do not usually include pirouettes or shots that reach triple digits on a radar gun. He scuffles for everything he gets.</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner scuffled to score his 12th goal of the season tonight, and it was a big one for the Devils. Eighteen seconds into the third period, he broke a tie by slapping in the rebound of a shot by Patrik Elias, and the Devils defeated the Florida Panthers, 3-1, before 15,014 at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>''They teach us to go to the net, and I just went to the net,'' Langenbrunner said.</p>
        <p>The Devils (33-26-9-4) won for the third time in four games since they acquired Langenbrunner and Joe Nieuwendyk from Dallas. They also stayed 2 points behind the Islanders in the race for sixth place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>''I just like it that he competes hard all the time,'' Devils Coach Kevin Constantine said of Langenbrunner. ''You can trust that he's going to give you the same effort every single shift.''</p>
        <p>Langenbrunner, a 26-year-old right wing, has scored two goals in his four games with the team. The game-winning sequence included a gorgeous pass from Nieuwendyk to Elias, who scored in the second period. Langenbrunner smacked in the rebound for the Devils, who also got a goal from John Madden with 30 seconds left in the game.</p>
        <p>Florida (19-41-7-5), outshot tonight by 37-15, dropped out of the race for a playoff berth long ago. But the Devils had to play without center Bobby Holik for the first time this season. Petr Sykora also missed his fourth straight game because of the flu.</p>
        <p>Earlier today, the National Hockey League suspended Holik for one game for his role in a high-sticking incident Saturday with Carolina Hurricanes center Rod Brind'Amour. Holik, who has been suspended four times over the past five seasons, jabbed the butt end of his stick into Brind'Amour's face on a face-off. Brind'Amour retaliated by chasing Holik around the ice until he was penalized for crosschecking, but he was not punished further.</p>
        <p>''In my mind, there's nothing to be regretful about,'' Holik said before tonight's game.</p>
        <p>Holik, who forfeited his salary of $18,041.24 for tonight's game to the N.H.L.'s Players Emergency Fund, said he did not plan to appeal the suspension or, for that matter, to discuss what happened Saturday. After the game Saturday, Brind'Amour alleged that Holik tended to thrust his stick upward after losing a face-off, but Holik did not want to reply.</p>
        <p>''We could have a good time talking about these things all night long, if we'd want,'' Holik said. ''But I don't want to.''</p>
        <p>Valery Kamensky took Holik's place between Scott Gomez and Sergei Brylin, but the Devils got their best scoring chances from Nieuwendyk's line, which included Elias at the start of the game for the first time. The line looked good right away.</p>
        <p>Elias beat Trevor Kidd 27 seconds into the second period. With Florida's Brad Ference serving a tripping penalty, Elias cruised toward Kidd and got him off balance. Elias then swept around Kidd and tapped in his 24th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Elias had scored only once in his last eight games and twice in his last 14 games. Elias's struggles, coupled with the dwindling productivity of his linemates Jason Arnott and Sykora, led General Manager Lou Lamoriello to trade Arnott for Nieuwendyk.</p>
        <p>Florida tied the score at 7 minutes 15 seconds of the second period when Olli Jokinen drove Elias off the puck and slipped a pass to Ivan Novoseltsev, leading to a breakaway short-handed goal by Novoseltsev. That goal seemed to throw off the Devils for a while. Then Langenbrunner scored.</p>
        <p>Constantine was not in the mood to make any line combinations permanent. He pointed out that Stéphane Richer, acquired last week from Pittsburgh, played well with Nieuwendyk and Langenbrunner, too. But then he said, ''The idea that two guys have chemistry is something you do consider when you put together a line.''</p>
        <p>Nieuwendyk and Langenbrunner had that. Elias's brilliance provided Langenbrunner with another chance to scuffle for a goal.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
