<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Here, Islamic Law Guides How the Food Is Killed</title>
    <meta content="26BUTC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/26/nyregion/26BUTC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1378903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Musa Slaughterhouse (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Aaron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DB123BF935A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1159" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Here, Islamic Law Guides How the Food Is Killed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Here, Islamic Law Guides How the Food Is Killed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AARON DONOVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Donovan, Aaron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Musa Slaughterhouse in Bronx kills chickens, goats and sheep according to Islamic dietary laws, halal; also caters to large Hispanic and West African populations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along a gray industrial stretch of Third Avenue in the South Bronx, it is a surprise to hear a rooster crowing daybreak. But then one spots the sign at the corner of East 168th Street showing hand-painted heads of chickens, goats and sheep and the words ''You Pick Them, We Kill Them.''</p>
        <p>Inside the cinder-block walls of the building is the Musa Slaughterhouse, its pungency heavily influenced by the odor of animal droppings. Customers stand in a line, waiting to place their orders for snow white chickens, light brown hens, spotted guinea hens, roosters, quails, pigeons, ducks, chicks and rabbits.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Along a gray industrial stretch of Third Avenue in the South Bronx, it is a surprise to hear a rooster crowing daybreak. But then one spots the sign at the corner of East 168th Street showing hand-painted heads of chickens, goats and sheep and the words</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Along a gray industrial stretch of Third Avenue in the South Bronx, it is a surprise to hear a rooster crowing daybreak. But then one spots the sign at the corner of East 168th Street showing hand-painted heads of chickens, goats and sheep and the words ''You Pick Them, We Kill Them.''</p>
        <p>Inside the cinder-block walls of the building is the Musa Slaughterhouse, its pungency heavily influenced by the odor of animal droppings. Customers stand in a line, waiting to place their orders for snow white chickens, light brown hens, spotted guinea hens, roosters, quails, pigeons, ducks, chicks and rabbits.</p>
        <p>Musa is one of several slaughter-on-demand butchers in the city, which can be found in the yellow pages under Live Poultry. Many of the others in the city are smaller (and have less explicit signs), and Musa is one of the very few that slaughter and sell bigger animals like sheep, goats and cattle.</p>
        <p>Many of the customers are Muslim, and appreciate the fact that the slaughtering is carried out in accordance with Islamic dietary laws.</p>
        <p>Musa Sumrien, the owner, said that many slaughterhouses kept a low profile to avoid antagonizing people upset by the nature of the business. But he said he has not had a problem in his five years running the Musa Slaughterhouse because he treats the animals well.</p>
        <p>The animals are slaughtered according to the rules of halal, which are similar to those that govern kosher slaughtering. Halal rules mandate that the animal to be eaten must be killed by a Muslim who pronounces the name of God during the slaughter. The animal's throat must be cut quickly -- but not severed -- with a sharp knife so that the three main arteries are cut and the death is as quick and painless as possible.</p>
        <p>The slaughterhouse's customers are residents of the nearby Daniel Webster Houses, Muslim fathers who arrive by car seeking meat killed in accordance with halal preparation rules, people planning family feasts or mothers with children simply preparing for the evening meal. The customers seem to be united not so much by religion as by a desire for freshly slaughtered fowl; those standing in line spoke Spanish, Arabic and English.</p>
        <p>The offer on the sign notwithstanding, most of the customers simply said what bird they wanted and how many, and left the choice to Abdullah Alawi, who manages part of the slaughterhouse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alawi, a scruffy man with a knee-length white linen coat, a worn New York Rangers cap and a quick smile, worked at a grocery store in Brooklyn before he began at the slaughterhouse three years ago. He acknowledges that his is not the best work in the world, but that he is happy to have it. ''It's hard to get a job,'' he said. ''This is what we have to do.''</p>
        <p>When customers placed their orders, mostly for the tender white chickens or tougher brown hens, Mr. Alawi reached into the cages to retrieve the protesting fowl with gloved hand or a metal leg hook. The birds ran from their captor and fought him in every way they could. When he caught them they squawked, kicked and beat their wings. Feathers went flying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sumrien has run his 4,000-square-foot slaughterhouse for five years. It has just a half-dozen employees on any of the seven days a week it is open.</p>
        <p>He said the shop was inspected weekly by the United States Department of Agriculture and that he was not allowed to sell to restaurants or businesses, but could sell to mosques. Perhaps most important, he is not allowed to sell animals that are still alive.</p>
        <p>Sheep, like the popular white chickens, cost 99 cents a pound, which ends up being about $15 per bird or $200 for the sheep. The livestock comes from farms upstate, in Pennsylvania, and as far south as Virginia.</p>
        <p>After each order, Mr. Alawi took the animals through two red swinging doors and put them into a circular yellow plastic garbage bin. One by one he took the birds out of the bin, pulled their heads back and slit their throats with a single quick motion while saying a blessing, ''Bismillah Allah-u-Akbar,'' which he explained later meant, ''In the name of Allah, Allah is great.''</p>
        <p>The birds, with severed necks but still writhing, were then placed upside down in a metal container so the blood could quickly drain. From there, Mr. Alawi's assistant, Maria Perez, 24, took over while he went back to the selection room. She took the bodies and washed them in a bath of boiling water, and moved them to a plucking machine that spun the bodies in a metal cylinder with black rubber nodules sticking out from the sides to rub off the feathers.</p>
        <p>After spinning them for a minute or so, Ms. Perez took the now featherless bodies to an adjacent room where she washed them by hand before cutting them into pieces at a spinning circular saw, putting the parts into a double plastic bag and calling out the cutomer's number. The entire process, from order to receipt, took about 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Two doors down the street is the part of the slaughterhouse that houses the hooved animals: two levels of lambs, sheep, goats and cows that feed on grain and hay and jostle one another for space.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sumrien said many of his customers for those animals were Hispanic, Jamaican, Haitian, Italian or West African. ''Spanish people like to have fresh stuff,'' he said. ''Jamaicans, they like billy goats. They will not eat a female goat. Arabs like to have lambs; Italians, goats and lambs. This is for all the religions.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sumrien said he overbought last month in preparation for the holiday that ends the annual pilgrimage to Mecca, when Muslims traditionally have large family meals to celebrate the prophet Abraham's willingness to sacrifice his son Ishmael to God. As a result, a number of unslaughtered lambs and sheep padded about their side of the slaughterhouse, occasionally bumping into one another, but largely quiet.</p>
        <p>Chanis Dyer, 47, stood outside pushing her 3-month-old grandson, Gavin Bonar, in a stroller. Ms. Dyer, visiting from Jamaica, was getting ready to help cook for Gavin's christening party, with 50 people expected.</p>
        <p>She bought a billy goat for $106 and four chickens for $15, and spoke about the soup and curry she was planning to prepare. ''I'm glad they have it,'' she said, ''but I didn't expect to find a place like this in this city.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
