<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saudi Curbs on Yemeni Workers Sets Off a Migration</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="394078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="MIDEAST TENSIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">YEMEN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDA1739F931A15753C1A966958260" item-length="1539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saudi Curbs on Yemeni Workers Sets Off a Migration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>JIDDA, Saudi Arabia, Oct. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Saudi Government has suspended residency privileges for Yemenis working here in response to Yemen's support of Iraq in the Persian Gulf crisis and set off a mass migration of at least 350,000 of them in the Last three weeks.</p>
        <p>Officials say that by early summer the move could force out an estimated one million Yemenis, a quarter of the expatriate labor force here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Saudi Government has suspended residency privileges for Yemenis working here in response to Yemen's support of Iraq in the Persian Gulf crisis and set off a mass migration of at least 350,000 of them in the Last three weeks.</p>
        <p>Officials say that by early summer the move could force out an estimated one million Yemenis, a quarter of the expatriate labor force here.</p>
        <p>The departure of the Yemeni workers dramatically adds to the negative political, economic and demographic consequences brought to the region by the crisis, including the flight of roughly two million workers, mainly Egyptians and Asians, from Iraq and Iraqi-occupied Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The departures from Saudi Arabia differ from the migrations out of those two countries in that the Yemenis are apparently being allowed to take most of their earnings and savings with them. Blow to Yemeni Economy</p>
        <p>Redah M. Larry, editor of the daily Saudi Gazette here, estimated that the already wobbly economy of neighboring Yemen is being deprived of $350 million a month in remittances from the Saudi earnings of the expatriates. Confirming the impact, Yemen's President, Ali Abdullah Saleh, said several days ago that his country "is currently facing economic difficulties because of the gulf crisis and the return of thousands of expatriates from Saudi Arabia."</p>
        <p>In a comment underlining deep hostility to the Saudi move, the Yemeni Foreign Minister, Abdel Karim al-Iryani, told a meeting of Arab League foreign ministers on Thursday that "the 350,000 Yemenis who have so far returned left behind cash, properties and acquired rights they had earned over decades of hard work, sweat and effort."</p>
        <p>Saudi officials have vehemently denounced this charge as "an outright lie," saying all Yemenis were allowed to transfer any money they had and take all their possessions with them as they drove out of Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>Yemenis indeed readily acknowledged that they were not prevented from taking whatever they could with them, but their hurried departure has caused financial losses and severe social hardships in addition to the loss of their normal income. Relations Deteriorating</p>
        <p>Since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, relations between Saudi Arabia and Yemen have deteriorated sharply. As the Saudis have allowed foreign forces into the country to defend against Iraq, Yemen has opposed United Nations and Arab League resolutions against Baghdad and said it would not fully comply with anti-Iraqi sanctions.</p>
        <p>Iraq and Yemen have close economic and political ties, and Yemen sent forces to back Iraq during its war with Iran. Before the international embargo imposed against Baghdad in the present crisis, the Yemeni port at Aden was a major transhipment point for Iraqi imports and exports, including oil.</p>
        <p>The Saudis and the Yemenis have also had an interdependent relationship, but an often tense one stemming from the conservative Saudi monarchy's fear of foreign subversion. Yemenis have played a major role in Saudi Arabia's labor force and service sector and had been allowed free movement across the border -- an anomaly in Saudi Arabia's restricted contact with the outside world.</p>
        <p>The free movement of all Yemenis was permitted for decades, even before Marxist Southern Yemen and pro-Western Yemen merged this year.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 19 the Saudi Government, reacting sharply to Yemen's support of Iraq, expelled 32 Yemeni diplomats, then issued a decree saying all Yemenis living here had a month to obtain legal residency, which requires the guarantee of a Saudi employer. It also said all Yemenis owning businesses had to obtain a Saudi partner or sell their business to a Saudi. Most Yemenis say they could do neither in such a short period.  Selling at Distress Prices</p>
        <p>Although there are no precise figures, most businessmen among the 2 million Yemenis living here had to sell businesses at distress prices. Reflecting widespread hostility here toward Yemenis, Saudi employers have been slow to hire formally the Yemeni workers who worked for them without special permission before the decree.</p>
        <p>The effect on Saudi service industries was quickly felt.</p>
        <p>"In one week, I lost my driver, my gardener and the guy who washed our cars at the office," said an American banker who lives here. "A grocer I used to go to has shut down, and the other has told me he may have to sell his store at a price of no more than 20 percent the value. Saudis are telling them it's a take-it-or-leave-it proposition."</p>
        <p>"What happened to us is an earthquake," said a Yemeni who was waiting along with hundreds of others at the Saudi immigration authority's office here the other day to collect an application form for legal residence. 'We Will All Go'</p>
        <p>"I have not been able to find a sponsor yet," said the man, a laborer in his 40's, who added that he has lived in Saudi Arabia for 17 years and that most of his children were born here. "This application is useless. I'll probably go home. We will all go."</p>
        <p>Like almost all Yemenis interviewed, he asked not to be identified for fear of retribution.</p>
        <p>The Saudi move has resulted in some Yemeni families being painfully divided, since many of them obtained Saudi citizenship a decade ago when it was possible. Relatives have been unable to do so because the practice was suspended about three years ago.</p>
        <p>Saudi-Yemeni relations have always had a tense edge. Saudis worry about subversive activities by the Yemenis living here who have never professed much affection for Saudi Arabia. For their part, the Saudis have encouraged dissent among many of the pro-Saudi, conservative Yemeni tribes close to the Saudi border that resent the socialist Yemeni Government.</p>
        <p>Today, the semi-official Saudi newspaper Asharq al Awsat disclosed in a front-page article that more than 30,000 Yemenis from the pro-Saudi tribes held a three-day meeting in the Khafdah region recently at which they demanded that the Yemeni Government "clearly and openly" condemn the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq and suspend its support of Baghdad. They also formed a committee to support Kuwait. A Menacing Tone</p>
        <p>The article had a menacing tone to it, suggesting that the tribes might rebel against the Government and cut off supply lines of the Yemeni Army that pass through their region. The article also said the Yemeni Government came close to bombarding the meeting place.</p>
        <p>Foreign diplomats here say one of the most important aspects of the gulf crisis and the Yemen dispute is to highight the vulnerability of Saudi Arabia to the more heavily populated countries with which it shares borders, including Iraq, which has 16 million inhabitants, and southern and northern Yemen, which together have 14 million.</p>
        <p>By contrast, there is no reliable estimate of the Saudi population. Western diplomats here dispute the frequently cited official figure of 14 million Saudis. A senior Western envoy who asked not to be identified said there were "probably not more than 6 million native Saudis in the country and about 4 million expatriates, of whom half are Yemenis."</p>
        <p>"What they are doing," this envoy said of the Saudis, "is dangerous and almost suicidal, but since the invasion, this country has become either very brave or very emotional, or both."  Open Clash Feared</p>
        <p>Yemeni intellectuals, most of whom have lived here for decades, are most bitter about the Saudi decisions, arguing that they will deepen political differences, perhaps pushing the two countries toward an open clash.</p>
        <p>In private and highly guarded conversations, these Yemenis readily acknowledge the Saudi charge that Yemenis by and large are not loyal to Saudi Arabia and consider themselves superior to the Saudis. They maintain they have every right to feel this way, since they contributed greatly to the prosperity of this country, with its small native-born work force.</p>
        <p>The Saudis counter that they have done Yemenis a favor by treating them as Saudis, unlike all other Arab expatriates working here, and have been repaid with betrayal and treachery.</p>
        <p>A Yemeni intellectual said such charges are unfair. He said Yemenis accused of supporting President Hussein are not much different from many Arabs, including, he said, many Saudis. All Arabs, he said, agree with the Iraqi President when it comes to his criticism of American support of Israel, the American military presence here and the "well-documented" United States hostility to the Palestinian cause.</p>
        <p>"What Saddam Hussein says is logical and reasonable," the Yemeni man said. "The only problem is that it comes from him, from a man who has shown no respect for any principles or for Islam at all."  'Big Brother Rules'</p>
        <p>Another Yemeni, a highly educated individual who also asked not to be identified, said the Saudi move "is a whimsical and opportunistic decision, the sort of thing you do in a society where Big Brother rules, where illogical switches and reversals cannot be questioned and must be accepted as the new truth.</p>
        <p>"Yesterday we were brothers. Today we are enemies, but no one explores why. If the Yemeni Government made an error -- as I indeed agree that it has -- what is the fault of the millions of Yemenis who have lived here quietly and peacefully?"  MIDEAST TENSIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
