<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cigar, Thunder Gulch Will Not Be Alone</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="794537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BELMONT PARK RACE TRACK</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURSO, JOSEPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DB103FF935A35753C1A963958260" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cigar, Thunder Gulch Will Not Be Alone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DURSO, JOSEPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They will be starting on the first turn at Belmont Park just past the clubhouse because they must run a mile and a quarter to the finish line. They will probably be fighting for footing on a heavy race track. And they will be running against the premier horse in the country, Allen Paulson's Cigar, who will be gunning for his 11th straight victory and the title Horse of the Year.</p>
        <p>But "they" will include the star 3-year-old colt, Michael Tabor's Thunder Gulch, winner of the Kentucky Derby, the Belmont Stakes, the Travers and the Kentucky Cup Classic. And so, they will be running the race of the year, the $750,000 Jockey Club Gold Cup, to find the Horse of the Year, or, at least to establish claims to fame in the Breeders' Cup on the same track three weeks later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They will be starting on the first turn at Belmont Park just past the clubhouse because they must run a mile and a quarter to the finish line. They will probably be fighting for footing on a heavy race track. And they will be running against the premier horse in the country, Allen Paulson's Cigar, who will be gunning for his 11th straight victory and the title Horse of the Year.</p>
        <p>But "they" will include the star 3-year-old colt, Michael Tabor's Thunder Gulch, winner of the Kentucky Derby, the Belmont Stakes, the Travers and the Kentucky Cup Classic. And so, they will be running the race of the year, the $750,000 Jockey Club Gold Cup, to find the Horse of the Year, or, at least to establish claims to fame in the Breeders' Cup on the same track three weeks later.</p>
        <p>A total of 52 horses were entered yesterday in tomorrow's six stakes races at Belmont Park, a day heralded as the Breeders' Cup Preview day, spiced with a dozen or more horses from Europe and enhanced by $2.4 million in purses.</p>
        <p>Cigar drew the No. 6 post position in a field of eight horses that may lose one or two before race time, and was made the 1-5 favorite to win the race over Thunder Gulch, who drew the No. 4 lane and was next in the betting at 4-1. They will be staging their showdown earlier than expected, but D. Wayne Lukas decided this week not to wait for the Breeders' Cup but to bait the mighty Cigar here and now.</p>
        <p>"He's coming with a bold and game and gritty horse," said Bill Mott, who trains Cigar, "and he's always a factor."</p>
        <p>"Bill has a marvelous horse," Lukas said, "and I know I'm coming into his home turf. But I needed to be in this race to be ready for Oct. 28. And I think whichever horse wins the Breeders' Cup Classic, he's the Horse of the Year."</p>
        <p>Both trainers said their horses had never run in mud, nor even worked in mud. But both seemed to be expecting the Belmont track to dry out when the rain ended yesterday, and to continue drying with a forecast for clearer weather tomorrow.</p>
        <p>There was not much either of them could do, though, about the start smack in the middle of the first turn. Belmont's main track stretches for a mile and a half, meaning that the mile-and-a-quarter Gold Cup must be started a quarter of a mile past the finish line, or in the middle of the first turn.</p>
        <p>But the two superstars will not be alone. They will have to withstand the fast early pace likely to be set by Nick Zito's Star Standard and to hold off Scotty Schulhofer's Unaccounted For in the homestretch. They will also have to look over their shoulders for the late-running Concern, if he stays in the entry lists, but he was expected to run instead in the $500,000 Meadowlands Cup tonight if the track in New Jersey was dry enough.</p>
        <p>For that matter, Unaccounted For also was entered in both races, but was known to prefer the Gold Cup despite the odds: He was 9-2 at the Meadowlands and 10-1 at Belmont. The Meadowlands Cup, at a mile and an eighth, also includes French Deputy, who missed the Triple Crown races this year with a foot injury but who has won all four of his races. He was ranked second in the betting to Concern and his stablemate, Looming.</p>
        <p>The largest fields at Belmont Park were drawn for two races on the grass, the $200,000 Kelso with 15 horses led by Dove Hunt and the $500,000 Turf Classic Invitational with 10 led by Awad. But Lukas again had the favorites in the two races for juveniles, with Golden Attraction in the Frizette for fillies and Hennessy in the Moet Champagne for colts.</p>
        <p>Only five fillies were entered in the Beldame, but it looked like the most competitive race of the day. The favorite at 3-5 was Shug McGaughey's defending champion, Heavenly Prize, but she was opposed by Lukas's star filly Serena's Song and Lakeway, Incinerate and Unlawful Behavior.</p>
        <p>Lakeway had been aimed at the Spinster at Keeneland on Sunday, but her trainer Gary Jones "called an audible" and picked Belmont instead. But the Spinster still offers Inside Information, the stablemate to Heavenly Prize, and Mariah's Storm, who outran Serena's Song by five lengths in Kentucky. And all roads clearly were leading to Belmont for the Breeders' Cup.  HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
