<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Looking for Love in 3 Different Places</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="794350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FESTIVALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK FILM FESTIVAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARTLEY, HAL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FLIRT (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DD1239F935A35753C1A963958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Looking for Love in 3 Different Places</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You might describe "Flirt," Hal Hartley's smart, sexy, wafer-light new movie, as a jauntily romantic theme and variations on young love, international style.  Hopscotching from New York to Berlin to Tokyo, the film flaunts the perilously cute concept of telling the same story in three different places with three sets of characters speaking three different languages. Watching the movie is like eating ice cream -- or is it ice milk? -- in three different flavors: vanilla, chocolate and green tea. They go together nicely.</p>
        <p>"Flirt," which the New York Film Festival is showing at Alice Tully Hall tonight at 6 and tomorrow night at 11:30, is no "Rashomon." But neither is it a  dry exercise in cross-cultural style. In an airy, self-assured way, the three episodes suggest a common denominator of romantic attitudes (with significant differences from place to place) among the young, hip and urbane of three continents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You might describe "Flirt," Hal Hartley's smart, sexy, wafer-light new movie, as a jauntily romantic theme and variations on young love, international style.  Hopscotching from New York to Berlin to Tokyo, the film flaunts the perilously cute concept of telling the same story in three different places with three sets of characters speaking three different languages. Watching the movie is like eating ice cream -- or is it ice milk? -- in three different flavors: vanilla, chocolate and green tea. They go together nicely.</p>
        <p>"Flirt," which the New York Film Festival is showing at Alice Tully Hall tonight at 6 and tomorrow night at 11:30, is no "Rashomon." But neither is it a  dry exercise in cross-cultural style. In an airy, self-assured way, the three episodes suggest a common denominator of romantic attitudes (with significant differences from place to place) among the young, hip and urbane of three continents.</p>
        <p>If commitment is difficult, the movie implies, it is because love is so easy to come by, and the grass is always greener. In the artsy milieus the film visits, it is no big deal when love crosses conventional barriers of race, age and sexual orientation. The fly in the ointment, which all the liberation in the world can't seem to eliminate, is jealousy.</p>
        <p>"Flirt" begins in New York with Bill (Bill Sage), a handsome ladies' man whose girlfriend, Emily (Parker Posey), is about to leave for a vacation in Paris. Once there, she warns, she might hook up with an old lover unless Bill commits to her within the next 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>Bill loves Emily but has an itch for the wife of his close friend Walter (Martin Donovan). Running into him in a bar, Bill finds Walter carrying a gun and threatening suicide. His wife has left him, Walter announces, and he accuses Bill of having designs on her. During an ambiguous tussle for the gun, the weapon goes off, grazing Bill's face. As he is painfully stitched up in a hospital emergency room, he is encouraged to think of something pleasant and murmurs his sexual fantasies to the attendant nurses, who are clearly aroused. Then he dashes off for the airport.</p>
        <p>"Flirt" retells the same story twice more, but each time the personalities and details are different enough to make the new version fresh. In Berlin, the main character, Dwight (Dwight Ewell), is a saucy young black American who swivels around in black leather pants and a gold shirt while weighing his relationship with Johan, an older German art dealer. Dwight's latest crush is Werner, a middle-aged German painter who has just left his wife, Greta, in a state of suicidal despondency.</p>
        <p>The final flirt is Miho (Miho Nikaidoh), a Japanese dance student whose boyfriend, an American film maker, is about to go to Los Angeles. When rumors of Miho's flirtation with her dance teacher, Ozu, drive Ozu's wife to threaten to shoot herself, Ozu asks Miho to dispose of his wife's gun, and Miho finds herself pursued by the police and arrested for possession of a deadly weapon.</p>
        <p>Although "Flirt' doesn't stray very far from lighthearted comic realism, it follows the film maker's earlier movies in slipping in some delightful bits of absurdism. In the funniest recurrent set piece, each flirt impulsively blurts out his romantic confusion to a bunch of strangers and is heatedly regaled with  advice that is as amusing as it is wildly contradictory. At least one of the respondents offers a spontaneous disquisition that sounds like a parody of scholarly analysis.</p>
        <p>The emergency room sequences are completely different from one another. Where Bill is fawned over with discreet lust, Dwight is treated with calm detachment,  and Miho with frantic desperation. Although the sexual fantasies that the characters use to distract themselves from the pain of Novocaine injections are  very different, they share the image of "spooning," which they explain is lying  curled up side by side with their lovers.</p>
        <p>Whatever the language, Mr. Hartley's characters all speak in a way that often carries a deadpan comic edge. By the end of the film, certain phrases have acquired the quality of riddles. When one lover asks another if the two of them  have a future, yes or no, the response has cryptic resonance: "You don't have to see it if you know it's there."</p>
        <p>"Flirt" is exactly what its title implies, an artful tease that is more serious than it looks, but far from the last word on the uneasy comings and goings of modern love.</p>
        <p>In Ryc Montgomery's short film "The Beast," which opens the program, an animal researcher who has figured out how to electronically translate monkey thoughts into human speech demonstrates his discovery in a crowded courtroom. This clever, mean-spirited film seduces the viewer into falling for an adorable  chimp named Martha, then gleefully pulls the rug out.</p>
        <p>FLIRT</p>
        <p>Written (in English, German and Japanese, with English subtitles) and directed by Hal Hartley; director of photography, Michael Spiller; music by Ned Rifle and Jeffrey Taylor; production designer, Steve Rosenzweig; produced by Ted Hope. At  Alice Tully Hall tonight at 6 and tomorrow at 11:30 P.M. as part of the 33d New  York Film Festival. Running time: 85 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Bill Sage (Bill), Parker Posey (Emily) and Martin Donovan (Walter).</p>
        <p>FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
