<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Council Hearing Ends in Chaos After Shouts and Curses</title>
    <meta content="08HRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1008253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Human Resources Administration (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Jason A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dibrienza, Stephen (Councilman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menges, Jake</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henry, Lloyd (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D71F3AF93BA35757C0A96E958260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Council Hearing Ends in Chaos After Shouts and Curses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Human Resources Comr Jason A Turner storms out of City Council hearing intended to assess city's welfare programs, saying that Councilman Stephen DiBrienza's thundering tone is not 'civilized'; hearing erupts in shouts and curses when Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's aide, Jake Menges, threatens Councilman Lloyd Henry after he suggests that Turner be served with subpoena to force him to testify (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Outraged by the soaring decibels of a city councilman's voice, Jason A. Turner, the newly appointed Commissioner of the Human Resources Administration, stormed out of a City Council hearing yesterday, saying the councilman's thundering tone was not ''civilized.''</p>
        <p>Minutes later, the hearing erupted in shouts and curses as an aide to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, using an obscenity, threatened a council member who had suggested that Mr. Turner be served with a subpoena to force him to testify.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Outraged by the soaring decibels of a city councilman's voice, Jason A. Turner, the newly appointed Commissioner of the Human Resources Administration, stormed out of a City Council hearing yesterday, saying the councilman's thundering tone was not ''civilized.''</p>
        <p>Minutes later, the hearing erupted in shouts and curses as an aide to Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, using an obscenity, threatened a council member who had suggested that Mr. Turner be served with a subpoena to force him to testify.</p>
        <p>The aide, Jake Menges, told the stunned Councilman, Lloyd Henry, that he ''can forget about'' having a beacon school -- a specialized school coveted by many local communities -- in his district.</p>
        <p>And so it was that a hearing intended to assess welfare programs dissolved into a raucous New York-style political circus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Menges first denied making the threat, then apologized for it. (He was, after all, caught on camera.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner stood firm. Randy Mastro, the Deputy Mayor for Operations, apologized for Mr. Menges, his deputy chief of staff, but said that there was no need to apologize for Mr. Turner because the Commissioner had been abused by Councilman Stephen DiBrienza.</p>
        <p>And Mr. DiBrienza, known for his booming voice, aggressive questions and pointed criticism of Mr. Giuliani's social programs, countered that Mr. Turner should get used to the speech patterns of New Yorkers, who often roar during political discussions.</p>
        <p>''I didn't attack him,'' Mr. DiBrienza said of his questioning of Mr. Turner, who recently moved to New York from Wisconsin. ''I simply raised my voice because it's my habit to speak loudly.''</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. DiBrienza's manner of questioning offended another City Commissioner, Nicholas Scoppetta, who runs the Administration for Children's Services. Mr. Scoppetta walked out, too, although, he has since reappeared before the Council.</p>
        <p>The questions that spurred yesterday's walkout were about the city's plans for its welfare program. Mr. DiBrienza, who has criticized the workfare program, was asking Mr. Turner how he planned to move the vast majority of welfare recipients into real jobs, a sensitive topic for an administration that has offered scant evidence to show that workfare actually connects people to jobs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turner asked him to lower his voice. Mr. DiBrienza refused. And so Mr. Turner stalked out without answering the question, with his startled deputies trailing behind. Mayor Giuliani said he was right to do so.</p>
        <p>''Mr. DiBrienza conducted that hearing in a way that was unprofessional and provocative,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''He was yelling at the Commissioner.''</p>
        <p>The members of Mr. DiBrienza's General Welfare Committee disagreed, with some speculating that the Commissioner had staged the walkout to avoid answering tough questions. Together, the council members roundly condemned Mr. Menges and unanimously voted to compel Mr. Turner to reappear at another hearing, on a yet undetermined date.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
