<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oh, That Brazen, Raucous, Glorious Hibiscus</title>
    <meta content="29CUTT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1005803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hibiscus (Plant)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peterson, Cass</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DE143BF93AA15750C0A96E958260" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oh, That Brazen, Raucous, Glorious Hibiscus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Cass Peterson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Peterson, Cass</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gardening column on opulent blooms of the hibiscus; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the subject of hibiscus, there is little room for neutrality. Some gardeners adore it, some hate it, and a few profess to admire the tropical varieties while despising the hardy perennial types. Hibiscus inspires opinion.</p>
        <p>It is, for sure, a plant that is not easily overlooked. Some garden residents get by on tolerance, whether they are loved or not, because they are so understated that they cannot offend. Persian stonecress fills its niche in the rock garden without being in the least obtrusive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the subject of hibiscus, there is little room for neutrality. Some gardeners adore it, some hate it, and a few profess to admire the tropical varieties while despising the hardy perennial types. Hibiscus inspires opinion.</p>
        <p>It is, for sure, a plant that is not easily overlooked. Some garden residents get by on tolerance, whether they are loved or not, because they are so understated that they cannot offend. Persian stonecress fills its niche in the rock garden without being in the least obtrusive.</p>
        <p>Creeping phlox, after its brief spring glory, settles into a humdrum appearance that is not much more decorative than chickweed, but not unattractive, either.</p>
        <p>Hibiscus, a member of the Malvaceae or mallow family, is the antithesis of inconspicuous. Most species grow to 4 feet; some will top out at 15 feet. Its flamboyant blossoms unfurl from fat buds like parasols, as much as a foot across, and colors tend to be bold -- brilliant pink, brooding maroon, intense blue-lavender.</p>
        <p>White and pale-pink varieties often sport a vivid color contrast at the throat, and in any case the sheer mass of the flower demands attention, no matter how muted the shade.</p>
        <p>In the perennial border, nestled amid the feathery flax and the delicate dianthus, a hibiscus looks not only out of place but even downright raucous.</p>
        <p>But like peonies, Oriental poppies and cabbage roses, the opulent blooms of hibiscus have their place. For most gardeners, the right place for the tropical varieties (H. Rosa-sinensis) is in a big pot or tub on the deck or patio. The closer to the house the better, because unless the garden is somewhere south of Georgia, frost-tender tropical hibiscus will need to be lugged inside for the winter.</p>
        <p>Tropical hibiscus has dark-green glossy foliage. Thanks to many professional and amateur devotees, the blooms come in a zillion or so colors (everything except true blue and black), and a variety of single and double shapes. It is the state flower of Hawaii and is so esteemed elsewhere that it has an organization dedicated to its cultivation, the American Hibiscus Society (P.O. Drawer 321540W, Cocoa Beach, Fla. 32932-1540).</p>
        <p>There apparently is no fan club for hardy hibiscus (H. moscheutos, commonly called rose mallow), and gardeners of very polished tastes tend to think it crude. The Thompson &amp; Morgan catalogue offers only one variety of H. moscheutos (the dwarf Disco Belle, which grows only two feet tall), suggesting it for use as an accent plant.</p>
        <p>This attitude seems unfair. Hardy hibiscus does not have the fine foliage of the tropicals. Its leaves are dull green and a little dusty looking. But its blossoms are no less grand than the tropical types and are even useful in the kitchen. Dried hibiscus flowers make a fine tea, and the fresh blossoms are edible.</p>
        <p>Blossoms last but a day. They don't need water to stay fresh looking. A plate lined with a hibiscus flower makes a spectacular setting for seafood or fruit salad.</p>
        <p>Hardy hibiscus is perfectly content outdoors as far north as New England. It dies to the ground in winter and emerges late in the spring. This habit makes it a good companion for Oriental poppies, which emerge early and then go dormant in summer.</p>
        <p>Even first-year plants will put on a respectable show, and mature plants will bloom heartily from late July until frost. If the garden has space for only small plants, then Disco Belle it is. But the voluptuous hibiscus blossoms are out of scale on short plants, like an adult's umbrella carried by a small child.</p>
        <p>My preference would be Southern Belle, which will grow to four feet and comes in gala red, pink and white shades, or the brilliant red Lord Baltimore or rich pink Lady Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Hardy hibiscus is fine as an accent plant, but it's even better in a massed planting, possibly underplanted with creeping phlox or some other spring-blooming ground cover that will be content, come summer, to provide a green backdrop to the hibiscus spectacle.</p>
        <p>Equally underrated is the woody form of hibiscus, Rose of Sharon (H. syriacus). This plant belongs among the shrubs or as a lawn specimen. Some species will grow to about 15 feet. It looks especially nice in massed plantings and produces four- to five-inch blooms from summer through fall, unaffected by heat, drought and urban pollution.</p>
        <p>Rose of Sharon used to be more popular as a summer-flowering shrub or hedge, possibly falling out of favor because of its habit of self-seeding. Plants that grew from the seeds were troublesome weeds, and rarely as attractive as the mother plant. Many a city alleyway is still decorated with illegitimate Rose of Sharon, growing out of cracks in the pavement and usually bearing muddy pink or faded magenta blossoms.</p>
        <p>But breeding work at the National Arboretum has resulted in lovely hybrids that are self-sterile. As a bonus, the new hybrids improved the color range into deeper lavenders and darker pinks. The plants are also more compact, topping out at 9 to 12 feet, although they can be kept shorter with pruning.</p>
        <p>Among the best of the new hybrids are Aphrodite, with dark pink blossoms, Minerva, deep lavender, and Helene, white with a dark-red throat.</p>
        <p>To my eye, these plants are not gaudy but glorious. But then, that's only my opinion.</p>
        <p>THIS WEEK  Control Weeds and Put Shears to Work</p>
        <p>It's time to think about controlling weeds in lawns: instead of dangerous herbicides, apply corn gluten meal before weeds emerge. Recent University of Iowa research has shown that this natural byproduct is very effective on common weeds like crabgrass, plantain and dandelion. Some garden centers stock it, and Gardens Alive sells it by mail, (812) 537-8650.</p>
        <p>Shear back thyme and cut out old wood on culinary sage (Salvia officianalis). When new growth emerges on stems, it will be easier to tell dead wood from live on lavender and santolina.</p>
        <p>Do maintenance pruning of witch hazel (Hamamelis x intermedia) and Chinese witch hazel (Hamamelis mollis) after their extended period of bloom and before their leaves unfurl.</p>
        <p>And if you haven't pruned your roses yet, forsythia in full bloom is nature's signal to get busy.</p>
        <p>PATRICIA JONAS</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
