<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Couples Build Bigger as Their Children Leave Home</title>
    <meta content="04BIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Padding The Empty Nest" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Padding The Empty Nest"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Iovine, Julie V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Age, Chronological</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E6D71430F937A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="2033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Couples Build Bigger as Their Children Leave Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE V. IOVINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Iovine, Julie V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many affluent baby boomers reaching their 50's are diverging from pattern of their parent's generation and building larger, more luxurious houses when their children leave home; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LYNN KORDA and Jules Kroll raised four children in a 5,900-square-foot home in Rye, N.Y. But now that their children are grown, they have decided to upsize, as builders say, and are planning a new house of at least 8,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>While Charles and Elaine Evans's three children were growing up, their country house in East Hampton, N.Y., had only one bathroom in its 980 square feet. Now that the youngest is 26 and on his own, the Evanses have more than doubled the house's size -- adding 1,000 square feet, including a second story and two bathrooms. ''Our means finally caught up with our past desires,'' Mrs. Evans said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LYNN KORDA and Jules Kroll raised four children in a 5,900-square-foot home in Rye, N.Y. But now that their children are grown, they have decided to upsize, as builders say, and are planning a new house of at least 8,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>While Charles and Elaine Evans's three children were growing up, their country house in East Hampton, N.Y., had only one bathroom in its 980 square feet. Now that the youngest is 26 and on his own, the Evanses have more than doubled the house's size -- adding 1,000 square feet, including a second story and two bathrooms. ''Our means finally caught up with our past desires,'' Mrs. Evans said.</p>
        <p>The two couples are joining the growing ranks of empty-nesters who are rejecting the traditional image of mature homeowners as people intent on cutting back and gearing down. With the last tuition check canceled and the pounding music just a ghostly echo, more couples past the breeding age are finally asking themselves how they really want to live. And surprisingly the answer often is: big.</p>
        <p>The building industry is feeling the effects of these expansive feathered nesters. While it is a trend primarily affecting the high end, most of the more than 40 builders and developers interviewed across the country said that these clients had altered the complexion of their businesses.</p>
        <p>''We're beginning to see the impact of baby boomers as they enter their 50's,'' said Boyce Thompson, the editor in chief of Builder magazine, which devoted a special section to the housing patterns of older buyers in July. ''These people have a desire for larger houses and more luxuries. It has nothing to do with the needs of their children.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Bowman, a builder in Huntington, N.Y., said that half of his business is from couples with adult or nearly adult children. ''One might think that the older buyers would be thinking of consolidating and making life simpler, but no, they aren't,'' he said. ''These are people who gave up a lot for a lot of years, and now they are looking for quality of life.''</p>
        <p>The National Association of Home Builders estimates that in the year 2000, the average American house will have 2,500 square feet, up significantly from 1,900 square feet in 1977. ''Everybody wants four bedrooms when they only use two for sleeping,'' said Gopal Ahluwalia, the association's director of research. ''And in California, every house has to have three fireplaces that never get used.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, the average number of occupants per house is dropping. ''It is now at 2.6,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But increasingly, occupancy is a relative term, in more ways than one. Inspiration for these big houses frequently is the hope that the family -- especially grandchildren -- will like the new surroundings enough to want to visit. Often.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Evans said that even though her children had to make do with sharing the bathroom, she hoped that the new expanded house would ''pay off with the grandchildren.''</p>
        <p>Builders of custom houses speak of being asked frequently to design special features calculated to impress youngsters, including sunken ball courts, built-in bunk beds, small video arcades and pinball parlors.</p>
        <p>''We tell people how they can design a house to be attractive to kids,'' said Orren Pickell, a home builder in Chicago. ''First, we suggest finishing the lower level and then putting in all the things the parents won't let them do at their own home, like video games, pool and Ping-Pong tables. It's a bribe, but so what? It works.''</p>
        <p>Builders call the houses they are designing for this powerful new market ''entertainment houses,'' ''homesteads,'' ''quarterly houses'' or ''transitional homes'' -- anything, it seems, but ''empty nests.''</p>
        <p>''I could easily plan the perfect house for the past 26 years,'' said Ms. Korda, 53, who is interviewing architects. The new house will be next door to the one where she and her husband, the founder of Kroll Associates, the business investigations firm, now live. ''I can only begin to think about how to plan for the next 26 years.''</p>
        <p>She is already dreaming of a larger kitchen with more counter space (''I used to need lots of floor when the kids were underfoot,'' she said. ''Now, I need counter space for all the helping hands I'll have'').</p>
        <p>Ms. Korda said she would also like a proper library for those books that she will now have the time to read, a private sitting room, a billiards room and perhaps quarters for a live-in housekeeper. And the dining room will have to be very large for family reunions (''God willing, I hope there will be lots of people someday,'' she said).</p>
        <p>David Schless, the executive director of the American Seniors Housing Association, a trade group in Washington, said: ''It's a trend affecting a thin segment of the population at the well-to-do end of the market. Most people stay in the same home for as long as they possibly can.''</p>
        <p>Changes in capital-gains tax laws that took effect on July 28 (raising the exemption for selling a permanent residence to $500,000 for married homeowners and $250,000 for individual taxpayers) have meant that there should soon be more large houses on the market. Previously, older people who had bought their houses relatively cheaply decades ago were discouraged from selling at a profit because of the large tax bite.</p>
        <p>''The tax change will definitely enable many seniors to be more inclined to move,'' Mr. Schless said.</p>
        <p>The current empty-nest generation is also the first one to have so many two-career, two-income families. Furthermore, it is not a foregone conclusion that earning stops with retirement, as many older people are starting second careers late in life.</p>
        <p>''People are beginning to catch on to the possibility of a second adulthood,'' said Gail Sheehy, the author of ''New Passages: Mapping Your Life Across Time'' (Random House, 1995). ''They are retiring earlier and earlier and living longer. It used to be as life contracted, so did the living space. Now, life is opening up after 50, so why not open up your surroundings?''</p>
        <p>Adrienne Tindall describes herself and her husband, Jack, as ''barely in our 60's.'' The Tindalls spent 28 years raising their four daughters in what she calls ''a regular 3,500-square-foot house,'' near Chicago. ''I always thought we'd just move into a condo from there,'' said Mrs. Tindall, who has her own home-based sacred-music publishing business.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Tindall, an engineer, had always nursed a dream of building his own house. When their youngest daughter reached her mid-20's, they found that the value of their old house had appreciated enough that they could afford to build a new 6,000-square-foot homestead nearby: about as far from a generic condominium as imaginable, it is a timber-framed, lodge-style affair with fieldstone walls.</p>
        <p>Since the new house was completed eight years ago, all of their four grown daughters have lived there at various times, some with husbands and children while their own new homes were being finished. As in so many contemporary houses, the living room and dining room, fast becoming as obsolete as the vestigial appendix, have been replaced by a Great Room. This one truly fits the bill, at more than 1,100 square feet.</p>
        <p>Need and desire have never been forced bunkmates when it comes to the high end of the housing market. And one of the enviable tasks for these affluent older buyers is to figure out what their desires are.</p>
        <p>As a builder with a keen marketing sense, Mr. Pickell understands the whims and wants of couples who are just waking up to their newfound freedom, and he has built elaborate concept houses to whet their appetites.</p>
        <p>''I sit them down and say, 'There's no one living with you now, so why should you live the same way?' '' he said. ''And they always look at me as if the thought had never occurred to them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pickell thinks about it plenty and has suggestions for those who, he says, have ''forgotten how to live on their own.''</p>
        <p>For instance, families with children need lots of doors that can be shut to cut out noise and insure privacy. With just a spouse around, he tells them, why not dispense with a few?</p>
        <p>Then there are quarterly rooms.</p>
        <p>''People tell us they only use the living and dining rooms on holidays,'' Mr. Pickell said. ''So, we call them quarterly rooms,'' meaning that they are used only about four times a year. ''And we treat them like art on the walls -- just to be looked at,'' he added. There might even be two master suites, one downstairs for the owners and one upstairs for visiting children with grandchildren, possibly with a separate entrance.</p>
        <p>For some, padding the empty nest, like empire building, starts modestly enough and then expands uncontrollably. Stephanie and Sam Lebowitz, who have a house in Clinton Hill, Brooklyn, started renovating the kitchen when their third child turned 20. (''As soon as we did it, I stopped cooking,'' Mrs. Lebowitz said.)</p>
        <p>Within a year, the Lebowitzes had turned their attentions to their 2,500-square-foot country house on Shelter Island, where they are planning to add 1,200 square feet. They hope to put in an additional bedroom, double the living room size and turn another room into a home gym for what Mrs. Lebowitz calls an ''older, fitter me.''</p>
        <p>''It is sort of weird that our house got bigger as soon as the kids were gone,'' she said. ''The reason is part economics and part finally having the time. The fact is that our needs are shrinking and expanding at the same time. Our children are much bigger physically than they used to be, and when they visit they bring other big adults with them.''</p>
        <p>But as houses get bigger, isn't there a danger that even two full-size adults might find themselves rattling around?</p>
        <p>Mrs. Tindall, of Illinois, said that she worried about just this. ''I didn't want to feel like a lodge keeper in my own home,'' she said of her new 10-room house. So, she and her husband placed the master suite with a study on the ground floor. Since the Great Room is adjacent to the kitchen and since Mrs. Tindall keeps her grand piano and small pipe organ there, it is in constant use.</p>
        <p>The Tindalls, who have eight grandchildren and are expecting one more, concentrated the guest rooms on the second floor, out of sight when out of use. They admit that they live in only the four or five rooms that cluster around the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Tom Lewis, a custom builder in Florida, calls this type of floor plan ''a home within a home.''</p>
        <p>''These houses aren't exactly built in separate pods,'' Mr. Lewis said, ''but they are organized so that a couple can live in a reduced amount of it most of the time and not feel as if they are living in a mausoleum.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, not using a space can be half the fun. Ken Alexander, a builder in Scottsdale, Ariz., recalled one couple who wanted to celebrate their liberation from years of happy if demanding servitude to their young.</p>
        <p>''The main thing they wanted was a magnificent kitchen,'' Mr. Alexander said. ''And they wanted it just so they could hang a sign on the door saying, KITCHEN  CLOSED .''</p>
        <p>Padding The Empty Nest</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
