<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Faces a Suit By Writers</title>
    <meta content="04SCRE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Working at Home</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Writers Guild of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EED61430F937A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Faces a Suit By Writers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Writers Guild of America sues City of Los Angeles, seeking to overturn ordinance requiring all people who operate businesses in their homes, including writers, to obtain a permit and pay a city tax (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Hollywood screenwriters union says it will take the City of Los Angeles to Federal court on Monday to overturn an ordinance requiring writers and artists to get city permits before they can work out of their homes.</p>
        <p>Two smaller writers groups said yesterday that they would file briefs supporting the suit by the Writers Guild of America, which represents movie and television screenwriters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Hollywood screenwriters union says it will take the City of Los Angeles to Federal court on Monday to overturn an ordinance requiring writers and artists to get city permits before they can work out of their homes.</p>
        <p>Two smaller writers groups said yesterday that they would file briefs supporting the suit by the Writers Guild of America, which represents movie and television screenwriters.</p>
        <p>Marvin J. Wolf, a freelance journalist who is president of one of the smaller groups, the Independent Writers of Southern California, said the ordinance ''is a clearly unconstitutional attempt to license journalists.''</p>
        <p>''It is very clear to us,'' he added, ''that once the city has the power to license writers, if they write something City Hall doesn't want to hear, there is the potential for city officials to deny your license or to say: 'We'll make you pay for that. Let's audit you.' ''</p>
        <p>The Writers Guild said the ordinance recalled the ''tyrannical and repressive'' registration system used by the former Soviet Union and other Communist countries to regulate writers.</p>
        <p>The ordinance does not mention writers and artists. It requires all people operating businesses out of their homes to get permits and to pay either a minimum tax or a gross receipts tax of less than one-half of 1 percent on all revenues, including reimbursed expenses.</p>
        <p>The ordinance also provides that ''the City Clerk and all of his deputies shall have the power and authority to enter, free of charge, during business hours any place of business required to be registered and taxed'' and makes failure to comply a misdemeanor.</p>
        <p>Allowing inspections in the homes of writers and artists is an unconstitutional intrusion, Mr. Wolf said.</p>
        <p>Ramona Ripston, executive director of the American Civil Liberties Union of Southern California, said that the gross receipts tax ''inevitably embroils city taxing authorities in investigations into the creative process that are at odds with First Amendment freedoms.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ripston and others said that disputes were sure to arise over whether a check sent to the home of a writer or artist was for work performed at home and subject to the city tax or for work outside the city.</p>
        <p>Deputy Mayor Stephanie Bradfield said Los Angeles was seriously considering the issues raised ''by the writers, especially the screenwriters, because movies and television are such an important part of the economy of Los Angeles.''</p>
        <p>She added that the ''suggestion that the city could regulate the content of what people write in their homes is ludicrous,'' and that in issuing permits to writers the city would never consider what they wrote.</p>
        <p>The ordinance, passed last fall, allows office-type businesses to operate out of homes in Los Angeles provided they have little impact on the neighborhood. Businesses with a steady stream of clients and those receiving more than three deliveries a day are prohibited, as is what the law vaguely describes as ''adult entertainment.''</p>
        <p>Mark Ryavec of Delphi Associates, the Writers Guild lobbyist, said the ''adult entertainment'' category was so broad that the city could deny permits to a writer of such works as ''The English Patient,'' the novel and the movie, because of its erotic themes. The film won the Oscar for best picture this year.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bradfield said that before the ordinance was adopted, it was technically illegal in Los Angeles to write in your home for money unless you did so as an employee. Thus a staff writer for a television series could write at home, but a writer working on contract for the same show could not.</p>
        <p>''In this city, until this ordinance passed, you couldn't get a business license if you used your home address as a place of business because you couldn't do business in residential areas,'' she said. ''If you are a tax preparer, an architect, an engineer, a business consultant, a legal researcher or a writer and if you want to do business legitimately in this city, you need a business license.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bradfield said that ''theoretically if you have been writing out of your home and making money on it you have owed city taxes all along.''</p>
        <p>The ordinance requires a permit, which costs $25 annually, to conduct business from a home and it imposes a gross receipts tax at various rates for various businesses. For a print writer making $30,000, the permit and the tax would total about $200 annually.</p>
        <p>The Writers Guild said that a gross receipts tax on writers was an unconstitutional intrusion but that even if it were allowed the city could not tax writers at different rates depending on whether they worked in films, television or print.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf said the tax would inevitably result in audits in which the city would seek documents identifying confidential sources, like a police officer who had lunch with a freelance journalist and told about corruption at City Hall with the understanding that his name would never be revealed.</p>
        <p>The business license offices of three cities neighboring Los Angeles -- Long Beach, Pasadena and Santa Monica -- said that their ordinances required writers and artists to get licenses or permits to work from their homes. But senior officials in each city said they were unaware of any enforcement of the requirement.</p>
        <p>West Hollywood, which is surrounded by Los Angeles, exempts ''creative enterprises'' like writing, painting and making handicrafts from its permit requirements, and Mr. Ryavec has asked Los Angeles to do the same.</p>
        <p>New York City does not require writers to get permits or licenses to work in their homes. Shonna Keoghan, the spokeswoman for the City Consumer Affairs Department, said she could not imagine the city trying to license activity protected by the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>Under an amnesty program, Los Angeles has given operators of the estimated 20,000 home businesses until tomorrow to file for a permit, after which the city says it will seek back taxes and a 40 percent penalty plus interest on those who fail to comply.</p>
        <p>Gary Bostwick, a lawyer in Santa Monica, Calif., who was hired by the Writers Guild to sue the city, said that when the amnesty expired the guild would have a basis to take the city to court. He said he would file a lawsuit when the Federal Courthouse in downtown Los Angeles opened on Monday morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolf said the Independent Writers would file a ''friend of the court'' brief supporting the lawsuit. The Southern California chapter of the American Society of Journalists and Authors will also file a brief, its president, Carey Simon, said.</p>
        <p>Martin Garbus, a New York lawyer who specializes in literary litigation, predicted that a Federal judge would strike down the ordinance.</p>
        <p>''Writers don't have to have permits, period,'' Mr. Garbus said. ''This is unconstitutional on its face. You cannot put any burden on creative expression even if all you have to do is get a permit that is free.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
