<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="04DIGE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="955053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1D81530F937A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Economic Reports Strong, But Market Effect Is Muted  The index of leading economic indicators rose at the fastest rate in five months during July, and construction spending advanced.</p>
        <p>But inflation-wary investors, who had already seen evidence of strength in other data, did not seem overly troubled. $(Page D8.$)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Economic Reports Strong, But Market Effect Is Muted  The index of leading economic indicators rose at the fastest rate in five months during July, and construction spending advanced.</p>
        <p>But inflation-wary investors, who had already seen evidence of strength in other data, did not seem overly troubled. $(Page D8.$)</p>
        <p>The stock market inched higher after its big gains on Tuesday, with the Dow industrials up 14.86 points, to 7,894.64. $(D8.$)</p>
        <p>The Treasury market weakened, however, with the yield on the 30-year bond rising to 6.60 percent from 6.55. $(D15.$)</p>
        <p>Big Rebound In Hong Kong  The benchmark stock index jumped 7.1 percent in Hong Kong as investors snapped up shares after their recent plunge. Some other Asian markets rose, too. $(D15.$)</p>
        <p>Deal for Canadian Energy Company  Pioneer Natural Resources, the energy company formed in the merger of Mesa and Parker &amp; Parsley, agreed to buy Chauvco Resources, a Canadian oil and gas company, for $975 million. $(D2.$)</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's Toll-Free Network in Crash  Callers seeking everything from airline tickets to insurance forms were frustrated by busy signals as parts of AT&amp;T's toll-free telephone network briefly crashed. $(D4.$)</p>
        <p>Threat Seen for Tobacco Accord  Congressional leaders said they had no plans to act quickly on the proposed tobacco settlement, while advocates for it warned that delay could kill the deal. $(A22.$)</p>
        <p>Time Warner and TCI Expand Links  Time Warner and Tele-Communications have agreed to create a new joint venture that will own cable systems, and to expand an existing partnership. The moves will also allow both companies to reduce their debt. $(D7.$)</p>
        <p>New Units at Ad Agency Companies  WPP is forming a specialty unit devoted to advertising aimed at children and teen-agers, and Omnicom is creating one for public relations. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. $(D7.$)</p>
        <p>ESPN Goes Retro  ESPN agreed to acquire the Classic Sports cable TV channel, which has carved a nostalgic niche by repackaging old sports events. $(D7.$)</p>
        <p>Pepsico Wins Arbitration Award  Pepsico, whose longtime Venezuelan bottler defected to Coca-Cola last summer, was awarded $94 million by the International Court of Arbitration in Paris. $(D5.$)</p>
        <p>Weight Loss Center to Drop Drugs  Nutri/System Weight Loss Centers said it would discontinue a drug combination known as fen-phen after reports of heart valve damage among users of it. $(D8.$)</p>
        <p>2d Chance For a 2d Hoffa  James R. Hoffa Jr., left, the bearer of one of the most famous names in labor history, finds the spotlight on him as he again runs for teamster president. A Federal overseer ordered new elections, charging that illegal contributions on the side of his opponent, Ron Carey, might have tilted the initial vote. $(A1.$)</p>
        <p>Screenwriters to Sue Los Angeles  The Hollywood screenwriters' union says it will take Los Angeles to court, seeking to overturn an ordinance requiring writers and artists to get city permits before they can work out of their homes. $(C13.$)</p>
        <p>Federal Benefit Site to Return  The Clinton Administration plans to re-establish an Internet site where people can see how much they are entitled to in future Social Security benefits, but the Government will impose new privacy safeguards. $(A1.$)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
