<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Secret of the Old Crock</title>
    <meta content="027REHAK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/27/books/review/027REHAK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1660030"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rehak, Melanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cain, Chelsea</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions of a Teen Sleuth: A Parody (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cain, Chelsea</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Confessions of a Teen Sleuth: A Parody (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EEDC1E3CF934A15750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Secret of the Old Crock</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'Confessions of a Teen Sleuth': Secret of the Old Crock</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELANIE REHAK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rehak, Melanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Melanie Rehak reviews book Confessions of a Teen Sleuth: A Parody by Chelsea Cain; photo; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Confessions of A Teen Sleuth</p>
        <p>A Parody.</p>
        <p>By Chelsea Cain.</p>
        <p>Illustrations by Lia Miternique.</p>
        <p>160 pp. Bloomsbury. $15.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this affectionate parody, by Chelsea Cain, Nancy Drew grows up and grows old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Confessions of A Teen Sleuth</p>
        <p>A Parody.</p>
        <p>By Chelsea Cain.</p>
        <p>Illustrations by Lia Miternique.</p>
        <p>160 pp. Bloomsbury. $15.95.</p>
        <p>She wears flimsy lingerie! She's secretly in love with one of the Hardy boys! She's (gasp) middle-aged! Reader, this is not your mother's -- or even your -- Nancy Drew.</p>
        <p>Then again, maybe she is. Chelsea Cain's gleeful parody ''Confessions of a Teen Sleuth'' affectionately hits all the formulaic high points of a Nancy Drew mystery, sending up and yet saluting America's favorite girl detective. All the unspoken truths about money, social status and teenage identity crises ordinarily crammed between the lines of her adventures are outrageously exposed, and the book is no less endearing for it. Nancy's tomboy friend George (no, it's not short for Georgia) ends up first at Smith College and later living in ''an area of town where many young women with short hair and boys' names lived.'' Nancy's ever-plump chum Bess develops an eating disorder and eventually runs off with a younger man. And Carson Drew, Nancy's widower (or so you thought!) father, whom she now calls ''the world-renowned attorney-turned-judge-turned-losing-city-council-candidate,'' at long last exchanges noble bachelorhood for a tacky second wife who summarily disposes of all of Nancy's sleuthing mementos.</p>
        <p>As for Nancy, we first meet her in a posthumously published introduction. Now married to her longtime sweetheart, Ned Nickerson, she reveals that her college friend Carolyn Keene has made a fortune by ripping off her stories, and that she has entrusted a manuscript disclosing the true details of her life to Chelsea Cain. From there, we follow Nancy and her trademark flashing blue eyes and blue car through a series of absurd mysteries that take place from 1926 to 1992. Nancy goes from cloche hats and pencil skirts to Jazzercise and New Age cruises. Cain has a great time poking gentle fun at all the tics -- physical and otherwise -- that make us love Miss Drew so much.</p>
        <p>''It's good to see you looking as slim and attractive as always,'' Frank Hardy tells her just before their love affair is consummated, in a very un-Nancy way, in the back room of a suspicious cafe. As the plot unfolds, Nancy's all-American good looks fade -- at one point in the 1970's she is late to a crime scene because her hair and makeup take so long, and the phrase ''slim and attractive'' recurs here with hilarious regularity -- but she's still in charge. When she decides, daringly, to enter a spooky, deserted speakeasy, her hapless suitors are reduced to mere sheep: ''I took a step inside. Frank followed. Ned followed behind Frank.''</p>
        <p>Apparently being a go-getter runs in the family. It turns out Nancy's mother isn't really dead, but a suffragist who ran away from the oppressive stability of River Heights in 1913. Not only that, Mom is also the sister of Nancy's beloved housekeeper, Hannah Gruen, who, among other things, is arrested for being a Communist spy in the McCarthy-era section of the book. These are just a few of Cain's doozies. She drags in a host of other fictional teenage detectives, including Cherry Ames (who comments that ''You're wearing the exact same skirt you had on when we met. . . . And it's looking a little tight around the hips''), Tom Swift Jr., the Dana Girls and Encyclopedia Brown.</p>
        <p>Along with all the high jinks (as Nancy puts it at one point, ''everything goes catawampus''), there's a big dose of perhaps the only thing missing from the original Nancy Drew Mystery Stories: reality. But even that can't stop the girl sleuth. By the end of the book Nancy is wearing control-top pantyhose and has crow's feet, but somehow, she still manages to speak for her loyal fans. Arriving at the scene of a murder, all vim and vigor, she tells us pertly, ''I may have been middle-aged, but I was still a teen sleuth at heart.'' Amen to that.</p>
        <p>Melanie Rehak is the author of ''Girl Detective: Nancy Drew and the Women Who Created Her,'' to be published in September.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Melanie Rehak is the author of ''Girl Detective: Nancy Drew and the Women Who Created Her,'' to be published in September.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
