<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theme for Today, Class: Role Models and How to Succeed</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="139621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROPOUTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DALEY, SUZANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED7173DF935A15757C0A96E948260" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theme for Today, Class: Role Models and How to Succeed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE DALEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DALEY, SUZANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Wendell Niles, a graphic artist who founded his own company, was telling a group of seventh graders from Harlem recently that there were all kinds of jobs for them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Wendell Niles, a graphic artist who founded his own company, was telling a group of seventh graders from Harlem recently that there were all kinds of jobs for them.</p>
        <p>Wendell Niles, a graphic artist who founded his own company, was telling a group of seventh graders from Harlem recently that there were all kinds of jobs for them.</p>
        <p>For instance, he said, people were paid to design the textbooks they were reading, the packaging around their candy, the patterns on their clothes.</p>
        <p>''Anyone can do these things,'' he said. ''It has nothing to do with what you come from. It's your brain. You can do it. That's what's so great about America.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Niles is among more than 100 business, government and arts leaders who have signed up to visit a seventh-grade class twice a month, in an effort to provide encouragement and role models in a public school system with one of the highest dropout rates in the country.</p>
        <p>Under the program, called Adopt-a-Class, each sponsor chooses a theme and creates a curriculum involving a mix of classroom sessions and outings. The Board of Education provides some advice and support services and will pay for the costs of the trips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Niles, whose Bronx-based concern, Corporate Image Builders, designs such items as logos and stationery, plans to have the class he has adopted create both for an imaginary company. He will also take the children to see typesetting and printing operations.</p>
        <p>Recently, however, Mr. Niles spent the morning in their classroom at Intermediate School 10 at 2581 Adam Clayton Powell Jr. Boulevard explaining various aspects of his business, including being aware of one's market.</p>
        <p>''Is a construction company going to want pink stationery?'' Mr. Niles asked his class. They giggled.  The sponsors who have signed up so far range from Mayor Koch and dozens of other city officials, to executives of large companies such as Peter Georgescu, the president of Young &amp; Rubicam Advertising, and civic leaders such as Sally Goodgold, the president of the City Club of New York.</p>
        <p>The themes each has chosen vary enormously. One man is teaching the children about making leather goods, another video production. An executive of a Japanese bank is combining a study of Japanese culture and banking.</p>
        <p>At times, the sponsors are a little awkward, fumbling with the chalk as they try to write on blackboards or discombobulated by the ringing bells that are a routine part of the city's schools. Some even have stage fright.</p>
        <p>Before greeting his class of seventh graders recently, Deputy Mayor Stanley Brezenoff paced the floor at City Hall. ''I think I'd rather be addressing a neighborhood that was getting a shelter for the homeless,'' Mr. Brezenoff said.</p>
        <p>But the encounters seem to abound with good will and youngsters dressed in their Sunday best, delighted with the excursions and eager to make friends. Involving the Public</p>
        <p>''Sit here, Mr. Brezenoff, sit here,'' several of the children shouted to the Deputy Mayor as they settled in around a table in the Blue Room. The class from Intermediate School 145 in Jackson Heights, Queens, eventually heard a presentation on the city's garbage dumps.</p>
        <p>The program, under way for only a few months, is the board's newest attempt to involve the public in the school system. Taraja Samuel, who runs Adopt-a-Class for the Board, said it was Mayor Koch who suggested the idea because he felt many New Yorkers wanted to reach out to the children but were not able to invest large amounts of money.</p>
        <p>In the past, a number of wealthy individuals have taken responsibility for a class in a low-income area of the city and have invested trust funds in their behalf to pay for counselors, extra tutoring and, eventually, college fees.</p>
        <p>''The Mayor thought the kids could get a lot out of just spending time with caring, successful adults even if there was no huge financial investment,'' Ms. Samuel said. 'Things Can Be Done'</p>
        <p>Many people in the program say they were drawn to it because it was a manageable, perhaps meaningful way of making a difference in the children's lives.</p>
        <p>Some, like Mr. Niles, spoke of growing up in the city's poorer neighborhoods, without advice or mentors.</p>
        <p>''I wanted them to have that kind of contact,'' Mr. Niles said. ''And, I also wanted to say to them 'hey kids, the situation isn't the greatest for you, but things can be done, so do it.' ''</p>
        <p>In some cases, the sponsors are meeting children who have been battered by many of the city's ills -burned out of their homes, living with drug addicts, or surviving on welfare. 'Now Listen, Mommy'</p>
        <p>But the children remain children, they said, with the shyness, the awe, the hopes and the fears that might be expected of any adolescent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodgold said that she had grown particularly fond of a boy who was often absent because his mother ran a crack den. The boy stayed home for fear that the younger children would be abused.</p>
        <p>''One day,'' said Ms. Goodgold, ''he said to me, 'Now listen, Mommy,' and I thought to myself, oh, God, he needs that so badly. The child-sweetness is still there in all of them.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Goodgold, whose theme in the program is ''behind the scenes in New York City,'' has taken her class from the Creative Learning Community at 19 East 103d Street in Manhattan on a number of outings, including a visit to the 911 operators of the city's police department. 'A Pot of Gold'</p>
        <p>''The girls especially saw a pot of gold,'' said Ms. Goodgold, ''a job that they might want.''</p>
        <p>Many details about the program, including how many adults will be allowed to be sponsors and how much the city will spend on the program, have yet to be worked out, Ms. Samuel said. Already, in addition to the more than 100 adults who have adopted classes in the last few months, 50 are on a waiting list.</p>
        <p>''We're not sure how big we want this to get,'' Ms. Samuels said. ''We don't want it getting out of hand.''</p>
        <p>It is also unclear whether the program will be continued into the eighth grade next year or whether the sponsors will be asked to take over new seventh-grade classes.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Niles, the morning went by with his description of different types of printing, an explanation of technical terms like typography and thermography, and the passing around of embossed stationery. He also used a magnifying glass to show the children how photographs in newspapers were made up of hundreds of dots.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Niles sat in the back of the room and asked each student to tell what he wanted to be when he grew up and consider how graphic design and printing might be a part of that field.</p>
        <p>Drawing them out, Mr. Niles convinced Jose Hidalgo, who wanted to be a pilot, that graphics and printing would be in his life in the form of maps and manuals. Charmaine Johnson, he pointed out, would need a resume and portfolio as a model. Becky Morales would need books and report cards as a teacher.</p>
        <p>Faced with a young girl who said that she had no ambition and would settle for anything, Mr. Niles drew a deep breath.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to hear that,'' Mr. Niles said. ''That's not good enough for you. You reach for the stars. Reach right up there, the world will bring you down to reality.''</p>
        <p>After a moment, the girl smiled: ''Okay,'' she said, ''I'll be a policeman.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
