<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Flowers for Russians: Pair Make Do With Gold</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="663256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="FIGURE SKATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE SKATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIGURE SKATING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D81430F933A15752C0A962958260" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Flowers for Russians: Pair Make Do With Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIOSTOPHER CLAREY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN, Jan. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No roses were tossed onto the ice tonight for Yekaterina Gordeyeva and Sergei Grinkov. The few fans with the good fortune to be in the Brondby Arena already had used up all their flowers on a mediocre Danish skater dressed to resemble an electric cowboy.</p>
        <p>But if ever a performance deserved a shower of bouquets, Gordeyeva's and Grinkov's freestyle program at the European championships was it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No roses were tossed onto the ice tonight for Yekaterina Gordeyeva and Sergei Grinkov. The few fans with the good fortune to be in the Brondby Arena already had used up all their flowers on a mediocre Danish skater dressed to resemble an electric cowboy.</p>
        <p>But if ever a performance deserved a shower of bouquets, Gordeyeva's and Grinkov's freestyle program at the European championships was it.</p>
        <p>Skating to Beethoven's "Moonlight Sonata," the Russian pair from Moscow, gold medal winners at the 1988 Olympics, earned perfect scores of 6.0 for artistic impression from four of the judges and 5.9's from the other five.</p>
        <p>Those marks were more than enough to give them the gold ahead of the two other Russian pairs: Yevgeniya Shishkova and Vadim Naumov, who took the silver, and Natalya Mishkutienok and Artur Dimitriyev, the 1992 Olympic gold medalists, who rallied to take the bronze. Russians Now Favored in Norway</p>
        <p>Gordeyeva and Grinkov have now firmly established themselves as the pair to beat at next month's Winter Olympics in Lillehammer, Norway, which is hardly a bold statement considering that skaters from the former Soviet Union have won the last eight gold medals in pairs.</p>
        <p>"When we skated as amateurs before, we were not like machines but we didn't feel everything," said Gordeyeva, a 22-year-old mother of one and charmer of many. "Now, we are trying to feel our skating."</p>
        <p>The feeling of Olympic triumph is nothing new to these Russians. In 1988, they won the gold medal in Calgary, Alberta, when the effervescent Gordeyeva was only 16 and the silent Grinkov 21. At that time, it seemed clear that they would reign for many years.</p>
        <p>Two years later, with the Soviet Union beginning to crumble, they elected to turn professional after winning their fourth world championship. In April 1991, they were married, and on Sept. 11, 1992, Gordeyeva gave birth to their daughter, Daria. Petrenko Takes Lead</p>
        <p>Gordeyeva and Grinkov were not the only former Soviet athletes to light up the scoreboard today. Skating his original program in the afternoon, Viktor Petrenko of Ukraine received two 6.0's for artistic impression and took a commanding lead heading into Thursday night's decisive freestyle program.</p>
        <p>FIGURE SKATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
