<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Bracing for Northwest Air's Issue</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="663219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTHWEST AIRLINES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORTUNE (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, ADAM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E6D91430F933A15752C0A962958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Bracing for Northwest Air's Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BRYANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRYANT, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Watching the frequent surges and drops in airline fortunes is enough to give even the most limber investor neck cramps. So, a restraining collar may be appropriate while considering the bid by Northwest Airlines to go public again.</p>
        <p>Just months after narrowly averting a bankruptcy filing, the airline said on Tuesday that it wanted to raise $460 million through a stock offering, its first trip to the markets since it was taken private in a $3.6 billion buyout in 1989.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Watching the frequent surges and drops in airline fortunes is enough to give even the most limber investor neck cramps. So, a restraining collar may be appropriate while considering the bid by Northwest Airlines to go public again.</p>
        <p>Just months after narrowly averting a bankruptcy filing, the airline said on Tuesday that it wanted to raise $460 million through a stock offering, its first trip to the markets since it was taken private in a $3.6 billion buyout in 1989.</p>
        <p>Northwest is clearly betting that despite some concerns about its debt load and other matters, the market will welcome its offering -- if only because of the appetite for new issues these days. But the company may not get its hoped-for price of $20 a share.</p>
        <p>"If they get it done even at $17, it would be a very respectable offering for a company that was perceived to be in a lot of trouble just six months ago," said Phillip Brannon, a high-yield bond analyst at Mabon Securities. Troubles Remain</p>
        <p>Many of those troubles are still there, and were added to by a survey in Fortune magazine this month that rated Northwest Airlines as one of the least admired companies (it ranked No. 400 of 404 companies, better than Trans World Airlines at 403, but worse than Continental Airlines at 396).</p>
        <p>Still, there are stars aligned in Northwest's favor. For one, investors seem to have a lot of faith in airline debt and equity offerings, lapping up 14 of them, valued at more than $5.8 billion, since 1991.</p>
        <p>After Northwest's employees agreed last fall to help the company avoid bankruptcy by trading $886 million worth of concessions for roughly a third of the company, the carrier reported a third-quarter net income of $110.7 million, the highest net margin of any big carrier except Southwest Airlines.</p>
        <p>The outlook for Northwest's most profitable routes to the Pacific are also improving, and the company will probably report a small profit for the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Investors may also be enthused by the recent market performance of Continental, which, after emerging from bankruptcy last year, has seen its recently issued shares trade up roughly 20 percent in the last few weeks.</p>
        <p>Some investors may even take their cues from the experience of the Southern Pacific Rail Corporation, which has seen its stock rise nearly 50 percent since going public last August. Northwest and Southern Pacific are in different industries, of course, but they have some striking similarities. Both have suffered from heavy debt loads from leveraged buyouts, and like Northwest, Southern Pacific had no equity at the time of its filing.</p>
        <p>All that sounds good, and may be more than enough for Northwest to carry off its offering. But these broad and generous comparisons are just that.</p>
        <p>Continental, after all, has limited debt from its tour of bankruptcy courts, and low labor costs. Northwest lowered its labor costs in the concessions-for-equity swap, but those costs are scheduled to snap back after three years.</p>
        <p>And while Northwest managed to reschedule much of its debt, its debt load in the years to come remains high, with about $2 billion in repayments due in 1996 and 1997. Indeed, much of the proceeds from Northwest's offering will go to reduce its debt.</p>
        <p>The Southern Pacific comparison also breaks down because investors in the railroad are betting in large part on the restructuring being engineered by its new chairman, Edward L. Moyers, who was hired by the company last July because of his reputation as a turnaround artist.</p>
        <p>Other concerns weighing down Northwest include its negative net worth of $1.9 billion, and a debt-to-capital ratio of 126 percent. Its debt and lease obligations of $9.6 billion also represent 112 percent of its annual revenues, which, though high, is still lower than the ratios of the parent companies of American Airlines, United Airlines and USAir, according to Standard &amp; Poor's. S.&amp; P. and Moody's Investors Service put Northwest's debt rating up for review, with positive implications, pending the offering.</p>
        <p>There is also the question of what will happen to Northwest's costs when wages snap back in three years. But for now, Northwest is seen as a low-cost airline, and low-cost airlines are in vogue. In fact, if the offering goes well for Northwest, maybe T.W.A., which emerged from bankruptcy last fall with low costs, might consider an offering.</p>
        <p>Keep the neck brace close at hand.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
