<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Close Mixed as Dow Falls by 18.32</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLE, ROBERT J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DE1631F937A35757C0A967958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Close Mixed as Dow Falls by 18.32</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT J. COLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLE, ROBERT J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock prices ended on a mixed note yesterday with the blue chips and the rest of the big stocks giving way but the smaller stocks continuing to show strong gains.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial index slid 18.32, or six-tenths of a percent, to 2,926.73, but the Russell 2,000, a small-stock index, rose almost seven-tenths of a percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock prices ended on a mixed note yesterday with the blue chips and the rest of the big stocks giving way but the smaller stocks continuing to show strong gains.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial index slid 18.32, or six-tenths of a percent, to 2,926.73, but the Russell 2,000, a small-stock index, rose almost seven-tenths of a percent.</p>
        <p>There were signs, though, that the bull market could be winding down soon.</p>
        <p>Michael Burke, editor of Investors Intelligence of New Rochelle, N.Y., said yesterday that 49.6 percent of stock market newsletter writers he surveys regularly were bullish about stocks now, down sharply from the 58.6 percent a month ago.  'More People Are Scared'</p>
        <p>"Obviously, more people are scared," he said. "The bull market may be 75 percent over, but we've still got 25 percent left."</p>
        <p>Michael Metz, chief market analyst for Oppenheimer &amp; Company, the big Manhattan investment house, also flashed a cautionary signal.</p>
        <p>Pointing to the sharp rise in the smaller stocks, he said, "Unfortunately, this is also symptomatic of a strong upsurge in speculative enthusiasm which often marks the end of a market advance rather than the beginning."</p>
        <p>Still, stock market records were broken again yesterday in many of the big market indexes. The Nasdaq composite reached an all-time high of 495.05, up 3.85, The Russell 2,000 reached a high for the year of 173.75, up 1.13, The S.&amp;P. 500 did not end at a record level but briefly touched an all-time high during the day of 381.56.</p>
        <p>Trading volume, 189.5 million on Tuesday, soared to 213.7 million yesterday, with advances leading declines -- known as the breadth of the market -- by almost 5 to 3.</p>
        <p>And while only four hit new lows, 189 rose to new highs.</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp;T., the most widely held stock, rose during the day to within 1/4 point of its high for the year of 35 1/8. It ended yesterday at 34 1/2, up 1/8.</p>
        <p>Quick &amp; Reilly, the discount broker, rose to a high of 20 1/4 before ending at 20, up 3/4. Coca-Cola hit a new high of 56 3/4 before ending at 55 3/4, down 3/4. Pepsico matched its high of 35 5/8 before ending at 34, down 1 3/4, in heavy trading after what appeared to be disappointing earnings expectations.</p>
        <p>With trading so strong and the growing number of new securities offerings, market sleuths have begun recommending stockbrokers.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Eckenfelder of Prudential Securities is recommending Bear Stearns; Merrill Lynch; Morgan Stanley, and Paine Webber.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley rose 2 7/8 yesterday, to 87; Paine Webber 1, to 23 7/8; Bear Stearns 1/2, to 16, and Merrill Lynch 1/2, to 37 1/2. The Dreyfus Corporation and T. Rowe Price, two mutual fund giants, rose, respectively, 1 7/8, to 39 3/4, and 2 1/4, to 30 3/4.</p>
        <p>"If you look at the breadth of the market," Mr. Metz said, "it's very very strong. Everybody's playing catch-up with the big stocks. That's why the Dow's down and most stocks are up; the big stocks are taking a back seat and the small stocks are taking over the leadership."</p>
        <p>It was at this point that he warned of "speculative enthusiasm" that often comes at the end of a market rise.</p>
        <p>Asked about yesterday's market, he argued that because of current low interest rates and weak real estate "there are few attractive alternatives right now." He continued, "Every day that the market gives a good performance it gains new converts."</p>
        <p>A look at the day's movement in the Dow industrials and the Russell 2,000 show two different stock markets. By 10 A.M. the Dow had climbed a little but lost it; the Russell had climbed a bit but held it. By 1 P.M. the Dow was in minus territory for a second time but the Russell, giving way a little, was still strongly ahead. In the final hour both retreated but the Dow fell back far more sharply.</p>
        <p>Birinyi Associates said repeated waves of program selling took 5 points off the Dow.  Regeneron Is Big Mover</p>
        <p>Among the big movers, Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, a biotechnology stock that came to market Tuesday at $22 a share, fell 2 7/8, or 13.6 percent, to 18 1/4, with 1.7 million shares changing hands. The stock was so eagerly sought that it raised $99 million, or nearly twice as much money as planned.</p>
        <p>Dillard Department Stores, recommended a month ago by William Smith of Smith Barney, jumped 7, to 108, hitting a high of 109 1/4. Vendamerica B.V. of the Netherlands, owner of some 25 percent, offered its stock yesterday at $99 a share.</p>
        <p>U.S. Surgical, maker of surgical staplers, jumped 6 3/8, to 126 1/8, after a new high of 127. Robert Goldman of Dean Witter recommended the stock on the basis of developments to be announced at an April 18 conference.</p>
        <p>Legent, a computer software producer, slid 4 1/4, to 34 1/4, with 2.8 million shares changing hands on Nasdaq after it said second-quarter profits would not meet its own previous estimates.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Tokyo Stocks Close Lower</p>
        <p>TOKYO, Thursday, April 4 (Reuters) -- Japanese stocks pulled back slightly today after a strong rally on Wednesday. Traders attributed the retreat to profit-taking. The Nikkei index of 225 issues lost 90.25 points, to close at 26,689.81. On Wednesday, the Nikkei gained 528.06 points.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
