<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wringing More Costs Out of Wall St. Firms</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="434840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BROKERS AND BROKERAGE FIRMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">EICHENWALD, KURT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB123AF937A35757C0A967958260" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wringing More Costs Out of Wall St. Firms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EICHENWALD, KURT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The falling ax on Wall Street has become as commonplace as the rising Dow. But now, with the most obvious cuts of employees and expenses out of the way, investment houses are picking up the scalpel in hopes of completing a historic and complex reorganization of the back office, one of the least understood aspects of their business.</p>
        <p>Some major firms are considering merging their underused back offices, through which stocks, bonds and other financial instruments are moved to the account that purchased them and cash is moved to the seller. Some plan to sell part or all of the operations to outside contractors and then lease them back, or move pieces of the back offices out of Manhattan -- even to third-world countries -- to reduce overhead and labor costs.  Accompanying Layoffs</p>
        <p>"The cost pressure on Wall Street generally is encouraging people to look at lowering costs through changes in their back office and support systems," said Rick Adam, the partner in charge of global operations and technology at Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The falling ax on Wall Street has become as commonplace as the rising Dow. But now, with the most obvious cuts of employees and expenses out of the way, investment houses are picking up the scalpel in hopes of completing a historic and complex reorganization of the back office, one of the least understood aspects of their business.</p>
        <p>Some major firms are considering merging their underused back offices, through which stocks, bonds and other financial instruments are moved to the account that purchased them and cash is moved to the seller. Some plan to sell part or all of the operations to outside contractors and then lease them back, or move pieces of the back offices out of Manhattan -- even to third-world countries -- to reduce overhead and labor costs.  Accompanying Layoffs</p>
        <p>"The cost pressure on Wall Street generally is encouraging people to look at lowering costs through changes in their back office and support systems," said Rick Adam, the partner in charge of global operations and technology at Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>If any of the mergers come to pass, analysts predict there will be yet another wave of dismissals on top of the 60,000 jobs lost since the October 1987 market crash. "If joint ventures do occur, the number of people laid off in the back office will go up substantially," said A. Michael Lipper, president of the Lipper Analytical Securities Corporation. "An additional 25,000 dismissals would not surprise me."</p>
        <p>Too many people and too much capacity highlight the back office difficulties. "As a general matter, cost cutting is a No. 1 priority throughout the service economy," said Lawrence A. Kudlow, chief economist with Bear, Stearns &amp; Company. "If you need any convincing, you just need to look at employment numbers in recent months, which are hemorrhaging badly in that area."</p>
        <p>The back office is the nerve center of a Wall Street firm. Most back offices are huge operations with whirring computers in climate-controlled rooms and few paper shufflers. While some paper still flows through back offices -- monthly statements, dividend checks and the like -- an enormous amount of the work has been turned over to computers, which match the buyers and sellers of securities electronically.</p>
        <p>The potential for savings in merged back offices is between 20 percent and 40 percent of fixed costs, securities industry consultants said. "The beauty of merging the back offices of two major firms is that the economies of scale are phenomenal," said Stephen G. Racioppo, a managing partner with Andersen Consulting.</p>
        <p>After years of being criticized for short-term thinking, Wall Street tried the long view in the giddy 1980's, by laying out billions of dollars for more back office computers and employees in a bet that customer orders would keep climbing.</p>
        <p>They were wrong. Now, Wall Street is paying dearly for its failed fling with long-term planning.</p>
        <p>The buildup was rapid. Lipper Analytical said that by early 1985, Wall Street firms had 118,522 employees who did not produce income, most of them in back offices. By December, there were 140,951, and by late 1987, 168,226. Still More Than 1985</p>
        <p>Since the 1987 crash, back office staffs have been cut, to 138,763 employees now, although that is still more than in 1985.</p>
        <p>In the last year, virtually every major firm has looked hard at its back office. And the discussions are "creating interesting bedfellows," said DuWayne J. Peterson, executive vice president of operations systems and telecommunications at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>"These changes are not only a capacity issue, but an investment issue," Mr. Lipper said. The firms "are looking at significant increases they feel are required for investing in new equipment, and so are considering ways to decrease their existing fixed costs."</p>
        <p>One of the more aggressive planners is Salomon Brothers Inc., several Wall Street executives said. Over the last two years, Salomon has negotiated -- albeit unsuccessfully -- to merge its back office with Goldman, Sachs's; hired an outside company, Andersen Consulting, to maintain and operate computer programming, and agreed to move its back office to Tampa, Fla., from Manhattan. Recently, Salomon has also reportedly been considering providing back office services for other Wall Street firms. Thomas W. Strauss, Salomon's president, declined to comment on its back office plans.</p>
        <p>"The time is becoming ripe for collaborative ventures and other moves to make fixed costs lower." said Jean Louis Lelogeais, who specializes in capital markets at Booz Allen &amp; Hamilton, the consulting firm. "That is the name of the game."</p>
        <p>Wall Street executives say efforts to cut back on the costs are being hampered by the egos of some executives, as each investment house tries to make sure that no matter what savings are made, it will stay in control.</p>
        <p>Part of that desire for control is driven by bitter experience. Until the 1960's, no one paid much attention to the operations until the 1968 stock market boom surpassed the capacity of back offices to keep up with trades, resulting in one of the most dramatic technical failures in the history of financial services.</p>
        <p>As a result, trading in the stock markets was suspended one day a week, which had not happened since the crash of 1929. And a number of firms, unable to match buy and sell orders, teetered on insolvency or failed.</p>
        <p>After that experience, Wall Street firms developed extensive back office abilities, which they are still wary of surrendering. "If you share the back office, you lose absolute control," said Samuel Hayes 3d, a professor of investment banking at Harvard University. "And the investment banks remember well the late 1960's, when the back offices got out of control."</p>
        <p>But the pressures on Wall Street profits are forcing new thinking at a number of firms. The First Boston Corporation, for example, is in separate talks with Morgan Stanley &amp; Company, Shearson Lehman Brothers, and Goldman about possible mergers, Wall Street executives said. Similar talks between Shearson and Prudential Securities Inc. broke off last month after the resignation of George L. Ball, Prudential Securities' chairman, who was driving the effort.</p>
        <p>Shearson's data-processing operations have since been combined with the Information Services Corporation, a subsidiary of the American Express Company.  Talks Break Down</p>
        <p>Wall Street executives said a number of other firms had also been talking seriously about merging their back offices. Goldman and Morgan Stanley began talks in 1989 but the negotiations stalled when neither firm was willing to cede control. Securities industry executives said that each firm essentially wanted to run the operation and keep the other as a customer.</p>
        <p>When the talks with Morgan collapsed, Goldman began new talks with Salomon Brothers. But these talks also broke down over differences, people involved in the discussions said.</p>
        <p>Andersen Consulting has already taken over the maintenance of computer programs at Salomon Brothers while working on a long-range plan to build new systems. And First Boston recently asked for bids in a deal to sell its data-processing operation and lease it back.</p>
        <p>Wall Street executives added that some firms, including Wall Street's largest investment houses, are looking into using technology to move their back offices to countries like Thailand and India, where salaries are significantly lower than in the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
