<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY: July 10, 1988</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="160337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEWS SUMMARY (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SUMMARY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D7113CF933A25754C0A96E948260" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY: July 10, 1988</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-15</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  INTERNATIONAL/3-15</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL/3-15</p>
        <p>Mexico's election commission indicated that the presidential candidate of the governing Institutional Revolutionary Party is leading in the race but does not have a majority. Complete results have not been announced. Page 1</p>
        <p>Moscow aims to emulate Hungary in carrying out economic and political change, Mikhail Gorbachev told Karoly Grosz, the Hungarian Communist Party chief. Mr. Grosz called for political and economic changes in Hungary. 1</p>
        <p>Washington and Polish emigres are helping the Polish underground smuggle books, printing machinery, radio equipment into Poland. Washington has given more than $5 million in cash to the Polish opposition.</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Nikolai I. Bukharin was reinstated posthumously as a member of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union on June 21 by a party commission reviewing repressions under Stalin, the commission announced. 13</p>
        <p>Opportunities for corruption in China have flourished with the country's new economic policies. Some Chinese fear that corruption has penetrated society so deeply that government can no longer function without it. 1</p>
        <p>Iranians do not want to end the war with Iraq without a settlement that includes some measure of compensation for their suffering, informal interviews show. People display a mix of determination and despair. 1</p>
        <p>Civilian flights over the Persian Gulf face increased danger because of the military buildup in the region over the last year, pilots and air traffic controllers say. Procedures of warships cause some of the danger. 10</p>
        <p>Malaysia wants to block refugees arriving by boat from Vietnam and is sending its Foreign Minister to Hanoi to urge Vietnam to stop the flow. Malaysia has said it would stop accepting refugees next April. 3</p>
        <p>Israel ordered higher hospital fees for government hospitals in the West Bank. Palestinian doctors said the move was related to the uprising. Israel said the increase was to make hospitals more cost-efficient. 11</p>
        <p>Sandinistas ban March by opposition in Managua  4</p>
        <p>U.N. envoy pushes Afghan cease-fire  5</p>
        <p>Nazi victims seek Argentine justice  9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL/16-21</p>
        <p>Stereotypes of Asian students at the University of California at Berkely as a ''model minority'' leave them at a disadvatange, some officials say. Asians who have problems say they do not get the help they need. 16</p>
        <p>Sudden shifts in a nuclear reaction at a plant in Seneca, Ill., have prompted an inquiry into whether a whole class of nuclear plants is vulnerable to a dangerous condition that engineers had predicted was impossible. 16</p>
        <p>Changes in Pentagon procurement are being considered by Congress and the Defense Department in the wake of the inquiry into military purchasing fraud. The Pentagon argues against sweeping changes. 20</p>
        <p>The danger of forest fires is great this summer because of drought, firefighting officials say. Much of the West is in extreme danger of wildfires, while danger in the East is considered high. 21</p>
        <p>A ruling in Oliver North's case that gives him broader access to secret Government documents for his defense raises the possibility that he will not be tried on the main charges in the Iran-contra case. 20</p>
        <p>U.S. falling short on its infant health goals  17</p>
        <p>Pregnant women increasingly fearful of VDT's  19</p>
        <p>Show turns farm into puppet state  32</p>
        <p>Politics/18</p>
        <p>Jesse Jackson vowed to continue his Presidential campaign despite criticism that he did not know when to stop. Mr. Jackson also denied saying that he might leave the convention hall to speak.  1</p>
        <p>Michael Dukakis dismissed signals that Jesse Jackson would take his case outside the Democratic National Convention if he does not agree with the platform or the selection for Vice President.  18</p>
        <p>REGIONAL/21-25</p>
        <p>Nearly all ocean beaches were open on Long Island and in New York City's Rockaways as the authorities reported no new sightings of the medical waste that had been spotted for the past three days.  1</p>
        <p>Hundreds of paintings and artifacts that are being stored by the New York Historical Society in a Manhattan warehouse are in such acute stages of deterioration that some may be lost permanently. 1</p>
        <p>Studies in Corona and Elmhurst, two middle-class neighborhoods in Queens, are being conducted by anthropologists to chronicle how immigrants either settle into established neighborhoods or remain apart. 22</p>
        <p>Three Buddhist monks will sift sand for the next six weeks into an intricate pattern at the American Museum of Natural History in New York City as part of project to preserve Asian art forms. 23</p>
        <p>Teacher recruitment and placement in New York City was criticized by a State Senate panel, which said that New York City's Board of Education lacked the basic information to carry out the tasks properly. 26</p>
        <p>Homeless protest ruling on aid cutoff  21</p>
        <p>O'Neill house's journey into blight  22</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
