<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1993 ELECTIONS: Propositions; Ballot Measures on Term Limits and Crime Draw Wide Support</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="647198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERM LIMITS (POLITICAL OFFICE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">EGAN, TIMOTHY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DF1F3FF937A35752C1A965958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1993 ELECTIONS: Propositions; Ballot Measures on Term Limits and Crime Draw Wide Support</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EGAN, TIMOTHY</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Nov. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Voters across the country continued to show strong support for term limits, a tougher than ever stand on crime and opposition to gay rights, while indicating they would pay higher taxes if the revenue was used for health care or education.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of significant ballot measures were on state electoral plates in Tuesday's matchups, but the results showed an electorate that was generally unwilling to experiment with new ideas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Voters across the country continued to show strong support for term limits, a tougher than ever stand on crime and opposition to gay rights, while indicating they would pay higher taxes if the revenue was used for health care or education.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of significant ballot measures were on state electoral plates in Tuesday's matchups, but the results showed an electorate that was generally unwilling to experiment with new ideas.</p>
        <p>The exception is crime. Here in Washington state, 76 percent of the voters approved a referendum called "Three Strikes, You're Out," which would mandate life sentences without chance of parole for people convicted of three consecutive felony offenses. It would not apply to juveniles.</p>
        <p>The measure, which had strong support across party lines and in rural as well as urban areas, is likely to show up on the ballots of other states. 'Blueprint for Other States'</p>
        <p>"This crime initiative is the first of its kind, and it will serve as a blueprint for other states," said Peter Wehner, policy director of Empower America, a conservative advocacy group based in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>School vouchers, another major initiative supported by conservatives, failed by a huge margin in California. Proposition 174, which would have provided $2,600 in vouchers for each of the state's 5.8 million schoolchildren, was rejected by 70 percent of California's voters. School voucher plans have now been voted down in all three states where they have been tried. The others are Colarado and Oregon.</p>
        <p>California's political establishment, including Gov. Pete Wilson, a Republican, joined teachers' unions and President Clinton in opposing school vouchers. Proponents said the measure suffered from a lack of campaign money and was too broadly written.</p>
        <p>Here's a look at how the other issues fared on Tuesday: Taxes</p>
        <p>The tax revolt, which started nearly 15 years ago in California, seemed to run out of steam on Tuesday. Voters in California, suffering from the state's worst economic slump in a generation, nonetheless approved by 58 percent to 42 percent a half-cent rise in the sales tax. The increase, passed this year by the Legislature but needing voter approval to become permanent, would be used for increased police protection.</p>
        <p>In Washington state, an attempt to roll back nearly a $1 billion in new taxes was defeated by a margin of about 12 percent. The measure, Initiative 602, holds some lessons for Mr. Clinton, as he has said he will seek higher taxes on tobacco products to pay for health care.</p>
        <p>Washington passed a universal health care plan this year that is very similar to the one proposed by the President. It raises taxes on tobacco and alcohol to help pay for the program. In this case, voters chose the higher taxes.</p>
        <p>But a companion measure, Initiative 601, which limits the growth of state government to the rate of inflation and population increase, was winning approval by a margin of less than 1 percent. The measure would require voter approval for any new state taxes in the next 18 months; beyond that, new taxes would have to be approved by a two-thirds majority in the Legislature.</p>
        <p>"The latest trend in tax revolt, voter approval for new taxes, apparently has continued," said David Keating, executive vice president for the National Taxpayers Union in Washington, D.C. Gay Rights</p>
        <p>For those seeking legal protection from discrimination against homosexuals, Tuesday was the latest in a series of defeats, as voters in Cincinnati, Lewiston, Me., and Portsmouth, N.H., rejected gay rights.</p>
        <p>By 62 percent to 38 percent, Cincinnati voters repealed a 1992 ordinance protecting homosexuals from discrimination. A similar law was repealed by a margin of more than 2 to 1 in Lewiston, and a nonbinding vote on gay rights in Portsmouth failed by a 3-to-2 margin.</p>
        <p>The defeats come as a dozen states are considering ballot measures for next year that would bar legal protection for homosexuals. The measures are modeled after an initiative approved by Colorado voters last year, and is now tied up in a court challenge. On Monday, the Supreme Court declined to hear an appeal by the State of Colorado from a ruling requiring it to prove that the gay rights measure serves a "compelling state interest."</p>
        <p>Gay rights supporters are taking a new look at their strategy.</p>
        <p>"The initiatives show that we've got a lot of work to do," said Gregory King, a spokesman for the Human Rights Campaign Fund, based in Washington, D.C. "It's clear that our message is not moving the public." Term Limits</p>
        <p>The national campaign to limit the terms of elected officials continues to roll, and is gaining momentum. Already, 16 states have approved term limits. The one state where it had lost -- Washington -- voted in favor of term limits last year when a less severe measure was presented to voters.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, voters in New York City and Maine joined the bandwagon. The Maine proposal, limiting the terms of state officeholders, passed by a 2-to-1 margin. Voters in New York City approved, by a roughly 3-to-2 margin, a referendum to limit the terms of the mayor, comptroller, public advocate, borough presidents and City Council members.</p>
        <p>Term limits for members of Congress are clouded by a legal challenge. Opponents, led by the Speaker of the House, Thomas S. Foley of Washington, have filed suit here to overturn last year's voter mandate. The suit contends that limiting the terms of Federal officeholders is unconstitutional. A trial is expected next year.</p>
        <p>In another referendum, voters in Houston defeated a proposal to bring zoning to that city.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
