<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dublin Journal; Nemesis of I.R.A., and No Friend to Protestants</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="647247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHERN IRELAND</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC PARTY (NORTHERN IRELAND)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLARITY, JAMES F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUME, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1731F937A35752C1A965958260" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dublin Journal; Nemesis of I.R.A., and No Friend to Protestants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES F. CLARITY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLARITY, JAMES F</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, Nov. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his hometown of Londonderry, there is an old joke about John Hume, the most respected and influential Roman Catholic leader in Northern Ireland: What is the difference between John Hume and God? The answer: "God doesn't think he's John Hume."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume, a 56-year-old former French teacher with a reputation for being haughty and humorless, has been the target of this kind of criticism for most of the 20 years he has been the chief Roman Catholic enemy of the Irish Republican Army and its campaign of violence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his hometown of Londonderry, there is an old joke about John Hume, the most respected and influential Roman Catholic leader in Northern Ireland: What is the difference between John Hume and God? The answer: "God doesn't think he's John Hume."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume, a 56-year-old former French teacher with a reputation for being haughty and humorless, has been the target of this kind of criticism for most of the 20 years he has been the chief Roman Catholic enemy of the Irish Republican Army and its campaign of violence.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he shares the I.R.A.'s ultimate objective of a Northern Ireland free of British sovereignty and incorporated into the Irish Republic to the south. This makes him an enemy of the leaders of the province's Protestant majority, who want to remain part of Britain. 'Talking About History'</p>
        <p>In recent months he has been the catalyst for a new move toward peace. The British Government curries his favor, and in the Irish Republic he is often accorded an enthusiastic standing ovation.</p>
        <p>"We are talking about history here," Mr. Hume said in an interview, discussing his latest efforts. "This could be it. This could work."</p>
        <p>Along with Gerry Adams, the president of Sinn Fein, the I.R.A.'s political wing, Mr. Hume has lately put forward a peace initiative and presented it to the Irish Prime Minister, Albert Reynolds, who accepted it and passed parts of it on to Prime Minister John Major of Britain.</p>
        <p>This week Mr. Major did not acknowledge in his remarks to Parliament that he and Mr. Reynolds had used some of the Hume-Adams proposals in their own initiative. And he said the two Prime Ministers had decided to make their own initiative because the Hume-Adams suggestion was "not the right way to proceed."</p>
        <p>But Irish and British officials said that it was clear that the Reynolds-Major proposal did subsume aspects of Hume-Adams, and that Mr. Major's formal rejection was made because anything bearing Mr. Adams's fingerprints would have left him open to accusations by Protestants that he was negotiating with terrorists.</p>
        <p>British policy excludes Sinn Fein from peace talks because it refuses to denounce I.R.A. terrorism. Both initiatives are efforts to work out a way to provide for a total cessation of violence and the inclusion of Sinn Fein in negotiations.</p>
        <p>While rejecting the initiative, Mr. Major nonetheless praised Mr. Hume as "courageous" in the House of Commons in London this week. Mr. Hume is scheduled to meet privately with Mr. Major on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Depending on whether the efforts toward peace succeed, Irish history is likely to raise Mr. Hume to the pedestals of statuary, or relegate him to a footnote as another failed hope.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume is also a member of the European Parliament, the legislative body of the European Community, where last year he was proposed for its presidency, but declined. He has indicated he will continue talking to Mr. Adams and believes his approach is the only one with a chance.</p>
        <p>He is, supporters and critics point out, probably the only outside politician trusted by Sinn Fein or the I.R.A.</p>
        <p>He has been the I.R.A.'s enemy for 20 years. His party, the Social Democratic Labor Party, took away Mr. Adams's seat in the British Parliament last year. Belief in Gerry Adams</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume was already a respected Catholic leader in 1972, when the British Government released Mr. Adams from jail, where he was interned as an I.R.A. commander, and flew him to London for talks that failed. Mr. Hume believes that Mr. Adams is the only political leader who might persuade the I.R.A. to lay down its arms.</p>
        <p>The most Mr. Hume has said publicly about the Hume-Adams proposals is that they "can lead to a dialogue including all parties, including Sinn Fein in a situation in which there is no violence."</p>
        <p>To claims by Protestant leaders that his talks with Mr. Adams encourage I.R.A. violence, Mr. Hume said in a recent interview: "There is no way that I have ever endorsed violence. My home has been attacked on numerous occasions by supporters of the I.R.A. In fact in the last attack my wife and daughter were lucky to emerge alive."</p>
        <p>"Given that the British Government has stated it cannot defeat the I.R.A. and that the I.R.A. has stated it cannot defeat the British Government, my simple Irish mind tells me the logic of that is that the only thing that'll solve the problem is dialogue," he said in a recent interview on Ulster Televison in Belfast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume began his agitation 25 years ago as a moderate, nonviolent Catholic marching in the civil rights demonstration in Londonderry. The Protestant-dominated police attacked the marchers and the current period of murderous sectarian violence began. Became an I.R.A. Enemy</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume quickly became the chief northern Irish enemy of the I.R.A., traveling frequently to Washington to persuade Irish-American politicians, including Senator Edward M. Kennedy, to oppose Irish-American groups who were raising money for the I.R.A.</p>
        <p>His efforts, the Irish Government has acknowledged, did much to dry up these funds. The I.R.A. had to turn to Libya to restock its supplies of explosives, mortars and guns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume's hope for Ireland is that after the violence ends, the British forces will gradually depart and the two Irelands will eventually merge, encouraged by tendencies toward economic and political unity in the European Community. Ireland, he says, is in a "post-nationalism" age, where "independence must be replaced by interdependence."</p>
        <p>"If you dismiss the I.R.A. as gangsters -- I wish they were -- they'd be gone in a fornight," Mr. Hume said on Ulster Television. "It's because they're a handed-down version of Irish patriotism and the reasons that they give me are historic reasons and I'm arguing with them that they're out of date."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
